<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id957"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-8,114"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>79-8,114</statuteno><catchline>Grants; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) A teacher may apply to the department for a grant. The department shall not prioritize a grant based upon the school where the applicant teaches.</para><para>(2) A teacher is eligible to apply for:</para><para>(a) A retention one grant of two thousand five hundred dollars if the teacher has signed a contract to complete such teacher's second complete school year of full-time employment as a teacher at a Nebraska school in school year 2023-24, 2024-25, 2025-26, or 2026-27;</para><para>(b) A retention two grant of two thousand five hundred dollars if the teacher has signed a contract to complete such teacher's fourth complete school year of full-time employment as a teacher at a Nebraska school in school year 2023-24, 2024-25, 2025-26, or 2026-27;</para><para>(c) A retention three grant of two thousand five hundred dollars if the teacher has signed a contract to complete such teacher's sixth complete school year of full-time employment as a teacher at a Nebraska school in school year 2023-24, 2024-25, 2025-26, or 2026-27; and</para><para>(d)(i) A high-need retention grant of five thousand dollars if on or after June 2, 2023, a teacher:</para><para>(A) Obtains an endorsement in special education, mathematics, science, technology, or dual credit; and</para><para>(B) Signs a contract to complete a school year of full-time employment as a teacher at a Nebraska school in school year 2024-25, 2025-26, or 2026-27.</para><para>(ii) A teacher shall only be eligible to receive one high-need retention grant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 46. </para><operativedate>June 2, 2023</operativedate><terminationdate>January 1, 2028</terminationdate></source></law>
</legaldoc>