<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-769"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>79-769</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Focus programs;
focus schools; magnet schools; authorized; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Any one or more member school districts of a learning community
may establish one or more focus programs, focus schools, or magnet schools. If included as part of the diversity
plan of a learning community, the focus school or focus program shall be eligible
for a focus school and program allowance pursuant to section 79-1007.05.</para>
<para>(2) Focus schools, focus programs, and magnet schools may
be included in pathways across member school districts pursuant to the diversity
plan developed by the learning community coordinating council pursuant to
section 79-2104.</para>
<para>(3) If multiple member school districts collaborate on a focus program,
focus school, or magnet school, the school districts shall form a joint
entity pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act for the purpose of creating,
implementing, and operating such focus program, focus school, or magnet school.
The agreement creating such joint entity shall address legal, financial, and
academic responsibilities and the assignment to participating school districts
of students enrolled in such focus program, focus school, or magnet school
who reside in nonparticipating school districts.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Focus program means a program that does not have an attendance
area, whose enrollment is designed so that the socioeconomic diversity of
the students attending the focus program reflects as nearly as possible the
socioeconomic diversity of the student body of the learning community, which
has a unique curriculum with specific learning goals or teaching techniques
different from the standard curriculum, which may be housed in a building
with other public school programs, and which may consist of either the complete
education program for participating students or part of the education program
for participating students;</para>
<para>(b) Focus school means a school that does not have an attendance
area, whose enrollment is designed so that the socioeconomic diversity of
the students attending the focus school reflects as nearly as possible the
socioeconomic diversity of the student body of the learning community, which
has a unique curriculum with specific learning goals or teaching techniques
different from the standard curriculum, and which is housed in a building
that does not contain another public school program;</para>
<para>(c) Magnet school means a school having a home attendance
area but which reserves a portion of its capacity specifically for students
from outside the attendance area who will contribute to the socioeconomic
diversity of the student body of such school and which has a unique curriculum
with specific learning goals or teaching techniques different from the standard
curriculum; and</para>
<para>(d) Pathway means elementary, middle, and high school focus
programs, focus schools, and magnet schools with coordinated curricula based
on specific learning goals or teaching techniques.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB558, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>