<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-981" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-981</statuteno><catchline>Employees retirement system; board of education or Class V Retirement System Board; rules and regulations; administrator; employees compensation.</catchline><para>The board of education or Class V Retirement System Board shall from time to time establish rules and regulations for the administration of the retirement system and for the transaction of its business and shall appoint an administrator of the retirement system. The board may contract for such medical and other services as shall be required to transact the business of the retirement system. Compensation for all persons employed by the board and all other expenses of the board necessary for the proper and efficient operation of the retirement system shall be paid in such amounts as the board determines and approves.</para><para>In addition to such duties and other duties arising out of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act not specifically reserved or assigned to others, the board shall maintain a separate account of each member's contribution, the record of which shall be available to the member upon request, compile such data as may be necessary for the required actuarial valuation, consider and pass on all applications for annuities or other benefits and have examinations made when advisable of persons receiving disability benefits, and direct and determine all policies necessary in the administration of the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 4, p. 913; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 215, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 350, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1035; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 616; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 62.</para></source></law></legaldoc>