<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id13" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-760.06">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-760.06</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Accountability
system; combine multiple indicators; State Department
of Education; powers; duties;
designation of priority schools.</catchline><para>(1) On or before August 1,
2012, the State Board of Education shall establish an accountability system
to be used to measure the performance of individual public schools and school
districts. The accountability system shall combine multiple indicators, including,
but not limited to, graduation rates, student growth and student improvement
on the assessment instruments provided in section 79-760.03, and other indicators
of the performance of public schools and school districts as established by
the state board.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning with the reporting of data
from school year 2014-15, the indicators selected by the state board for the accountability system shall be combined into a school performance
score and district performance score. </para>
<para>The state board shall establish
levels of performance based upon school performance scores and district performance
scores in order to classify the performance of public schools
and school districts beginning with the
reporting of data from school year 2014-15. The state board shall designate priority
schools based on such classification. Schools designated as priority schools
shall be at the lowest performance level at the time of the initial priority
school designation. Schools designated as priority schools shall remain priority
schools until such designation is removed by the state board. No more than
three schools may have a priority school designation at one time. Schools
designated as priority schools shall be subject to the requirements of section 79-760.07.
Progress plans for the initial schools designated as priority schools shall
be approved by the state board no later than August 1, 2016. The
State Department of Education shall annually report the performance level of
individual public schools and school districts as part of the statewide assessment
and reporting system.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB870, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB438, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>April 10, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>