<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-540"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-540</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 87. Operative date January 1, 2019. Class I school district; district meetings; challenge voter qualifications; oath.</catchline><para>If any person offering to vote at any Class I school district meeting is challenged as unqualified by any legal voter of such school district, the chairperson presiding at such meeting shall explain to the person challenged the qualifications of a legal voter. If such person states that he or she is qualified and the challenge is not withdrawn, the chairperson shall administer an oath, reduced to writing, in substance as follows: "You do solemnly swear (or affirm) that you are a citizen of the United States, that you are of the constitutionally prescribed age of an elector or upwards, that you are domiciled in this precinct or ward, which precinct or ward lies in whole or in part within the boundaries of this school district, and that you are registered to vote in this precinct or ward, so help you God." Every person taking such oath and signing his or her name to it shall be permitted to vote on all questions proposed at such meeting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision II, &#167; 5, p. 339; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6734; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6272; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-205; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-205; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 67, p. 714; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 388, &#167; 1, p. 1343; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 712, &#167; 3, p. 2738; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1070, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 557, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 897, &#167; 13; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-428; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 293; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 345, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 347, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 12. </para></source><annotation><para>Oath was filed by challenged voters. Olsen v. Grosshans, 160 Neb. 543, 71 N.W.2d 90 (1955).</para><para>Person whose vote at a district meeting is challenged is required to make oath that he owns property assessed in his name, or has children of school age. Cunningham v. Ilg, 118 Neb. 682, 226 N.W. 333 (1929).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>