<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id154">
<sectno id="id155">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id156" statutenumber="79-317"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id158">79-317</statuteno><catchline id="id159">State Board
of Education; meetings; open to public; exceptions; compensation and expenses.</catchline>
<para>(1) The State Board of Education shall meet regularly and
periodically in the office of the State Department of Education at least four
times annually and at such other times and places as it may
determine necessary for the proper and efficient conduct of its duties. All meetings shall be called in accordance
with this section and the Open Meetings Act. Five members of the board shall
constitute a quorum.</para>
<para>(2) The public shall be admitted to all meetings of the State
Board of Education except to such closed sessions as the board may direct
in accordance with the Open Meetings Act. The board shall cause to be kept
a record of all public meetings and proceedings of the board. The commissioner,
or his or her designated representative, shall be present at all meetings
except when the order of business for the board is the selection of a Commissioner
of Education.</para>
<para>(3) The members of the State Board of Education shall receive
no compensation for their services but shall be reimbursed for actual and
essential expenses incurred in attending meetings or incurred in the performance
of duties as directed by the board as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 320, &#167; 7, p. 1055; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 421, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 325, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 153; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-327; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 17.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>