<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id484"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-874.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>79-874.01</statuteno><catchline>Professional employees' organization; access; requirements; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Certificated employee has the same meaning as in section 79-824; and</para><para>(b) Professional employees' organization means any organization that engages in one or more of the following activities: Providing liability protection or collective bargaining on behalf of certificated employees.</para><para>(2) A school board shall grant access upon a request made by a professional employees' organization to the physical or electronic mailbox of any certificated employee.</para><para>(3) A professional employees' organization, in an effort to recruit new members, is permitted to display information at or send a representative who either is an employee of the school district or represents an employee of the school district to attend a certificated employee meeting or event, including, but not limited to, a certificated employee orientation meeting.</para><para>(4) If a professional employees' organization is allowed to create and post signage or materials in a school such as an information board, a bulletin board, a poster, or a pamphlet, any other professional employees' organization shall also be granted permission to create and post signage and materials in an equal manner.</para><para>(5) A school board shall not designate any day or break in the school calendar by naming or referring to the day or break using the name of any professional employees' organization.</para><para>(6) Nothing in this section shall be construed to apply to, modify, supersede, or affect in any way the provisions of the Industrial Relations Act, section 48-842, or any rights, duties, procedures, or obligations established pursuant to such act or section, including, but not limited to, any matters relating to collective bargaining, industrial disputes, certification of bargaining agents, prohibited practices, or jurisdiction of the Commission of Industrial Relations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB429, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Industrial Relations Act,</emphasis> see section 48-801.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>