<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id24" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-527.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-527.01</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Council on Student Attendance; created;
members; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Council
on Student Attendance is created. The council shall
consist of:</para>
<para>(i) A member
of a school board in any class of school district to be appointed by the State
Board of Education;</para><para>(ii) Two parents not related to each other who have children attending
school in this state to be appointed by the State Board of Education;</para>
<para>(iii) A superintendent
or his or her designee of a school district to be appointed by the State Board
of Education;</para><para>(iv) A student attending a public school in this state to be appointed
by the State Board of Education;</para><para>(v) A representative of a community or advocacy
organization to be appointed by the State Board of Education;</para>
<para>(vi) A county
attorney to be appointed by the State Board of Education;</para>
<para>(vii) The probation administrator
or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(viii) The Commissioner of
Education or his or her designee; and</para>
<para>(ix) The chief executive officer
of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee.</para>
<para>(b) The members
of the council appointed by the State Board of Education shall serve three-year
staggered terms, as designated by the board.</para><para>(c) The members of the
council shall serve on the council without any additional compensation, but
they shall be entitled to receive reimbursement for any actual expenses incurred
as necessary incident to such service as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
<para>(2) The council shall:</para>
<para>(a) Study and evaluate the
data contained in the reports required by subsection (2) of section 79-527;</para>
<para>(b) Develop recommendations
to reduce incidents of absenteeism;</para>
<para>(c) Consider
whether school district policies and practices for addressing absenteeism
are operational and effectively working to address absenteeism and make recommendations
for improvements where necessary; and</para><para>(d) Review all school district policies
developed under subsection (2) of section 79-209 and make specific recommendations
for school district policy improvement.</para><para>The council may
contact a school district or a county attorney for additional information in order to carry out its duties under
this section.</para>
<para>(3) The council
shall report on its activities electronically to the Legislature on or before
October 1 of each year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB410, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 35.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>