<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id392">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id394" statutenumber="79-9,113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,113</statuteno><catchline id="id397">Employees
retirement system; federal Social Security Act; state retirement plan; how
affected; required contributions; payment; membership service annuity; computations.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) If, at any future time, a majority of the eligible
members of the retirement system votes to be included under an agreement providing
old age and survivors insurance under the Social Security Act of the United
States, the contributions to be made by the member and the school district
for membership service, from and after the effective date of the agreement
with respect to services performed subsequent to December 31, 1954, shall
each be reduced from five to three percent but not less than three percent
of the member's salary per annum, and the credits for membership service under
this system, as provided in section 79-999, shall thereafter be reduced from
one and one-half percent to nine-tenths of one percent and not less than nine-tenths
of one percent of salary or wage earned by the member during each fiscal year,
and from one and sixty-five hundredths percent to one percent and not less
than one percent of salary or wage earned by the member during each fiscal
year and from two percent to one and two-tenths percent of salary or wage
earned by the member during each fiscal year, and from two and four-tenths
percent to one and forty-four hundredths percent of salary or wage earned
by the member during each fiscal year, except that after September 1, 1963,
and prior to September 1, 1969, all employees of the school district shall
contribute an amount equal to the membership contribution which shall be two
and three-fourths percent of salary covered by old age and survivors insurance,
and five percent above that amount. Commencing September 1, 1969, all employees
of the school district shall contribute an amount equal to the membership
contribution which shall be two and three-fourths percent of the first seven
thousand eight hundred dollars of salary or wages earned each fiscal year
and five percent of salary or wages earned above that amount in the same fiscal
year. Commencing September 1, 1976, all employees of the school district shall
contribute an amount equal to the membership contribution which shall be two
and nine-tenths percent of the first seven thousand eight hundred dollars
of salary or wages earned each fiscal year and five and twenty-five hundredths
percent of salary or wages earned above that amount in the same fiscal year.
Commencing on September 1, 1982, all employees of the school district shall
contribute an amount equal to the membership contribution which shall be four
and nine-tenths percent of the compensation earned in each fiscal year. Commencing
September 1, 1989, all employees of the school district shall contribute an
amount equal to the membership contribution which shall be five and eight-tenths
percent of the compensation earned in each fiscal year. Commencing September
1, 1995, all employees of the school district shall contribute an amount equal
to the membership contribution which shall be six and three-tenths percent
of the compensation earned in each fiscal year. Commencing September 1, 2007,
all employees of the school district shall contribute an amount equal to the
membership contribution which shall be seven and three-tenths percent of the
compensation paid in each fiscal year. Commencing September 1, 2009, all employees
of the school district shall contribute an amount equal to the membership
contribution which shall be eight and three-tenths percent of the compensation
paid in each fiscal year. Commencing
September 1, 2011, all employees of the school district shall contribute an
amount equal to the membership contribution which shall be nine and three-tenths
percent of the compensation paid in each fiscal year.</para>
<para>(b) The contributions by the school district in any fiscal year beginning
on or after September 1, 1999, shall be the greater of (i) one hundred percent
of the contributions by the employees for such fiscal year or (ii) such amount
as may be necessary to maintain the solvency of the system, as determined
annually by the board upon recommendation of the actuary and the trustees.</para>
<para>(c) The contributions by the school district in any fiscal
year beginning on or after September 1, 2007, shall be the greater of (i)
one hundred one
percent of the contributions by the employees for such fiscal year or (ii)
such amount as may be necessary to maintain the solvency of the system, as
determined annually by the board upon recommendation of the actuary and the
trustees.</para>
<para>(d) The employee's contribution shall be made in the form
of a monthly deduction from compensation as provided in subsection (2) of
this section. Every employee who is a member of the system shall be deemed
to consent and agree to such deductions and shall receipt in full for compensation,
and payment to such employee of compensation less such deduction shall constitute
a full and complete discharge of all claims and demands whatsoever for services
rendered by such employee during the period covered by such payment except
as to benefits provided under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para>
<para>(e) After September 1, 1963, and prior to September 1, 1969,
all employees shall be credited with a membership service annuity which shall
be nine-tenths of one percent of salary or wage covered by old age and survivors
insurance and one and one-half percent of salary or wages above that amount,
except that those employees who retire on or after August 31, 1969, shall
be credited with a membership service annuity which shall be one percent of
salary or wages covered by old age and survivors insurance and one and sixty-five
hundredths percent of salary or wages above that amount for service performed
after September 1, 1963, and prior to September 1, 1969. Commencing September
1, 1969, all employees shall be credited with a membership service annuity
which shall be one percent of the first seven thousand eight hundred dollars
of salary or wages earned by the employee during each fiscal year and one
and sixty-five hundredths percent of salary or wages earned above that amount
in the same fiscal year, except that all employees retiring on or after August
31, 1976, shall be credited with a membership service annuity which shall
be one and forty-four hundredths percent of the first seven thousand eight
hundred dollars of salary or wages earned by the employee during such fiscal
year and two and four-tenths percent of salary or wages earned above that
amount in the same fiscal year, and
the retirement annuities of employees who have not retired prior to September
1, 1963, and who elected under the provisions of section 79-988 as such section
existed immediately prior to February 20, 1982, not to become members of the
system shall not be less than they would have been had they remained under
any preexisting system to date of retirement.</para>
<para>(f) Members of this system having the service qualifications
of members of the School Employees Retirement
System of the State of Nebraska, as provided by section 79-926, shall receive
the state service annuity provided by sections 79-933 to 79-935 and 79-951.</para>
<para>(2) The school district shall pick up the employee contributions
required by this section for all compensation paid on or after January 1,
1985, and the contributions so picked up shall be treated as employer contributions
in determining federal tax treatment under the Internal Revenue Code, except
that the school district shall continue to withhold federal income taxes based
upon these contributions until the Internal Revenue Service or the federal
courts rule that, pursuant to section 414(h) of the Internal Revenue Code,
these contributions shall not be included as gross income of the employee
until such time as they are distributed or made available. The school district
shall pay these employee contributions from the same source of funds which
is used in paying earnings to the employee. The school district shall pick
up these contributions by a salary deduction either through a reduction in
the cash salary of the employee or a combination of a reduction in salary
and offset against a future salary increase. Beginning September 1, 1995,
the school district shall also pick up any contributions required by sections
79-990, 79-991, and 79-992 which are made under an irrevocable payroll deduction
authorization between the member and the school district, and the contributions
so picked up shall be treated as employer contributions in determining federal
tax treatment under the Internal Revenue Code, except that the school district
shall continue to withhold federal and state income taxes based upon these
contributions until the Internal Revenue Service rules that, pursuant to section
414(h) of the Internal Revenue Code, these contributions shall not be included
as gross income of the employee until such time as they are distributed from
the system. Employee contributions picked up shall be treated for all purposes
of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act in the same manner and to the
extent as employee contributions made prior to the date picked up.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 25, p. 923; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 308, &#167; 4, p. 1029; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 321, &#167; 3, p. 993; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 490, &#167; 5, p. 1567; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 724, &#167; 2, p. 2755; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1116, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 994, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 131, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 488, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 218, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 237, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 505, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 77; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1056; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 648; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 155, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB596, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB187, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB382, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 35.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For provisions of federal Social Security Act,</emphasis> see Chapter 68, article 6.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>