<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id634"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-734.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>79-734.02</statuteno><catchline>Projection maps; requirements for use; school board; adopt policy.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, beginning in school year 2024-25, a public school shall not allow the use of a Mercator projection map in school. A public school shall only use the Gall-Peters projection map or a similar cylindrical equal-area projection map or the AuthaGraph projection map for display or use in the classroom.</para><para>(2) A Mercator projection map may be used in a classroom if such map is:</para><para>(a) Used in conjunction with other projection maps in a teaching exercise to demonstrate that all maps are flawed in some way and different map projections serve different functions and may affect how an individual views the world; or</para><para>(b)(i) Part of any (A) book or material obtained prior to July 19, 2024, (B) geographic information system, or (C) computer program that renders a three-dimensional representation of Earth based primarily on satellite imagery, such as Google Earth or similar software; and</para><para>(ii) A Gall-Peters projection map or a similar cylindrical equal-area projection map or an AuthaGraph projection map is displayed in the classroom or shown to students during the lesson in which a Mercator projection map is used.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a school to dispose of or replace any book or material used in the classroom or obtained prior to July 19, 2024.</para><para>(4) The school board of each public school district shall adopt a policy to implement the requirements of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 90. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>