<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id296">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id298" statutenumber="79-933.03">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-933.03</statuteno><catchline id="id301">Contributing
member; credit for service in other schools; limitation; procedure; payment.</catchline>
<para>(1) Under such rules and regulations as the board shall adopt
and promulgate, a contributing member under contract or employed on July 19,
1996, may receive credit for not to exceed ten years of creditable teaching
service rendered in public schools in another state or schools in this state
covered by a school retirement system established pursuant to section 79-979,
if such member files an application for service credit within three years
of membership or reinstatement in the School Employees Retirement System of the State of
Nebraska and makes payment into the retirement system of an amount equal to
the required deposits he or she would have paid had he or she been employed
in this state by a school covered by the retirement system, plus the interest which would
have accrued on such amount. Payment must be completed within five years of
membership or reinstatement in the retirement system, or prior to termination
of employment, whichever occurs first, and may be made through direct payment,
installment payments, or an irrevocable payroll deduction authorization.</para>
<para>(2) A member who retires as a school employee of this state
shall not receive credit for time in service outside of this state or in a
school in this state covered by the school retirement system established pursuant
to section 79-979 in excess of the time he or she has been in service as a
school employee in this state of a school covered by the School Employees Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska. The board shall refund to the member the payments
made pursuant to subsection (1) of this section to the extent that the member
does not receive credit for such service.</para>
<para>(3) A member who purchases service credit pursuant to this
section shall provide such documentation as the board may require to prove
that the member has forfeited the receipt of any benefits from the retirement
system of the public school in another state or a school in this state covered
by a retirement system established pursuant to section 79-979 for the creditable
service rendered in such school.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 24.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
