<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id372" statutenumber="79-984"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>79-984</statuteno><catchline id="id375">Employees retirement system; actuary; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Until July 1, 2021, the board of trustees shall contract for the services of an actuary who shall be the technical advisor of the board of trustees on matters regarding the operation of the retirement system. The selection of the actuary shall be approved by the board of education. The actuary shall (a) make a general investigation of the operation of the retirement system annually, which investigation shall cover mortality, retirement, disability, employment, turnover, interest, and earnable compensation, and (b) recommend tables to be used for all required actuarial calculations. The actuary shall perform such other duties as may be assigned by the board of trustees.</para><para>(2) Beginning July 1, 2021, and until September 1, 2024, the board of education shall contract for the services of an actuary who shall be the technical advisor of the board of education and the board of trustees on matters regarding the operation of the retirement system. The actuary shall:</para><para>(a) Make a general investigation of the operation of the retirement system annually, which investigation shall cover mortality, retirement, disability, employment, turnover, interest, and earnable compensation;</para><para>(b) Recommend tables to be used for all required actuarial calculations; and</para><para>(c) Perform such other duties as may be assigned by the board of education.</para><para>(3) Beginning September 1, 2024, the retirement board shall select and appoint the actuary for the retirement system pursuant to section 84-1503.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 7, p. 915; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1038; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 619; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>