
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-809"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-809</statuteno><catchline>Teachers' entry-level certificates or permits; qualifications.</catchline><para>In addition to the requirements in section 79-808, the maximum which the board may require for the issuance of any entry-level certificate or permit shall be that the applicant (1) has a baccalaureate degree that qualifies for a certificate to teach, (2) has satisfactorily completed, within two years of the date of application, an approved program at a standard institution of higher education, (3) has special education training, (4) has earned college credit in an approved program, at a standard institution of higher education, for which endorsement is sought, and (5) has paid a nonrefundable fee to the department as provided in section 79-810. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 491, &#167; 4, p. 1570; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 833, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 994, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 633, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1090, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1310, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 754, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1247.06; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 439; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 314, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB150, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 85. </para></source><annotation><para>A state agency which requires, as a minimum for certification of an individual, the maximum requirement permitted by statute does not violate the limiting terms of such statute. The state has a compelling interest in the quality and ability of those who are employed to teach its young people, and a requirement that such teacher possess an appropriate baccalaureate degree is neither arbitrary nor unreasonable and is a reliable indicator of the probability of success as a teacher. State ex rel. Douglas v. Faith Baptist Church of Louisville, 207 Neb. 802, 301 N.W.2d 571 (1981).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>