<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-602"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-602</statuteno><catchline>Pupil transportation vehicles; inspections;
correction of defects.</catchline><para>All school boards, the governing authorities
of any nonpublic schools in this state, and all independent contractors who
or which provide student transportation services for such boards and governing
authorities and for military installations shall cause all pupil transportation
vehicles used for the transportation of students to be inspected before school
opens in the fall and each eighty days during that part of the year when school
is in session by a motor vehicle mechanic appointed by the board or governing
authority having jurisdiction over such students, except that any pupil transportation
vehicle that has been inspected under rules and regulations of the Public
Service Commission shall be exempted from the provisions of this section.
The mechanic shall thoroughly inspect every vehicle used for the transportation
of students as to brakes, lights, windshield wipers, window glass, tires,
doors, heaters, defrosting equipment, steering gear, exhaust system, and the
mechanical condition of every part of such pupil transportation vehicle to
ensure compliance with the minimum allowable safety criteria established pursuant
to section 79-607 and subdivision (12) of section 79-318. Within
five days after such inspection, the mechanic shall make a report of his or
her inspection in writing on regular forms provided by the State Department
of Education which shall show if the vehicle met the minimum allowable safety
criteria for use. Any item not meeting such criteria shall be brought into
compliance prior to the vehicle being used to transport students. One copy
of the mechanic's report shall be filed with the board or governing authority
and, if the school contracts with an independent contractor to provide transportation
services, one copy with the independent contractor. The chief administrative
officer of each school district shall annually certify, by a written verification
statement, to the State Department of Education that the inspections required
pursuant to this section have been performed. Such verification statement
shall be sent to the department no later than June 30.</para>
<para>In addition to the inspection requirements prescribed in this section,
the driver of each pupil transportation vehicle shall make daily inspections
of such vehicle to ensure that all lights and equipment are fully operational
or repaired before his or her daily route. Reports of such daily inspections
shall be kept by the driver in the vehicle and filed weekly with the head
mechanic or administrator in charge of the transportation system. If the inspection
reveals any significant defect in the lights or equipment, the driver shall
immediately report the defect to the head mechanic or administrator in charge
of the transportation system.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 304, &#167; 1, p. 922; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2113.03; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 126, p. 734; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 394, &#167; 1, p. 1352; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 523, &#167; 1, p. 1651; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 292, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 358, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 250; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 743, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 933, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 538, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1310, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-488; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 363; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 36, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 33.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor carrier regulations,</emphasis> scope of, see section 75-303.</para><para><emphasis>Penalty for violation of section,</emphasis> see section 79-603.</para><para><emphasis>Registration fees,</emphasis> see section 60-3,144.</para><para><emphasis>Safety glass required,</emphasis> see section 60-6,263.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>