<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-9,108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,108</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Employees retirement system; funds; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to January 1, 2017, the board of trustees, with approval of the board of education or Class V Retirement System Board, shall invest and reinvest funds of the retirement system. Beginning January 1, 2017, the funds of the retirement system shall be invested and reinvested solely by the council and the state investment officer in accordance with the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) Prior to January 1, 2017, a professional investment manager may be employed by the board of trustees subject to approval of the board of education or Class V Retirement System Board. The professional investment manager shall be responsible for the purchase, sale, exchange, investment, or reinvestment of such funds subject to guidelines determined by the board of trustees. Prior to January 1, 2017, the trustees shall each month submit a report to the board of education or Class V Retirement System Board with respect to the investment of funds. The board of education or Class V Retirement System Board shall approve or disapprove the investments in the report, and in the event of disapproval of any investment, the board of trustees shall direct the sale of all or part of such investment or establish future policy with respect to that type of investment. Beginning January 1, 2017, the funds of the retirement system shall be invested and reinvested by the council and the state investment officer, who may employ advisers, counsel, managers, and other professionals in accordance with the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) Beginning January 1, 2017, the board of trustees and the board of education shall not have any duty, responsibility, or authority for the investment and reinvestment of the funds of the retirement system, or any investment decision, contract, rule, or regulation related thereto.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 545, &#167; 2, p. 1791; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 350, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1051.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 643; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 39. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>