<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id166">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id168" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-408"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>79-408</statuteno><catchline id="id171">Class IV school
district; boundaries; body corporate; powers; retirement plans; restrictions.</catchline>
<para>The territory now or hereafter embraced within each incorporated
city of the primary class in the State of Nebraska that is not in part within
the boundaries of a learning community, such adjacent territory as now or
hereafter may be included therewith for school purposes, and such territory
not adjacent thereto as may have been added thereto by law shall constitute
a Class IV school district, except that nothing in this section shall be construed
to change the boundaries of any school district that is a member of a learning
community. A Class IV school district shall be a body corporate and possess
all the usual powers of a corporation for public purposes, may sue and be
sued, and may purchase, hold, and sell such personal and real estate and contract
such obligations as are authorized by law. The powers of a Class IV district
include, but are not limited to, the power to adopt, administer, and amend
from time to time such retirement, annuity, insurance, and other benefit plans
for its present and future employees after their retirement, or any reasonable
classification thereof, as may be deemed proper by the board of education.
The board of education shall not establish a retirement system for new employees
supplemental to the School Employees Retirement
System of the State of Nebraska.</para>
<para>The title to all real or personal property owned by such
school district shall, upon the organization of the school district, vest
immediately in the school district so created. The board of education shall
have exclusive control of all property belonging to the school district.</para>
<para>In the discretion of the board of education, funds accumulated
in connection with a retirement plan may be transferred to and administered
by a trustee or trustees to be selected by the board of education, or if the
retirement plan is in the form of annuity or insurance contracts, such funds,
or any part thereof, may be paid to a duly licensed insurance carrier or carriers
selected by the board of education. Funds accumulated in connection with any
such retirement plan, and any other funds of the school district which are
not immediately required for current needs or expenses, may be invested and
reinvested by the board of education or by its authority in securities of
a type permissible either for the investment of funds of a domestic legal
reserve life insurance company or for the investment of trust funds, according
to the laws of the State of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 225, &#167; 1, p. 550; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6610; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2601; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 294, &#167; 1(1), p. 907; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 244, p. 772; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 489, &#167; 1, p. 1561; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 475, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1142, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-901; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 157; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 22; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 15.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>