<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-435"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-435</statuteno><catchline>State Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts; members; appointment; term; qualifications; expenses.</catchline><para>The State Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts is created. The state committee shall be composed of six members. The Commissioner of Education shall be a member of the committee ex officio and shall serve as a nonvoting member of the committee. Within thirty days after September 18, 1955, the State Board of Education, by a resolution adopted with the assent of a majority of its members, shall appoint the remaining five members of the state committee, one each for terms of one, two, three, four, and five years respectively. As the term of each member expires, a successor shall be appointed in the same manner for a term of five years. Three members of the state committee shall at all times be laypersons, and two members shall at all times be persons holding teachers' certificates issued by the authority of the State of Nebraska. Vacancies in the membership of the state committee shall be filled for the unexpired term by appointment in the same manner as the original appointment to membership. Members of the state committee shall serve without compensation but shall be reimbursed for expenses necessarily incurred in the performance of their duties, as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 and paid from funds appropriated by the Legislature to the office of the State Board of Education. The State Board of Education shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the state committee to carry out its duties as provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 249, &#167; 3, p. 674; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 311, &#167; 1, p. 956; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 154; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-426.03; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 184; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 26; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422.</para></source></law></legaldoc>