<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<sectno id="id21">Sec. 46.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id22" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="79-2,141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2,141</statuteno><catchline>Model dating violence policy; department;
school district; duties; publication; staff training; redress under other
law.</catchline><para>(1)
On or before March 1, 2010, the department shall develop and adopt a model
dating violence policy to assist school districts in developing policies for
dating violence.</para>
<para>(2) On or before
July 1, 2010, each school district shall develop and adopt a specific policy
to address incidents of dating violence involving students at school, which
shall be made a part of the requirements for accreditation in accordance with
section 79-703. Such policy shall include a statement that dating violence
will not be tolerated.</para><para>(3) To ensure notice of a school district's dating violence policy,
the policy shall be published in any school district handbook, manual, or
similar publication that sets forth the comprehensive rules, procedures, and
standards of conduct for students at school.</para><para>(4) Each school district
shall provide dating violence training to staff deemed appropriate by a school
district's administration. The dating violence training shall include, but
not be limited to, basic awareness of dating violence, warning signs of dating
violence, and the school district's dating violence policy. The dating violence
training may be provided by any school district or combination of school districts,
an educational service unit, or any combination of educational service units.</para>
<para>(5) Each school
district shall inform the students' parents or legal guardians of the school
district's dating violence policy. If requested, the school district shall
provide the parents or legal guardians a copy of the school district's dating
violence policy and relevant information.</para><para>(6) This section does not prevent a victim
of dating violence from seeking redress under any other available law, either
civil or criminal, and does not create or alter any existing tort liability.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 46.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>