<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-419" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-419</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Districts; creation from other districts; petition; contents.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) When a new district is to be created from other districts as provided in section 79-413, the petition shall contain:</para><para id="id00">(a) A description of the proposed boundaries of the reorganized districts;</para><para id="id00">(b) A summary of the terms on which reorganization is to be made between the reorganized districts, which terms may include a provision for initial school board districts or wards within the proposed district for the appointment of the first school board and also for the first election as provided in section 79-451, which proposed initial school board districts or wards shall be determined by the State Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts taking into consideration population and valuation, and a determination of the terms of the board members first appointed to membership of the board of the newly reorganized district;</para><para id="id00">(c) A map showing the boundaries of established school districts and the boundaries proposed under any plan or plans of reorganization;</para><para id="id00">(d) A separate statement as to whether the reorganization is contingent upon the success of a bond election held in conjunction with the reorganization;</para><para id="id00">(e) An affidavit from the county clerk or election commissioner regarding the validity of the signatures on the petition; and</para><para id="id00">(f) Such other matters as the petitioners determine proper to be included.</para><para id="id00">(2) A petition under subsection (1) of this section may contain provisions for the holding of school within existing buildings in the newly reorganized district and that a school constituted under this section shall be maintained from the date of reorganization unless the legal voters served by the school vote by a majority vote for discontinuance of the school.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 475, &#167; 2, p. 1528; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, (1966), &#167; 79-402.01; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 468, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 662, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-402.07; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 168; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 394, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 21; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 18. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Under the precursor to subsection (2) of this section, merging school boards were not authorized to include in their merger petition a requirement that the surviving school board obtain a majority vote from voters in a former school district or a unanimous vote from school board members before moving grades four through six from an elementary school in a former district. Citizens for Eq. Ed. v. Lyons-Decatur Sch. Dist., 274 Neb. 278, 739 N.W.2d 742 (2007).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>