
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id315">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id317" statutenumber="79-933.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-933.06</statuteno><catchline id="id320">Contributing
member; credit for leave of absence; limitation; procedure; payment.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any contributing member may purchase service credit for
time he or she was on a leave of absence authorized by the school board or
board of education of the school district by which he or she was employed
at the time of such leave of absence or pursuant to any contractual agreement
entered into by such school district. Such credit shall increase the benefits
provided by the retirement system and shall be included in creditable service
when determining eligibility for death, disability, termination of employment,
and retirement benefits. The amount to be paid by the member for such service
credit shall equal the actuarial cost to the retirement system for allowing
such additional service credit to the employee. Payment shall be completed
within five years after such member's election to purchase service credit
or prior to termination of employment, whichever occurs first, and may be
made through direct payment, installment payments, or an irrevocable payroll
deduction authorization.</para>
<para>(2) Leave of absence shall be construed to include, but not
be limited to, sabbaticals, maternity leave, exchange teaching programs, full-time
leave as an elected official of a professional association or collective-bargaining
unit, or leave of absence to pursue further education or study. Such leave
shall not exceed four years in length, and in order to receive credit for
the leave of absence the member must return to employment with a school district,
other than a Class V school district, in the state within one year after termination
of the leave of absence.</para>
<para>(3) Compensation for the period of service purchased shall
not be included in determining the member's final average compensation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 26.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>