<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-8,145"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-8,145</statuteno><catchline>Teacher education program; baccalaureate degree, graduate degree, or professional degree; forty-eight or more semester credit hours or associate degree; temporary certificate to teach; issuance; terms and conditions.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to certificates issued pursuant to sections 79-806 to 79-815:</para><para>(a) The Commissioner of Education shall, subject to the provisions of subsection (3) of this section, grant a temporary certificate to teach on a full-time basis to any applicant who:</para><para>(i) Has completed a teacher education program at a standard institution of higher education as defined in section 79-807; and</para><para>(ii) Currently possesses a certificate to teach in good standing from another state;</para><para>(b) The commissioner may, subject to subsection (3) of this section, grant a temporary certificate to teach on a full-time basis to any applicant who:</para><para>(i) Has earned and been awarded a baccalaureate degree, graduate degree, or professional degree from a college or university accredited by an accrediting organization recognized by the United States Department of Education; and</para><para>(ii) Has passed any appropriate subject area examination as designated by the State Board of Education; and</para><para>(c) Beginning in fiscal year 2024-25, the commissioner shall, subject to subsection (3) of this section, grant a temporary certificate to teach on a full-time basis to any applicant who:</para><para>(i) Has completed two years at a college or university accredited by an accrediting organization recognized by the United States Department of Education with at least forty-eight or more semester credit hours or obtained an associate degree from such a college or university;</para><para>(ii) Is employed as a paraprofessional or paraeducator at an elementary school, middle school, or high school in Nebraska; and</para><para>(iii) Has passed any appropriate subject area examination as designated by the State Board of Education.</para><para>(2) Any temporary certificate to teach issued pursuant to this section shall be valid for a period not to exceed two years, during which the holder of such temporary certificate must obtain a certificate to teach pursuant to sections 79-806 to 79-815 by completing the requirements contained in such sections.</para><para>(3) Issuance of a temporary certificate to teach pursuant to this section shall be subject to a criminal history record information check pursuant to section 79-814.01 and payment of any required fees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 88. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>