<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id63">
<sectno id="id64">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id65" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-237"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id67">79-237</statuteno><catchline id="id68">Attendance; application;
cancellation; forms.</catchline><para>(1) For a student to begin
attendance as an option student in an option school district which is not
in a learning community in which the student resides, the student's parent
or legal guardian shall submit an application to the school board of the option
school district between September 1 and March 15 for attendance during the
following and subsequent school years. Applications submitted after March
15 shall contain
a release approval from the resident school district on the application form prescribed and
furnished by the State Department of Education pursuant to subsection (7)
of this section. A district may not accept or approve any applications submitted
after such date without such a release approval. The option school
district shall provide the resident school district with the name of the applicant
on or before April 1 or, in
the case of an application submitted after March 15, within sixty days after
submission. The option school district shall notify, in writing,
the parent or legal guardian of the student, the resident school district,
and the State Department of Education whether the application is accepted
or rejected on or before April 1 or,
in the case of an application submitted after March 15, within sixty days
after submission.</para>
<para>(2) For a student who resides in a learning community to begin
attendance in an option school district which is a member of such learning
community, the student's parent or legal guardian shall submit an application
to the school board of the option school district (a) for any learning community
established prior to February
13, 2009, between February
13, 2009, and April 1, 2009, or (b) for any learning community
established thereafter, between September 1 and March 15. Applications submitted
after such deadlines shall be accompanied by a written release from the resident
school district. Students who reside in a learning community shall only begin
attendance in an option school district which is a member of such learning
community prior to the end of the first full school year for which the option
school district is a member of such learning community. The option school
district shall provide the resident school district with the name of the applicant
within five days after the applicable deadline. The option school district
shall notify, in writing, the parent or legal guardian of the student, the
resident school district, and the State Department of Education whether the
application is accepted or rejected on or before April 10 for applications
submitted for school year 2009-10 and on or before April 1 for applications
submitted for any school year thereafter. A parent or guardian may provide
information on the application regarding the applicant's potential qualification
for free or reduced-price lunches. Any such information provided shall be
subject to verification and shall only be used for the purposes of subsection (4) of section 79-238. Nothing in this subsection
requires a parent or guardian to provide such information. Determinations
about an applicant's qualification for free or reduced-price lunches for purposes
of subsection (4) of section 79-238 shall
be based on any verified information provided on the application. If no such
information is provided, the student shall be presumed not to qualify for
free or reduced-price lunches for the purposes of subsection (4) of
section 79-238.</para>
<para>(3) Applications for students who do not actually attend the
option school district may be withdrawn in good standing upon mutual agreement
by both the resident and option school districts.</para>
<para>(4) No option student shall attend an option school district
for less than one school year unless the student relocates to a different
resident school district, completes requirements for graduation prior to the
end of his or her senior year, transfers to a private or parochial school,
or upon mutual agreement of the resident and option school districts cancels
the enrollment option and returns to the resident school district.</para>
<para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section,
the option student shall attend the option school district until graduation
unless the student relocates in a different resident school district, transfers
to a private or parochial school, or chooses to return to the resident school
district.</para>
<para>(6) In each case of cancellation pursuant to subsections (4)
and (5) of this section, the student's parent or legal guardian shall provide written notification to the school board
of the option school district, the resident school district, and the department on
forms prescribed and furnished by the department under subsection (7) of this
section in advance of such cancellation.</para>
<para>(7) The application and cancellation forms shall be prescribed
and furnished by the State Department of Education.</para>
<para>(8) An option student who subsequently chooses to attend a
private or parochial school shall be automatically accepted to return to either
the resident school district or option school district upon the completion
of the grade levels offered at the private or parochial school. If such student
chooses to return to the option school district, the student's parent or legal
guardian shall submit another application to the school board of the option
school district which shall be automatically accepted, and the deadlines prescribed
in this section shall be waived.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 183, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 843, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 838, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3406; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB62, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>