<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id90"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id92" statutenumber="79-933"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id94">79-933</statuteno><catchline id="id95">Retirement; member; amount of allowance.</catchline><para>(1) Upon retirement under section 79-931, a member or emeritus member shall receive a school retirement allowance which shall consist of the sum of: (a) A savings annuity which shall be the actuarial equivalent, as determined by the retirement board, of the member's accumulated contributions at the time of his or her retirement or, in the case of an emeritus member, the savings annuity fixed by the retirement board at the time of his or her original retirement; and (b) a service annuity to be paid by the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(2) The amount of any individual service annuity for (a) a full-time school employee hired on or before April 1, 1988, who retires with thirty-five or more years of service or who retires under the provisions of disability retirement, (b) a full-time school employee who provided compensated service after April 1, 1988, but prior to July 19, 1996, if the service annuity commences on or after the member's sixty-fifth birthday, who retires with thirty-five or more years of service or who retires under the provisions of disability retirement, or (c) an emeritus member shall be three dollars and fifty cents per month for each year of creditable service commencing with his or her retirement on or after May 19, 1981. For employees not enumerated in subdivision (a) or (b) of this subsection or for employees hired on or after July 19, 1996, if the service annuity commences prior to the member's sixty-fifth birthday, it shall be on an actuarially reduced basis. Each school employee or emeritus member who retired before July 1, 1973, and who is receiving a service annuity as of that date shall have such service annuity adjusted by the increase in the cost of living as determined by the difference between the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers from the date the service annuity commenced and July 1, 1973, except that such annuity shall not exceed three dollars and fifty cents monthly per year of service based on the same number of years of service that is currently being used to determine his or her service annuity. Such increased service annuity shall commence on July 1, 1973.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 219, &#167; 23, p. 645; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2923; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 456, p. 847; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 291, &#167; 4, p. 966; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 315, &#167; 4, p. 1046; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 382, &#167; 6, p. 1326; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 414, &#167; 1, p. 1387; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 495, &#167; 2, p. 1383; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 531, &#167; 2, p. 1674; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 546, &#167; 6, p. 1803; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 735, &#167; 6, p. 2779; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 445, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 248, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 369, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 325, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 549, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 35; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1522; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 568; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1147, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
