
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-850" amended="yes"  id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-850</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">For purposes of sections 79-850 to 79-858:</para><para id="id00">(1) Reorganized school district means: (a) Any expanded or altered school district, organized or altered by any of the means provided by Nebraska law including, but not limited to, the methods provided by the Reorganization of School Districts Act, the Learning Community Reorganization Act, or section 79-407, 79-413, 79-415, or 79-473; or (b) any school district to be formed in the future if the petition or plan for such reorganized school district has been approved pursuant to any of the methods set forth in subdivision (1)(a) of this section when the effective date of such reorganization is prospective. For purposes of this subdivision, a petition or plan shall be deemed approved when the last legal action has been taken, as prescribed in section 79-413 or 79-450, necessary to effect the changes in boundaries as set forth in the petition or plan; and</para><para id="id00">(2) Unified system means a unified system as defined in section 79-4,108 recognized by the State Department of Education pursuant to subsection (3) of such section, which employs certificated staff.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 844, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 662, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 520, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-12,104; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 480; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 347, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 59; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 61. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Learning Community Reorganization Act,</emphasis> see section 79-4,117.</para><para><emphasis>Reorganization of School Districts Act,</emphasis> see section 79-432.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>