<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-217"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-217</statuteno><catchline>School board and governing authority;
student; immunization against certain contagious diseases; exception.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except
as provided in sections 79-221 and 79-222, the school board or board of education
of each school district and the governing authority of each private, denominational,
or parochial school in this state shall require each student to be protected
against measles, mumps, rubella, poliomyelitis, diphtheria, pertussis, and
tetanus by immunization prior to enrollment. Any student who does not comply
with this section shall not be permitted to continue in school until he or
she so complies, except as provided by section 79-222. Each school district
shall make diligent efforts to inform families prior to the date of school
registration of the immunization requirements of this section.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided
in sections 79-221 and 79-222, on and after July 1, 2010, every student entering
the seventh grade shall have a booster immunization containing diphtheria
and tetanus toxoids and an acellular pertussis vaccine which meets the standards
approved by the United States Public Health Service for such biological products,
as such standards existed on January 1, 2009.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in
the Childhood Vaccine Act, the cost of such immunizations shall be borne
by the parent or guardian of each student who is immunized or by the Department
of Health and Human Services for those students whose parent or guardian is
financially unable to meet such cost.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 173, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 546, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 59, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 431, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 128; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-444.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 811; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 301, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 707; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB464, &#167;  1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Childhood Vaccine Act,</emphasis> see section 71-526.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>An unimmunized student's right to attend school on presentation of a properly signed immunization waiver is limited by a school board's authority, under former section 79-4,177(1), to exclude the unimmunized student from school during presence of a disease specified by this section. Maack v. School Dist. of Lincoln, 241 Neb. 847, 491 N.W.2d 341 (1992).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>