<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id883"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-533.04" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>79-533.04</statuteno><catchline>School library materials; access by parent, guardian, or educational decisionmaker; school board adopt policy.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, educational decisionmaker has the same meaning as in section 79-530.</para><para>(2) Each school board of a public school district shall adopt a policy for implementation at the beginning of the 2026-27 school year, relating to the rights of a parent, guardian, or educational decisionmaker to access school library materials. Such policy shall:</para><para>(a) Require the creation of a catalog of all books in the school district's library, categorized by school building, which shall be accessible for viewing by a parent, guardian, or educational decisionmaker of a student attending such school district; and</para><para>(b) Provide the opportunity for a parent, guardian, or educational decisionmaker of a student to be notified when the student of such parent, guardian, or educational decisionmaker checks out a book from the school library by means of a website or application notification or by opting in to email notifications. Such notification shall include:</para><para>(i) The title of the book checked out by the student;</para><para>(ii) The name of the author of the book checked out by the student; and</para><para>(iii) The date the book checked out by the student is due to be returned to the school library.</para><para>(3) This section shall only apply to a school library that is located on school district property and shall not apply to any other public library regardless if such library contracts with a school district for use by students.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB390, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law></legaldoc>