<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-744"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-744</statuteno><catchline>State Board of Vocational Education; additional duties.</catchline><para>The State Board of Vocational Education shall (1) cooperate with the boards authorized by sections 79-738 to 79-744 to establish vocational schools, departments, or courses, (2) cooperate with the United States Department of Education in the administration of federal legislation relating to vocational education and the Nebraska State Plan for Vocational Education, (3) administer the funds provided by the federal government under such federal legislation, by the State of Nebraska, and by donations or contributions for the promotion of vocational education in the public schools of Nebraska, (4) appoint staff members to administer such federal legislation and sections 79-738 to 79-744 for the State of Nebraska, (5) fix the compensation of such personnel and pay such compensation and other necessary expenses of administration from funds appropriated by the Legislature or available federal funds, (6) make studies and investigations relative to vocational education, (7) promote and aid in the establishment of vocational schools, departments, or courses in communities giving training in such subjects and cooperate with local boards in the maintenance of such schools, departments, or courses, (8) prescribe qualifications and provide for the certification of teachers and supervisors of vocational education and related subjects, (9) cooperate in the maintenance of postsecondary training courses for the preparation of teachers and supervisors of vocational education and related subjects or maintain such courses under its own direction and control, and (10) establish and determine by general regulations the qualifications to be possessed by persons engaged in the training of vocational teachers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 267, &#167; 5, p. 1070; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6564; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2214; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2211; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 418, p. 833; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 290, &#167; 7, p. 962; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 313, &#167; 2, p. 1039; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 325, &#167; 6, p. 1010; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 756, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 724, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1090, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1429; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 418; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 347, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>