<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id419">
<sectno id="id420">Sec. 36.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id421" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-527">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id423">79-527</statuteno><catchline id="id424">Dropouts; long-term suspension, expulsion, or excessive absenteeism;
contact with law enforcement officials; report to
Commissioner of Education; required;
copy to learning community coordinating council.</catchline><para>(1) The
superintendent or head administrator of a public school district or a nonpublic
school system shall annually report to the Commissioner of Education in such
detail and on such date as required by the commissioner the number of students
who have dropped out of school. School districts that
are members of learning communities shall also provide the learning community
coordinating council with a copy of such report on or before the date the
report is due to the commissioner.</para>
<para>(2) The superintendent
or head administrator of a public school district or a nonpublic school system
shall report on a monthly basis to the Commissioner of Education as directed
by the commissioner regarding the number of and reason for any long-term suspension,
expulsion, or excessive absenteeism of a student; referral of a student to
the office of the county attorney for excessive absenteeism; or contacting
of law enforcement officials, other than law enforcement officials employed
by or contracted with the school district as school resource officers, by
the district or system relative to a student enrolled in the district or system.
A school district that is a member of a learning community shall also provide
the learning community coordinating council with a copy of such report on
or before the date the report is due to the commissioner.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 520, &#167; 2, p. 1646; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 487, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-449.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 280; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>