<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-854"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-854</statuteno><catchline>Reduction in force; Retirement Incentive Plan; Staff Development Assistance; continued employment; notification; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) If the unification or reorganization of two or more school districts will involve a reduction in force, all certificated employees from the district or districts involved in the unification or reorganization shall have, except as limited by subsection (2) of this section, the option to: (a) Retire under the Retirement Incentive Plan pursuant to section 79-855; (b) terminate employment and receive Staff Development Assistance pursuant to section 79-856; or (c) remain employed by the district subject to personnel policies and staffing requirements of the unified system or reorganized district or districts. Each certificated employee shall be notified in writing of the proposed unification or reorganization, the number of employees which will be reduced, and the availability of the Retirement Incentive Plan and Staff Development Assistance prior to such unification or reorganization. If the unification or reorganization will involve a reduction in force prior to the effective date of the unification or reorganization, the notification shall be made by March 15 of the school year in effect. If the unification or reorganization will not involve a reduction in force prior to the effective date of the unification or reorganization, the notification shall be made at least thirty calendar days prior to the effective date of the unification or reorganization but in no event later than March 15 of the calendar year in which action on the reduction in force will occur. The employee election to retire under the Retirement Incentive Plan or to terminate employment and receive Staff Development Assistance shall be made within fifteen calendar days after receiving the notification, or those options are waived.</para><para>(2) For each unification or reorganization, the number of certificated employees which receive either the Retirement Incentive Plan or Staff Development Assistance shall be limited to the number of certificated employees which are reduced due to the unification or reorganization. If the number of employees electing participation in the Retirement Incentive Plan or Staff Development Assistance exceed the number of employees which will be reduced, selection for participation shall be determined by the date and time of receipt of the employee election. Employee elections which are received first shall be selected, and all certificated employees in all districts involved in the unification or reorganization shall be treated equally in determining such selection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1050, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Reduction-in-force policy,</emphasis> see sections 79-846 to 79-849.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>