
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id345">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id347" statutenumber="79-947"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-947</statuteno><catchline id="id350">Adjusted supplemental
retirement benefit; determination; computation; payment; funding.</catchline>
<para>(1) Commencing October 1, 1988, the retirement board shall
determine an adjusted supplemental retirement benefit to reflect changes in
the cost of living and wage levels that have occurred subsequent to the date
of retirement for each person who is retired from the School Employees Retirement System of the State of
Nebraska or from the retirement system for Class V school districts as provided
by the Class V School Employees Retirement Act with twenty-five or more years
of creditable service as of October 1, 1988.</para>
<para>(2) For each person who qualifies under subsection (1) of
this section, the retirement board shall determine the value of the total
monthly benefit being received from the School Employees Retirement System of the State of
Nebraska or from the retirement system for Class V school districts as provided
by the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and the supplemental benefit
provided by section 79-942 if applicable. From two hundred fifty dollars,
the board shall subtract the total monthly benefit. Such difference, if positive,
shall be the adjusted supplemental retirement benefit and shall be paid to
the retired person each month, except that if this difference is less than
five dollars, a minimum payment of five dollars per month shall be made to
such person. The adjusted supplemental retirement benefit shall be paid to
a retired person during his or her life.</para>
<para>(3) The retirement board may buy a paid-up annuity for a
retired person which guarantees the adjusted supplemental retirement benefit
provided under this section.</para>
<para>(4) The adjusted supplemental retirement benefit provided
under this section shall be funded from the Contingent Account but only from
such income that is attributable to employer and employee contributions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1170, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1566; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 582; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 30.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Class V School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-978.01.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>