<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id256">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id258" statutenumber="79-904.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-904.01</statuteno><catchline id="id261">Board; power
to adjust contributions and benefits.</catchline><para>(1) If the
board determines that the retirement system has previously received contributions
or distributed benefits which for any reason are not in accordance with the
statutory provisions of the School Employees Retirement Act, the board shall
refund contributions, require additional contributions, adjust benefits, or
require repayment of benefits paid. In the event of an overpayment of a benefit,
the board may, in addition to other remedies, offset future benefit payments
by the amount of the prior overpayment, together with regular interest thereon.
In the event of an underpayment of a benefit, the board shall immediately
make payment equal to the deficit amount plus regular interest.</para>
<para>(2) The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
implementing this section, which shall include, but not be limited to, the
following: (a) The procedures for refunding contributions, adjusting future
contributions or benefit payments, and requiring additional contributions
or repayment of benefits; (b) the process for a member, member's beneficiary,
employee, or employer to dispute an adjustment of contributions or benefits;
and (c) notice provided to all affected persons. All notices shall be sent
prior to an adjustment and shall describe the process for disputing an adjustment
of contributions or benefits.</para>
<para>(3) The board
shall not refund contributions made on compensation in excess of the limitations
imposed by subdivision (35) of section 79-902.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 20.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
