<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id386" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-987"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-987</statuteno><catchline id="id389">Employees retirement system;
audit; cost; report.</catchline><para>(1) An annual audit of the affairs of
the retirement system shall be conducted. At the option of the board, such
audit may be conducted by a certified public accountant or the Auditor of
Public Accounts. The costs of such audit shall be paid from funds of the retirement
system. A copy of such audit shall be filed with the Auditor of Public Accounts.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning March 31, 2012, and each March 31 thereafter, if such
retirement plan is a defined benefit plan, the trustees of a retirement system
established pursuant to section 79-979 shall cause to be prepared an annual
report and the administrator shall file the same with the Public Employees
Retirement Board and submit to the members of the Nebraska Retirement Systems
Committee of the Legislature a copy of such report. The report submitted to the committee shall be submitted
electronically. The report shall consist of a full actuarial analysis
of each such retirement plan established pursuant to section 79-979. The analysis
shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public entity
employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy
of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise
to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization offering
investment advice or which provides investment management services to the
retirement plan.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 19, p. 921; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 215, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1050; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 622; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 157.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>