<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id14"  statutenumber="79-777"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-777</statuteno><catchline>Career academy; establishment and
operation; duties; funding; department; define standards and criteria.</catchline>
<para>(1)
Any school district, with the approval of the State Department of Education,
may establish and operate a career academy. The purpose of a career academy
is to provide students with a career-based educational curriculum. A school
district may partner with another school district, an educational service
unit, a learning community, a postsecondary educational institution, or a
private entity in the establishment and operation of a career academy.</para>
<para>(2)
A career academy established pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall:</para>
<para>(a)
Recruit students who seek a career-based curriculum, which curriculum shall
be based on criteria determined by the department;</para><para>(b) Recruit and
hire instructors based on their expertise in career-based education; and</para>
<para>(c)
Provide a rigorous academic curriculum with a transition component to prepare
students for the workforce, including, but not limited to, internships, job
training, and skills training.</para><para>(3) In addition to funding from the establishing
school district or any of the district's partners, a career academy may also
receive private donations for operating expenses.</para><para>(4) The department shall
define standards and criteria for (a) the establishment, evaluation, and continuing
approval of career academies, (b) career-based curriculum utilized by career
academies, (c) the necessary data elements and collection of data pertaining
to career academies, including, but not limited to, the number of students
enrolled in a career academy and their grade levels, and (d) the establishment
of advisory boards consisting of business and education representatives to
provide guidance and direction for the operation of career academies.</para>
<para>(5) The State Board of
Education may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this
section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB870, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>