<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id228"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-979.02" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>79-979.02</statuteno><catchline>Employees retirement system; immunity from liability, when.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning September 1, 2024, the State of Nebraska, the retirement board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, and their respective officers, members, employees, and agents shall be indemnified and held harmless by the school district and board of education from any and all liabilities, claims, suits, losses, damages, and costs that arise from, or are reasonably related to, any conduct, decision, action, inaction, or omission of the board of trustees, the board of education, or the school district or any consequences arising thereof during the course of performing their respective duties and responsibilities for, or actions or services related to or in support of, the retirement system under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act prior to September 1, 2024.</para><para>(2) The school district of a retirement system described under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act shall remain at all times and in all circumstances solely liable for all funding obligations and responsibilities as described in the act.</para><para>(3) At no time and under no circumstances shall the State of Nebraska, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, the retirement board, or any other state entity or its officers, employees, or assigns with duties related to the Class V school employees retirement system be liable for any funding obligations of any Class V school employees retirement system.</para><para>(4) The retirement board shall not be liable for any acts or omissions occurring prior to September 1, 2024, in the administration of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and made at the direction of or by the board of trustees or its employees, the school district or its employees, or the board of education.</para><para>(5) A member of the board of education, the board of trustees, or the retirement board shall not be personally liable for any action related to such board member's retirement duties except in cases of willful dishonesty, gross negligence, or intentional violation of law.</para><para>(6) Except as otherwise provided in this section, the school district shall not be liable for any act or omission in the administration of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act made at the direction of the retirement board or the administrator of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems or its employees on and after September 1, 2024.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>