<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-715"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-715</statuteno><catchline>Eye protective devices; required; when; term, defined; commissioner; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Every student and teacher in schools or other educational institutions shall be required to wear appropriate industrial-quality eye protective devices at all times while participating in or observing the following courses of instruction:</para><para>(a) Vocational, technical, industrial arts, chemical, or chemical-physical, involving exposure to:</para><para>(i) Hot molten metals or other molten materials;</para><para>(ii) Milling, sawing, turning, shaping, cutting, grinding, or stamping of any solid materials;</para><para>(iii) Heat treatment, tempering, or kiln firing of any metal or other materials;</para><para>(iv) Gas or electric arc welding or other forms of welding processes;</para><para>(v) Repair or servicing of any vehicle; or</para><para>(vi) Caustic or explosive materials; and</para><para>(b) Chemical, physical, or combined chemical-physical laboratories involving caustic or explosive materials, hot liquids or solids, injurious radiations, or other hazards not enumerated.</para><para>Such devices shall be furnished by the school or educational institution for all students, teachers, and visitors to shops and laboratories of such institutions.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, unless the context otherwise requires, industrial-quality eye protective devices means devices which meet the standard of the American National Standard Practice for Occupational and Educational Eye and Face Protection, Z 87.1(1979) as approved by the American National Standards Institute, Inc.</para><para>(3) The Commissioner of Education shall prepare and circulate to each public and private educational institution in this state instructions and recommendations for implementing the eye safety provisions of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 999, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-4,144; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 389; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1172, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Postsecondary educational institutions,</emphasis> eye protective devices, see section 85-901.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>