<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id13" statutenumber="79-592"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id15">79-592</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Class V school
district; treasurer; bond or insurance; duties.</catchline><para>The
treasurer of a Class V school district shall receive all taxes of the school
district from the county treasurer. The treasurer of the school district shall
attend all meetings of the board of education of the Class V district when
required to do so, shall prepare and submit in writing a monthly report of
the state of the district's finances, and shall pay school money either upon a warrant signed by the president,
or in the president's absence by the vice president, and countersigned by
the secretary or upon a check
or other instrument drawn upon bank depository funds of the school district.
The treasurer shall also perform such other duties as designated by the board
of education. Before entering into the discharge of his or her duties and
during the entire time he or she so serves, the treasurer shall give bond
or evidence of equivalent insurance coverage payable to the board in such
amount as may be required by the board, but in no event less than two hundred
thousand dollars, conditioned for the faithful discharge of his or her duties
as treasurer of the school district, for the safekeeping and proper disbursement
of all funds and money of the school district received by the treasurer. Such
bond shall be signed by one or more surety companies of recognized responsibility,
to be approved by the board. The cost of the bond or insurance shall be paid
by the school district. Such bond or insurance coverage may be enlarged at
any time the board may deem an enlargement or additional bond or insurance
coverage to be necessary.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1891, c. 45, &#167; 12, p. 321; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 96, &#167; 1, p. 553; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7020; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6651; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2714; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2715; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 297, &#167; 1, p. 912; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 260, p. 778; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 604, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1004.04; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 345; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 380, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>The 1947 amendment to this section was operative prospectively only. School District of Omaha v. Adams, 151 Neb. 741, 39 N.W.2d 550 (1949).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>