<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-907"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-907</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Statement of information; board; powers and duties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1)(a) On or before October 1, 2001, and at least every two years thereafter, the retirement board shall send to each contributing member of the retirement system by first-class mail, a statement of creditable service, reported salary, and other such information as is determined by the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems to be necessary in calculating the member's retirement benefit.</para><para id="id00">(b) If the member requests a modification or correction of his or her statement of information, the member shall provide documentation to the board supporting such modification or correction and provide clear and convincing evidence that the statement is in error. The board shall, within sixty days after receipt of the documentation supporting the modification or correction, determine whether the member has proven by clear and convincing evidence that the statement shall be modified or corrected. If the board determines that the member has provided clear and convincing evidence, the board shall modify or correct the statement. If the board determines that the member has not provided clear and convincing evidence, the board shall deny the modification or correction. In either case, the board shall notify the member. The member may appeal the decision of the board pursuant to section 79-950.</para><para id="id00">(c) The board has an ongoing fiduciary duty to modify or correct a member's statement if the board discovers an error in the information it has on record. A modification or correction shall be made within sixty days after the error is brought to the attention of the board.</para><para id="id00">(2) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations and prescribe the necessary forms to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1192, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 961, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 144, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1005, &#167; 22. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>