<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id46">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id48" statutenumber="79-760.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>79-760.05</statuteno><catchline id="id51">Statewide system
for tracking individual student achievement; State Board of Education; duties;
school districts; provide data; analysis and reports.</catchline><para>(1)
The State Board of Education shall implement a statewide system for tracking
individual student achievement, using the student identifier system of the
State Department of Education, that can be aggregated to track student progress
by demographic characteristics, including, but not limited to, race, poverty,
high mobility, attendance, and limited English proficiency, on available measures
of student achievement which include, but need not be limited to, national
assessment instruments and state assessment instruments. Such a system shall
be designed so as to aggregate student data by available educational input
characteristics, which may include class size, teacher education, teacher
experience, special education, early childhood programs, federal programs,
and other targeted education programs. School districts shall provide the
department with individual student achievement data from assessment instruments
required pursuant to section 79-760.03 in order to implement the statewide
system.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall
annually analyze and report on student achievement for the state, each school
district, and each learning community aggregated by the demographic characteristics
described in subsection (1) of this section. The department shall report the
findings to the Governor, the Legislature, school districts, educational service
units, and each learning community. Such analysis shall include aggregated
data that would indicate differences in achievement due to available educational
input characteristics described in subsection (1) of this section. Such analysis
shall include indicators of progress toward state achievement goals for students
in poverty, limited English proficient students, and highly mobile students.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB653, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1157, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB333, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
