<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id36" statutenumber="79-8,137"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-8,137</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program; eligible student; contract requirements; loan payments; suspension; loan forgiveness; amount.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Prior to receiving any money from a loan pursuant to the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program, an eligible student shall enter into a contract with the department. Such contract shall be exempt from the requirements of sections 73-501 to 73-510.</para><para>(b) For eligible students who applied for the first time prior to April 23, 2009, the contract shall require that if (i) the borrower is not employed as a teacher in Nebraska for a time period equal to the number of years required for loan forgiveness pursuant to subsection (2) of this section and is not enrolled as a full-time student in a graduate program within six months after obtaining an undergraduate degree for which a loan from the program was obtained or (ii) the borrower does not complete the requirements for graduation within five consecutive years after receiving the initial loan under the program, then the loan must be repaid, with interest at the rate fixed pursuant to section 45-103 accruing as of the date the borrower signed the contract, and an appropriate penalty as determined by the department may be assessed. If a borrower fails to remain enrolled at an eligible institution or otherwise fails to meet the requirements of an eligible student, repayment of the loan shall commence within six months after such change in eligibility. The State Board of Education may by rules and regulations provide for exceptions to the conditions of repayment pursuant to this subdivision based upon mitigating circumstances.</para><para>(c) For eligible students who apply for the first time on or after April 23, 2009, the contract shall require that if (i) the borrower is not employed as a full-time teacher teaching in an approved or accredited school in Nebraska and teaching at least a portion of the time in the shortage area for which the loan was received for a time period equal to the number of years required for loan forgiveness pursuant to subsection (3) of this section or is not enrolled as a full-time student in a graduate program within six months after obtaining an undergraduate degree for which a loan from the program was obtained or (ii) the borrower does not complete the requirements for graduation within five consecutive years after receiving the initial loan under the program, then the loan shall be repaid with interest at the rate fixed pursuant to section 45-103 accruing as of the date the borrower signed the contract and actual collection costs as determined by the department. If a borrower fails to remain enrolled at an eligible institution or otherwise fails to continue to be an eligible student, repayment of the loan shall commence within six months after such change in eligibility. The State Board of Education may by rule and regulation provide for exceptions to the conditions of repayment pursuant to this subdivision based upon mitigating circumstances.</para><para>(2) If the borrower applied for the first time prior to April 23, 2009, and (a) successfully completes the teacher education program and becomes certified pursuant to sections 79-806 to 79-815, (b) becomes employed as a teacher in this state within six months of becoming certified, and (c) otherwise meets the requirements of the contract, payments shall be suspended for the number of years that the borrower is required to remain employed as a teacher in this state under the contract. For each year that the borrower teaches in Nebraska pursuant to the contract, payments shall be forgiven in an amount equal to the amount borrowed for one year, except that if the borrower teaches in a school district that is in a local system classified as very sparse as defined in section 79-1003 or teaches in a school district in which at least forty percent of the students are poverty students as defined in section 79-1003, payments shall be forgiven each year in an amount equal to the amount borrowed for two years.</para><para>(3)(a) If the borrower applies for the first time on or after April 23, 2009, and (i) successfully completes the teacher education program and major for which the borrower is receiving a forgivable loan pursuant to the program and becomes certified pursuant to sections 79-806 to 79-815 with an endorsement in the shortage area for which the loan was received, (ii) becomes employed as a full-time teacher teaching at least a portion of the time in the shortage area for which the loan was received in an approved or accredited school in this state within six months of becoming certified, and (iii) otherwise meets the requirements of the contract, payments shall be suspended for the number of years that the borrower is required to remain employed as a teacher in this state under the contract.</para><para>(b) Beginning after the first two years of teaching full-time in Nebraska following graduation for the degree for which the loan was received, for each year that the borrower teaches full-time in Nebraska pursuant to the contract, the loan shall be forgiven in an amount equal to three thousand dollars, except that if the borrower teaches full-time in a school district that is in a local system classified as very sparse as defined in section 79-1003, teaches in a school building that provides free meals to all students pursuant to the community eligibility provision, teaches in a school building in which at least forty percent of the formula students are poverty students as defined in section 79-1003, or teaches in an accredited or approved private school in Nebraska in which at least forty percent of the enrolled students qualified for free lunches as determined by the most recent data available from the department, payments shall be forgiven each year in an amount equal to six thousand dollars.</para><para>(4) Beginning on August 1, 2022, if the borrower provides service as a pre-service teacher intern for a full academic semester as part of a clinical experience within an accredited or approved public, private, denominational, or parochial school in Nebraska and subsequently passes all related semester requirements, then the loan shall be forgiven in an amount equal to one thousand dollars for such borrower.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1399, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB547, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB858, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB497, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB519, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB525, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1218, &#167; 16. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>