<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 9.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id6" statutenumber="79-575"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">79-575</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Secretary; disbursements;
how made.</catchline><para>The secretary of a school district shall
draw and sign all orders upon the treasurer for all money to be disbursed
by the district and all warrants upon the county treasurer for money raised
for district purposes or apportioned to the district by the county treasurer
and shall present the same to the president to be countersigned. No warrant, check, or other instrument drawn upon
bank depository funds of the district shall be issued until so
countersigned. No warrant,
check, or other instrument drawn upon bank depository funds of the district shall
be countersigned by the president until the amount for which it is
drawn is written upon its face. Facsimile signatures of board members may
be used, and a person or persons delegated by the board may sign and validate
all warrants, checks, and other
instruments drawn upon bank depository funds of the district.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision IV, &#167; 16, p. 350; </para><para>Laws 1883, c. 72, &#167; 8, p. 292; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6778; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6319; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-416; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-418; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 89, p. 722; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 315, &#167; 6, p. 976; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 734, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-450; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 328; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 9.</para></source><annotation><para>District warrants do not possess qualities of negotiable instruments. State ex rel. Brandeis &amp; Sons v. Melcher, 87 Neb. 359, 127 N.W. 241 (1910).</para><para>Mandamus will lie to compel moderator to sign orders. Montgomery v. State ex rel. Thompson, 35 Neb. 655, 53 N.W. 568 (1892).</para><para>Endorsee takes subject to equities. School Dist. No. 2 of Dixon County v. Stough, 4 Neb. 357 (1876).</para><para>Demand on treasurer should be accompanied by proper order. State ex rel. McMillan v. Hodge, 4 Neb. 265 (1876).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>