<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-983"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-983</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Employees retirement system; administrator; appointment; termination; retirement system staff.</catchline><para>(1) Until July 1, 2021, the administrator of the retirement system shall be appointed by the board of trustees and approved by the board of education and shall serve at the pleasure of the board of trustees. Beginning July 1, 2021, the administrator of the retirement system shall be appointed by the board of education. The administrator shall hire, dismiss, and otherwise supervise the other staff of the retirement system as approved and directed by the board, shall keep the minutes and records of the retirement system, shall be the executive officer in charge of the administration of the detailed affairs of the retirement system, and shall perform such other duties as may be assigned by the board. The administrator and retirement system staff shall be employees of the Class V school district, with compensation and the benefits as available to school district employees determined by the board. The retirement system shall reimburse the Class V school district for all employee costs of salary, employment taxes, and benefits provided to the administrator and retirement system staff. The administrator shall serve as a nonvoting, ex officio member of the council and shall not be deemed a fiduciary of the council.</para><para>(2) Effective September 1, 2024, the position of the administrator and all retirement system staff positions shall terminate. The administrator duties shall be assumed by the director appointed by the retirement board pursuant to section 84-1503.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 6, p. 915; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 350, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1037; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 618; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>