<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id287">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id289" statutenumber="79-926"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-926</statuteno><catchline id="id292">Retirement system;
members; statement of service record; requirements for prior service credit;
exception; reemployment; military service; credit; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Under such rules and regulations as the retirement board adopts
and promulgates, each person who was a school employee at any time prior to
the establishment of the retirement system and who becomes a member of the
retirement system shall, within two years after becoming a member, file a
detailed statement of all service as a school employee rendered by him or
her prior to the date of establishment of the retirement system. In order
to qualify for prior service credit toward a service annuity, a school employee,
unless temporarily out of service for further professional education, for
service in the armed forces, or for temporary disability, must have completed
four years of service on a part-time or full-time basis during the five calendar
years immediately preceding July 1, 1945, or have completed eighteen years
out of the last twenty-five years prior to July 1, 1945, full time or part
time, and two years out of the five years immediately preceding July 1, 1945,
full time or part time, or such school employee must complete, unless temporarily
out of service for further professional education, for service in the armed
forces, or for temporary disability, four years of service within the five
calendar years immediately following July 1, 1945. In order to qualify for
prior service credit toward a service annuity, a school employee who becomes
a member of the retirement
system on or before September 30, 1951, or from July 1, 1945,
to the date of becoming a member shall have been continuously employed in
a public school in Nebraska operating under any other regularly established
retirement or pension system.</para>
<para>(2) Any person who, after having served or signing a contract
to serve as a school employee, entered into and served or enters into and
serves in the armed forces of the United States during a declared emergency
or was drafted under a federal mandatory draft law into the armed forces of
the United States during a time of peace, as described and prescribed under
such rules and regulations as the retirement board adopts and promulgates,
and who, within three calendar years after honorable discharge or honorable
separation from active duty or within one year from the date of completion
of training provided in the federal Servicemen's Readjustment Act of 1944
or the federal Veterans' Readjustment Assistance
Act of 1952, became or becomes a school employee shall be credited, in determining
benefits due such member from the retirement system, for a maximum of five
years of the time actually served in the armed forces as if such person had
been a school employee throughout such time.</para>
<para>(3) Under such rules and regulations as the retirement board
adopts and promulgates, any school employee who is reemployed on or after
December 12, 1994, pursuant to 38 U.S.C. 4301 et seq., shall be treated as
not having incurred a break in service by reason of his or her period of military
service. Such military service shall be credited for purposes of determining
the nonforfeitability of the member's accrued benefits and the accrual of
benefits under the plan. The employer shall be liable for funding any obligation
of the plan to provide benefits based upon such period of military service.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 219, &#167; 15, p. 643; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2915; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 449, p. 845; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 291, &#167; 2, p. 965; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 316, &#167; 1, p. 1048; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 236, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1515; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 561; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 23.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
