<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id355" statutenumber="79-958"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>79-958</statuteno><catchline id="id358">Employee; employer; required deposits and contributions.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning on September 1, 2012, for the purpose of providing the funds to pay for formula annuities, every employee shall be required to deposit in the School Retirement Fund nine and seventy-eight hundredths percent of compensation. Such deposits shall be transmitted at the same time and in the same manner as required employer contributions.</para><para>(2) For the purpose of providing the funds to pay for formula annuities, every employer shall be required to deposit in the School Retirement Fund one hundred one percent of the required contributions of the school employees of each employer. Such deposits shall be transmitted to the retirement board at the same time and in the same manner as such required employee contributions.</para><para>(3) The employer shall pick up the member contributions required by this section for all compensation paid on or after January 1, 1986, and the contributions so picked up shall be treated as employer contributions pursuant to section 414(h)(2) of the Internal Revenue Code in determining federal tax treatment under the code and shall not be included as gross income of the member until such time as they are distributed or made available. The contributions, although designated as member contributions, shall be paid by the employer in lieu of member contributions. The employer shall pay these member contributions from the same source of funds which is used in paying earnings to the member. The employer shall pick up these contributions by a compensation deduction through a reduction in the cash compensation of the member. Member contributions picked up shall be treated for all purposes of the School Employees Retirement Act in the same manner and to the same extent as member contributions made prior to the date picked up.</para><para>(4) The employer shall pick up the member contributions made through irrevocable payroll deduction authorizations pursuant to sections 79-921 and 79-933.03 to 79-933.06, and the contributions so picked up shall be treated as employer contributions in the same manner as contributions picked up under subsection (3) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 219, &#167; 32, p. 649; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2932; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 465, p. 851; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 291, &#167; 6, p. 968; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 414, &#167; 2, p. 1388; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 546, &#167; 9, p. 1806; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 457, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 353, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 325, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 160, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1170, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 700, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1531; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 593; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 503, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB596, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB187, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB382, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB553, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>