
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id733"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-297"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-297</statuteno><catchline>Youth organization; provide information, services, and activities; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) School has the same meaning as in section 79-101;</para><para>(b) School district has the same meaning as in section 79-101; and</para><para>(c) Youth organization means a corporation chartered by Congress and listed in 36 U.S.C. Subtitle II, Part B, as of January 1, 2023.</para><para>(2)(a) Each school district shall, upon request, allow a representative of any youth organization to provide (i) oral or written information to the students of such school district regarding the youth organization and how such youth organization furthers the educational interests and civic involvement of students in a manner consistent with good citizenship and (ii) services and activities to any student of such school district who is a member of such youth organization.</para><para>(b) Each requesting youth organization shall be permitted to provide such information, services, and activities in a school building or on the school grounds of a school in each school district at least once during each school year.</para><para>(3) Each school district shall make a good faith effort to select a date, time, and location for each requesting youth organization to provide such information, services, or activities that is mutually agreeable to the school district and to the youth organization. Oral information provided under subdivision (2)(a)(i) of this section may only be provided during noninstructional time.</para><para>(4) Prior to allowing a representative of a youth organization to provide information, services, or activities at a school pursuant to this section, such representative shall be subject to a background check. Except as otherwise provided by this section or by the rules and regulations of the Nebraska State Patrol, the parameters of the background check shall be determined by the relevant school district. A school district may prohibit any representative of a youth organization that has been convicted of a felony from providing information, services, or activities pursuant to this section at any school in such school district. Each representative of a youth organization is responsible for all costs associated with obtaining such background check.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to supersede a parent's ability to exercise any rights such parent has under a school district policy established pursuant to section 79-531.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 126. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>