<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-479" amended="yes"  id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-479</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Change of boundaries; order; transfer of assets and liabilities.</catchline><para id="id00">(1)(a) Beginning January 1, 1992, any school district boundaries changed by the means provided by Nebraska law, but excluding the method provided by sections 79-407 and 79-473 to 79-475, shall be made only upon an order issued by the State Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts or county clerk.</para><para id="id00">(b) The order issued by the state committee shall be certified to the county clerk of each county in which boundaries are changed and shall also be certified to the State Department of Education. Whenever the order changes the boundaries of a school district due to the transfer of land, the county assessor, the Property Tax Administrator, and the State Department of Education shall be provided with the legal description and a map of the parcel of land which is transferred. Such order shall be issued no later than June 1 and shall have an effective date no later than August 1 of the same year. For purposes of determining school district counts pursuant to sections 79-524 and 79-578 and calculating state aid allocations pursuant to the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act, any change in school district boundaries with an effective date between June 1 and August 1 of any year shall be considered effective July 1 of such year.</para><para id="id00">(2) Unless otherwise provided by state law or by the terms of a reorganization plan or petition which is consistent with state law, all assets, including budget authority as provided in sections 79-1023 to 79-1030, and liabilities, except bonded obligations, of school districts merged, dissolved, or annexed shall be transferred to the receiving district or districts on the basis of the proportionate share of assessed valuation received at the time of reorganization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 604, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 228; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 347, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 394, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 50; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 26. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1001.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>