<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-241"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-241</statuteno><catchline>Transportation; fee authorized; reimbursement; when.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, section 79-611 does not apply to the transportation of an option student. The parent or legal guardian of the option student shall be responsible for required transportation. A school district may, upon mutual agreement with the parent or legal guardian of an option student, provide transportation to the option student on the same basis as provided for resident students. The school district may charge the parents of each option student transported a fee sufficient to recover the additional costs of such transportation.</para><para>(2) Parents or guardians of option students who qualify for free lunches shall be eligible for transportation reimbursement as described in section 79-611, except that they shall be reimbursed at the rate of one hundred forty-two and one-half percent of the mandatorily established mileage rate provided in section 81-1176 for each mile actually and necessarily traveled on each day of attendance by which the distance traveled one way from the residence of such student to the schoolhouse exceeds three miles. The State Department of Education shall reimburse the option school district for transportation expenses paid to the parents of qualifying option students or incurred in actual transportation of qualifying option students. If a parent or guardian of a qualifying option student has an agreement with the option school district for the provision of transportation, the department shall reimburse the option school district only if option students who are not eligible for transportation reimbursement are charged fees for transportation, and reimbursement shall be only for the actual miles traveled one way beyond the normal transportation route at the rate described in this subsection. Reimbursement shall be made on or before June 30 for expenses incurred during the current school year. If sufficient funds are not appropriated to fully fund the provisions of this section, the department shall make a proportionate reduction in each payment made pursuant to this section.</para><para>(3) For option students verified as having a disability as defined in section 79-1118.01, the transportation services set forth in section 79-1129 shall be provided by the resident school district. The department shall reimburse the resident school district for the cost of transportation in accordance with section 79-1144.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 183, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 843, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 207, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 838, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 69; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3410; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>