<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-532"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-532</statuteno><catchline>Involvement of parents, guardians, and educational decisionmakers; policy; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The policy required by section 79-531 shall include, but need not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) How the school district will provide access to parents, guardians, or educational decisionmakers concerning textbooks; tests; activities information; digital materials; websites or applications used for learning; training materials for teachers, administrators, and staff; procedures for the review and approval of training materials, learning materials, and activities; and other curriculum materials used in the school district;</para><para>(b) How the school district will accommodate requests by parents, guardians, or educational decisionmakers to attend and monitor courses, assemblies, counseling sessions, and other instructional activities;</para><para>(c) Under what circumstances parents, guardians, or educational decisionmakers may ask that their children be excused from testing, classroom instruction, learning materials, activities, guest speaker events, and other school experiences the parents, guardians, or educational decisionmakers may find objectionable;</para><para>(d) How the school district will provide access to records of students;</para><para>(e) What the school district's testing policy will be; and</para><para>(f) How the school district participates in surveys of students and the right of parents, guardians, or educational decisionmakers to remove their children from such surveys.</para><para>(2) Nothing in this section shall be construed to require disclosure of information in violation of the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974, as amended, 20 U.S.C. 1232g, or any federal regulations and applicable guidelines adopted in accordance with such act, as such act, regulations, and guidelines existed on January 1, 2024.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1161, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-4,244; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 285; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB71, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>