
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-989"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-989</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Employees retirement system; board of education; records available; administrator; powers and duties; information not considered public record.</catchline><para>(1) The board of education shall have available records showing the name, address, title, social security number, beneficiary records, annual compensation, sex, date of birth, length of creditable and noncreditable service in hours, standard hours, and contract days, bargaining unit, and annual contributions of each employee entitled to membership in the retirement system and such other information as may be reasonably requested by the board of trustees until September 1, 2024, and by the retirement board beginning September 1, 2024, regarding such member as may be necessary for actuarial study and valuation and the administration of the retirement system. This information shall be available in a timely manner to the board or retirement board, as applicable, upon request.</para><para>(2) Beginning September 1, 2024:</para><para>(a)(i) The administrator of the retirement system shall keep a complete record of all members with respect to name, current address, age, contributions, and any other facts and information as may be necessary in the administration of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. The information in the records shall be provided by an employer in an accurate and verifiable form, as specified by the administrator; and</para><para>(ii) The administrator shall, from time to time, carry out testing procedures pursuant to section 84-1512 to verify the accuracy of such facts and information. For the purpose of obtaining such facts and information, the administrator shall have access to the records of an employer and the holder of the records shall comply with a request by the administrator for access by providing such facts and information to the administrator in a timely manner. A certified copy of a birth certificate or delayed birth certificate shall be prima facie evidence of the age of the person named in the certificate;</para><para>(b) An employer and every employee shall send to the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, as specified in this section, upon request and in the manner required by the director, such information as he or she may require (i) for the identification of employees and (ii) for the determination of the membership of the retirement system and the obligations of an employer and employee to the retirement system; and</para><para>(c) The administrator shall develop and implement an employer education program using principles generally accepted by public employee retirement systems so an employer has the knowledge and information necessary to prepare and file reports as the retirement board requires.</para><para>(3) The information maintained by the board of education and obtained from the board by the board of trustees or information obtained and maintained by the retirement board for the administration of the retirement system pursuant to this section shall not be considered public records subject to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, except that the following information shall be considered public records: The member's name, the date the member's participation in the retirement system commenced, and the date the member's participation in the retirement system ended, if applicable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 11, p. 917; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1042; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 624; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB33, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 22. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>