<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-473" amended="yes"  id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>79-473</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class III school district; annexed school district territory; negotiation; criteria.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) If the territory annexed by a change of boundaries of a city or village which lies within a Class III school district as provided in section 79-407 has been part of a Class IV or Class V school district prior to such annexation, a merger of the annexed territory with the Class III school district shall become effective only if the merger is approved by a majority of the members of the school board of the Class IV or V school district and a majority of the members of the school board of the Class III school district within ninety days after the effective date of the annexation ordinance, except that a merger shall not become effective pursuant to this section if such merger involves a school district that is a member of a learning community.</para><para id="id00">(2) Notwithstanding subsection (1) of this section, when territory which lies within a Class III school district or which does not lie within a Class IV or V school district is annexed by a city or village pursuant to section 79-407, the affected school board of the city or village school district and the affected school board or boards serving the territory subject to the annexation ordinance shall meet within thirty days after the effective date of the annexation ordinance if neither school district is a member of a learning community and negotiate in good faith as to which school district shall serve the annexed territory and the effective date of any transfer. During the process of negotiation, the affected boards shall consider the following criteria:</para><para id="id00">(a) The educational needs of the students in the affected school districts;</para><para id="id00">(b) The economic impact upon the affected school districts;</para><para id="id00">(c) Any common interests between the annexed or platted area and the affected school districts and the community which has zoning jurisdiction over the area; and</para><para id="id00">(d) Community educational planning.</para><para id="id00">If no agreement has been reached within ninety days after the effective date of the annexation ordinance, the territory shall transfer to the school district of the annexing city or village ten days after the expiration of such ninety-day period unless an affected school district petitions the district court within the ten-day period and obtains an order enjoining the transfer and requiring the boards of the affected school districts to continue negotiation. The court shall issue the order upon a finding that the affected board or boards have not negotiated in good faith based on one or more of the criteria listed in this subsection. The district court shall require no bond or other surety as a condition for any preliminary injunctive relief. If no agreement is reached after such order by the district court and additional negotiations, the annexed territory shall become a part of the school district of the annexing city or village.</para><para id="id00">(3) Whenever an application for approval of a final plat or replat is filed for territory which lies within the zoning jurisdiction of a city of the first or second class and does not lie within the boundaries of a Class IV or V school district, the boundaries of a school district that is a member of a learning community, the boundaries of any county in which a city of the metropolitan class is located, or the boundaries of any county that has a contiguous border with a city of the metropolitan class, the affected school board of the school district within the city of the first or second class or its representative and the affected board or boards serving the territory subject to the final plat or replat or their representative shall meet within thirty days after such application and negotiate in good faith as to which school district shall serve the platted or replatted territory and the effective date of any transfer based upon the criteria prescribed in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para id="id00">If no agreement has been reached prior to the approval of the final plat or replat, the territory shall transfer to the school district of the city of the first or second class upon the filing of the final plat unless an affected school district petitions the district court within ten days after approval of the final plat or replat and obtains an order enjoining the transfer and requiring the affected boards to continue negotiation. The court shall issue the order upon a finding that the affected board or boards have not negotiated in good faith based on one or more of the criteria listed in subsection (2) of this section. The district court shall require no bond or other surety as a condition for any preliminary injunctive relief. If no agreement is reached after such order by the district court and additional negotiations, the platted or replatted territory shall become a part of the school district of the city of the first or second class.</para><para id="id00">For purposes of this subsection, plat and replat apply only to (a) vacant land, (b) land under cultivation, or (c) any plat or replat of land involving a substantive change in the size or configuration of any lot or lots.</para><para id="id00">(4) Notwithstanding any other provisions of this section, all negotiated agreements relative to boundaries or to real or personal property of school districts reached by the affected school boards shall be valid and binding, except that such agreements shall not be binding on reorganization plans pursuant to the Learning Community Reorganization Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 222; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 345, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 48; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 25. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Learning Community Reorganization Act,</emphasis> see section 79-4,117.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Annexation of territory</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Annexation of territory</emphasis></para><para>The proviso of this section distinguishes only between territory annexed to a Class III, IV, V, or VI district by petition, and territory which was a part of the original district or later became a part of it by means other than by petition. The proviso does not distinguish between different methods of creation of school districts. State ex rel. Halloran v. Hawes, 203 Neb. 405, 279 N.W.2d 96 (1979).</para><para>Apportionment of assets of school districts upon partial or complete merger, division, or annexation decided. School Dist. No. 74 of Hall County v. School Dist. of Grand Island, 186 Neb. 728, 186 N.W.2d 485 (1971).</para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para>Annexation by city council resolution in compliance with a subdivision ordinance adopted by the city under section 19-916 constitutes a declaration of boundaries of the city by ordinance within the meaning of former section 79-801. The effective date of the city annexation ordinance is the date of the city council resolution of approval. Northwest High School Dist. No. 82 of Hall and Merrick Counties v. Hessel, 210 Neb. 219, 313 N.W.2d 656 (1981).</para><para>An action to enjoin a school district or part thereof, consequent upon annexation of territory by a city of the first class, is barred by the statute of limitations unless brought within one year from effective date of annexation ordinance. School Dist. No. 127 of Lincoln County v. Simpson, 191 Neb. 164, 214 N.W.2d 251 (1974).</para><para>Effect of annexation upon school district boundaries gave owner of land purportedly annexed standing to contest validity of annexation ordinances. Doolittle v. County of Lincoln, 191 Neb. 159, 214 N.W.2d 248 (1974).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Subsection (4) of this section does not violate either the U.S. Constitution or the Constitution of the State of Nebraska. School Dist. No. 46 of Sarpy County v. City of Bellevue, 224 Neb. 543, 400 N.W.2d 229 (1987).</para><para>Former section 79-801.02 is limited to provisions of this section, and is not applicable to school district boundary changes under other statutes. Corcoran v. Boone County Board of Equalization, 196 Neb. 363, 243 N.W.2d 60 (1976).</para><para>Merger not even in existence until required approval forthcoming. School Dist. of Bellevue v. Strawn, 185 Neb. 392, 176 N.W.2d 42 (1970).</para><para>Plan of government of school district organized under this article is representative in form. State ex rel. Strange v. School District of Nebraska City, 150 Neb. 109, 33 N.W.2d 358 (1948).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>