<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id408" statutenumber="79-992"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-992</statuteno><catchline id="id411">Employees retirement system; termination of employment; refunds; reemployment; separation from service; return to work.</catchline><para>(1) A member who has five years or more of creditable service, excluding years of prior service acquired pursuant to section 79-990, 79-991, 79-994, 79-995, or 79-997, and who terminates his or her employment may elect to leave his or her contributions in the retirement system, in which event he or she shall receive a retirement allowance at normal retirement age based on the annuity earned to the date of such termination of employment. Such member may elect to receive a retirement allowance at early retirement age if such member retires at an early retirement date. Such annuity shall be adjusted in accordance with section 79-9,100. Upon termination of employment, except on account of retirement, a member shall be entitled to receive refunds as follows: (a) An amount equal to the accumulated contributions to the retirement system by the member; and (b) any contributions made to a previously existing system which were refundable under the terms of that system. Any member receiving a refund of contributions shall thereby forfeit and relinquish all accrued rights in the retirement system including all accumulated creditable service, except that if any member who has withdrawn his or her contributions as provided in this section reenters the service of the district and again becomes a member of the retirement system, he or she may restore any or all money previously received by him or her as a refund, including the interest on the amount of the restored refund for the period of his or her absence from the district's service as determined using the interest rate for interest on such restored refunds, and he or she shall then again receive credit for that portion of service which the restored money represents. Such restoration may be made as the board may direct until September 1, 2024, and as the retirement board may direct beginning September 1, 2024, through direct payments to the system or on an installment basis pursuant to a binding irrevocable payroll deduction authorized between the member and the school district over a period of not to exceed five years from the date of reemployment. Interest on delayed payments shall be at the rate of interest for determining interest on delayed payments by members to the retirement system. Creditable service may be purchased only in one-tenth-year increments, starting with the most recent years' salary.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 79-992.01:</para><para>(a)(i) A retired member, or a member described in subdivision (2)(c) or (d) of this subsection, who returns to employment as or again becomes an employee of the school district shall again participate in the retirement system as a new member and shall make contributions to the retirement system commencing upon reemployment as an employee.</para><para>(ii) The retirement annuity of a retired member who returns to employment with the school district shall continue to be paid by the retirement system. A retired member who returns to employment as an employee of the school district shall receive creditable service only for service performed after his or her return to employment and in no event shall creditable service which accrues or the compensation paid to the member after such return to employment after retirement increase the amount of the member's original retirement annuity;</para><para>(b) Upon termination of employment of the reemployed member, the member shall receive in addition to the retirement annuity which commenced at the time of the previous retirement (i) if the member has accrued five years or more of creditable service after his or her return to employment, excluding years of prior service acquired pursuant to section 79-990, 79-991, 79-994, 79-995, or 79-997, a retirement annuity as provided in section 79-999 or 79-9,100, as applicable, calculated solely on the basis of creditable service and final average compensation accrued and earned after the member's return to employment after his or her original retirement, and as adjusted to reflect any payment in other than the normal form or (ii) if the member has not accrued five years or more of creditable service after his or her return to employment, a refund equal to the member's accumulated contributions which were credited to the member after the member's return to employment. In no event shall the member's creditable service which accrued prior to a previous retirement be considered as part of the member's creditable service after his or her return to employment for any purpose of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act;</para><para>(c) A member who experiences a separation from service but has not submitted a retirement application or request for distribution pursuant to this section or as described in subdivision (32) of section 79-978, or received a retirement benefit, disability retirement benefit, or refund may return to work as a temporary employee, substitute employee, or volunteer. Such a temporary employee, substitute employee, or volunteer:</para><para>(i) Shall be deemed to have incurred a termination of employment for purposes of section 79-991;</para><para>(ii) Shall not be deemed to have incurred a termination of employment for purposes of this section or section 79-992.01, 79-9,105, or 79-9,106, or for any other purposes under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act, and shall not be eligible to receive a retirement benefit, disability retirement benefit, or distribution pursuant to this section, until the member incurs a termination of employment as described in subdivision (42) of section 79-978; and</para><para>(iii) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(a)(i) of this section, shall not be eligible to contribute to the retirement system pursuant to section 79-9,113 or earn membership service credit in the retirement system as described in subdivision (23) of section 79-978; and</para><para>(d)(i) A member who experiences a separation from service and has submitted a retirement application or request for distribution pursuant to this section or as described in subdivision (32) of section 79-978, or received a retirement benefit, disability retirement benefit, or distribution, shall not be deemed to have incurred a termination of employment if the member subsequently returns to work for the district within one hundred eighty days after separating from service, unless such work is limited to:</para><para>(A) Bona fide unpaid voluntary service;</para><para>(B) Work performed as a substitute employee on an intermittent basis; or</para><para>(C) Work as a temporary employee following a bona fide separation of service of not less than thirty calendar days and which is provided to accomplish a specific purpose or task for a limited period not to exceed one year.</para><para>(ii) For purposes of subdivision (2)(d) of this section:</para><para>(A) Intermittent basis means work provided on a day-to-day basis that is not greater than eight days of work during a calendar month; and</para><para>(B) Day of work means any length of work as a substitute employee provided during a single calendar day.</para><para>(iii) The one-hundred-eighty-day period described in subdivision (2)(d)(i) of this section begins on the later of:</para><para>(A) The date the member experienced a bona fide separation from service of all employment as an employee with the school district; or</para><para>(B) The date the board receives the member's retirement application or request for distribution as described in subdivision (32) of section 79-978.</para><para>(iv) A member may seek a determination from the administrator that it has been at least one hundred eighty days since the member satisfied the requirements described in this subdivision (2)(d). The administrator shall make such determination if the member produces clear and convincing evidence that is received by the administrator within forty-five days after the later of:</para><para>(A) The date the member experienced a bona fide separation of service of all employment as an employee with the district; or</para><para>(B) The date the board receives the member's retirement application or request for distribution as described in subdivision (32) of section 79-978.</para><para>(v) A member may appeal the administrator's determination to the board within thirty days after the determination by the administrator. The board's determination on appeal shall be final and shall not be appealable to any court.</para><para>(3) In the event a member is entitled to receive a refund of contributions pursuant to subsection (1) or subdivision (2)(b)(ii) of this section in an amount greater than one thousand dollars, if the member does not elect to have the refund paid directly to himself or herself or transferred to an eligible retirement plan designated by the member as a direct rollover pursuant to section 79-998, then the refund of contributions shall be paid in a direct rollover to an individual retirement plan as designated by the board until September 1, 2024, and as designated by the retirement board beginning September 1, 2024.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 18, p. 920; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 321, &#167; 2, p. 992; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 490, &#167; 3, p. 1565; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 544, &#167; 3, p. 1789; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1116, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 131, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 215, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 298, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 551, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 107, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1049; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 627; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB198, &#167; 14. </para><effectivedate>March 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>