<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-986"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>79-986</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Employees retirement system; school district as treasurer; when; duties; State Treasurer as treasurer; when; duties.</catchline><para>Prior to January 1, 2017, the school district, if there is only one Class V school district in the retirement system, or the Class V school district designated by the Class V Retirement System Board, if there is more than one Class V school district in the retirement system, shall act as the treasurer of the system and the official custodian of the cash and securities belonging to the retirement system, shall provide adequate safe deposit facilities for the preservation of such securities, and shall hold such cash and securities subject to the order of the board of education or Class V Retirement System Board.</para><para>Beginning January 1, 2017, the State Treasurer shall act as treasurer of the retirement system and the official custodian of the cash and securities belonging to the system, shall provide adequate safe deposit facilities for the preservation of such securities, and shall hold such cash and securities subject to the order of the council.</para><para>The school district or designated school district shall receive all items of taxes or cash belonging to the retirement system and shall deposit in banks approved by the board of education or Class V Retirement System Board and, beginning January 1, 2017, banks approved by the State Treasurer, all such amounts in trust or custodial accounts. Notwithstanding any limitations elsewhere imposed by statute on the location of the retirement system's depository bank, such limitations shall not apply to the use of depository banks for the custody of the system's cash, securities, and other investments.</para><para>Prior to January 1, 2017, the school district or designated school district, as treasurer of the system, shall make payments for purposes specified in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para><para>Beginning January 1, 2017, the State Treasurer as treasurer of the retirement system shall make payments to the school district upon request of the administrator of a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and as directed by the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems. The school district shall use payments received from the State Treasurer to make payments for purposes specified in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. All banks and custodians which receive and hold securities and investments for the retirement system may hold and evidence such securities by book entry account rather than obtaining and retaining the original certificate, indenture, or governing instrument for such security.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 9, p. 915; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1142, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 505, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 604, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1040; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 621; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 25. </para><operativedate>March 31, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>