<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id264" statutenumber="79-998"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-998</statuteno><catchline id="id267">Additional service credits; accept payments and rollovers; limitations; how treated; tax consequences; direct transfer to retirement plan.</catchline><para>(1) The retirement system may accept as payment for additional service credit that is purchased pursuant to sections 79-990 to 79-992 an eligible rollover distribution from or on behalf of the member who is making payments for such service credit if the eligible rollover distribution does not exceed the amount of payment required for the service credit being purchased by the member. The eligible rollover distribution may be contributed to the retirement system by the member or directly transferred from the plan that is making the eligible rollover distribution on behalf of the member. Contribution by a member pursuant to this section may only be made in the form of a cash contribution. For purposes of this section, an eligible rollover distribution means all or any portion of an amount that qualifies as an eligible rollover distribution under the Internal Revenue Code from:</para><para>(a) A plan of another employer which is qualified under section 401(a) or 403(a) of the Internal Revenue Code;</para><para>(b) An annuity contract or custodial account described in section 403(b) of the Internal Revenue Code;</para><para>(c) An eligible deferred compensation plan under section 457(b) of the Internal Revenue Code which is maintained by a governmental employer described in section 457(e)(1)(A) of the Internal Revenue Code; or</para><para>(d) An individual retirement account or annuity described in section 408(a) or section 408(b) of the Internal Revenue Code that is eligible to be rolled over to an employer plan under the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(2) The retirement system may accept as payment for service credit that is purchased pursuant to sections 79-990 to 79-992 a direct trustee-to-trustee transfer from an eligible deferred compensation plan as described in section 457(e)(17) of the Internal Revenue Code on behalf of a member who is making payments for such service credit if the amount transferred from the eligible deferred compensation plan does not exceed the amount of payment required for the service credit being purchased and the purchase of such service credit qualifies as the purchase of permissive service credit by the member as defined in section 415(n)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(3) Until September 1, 2024, the board, and, beginning September 1, 2024, the retirement board, may establish rules, regulations, and limitations on the eligible rollover distributions and direct trustee-to-trustee transfers that may be accepted by the retirement system pursuant to this section, including restrictions on the type of assets that may be transferred to the retirement system.</para><para>(4) Cash and other properties contributed or transferred to the retirement system pursuant to this section shall be deposited and held as a commingled asset of the retirement system and shall not be separately accounted for or invested for the member's benefit. Contributions or direct transfers made by or on behalf of any member pursuant to this section shall be treated as qualifying payments under sections 79-990 to 79-992 and as employee contributions for all other purposes of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act except in determining federal and state tax treatment of distributions from the system.</para><para>(5) The retirement system, the board of education, the board of trustees, the retirement board, and their respective members, officers, and employees shall have no responsibility or liability with respect to the federal and state income tax consequences of any contribution or transfer to the retirement system pursuant to this section. Until September 1, 2024, the board, and, beginning September 1, 2024, the retirement board, may require as a condition to the retirement system's acceptance of any rollover contribution or transfer satisfactory evidence that the proposed contribution or transfer is a qualifying rollover contribution or trustee-to-trustee transfer under the Internal Revenue Code and reasonable releases or indemnifications from the member against any and all liabilities which may in any way be connected with such contribution or transfer.</para><para>(6) Effective January 1, 1993, any member who is to receive an eligible rollover distribution, as defined in the Internal Revenue Code, from the retirement system may, in accordance with such rules, regulations, and limitations as may be established by the board or the retirement board, as applicable, elect to have such distribution made in the form of a direct transfer to a retirement plan eligible to receive such transfer under the provisions of the Internal Revenue Code. Any such election shall be made in the form and within the time periods established by the board or the retirement board, as applicable.</para><para>(7) A member's surviving spouse or former spouse who is an alternate payee under a qualified domestic relations order and, on or after September 1, 2010, any designated beneficiary of a member who is not a surviving spouse or former spouse who is entitled to receive an eligible rollover distribution from the retirement system may, in accordance with such rules, regulations, and limitations as may be established by the board or the retirement board, as applicable, elect to have such distribution made in the form of a direct transfer to a retirement plan eligible to receive such transfer under the provisions of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(8) An eligible rollover distribution on behalf of a designated beneficiary of a member who is not a surviving spouse or former spouse of the member may be transferred to an individual retirement account or annuity described in section 408(a) or section 408(b) of the Internal Revenue Code that is established for the purpose of receiving the distribution on behalf of the designated beneficiary and that will be treated as an inherited individual retirement account or individual retirement annuity described in section 408(d)(3)(C) of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(9) All distributions from the retirement system shall be subject to all withholdings required by federal or state tax laws.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 107, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 76; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1049.06; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 633; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 29. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>