<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id21" statutenumber="79-234"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-234</statuteno><catchline id="id24">Enrollment option
program; established; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) An enrollment
option program is hereby established to enable any kindergarten through twelfth
grade Nebraska student to attend a school in a Nebraska public school district
in which the student does not reside subject to the limitations prescribed
in section 79-238. The option shall be available only once to each student
prior to graduation, except
that the option does not count toward such limitation if such option meets,
or met at the time of the option, one of the following criteria: (a) The student relocates
to a different resident school district, (b) the option school district merges
with another district, (c) the option school district is a Class I district,
(d) the student will have completed
either the grades offered in the school building originally attended in the
option school district or the grades immediately preceding the lowest grade
offered in the school building for which a new option is sought, (e) the
option would allow the student to continue current enrollment in a school
district, or (f) the option would allow
the student to enroll in a school district in which the student was previously
enrolled as a resident student. Sections 79-232 to 79-246 do not relieve a parent
or guardian from the compulsory attendance requirements in section 79-201.</para>
<para>(2) The program shall not apply to any student who resides
in a district which has entered into an annexation agreement pursuant to section
79-473, except that such student may transfer to another district which accepts
option students.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 183, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 843, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 207, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 64; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3403; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB410, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>