<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id955"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-979.01" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>79-979.01</statuteno><catchline>Employees retirement system; transition and transfer of management and general administration; plan; consistent with work plan; powers and duties; costs, fees, and expenses.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The board of trustees or its designee, the school district, the board of education or its designee, and the retirement board shall enter into a plan for the transition and transfer of management and general administration of the retirement system from the board of trustees, the school district, and board of education to the retirement board.</para><para>(b) The plan shall be consistent with the applicable requirements and recommendations of the work plan submitted to the Clerk of the Legislature as required by section 79-9,121. The plan shall be completed no later than December 31, 2021, and shall also address additional duties, obligations, and examinations related to the transition and transfer of management of the retirement system to the retirement board as described in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act as amended by Laws 2021, LB147. A copy of the plan described in this section shall be filed with the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and the Governor upon completion.</para><para>(2) The board of trustees, the school district, and the board of education shall timely provide to the retirement board all records, documents, member and annuitant data, agreements, accounting and recordkeeping systems, information technology, and other information related to the administration of the retirement system as may be necessary or appropriate for the performance and completion of the work plan required by section 79-9,121, the plan described in subsection (1) of this section, and any other duties and obligations related to the transition and transfer of management and general administration of the retirement system requested by the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems.</para><para>(3)(a) All costs, fees, and expenses incurred by the retirement board on or after May 27, 2021, until September 1, 2025, related to the transition and transfer of management and general administration of the retirement system to the retirement board shall be paid by an employer of the retirement system.</para><para>(b) The retirement board may bill an employer of the retirement system monthly for all services and expenses relating to the work performed as required in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act by the retirement board and the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems staff, consultants, and contractors. An employer shall remit payment as provided in section 79-9,122 and within the time period and in the manner negotiated in the transition and transfer of management and administration plan entered into pursuant to this section.</para><para>(4) No later than September 1, 2024, except for information technology stabilization work performed until September 1, 2025, the retirement board or its designee shall complete the applicable requirements and carry out recommendations consistent with the work plan and the plan entered into as described in subsection (1) of this section for the transition and transfer of management and general administration of the retirement system to the retirement board that was submitted to the Clerk of the Legislature as required by section 79-9,121. The retirement board is authorized to perform such tasks, enter into contracts for services, access and copy administrative and computer systems and records of the retirement system, and generally perform and take all other action it determines necessary or appropriate to transfer the management and general administration of the retirement system to the retirement board.</para><para>(5)(a) Beginning September 1, 2024, the school district and board of education shall not have any duty or authority for management, operation, or general administration of the retirement system except for reporting requirements and funding obligations as described in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para><para>(b) On and after such date, the retirement board, acting through the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, shall have the duty and authority for the management, operation, and general administration of the retirement system. Such duty and authority of the retirement board and its officers, employees, or assigns does not include financial responsibility or liability for funding obligations of the retirement system which remain the responsibility of the school district as described in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>