<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id92">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id94" statutenumber="79-9,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,104</statuteno><catchline id="id97">Employees retirement
system; annuities; benefits; exempt from claims of creditors; exceptions; payment for civil damages; conditions.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of
this section, all annuities and other benefits payable under the
Class V School Employees Retirement Act and all accumulated credits of members
of the retirement system shall not be assignable or subject to execution,
garnishment, or attachment except to the extent that such annuity or benefit
is subject to a qualified domestic relations order as such term is defined
in and which meets the requirements of section 414(p) of the Internal Revenue
Code. The payment of any annuity
or benefit subject to such order shall take priority over any payment made
pursuant to subsection (4) of this section. Payments under such
a qualified domestic relations order shall be made only after the administrator
of the retirement system receives written notice of such order and such additional
information and documentation as the administrator may require.</para>
<para>(2) In lieu of the assignment of a member's future annuity
or benefit to the member's spouse or former spouse, the retirement system
shall permit the spouse or former spouse of a member to receive, pursuant
to a qualified domestic relations order, a single sum payment of a specified
percentage of the member's accumulated contributions on the condition that
upon the payment of such amount the spouse or former spouse shall have no
further interest in the retirement system or in the remaining benefit of the
member under the retirement system.</para>
<para>(3) A member's interest and benefits under the retirement
system shall be reduced, either at termination of employment, retirement,
disability, or death, by the actuarial value of the benefit assigned or paid
to the member's spouse, former spouse, or other dependents under a qualified
domestic relations order, as determined by the plan actuary on the basis of
the actuarial assumptions then recommended by the actuary pursuant to section
79-984.</para>
<para>(4) If a member
of the retirement system is convicted of or pleads no contest to a felony
that is defined as assault, sexual assault, kidnapping, child abuse, false
imprisonment, or theft by embezzlement and is found liable for civil damages
as a result of such felony, following distribution of the member's annuities
or benefits from the retirement system, the court may order the payment of
the member's annuities or benefits earned under the retirement system for
such civil damages, except that the annuities or benefits to the extent reasonably
necessary for the support of the member or any of his or her beneficiaries
shall be exempt from such payment. Any order for payment of annuities or benefits
shall not be stayed on the filing of any appeal of the conviction. If the
conviction is reversed on final judgment, all annuities or benefits paid as
civil damages shall be forfeited and returned to the member. The changes made
to this section by Laws 2012, LB916, shall apply to persons convicted of or
who have pled no contest to such a felony and who have been found liable for
civil damages as a result of such felony prior to, on, or after April 7, 2012.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 29, p. 925; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 350, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1060; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 639; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 155, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 26.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>