
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id305">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id307" statutenumber="79-933.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-933.05</statuteno><catchline id="id310">Contributing
member; credit for service in other schools; limitation; procedure; payment.</catchline>
<para>(1) A contributing member may purchase service credit for
not to exceed ten years of creditable service rendered in public schools in
another state or schools in this state covered by the school retirement system
established pursuant to section 79-979. The amount to be paid by the member
for such service credit shall equal the actuarial cost to the School Employees Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska for allowing such additional service credit to the
employee. Payment shall be completed within five years after making the election
to purchase service credit or prior to termination of employment, whichever
occurs first, and may be made through direct payment, installment payments,
or an irrevocable payroll deduction authorization.</para>
<para>(2) A member who retires as a school employee of this state
shall not receive credit for time in service outside of this state or in a
school in this state covered by the school retirement system established pursuant
to section 79-979 in excess of the time he or she has been in service as a
school employee in this state of a school covered by the School Employees Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska. The board shall refund to the member the payments
made pursuant to this section to the extent that the member does not receive
credit for such service.</para>
<para>(3) Compensation for the period of service purchased shall
not be included in determining the member's final average compensation.</para>
<para>(4) A member who purchases service credit pursuant to this
section shall provide such documentation as the board may require to prove
that the member has forfeited the receipt of any benefits from the retirement
system of the public school in another state or a school in this state covered
by a retirement system established pursuant to section 79-979 for the creditable
service rendered in such school.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 25.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>