
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id346"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-226"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-226</statuteno><catchline>Menstrual products; pilot program; priorities; school board; policy; report.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning in school year 2025-26 and subject to available appropriations, the State Department of Education shall develop a pilot program to make menstrual products, including both pads and tampons, available to each school district. Priority shall be given to each school district:</para><para>(a) That classifies as a needs improvement school under the accountability system developed by the State Board of Education pursuant to section 79-760.06; or</para><para>(b) In which forty percent of the students are poverty students as defined in section 79-1003.</para><para>(2) For school year 2025-26, a school district that receives free menstrual products pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall ensure that free menstrual products, including both pads and tampons, are available in school bathrooms.</para><para>(3) A school board or board of education may adopt a policy relating to the requirements of this section.</para><para>(4) The State Department of Education shall submit a report electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature and the Education Committee of the Legislature relating to the pilot program for free menstrual products pursuant to this section on or before December 1, 2026.</para><para>(5) It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate an amount not to exceed two hundred fifty thousand dollars from the Education Future Fund for fiscal year 2025-26 to the State Department of Education to carry out this section.</para><para>(6) The State Board of Education may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1284, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>