<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id433">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id435" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="79-9,117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,117</statuteno><catchline id="id438">Board; establish
preretirement planning program; for whom; required information; funding; attendance;
fee.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall establish a comprehensive
preretirement planning program for school employees who are members of the
retirement system. The program shall provide information and advice regarding
the many changes employees face upon retirement, including, but not limited
to, changes in physical and mental health, housing, family life, leisure activity,
and retirement income.</para>
<para>(2) The preretirement planning program shall be available
to all employees who have attained the age of fifty years or are within five
years of qualifying for retirement or early retirement under their retirement
systems.</para>
<para>(3) The preretirement planning program shall include information
on the federal and state income tax consequences of the various annuity or
retirement benefit options available to the employee, information on social
security benefits, information on various local, state, and federal government
programs and programs in the private sector designed to assist elderly persons,
and information and advice the board deems valuable in assisting employees
in the transition from public employment to retirement.</para>
<para>(4) The board shall work with any governmental agency, including
political subdivisions or bodies whose services or expertise may enhance the
development or implementation of the preretirement planning program.</para>
<para>(5) The costs of the preretirement planning program shall
be charged back to the retirement system.</para>
<para>(6) The employer shall provide each eligible employee leave
with pay to attend up to two preretirement planning programs. For purposes
of this subsection, leave with pay means a day off paid by the employer and
does not mean vacation, sick, personal, or compensatory time. An employee
may choose to attend a program more than twice, but such leave shall be at
the expense of the employee and shall be at the discretion of the employer.
An eligible employee shall not be entitled to attend more than one preretirement
planning program per fiscal year prior to actual election of retirement.</para>
<para>(7) A nominal registration fee may be
charged each person attending a preretirement planning program to cover the
costs for meals, meeting rooms, or other expenses incurred under such program.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>