<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-455"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-455</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 87. Operative date January 1, 2019. Proposal; election; approve; county clerk; order; certificate; filing; appeal.</catchline><para>If the proposal provided for in section 79-452 is approved by a majority of the legal voters of the school district voting on the matter, the secretary of the school board shall within five days certify the approval to the county clerk. The county clerk shall immediately notify the secretary of each Class II, III, IV, or V district affected of the action taken by the Class I or II district, and such secretary shall within ten days certify to the county clerk that the school board of the Class II, III, IV, or V district has, by a majority vote, officially approved the proposal as provided in section 79-452. The county clerk shall issue an order effecting the changes in school district boundaries in accordance with the proposal provided in section 79-452. He or she shall also file certificates with the county assessor, county treasurer, and State Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts showing the changes. An appeal may be taken from such order within twenty days after the rendition of the order in the same manner as appeals are taken from the action of the county board in allowing or disallowing claims against the county. Such appeal shall be filed in the district court for the county whose county clerk has jurisdiction of the Class I or II district. When more than one county clerk has jurisdiction of the Class I or II district, the appeal may be filed in the district court for either of the counties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 510, &#167; 4, p. 1631; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 530, &#167; 3, p. 1763; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 662, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-426.26; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 204; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 32; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For appeal from action of county board on claim,</emphasis> see section 23-135.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>