<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id55">
<sectno id="id56">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id57" statutenumber="79-234"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id59">79-234</statuteno><catchline id="id60">Enrollment option
program; established; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) An enrollment
option program is hereby established to enable any kindergarten through twelfth
grade Nebraska student to attend a school in a Nebraska public school district
in which the student does not reside subject to the limitations prescribed
in section 79-238. The option shall be available only once to each student
prior to graduation unless (a) the student relocates to a different resident
school district, (b) the option school district merges with another district,
(c) the option school district is a Class I district, (d) the option would
allow the student to continue current enrollment in a school district, or
(e) the option would allow the student to enroll in a school district in which
the student was previously enrolled as a resident student. In the case of an event described in subdivision (1)(a)
or (b) of this section, the student's parent or guardian shall submit an application
to the new option school district within thirty days after the date of relocation
or the effective date of the merger. This subsection does not relieve a parent
or guardian from the compulsory attendance requirements in section 79-201
during the pendency of such application or approval.</para>
<para>(2) The program shall not apply to any student who
resides in a district which has entered into an annexation agreement pursuant
to section 79-473, except that such student may transfer to another district
which accepts option students.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 183, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 843, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 207, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 64; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3403; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>