<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id158" statutenumber="79-966"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>79-966</statuteno><catchline id="id161">School Retirement Fund; state deposits; amount; determination; contingent state deposit; how calculated; hearing.</catchline><para>(1)(a) On the basis of all data in the possession of the retirement board, including such mortality and other tables as are recommended by the actuary engaged by the retirement board and adopted by the retirement board, the retirement board shall annually, on or before July 1, determine the state deposit to be made by the state in the School Retirement Fund for that fiscal year. The amount of such state deposit shall be determined pursuant to section 79-966.01. The retirement board shall thereupon certify the amount of such state deposit, and on the warrant of the Director of Administrative Services, the State Treasurer shall, as of July 1 of such year, transfer from funds appropriated by the state for that purpose to the School Retirement Fund the amount of such state deposit.</para><para>(b) Beginning July 1, 2016, the contingent state deposit described in this subsection shall be calculated as a percent of compensation of all members of the retirement system. For any year in which a deposit is made to the School Retirement Fund under this subsection, if the actuary for a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act determines that the actuarially required contribution rate, for the fiscal year of the retirement system that begins before the state deposit, exceeds the rate of all contributions required pursuant to the Class V School Employees Retirement Act, using the thirty-year amortization period specified in section 79-966.01, the Class V district school board may request a public hearing of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature to ask the state to transfer to the funds of the retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act an amount determined by multiplying the compensation of all members of such retirement system by the lesser of the percent of compensation deposited into the School Retirement Fund under this subsection or the percent of compensation of the members of the retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act needed to meet the actuarially required contribution rate for such system, using the thirty-year amortization period specified in section 79-966.01. Any additional amount of transfer so calculated, recommended by the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and approved by the Legislature, shall be added to the two percent specified in subsection (2) of this section for the amount required by subsection (2) of section 79-916 to be transferred to the funds of the retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para><para>(2) For each fiscal year beginning July 1, 2014, in addition to the state deposits required by subsections (1) and (3) of this section, the state shall deposit in the School Retirement Fund an amount equal to two percent of the compensation of all members of the retirement system.</para><para>(3) In addition to the state deposits required by subsections (1) and (2) of this section, beginning on July 1, 2005, and each fiscal year thereafter for employees who become members prior to July 1, 2016, the state shall deposit in the Service Annuity Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay the normal cost and amortize the unfunded actuarial accrued liability of the service annuity benefit established pursuant to sections 79-933 and 79-952 as accrued through the end of the previous fiscal year of the school employees who are members of the retirement system established pursuant to the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 219, &#167; 41, p. 651; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2941; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 474, p. 853; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 530, &#167; 4, p. 1668; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 735, &#167; 12, p. 2782; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 248, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 457, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1170, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1540; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 601; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB187, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB382, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB553, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>March 31, 2016</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Class V School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-978.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>