<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id174" statutenumber="79-9,100"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,100</statuteno><catchline id="id177">Employees retirement system; formula retirement annuity; computation.</catchline><para>(1) In lieu of the retirement annuity provided by section 79-999 or 79-9,113, any member who becomes eligible to receive a retirement annuity after February 20, 1982, under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act shall receive a formula retirement annuity based on final average compensation, except that if the monthly formula retirement annuity based on final average compensation is less than the monthly retirement annuity specified in section 79-999 or 79-9,113, accrued to the date of retirement or August 31, 1983, whichever first occurs, the member shall receive the monthly retirement annuity specified in section 79-999 or 79-9,113 accrued to the date of retirement or August 31, 1983, whichever first occurs.</para><para>(2) The monthly formula retirement annuity based on final average compensation shall be determined by multiplying the number of years of creditable service for which such member would otherwise receive the retirement annuity provided by section 79-999 or 79-9,113 by one and one-half percent of his or her final average compensation. For retirements after June 15, 1989, and before April 18, 1992, the applicable percentage shall be one and sixty-five hundredths percent of his or her final average compensation. For retirements on or after April 18, 1992, and before June 7, 1995, the applicable percentage shall be one and seventy-hundredths percent of his or her final average compensation. For retirements on or after June 7, 1995, and before March 4, 1998, the applicable percentage shall be one and eighty-hundredths percent of his or her final average compensation. For retirements on or after March 4, 1998, and before March 22, 2000, the applicable percentage shall be one and eighty-five hundredths percent of his or her final average compensation. For retirements on or after March 22, 2000, the applicable percentage shall be two percent of his or her final average compensation.</para><para>(3) Final average compensation shall be determined:</para><para>(a) Except as provided in subdivision (3)(b) of this section, by dividing the member's total compensation for the three fiscal years in which such compensation was the highest by thirty-six; and</para><para>(b) For an employee who became a member on or after July 1, 2013, by dividing the member's total compensation for the five fiscal years in which such compensation was the highest by sixty.</para><para>(4)(a) In the determination of compensation for members whose retirement date is on or after July 1, 2016, that part of a member's compensation for the plan year which exceeds the member's compensation for the preceding plan year by more than eight percent during the capping period shall be excluded. If the compensation for the preceding plan year was reduced as a result of unpaid absence from work, the compensation used in the capping calculation will be the greater of (i) the annualized compensation for the preceding year as if it had been fully received or (ii) the most recent preceding plan year in which the member had no unpaid absence from work. Such member's compensation for the first plan year of the capping period shall be compared to the member's compensation received for the plan year immediately preceding the capping period. If the first plan year of the capping period is the member's first year of membership service, these capping provisions shall not be applied to that first plan year.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this subsection:</para><para>(i) Capping period means the five plan years preceding the later of (A) such member's retirement date or (B) such member's final compensation date; and</para><para>(ii) Final compensation date means the later of (A) the date on which a retiring member's final compensation is actually paid or (B) if a retiring member's final compensation is paid in advance as a lump sum, the date on which such final compensation would have been paid to the member in the absence of such advance payment.</para><para>(5) For retirements before June 7, 1995, if the annuity begins prior to the sixty-second birthday of the member and the member has not completed thirty-five or more years of creditable service, the annuity at the date it begins shall be the actuarial equivalent of the annuity deferred to the sixty-second birthday of the member. If the annuity begins prior to the sixty-second birthday of the member and the member has completed thirty-five or more years of creditable service, the annuity shall not be reduced. For retirements on or after June 7, 1995, any retirement annuity which begins prior to the sixty-second birthday of the member shall be reduced by twenty-five hundredths percent for each month or partial month between the date the annuity begins and the member's sixty-second birthday. If the annuity begins at a time when:</para><para>(a) The sum of the member's attained age and creditable service is eighty-five or more, the annuity shall not be reduced;</para><para>(b) The sum of the member's attained age and creditable service totals eighty-four, the annuity shall not be reduced by an amount greater than three percent of the unreduced annuity;</para><para>(c) The sum of the member's attained age and creditable service totals eighty-three, the annuity shall not be reduced by an amount greater than six percent of the unreduced annuity; and</para><para>(d) The sum of the member's attained age and creditable service totals eighty-two, the annuity shall not be reduced by an amount greater than nine percent of the unreduced annuity.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section, a member's creditable service and attained age shall be measured in one-half-year increments.</para><para>(7) The normal form of the formula retirement annuity based on final average compensation shall be an annuity payable monthly during the remainder of the member's life with the provision that in the event of his or her death before sixty monthly payments have been made the monthly payments will be continued to his or her estate or to the beneficiary he or she has designated until a total of sixty monthly payments have been made. A member may elect to receive, in lieu of the normal form of annuity, an actuarially equivalent annuity in any optional form provided by section 79-9,101.</para><para>(8) Any member receiving a formula retirement annuity based on final average compensation shall also receive the service annuity to be paid by the State of Nebraska as provided in sections 79-933 to 79-935 and 79-951.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 131, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 215, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 237, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 505, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1044.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 635; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 155, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB553, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB446, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For supplemental retirement benefits,</emphasis> see sections 79-940 to 79-947.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>