<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-826"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-826</statuteno><catchline>Certificated employee; disciplinary action; superintendent; powers; procedures.</catchline><para>The superintendent or the superintendent's designee may take action with regard to a certificated employee's performance or conduct which is deemed reasonably necessary to assist the certificated employee and further school purposes, including: (1) Counseling; (2) oral reprimand; (3) written reprimand; and (4) suspension without pay for not to exceed thirty working days.</para><para>Prior to taking any action under subdivision (3) of this section, the certificated employee shall be advised of the alleged reasons for the proposed action and provided the opportunity to present the certificated employee's version of the facts. The certificated employee may proceed under the school district's grievance procedure if the school district has such a grievance procedure which provides for a review of such action or may, within seven calendar days after the superintendent or superintendent's designee takes such action, challenge the decision through the administrative chain of command.</para><para>Prior to taking any action under subdivision (4) of this section, the certificated employee shall be advised in writing of the alleged reasons for the proposed action and provided the opportunity to present the certificated employee's version of the facts. Within seven calendar days after receipt of such notice, the certificated employee may make a written request to the secretary of the school board or the superintendent or superintendent's designee for formal due process hearing under section 79-832. If such a request is not delivered within such time, the action of the superintendent or the superintendent's designee shall become final.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 259, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-12,109; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 456. </para></source><annotation><para>For purposes of bringing error proceedings, this statute does not require a school board to act in a judicial manner when administering pay scale grievances. Kropp v. Grand Island Pub. Sch. Dist. No. 2, 246 Neb. 138, 517 N.W.2d 113 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>