<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id89" statutenumber="79-239"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>79-239</statuteno><catchline id="id92">Application; request for release; rejection; notice; appeal; school district; State Department of Education; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If an application is rejected by the option school district or if the resident school district rejects a request for release under subsection (1) of section 79-237, the rejecting school district shall provide written notification to the parent or guardian stating (a) the specific reasons for the rejection including, for students with an individualized education program under the federal Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, 20 U.S.C. 1400 et seq., or with a diagnosed disability as defined in section 79-1118.01, a description of services and accommodations required that the school district does not have the capacity to provide, and (b) the process for appealing such rejection to the State Board of Education. Such notification shall be sent by certified mail.</para><para>(2) The parent or legal guardian may appeal a rejection to the State Board of Education by filing a written request, together with a copy of the rejection notice, with the State Board of Education. Such request and copy of the notice must be received by the board within thirty days after the date the notification of the rejection was received by the parent or legal guardian. Such hearing shall be held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and shall determine whether the procedures of sections 79-234 to 79-241 have been followed.</para><para>(3)(a) Beginning July 1, 2024, and on or before July 1 of each year thereafter, each school district shall provide to the State Department of Education, on forms prescribed by the department, information relating to all applications rejected by the option school district. Such information shall include, but not be limited to, (a) the number of applications rejected in each public school in such district, (b) an explanation why each application was rejected, (c) whether each application for option enrollment indicated that the student had an individualized education program under the federal Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, 20 U.S.C. 1400 et seq., or had been diagnosed with a disability as defined in section 79-1118.01, and (d) whether information regarding the requirements of subsection (4) of section 79-238 was provided to the applicant.</para><para>(b) The State Department of Education shall annually compile the information received pursuant to this subsection and provide a report on such information electronically to the Legislature beginning on September 1, 2024, and on or before September 1 of each year thereafter. The State Board of Education may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 183, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 67; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3408; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 56. </para><operativedate>September 2, 2023</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>