<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id52">
<sectno id="id53" opdate="April 15, 2010">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id54" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="79-8,137.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id56">79-8,137.01</statuteno><catchline id="id57">Enhancing
Excellence in Teaching Program; created; terms, defined.</catchline><para>The Enhancing Excellence in Teaching Program is created. For purposes
of the Enhancing Excellence in Teaching Program:</para>
<para>(1) Department means the State Department of Education;</para>
<para>(2) Eligible
graduate program means a program of study offered by an eligible institution
which results in obtaining a graduate degree;</para><para>(3) Eligible institution means a not-for-profit
college or university which (a) is located in Nebraska, (b) is accredited
by the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools, (c) has a teacher
education program, and (d) if a privately funded college or university, has
not opted out of the Enhancing Excellence in Teaching Program pursuant
to rules and regulations;</para>
<para>(4) Eligible student means
an individual who (a) is a certificated teacher employed to teach in an approved
or accredited school in Nebraska, (b) is enrolled in an eligible graduate program, (c) if enrolled
at a state-funded eligible institution, is a resident student as described
in section 85-502 or, if enrolled in a privately funded eligible institution,
would be deemed a resident student if enrolled in a state-funded eligible
institution, and (d) is majoring in a shortage area, curriculum and instruction,
a subject area in which the individual already holds a secular teaching endorsement,
or a subject area that will result in an additional secular teaching endorsement
which the superintendent of the school district or head administrator of the
private, denominational, or parochial school employing the individual believes
will be beneficial to the students of such school district or school as evidenced
by a statement signed by the superintendent or head administrator;</para>
<para>(5) Majoring
in a shortage area or subject area means pursuing a degree which will allow
an individual to be properly endorsed to teach in such shortage area or subject
area; and</para>
<para>(6) Shortage area means a secular field of teaching for which
there is a shortage, as determined by the department, of properly endorsed
teachers at the time the borrower first receives funds pursuant to the Enhancing Excellence in Teaching Program.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB547, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167;  8.</para><operativedate>April 15, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>