
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id525"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-9,121"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,121</statuteno><catchline>Work plan for transfer of management and actuarial services; contents; access to records, documents, data, or other information; report; billing for work.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Public Employees Retirement Board, in consultation with stakeholders including, but not limited to, the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and the board of trustees and employer of any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and which existed on January 1, 2019, shall develop a work plan for the transfer of management and actuarial services of any such Class V school employees retirement system to the Public Employees Retirement Board.</para><para>(b) The work plan shall include, but not be limited to, a detailed analysis and recommendations regarding (i) management, administration, actuarial service, information technology, computer infrastructure, accounting, and member data and record transfer; (ii) necessary statutory changes to achieve the transfer of management and actuarial services; (iii) staff training and assessment of staffing needs; (iv) educational and communication plans to fully inform all system stakeholders and affected governmental entities regarding management changes; (v) sufficient timeframes for an orderly transition and implementation of management and actuarial changes; (vi) cost estimates associated with the tasks necessary to carry out the management transition; and (vii) a comparison of the current annual cost to administer any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and which existed on January 1, 2019, with an estimate of the annual cost for the Public Employees Retirement Board to administer such system after a management transfer occurs.</para><para>(c) The employer of any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and which existed on January 1, 2019, shall provide all records, documents, data, or other information to the Public Employees Retirement Board within thirty calendar days after receiving a written request from the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, or from the director's representative on behalf of the Public Employees Retirement Board, for such records, documents, data, or other information.</para><para>(d) The Public Employees Retirement Board shall electronically report the work plan, including any recommendations, cost estimates, and cost comparisons, to the Clerk of the Legislature no later than June 30, 2020.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, management does not include:</para><para>(a) A merger or consolidation of any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and which existed on January 1, 2019, with the School Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska or any other retirement system administered by the Public Employees Retirement Board; or</para><para>(b) An assumption of any of the liability for any such Class V school employees retirement system by the State of Nebraska, the Public Employees Retirement Board, or the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems.</para><para>(3) The Public Employees Retirement Board may quarterly bill the employer of any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act and which existed on January 1, 2019, for all work performed by the Public Employees Retirement Board for services and related expenses in completion of the work plan described in this section. Such employer shall remit payment as provided in section 79-9,122 within forty-five calendar days after receipt of each bill.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB31, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>