<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-266"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-266</statuteno><catchline>Pre-expulsion procedures; when; expelled student; alternative assignments; suspension of enforcement; agreement between school boards; reinstatement; when; expungement.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning July 1, 1997, each school district shall have an alternative school, class, or educational program or the procedures of subsection (2) of this section available or in operation for all expelled students.</para><para>Any two or more school boards or boards of education may join together in providing alternative schools, classes, or educational programs. Any district may by agreement with another district send its suspended or expelled students to any alternative school, class, or educational program already in operation by such other district. An educational program may include, but shall not be limited to, individually prescribed educational and counseling programs or a community-centered classroom with experiences for the student as an observer or aide in governmental functions, as an on-the-job trainee, or as a participant in specialized tutorial experiences. Such programs shall include an individualized learning program to enable the student to continue academic work for credit toward graduation. The State Department of Education shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations relating to alternative schools, classes, and educational programs.</para><para>(2) If a district does not provide an alternative school, class, or educational program for expelled students, the district shall follow the procedures in this subsection prior to expelling a student unless the expulsion was required by subsection (4) of section 79-283: A conference shall be called by a school administrator and held to assist the district in the development of a plan with the participation of a parent or legal guardian, the student, a school representative, and a representative of either a community organization with a mission of assisting young people or a representative of an agency involved with juvenile justice. The plan shall be in writing and adopted by a school administrator and presented to the student and the parent or legal guardian. The plan shall (a) specify guidelines and consequences for behaviors which have been identified as preventing the student from achieving the desired benefits from the educational opportunities provided, (b) identify educational objectives that must be achieved in order to receive credits toward graduation, (c) specify the financial resources and community programs available to meet both the educational and behavioral objectives identified, and (d) require the student to attend monthly reviews in order to assess the student's progress toward meeting the specified goals and objectives.</para><para>(3) A school district that has expelled a student may suspend the enforcement of such expulsion unless the expulsion was required by subsection (4) of section 79-283. The suspension may be for a period not to exceed the length of the expulsion. As a condition of such suspended action, the school district may require participation in a plan pursuant to subsection (2) of this section or assign the student to a school, class, or educational program which the school district deems appropriate.</para><para>At the conclusion of such suspension period, the school district shall (a) reinstate any student who has satisfactorily participated in a plan pursuant to subsection (2) of this section or the school, class, or educational program to which such student has been assigned and permit the student to return to the school of former attendance or to attend other programs offered by the district or (b) if the student's conduct has been unsatisfactory, enforce the remainder of the expulsion action.</para><para>If the student is reinstated, the district may also take action to expunge the record of the expulsion action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1250, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 658, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-4,179.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1050, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 232, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>