<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id165">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id167" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-966.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>79-966.01</statuteno><catchline id="id170">School Retirement
Fund; annual actuarial valuations.</catchline><para>Beginning July
1, 2013, and each year thereafter,
this section shall govern annual actuarial valuations of the School Retirement
Fund. In order to determine the additional required deposits by the State
of Nebraska, as required by section 79-966, the board shall cause an annual
actuarial valuation to be performed that will value the plan assets for the
year and ascertain the contributions required for such fiscal year. The actuary
for the board shall perform the annual valuation using the entry age actuarial
cost method. Under this method, the actuarially required funding rate is equal
to the normal cost rate, plus the contribution rate necessary to amortize
the unfunded actuarial accrued liability on a level percentage
of salary basis. The normal cost under this method shall be determined
for each individual member on a level percentage of salary basis. The normal
cost amount is then summed for all members. Beginning July 1, 2006, any existing
unfunded liabilities shall be reinitialized and amortized over a thirty-year
period, and during each subsequent actuarial valuation, changes in the funded
actuarial accrued liability due to changes in benefits, actuarial assumptions,
the asset valuation method, or actuarial gains or losses shall be measured
and amortized over a thirty-year period beginning on the valuation date of
such change. If the unfunded actuarial accrued liability under the entry age
actuarial cost method is zero or less than zero on an actuarial valuation
date, then all prior unfunded actuarial accrued liabilities shall be considered
fully funded and the unfunded actuarial accrued liability shall be reinitialized
and amortized over a thirty-year period as of the actuarial valuation date.
If the actuarially required contribution rate exceeds the rate of all contributions
required pursuant to the School Employees Retirement Act, the actuary shall
determine the added contributions required to be paid by the State of Nebraska
that constitute the difference between the actuarially required contribution
rate and the rate of all other required contributions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB553, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>