<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id42">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id44" statutenumber="79-241"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>79-241</statuteno><catchline id="id47">Transportation;
fee authorized; reimbursement; when.</catchline><para>(1) Except
as provided in subsection (2) of this section, section 79-611 does not apply
to the transportation of an option student. The parent or legal guardian of
the option student shall be responsible for required transportation. A school
district may, upon mutual agreement with the parent or legal guardian of an
option student, provide transportation to the option student on the same basis
as provided for resident students. The school district may charge the parents
of each option student transported a fee sufficient to recover the additional
costs of such transportation.</para>
<para>(2) Parents or guardians of option students who qualify for
free lunches shall be eligible for transportation reimbursement as described
in section 79-611, except that they shall be reimbursed at the rate of one
hundred forty-two and one-half percent of the mandatorily established mileage
rate provided in section 81-1176 for each mile actually and necessarily traveled
on each day of attendance by which the distance traveled one way from the
residence of such student to the schoolhouse exceeds three miles.</para>
<para>(3) For option students verified as having a disability as
defined in section 79-1118.01, the transportation services set forth in section
79-1129 shall be provided by the resident school district. The State Department of Education shall reimburse
the resident school district for the cost of transportation in accordance
with section 79-1144.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 183, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 843, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 207, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 838, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 69; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3410; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB410, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>May 30, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>