<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-294"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-294</statuteno><catchline>Removal of minor from school premises; release to peace officer; principal or other school official; duties; peace officer; duties; juvenile court review; when.</catchline><para>When a principal or other school official releases a minor student to a peace officer as defined in section 49-801 for the purpose of removing the minor from the school premises, the principal or other school official shall take immediate steps to notify the parent, guardian, or responsible relative of the minor regarding the release of the minor to the officer and regarding the place to which the minor is reportedly being taken, except when a minor has been taken into custody as a victim of suspected child abuse, in which case the principal or other school official shall provide the peace officer with the address and telephone number of the minor's parent or guardian. The peace officer shall take immediate steps to notify the parent, guardian, or responsible relative of the minor that the minor is in custody and the place where he or she is being held. If the peace officer has a reasonable belief that the minor would be endangered by a disclosure of the place where the minor is being held or that the disclosure would cause the custody of the minor to be disturbed, the peace officer may refuse to disclose the place where the minor is being held for a period not to exceed twenty-four hours. The peace officer shall, however, inform the parent, guardian, or responsible relative whether the child requires and is receiving medical or other treatment. The juvenile court shall review any decision not to disclose the place where the minor is being held at any subsequent detention hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1250, &#167; 43; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-4,205.02; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 98. </para></source></law></legaldoc>