<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-857"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-857</statuteno><catchline>Allocation of certificated employees; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) For reorganizations involving consolidation of school districts into one or more reorganized districts, staff not electing retirement pursuant to section 79-855 or Staff Development Assistance pursuant to section 79-856 shall be allocated prior to the effective date of reorganization as follows:</para><para>(a) All districts involved may enter into an agreement on the allocation of all certificated employees to one or more of the reorganized districts. No certificated employee shall be allocated to more than one district. Such agreement shall be signed by all the districts involved;</para><para>(b) All certificated employees from the district or districts who have not been allocated pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall be totaled and allocated among the reorganized districts based upon the proportion of students transferring to the reorganized district;</para><para>(c) All certificated employees from the district shall be treated equally in the allocation regardless of seniority. Staff shall not be given the option to choose the reorganized district in which to relocate. Random selection shall be utilized to allocate individual employees among all reorganized districts; and</para><para>(d) Once the selection and allocation is completed, employees from the district or districts shall retain years of service from the previous district for purposes of seniority. Within each reorganized district, employees from the receiving district shall not have priority over transferring employees. All reduction-in-force laws and policies shall apply.</para><para>(2) For unifications, staff not electing retirement pursuant to section 79-855 or Staff Development Assistance pursuant to section 79-856 shall be allocated prior to the effective date of the unification in compliance with an agreement signed by all participating districts. Once the selection and allocation is completed, employees shall retain years of service from the participating district for purposes of seniority. All reduction-in-force laws and policies shall apply.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1050, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 44; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Reduction-in-force policy,</emphasis> see sections 79-846 to 79-849.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>