<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-740"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-740</statuteno><catchline>State Board of Vocational Education; designation; meetings; quorum; executive officer.</catchline><para>(1) The State Board of Education shall also be the State Board of Vocational Education and, when acting as the State Board of Vocational Education, shall assume the powers and duties provided in sections 79-738 to 79-744.</para><para>(2) The Commissioner of Education shall be the executive officer of the State Board of Vocational Education. The members of the State Board of Vocational Education shall receive no compensation for their services. They shall be reimbursed for actual and essential expenses incurred in attending meetings or incurred in the performance of their duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The State Board of Vocational Education shall meet in the office of the State Department of Education at least four times annually. It may meet at such other times and places as the board determines necessary for the proper and efficient conduct of its duties. Special meetings may be called by the presiding officer upon a written notice given at least five days preceding the meeting. In the absence of such a call by the presiding officer, the Commissioner of Education shall call such special meeting upon the written request of a majority of the board. Five members of the board shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 227, &#167; 3, p. 559; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 75, &#167; 1, p. 282; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6555; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2203; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 164, &#167; 12, p. 657; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-2203; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 206, &#167; 1, p. 685; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2203; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 410, p. 829; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 290, &#167; 1, p. 958; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 1038; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 325, &#167; 2, p. 1008; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 421, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 160; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1090, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 44; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1421; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 414. </para></source><annotation><para>Rule-making authority of State Board of Education extends to State Board of Vocational Education. Campbell v. Area Vocational Technical School No. 2, 183 Neb. 318, 159 N.W.2d 817 (1968).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>