
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-9,115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,115</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class V School Employees Retirement Fund; created; use; expenses; payment.</catchline><para>(1) The Class V School Employees Retirement Fund is created.</para><para>(2) Until September 1, 2024, except as provided in this section:</para><para>(a) All allowances, annuities, or other benefits granted under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act, and all expenses incurred in connection with the administration of the act, except clerical work incurred in connection with maintenance of records and payment of benefits, shall be paid from the Class V School Employees Retirement Fund;</para><para>(b) Such clerical work shall be performed by employees of the school district or districts;</para><para>(c) The administrator and staff of the retirement system shall be permitted reasonable office and records storage space in the central office building of the Class V school district formed before September 13, 1997; and</para><para>(d) All expenses for the retirement system office accommodations and integrated pension benefit information management systems, including all services, support, furniture, and equipment provided to or by any central office department of the school district, shall be charged to the retirement system.</para><para>(3)(a) Beginning September 1, 2024, the required deposits of the school district and the amounts transferred to the school district by the State Treasurer for transmission to the retirement system and required deposits of the employees shall be credited to the Class V School Employees Retirement Fund and all allowances, annuities, and other benefits shall be paid from such fund as directed by the retirement board as provided in the Class V School Employees Retirement Act.</para><para>(b) The account of each member in the Class V School Employees Retirement Fund shall be credited with regular interest earned monthly, quarterly, semiannually, or annually as the retirement board may direct.</para><para>(4) Beginning on August 24, 2017, any expenses with respect to the transfer to and assumption by the council and the state investment officer of the duty and authority to invest the assets of a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act shall be charged to the Class V School Employees Retirement Fund. Such expenses shall be paid without the approval of the board of trustees or the retirement board, as applicable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 27, p. 925; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1058; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 650; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB29, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 36. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>