<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-557"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-557</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 87. Operative date January 1, 2019. Class I school districts; special school meetings; how called; notice; limitation upon transaction of business.</catchline><para>Special meetings of Class I school districts may be called by the school board by majority vote, or by any one of the members of such board, on the written request of legal voters of the district equal in number to at least ten percent of those voting at the last general election for Governor in the district by giving the notice required in section 79-558. When so requested, the board or the member receiving such request shall call the meeting. In all notices of special meetings, the object of the meeting shall be stated and no business shall be transacted at such meetings except such as is mentioned in the call.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision II, &#167; 2, p. 338; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6731; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6269; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-902; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-202; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 186, p. 752; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 487, &#167; 1, p. 1558; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-502; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 310; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>Board of education had power to provide for bussing, but duty to do so was not imposed and mandamus not warranted. Connot v. Monroe, 193 Neb. 453, 227 N.W.2d 827 (1975).</para><para>Request for calling of special election was sufficient. Richards v. McBride, 160 Neb. 57, 68 N.W.2d 692 (1955).</para><para>In absence of notice, taxes for purchase of school building cannot be voted at annual meeting. Fulk v. School District No. 8 of Lancaster County, 155 Neb. 630, 53 N.W.2d 56 (1952).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>