<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-558"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-558</statuteno><catchline>Class I school districts; annual or special meetings; notice; change of schoolhouse site; building, purchase, or lease of schoolhouse.</catchline><para>All notices of annual or special meetings of Class I school districts shall state the day, hour, and place of meeting, which place shall be within the district, and shall be given at least five days previous to such meeting by posting copies of the notice in three public places within the district. No annual meeting shall be deemed illegal for want of such notice. No schoolhouse site shall be changed and no taxes shall be voted for building, purchase, or lease of a schoolhouse at any district meeting unless notices have been given of such meeting as provided in this section, including the fact that such subjects will be considered at such meeting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision II, &#167; 3, p. 338; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 130, &#167; 1, p. 552; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6732; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6270; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-203; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 187, p. 753; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-503; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 311; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 15. </para></source><annotation><para>Architectural fees are general expenses and are not expenses of buildings which must be submitted to the school district voters for approval. Banks v. Board of Education of Chase County, 202 Neb. 717, 277 N.W.2d 76 (1979).</para><para>The authority to direct the purchase of a site for a schoolhouse or other school buildings in a class six district is reserved to the voters of the district. Banks v. Board of Education of Chase County, 202 Neb. 717, 277 N.W.2d 76 (1979).</para><para>Regular annual meeting is not invalidated by failure of notice. Fulk v. School District No. 8 of Lancaster County, 155 Neb. 630, 53 N.W.2d 56 (1952).</para><para>Change of schoolhouse site cannot be made unless notice is given that subject will be considered at meeting. State ex rel. Arterburn v. Cruise, 111 Neb. 114, 196 N.W. 116 (1923).</para><para>Notice, calling meeting to select place for holding school, justifies adoption of resolution directing leasing of certain building. Krull v. State ex rel. Furgason, 59 Neb. 97, 80 N.W. 272 (1899).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>