
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-205</statuteno><catchline>Compulsory attendance; records required.</catchline><para>Each school district and each private, denominational, or parochial school shall keep a record showing the name, age, and address of each child enrolled. Each teacher in such school district or school shall record the number of days each pupil was present and the number of days absent and the cause of absence. On the third day on which a public, private, denominational, and parochial school is in session at the beginning of each school year, each superintendent of a school district and each administrator of a private, denominational, or parochial school shall compile a list of the pupils enrolled in such district or school with the age, grade, and address of each pupil.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 70, &#167; 1, p. 454; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 549; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 140, &#167; 1, p. 575; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 131, &#167; 1, p. 430; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6924; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 155, &#167; 1, p. 346; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 53, &#167; 1(f), p. 228; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6508d; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-1904; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-1911; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 13, p. 694; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 210, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-207; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 12. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The state, having a high responsibility for the education of its citizens, has the power to impose reasonable regulations for the control and duration of basic education. Parents have a right to send their children to private schools but do not have the right to be completely unfettered by reasonable government regulations as to the quality of the education furnished and the maintenance of minimum standards. State ex rel. Douglas v. Faith Baptist Church of Louisville, 207 Neb. 802, 301 N.W.2d 571 (1981).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>