<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-403"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-403</statuteno><catchline>Creation of new district; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, no new school district shall be created unless such district provides instruction in kindergarten through grade twelve.</para><para>(2) A new Class VI school district may be created if:</para><para>(a) Such Class VI school district will include at least two or more previously existing Class II or Class III school districts, except that if a reorganization petition for formation of a Class VI school district is initiated by a petition signed by fifty-five percent of the legal voters of a Class II or III school district, then such Class VI school district may include only one Class II or III school district; and</para><para>(b) The enrollment of the new Class VI school district is (i) at least one hundred twenty-five pupils if the district offers instruction in grades nine through twelve, (ii) at least one hundred seventy-five pupils if the district offers instruction in grades seven through twelve, or (iii) at least two hundred students if the district offers instruction in grades six through twelve, except that if such district will have population density of less than three persons per square mile, then the enrollment shall be at least seventy-five students if the district offers instruction in grades nine through twelve, at least one hundred students if the district offers instruction in grades seven through twelve, or at least one hundred twenty-five students if the district offers instruction in grades six through twelve.</para><para>(3) One or more new Class I districts may be created as a part of a reorganization petition pursuant to subsection (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 703, &#167; 1, p. 2702; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 940, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1021, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-102.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 152; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 394, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 11; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422.</para></source></law></legaldoc>