<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id61" statutenumber="79-4,108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id63">79-4,108</statuteno><catchline id="id64">Unified system;
interlocal agreement; contents; application; procedure; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Unified system means two or more Class II or III school districts
participating in an interlocal agreement under the Interlocal Cooperation
Act with approval from the State Committee for the Reorganization of School
Districts. The interlocal agreement may include Class I districts if the entire
valuation is included in the unified system. The interlocal agreement shall
provide:</para>
<para>(a) For a minimum term of three school years;</para>
<para>(b) That all property
tax and state aid resources shall be shared by the unified system;</para>
<para>(c) That a board composed of school board members,
with at least one school board member from each district, shall determine
the general fund levy, within the limitations placed on school districts and
multiple-district school systems pursuant to section 77-3442, to be applied
in all participating districts and shall determine the distribution of property
tax and state aid resources within the unified system. For purposes of section
77-3442, the multiple-district school system shall include all of the Class
I, II, and III districts participating in the unified system and the Class
I districts or portions thereof affiliated with any of the participating Class
II and III districts;</para>
<para>(d) That certificated
staff will be employees of the unified system. For any certificated staff
employed by the unified system, tenure and seniority as of the effective date
of the interlocal agreement shall be transferred to the unified system and
tenure and seniority provisions shall continue in the unified system except
as provided in sections 79-850 to 79-858. If a district withdraws from the
unified system or if the interlocal agreement expires and is not renewed,
certificated staff employed by a participating district immediately prior
to the unification shall be reemployed by the original district and tenure
and seniority as of the effective date of the withdrawal or expiration shall
be transferred to the original district. The certificated staff hired by the
unified system but not employed by a participating district immediately prior
to the unification shall be subject to the reduction-in-force policy of the
unified system;</para>
<para>(e) That the participating
districts shall pay obligations of the
unified system pursuant to sections 79-850 to 79-858 on a pro rata basis based
on the adjusted valuations if a district withdraws from the unified system
or if the interlocal agreement expires and is not renewed; and</para>
<para>(f) The permissible method
or methods for accomplishing the partial or complete termination of the interlocal
agreement and for disposing of assets and liabilities upon such partial or
complete termination.</para><para>Additional provisions in the interlocal agreement shall
be determined by the participating districts and shall encourage cooperation
within the unified system.</para>
<para>(2) Application for unification shall be made to the state committee.
The application shall contain a copy of the interlocal agreement signed by
the president of each participating school board. The state committee shall
approve or disapprove applications for unification within forty days after
receipt of the application. If the interlocal agreement complies with subsection
(1) of this section and all school boards of the participating districts have
approved the interlocal agreement, the state committee shall approve the application.
Unification agreements shall be effective on June 1 following approval from
the state committee for status as a unified system or on the date specified
in the interlocal agreement, except that the date shall be on or after June
1 and on or before September 1 for a specified year. The board established
in the interlocal agreement may begin meeting any time after the application
has been approved by the state committee.</para>
<para>(3) Upon granting the application for unification, the State Department
of Education shall recognize the unified system as a single Class II or III
district for state aid, budgeting, accreditation, enrollment of students,
state programs, and reporting. Except as otherwise
required by the department, the unified system shall submit a single report
document for each of the reports required of school districts pursuant to
Chapter 79 and shall submit a single budget document pursuant to the Nebraska
Budget Act and sections 13-518 to 13-522. The class of district shall be the
same as the majority of participating districts, excluding Class I districts.
If there are an equal number of Class II and Class III districts in the unified
system, the unified system shall be recognized by the department as a Class
III district.</para>
<para>(4) The school districts participating in a unified system shall retain
their separate identities for all purposes except those specified in this
section, and participation in a unified system shall not be considered a reorganization.</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 38; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB711, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Budget Act,</emphasis> see section 13-501.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>