<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id102">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id104" statutenumber="79-916"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>79-916</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Retirement system;
membership; member of any other system; transfer of funds; when; Service Annuity
Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1)(a) On July
1, 2004, the board shall transfer from the School Retirement Fund to the Service
Annuity Fund an amount equal to the funded ratio of the retirement system
which is equal to the market value of the retirement system assets divided
by the actuarial accrued liability of the retirement system, times the actuarial
accrued liability of the service annuity, as determined pursuant to section
79-966.01, of the employees who are members of the retirement system established
pursuant to the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. Beginning
July 1, 2013, such actuarial accrued liability shall be determined
for each employee on a level percentage
of salary basis. On or before July 1 of each fiscal year, the state shall deposit into the
Service Annuity Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay the normal cost
and amortize the unfunded actuarial accrued liability of the service annuity,
as determined pursuant to section 79-966.01, as of the end of the previous
fiscal year of the employees who are members of the retirement system established
pursuant to the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. Based on the fiscal
year of the retirement system established pursuant to the Class V School Employees
Retirement Act, the administrator of such system shall provide all membership
information needed for the actuary engaged by the retirement board to determine
the normal cost and the amortization payment of the unfunded actuarial accrued
liability, as determined pursuant to section 79-966.01, to be paid by the
state to the Service Annuity Fund each fiscal year as required by this subdivision.</para>
<para>(b) At the time of retirement of any employee who is a member
of the retirement system established pursuant to the Class V School Employees
Retirement Act, the retirement board shall, upon receipt of a certification
of the administrator of such retirement system of the name, identification
number, date of birth, retirement date, last date of employment, type of retirement,
and number of years of service credited to such eligible employee at the date
of retirement, transfer to such retirement system from the Service Annuity
Fund the actuarial accrued liability of the service annuity to be paid by
the state to the eligible employee for the years of service thus certified
as provided for members of the School Employees Retirement System of the State
of Nebraska under sections 79-933 and 79-952. Such transfer of the actuarial
accrued liability to the retirement system established pursuant to the Class
V School Employees Retirement Act shall be in lieu of the payment of the service
annuity to which the employee would be entitled.</para>
<para>(c) The Service Annuity Fund is created. The fund shall consist
of the amounts paid by the state and transferred from the School Retirement
Fund pursuant to this section to pay the service annuity to be paid by the
state to employees who are members of the retirement system established pursuant
to the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. Any money in the Service Annuity
Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) In addition to the transfer of the actuarial accrued
liability of the service annuity to be paid by the state, the state shall
also transfer to the funds of the Class V school district's retirement system
an amount determined by multiplying the compensation of all members of such
retirement system by the percent specified in subsection (2) of section 79-966
for determining the amount of the state's payment to the School Retirement
Fund. The transfer shall be made annually on or before July 1 of each fiscal
year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 219, &#167; 12, p. 642; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2912; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 446, p. 845; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 292, &#167; 1, p. 970; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 530, &#167; 2, p. 1667; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 547, &#167; 2, p. 1810; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 546, &#167; 5, p. 1802; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 735, &#167; 3, p. 2777; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 457, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 549, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1170, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1512; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 551; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB553, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Class V School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-978.01.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>