<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-9,100.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,100.01</statuteno><catchline>Employees retirement system; annuity reductions; when; computation.</catchline><para>(1)(a) For employees who become members on or after July 1, 2016, and prior to July 1, 2018, if the annuity begins at a time when the sum of the member's attained age and creditable service totals eighty-five and the member is at least fifty-five years of age, the annuity shall not be reduced.</para><para>(b) For employees who become members on or after July 1, 2018, if the annuity begins at a time when the sum of the member's attained age and creditable service totals eighty-five and the member is at least sixty years of age, the annuity shall not be reduced.</para><para>(2)(a) For an employee who becomes a member prior to July 1, 2018, if the annuity begins on or after the sixtieth birthday of the member and the member has completed at least a total of five years of creditable service, the annuity shall be reduced by twenty-five hundredths percent for each month or partial month between the date the annuity begins and the member's sixty-fifth birthday.</para><para>(b) For a member hired or rehired on or after July 1, 2018, if the annuity begins on or after the sixtieth birthday and the member has completed at least a total of five years of creditable service including eligibility and vesting credit but has not qualified for an unreduced annuity as specified in this section, the annuity shall be reduced by twenty-five hundredths percent for each month or partial month between the date the annuity begins and the member's sixty-fifth birthday.</para><para>(3) A member's attained age shall be measured in one-half-year increments.</para><para>(4) Except as provided in section 42-1107, the normal form of the formula retirement annuity based on final average compensation shall be an annuity payable monthly during the remainder of the member's life with the provision that, in the event of his or her death before sixty monthly payments have been made, the monthly payments will be continued to his or her estate or to the beneficiary he or she has designated until a total of sixty monthly payments have been made. A member may elect to receive, in lieu of the normal form of annuity, an actuarially equivalent annuity in any optional form provided by section 79-9,101.</para><para>(5) All formula annuities shall be paid from the Class V School Employees Retirement Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 40. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>