<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id416" statutenumber="79-9,118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,118</statuteno><catchline>Participation in retirement system; qualification.</catchline><para>No employee shall be authorized to participate in the retirement system unless the employee is a United States citizen or is lawfully present in the United States. The employing public school and the school employee shall maintain at least one of the following documents which shall be unexpired, if applicable to the particular document, to demonstrate United States citizenship or lawful presence in the United States as of the employee's date of hire, and, beginning September 1, 2024, produce any such document so maintained upon request of the retirement board or the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems:</para><para>(1) A state-issued driver's license;</para><para>(2) A state-issued identification card;</para><para>(3) A certified copy of a birth certificate or delayed birth certificate issued in any state, territory, or possession of the United States;</para><para>(4) A Consular Report of Birth Abroad issued by the United States Department of State;</para><para>(5) A United States passport;</para><para>(6) A foreign passport with a United States visa;</para><para>(7) A United States Certificate of Naturalization;</para><para>(8) A United States Certificate of Citizenship;</para><para>(9) A tribal certificate of Native American blood or similar document;</para><para>(10) A United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Employment Authorization Document, Form I-766;</para><para>(11) A United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Permanent Resident Card, Form I-551; or</para><para>(12) Any other document issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security or the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services granting employment authorization in the United States and approved (a) until September 1, 2024, by the board of trustees and (b) beginning September 1, 2024, by the retirement board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB198, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>