<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id344" statutenumber="79-451"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-451</statuteno><catchline id="id347">New school district; state committee; appoint board; members; appointment; terms; duties.</catchline><para>Within thirty days after the classification of the reorganized school districts by the county clerk under section 79-450, the state committee shall appoint from among the legal voters of each new school district created the number of school board members specified in the plan of reorganization. A reorganized school district shall be formed and organized and shall have a school board not later than April 1 following the last legal action, as prescribed in section 79-450, necessary to effect the changes in boundaries as set forth in the plan of reorganization, although the physical reorganization of such reorganized school district may not take effect until June 1. The first board shall be appointed on an at-large basis, and all boards shall be elected at large until such time as school districts are established as provided in section 32-554.</para><para>In appointing the first school board of a Class I, II, or III school district, the terms of approximately one-half of the members shall expire on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January after the first even-numbered year following their appointment and the terms of the remaining members shall expire on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January after the second even-numbered year following their appointment.</para><para>The school board so appointed shall proceed at once to organize in the manner prescribed by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 249, &#167; 18, p. 679; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 311, &#167; 7, p. 962; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, (1958),&#167; 79-426.18; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 479, &#167; 13, p. 1545; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 557, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 592, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 520, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 789, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 593; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-426.19; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 200; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 967, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 345, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 27. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>