<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-216"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-216</statuteno><catchline>Children of members in military service; children of parents employed by federal government and living on national parks; admission discretionary; when exempt from tuition.</catchline><para>In all cases when any officer or enlisted member of the United States Army, Navy, Marine Corps, or Air Force is on active duty in the State of Nebraska and is residing on property acquired by the United States pursuant to Chapter 72, article 6, prior to the repeal of such article by Laws 1969, Chapter 593, the children of any such officer or enlisted member who are of school age may be admitted to any of the public schools in any school district, in, near, or adjacent to the place where such officer or enlisted member is stationed so long as such officer or enlisted member is on active duty in Nebraska, and such children may be admitted to the public schools of any such district without payment of tuition.</para><para>This section also applies to children of parents employed by the federal government and residing with their parents on national parks or national monuments within this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 185, &#167; 1, p. 742; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-521; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-518; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 85, p. 721; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 390, &#167; 1, p. 1345; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 533, &#167; 1, p. 1767; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 292, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 839, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-446; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 20. </para></source><annotation><para>Military personnel living off and on air base are part of population of county. Ludwig v. Board of County Commissioners of Sarpy County, 170 Neb. 600, 103 N.W.2d 838 (1960).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>