<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-311"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-311</statuteno><catchline>State Board of Education; districts; numbers; boundaries; established by maps; Clerk of Legislature;
Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For the purpose of section 79-310, the state
is divided into eight districts. Each
district shall be entitled to one member on the board.</para>
<para>(2)
The numbers and boundaries of the districts are designated and established
by maps identified and labeled as maps ED11-1, ED11-2, ED11-3, ED11-4, ED11-5,
ED11-5A, ED11-6, ED11-7, and ED11-8, filed with the Clerk of the Legislature,
and incorporated by reference as part of Laws 2011, LB702.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The Clerk of the
Legislature shall transfer possession of the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section to the Secretary of State on May 27, 2011.</para>
<para>(b) When questions of
interpretation of district boundaries arise, the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section in possession of the Secretary of State shall serve as
the indication of the legislative intent in drawing the district boundaries.</para>
<para>(c) Each election commissioner
or county clerk shall obtain copies of the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section for the election commissioner's or clerk's county from
the Secretary of State.</para><para>(d)
The Secretary of State shall also have available for viewing on his or her
web site the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section identifying
the boundaries for the districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 527, &#167; 2, p. 1751; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 735, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 554, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 619, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-322.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 139; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 856, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB702, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
