
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-813"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-813</statuteno><catchline>Teachers' and administrators' certificates or permits; military spouses; applicants by reciprocity; requirements.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The board shall authorize the issuance of a certificate or permit to any applicant for such certificate or permit who:</para><para>(i) Is a military spouse or has been offered employment to teach, administer, or provide special services by an accredited school district in Nebraska or an approved and accredited private, denominational, or parochial school in Nebraska;</para><para>(ii) Holds a valid certificate or permit, in force in another state at the time of application, to teach, administer, or provide special services;</para><para>(iii) Has held such certificate or permit for at least one year;</para><para>(iv) Is in good standing in all states in which the applicant holds a certificate or permit to teach, administer, or provide special services;</para><para>(v) Does not have any pending investigation or complaint against any such certificate or permit;</para><para>(vi) Meets all residency and background check requirements otherwise required for a Nebraska certificate or permit; and</para><para>(vii) Pays any applicable fees.</para><para>(b) The commissioner shall verify that the applicant for a certificate or permit under this subsection meets the requirements of subdivisions (a)(iv) and (v) of this subsection. Such applicant shall not be required to meet the human relations training requirement under section 79-808 to obtain such certification or permit. Such certificate or permit shall be valid for at least three years and shall include the same or similar endorsements to teach in all subject areas for which the applicant had been certified to teach in such other state if a similar endorsement is offered in Nebraska.</para><para>(c) A preliminary permit shall be issued to an applicant upon submission of the application, payment of the applicable fees, and the successful completion of the criminal history record information check as provided in section 79-814.01. The preliminary permit shall remain in force until the commissioner completes the review of all requirements in subdivision (1)(a) of this section and either issues a certificate or permit or notifies the applicant of the reason such certificate or permit cannot be issued.</para><para>(d) The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to (i) expedite the processing of an application submitted under this subsection by an applicant whose spouse is serving on active duty at the time of such submission and (ii) specify the documentation necessary to establish the applicant's status as a spouse of a person who is serving on active duty at the time of such submission.</para><para>(e) For purposes of this subsection:</para><para>(i) Active duty means full-time duty status in the active uniformed service of the United States, including members of the National Guard and Reserve on active duty orders pursuant to 10 U.S.C. chapters 1209 and 1211; and</para><para>(ii) Military spouse has the same meaning as in section 38-118.01.</para><para>(2)(a) The board shall authorize the issuance of a certificate or permit to any applicant for such certificate or permit who:</para><para>(i) Holds a valid certificate or permit to teach in force in another state at the time of application;</para><para>(ii) Is in good standing in all states in which the applicant holds a certificate or permit to teach;</para><para>(iii) Does not have any pending investigation or complaint against any such certificate or permit;</para><para>(iv) Meets all residency and background check requirements otherwise required for a Nebraska certificate or permit; and</para><para>(v) Pays any applicable fees.</para><para>(b) The commissioner shall verify that the applicant for a teaching certificate or permit under this subsection meets the requirements of subdivisions (2)(a)(ii) and (iii) of this section. Such applicant shall not be required to meet the human relations training requirement under section 79-808 to obtain such certification or permit. Such certificate or permit shall include the same or similar endorsements to teach in all subject areas for which the applicant had been certified to teach in such other state if a similar endorsement is offered in Nebraska.</para><para>(c) A conditional permit shall be issued to an applicant upon submission of the application, payment of the applicable fees, and the successful completion of the criminal history record information check as provided in section 79-814.01. The conditional permit shall remain in force until the commissioner completes the review of all the requirements of subdivision (2)(a) of this section and either issues a certificate or permit to teach or notifies the applicant of the reason such certificate or permit cannot be issued.</para><para>(d) The department shall make available on a portal on the department's website the option or ability for individuals to apply for a certificate to teach pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(3) In addition to certificates and permits issued pursuant to subsections (1) and (2) of this section, the board may authorize the issuance of other certificates or permits to applicants who hold a valid certificate or permit currently in force in another state if the requirements for the certificate or permit held by the applicant are comparable and equivalent to those required for a similar type of certificate or permit issued under sections 79-806 to 79-815.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 491, &#167; 8, p. 1571; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 802, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1247.10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 443; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB389, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1218, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 70. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>