<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00"  statutenumber="79-407"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-407</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class III school district; boundaries; body corporate; powers.</catchline><para id="id00">The territory within the corporate limits of each incorporated municipality in the State of Nebraska that is not in part within the boundaries of a learning community, together with such additional territory and additions to such municipality as may be added thereto, as declared by ordinances to be boundaries of such municipality, having a population of less than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, including such adjacent territory as now is or hereafter may be attached for school purposes, shall constitute a Class III school district, except that nothing in this section shall be construed to change the boundaries of any school district that is a member of a learning community. The school district shall be a body corporate and possess all the usual powers of a corporation for public purposes and may sue and be sued, purchase, hold, and sell such personal and real property, and control such obligations as are authorized by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision XIV, &#167; 1, p. 376; </para><para>Laws 1883, c. 72, &#167; 18, p. 296; </para><para>Laws 1897, c. 69, &#167; 1, p. 315; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 128, &#167; 1, p. 472; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6948; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 128, &#167; 1, p. 309; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6582; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2501; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2501; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 232, p. 767; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 382, &#167; 4, p. 1325; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 541, &#167; 1, p. 1782; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 383, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 743, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 16, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 465, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 908, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1142, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 835, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-801; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 156; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 345, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 629, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 21; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 14. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Annexation by change of city boundaries,</emphasis> see section 79-473.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The selection of a site for a new school building in a Class III district is an administrative determination to be made by the board of education of the district. Christian v. Geis, 193 Neb. 146, 225 N.W.2d 868 (1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>