<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-9,122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,122</statuteno><catchline>Class V School Employees Retirement System Management Work Plan Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Class V School Employees Retirement System Management Work Plan Fund is created. The purpose of the fund is to transfer funds as specified in this section. The fund shall consist of the amounts transferred from an employer of any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act for all work performed by the Public Employees Retirement Board for services and related expenses in completion of the work described in sections 79-979.01, 79-9,121, and 79-9,124. The fund shall be administered by the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) An employer of any Class V school employees retirement system established under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act shall remit the payments described in subsection (3) of section 79-9,121, subsection (3) of section 79-979.01, and section 79-9,124 to the State Treasurer for credit to the Class V School Employees Retirement System Management Work Plan Fund for all work performed by the retirement board for (a) services and related expenses in completion of the work plan, (b) additional identification and examination of issues as required under section 79-9,124, and (c) the transfer of management of the retirement system to the retirement board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB31, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB147, &#167; 41. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>