<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-309.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>79-309.01</statuteno><catchline>Teacher performance pay; local
collective-bargaining agreements; data; Commissioner of Education; duties;
school district; use of funds; return of funds.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Beginning in 2016, the Commissioner
of Education shall annually collect data from each school district prior to
February 25 and determine whether at least seventy-five percent of the school
districts have included a system for distributing apportionment funds attributable
to income from solar or wind energy leases on school lands for teacher performance
pay within such districts' local collective-bargaining agreements for the
ensuing school fiscal year.</para>
<para>(b)(i) If the
seventy-five percent requirement has been met for the year, the Commissioner
of Education shall use the separate accounting provided by the State Treasurer
under subdivision (1)(b) of section 79-1035 to determine the amount of the
apportionment to each school district under section 79-1035 that is attributable
to income from solar or wind energy leases on school lands. The commissioner
shall notify each school district of such amount within five days after certification
of the apportionment required pursuant to subsection (3) of section 79-1035.
Each school district shall use the amount of apportionment funds specified
in the notice provided by the commissioner for the purpose of teacher performance
pay. Such amount shall be used as a supplement to the salary schedule as provided
in local collective-bargaining agreements. For purposes of distribution of
such funds only, the Legislature finds that teacher performance pay measurements,
criteria, and payout amounts are mandatory topics of collective bargaining.
If a school district has not included a system for distributing apportionment
funds attributable to income from solar or wind energy leases on school lands
for teacher performance pay within its local collective-bargaining agreement,
the amount of apportionment funds specified in the notice provided by the
commissioner shall be returned to the State Treasurer within one month of
receipt of such funds. The State Treasurer shall immediately credit any funds
returned under this section to the temporary school fund. Any funds returned
under this section shall be redistributed from the temporary school fund in
the following year and shall no longer be designated as income attributable
to solar or wind energy leases on school lands.</para><para>(ii) If the seventy-five
percent requirement has not been met for the year, then subdivision (1)(b)(i)
of this section shall not apply for that year.</para><para>(2) If the seventy-five
percent requirement has not been met in 2016, 2017, or 2018, then this section
shall not apply in 2019 or any year thereafter.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this
section:</para><para>(a) Lease means any lease, easement, covenant, or other such contractual
arrangement; and</para><para>(b) Teacher performance pay means a systematic process for measuring
teachers' performance and linking the measurements to changes in teacher pay.
Indicators of teacher performance may include improving professional skills
and knowledge, classroom performance or instructional behavior, and instructional
outcomes. Teacher performance pay may include predetermined bonus amounts
and payout criteria.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1014, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>