<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id104" statutenumber="79-2,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2,104</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Access to
school files or records; limitation; fees; disciplinary material; removed
and destroyed; when; sharing
of student data, records, and information.</catchline><para>(1)
Any student in any public school or his or her parents, guardians, teachers,
counselors, or school administrators shall have access to the school's files
or records maintained concerning such student, including the right to inspect,
review, and obtain copies of such files or records. No other person shall
have access to such files or records except (a) when a parent, guardian, or
student of majority age provides written consent or (b) as provided in subsection
(3) of this section. The contents of such files or records shall not be divulged
in any manner to any unauthorized person. All such files or records shall
be maintained so as to separate academic and disciplinary matters, and all
disciplinary material shall be removed and destroyed after a student's continuous
absence from the school for a period of three years.</para>
<para>(2) Each public school may establish a schedule of fees representing
a reasonable cost of reproduction for copies of a student's files or records
for the parents or guardians of such student, except that the imposition of
a fee shall not prevent parents of students from exercising their right to
inspect and review the students' files or records and no fee shall be charged
to search for or retrieve any student's files or records.</para>
<para>(3)(a) This section does not preclude authorized representatives of
(i) auditing officials of the United States, (ii) auditing officials of this
state, or (iii) state educational authorities from having access to student
or other records which are necessary in connection with the audit and evaluation
of federally supported or state-supported education programs or in connection
with the enforcement of legal requirements which relate to such programs,
except that, when collection of personally identifiable data is specifically
authorized by law, any data collected by such officials with respect to individual
students shall be protected in a manner which shall not permit the personal
identification of students and their parents by other than the officials listed
in this subsection. Personally identifiable data shall be destroyed when no
longer needed for such audit, evaluation, or enforcement of legal requirements.</para>
<para>(b) This section does not preclude or prohibit the disclosure of student
records to any other person or entity which may be allowed to have access
pursuant to the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974,
20 U.S.C. 1232g, as such act existed on February
1, 2013, and regulations adopted thereunder.</para>
<para>(4) The Legislature finds
and declares that the sharing of student data, records, and information among
school districts, educational service units, learning communities, and the
State Department of Education, to the fullest extent practicable and permitted
by law, is vital to advancing education in this state. Whenever applicable
law permits the sharing of such student data, records, and information, each
school district, educational service unit, and learning community shall comply
unless otherwise prohibited by law. The State Board of Education shall adopt
and promulgate rules and regulations providing for and requiring the uniform
sharing of student data, records, and information among school districts,
educational service units, learning communities, and the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 370, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 133, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 642, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-4,157; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB262, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>