<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-401</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 87. Operative date January 1, 2019. Reorganization of school districts; findings; intent; goals.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds and declares that orderly and appropriate reorganization of school districts may contribute to the objectives of tax equity, educational effectiveness, and cost efficiency. The Legislature further finds that there is a need for greater flexibility in school reorganization options and procedures. It is the intent of the Legislature to encourage an orderly and appropriate reorganization of school districts. The Legislature establishes as its goals for the reorganization of school districts that:</para><para>(1) All real property and all elementary and secondary students should be within school systems which offer education in grades kindergarten through twelve. For purposes of meeting this goal, Class I and Class VI school district combinations shall be considered as including all real property and all elementary and secondary students within a school district which offers education in kindergarten through grade twelve;</para><para>(2) School districts offering education in kindergarten through grade twelve should be encouraged, when possible, to consider cooperative programs in order to enhance educational opportunities to students; and</para><para>(3) The State Department of Education in conjunction with the Bureau of Educational Research and Field Studies in the Department of Education Administration at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln should be encouraged to offer greater technical assistance to school districts which are considering reorganization options.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 940, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-426.27; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 150; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 9; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422.</para></source></law></legaldoc>