<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id426" statutenumber="79-9,102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-9,102</statuteno><catchline id="id429">Employees retirement system; annuity or other benefit; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of the Class V School Employees Retirement Act, no member or beneficiary of the retirement system shall receive in any calendar year an annuity or other benefit which would exceed the maximum benefit permitted under section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code, or any successor provision and the regulations issued thereunder, as they may be amended from time to time, and as adjusted as of January 1 of each calendar year to the dollar limitation as determined for such year by the Commissioner of Internal Revenue pursuant to section 415(d) of the Internal Revenue Code to reflect cost-of-living adjustments, and the amount of benefit to be paid to any member or beneficiary by the retirement system shall be adjusted each calendar year, if necessary, to conform with the maximum benefit permitted under section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code. The cost-of-living adjustment to the maximum benefit permitted under section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code shall apply to determining the maximum benefit of a member who severed employment or commenced receiving benefits prior to the effective date of the adjustment.</para><para>(2) Any payments provided for by sections 79-990, 79-991, and 79-992 for the purchase or restoration of creditable service shall be subject to the limitations of section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code on annual additions to the system, and the board of trustees may suspend payments, alter installment periods, or, if such suspension or alteration is not possible, deny the purchase of all or a portion of the creditable service desired to be purchased, as necessary to comply with the requirements of section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(3) This section is intended to meet and incorporate the requirements of section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code and regulations under that section that are applicable to governmental plans and shall be construed in accordance with section 415 of the Internal Revenue Code and the regulations issued thereunder and shall, by this reference, incorporate any subsequent changes made to such section as the same may apply to the retirement system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 215, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 75; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1046.01; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 637; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 35. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>