<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id25">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id27"  statutenumber="79-536"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-536</statuteno><catchline id="id30">Summer
school; children in school system; unsatisfactory progress; summer
school sessions; curricula.</catchline><para>(1) Summer school means educational opportunities that, except as
otherwise provided in this section, are undertaken on a voluntary basis by
students who will be entering any of grades one through twelve in the next
school year and are offered during the period of time between two consecutive
school years.</para><para>(2) Summer school may be offered by any school district.</para>
<para>(3) The
board of education of any school district may require children between and
including the ages of six and fifteen years, regularly enrolled within the
system and deemed by the school administration to be making unsatisfactory
progress, to attend summer school for up to one-half of a regular school day
if in the opinion of the administration they would benefit from the experience.
Chief emphasis in such summer classes shall be on reading, language arts,
and arithmetic and those areas of personality development especially in need
of development. Teachers shall be encouraged to design new and imaginative
techniques and curricula not usually used during the regular school year which
in the opinion of such teachers will offer new incentives towards learning,
with special emphasis on those techniques that seek to develop the students'
personalities in a wholesome manner, especially developing pride, self-confidence,
and self-control. Teachers of such classes shall not be assigned more than
fifteen students, or more than twenty-five students if assisted full time
by an aide or paraprofessional. Such students shall be graded at the end of
the course upon their relative degree of striving to improve their skills,
attitudes, and personalities.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 699, &#167; 1, p. 2698; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1001.02; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 289; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB235, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>