
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id367" statutenumber="79-4,129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-4,129</statuteno><catchline id="id370">State committee; duties; school board; appointments; terms; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Within thirty days after the classification of the reorganized school districts by the county clerk under section 79-4,128, the state committee shall appoint from among the legal voters of each new school district created the number of school board members specified in the plan of reorganization. A reorganized school district shall be formed and organized and shall have a school board not later than April 1 following the last legal action, as prescribed in section 79-4,128, necessary to effect the changes in boundaries as set forth in the plan of reorganization, although the physical reorganization of such reorganized school district shall take effect July 1 following the classification of the reorganized school districts under section 79-4,128. The first board shall be appointed on an at-large basis, and all boards shall be elected at large until such time as election districts are established as provided in section 32-554.</para><para>(2) In appointing the first school board of a Class I, II, or III school district, the terms of approximately one-half of the members shall expire on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January after the first even-numbered year following their appointment and the terms of the remaining members shall expire on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January after the second even-numbered year following their appointment. Thereafter all Class I, II, or III district school boards shall be elected to terms of four years.</para><para>(3) In appointing the first school board of a Class IV school district, the members shall be appointed so that the terms of three members shall expire on the third Monday in May of the first odd-numbered year following their appointment and the terms of four members shall expire on the third Monday in May of the second odd-numbered year following their appointment. Thereafter all Class IV district school boards shall be elected to terms of four years.</para><para>(4) In appointing the first school board of a Class V school district after a reorganization under this section with a nine-member board serving terms of four years, the terms of the members shall expire as provided in section 32-545. All Class V district school boards shall be elected to terms of four years.</para><para>(5) The school boards appointed under this section shall proceed at once to organize in the manner prescribed by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB125, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 35. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>