<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id572" statutenumber="79-810"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>79-810</statuteno><catchline id="id575">Certificates or permits; issuance by Commissioner of Education; fee; disposition; contents of certificate or permit; endorsements; Certification Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Certificates and permits shall be issued by the commissioner upon application on forms prescribed and provided by him or her which shall include the applicant's social security number.</para><para>(2) Each certificate or permit issued by the commissioner shall indicate the area of authorization to teach, provide special services, or administer and any areas of endorsement for which the holder qualifies. During the term of any certificate or permit issued by the commissioner, additional endorsements may be made on the certificate or permit if the holder submits an application, meets the requirements for issuance of the additional endorsements, and pays a nonrefundable fee as set by the commissioner, not to exceed fifty-five dollars.</para><para>(3) The department shall make available on a portal on the department's website the option or ability for an individual with a certificate or permit to apply for an endorsement. Such portal shall also include a list of courses that an individual with a certificate or permit may take to add an endorsement to such certificate or permit. The commissioner shall allow an individual with a certificate or permit the following alternative methods of obtaining an endorsement:</para><para>(a) Taking a subject-specific content examination in designated endorsement areas and indicating such subject as an endorsement on such individual's certificate or permit based solely on passage of the examination; or</para><para>(b) Completing an approved program of equivalent professional education in a designated endorsement area that is provided by an accredited public school.</para><para>(4) The Certification Fund is created. Any fee received by the department under sections 79-806 to 79-815 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. The fund shall be used by the department in paying the costs of certifying educators pursuant to such sections and to carry out subsection (3) of section 79-808. For issuance of a certificate or permit valid in all schools, the nonrefundable fee shall be set by the commissioner, not to exceed sixty-five dollars. Transfers may be made from the Professional Practices Commission Fund to the Education Future Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer any money remaining in the Professional Practices Commission Fund on July 19, 2024, to the Certification Fund as soon after such date as administratively possible. Any money in the Certification Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 491, &#167; 5, p. 1571; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 549, &#167; 8, p. 1814; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 728, &#167; 1, p. 2763; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 729, &#167; 1, p. 2764; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 79, p. 2393; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 540, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 771, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 855, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 89; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1247.07; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 440; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 206, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 216; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB150, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1218, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1306, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1413, &#167; 48. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB1306, section 1, with LB1329, section 69, and LB1413, section 48, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB1306 became effective July 19, 2024. Changes made by LB1329 became effective July 19, 2024. Changes made by LB1413 became effective April 2, 2024.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>