<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-525" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-525</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class III or IV school district; school board; duty to maintain schoolhouse; accounts.</catchline><para id="id00">The school board or board of education of a Class III or IV school district shall (1) provide the necessary appendages for the schoolhouse, (2) keep the same in good condition and repair during the time school is taught in the schoolhouse, and (3) keep an accurate account of all expenses incurred. Such account shall be prepared by the secretary, audited by the president and treasurer, and, on their written order, paid out of the general school fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision IV, &#167; 13, p. 349; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6775; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6316; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-413; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-415; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 79, p. 719; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-440; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 278; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 34. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><annotation><para>This section (formerly section 79-440) gives a school district the power to provide necessary appendages to the schoolhouse and to secure the regular attendance of students at school; necessarily implied in this section is the power to construct an access road when the only party in a position to build the road in the necessary timeframe is the school district. Robertson v. School Dist. No. 17 of Douglas County, 252 Neb. 103, 560 N.W.2d 469 (1997).</para><para>Claim for transportation should be filed with secretary of district. George v. School Dist. No. 24 of Red Willow County, 157 Neb. 791, 61 N.W.2d 401 (1953).</para><para>Board was not authorized to purchase residence for teachers. Fulk v. School District No. 8 of Lancaster County, 155 Neb. 630, 53 N.W.2d 56 (1952).</para><para>Duty to make necessary repairs to school building is vested in school board without special authority from voters. Morfeld v. Huddin, 131 Neb. 180, 267 N.W. 350 (1936).</para><para>Director, with consent of moderator, may contract for repairs during vacation. Leonard v. State ex rel. Tressler, 67 Neb. 635, 93 N.W. 988 (1903).</para><para>Architect's fees for plans for new building are general expense. Fiske v. School Dist. of City of Lincoln, 59 Neb. 51, 80 N.W. 265 (1899), reversing on rehearing 58 Neb. 163, 78 N.W. 392 (1899).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>