<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id275">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id277" statutenumber="79-920"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-920</statuteno><catchline id="id280">State school
official; department employee; retirement system options.</catchline><para>(1) An individual who was, prior to July 19, 1980, a state school
official and did not become a member of the State Employees Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska pursuant to the State Employees Retirement Act may,
within sixty days after September 1, 1986, elect to become a member of such
system. An individual so electing shall pay the contributions required by
such system when the service and minimum age requirements have been met.</para>
<para>(2)(a) An individual (i) who is or was previously a school
employee or who was employed in an out-of-state or a Class V school district,
(ii) who becomes employed by the State Department of Education after July
1, 1989, and (iii) who is a state school official may file with the retirement
board within thirty days after employment an election to become or remain
a member of the School Employees Retirement
System of the State of Nebraska. Employees electing not to participate in
the School Employees Retirement
System shall participate in the State Employees Retirement System of the State
of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(b) An individual shall be required to participate in the
State Employees Retirement System if (i) the individual terminated employment
from a public school participating in the School Employees Retirement System and retired pursuant
to the School Employees Retirement Act and (ii) the employment by the State
Department of Education began or will begin within one hundred eighty days
after terminating employment from the school.</para>
<para>(3) An employee electing not to be covered by the School Employees Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska under this section shall not be subject to section
79-957 but shall be allowed to retain his or her accumulated contribution
in the system and continue to become vested in the state's accumulated contribution
as well as the State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska
according to the following:</para>
<para>(a) The years of participation in the School Employees Retirement System of the State of
Nebraska before an election is made plus the years of participation in the
State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska after the election
is made shall both be credited toward compliance with the service requirements
provided under section 79-931; and</para>
<para>(b) The years of participation in the School Employees Retirement System of the State of
Nebraska before the election is made plus the years of participation in the
State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska after the election
is made shall both be credited toward compliance with section 84-1321.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 818, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 325, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 506, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1565; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 555; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 22.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1331.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>