
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-265"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-265</statuteno><catchline>Principal; suspend student; grounds; procedure; written statement; conference.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in section 79-265.01, the principal may deny any student the right to attend school or to take part in any school function for a period of up to five school days on the following grounds:</para><para>(a) Conduct constituting grounds for expulsion as set out in the Student Discipline Act; or</para><para>(b) Any other violation of rules and standards of behavior adopted under the act.</para><para>(2) Such short-term suspension shall be made only after the principal has made an investigation of the alleged conduct or violation and has determined that such suspension is necessary to help any student, to further school purposes, or to prevent an interference with school purposes.</para><para>(3) Before such short-term suspension takes effect, the student shall be given oral or written notice of the charges against him or her, an explanation of the evidence the authorities have, and an opportunity to present his or her version.</para><para>(4) Within twenty-four hours or such additional time as is reasonably necessary, not to exceed an additional forty-eight hours, following such suspension, the principal shall send a written statement to the student and his or her parent or guardian describing the student's conduct, misconduct, or violation of the rule or standard and the reasons for the action taken. The principal shall make a reasonable effort to hold a conference with the parent or guardian before or at the time the student returns to school and shall document such effort in writing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 503, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1250, &#167; 14; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-4,178; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 64. </para></source><annotation><para>The statutory procedures to be followed in establishing and promulgating rules and standards of student conduct and in suspending students for violation of such rules embody all due process requirements set out in Goss v. Lopez, 419 U.S. 565 (1975). Walker v. Bradley, 211 Neb. 873, 320 N.W.2d 900 (1982).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>