<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-852"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-852</statuteno><catchline>Collective-bargaining agreement; continued; effect.</catchline><para>The collective-bargaining agreement of the school district or districts forming the unified system or reorganized school district with the largest number of teacher employees shall continue in full force and effect and govern all teachers in the unified system or reorganized school district until replaced by a successor agreement, and the teachers employed by the unified system or reorganized school district and previously employed by the school districts involved in the formation of the unified system or reorganized school district shall automatically be included in that bargaining unit but no certificated public school employee shall be compelled to join any organization or association. If only one collective-bargaining agreement is in effect in the school districts which are a part of the unification or reorganization, that collective-bargaining agreement shall continue in full force and effect until replaced by a successor agreement and the teachers employed by the other school districts involved in the unification or reorganization shall automatically be included in that bargaining unit. For purposes of the Industrial Relations Act, the unified system shall be deemed an employer as defined in section 48-801.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 844, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-12,106; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 482; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Industrial Relations Act,</emphasis> see section 48-801.01.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>