<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-590"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-590</statuteno><catchline>Class III school district; board of education; treasurer; duties; bond or insurance; compensation.</catchline><para>The board of education of a Class III school district may employ a treasurer for such district who shall be paid a salary, to be fixed by the board, of not to exceed one thousand two hundred dollars per annum. If the board does not employ such a treasurer, the city treasurer or deputy city treasurer of the city which is within such district shall be ex officio treasurer of the school district. He or she shall attend all meetings of the board when required so to do, prepare and submit in writing a monthly report of the state of the district's finances, and pay school money only upon warrants signed by the president of the board or, in the president's absence, by the vice president, and countersigned by the secretary. If the city treasurer or his or her deputy acts as ex officio treasurer of the school district, he or she shall be paid for such services by the school district a sum to be fixed by the board. The treasurer of such district, or the city treasurer or deputy city treasurer acting as ex officio treasurer, shall give a bond or evidence of equivalent insurance coverage payable to the county in such sum as may be fixed by the board of education. Such bond shall be signed by one or more surety companies of recognized responsibility. The cost of such bond or insurance coverage shall be paid by the school district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision XIV, &#167; 13, p. 381; </para><para>Laws 1883, c. 72, &#167; 22, p. 299; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 59, &#167; 4, p. 287; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6960; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6594; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2513; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2515; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 242, p. 771; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 305, &#167; 1, p. 1020; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 488, &#167; 1, p. 1559; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-809; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 343; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 380, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For applicability of this section to certain Class III school districts,</emphasis> see section 79-589.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>