<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-454"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-454</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 87. Operative date January 1, 2019. Proposal; state committee; approve; election; notice.</catchline><para>If the proposal provided for in section 79-452 has been approved by the State Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts, the state committee shall notify the school board of the Class I or II district. The school board shall, within fifteen days after the notification, set a date for a special election for the purpose of submitting the proposal to the legal voters of the district. At least twenty days' notice of such election shall be given by publication twice in a newspaper of general circulation in the district, the latest publication to be not more than one week before the election. If there is no such newspaper, notice shall be given by posting it on the door of the schoolhouse and at least four other public places throughout the district. The proposal shall not be submitted to a special election more than once in any calendar year. Legal voters may cast their ballots, written or printed, between the hours of 12 noon and 8 p.m. on the date of such election. The county clerk or election commissioner of the county which has the largest number of pupils residing in the district shall conduct such special election in accordance with the Election Act and shall record the names and residence of persons voting at the special election. The ballots shall be canvassed as provided in section 79-447.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 510, &#167; 3, p. 1630; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 530, &#167; 2, p. 1762; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 661, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 662, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 594; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-426.25; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 203; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 31; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act, </emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Lack of preelection hearing on sufficiency of petitions did not violate due process. Hall v. Simpson, 184 Neb. 762, 171 N.W.2d 805 (1969).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>