<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-205</statuteno><catchline>Compulsory attendance; record of attendance; annual attendance reports; made where.</catchline><para>Each teacher in the public, private, denominational, and parochial schools of this state shall keep a record showing (1) the name, age, and address of each child enrolled, (2) the number and county of the school district in which the school is located, (3) the number of days each pupil was present and the number of days absent, and (4) the cause of absence. On the third day on which the public, private, denominational, and parochial schools are in session at the beginning of each school year, each teacher shall send to the superintendent or administrator of the school a list of the pupils enrolled in his or her school with the age, grade, and address of each.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 70, &#167; 1, p. 454; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 549; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 140, &#167; 1, p. 575; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 131, &#167; 1, p. 430; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6924; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 155, &#167; 1, p. 346; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 53, &#167; 1(f), p. 228; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6508d; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-1904; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-1911; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 13, p. 694; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 210, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-207; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 25. </para></source><annotation><para>The state, having a high responsibility for the education of its citizens, has the power to impose reasonable regulations for the control and duration of basic education. Parents have a right to send their children to private schools but do not have the right to be completely unfettered by reasonable government regulations as to the quality of the education furnished and the maintenance of minimum standards. State ex rel. Douglas v. Faith Baptist Church of Louisville, 207 Neb. 802, 301 N.W.2d 571 (1981).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>