<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id94" statutenumber="79-8,137.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-8,137.05</statuteno><catchline id="id97">Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund is created. The fund shall consist of appropriations by the Legislature, transfers pursuant to section 9-812, and loan repayments, penalties, and interest payments received in the course of administering the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program and the Enhancing Excellence in Teaching Program.</para><para>(2) For all fiscal years, the department shall allocate on an annual basis up to four hundred thousand dollars in the aggregate of the funds to be distributed for the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program to all eligible institutions according to the distribution formula as determined by rule and regulation. The eligible institutions shall act as agents of the department in the distribution of the funds for the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program to eligible students. The department shall allocate on an annual basis up to eight hundred thousand dollars of the remaining available funds to be distributed to eligible students for the Enhancing Excellence in Teaching Program. Funding amounts granted in excess of one million two hundred thousand dollars shall be evenly divided for distribution between the two programs.</para><para>(3) Any money remaining in the fund on August 1, 2021, shall be transferred to the Nebraska Education Improvement Fund on such date.</para><para>(4) Any money in the Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1399, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2001, Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 79-8,136; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB547, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB333, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB967, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB519, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>