<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-580" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-580</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class III school district; board of education; claims against; record of proceedings; secretary; duty to publish.</catchline><para id="id00">The secretary of the school board or board of education of each Class III school district shall, within ten days after any regular or special meeting of the board, publish one time in a legal newspaper published in or of general circulation in such district a list of the claims, arising on contract or tort, allowed at the meeting. The list shall set forth the name of the claimant and the amount and nature of the claim allowed, to consist of not more than ten words in stating the nature of each such claim. The secretary shall likewise cause to be published a concise summary of all other proceedings of such meetings. Publication of such claims or proceedings in a legal newspaper shall not be required unless the publication can be done at an expense not exceeding the rates provided by law for the publication of proceedings of county boards.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1255, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-552; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 333; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 49. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Salaries of school district employees are not "claims" within the meaning of this section and are not required to be published individually. State ex rel. Thompson v. Alderman, 230 Neb. 335, 431 N.W.2d 625 (1988).</para><para>This section, requiring the publication of claims allowed by school boards of Class III school districts, does not require the publication of the individual salaries of the employees of the district. Employees did not make any demand for payment of their salaries; no school board action was necessary; no board action was taken; and no publication was necessary. State ex rel. Thompson v. Alderman, 230 Neb. 335, 431 N.W.2d 625 (1988).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>