<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-8,145.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-8,145.01</statuteno><catchline>Alternative certificate to teach; issuance; terms and conditions.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to certificates issued pursuant to section 79-806 to 79-815, the Commissioner of Education shall, subject to subsections (2) and (3) of this section, issue an alternative certificate to teach on a full-time basis to any applicant who:</para><para>(a) Possesses a baccalaureate degree; and</para><para>(b) Has successfully completed an alternative teacher program operated by an organization that satisfies the following criteria:</para><para>(i) The organization operates in at least five states;</para><para>(ii) The organization has operated an alternative teacher certification program for at least ten years; and</para><para>(iii) The program requires candidates to pass a subject area examination and a pedagogy examination to receive a documentation of successful completion of such program.</para><para>(2) An alternative certificate issued by the Commissioner of Education under this section only authorizes an individual to teach the subject and educational levels for which the individual has successfully completed an alternative teacher program.</para><para>(3) Issuance of an alternative certificate pursuant to this section shall also be subject to any rules, regulations, or procedures established pursuant to subdivisions (1)(c) and (f) of section 79-808 and section 79-810.</para><para>(4) An individual who receives an alternative certificate pursuant to this section shall:</para><para>(a) Participate in a school district clinical experience for one semester in such individual's first semester of employment as a teacher pursuant to this section; and</para><para>(b) Be subject to the same certification criteria as an individual who completes a traditional teacher preparation program if converting the alternative certificate to a standard certificate to teach.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 71. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>