<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-442"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-442</statuteno><catchline>State committee; plan of reorganization; public hearings; notice.</catchline><para>Before any plan of reorganization is completed or approved by the state committee, it shall hold one or more public hearings. At such hearings, it shall hear any and all persons interested with respect to (1) the merits of proposed reorganization plans, (2) the value and amount of all school property of whatever nature involved in the proposed action, (3) the amount of outstanding indebtedness of each district and proposed disposition thereof, and (4) the equitable adjustment of all property, debts, and liabilities among the districts involved. The state committee shall keep a record of all hearings in the formulation or approval of plans for the reorganization of school districts. Notice of such public hearings of the state committee shall be given by publication in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the county or counties in which the affected districts are located at least ten days prior to such hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 249, &#167; 10, p. 677; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 479, &#167; 5, p. 1539; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-426.10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 191; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 9. </para></source><annotation><para>This section provides for a public hearing before the completion of a plan of reorganization. Arends v. Whitten, 172 Neb. 297, 109 N.W.2d 363 (1961).</para><para>Omission from record of items not specifically required to be kept was not a fatal defect. School District No. 49 of Lincoln County v. School District No. 65-R of Lincoln County, 159 Neb. 262, 66 N.W.2d 561 (1954).</para><para>Notice and hearing on plan is provided. Nickel v. School Board of Axtell, 157 Neb. 813, 61 N.W.2d 566 (1953).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>