<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id36">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id38" statutenumber="79-319"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-319</statuteno><catchline id="id41">State Board of
Education; additional powers; enumerated.</catchline><para>The State
Board of Education has the authority to (1) provide for the education of and
approve special educational facilities and programs provided in the public
schools for children with disabilities, (2) act as the state's authority for
the approval of all types of veterans educational programs and have jurisdiction
over the administration and supervision of on-the-job and apprenticeship training,
on-the-farm training, and flight training programs for veterans which are
financially supported in whole or in part by the federal government, (3) supervise
and administer any educational or training program established within the
state by the federal government, except postsecondary education in approved
colleges, (4) coordinate educational activities in the state that pertain
to elementary and secondary education and such other educational programs
as are placed by statute under the jurisdiction of the board, (5) receive
and distribute according to law any money, commodities, goods, or services
made available to the board from the state or federal government or from any
other source and distribute money in accordance with the terms of any grant
received, including the distribution of money from grants by the federal government
to schools, preschools, day care centers, day care homes, nonprofit agencies,
and political subdivisions of the state or institutions of learning not owned
or exclusively controlled by the state or a political subdivision thereof,
so long as no public funds of the state, any political subdivision, or any
public corporation are added to such federal grants, (6) publish, from time
to time, directories of schools and educators, pamphlets, curriculum guides,
rules and regulations, handbooks on school constitution and other matters
of interest to educators, and similar publications. Such publications may
be distributed without charge to schools and school officials within this
state or may be sold at a price not less than the actual cost of printing.
The proceeds of such sale shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the State Department of Education Cash Fund which may be used by the State
Department of Education for the purpose of printing and distributing further
such publications on a nonprofit basis. Copies of such publications shall be provided to the Nebraska Publications
Clearinghouse pursuant to section
51-413, and (7) when necessary for the proper administration of
the functions of the department and with the approval of the Governor and
the Department of Administrative Services, rent or lease space outside the
State Capitol.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 320, &#167; 9, p. 1058; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 384, &#167; 1, p. 1332; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 395, &#167; 1, p. 1202; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 469, &#167; 5, p. 1504; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1284, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 863, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 359, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 733, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 417, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 997, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-329; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 147; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB967, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>