<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id6" statutenumber="79-921"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-921</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Retirement system;
membership; termination; employer; duty; reinstatement; application for restoration of relinquished
creditable service; payment required.</catchline><para>(1)
The membership of any person in the retirement system shall cease only if
he or she (a) withdraws his or her accumulated contributions under section
79-955, (b) retires on a school or formula or disability retirement allowance,
or (c) dies.</para>
<para>(2) The employer shall notify the board of the date upon which
a termination has occurred. It is the responsibility of the employer that
is involved in the termination of employment to notify the board of such change
in employment and provide the board with such information as the board deems
necessary.</para>

<para>(3)(a) A former
member of the retirement system who has withdrawn his or her accumulated contributions
under section 79-955 shall be reinstated to membership in the retirement system
if such person again becomes a school employee.</para><para>(b) The date of such membership
shall relate back to the beginning of his or her original membership in the
retirement system only if such school employee has repaid all amounts required
in accordance with subsection (4) of this section. Unless and until all such
amounts are repaid, the school employee shall be considered a new member,
effective as of the date he or she again becomes a school employee.</para>
<para>(4)(a) With respect to
any person who is reinstated to membership in the retirement system pursuant
to subdivision (3)(a) of this section prior to April 17, 2014, and who files
a valid and complete one-time application with the retirement board for the
restoration of part or all of his or her relinquished creditable service prior
to six years after April 17, 2014, but prior to termination, the following
shall apply:</para><para>(i)
Such member shall pay to the retirement system an amount equal to the previously
withdrawn contributions for the creditable service to be restored, plus an
amount equal to the actuarial assumed rate of return on such amount to the
date of repayment; and</para><para>(ii)
Payment for restoration of such relinquished creditable service must be completed
within six years of April 17, 2014, or prior to termination, whichever is
earlier.</para><para>(b)
With respect to any person who is reinstated to membership in the retirement
system pursuant to subdivision (3)(a) of this section on and after April 17,
2014, and who files a valid and complete one-time application with the retirement
board for the restoration of part or all of his or her relinquished creditable
service within five years after the date of such member's reinstatement to
membership in the retirement system but prior to termination, the following
shall apply:</para><para>(i)
Such member shall pay to the retirement system an amount equal to the previously
withdrawn contributions for the creditable service to be restored, plus an
amount equal to the actuarial assumed rate of return on such amount to the
date of repayment; and</para><para>(ii)
Payment for restoration of such relinquished creditable service must be completed
within five years of the date of such member's reinstatement to membership
in the retirement system or prior to termination, whichever is earlier.</para>
<para>(5) If less
than full payment is made by the member, relinquished creditable service shall
be restored in proportion to the amounts repaid. Repayment may be made through
direct payment, installment payments, an irrevocable payroll deduction authorization,
cash rollover contributions pursuant to section 79-933.02, or trustee-to-trustee
transfers pursuant to section 79-933.09.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 219, &#167; 14, p. 643; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1947, &#167; 79-2914; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 448, p. 845; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 735, &#167; 4, p. 2778; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 325, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1514; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 556; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1042, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>April 17, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>