
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id143"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-303.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-303.01</statuteno><catchline>State Department of Education; Department of Health and Human Services; Office of Probation Administration; State Court Administrator; sharing data relevant to court-involved students; memorandum of understanding; policies and procedures; consultant recommendations; reports.</catchline><para>(1) On or before October 1, 2023, the State Department of Education, the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Probation Administration, and the State Court Administrator shall enter into a memorandum of understanding for the sharing of data relevant to students who are under the jurisdiction of the juvenile court. The purpose for the sharing of data is to provide systems-wide coordination to improve educational opportunities and outcomes and to facilitate service coordination for such students. The memorandum shall include the intent for the State Department of Education to contract with an outside consultant with expertise in the education of court-involved students to assist in the development of such policies and procedures.</para><para>(2) The consultant shall provide recommendations addressing issues that include, but need not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) Identifying and defining the population of students whose data should be collected and shared;</para><para>(b) Defining the specific types of data to be collected and shared;</para><para>(c) Identifying shared data systems;</para><para>(d) Identifying the entities and persons for which the data should be accessible;</para><para>(e) Identifying both federal and state legal responsibilities and confidentiality parameters; and</para><para>(f) Developing a uniform approach for the transfer of educational credits.</para><para>(3) The development of such policies and procedures for the sharing of data shall be collaborative and shall include input from the appropriate entities including, but not limited to, the State Department of Education, the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Probation Administration, the State Court Administrator, the juvenile court system, the superintendent of schools for the youth and rehabilitation centers, public school districts, educators, and court-involved students and their parents. The consultant shall provide a draft report containing the recommendations described in subsection (2) of this section to the appropriate agency representatives and to the Commissioner of Education, the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court on or before September 1, 2024.</para><para>(4) The State Department of Education shall complete a final report detailing the recommendations of the consultant and any policies and procedures that are being considered for adoption by the State Department of Education, the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Probation Administration, and the State Court Administrator. The report shall be delivered electronically to the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, the Governor, and the Clerk of the Legislature on or before December 1, 2024.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 122. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>