
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-578"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-578</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class I, II, III, or IV school district; secretary; school census; duty to take; time allowed.</catchline><para id="id00">The secretary of a Class I, II, III, or IV school district shall take, or cause to be taken by some person appointed for the purpose by a majority vote of the school board, the census of the school district and then make or cause to be made a list in writing of the names of all the children belonging to such district, from birth through twenty years of age, together with the names of all the taxpayers in the district. A copy of the list, verified by oath of the person taking such census or by affidavit appended to or endorsed on the list, setting forth that it is a correct list of the names of all children belonging in the district from birth through twenty years of age and that it reflects such information as of June 30, shall be maintained as provided in section 79-524.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision IV, &#167; 12, p. 349; </para><para>Laws 1889, c. 78, &#167; 10, p. 546; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6774; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6315; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-412; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 139, &#167; 1, p. 385; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-412; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-412; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 97, p. 724; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 315, &#167; 7, p. 977; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 346, &#167; 1, p. 1189; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 534, &#167; 1, p. 1769; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 587, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 874, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1090, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 41; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-458; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 331; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 54. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Courts will take judicial notice of census. Kokes v. State ex rel. Koupal, 55 Neb. 691, 76 N.W. 467 (1898).</para><para>Record is best evidence on question of enumeration. State ex rel. Vale v. School Dist. of City of Superior, 55 Neb. 317, 75 N.W. 855 (1898).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>