<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-587" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-587</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class III or IV school district; treasurer; district funds; receipt and disbursement.</catchline><para id="id00">The treasurer of each Class III or IV school district shall apply for and receive from the county treasurer all school money apportioned to or collected for the district by the county treasurer, upon order of the secretary countersigned by the president. The treasurer shall pay out all money received by him or her, on the order of the secretary countersigned by the president of such district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision IV, &#167; 5, p. 346; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6767; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6308; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-405; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 99, p. 725; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-460; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 340; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 52. </para></source><annotation><para>It is function of treasurer to pay out funds on order of secretary countersigned by president. Fulk v. School District No. 8 of Lancaster County, 155 Neb. 630, 53 N.W.2d 56 (1952).</para><para>It is the duty of treasurer to pay over upon order all money received. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Bank of Otoe, 125 Neb. 414, 250 N.W. 547 (1933).</para><para>Bank receiving deposit of funds of school district treasurer, who is also active managing officer of bank, holds such funds as trustee. Lincoln Nat. Bank &amp; Trust Co. v. School District No. 79 of Boyd County, 124 Neb. 538, 247 N.W. 433 (1933).</para><para>Mandamus lies to compel performance of duty by district treasurers. Leonard v. State ex rel. Tressler, 67 Neb. 635, 93 N.W. 988 (1903).</para><para>Bank receiving deposit by treasurer becomes trustee for district. State v. Midland State Bank, 52 Neb. 1, 71 N.W. 1011 (1897).</para><para>Warrant must be properly drawn and countersigned. Montgomery v. State ex rel. Thompson, 35 Neb. 655, 53 N.W. 568 (1892); Donnelly v. Duras, 11 Neb. 283, 9 N.W. 45 (1881).</para><para>District cannot release treasurer from liability for money lost or misapplied. Ward v. School Dist. No. 15 of Colfax County, 10 Neb. 293, 4 N.W. 1001 (1880).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>