<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id61">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id63" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-980"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-980</statuteno><catchline id="id66">Employees retirement
system; administration; trustees; Class V Retirement System Board; liability.</catchline><para>(1) At any time that the retirement system consists of only one
Class V school district, the general administration of the retirement system
is hereby vested in the board of education. The board shall appoint, by a
majority of all its members, ten trustees to serve as executive officers to
administer the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. Such trustees shall
consist of (a) the superintendent of schools, as ex officio trustee, (b) four
members of the retirement system, two from the certificated staff, one from
the classified staff, and one from the annuitants, (c) three members of the
board of education, and (d) two trustees who are business persons qualified
in financial affairs and who are not members of the retirement system. The
trustees shall serve without compensation, but they shall be reimbursed from
the funds of the retirement system for expenses that they may incur through
service on the board of trustees as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.
A trustee shall serve until a successor qualifies, except that trustees who
are members of the retirement system or members of the board of education
shall be disqualified as trustees immediately upon ceasing to be a member
of the retirement system or of the board of education. Each trustee shall
be entitled to one vote on the board of trustees, and six trustees shall constitute
a quorum for the transaction of any business. The trustees who are appointed
from the board of education and the membership shall be appointed for each
fiscal year. The two trustees who are not members of the board of education
or of the retirement system shall be appointed for three fiscal years each.
The trustees and the administrator of the retirement system shall administer
the retirement system in compliance with the tax-qualification requirements
applicable to government retirement plans under section 401(a) of the Internal
Revenue Code, as defined in section 49-801.01, including: Section 401(a)(9) of the Internal Revenue Code
relating to the time and manner in which benefits are required to be distributed,
including the incidental death benefit distribution requirement of section
401(a)(9)(G) of the Internal Revenue Code; section 401(a)(25) of the Internal
Revenue Code relating to the specification of actuarial assumptions; section
401(a)(31) of the Internal Revenue Code relating to direct rollover distributions
from eligible retirement plans; and section 401(a)(37) of the Internal Revenue
Code relating to the death benefit of a member whose death occurs while performing
qualified military service. No member of the board of education or trustee
shall be personally liable, except in cases of willful dishonesty, gross negligence,
or intentional violations of law, for actions relating to his or her retirement
system duties.</para>
<para>(2) At any time that the retirement system consists of more
than one Class V school district, the general administration of the retirement
system is hereby vested in a Class V Retirement System Board composed of three
members of the school board for each participating Class V school district.
The board shall appoint, by a majority of all its members, trustees to serve
as executive officers to administer the Class V School Employees Retirement
Act. Such trustees shall consist of (a) the superintendent of each participating
Class V school district, as ex officio trustees, (b) four members of the retirement
system, two from the certificated staff, one from the classified staff, and
one from the annuitants, (c) three members of the board, and (d) two trustees
who are business persons qualified in financial affairs and who are not members
of the retirement system. The trustees who are appointed from the board and
the membership shall, to the extent feasible, be appointed equally from each
participating Class V school district. The trustees shall serve without compensation,
but they shall be reimbursed from the funds of the retirement system for expenses
that they may incur through service on the board of trustees as provided in
sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. A trustee shall serve until a successor qualifies,
except that trustees who are members of the retirement system or members of
the board shall be disqualified as trustees immediately upon ceasing to be
a member of the retirement system or of the board. Each trustee shall be entitled
to one vote on the board of trustees, and six trustees shall constitute a
quorum for the transaction of any business. The trustees who are appointed
from the board and the membership shall be appointed for each fiscal year.
The two trustees who are not members of the board or of the retirement system
shall be appointed for three fiscal years each. The trustees and the administrator
of the retirement system shall administer the retirement system in compliance
with the tax-qualification requirements applicable to government retirement
plans under section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code, as defined in section
49-801.01, including: Section 401(a)(9) of the Internal Revenue Code relating
to the time and manner in which benefits are required to be distributed, including
the incidental death benefit distribution requirement of section 401(a)(9)(G)
of the Internal Revenue Code; section 401(a)(25) of the Internal
Revenue Code relating to the specification of actuarial assumptions; section
401(a)(31) of the Internal Revenue Code relating to direct rollover distributions
from eligible retirement plans; and section 401(a)(37) of the Internal Revenue
Code relating to the death benefit of a member whose death occurs while performing
qualified military service. No
member of the Class V Retirement System Board or trustee shall be personally
liable, except in cases of willful dishonesty, gross negligence, or intentional
violations of law, for actions relating to his or her retirement system duties.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 274, &#167; 3, p. 913; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 490, &#167; 1, p. 1564; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 135, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 157; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 107, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 505, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-1034; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 615; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 497, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1042, &#167; 8.</para><effectivedate>April 17, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>