<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1323"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1323</statuteno><catchline>State Department of Education; instructional telecommunications; powers and duties; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>The State Department of Education shall, with funds specifically appropriated for instructional telecommunications by the Legislature and such other funds which may be available, make provision for the planning, developing, producing, leasing, disseminating, and utilizing of instructional telecommunications in the elementary and secondary schools of Nebraska.</para><para>Funds appropriated or acquired for the purpose of providing such programming to the elementary and secondary schools shall make provision for the employment of a director and such additional employees as may be necessary for the State Department of Education to assume the designated responsibilities of instructional telecommunications and to perform the assigned functions in an efficient manner. Funds may be used to contract with the Nebraska Educational Telecommunications Commission and other organizations designed to plan, produce, and acquire instructional telecommunications programming for elementary and secondary school use. The department may publish or cause to be published, develop or cause to be developed, acquire, and distribute such telecommunications resources as it deems necessary, and it may, at its discretion, charge appropriate fees therefor. The department shall make such resources available at cost to all individuals, schools, private and public institutions, and organizations. The proceeds of all such fees paid to the department shall be deposited in the State Department of Education Cash Fund and shall be used by the department for publication, development, acquisition, and distribution of such resource material.</para><para>The State Department of Education shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for approving the type and number of credits for telecommunications courses which are offered to elementary and secondary schools.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 404, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 645, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 48; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2110; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 979; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 347, &#167; 55. </para></source></law></legaldoc>