<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools"  statutenumber="79-10,120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,120</statuteno><catchline>School district; board of education; special fund for sites and buildings; levy of taxes.</catchline><para>The school board or board of education of any school district may establish a special fund for purposes of acquiring sites for school buildings or teacherages, purchasing existing buildings for use as school buildings or teacherages, including the sites upon which such buildings are located, and the erection, alteration, equipping, and furnishing of school buildings or teacherages and additions to school buildings for elementary and high school grades and for no other purpose. The fund shall be established from the proceeds of an annual levy, to be determined by the board, of not to exceed fourteen cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all taxable property in the district which shall be in addition to any other taxes authorized to be levied for school purposes. Such tax shall be levied and collected as are other taxes for school purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 462, &#167; 1, p. 1490; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 79-811; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 49, &#167; 4, p. 268; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 237; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 79-548.01; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 190; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-547.04; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 766; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 81. </para></source><annotation><para>The levying of taxes for accumulation of funds is within the constitutional provision that "necessary revenue" of the state and its governmental subdivisions be raised by taxation in such manner as the Legislature might direct. Banks v. Board of Education of Chase County, 202 Neb. 717, 277 N.W.2d 76 (1979).</para><para>This section is not an unconstitutional delegation of legislative authority. Banks v. Board of Education of Chase County, 202 Neb. 717, 277 N.W.2d 76 (1979).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>