<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id27">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id29" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1103</statuteno><catchline id="id32">Early Childhood
Education Grant Program; established; administration; priorities; programs;
requirements; report; hearing; endowment
agreement; effect.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The State Department
of Education shall establish and administer the Early Childhood Education
Grant Program. Upon the effective date of an endowment agreement, administration
of the Early Childhood Education Grant Program with respect to programs for
children from birth to age three shall transfer to the board of trustees.
If there is no endowment agreement in effect, the department shall request
proposals in accordance with this section for all early childhood education
programs from school districts, individually or in cooperation with other
school districts or educational service units, working in cooperation with
existing nonpublic programs which meet the requirements of subsection (2)
of section 79-1104. If there is an endowment agreement in effect, the board
of trustees shall administer the Early Childhood Education Grant Program with
respect to programs for children from birth to age three pursuant to section
79-1104.02 and the department shall continue to administer the Early Childhood
Education Grant Program with respect to other prekindergarten programs pursuant
to sections 79-1101 to 79-1104.05. All administrative procedures of the board
of trustees, including, but not limited to, rules, grant applications, and
funding mechanisms, shall harmonize with those established by the department
for other prekindergarten programs.</para>
<para>(b) The first priority shall be for (i) continuation grants
for programs that received grants in the prior school fiscal year and for
which the state aid calculation pursuant to the Tax Equity and Educational
Opportunities Support Act does not include early childhood education students,
in an amount equal to the amount of such grant, except that if the grant was
a first-year grant the amount shall be reduced by thirty-three percent, (ii)
continuation grants for programs for which the state aid calculation pursuant
to the act includes early childhood education students, in an amount equal
to the amount of the grant for the school fiscal year prior to the first school
fiscal year for which early childhood education students were included in
the state aid calculation for the school district's local system minus the
calculated state aid amount, and (iii) for school fiscal year 2007-08, continuation
grants for programs for which the state aid calculation pursuant to the act
includes early childhood education students, but such state aid calculation
does not result in the school district receiving any equalization aid, in
an amount equal to the amount of the grant received in school fiscal year
2006-07. The calculated state aid amount shall be calculated by multiplying
the basic funding per formula student for the school district by the formula
students attributed to the early childhood education programs pursuant to
the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act.</para>
<para>(c) The second priority shall be for new grants and expansion
grants for programs that will serve at-risk children who will be eligible
to attend kindergarten the following school year. New grants may be given
for up to three years in an amount up to one-half of the total budget of the
program per year. Expansion grants may be given for one year in an amount
up to one-half of the budget for expanding the capacity of the program to
serve additional children.</para>
<para>(d) The third priority shall be for new grants, expansion
grants, and continuation grants for programs serving children younger than
those who will be eligible to attend kindergarten the following school year.
New grants may be given for up to three years in an amount up to one-half
the total budget of the program per year. Expansion grants may be given for
one year in an amount up to one-half the budget for expanding the capacity
of the program to serve additional children. Continuation grants under this
priority may be given annually in an amount up to one-half the total budget
of the program per year minus any continuation grants received under the first
priority.</para>
<para>(e) Programs serving children who will be eligible to attend
kindergarten the following school year shall be accounted for separately for
grant purposes from programs serving younger children, but the two types of
programs may be combined within the same classroom to serve multi-age children.
Programs that receive grants for school fiscal years prior to school fiscal
year 2005-06 to serve both children who will be eligible to attend kindergarten
the following school year and younger children shall account for the two types
of programs separately for grant purposes beginning with school year 2005-06
and shall be deemed to have received grants prior to school fiscal year 2005-06
for each year that grants were received for the types of programs representing
the age groups of the children served.</para>
<para>(2) Each program proposal which is approved by the department
shall include (a) a planning period, (b) an agreement to participate in periodic
evaluations of the program to be specified by the department, (c) evidence
that the program will be coordinated or contracted with existing programs,
including those listed in subdivision (d) of this subsection and nonpublic
programs which meet the requirements of subsection (2) of section 79-1104,
(d) a plan to coordinate and use a combination of local, state, and federal
funding sources, including, but not limited to, programs for children with
disabilities below five years of age funded through the Special Education
Act, the Early Intervention Act, funds available through the flexible funding
provisions under the Special Education Act, the federal Head Start program,
42 U.S.C. 9831 et seq., the federal Even Start Family Literacy Program, 20
U.S.C. 6361 et seq., Title I of the federal Improving America's Schools Act
of 1994, 20 U.S.C. 6301 et seq., and child care assistance through the Department
of Health and Human Services, (e) a plan to use sliding fee scales and the
funding sources included in subdivision (d) of this subsection to maximize
the participation of economically and categorically diverse groups and to
ensure that participating children and families have access to comprehensive
services, (f) the establishment of an advisory body which includes families
and community members, (g) the utilization of appropriately qualified staff,
(h) an appropriate child-to-staff ratio, (i) appropriate group size, (j) compliance
with minimum health and safety standards, (k) appropriate facility size and
equipment, (l) a strong family development and support component recognizing
the central role of parents in their children's development, (m) developmentally
and culturally appropriate curriculum, practices, and assessment, (n) sensitivity
to the economic and logistical needs and circumstances of families in the
provision of services, (o) integration of children of diverse social and economic
characteristics, (p) a sound evaluation component, including at least one
objective measure of child performance and progress, (q) continuity with programs
in kindergarten and elementary grades, (r) instructional hours that are similar
to or less than the instructional hours for kindergarten except that a summer
session may be offered, (s) well-defined language development and early literacy
emphasis, including the involvement of parents in family literacy activities,
(t) a plan for ongoing professional development of staff, and (u) inclusion
of children with disabilities as defined in the Special Education Act, all
as specified by rules and regulations of the department in accordance with
sound early childhood educational practice.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall make an effort to fund programs widely
distributed across the state in both rural and urban areas.</para>
<para>(4) The department, in collaboration with the board of trustees
if an endowment agreement is in effect, shall provide a report evaluating
the programs to the State Board of Education and the Legislature
by January 1 of each odd-numbered year. The report submitted to the Legislature
shall be submitted electronically. The
Education Committee of the Legislature shall hold a public hearing regarding
the report. Up to five percent of the total appropriation for
the Early Childhood Education Grant Program for
grants administered by the department may be reserved by the department
for evaluation and technical assistance for the programs.</para>
<para>(5) Early childhood education programs, whether established
pursuant to this section or section 79-1104, may be approved for purposes
of the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act, expansion grants,
and continuation grants on the submission of a continuation plan demonstrating
that the program will meet the requirements of subsection (2) of this section
and a proposed operating budget demonstrating that the program will receive
resources from other sources equal to or greater than the sum of any grant
received pursuant to this section for the prior school year plus any calculated
state aid as calculated pursuant to subsection (1) of this section for the
prior school year.</para>
<para>(6) The State Board of Education may adopt and promulgate
rules and regulations to implement the Early Childhood Education Grant Program,
except that if there is an endowment agreement in effect, the board of trustees
shall recommend any rules and regulations relating specifically to the Early
Childhood Education Grant Program with respect to programs for children from
birth to age three. It is the intent of the Legislature that the rules and
regulations for programs for children from birth to age three be consistent
to the greatest extent possible with those established for other prekindergarten
programs.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 567, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 70; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3703; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 785; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 759, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 577, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1256, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1153, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB235, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 160; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB495, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>April 25, 2013</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Early Intervention Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Special Education Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1110.</para><para><emphasis>Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>