<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1070"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1070</statuteno><catchline>Power to borrow money; conditions; authorization to accept loans from state or federal government.</catchline><para>(1) Any class of school district may borrow money to the amount of seventy percent of the unexpended balance of total anticipated receipts of the general fund, special building fund, bond fund, or qualified capital purpose undertaking fund for the current school fiscal year and the following school fiscal year. Total anticipated receipts of the general fund, special building fund, bond fund, or qualified capital purpose undertaking fund for the current school fiscal year and the following school fiscal year shall mean a sum equal to the total of (a) the anticipated receipts from the current existing levy multiplied by two, (b) the anticipated receipts from the United States for the current school fiscal year and the following school fiscal year, and (c) the anticipated receipts from other sources for the current school fiscal year and the following school fiscal year.</para><para>Any class of school district may execute and deliver in evidence thereof their promissory notes which they are hereby authorized and empowered to make and negotiate, bearing a rate of interest set by the school board and maturing not more than two school fiscal years from the date thereof. Such notes, before they are negotiated, shall be presented to the treasurer of the school district and registered by him or her and shall be payable out of the funds collected by such school district in the order of their registry after the payment of prior registered warrants but prior to the payment of any warrant subsequently registered, except that if both warrants and notes are registered, the total of such registered notes and warrants shall not exceed one hundred percent of the unexpended balance of the total anticipated receipts of the general fund, special building fund, bond fund, or qualified capital purpose undertaking fund of such district for the current school fiscal year and the following school fiscal year. For the purpose of making such calculation, such total anticipated receipts shall not include any anticipated receipts against which the school district has borrowed and issued notes pursuant to this section in either the current or the immediately preceding school fiscal year.</para><para>(2) In addition to the authority granted by subsection (1) of this section, such school districts may accept interest-free or low-interest loans from the state or federal government and may execute and deliver in evidence thereof their promissory notes maturing not more than twenty years from the date of execution.</para><para>(3) In addition to the authority granted by subsections (1) and (2) of this section, any class of school district may enter into loan agreements for the purpose of borrowing money from financial institutions, including banks, in amounts not in excess of seventy percent of the unexpended balance of their current existing levy. As evidence of such borrowing, a school district may execute and deliver one or more written loan agreements but shall not be required to execute and deliver separate promissory notes for each borrowing under such agreements. Money borrowed pursuant to such agreements shall bear interest at such rate or rates and shall become due and be repaid as provided in such agreements. Any such agreement shall provide for repayment in full at least once each school fiscal year and shall be for a term not exceeding one school fiscal year. Any such agreement shall be registered upon books kept by the treasurer of the school district, and money borrowed pursuant to such agreement shall be paid out of funds collected upon the current existing levy prior to the payment of any warrant or note registered subsequent to any such loan agreement. If a school district has any such loan agreement or agreements outstanding and has warrants or notes registered, as described in subsection (1) of this section, the total amount (a) of borrowings pursuant to such loan agreement or agreements and (b) of registered notes and warrants shall not exceed one hundred percent of the unexpended balance of the current existing levy.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to exempt a school district from the terms and conditions contained in sections 10-701 to 10-716.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1931, c. 143, &#167; 1, p. 391; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 176, &#167; 7, p. 699; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 168, &#167; 1, p. 666; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-2523; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 204, &#167; 2, p. 679; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2531; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 207, p. 759; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 539, &#167; 1, p. 1779; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 719, &#167; 2, p. 2747; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 120, p. 347; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 596, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 441, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 587, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 79-520; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 382, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1384; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 716; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 710, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>