
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1021"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1021</statuteno><catchline>Education Future Fund; created; use; priority; investment; fund transfers.</catchline><para>(1) The Education Future Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the department and shall consist of money transferred to the fund by the Legislature. Transfers may be made from the Education Future Fund to the Computer Science and Technology Education Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Education Future Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) The fund shall be used only for the following purposes, in order of priority:</para><para>(a) To fully fund equalization aid under the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act;</para><para>(b) To fund reimbursements related to special education under section 79-1142;</para><para>(c) To fund foundation aid under the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act;</para><para>(d) To increase funding for school districts in a way that results in direct property tax relief, which means a dollar-for-dollar replacement of property taxes by a state funding source;</para><para>(e) To provide funding for a grant program created by the Legislature to address teacher turnover rates and keep existing teachers in classrooms;</para><para>(f) To provide funding to increase career and technical educational classroom opportunities for students, including, but not limited to, computer science education. Such funding must provide students with the academic and technical skills, knowledge, and training necessary to succeed in future careers;</para><para>(g) To provide funding for a grant program created by the Legislature to provide students the opportunity to have a mentor who will continuously engage with the student directly to aid in the student's professional growth and give ongoing support and encouragement to the student;</para><para>(h) To provide funding for extraordinary increases in special education expenditures to allow school districts with large, unexpected special education expenditures to more easily meet the needs of all students;</para><para>(i) To provide funding to help recruit teachers throughout the state by utilizing apprenticeships through a teacher apprenticeship program and an alternative certification process;</para><para>(j) To provide funding to develop and implement a professional learning system to help provide sustained professional learning and training regarding evidence-based reading instruction and for a grant program relating to dyslexia research; and</para><para>(k) To provide funding for a pilot project administered by the State Department of Education to provide menstrual products to school districts.</para><para>(3)(a) The State Treasurer shall transfer one billion dollars from the General Fund to the Education Future Fund in fiscal year 2023-24, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(b) The State Treasurer shall transfer two hundred fifty million dollars from the General Fund to the Education Future Fund in fiscal year 2024-25, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(c) It is the intent of the Legislature that two hundred fifty million dollars be transferred from the General Fund to the Education Future Fund in fiscal year 2025-26 and each fiscal year thereafter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1059, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 840, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-3812; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 667; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1050, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1284, &#167; 12. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>