<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id610"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1089.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1089.01</statuteno><catchline>Database of financial information; Department of Administrative Services; school districts; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Administrative Services shall develop, maintain, and make available for public inspection on its website a database of financial information from all school districts in the state. The information required shall include, but not be limited to, revenue sources, expenditures, and a balance sheet that contains all assets and liabilities for each school district from the most recent audit reports filed with the Commissioner of Education pursuant to section 79-1089. The budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services shall designate an implementation date for such database which date is on or before January 1, 2026.</para><para>(2)(a) School districts shall provide to the Department of Administrative Services such information from the school district's most recent audit report filed with the Commissioner of Education pursuant to section 79-1089 as is necessary to develop and maintain the database. School districts shall provide updated information to the department on an annual basis, and the department shall update the database no later than thirty days after receiving any such information.</para><para>(b) School districts shall provide historical financial information beginning with calendar year 2005 to the department. Such information shall be collected and added to the database if available as soon as practicable.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section requires the disclosure of information which is considered confidential under state or federal law or is not a public record under section 84-712.05.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB306, &#167; 11. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>