<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id122" statutenumber="79-1005.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1005.01</statuteno><catchline id="id125">Tax Commissioner; certify data; department; calculate allocation percentage and local system's allocated income tax funds.</catchline><para>(1) Not later than November 15 of each year, the Tax Commissioner shall certify to the department for the preceding tax year the income tax liability of resident individuals for each local system.</para><para>(2) For school fiscal years prior to 2017-18, one hundred two million two hundred eighty-nine thousand eight hundred seventeen dollars which is equal to the amount appropriated to the School District Income Tax Fund for distribution in school fiscal year 1992-93 shall be disbursed as option payments as determined under section 79-1009 and as allocated income tax funds as determined in this section and sections 79-1008.01, 79-1015.01, 79-1017.01, and 79-1018.01. For school fiscal years prior to school fiscal year 2017-18, funds not distributed as allocated income tax funds due to minimum levy adjustments shall not increase the amount available to local systems for distribution as allocated income tax funds.</para><para>(3) Using the data certified by the Tax Commissioner pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the department shall calculate the allocation percentage and each local system's allocated income tax funds. The allocation percentage shall be the amount stated in subsection (2) of this section minus the total amount paid for option students pursuant to section 79-1009, with the difference divided by the aggregate statewide income tax liability of all resident individuals certified pursuant to subsection (1) of this section. Each local system's allocated income tax funds shall be calculated by multiplying the allocation percentage times the local system's income tax liability certified pursuant to subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(4) For school fiscal year 2017-18 and each school fiscal year thereafter, each local system’s allocated income tax funds shall be calculated by multiplying the local system’s income tax liability certified pursuant to subsection (1) of this section by two and twenty-three hundredths percent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 149, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 898, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1093, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB5, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB235, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB959, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1066, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB675, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>