<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id418">
<sectno id="id419">Sec. 35.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id420" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1084"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id422">79-1084</statuteno><catchline id="id423">Class III school
district; school board; budget; tax; levy; publication of expenditures; violation;
penalty; duty of county board.</catchline><para>The school board
of a Class III school district shall annually, on or before September 20,
report in writing to the county board and the learning community coordinating
council if the school district is a member of a learning community the entire
revenue raised by taxation and all other sources and received by the school
board for the previous school fiscal year and a budget for the ensuing school
fiscal year broken
down generally as follows: (1) The amount of funds required for the support
of the schools during the ensuing school fiscal year; (2) the amount of funds
required for the purchase of school sites;
(3) the amount of funds required for the erection of school buildings; (4)
the amount of funds required for the payment of interest upon all bonds issued
for school purposes; and (5) the amount of funds required for the creation
of a sinking fund for the payment of such indebtedness. The secretary shall
publish, within ten days after the filing of such budget, a copy of the fund
summary pages of the budget one time at the legal rate prescribed for the
publication of legal notices in a legal newspaper published in and of general
circulation in such city or village or, if none is published in such city
or village, in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the city or village.
The secretary of the school board failing or neglecting to comply with this
section shall be deemed guilty of a Class V misdemeanor and, in the discretion
of the court, the judgment of conviction may provide for the removal from
office of such secretary for such failure or neglect. For Class III school
districts that are not members of a learning community, the county board shall
levy and collect such taxes as are necessary to provide the amount of revenue
from property taxes as indicated by all the data contained in the budget and
the certificate prescribed by this section, at the time and in the manner
provided in section 77-1601.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision XIV, &#167; 23, p. 385; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 80, &#167; 1, p. 329; </para><para>Laws 1893, c. 31, &#167; 2, p. 358; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6670; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6604; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2522; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2527; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 292, &#167; 1, p. 904; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 243, p. 771; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 404, &#167; 1, p. 1366; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1070, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1193, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 32; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-810; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 730; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 710, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 35.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For legal rate for publications,</emphasis> see section 33-141.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Act creating Court of Industrial Relations is not amendatory of this section. Orleans Education Assn. v. School Dist. of Orleans, 193 Neb. 675, 229 N.W.2d 172 (1975).</para><para>Class III school district did not have authority to enter into a lease-purchase agreement of a school building. Haschke v. School Dist. of Humphrey, 184 Neb. 298, 167 N.W.2d 79 (1969).</para><para>Power of a Class III school district to raise money for general school purposes is set forth in this section. State ex rel. School Dist. of City of Grand Island v. Board of Equalization, 166 Neb. 785, 90 N.W.2d 421 (1958).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>