<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1236"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1236</statuteno><catchline>Tenure; certificated employee; contract amendment, termination, or nonrenewal; procedure; confidentiality.</catchline><para>(1) Any certificated employee whose contract of employment may be amended, terminated, or not renewed for the following school year shall be notified in writing on or before April 15 of each year of such possible action on the contract. If the certificated employee wishes a hearing, a written request shall be sent to the secretary of the board or the administrator of the educational service unit within seven calendar days after receipt of the written notice. If a hearing on such amendment, termination, or nonrenewal is not requested within the time provided in this section, the board shall make a final determination. With regard to all hearings under sections 79-1234 to 79-1239, the certificated employee shall be advised in writing at least five days prior to the hearing of the date, time, and place of the hearing. All such hearings shall be held within thirty days after the date of the request for the hearing, except when the parties or their representatives, by a mutual agreement confirmed in writing, extend the time for hearings or final determinations by the board under such sections. Unless continued by written agreement between the parties or their representatives, final action by the board shall be taken on or before May 15 of each year.</para><para>(2) Prior to the hearing or action on the matter, if requested by the certificated employee, the notice of possible amendment, termination, or nonrenewal and the supporting reasons shall be considered a confidential employment matter as provided in sections 79-539, 79-8,109, and 84-1410 and shall not be released to the public or news media.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 997, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2218; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 953. </para></source></law></legaldoc>