<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id33"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id35"  statutenumber="79-1104.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id37">79-1104.04</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Board of trustees; members; terms; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The board of trustees shall include the following six members:</para><para>(a) The Commissioner of Education or his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee; and</para><para>(c) The following persons appointed by the Governor, in his or her discretion:</para><para>(i) Two persons nominated by the endowment provider;</para><para>(ii) An early childhood professional representing an urban at-risk area appointed pursuant to subsection (5) of this section; and</para><para>(iii) An early childhood professional representing a rural at-risk county appointed pursuant to subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(2) The terms of office for members initially appointed under subsection (1) of this section shall be three years. Upon completion of the initial terms of such members, the Governor shall appoint the two members under subdivision (1)(c)(i) of this section for terms of one and two years, the member under subdivision (1)(c)(ii) of this section for a term of three years, and the member under subdivision (1)(c)(iii) of this section for a term of two years. Succeeding appointees shall be appointed for terms of three years. An appointee to a vacancy occurring from an unexpired term shall serve out the term of his or her predecessor. Members whose terms have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have been appointed and qualified.</para><para>(3) The board of trustees shall by majority vote annually elect a chairperson from among the members of the board of trustees.</para><para>(4) The members of the board of trustees shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred while engaged in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(5) The Governor shall, in his or her discretion, appoint one member to the board of trustees who resides or works in an at-risk urban area consisting of not less than ten contiguous census tracts, as determined by the United States Bureau of the Census for the 2000 United States Census, within a city of the metropolitan class, which each contain a percentage of families below the poverty line of greater than twenty percent, as reported by the United States Bureau of the Census for the 2000 United States Census.</para><para>(6) The Governor shall, in his or her discretion, appoint one member to the board of trustees who resides or works in a county which does not contain a city of the metropolitan class or a city of the primary class and which contains a percentage of families below the poverty line of greater than eight and one-half percent, as reported by the United States Bureau of the Census for the 2000 United States Census.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1256, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 713; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1153, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
