
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id92">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id94"  statutenumber="79-1248"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id96">79-1248</statuteno><catchline id="id97">Educational Service
Unit Coordinating Council; powers and duties.</catchline><para>The
powers and duties of the Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council include,
but are not limited to:</para>
<para>(1) Providing public access to lists of qualified distance
education courses;</para>
<para>(2) Collecting and providing school schedules for participating
educational entities;</para>
<para>(3) Facilitation of scheduling for qualified distance education
courses;</para>
<para>(4) Brokering of qualified distance education courses to
be purchased by educational entities;</para>
<para>(5) Assessment of distance education needs and evaluation
of distance education services;</para>
<para>(6) Compliance with technical standards as set forth by the
Nebraska Information Technology Commission and academic standards as set forth
by the State Department of Education related to distance education;</para>
<para>(7) Establishment of a system for scheduling courses brokered by the council and
for choosing receiving educational entities when the demand for a course exceeds
the capacity as determined by either the technology available or the course
provider;</para>
<para>(8) Administration
of learning management systems, either through the staff of the council
or by delegation to an appropriate educational entity, with the funding for such systems provided
by participating educational entities; and</para>
<para>(9) Coordination with educational
service units and postsecondary educational institutions to provide assistance
for instructional design for both two-way interactive video distance education
courses and the offering of graduate credit courses in distance education.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 20; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 79-1334; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>