<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools"  statutenumber="79-1016"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1016</statuteno><catchline>Adjusted valuation; how established; objections; filing; appeal; notice; correction due to clerical error; injunction prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) On or before August 20, the county assessor shall certify to the Property Tax Administrator the total taxable value by school district in the county for the current assessment year on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. The county assessor may amend the filing for changes made to the taxable valuation of the school district in the county if corrections or errors on the original certification are discovered. Amendments shall be certified to the Property Tax Administrator on or before August 31.</para><para>(2) On or before October 10, the Property Tax Administrator shall compute and certify to the State Department of Education the adjusted valuation for the current assessment year for each class of property in each school district and each local system. The adjusted valuation of property for each school district and each local system, for purposes of determining state aid pursuant to the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act, shall reflect as nearly as possible state aid value as defined in subsection (3) of this section. The Property Tax Administrator shall notify each school district and each local system of its adjusted valuation for the current assessment year by class of property on or before October 10. Establishment of the adjusted valuation shall be based on the taxable value certified by the county assessor for each school district in the county adjusted by the determination of the level of value for each school district from an analysis of the comprehensive assessment ratio study or other studies developed by the Property Tax Administrator, in compliance with professionally accepted mass appraisal techniques, as required by section 77-1327. The Tax Commissioner shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations setting forth standards for the determination of level of value for state aid purposes.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, state aid value means:</para><para>(a) For real property other than agricultural and horticultural land, ninety-six percent of actual value;</para><para>(b) For agricultural and horticultural land, seventy-two percent of actual value as provided in sections 77-1359 to 77-1363. For agricultural and horticultural land that receives special valuation pursuant to section 77-1344, seventy-two percent of special valuation as defined in section 77-1343; and</para><para>(c) For personal property, the net book value as defined in section 77-120.</para><para>(4) On or before November 10, any local system may file with the Tax Commissioner written objections to the adjusted valuations prepared by the Property Tax Administrator, stating the reasons why such adjusted valuations are not the valuations required by subsection (3) of this section. The Tax Commissioner shall fix a time for a hearing. Either party shall be permitted to introduce any evidence in reference thereto. On or before January 1, the Tax Commissioner shall enter a written order modifying or declining to modify, in whole or in part, the adjusted valuations and shall certify the order to the State Department of Education. Modification by the Tax Commissioner shall be based upon the evidence introduced at hearing and shall not be limited to the modification requested in the written objections or at hearing. A copy of the written order shall be mailed to the local system within seven days after the date of the order. The written order of the Tax Commissioner may be appealed within thirty days after the date of the order to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission in accordance with section 77-5013.</para><para>(5) On or before November 10, any local system or county official may file with the Tax Commissioner a written request for a nonappealable correction of the adjusted valuation due to clerical error as defined in section 77-128 or, for agricultural and horticultural land, assessed value changes by reason of land qualified or disqualified for special use valuation pursuant to sections 77-1343 to 77-1347.01. On or before the following January 1, the Tax Commissioner shall approve or deny the request and, if approved, certify the corrected adjusted valuations resulting from such action to the State Department of Education.</para><para>(6) On or before May 31 of the year following the certification of adjusted valuation pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, any local system or county official may file with the Tax Commissioner a written request for a nonappealable correction of the adjusted valuation due to changes to the tax list that change the assessed value of taxable property. Upon the filing of the written request, the Tax Commissioner shall require the county assessor to recertify the taxable valuation by school district in the county on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. The recertified valuation shall be the valuation that was certified on the tax list, pursuant to section 77-1613, increased or decreased by changes to the tax list that change the assessed value of taxable property in the school district in the county in the prior assessment year. On or before the following July 31, the Tax Commissioner shall approve or deny the request and, if approved, certify the corrected adjusted valuations resulting from such action to the State Department of Education.</para><para>(7) No injunction shall be granted restraining the distribution of state aid based upon the adjusted valuations pursuant to this section.</para><para>(8) A school district whose state aid is to be calculated pursuant to subsection (5) of this section and whose state aid payment is postponed as a result of failure to calculate state aid pursuant to such subsection may apply to the state board for lump-sum payment of such postponed state aid. Such application may be for any amount up to one hundred percent of the postponed state aid. The state board may grant the entire amount applied for or any portion of such amount. The state board shall notify the Director of Administrative Services of the amount of funds to be paid in a lump sum and the reduced amount of the monthly payments. The Director of Administrative Services shall, at the time of the next state aid payment made pursuant to section 79-1022, draw a warrant for the lump-sum amount from appropriated funds and forward such warrant to the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1059, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 829, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 198; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1290, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 185; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-3809; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 662; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 934, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1050, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 271, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 342, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 595, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 713, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 994, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 126, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 263, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 968, &#167; 16; </para><para>Referendum 2006, No. 422; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB166, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB217, &#167; 31. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Tax Equalization and Review Commission,</emphasis> see section 77-5003.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The plain language of this section (formerly section 79-3809) requires the Nebraska Department of Revenue to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to regulate the valuation process. Loup City Pub. Sch. v. Nebraska Dept. of Rev., 252 Neb. 387, 562 N.W.2d 551 (1997).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>