<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id36">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id38" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-10,110.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,110.01</statuteno><catchline>Health and safety modifications,
qualified zone academy, or American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009
purpose bonds; refunding bonds; authorized; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) If a school board has issued or shall
issue bonds pursuant to section 79-10,110 and such bonds or any part of such
bonds are unpaid, are a legal liability against the school district governed
by such school board, and are bearing interest, the school board may issue
refunding bonds with which to call and redeem all or any part of such outstanding
bonds at or before the date of maturity or the redemption date of such bonds.
Such school board may include various series and issues of the outstanding
bonds in a single issue of refunding bonds and may issue refunding bonds to
pay any redemption premium and interest to accrue and become payable on the
outstanding bonds being refunded. The refunding bonds may be issued and delivered
at any time prior to the date of maturity or the redemption date of the bonds
to be refunded that the school board determines to be in the best interests
of the school district. The proceeds derived from the sale of the refunding
bonds issued pursuant to this section may be invested in obligations of or
guaranteed by the United States Government pending the time the proceeds are
required for the purposes for which such refunding bonds were issued. To further
secure the refunding bonds, the school board may enter into a contract with
any bank or trust company within or without the state with respect to the
safekeeping and application of the proceeds of the refunding bonds and the
safekeeping and application of the earnings on the investment. All bonds issued
under this section shall be redeemable at such times and under such conditions
as the school board shall determine at the time of issuance.</para>
<para>(2) Any outstanding
bonds or other evidences of indebtedness issued by a school board for which
sufficient funds or obligations of or guaranteed by the United States Government
have been pledged and set aside in safekeeping to be applied for the complete
payment of such bonds or other evidences of indebtedness at maturity or upon
redemption prior to maturity, interest thereon, and redemption premium, if
any, shall not be considered as outstanding and unpaid.</para>
<para>(3) Each refunding
bond issued under this section shall state on the bond (a) the object of its
issue, (b) this section or the sections of the law under which such issue
was made, including a statement that the issue is made in pursuance of such
section or sections, and (c) the date and principal amount of the bond or
bonds for which the refunding bonds are being issued.</para><para>(4) The refunding bonds
shall be paid, and the levy made and the tax collected for their payment in
the same manner and under the same authorization for levy of taxes as applied
for the bonds being refunded, in accordance with section 79-10,110.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB633, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>