<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id88">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id90" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1007.07"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1007.07</statuteno><catchline id="id93">Financial
reports relating to poverty allowance; department; duties; report; appeal
of department decisions.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The annual financial
report required pursuant to section 79-528 shall include:</para>
<para>(i) The amount of the poverty allowance used in the certification
of state aid pursuant to section 79-1022 for such school fiscal year;</para>
<para>(ii) The amount of federal funds received based on poverty
as defined by the federal program providing the funds;</para>
<para>(iii) The expenditures and sources of funding for each program
related to poverty with a narrative description of the program, the method
used to allocate money to the program and within the program, and the program's
relationship to the poverty plan submitted pursuant to section 79-1013 for
such school fiscal year;</para>
<para>(iv) The expenditures and sources of funding for support costs
directly attributable to implementing the district's poverty plan; and</para>
<para>(v) An explanation of how any required elements of the poverty
plan for such school fiscal year were met.</para>
<para>(b) The department shall set up accounting codes for the
receipts and expenditures required to be reported on the annual financial
report pursuant to this subsection.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall determine the poverty allowance
expenditures using the reported expenditures on the annual financial report
for the most recently available complete data year that would include in the
poverty allowance expenditures only those expenditures that are not included in other allowances, that
were used to specifically address issues related to the education of students
living in poverty or to the implementation of the poverty plan, that do not
replace expenditures that would have occurred if the students involved in
the program did not live in poverty, and that are paid for with
noncategorical funds generated by state or local taxes or funds distributed
through the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act pursuant
to the federal American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 or the federal
Education Jobs Fund created pursuant to Public Law 111-226. The department
shall establish a procedure to allow school districts to receive preapproval
for categories of expenditures that could be included in poverty allowance
expenditures.</para>
<para>(3) If the poverty allowance expenditures do not equal 117.65
percent or more of the poverty allowance for the most recently available complete
data year, the department shall calculate a poverty allowance correction.
The poverty allowance correction shall equal the poverty allowance minus eighty-five
percent of the poverty allowance expenditures. If the poverty allowance expenditures
do not equal fifty percent or more of the allowance for such school fiscal
year, the school district shall also be disqualified from receiving a poverty
allowance for the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated.</para>
<para>(4) If the department determines that the school district
did not meet the required elements of the poverty plan for the most recently
available complete data year, the department shall calculate a poverty allowance
correction equal to fifty percent of the poverty allowance for such school
fiscal year and the school district shall also be disqualified from receiving
a poverty allowance for the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated.
Any poverty allowance correction calculated pursuant to this subsection shall
be added to any poverty allowance correction calculated pursuant to subsection
(3) of this section to arrive at the total poverty allowance correction.</para>
<para>(5) The department may request additional information from
any school district to assist with calculations and determinations pursuant
to this section. If the school district does not provide information upon
the request of the department pursuant to this section, the school district
shall be disqualified from receiving a poverty allowance for the school fiscal
year for which aid is being calculated.</para>
<para>(6) The department shall provide electronically an annual
report to the Legislature containing a general description of the expenditures
and funding sources for programs related to poverty statewide and specific
descriptions of the expenditures and funding sources for programs related
to poverty for each school district.</para>
<para>(7) The state board shall establish a procedure for appeal
of decisions of the department to the state board for a final determination.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB18, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 158; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB407, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>May 22, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>