<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id425">
<sectno id="id426">Sec. 36.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id427" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1086"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id429">79-1086</statuteno><catchline id="id430">Class V school
district; board of education; budget; how prepared; certification of levy;
levy of taxes.</catchline><para>(1) The board of education of a
Class V school district that is not a member of a learning community shall
annually during the month of July estimate the amount of resources likely
to be received for school purposes, including the amounts available from fines,
licenses, and other sources. Before the county board of equalization makes
its levy each year, the board of education shall report to the county clerk
the rate of tax deemed necessary to be levied upon the taxable value of all
the taxable property of the district subject to taxation during the fiscal
year next ensuing for (a) the support of the schools, (b) the purchase of
school sites, (c) the erection, alteration, equipping, and furnishing of school
buildings and additions to school buildings, (d) the payment of interest upon
all bonds issued for school purposes, and (e) the creation of a sinking fund
for the payment of such indebtedness. The county board of equalization shall
levy the rate of tax so reported and demanded by the board of education and
collect the tax in the same manner as other taxes are levied and collected.</para>
<para>(2) The school board of a Class V school district that is
a member of a learning community shall annually, on or before September 20,
report in writing to the county board and the learning community coordinating
council the entire revenue raised by taxation and all other sources and received
by the school board for the previous school fiscal year and a budget for the
ensuing school fiscal year broken down generally as follows: (a) The
amount of funds required for the support of the schools during the ensuing
school fiscal year; (b) the amount of funds required for the purchase of
school sites; (c) the amount of funds required for the erection of school
buildings; (d) the amount of funds required for the payment of interest upon
all bonds issued for school purposes; and (e) the amount of funds required
for the creation of a sinking fund for the payment of such indebtedness. The
secretary shall publish, within ten days after the filing of such budget,
a copy of the fund summary pages of the budget one time at the legal rate
prescribed for the publication of legal notices in a legal newspaper published
in and of general circulation in such city or village or, if none is published
in such city or village, in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the
city or village. The secretary of the school board failing or neglecting to
comply with this section shall be deemed guilty of a Class V misdemeanor and,
in the discretion of the court, the judgment of conviction may provide for
the removal from office of such secretary for such failure or neglect.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1891, c. 45, &#167; 21, p. 325; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 68, &#167; 1, p. 299; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7027; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6658; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2721; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 146, &#167; 1, p. 400; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 183, &#167; 1, p. 722; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-2721; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2722; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 214, &#167; 1, p. 628; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 298, &#167; 1, p. 913; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 271, &#167; 4, p. 889; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 264, p. 780; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 320, &#167; 1, p. 989; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 757, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 240; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 198; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 169; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1007; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 732; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 36.</para></source><annotation><para>The county board of equalization makes the levy of taxes for a school district. C. R. T. Corp. v. Board of Equalization, 172 Neb. 540, 110 N.W.2d 194 (1961).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>