<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id66">
<sectno id="id67">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id68" statutenumber="79-1036"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id70">79-1036</statuteno><catchline id="id71">School funds;
public lands; amount in lieu of tax; reappraisement; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) In making the apportionment under section 79-1035, the Commissioner
of Education shall distribute from the school fund for school purposes, to
any and all learning communities
and school districts which
are not members of a learning community, in which there are situated
school lands which have not been sold and transferred by deed or saline lands
owned by the state, which lands are being used for a public purpose, an amount
in lieu of tax money that would be raised by
school district levies and learning community common levies for which the
proceeds are distributed to member school districts pursuant to sections 79-1073
and 79-1073.01 if such lands were taxable, to be ascertained in
accordance with subsection (2) of this section, except that:</para>
<para>(a) For Class I districts or portions thereof which are affiliated
and in which there are situated school or saline lands, 38.6207 percent of
the in lieu of land tax money calculated pursuant to subsection (2) of this
section, based on the affiliated school system tax levy computed pursuant
to section 79-1077, shall be distributed to the affiliated high school district
and the remainder shall be distributed to the Class I district;</para>
<para>(b) For Class I districts or portions thereof which are part
of a Class VI district which offers instruction in grades nine through twelve
and in which there are situated school or saline lands, 38.6207 percent of
the in lieu of land tax money calculated pursuant to subsection (2) of this
section, based on the Class VI school system levy computed pursuant to section
79-1078, shall be distributed to the Class VI district and the remainder shall
be distributed to the Class I district;</para>
<para>(c) For Class I districts or portions thereof which are part
of a Class VI district which offers instruction in grades seven through twelve
and in which there are situated school or saline lands, 55.1724 percent of
the in lieu of land tax money calculated pursuant to subsection (2) of this
section, based on the Class VI school system levy computed pursuant to section
79-1078, shall be distributed to the Class VI district and the remainder shall
be distributed to the Class I district; and</para>
<para>(d) For Class I districts or portions thereof which are part
of a Class VI district which offers instruction in grades six through twelve
and in which there are situated school or saline lands, 62.0690 percent of
the in lieu of land tax money calculated pursuant to subsection (2) of this
section, based on the Class VI school system levy computed pursuant to section
79-1078, shall be distributed to the Class VI district and the remainder shall
be distributed to the Class I district.</para>
<para>(2) The county assessor shall certify to the Commissioner
of Education the tax levies of
each school district and learning
community in which school land or saline land is located and the
last appraised value of such school land, which value shall be the same percentage
of the appraised value as the percentage of the assessed value is of market
value in subsection (2) of section 77-201 for the purpose of applying the
applicable tax levies for each district and learning community in
determining the distribution to the districts of such amounts. The school
board of any school district and
the learning community coordinating council of any learning community in
which there is located any leased or undeeded school land or saline land subject
to this section may appeal to the Board of Educational Lands and Funds for
a reappraisement of such school land if such school board or learning community coordinating council deems
the land not appraised in proportion to the value of adjoining land of the
same or similar value. The Board of Educational Lands and Funds shall proceed
to investigate the facts involved in such appeal and, if the contention of
the school board or learning
community coordinating council is correct, make the proper reappraisement.
The value calculation in this subsection shall be used by the Commissioner
of Education for making distributions in each school fiscal year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision VIII, &#167; 9, p. 364; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6906; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 82, &#167; 1, p. 296; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6482; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 187, &#167; 1, p. 651; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-1609; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 144, &#167; 2, p. 557; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-1609; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 200, &#167; 1, p. 670; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-1612; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 282, &#167; 1, p. 890; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 378, p. 818; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 359, &#167; 2, p. 1218; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 246; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 572, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 39, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1090, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 839, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 858, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1303; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 682; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 394, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>