<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1065.02" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1065.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">State aid payments; adjustments; application; calculation.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) State aid payments shall be adjusted when property within the boundaries of a school district is transferred to another school district due to a change in school district boundaries in response to annexation of the transferred property by a city or village.</para><para id="id00" /><para id="id00" /><para id="id00" /><para id="id00">(2) To qualify for additional state aid pursuant to this section, the school district from which property is being transferred shall apply on a form prescribed by the State Department of Education on or before August 20 preceding the first school fiscal year for which the property will not be available for taxation for the school district's general fund levy. On or before such deadline, the applicant school district shall send copies of the application to the high school districts of the local systems receiving valuation in the transfer. For purposes of this section, property is deemed transferred from the school district whether the property was within the boundaries of the school district or the property was affiliated with the school district.</para><para id="id00">(3) Upon receipt of the application, the department, with the assistance of the Property Tax Administrator, shall calculate the amount of additional state aid, if any, that the local system, as defined in section 79-1003, for the applicant school district would have received for such school fiscal year if the adjusted valuation for the transferred property had not been included in the adjusted valuation of such local system for the calculation of state aid for such school fiscal year. On or before September 20 of such school fiscal year, the department shall certify to the applicant school district the amount of additional state aid, if any, the district will receive. Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, if such applicant school district receives a lump-sum payment pursuant to subsection (2) of section 79-1022, such lump-sum payment shall be increased by the amount of additional state aid. Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, if such applicant school district does not receive a lump-sum payment pursuant to such subsection, state aid payments shall be increased by one-tenth of the amount of additional state aid for each of the ten state aid payments for such school fiscal year. If a portion of the total reduction calculated pursuant to subsection (4) of this section for local systems receiving valuation in the transfer of property that is the subject of the application is delayed until future years, the additional state aid to be paid in the school fiscal year described in subsection (2) of this section shall be reduced by the amount of the total reduction that is delayed until future years. The amount of the reduction shall be paid as additional aid in the next school fiscal year.</para><para id="id00">(4) The state aid payments shall be reduced for the high school district of each receiving local system. An amount equal to the additional state aid calculated pursuant to subsection (3) of this section for the local system of an applicant school district shall be attributed to the local systems receiving valuation in such transfer based upon the ratio of the adjusted valuation received by each local system divided by the total adjusted valuation transferred from the applicant school district. If such high school district receives a lump-sum payment pursuant to subsection (2) of section 79-1022, such lump-sum payment shall be reduced by the amount attributed to the receiving local system. If the high school district of a receiving local system does not receive a lump-sum payment pursuant to such subsection, state aid payments shall be reduced by one-tenth of the amount attributed to such receiving local system for each of the ten state aid payments for such school fiscal year. If the total reduction is greater than the total state aid payments for such school fiscal year, the remainder shall be subtracted from state aid payments in future school fiscal years until the total reduction has been subtracted from state aid payments. On or before September 20 of such school fiscal year, the department shall certify to the high school district of the receiving local system the amount of the reduction in state aid.</para><para id="id00">(5) For purposes of the final calculation of state aid pursuant to section 79-1065, the adjusted valuation of the property that was transferred shall also be transferred for purposes of adjusted valuation for the final calculation of state aid. For determining adjustments in state aid pursuant to section 79-1065, the final calculation of state aid shall be compared to the state aid certified for such school fiscal year combined with any adjustments in state aid payments and transfers from other districts pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 198, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 67. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>