<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id187">
<sectno id="id188" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id189" statutenumber="79-1013"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id191">79-1013</statuteno><catchline id="id192">Poverty plan;
submission required; when; review; approval; elements required; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) On or before October 15 of each year, each school
district designating a maximum poverty allowance greater than zero dollars
shall submit a poverty plan for the next school fiscal year to the department
and to the learning community coordinating council of any learning community
of which the school district is a member. On or before the immediately following
December 1, (a) the department shall approve or disapprove such plan for school
districts that are not members of a learning community based on the inclusion
of the elements required pursuant to this section and (b) the learning community
coordinating council and, as to the applicable portions thereof, each achievement
subcouncil, shall approve or disapprove such plan for school districts that
are members of such learning community based on the inclusion of such elements.
On or before the immediately following December 5, each learning community
coordinating council shall certify to the department the approval or disapproval
of the poverty plan for each member school district.</para>
<para>(2) In order to be approved pursuant to this section, a poverty
plan shall include an explanation of how the school district will address
the following issues for such school fiscal year:</para>
<para>(a) Attendance, including absence followup and transportation
for students qualifying for free or reduced-price lunches who reside more
than one mile from the attendance center;</para>
<para>(b) Student mobility, including transportation to allow a
student to continue attendance at the same school if the student moves to
another attendance area within the same school district or within the same
learning community;</para>
<para>(c) Parental involvement at the school-building level with
a focus on the involvement of parents in poverty and from other diverse backgrounds;</para>
<para>(d) Parental involvement at the school-district level with
a focus on the involvement of parents in poverty and from other diverse backgrounds;</para>
<para>(e) Class size reduction or maintenance of small class sizes
in elementary grades;</para>
<para>(f) Scheduled teaching time on a weekly basis that will be
free from interruptions;</para>
<para>(g) Access to early childhood education programs for children
in poverty;</para>
<para>(h) Student access to social workers;</para>
<para>(i) Access to summer school, extended-school-day programs,
or extended-school-year programs;</para>
<para>(j) Mentoring for new and newly reassigned teachers;</para>
<para>(k) Professional development for teachers and administrators,
focused on addressing the educational needs of students in poverty and students
from other diverse backgrounds;</para>
<para>(l) Coordination with elementary learning centers if the
school district is a member of a learning community; and</para>
<para>(m) An evaluation to determine the effectiveness of the elements
of the poverty plan.</para>
<para>(3) The state board shall establish a procedure for appeal
of decisions of the department and of learning community coordinating councils
to the state board for a final determination.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167;  36; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167;  17.</para><operativedate>July 15, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>