<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id390">
<sectno id="id391">Sec. 32.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id392" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1007.22"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id394">79-1007.22</statuteno><catchline id="id395">New learning
community transportation adjustment; application; department; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) For state aid calculated for each of the second and third
full school fiscal years of a new learning community, each member school district
may apply to the department for a new learning community transportation adjustment,
on a form prescribed by the department, on or before October 15 of
the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school fiscal year for which
the new learning community transportation adjustment would be included in
the calculation of state aid. Such form shall require evidence supporting
estimates of increased transportation costs for the district due to the provisions
of subsection (2) of section 79-611. On or before the immediately following
December 1, the department shall approve the estimate of increased transportation
costs for use in the adjustment, approve a modified estimate of increased
transportation costs for use in the adjustment, or deny the application based
on the requirements of this section, the evidence submitted on the application,
and any other information provided by the department. The state board shall
establish procedures for appeal of decisions of the department to the state
board for final determination.</para>
<para>(2) The new learning community transportation adjustment
shall equal the approved estimate of increased transportation costs due to
the provisions of subsection (2) of section 79-611. School districts shall
submit evidence of the actual increase in transportation costs due to the
provisions of subsection (2) of section 79-611, and the department shall recalculate
the adjustment using such actual costs pursuant to section 79-1065.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167;  24; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB62, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 32.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>