<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1167"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1167</statuteno><catchline>Hearing officer; findings, decision, or order; judicial review.</catchline><para>(1) Any party to a hearing conducted under sections 79-1162 to 79-1166 aggrieved by the findings, conclusions, or final decision and order of the hearing officer is entitled to judicial review under this section. Any party of record also may seek enforcement of the final decision and order of the hearing officer pursuant to this section.</para><para>(2) Proceedings for judicial review shall be instituted by filing a petition in the district court of the county in which the main administrative offices of the school district are located within two years after service of the final decision and order on the party seeking such review. All parties of record shall be made parties to the proceedings. The court, in its discretion, may permit other interested parties to intervene.</para><para>(3) The filing of a petition for judicial review shall operate to stay the enforcement of the final decision and order of the hearing officer. While judicial proceedings are pending and unless the school district and the parent or guardian otherwise agree, the child with a disability shall remain in his or her current educational placement or if applying for initial admission to a public school such child shall, with the consent of the parent or guardian, be placed in the public school program until all such proceedings have been completed. If the decision of the hearing officer agrees with the parent or guardian of the child that a change in placement is appropriate, then that placement shall be treated as an agreement between the parties for purposes of this subsection.</para><para>(4) Within fifteen days after receiving notification that a petition for judicial review has been filed or if good cause is shown within such further time as the court may allow, the State Department of Education shall prepare and transmit to the court a certified transcript of the proceedings before the hearing officer.</para><para>(5) Judicial review shall be conducted by the court without a jury. The court shall receive the records of the administrative proceedings, hear additional evidence at the request of a party, base its decision on the preponderance of the evidence, and grant such relief as the court determines is appropriate.</para><para>(6) An aggrieved party may secure a review of any final judgment of the district court under this section by appeal to the Court of Appeals. Such appeal shall be taken in the manner provided by law for appeals in civil cases and shall be heard de novo on the record.</para><para>(7) Proceedings for enforcement of a hearing officer's final decision and order shall be instituted by filing a petition for appropriate relief in the district court of the county in which the main administrative offices of the school district are located within one year after the date of the hearing officer's final decision and order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 871, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 855, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 511, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 43-666; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 367, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 147; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 63; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3354; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 849; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc>