<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1007.20">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1007.20</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Student growth
adjustment; school district; application; department; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) School districts may apply to the department for a student
growth adjustment, on a form prescribed by the department, on or before October
15 of the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school fiscal year
for which aid is being calculated. Such form shall require an estimate of
the average daily membership for the school fiscal year for which aid is being
calculated, the estimated student growth calculated by subtracting the fall
membership of the current school fiscal year from the estimated average daily
membership for the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated, and
evidence supporting the estimates. On or before the immediately following
December 1, the department shall approve the estimated student growth, approve
a modified student growth, or deny the application based on the requirements
of this section, the evidence submitted on the application, and any other
information provided by the department. The state board shall establish procedures
for appeal of decisions of the department to the state board for final determination.</para>
<para>(2) The student growth adjustment for each approved district
shall equal the sum of the product of the school district's basic funding
per formula student multiplied by the difference of the approved student growth
minus the greater of twenty-five students or one percent of the fall membership
for the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school fiscal year for
which aid is being calculated plus the product of fifty percent of the school
district's basic funding per formula student multiplied by the greater of
twenty-five students or one percent of the fall membership for the school
fiscal year immediately preceding the school fiscal year for which aid is
being calculated.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall calculate
a student growth adjustment correction for each district that received a student
growth adjustment for aid distributed in the most recently available complete
data year. Such student growth correction shall equal the product of the difference
of the actual student growth for such school
fiscal year minus the estimated student growth for such school
fiscal year used to calculate the student growth adjustment for such school
fiscal year multiplied by the school district's basic funding per formula
student used in the final calculation of aid pursuant to section 79-1065 for
such school fiscal year, except that the absolute value of a negative correction
shall not exceed the original adjustment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB410, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB725, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>April 3, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>