<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id513">
<sectno id="id514">Sec. 45.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id515" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id517">79-1204</statuteno><catchline id="id518">Role and mission.</catchline>
<para>(1) The role and mission of the educational service units
is to serve as educational service providers in the state's system of elementary
and secondary education.</para>
<para>(2) Educational service units shall:</para>
<para>(a) Act primarily as service agencies in providing core services
and services identified and requested by member school districts;</para>
<para>(b) Provide for economy, efficiency, and cost-effectiveness
in the cooperative delivery of educational services;</para>
<para>(c) Provide educational services through leadership, research,
and development in elementary and secondary education;</para>
<para>(d) Act in a cooperative and supportive role with the State
Department of Education and school districts in development and implementation
of long-range plans, strategies, and goals for the enhancement of educational
opportunities in elementary and secondary education; and</para>
<para>(e) Serve, when appropriate and as funds become available,
as a repository, clearinghouse, and administrator of federal, state, and private
funds on behalf of school districts which choose to participate in special
programs, projects, or grants in order to enhance the quality of education
in Nebraska schools.</para>
<para>(3) Core services shall be provided by educational
service units to all member school districts. Core services shall be defined
by each educational service unit as follows:</para>
<para>(a) Core services shall be within the following service areas
in order of priority: (i) Staff development which shall include access to
staff development related to improving the achievement of students in poverty
and students with diverse backgrounds; (ii) technology, including distance
education services; and (iii) instructional materials services;</para>
<para>(b) Core services shall improve teaching and student learning
by focusing on enhancing school improvement efforts, meeting statewide requirements,
and achieving statewide goals in the state's system of elementary and secondary
education;</para>
<para>(c) Core services shall provide schools with access to services
that:</para>
<para>(i) The educational service unit and its member school districts
have identified as necessary services;</para>
<para>(ii) Are difficult, if not impossible, for most individual
school districts to effectively and efficiently provide with their own personnel
and financial resources;</para>
<para>(iii) Can be efficiently provided by each educational service
unit to its member school districts; and</para>
<para>(iv) Can be adequately funded to ensure that the service
is provided equitably to the state's public school districts;</para>
<para>(d) Core services shall be designed so that the effectiveness
and efficiency of the service can be evaluated on a statewide basis; and</para>
<para>(e) Core services shall be provided by the educational service
unit in a manner that minimizes the costs of administration or service delivery
to member school districts.</para>
<para>(4) Educational service units shall meet minimum accreditation
standards set by the State Board of Education that will:</para>
<para>(a) Provide for accountability to taxpayers;</para>
<para>(b) Assure that educational service units are assisting and
cooperating with school districts to provide for equitable and adequate educational
opportunities statewide; and</para>
<para>(c) Assure a level of quality in educational programs and
services provided to school districts by the educational service units.</para>
<para>(5) Educational service units may contract to provide services
to:</para>
<para>(a) Nonmember public school districts;</para>
<para>(b) Nonpublic school systems;</para>
<para>(c) Other educational service units; and</para>
<para>(d) Other political subdivisions, under the Interlocal Cooperation
Act and the Joint Public Agency Act.</para>
<para>(6) Educational service units shall not regulate school districts
unless specifically provided pursuant to another section of law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 688, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2201.02; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 921; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167;  45.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>