<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id194" statutenumber="79-1015.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1015.01</statuteno><catchline id="id197">Local system formula resources; local effort rate yield; determination.</catchline><para>(1) Local system formula resources shall include local effort rate yield which shall be computed as prescribed in this section.</para><para>(2) For each school fiscal year except school fiscal years 2017-18 and 2018-19: (a) For state aid certified pursuant to section 79-1022, the local effort rate shall be the maximum levy, for the school fiscal year for which aid is being certified, authorized pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of section 77-3442 less five cents; (b) for the final calculation of state aid pursuant to section 79-1065, the local effort rate shall be the rate which, when multiplied by the total adjusted valuation of all taxable property in local systems receiving equalization aid pursuant to the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act, will produce the amount needed to support the total formula need of such local systems when added to state aid appropriated by the Legislature and other actual receipts of local systems described in section 79-1018.01; and (c) the local effort rate yield for such school fiscal years shall be determined by multiplying each local system's total adjusted valuation by the local effort rate.</para><para>(3) For school fiscal years 2017-18 and 2018-19: (a) For state aid certified pursuant to section 79-1022, the local effort rate shall be the maximum levy, for the school fiscal year for which aid is being certified, authorized pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of section 77-3442 less two and ninety-seven hundredths cents; (b) for the final calculation of state aid pursuant to section 79-1065, the local effort rate shall be the rate which, when multiplied by the total adjusted valuation of all taxable property in local systems receiving equalization aid pursuant to the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act, will produce the amount needed to support the total formula need of such local systems when added to state aid appropriated by the Legislature and other actual receipts of local systems described in section 79-1018.01; and (c) the local effort rate yield for such school fiscal years shall be determined by multiplying each local system's total adjusted valuation by the local effort rate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 149, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB235, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB407, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB725, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB409, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>