<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id18"><sectno id="id19">Sec. 53.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id20" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1337"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id22">79-1337</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Distance education incentives; application; contents; calculation of incentives; denial of incentives; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) For fiscal years 2007-08 through 2015-16, the State Department of Education shall provide distance education incentives from the Education Innovation Fund to school districts and educational service units for qualified distance education courses coordinated through the Distance Education Council until July 1, 2008, and the Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council on and after July 1, 2008, as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) School districts and educational service units shall apply for incentives annually to the department on or before August 1 on a form specified by the department. The application shall:</para><para>(a) For school districts, specify (i) the qualified distance education courses which were received by students in the membership of the district in the then-current school fiscal year and which were not taught by a teacher employed by the school district and (ii) for each such course (A) the number of students in the membership of the district who received the course, (B) the educational entity employing the teacher, and (C) whether the course was a two-way interactive video distance education course; and</para><para>(b) For school districts and educational service units, specify (i) the qualified distance education courses which were received by students in the membership of another educational entity in the then-current school fiscal year and which were taught by a teacher employed by the school district or educational service unit, (ii) for each such course for school districts, the number of students in the membership of the district who received the course, and (iii) for each such course (A) the other educational entities in which students received the course and how many students received the course at such educational entities, (B) any school district that is sparse or very sparse as such terms are defined in section 79-1003 that had at least one student in the membership who received the course, and (C) whether the course was a two-way interactive video distance education course.</para><para>(3) On or before September 1 of each year, the department shall certify the incentives for each school district and educational service unit which shall be paid on or before October 1 of such year. The incentives for each district shall be calculated as follows:</para><para>(a) Each district shall receive distance education units for each qualified distance education course as follows:</para><para>(i) One distance education unit for each qualified distance education course received as reported pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section if the course was a two-way interactive video distance education course;</para><para>(ii) One distance education unit for each qualified distance education course sent as reported pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section if the course was not received by at least one student who was in the membership of another school district which was sparse or very sparse;</para><para>(iii) One distance education unit for each qualified distance education course sent as reported pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section if the course was received by at least one student who was in the membership of another school district which was sparse or very sparse, but the course was not a two-way interactive video distance education course; and</para><para>(iv) Two distance education units for each qualified distance education course sent as reported pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section if the course was received by at least one student who was in the membership of another school district which was sparse or very sparse and the course was a two-way interactive video distance education course;</para><para>(b) The difference of the amount available for distribution in the Education Innovation Fund on the August 1 when the applications were due minus any amount to be paid to school districts pursuant to section 79-1336 shall be divided by the number of distance education units to determine the incentive per distance education unit, except that the incentive per distance education unit shall not equal an amount greater than one thousand dollars; and</para><para>(c) The incentives for each school district shall equal the number of distance education units calculated for the school district multiplied by the incentive per distance education unit.</para><para>(4) If there are additional funds available for distribution after equipment reimbursements pursuant to section 79-1336 and incentives calculated pursuant to subsections (1) through (3) of this section, school districts and educational service units may qualify for additional incentives for elementary distance education courses. Such incentives shall be calculated for sending and receiving school districts and educational service units as follows:</para><para>(a) The per-hour incentives shall equal the funds available for distribution after equipment reimbursements pursuant to section 79-1336 and incentives calculated pursuant to subsections (1) through (3) of this section divided by the sum of the hours of elementary distance education courses sent or received for each school district and educational service unit submitting an application, except that the per-hour incentives shall not be greater than ten dollars; and</para><para>(b) The elementary distance education incentives for each school district and educational service unit shall equal the per-hour incentive multiplied by the hours of elementary distance education courses sent or received by the school district or educational service unit.</para><para>(5) The department may verify any or all application information using annual curriculum reports and may request such verification from the council.</para><para>(6) On or before October 1 of each year, a school district or educational service unit may appeal the denial of incentives for any course by the department to the State Board of Education. The board shall allow a representative of the school district or educational service unit an opportunity to present information concerning the appeal to the board at the November board meeting. If the board finds that the course meets the requirements of this section, the department shall pay the district from the Education Innovation Fund as soon as practical in an amount for which the district or educational service unit should have qualified based on the incentive per distance education unit used in the original certification of incentives pursuant to this section.</para><para>(7) The State Board of Education shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 53.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
