<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id477"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-10,139.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,139.03</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Hunger-Free Schools Act:</para><para>(1) Department means the State Department of Education;</para><para>(2) Eligible meal means a school breakfast or school lunch that is served (a) by a participating school, (b) to a student who qualifies for reduced-price school meals under United States Department of Agriculture child nutrition programs, and (c) at no cost to such student;</para><para>(3) Federal reimbursement rate means the payment a school receives for a school meal and is dependent on whether the school meal was a breakfast or a lunch, whether or not the student qualifies for free or reduced-price school meals, and the school year in which the school meal is served, as published by the United States Department of Agriculture pursuant to the federal Child Nutrition Act of 1966, 42 U.S.C. 1771 et seq., and the federal Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act, 42 U.S.C. 1751 et seq., and regulations promulgated under such acts, as such acts and regulations existed on January 1, 2026;</para><para>(4) Participating school means a qualified school that is selected to participate in the Hunger-Free Schools Pilot Program; and</para><para>(5) Qualified school means a school which is participating in the school breakfast program or the national school lunch program under the federal Child Nutrition Act of 1966, 42 U.S.C. 1771 et seq., or the federal Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act, 42 U.S.C. 1751 et seq., as such acts existed on January 1, 2026, and which does not serve free meals to all students under the community eligibility provision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB966, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>