<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id151">
<sectno id="id152" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id153" statutenumber="79-1003.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id155">79-1003.01</statuteno><catchline id="id156">Summer school
allowance; summer school student unit, defined; calculation.</catchline><para>(1) For school fiscal year 2008-09, the department shall calculate
a summer school allowance for each district equal to two and one-half percent
of the summer school student units for such district multiplied by eighty-five
percent of the statewide average general fund operating expenditures per formula
student. For purposes of this subsection, summer school student unit means
one student enrolled in summer school in a school district, whether or not
the student is in the membership of the school district, for (a) at least
three hours but fewer than six hours per day and (b) at least twelve days
but fewer than twenty-four days. Each school district shall receive a summer
school student unit for each qualified time period for which a student is
enrolled, up to six units per student per summer.</para>
<para>(2) For school fiscal year 2009-10 and each school fiscal
year thereafter, the department shall calculate a summer school allowance
for each district which submits
the information required for the calculation on a form prescribed by the department
on or before October 15 of the school fiscal year preceding the school fiscal
year for which aid is being calculated. A summer school allowance shall be equal
to two and one-half percent of the summer school student units for such district
multiplied by eighty-five percent of the statewide average general fund operating
expenditures per formula student. Summer school student units shall be calculated
for each student enrolled in summer school in a school district who attends
such summer school for at least twelve days, whether or not the student is
in the membership of the school district. The initial number of units for
each such student shall equal the sum of the ratios, each rounded down to
the nearest whole number, of the number of days for which the student attended
summer school classes in such district for at least three hours and less than
six hours per day divided by twelve days and of two times the number of days
for which the student attended summer school classes in such district for
six or more hours per day divided by twelve days.</para>
<para>(3) Each school district shall receive an additional summer
school student unit for each summer school student unit attributed to remedial
math or reading programs. Each school district shall also receive an additional
summer school student unit for each summer school student unit attributed
to a free lunch and free milk student. This section does not prevent school
districts from requiring and collecting fees for summer school, except that
summer school student units shall not be calculated for school districts which
collect fees for summer school from students who qualify for free or reduced-price
lunches under United States Department of Agriculture child nutrition programs.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167;  10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>