
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id36">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id38"  statutenumber="79-1233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id40">79-1233</statuteno><catchline id="id41">Access to telecomputing
resources; powers and duties.</catchline><para>Each educational
service unit shall provide access for all school districts within the geographical
area served by the unit to telecomputing resources, which shall include the
capacity to receive and transmit distance education courses on at least a
regional basis beginning on or before August 1, 2007, through the installation
of necessary equipment at each educational service unit location or through
interlocal agreements with other educational service units and shall provide
support for training users to meet their specific telecomputing and distance
education needs. School districts may annually elect prior to a date determined
by the educational service unit not to connect to such telecomputing resources.
Each educational service unit shall also develop, with the State Department
of Education, a plan which provides for connecting the telecomputing and distance
education equipment of such school districts with the telecomputing and distance
education equipment of the unit.</para>
<para>Educational
service units may enter into agreements pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation
Act and the Joint Public Agency Act to carry out this section. Such agreements
may include, but need not be limited to, provisions requiring any school district
having telecomputing or distance education equipment connected to the educational
service unit's telecomputing or distance education equipment to pay periodic
fees necessary to cover the cost of such usage.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 452, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 860, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-2225; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 950; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 141, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 386, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 27.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>