<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1087"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1087</statuteno><catchline>Class V school district; board of education; bonds; interest and sinking fund; investment.</catchline><para>The board of education of a Class V school district shall provide for the interest on all existing bonds issued by the district before the interest becomes due. The board shall also, immediately after the expiration of one-half of the time for which such bonds are issued, proceed to set apart each year, for a sinking fund, a requisite amount or proportion sufficient to pay the principal of the bonds when they become due. All money set apart for the sinking fund shall be invested as follows:</para><para>(1) In the purchase of and redemption of bonds of the school district, which bonds shall be purchased in the open market in such manner as the board of education prescribes;</para><para>(2) In bonds of the city constituting the school district;</para><para>(3) In bonds of the county in which such district is situated;</para><para>(4) In bonds of the State of Nebraska; and</para><para>(5) In United States bonds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1891, c. 45, &#167; 26, p. 327; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7032; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6663; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2726; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 183, &#167; 3, p. 724; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-2726; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2730; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 214, &#167; 4, p. 630; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 267, p. 781; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1007.03; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 733. </para></source><annotation><para>The county board of equalization makes the levy of taxes for a school district. C. R. T. Corp. v. Board of Equalization, 172 Neb. 540, 110 N.W.2d 194 (1961).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>