<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id215">
<sectno id="id216">Sec. 12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id217" statutenumber="79-1011"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id219">79-1011</statuteno><catchline id="id220">Incentives
for consolidation; qualification; requirements; payment.</catchline><para>(1) To encourage consolidation of Class II and III school districts
with less than three hundred ninety students, incentives shall be paid to
reorganized Class II, III, IV, or V districts resulting from consolidations
which meet the requirements of this section. This section shall only apply
to consolidations with an effective date after May 31, 2009, and
before June 1, 2011.</para>
<para>(2) To qualify for incentive payments under this section,
the consolidation must be approved for incentive payments by the State Committee
for the Reorganization of School Districts. Consolidating school districts
shall file an application with the state committee on or before June 15, 2009, or within thirty
days following the issuance of the boundary change order pursuant to subsection
(1) of section 79-479, whichever
is later. The state committee shall approve or disapprove incentive
payments within thirty days after receipt of the application.</para>
<para>(3) For incentive payments to be approved by the state committee,
a reorganization study, including efficiency, demographic, curriculum, facility,
financial, and community components, must be completed prior to the reorganization. If a study containing
such elements has been completed and the study indicates that the reorganization
will most likely result in more efficiency in the delivery of educational
services or greater educational opportunities, the state committee may approve
incentive payments.</para>
<para>(4) Incentive payments shall be based on the number of students
moving from Class II or III school districts with less than three hundred
ninety students into a reorganized Class II, III, IV, or V school district
with at least three hundred ninety students based on the average daily membership
in each affected district in the school fiscal year immediately preceding
the first school fiscal year the boundary change will be in effect and the
average daily membership the consolidated district would have had following
the boundary change if it had occurred in the school fiscal year immediately
preceding the first school fiscal year the boundary change will be in effect.
The incentive
amount for each district involved in the reorganization having an average
daily membership of less than three hundred ninety students shall equal one hundred twenty-five thousand dollars plus the product of five hundred dollars per student multiplied by the difference
of three hundred ninety students minus the average daily membership
in such district.</para>
<para>(5) Except
as otherwise provided in this subsection, base fiscal year incentive payments
shall equal fifty percent of the amount calculated pursuant to subsection
(4) of this section. Base fiscal year incentive payments shall be calculated
as of August 2 immediately preceding the base fiscal year and shall be paid
directly to the reorganized district from the School District Reorganization
Fund pursuant to subsection (6) of this section. The payments
shall be made in ten as nearly as possible equal payments on the last business
day of each month, beginning in September and ending the following June, for
the base fiscal year. If the total amount of base fiscal year incentive payments
for that school fiscal year exceeds the amount in the School District Reorganization
Fund, the base fiscal year incentive payments shall be reduced proportionately
so that the total amount of base fiscal year incentive payments equals the
amount of funds so appropriated. The
base fiscal year incentive payments shall not be included in local system
formula resources as calculated under section 79-1018.01.</para>
<para>(6) The amount calculated
pursuant to subsection (4) of this section minus the amount of base fiscal
year incentive payments pursuant to subsection (5) of
this section shall be paid
out of any remaining funds in the School District Reorganization Fund after
base fiscal year incentive payments. If the total amount of second-year incentive
payments exceeds the remaining funds, the second-year incentive payments shall
be reduced proportionately so that the total amount of second-year incentive
payments equals the amount in the fund. Second-year incentive payments shall
not be included in local system formula resources as calculated pursuant to
section 79-1018.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>