<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id476"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-1340" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1340</statuteno><catchline>Cybersecurity support and services; coordinating council; implementation coordinator; educational service units; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The coordinating council shall serve as the statewide point of contact for implementation of the K-12 Education Cybersecurity Act. The coordinating council shall facilitate, support, and coordinate cybersecurity initiatives across educational service units and schools, with an emphasis on fostering partnerships, aligning statewide strategies, and encouraging the leveraging of multiple funding sources to sustain such initiatives.</para><para>(2) The coordinating council shall assign an implementation coordinator to support educational service units for the local implementation of the K-12 Education Cybersecurity Act. The coordinator shall: (a) Serve as a liaison between the department, educational service units, the office, and other key partners; (b) facilitate statewide alignment and collaboration on cybersecurity priorities and activities, including partnerships with other governmental entities, higher education institutions, and private sector organizations; (c) support educational service units in interpreting readiness assessments and translating results into action plans; (d) provide training and support for cybersecurity tools, cybersecurity frameworks, and cybersecurity best practices tailored to the kindergarten through twelfth grade education context; (e) help organize statewide or regional training opportunities, technical assistance, and knowledge-sharing events; (f) assist in monitoring progress toward statewide cybersecurity goals in order to ensure transparency and accountability; and (g) identify and promote opportunities to braid state, federal, and private funds to maximize resources.</para><para>(3) Educational service units shall be responsible for direct implementation of cybersecurity support and services for schools within their service areas, including assisting schools with readiness assessments and tool adoption.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB937, &#167; 28. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>