<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1155"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1155</statuteno><catchline>Special education programs; reports; special education program application; review and approval.</catchline><para>All school districts shall, on a date prescribed by the department, file with the department application information for special education programs and support services. Cooperatives of school districts or educational service units applying for grants or reimbursement for programs pursuant to section 79-1132, 79-1142, or 79-1144 shall also file application information pursuant to this section. The application forms shall conform to reporting requirements provided in section 79-1156. The department shall review and take action to approve, approve with modifications, or disapprove the application for special education programs of the school district, cooperative of school districts, or educational service unit. Supplementary amendments to any program application previously approved by the department may be submitted on dates specified by the department during the same school year and shall be subject to the same review and approval as the initial application. The department shall approve, approve with modifications, or disapprove all supplementary amendments to the program application. All final financial reports on special education and support services costs shall be reported to the department by October 31 of each year for the preceding school year on forms prescribed by the department. Any program that provides residential care shall show the costs of such care separately from the costs of the education program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 403, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 761, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 942, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1986, &#167; 43-643; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 367, &#167; 43; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3343; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 837; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 710, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 865, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB675, &#167; 39. </para><effectivedate>May 28, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>