<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id352"  statutenumber="79-1007.08"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1007.08</statuteno><catchline id="id355">Limited English proficiency allowance; calculation.</catchline><para>(1) For each school fiscal year, the department shall determine the limited English proficiency allowance for each school district that meets the requirements of this section. Each school district shall designate a maximum limited English proficiency allowance on or before October 15 of the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated. The school district may decline to participate in the limited English proficiency allowance by providing the department with a maximum limited English proficiency allowance of zero dollars on such form on or before October 15 of the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated.</para><para>(2) The limited English proficiency allowance for each school district that has not been disqualified pursuant to section 79-1007.09 shall equal the lesser of:</para><para>(a) The amount designated pursuant to subsection (1) of this section by the school district, if such school district designated a maximum amount, for the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated; or</para><para>(b) The statewide average general fund operating expenditures per formula student multiplied by 0.25 then multiplied by:</para><para>(i) The number of students in the school district who are limited English proficient as defined under 20 U.S.C. 7801, as such section existed on January 1, 2006, if such number is greater than or equal to twelve;</para><para>(ii) Twelve, if the number of students in the school district who are limited English proficient as defined under 20 U.S.C. 7801, as such section existed on January 1, 2006, is greater than or equal to one and less than twelve; or</para><para>(iii) Zero, if the number of students in the school district who are limited English proficient as defined under 20 U.S.C. 7801, as such section existed on January 1, 2006, is less than one.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1081, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>