<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id282" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-11,155"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>79-11,155</statuteno><catchline>Student achievement coordinator; appointment; qualifications; duties.</catchline><para>The Commissioner of Education shall appoint a student achievement coordinator, subject to confirmation by a majority vote of the members of the State Board of Education. The coordinator shall have a background and training in addressing the unique educational needs of low-achieving students, including students in poverty, limited English proficient students, and highly mobile students.</para><para>The coordinator shall evaluate and coordinate existing resources for effective programs to increase achievement for such students across the state and shall review poverty plans submitted to the State Department of Education pursuant to section 79-1013 and limited English proficiency plans submitted to the department pursuant to section 79-1014 to ascertain successful practices being used by school districts in Nebraska and to assist school districts in improving their poverty and limited English proficiency plans, including the evaluation components. The coordinator need not review the poverty and limited English proficiency plans of each school district on an annual basis but shall develop a review schedule which assures that plans are reviewed periodically.</para><para>The coordinator or other department staff designated by the Commissioner of Education shall also consult with learning communities, educational service units, and school districts on the development, implementation, and evaluation of community achievement plans. In addition, the coordinator or other department staff designated by the commissioner shall conduct an initial review of submitted community achievement plans and return the plans with any suggestions or comments prior to the final submission of the plan for approval by the State Board of Education.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB967, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 57. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>