<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-10,126"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,126</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class V school district; school fiscal year 2017-18 and thereafter; school tax; additional levy; funds established.</catchline><para>For school fiscal year 2017-18 and each school fiscal year thereafter, each Class V school district shall establish (1) for the general operation of the schools, such fund as will result from an annual levy of such rate of tax upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such school district as the board of education determines to be necessary for such purpose, (2) a fund resulting from an annual amount of tax to be determined by the board of education of not to exceed fourteen cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in the district for the purpose of acquiring sites of school buildings and the erection, alteration, equipping, and furnishing of school buildings and additions to school buildings, which tax levy shall be used for no other purposes, and (3) a further fund resulting from an annual amount of tax to be determined by the board of education to pay interest on and retiring, funding, or servicing of bonded indebtedness of the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1939, c. 112, &#167; 1, p. 485; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 79-2722; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2724; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 214, &#167; 3, p. 629; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 298, &#167; 3, p. 914; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 266, p. 780; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 285, &#167; 2, p. 952; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 307, &#167; 2, p. 1023; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 320, &#167; 3, p. 989; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 407, &#167; 2, p. 1370; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 44, p. 699; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 292, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 241; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 192; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1007.02; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 772; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 54. </para></source><annotation><para>The county board of equalization makes the levy of taxes for a school district. C. R. T. Corp. v. Board of Equalization, 172 Neb. 540, 110 N.W.2d 194 (1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>