<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id9">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id11" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-10,141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,141</statuteno><catchline>Summer Food Service Program; legislative
intent; department; duties; preference for grants; applications.</catchline>
<para>(1) Because
children are susceptible to hunger in the summertime, resulting in negative
health effects, the Legislature intends, as a state nutrition and health policy,
that the State of Nebraska's participation in the Summer Food Service Program
of the United States Department of Agriculture be strengthened where it is
needed to provide adequate nutrition for children.</para>
<para>(2) To encourage
participation and utilization of the Summer Food Service Program, the department
shall:</para><para>(a) Provide information to sponsors concerning the benefits and
availability of the Summer Food Service Program; and</para><para>(b) Award grants of up
to fifteen thousand dollars on a competitive basis to sponsors approved by
the department. Grants awarded under this section may be used for nonrecurring
expenses incurred in initiating or expanding services under the Summer Food
Service Program, including, but not limited to, the acquisition of equipment,
salaries of staff, training of staff in new capacities, outreach efforts to
publicize new or expanded services under the Summer Food Service Program,
minor alterations to accommodate new equipment, computer point-of-service
systems for food service, and the purchase of vehicles for transporting food
to sites. Funds shall not be used for food, computers, except point-of-service
systems, or capital outlay. The total amount of grants awarded under this
section shall be limited to one hundred forty thousand dollars per fiscal
year.</para><para>(3) In awarding grants under this section, the department shall
give preference in the following order of priority to:</para>
<para>(a) Sponsors located
within the boundaries of school districts in which fifty percent or more of
the students apply and qualify for free and reduced-price lunches or located
within the boundaries of a census tract in which fifty percent or more of
the children fall under the poverty threshold as defined by the United States
Department of Agriculture;</para><para>(b) Sponsors in which health or education activities are emphasized;
and</para><para>(c)
Sponsors that participate in the Summer Food Service Program at the time of
grant application.</para><para>(4) Sponsors may apply for grants under this section by:</para>
<para>(a) Submitting
to the department a plan to start or expand services under the Summer Food
Service Program;</para><para>(b) Agreeing to operate the Summer Food Service Program for a period
of not less than two years; and</para><para>(c) Assuring that the expenditure of funds
from state and local resources for the maintenance of other child nutrition
programs administered by the department shall not be diminished as a result
of grants received under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1090, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>