<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id138">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id140" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1007.17"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1007.17</statuteno><catchline id="id143">Local choice
adjustment; calculation.</catchline><para>For school fiscal years
through school fiscal year 2012-13, the department shall calculate
a local choice adjustment for each district that:</para>
<para>(1) Has fewer than three hundred ninety formula students;</para>
<para>(2) Is not in a sparse local system or a very sparse local
system; and</para>
<para>(3) Did not receive federal funds in excess of twenty-five
percent of its general fund budget of expenditures in the most recently available
complete data year or in either of the two school fiscal years preceding the
most recently available complete data year.</para>
<para>The local choice adjustment for each such district shall
equal fifty percent of the difference between the basic funding per formula
student for the district for which the local choice adjustment is being calculated
and the basic funding per formula student for the district that has the closest
to three hundred ninety formula students multiplied by the formula students
for the district for which the local choice adjustment is being calculated,
except that the local choice adjustment shall equal zero if the basic funding
per formula student for the district for which the local choice adjustment
is being calculated is less than the basic funding per formula student for
the district that has the closest to three hundred ninety formula students.
If more than one district has the closest to three hundred ninety formula
students, the basic funding representing the district that has the closest
to three hundred ninety formula students shall equal the average of the basic
funding per formula student for each such district. The closest to three hundred
ninety formula students shall be measured using the absolute value of the
difference of three hundred ninety students minus the district formula students
with the difference rounded to the nearest whole number.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB407, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>