<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id586">
<sectno id="id587">Sec. 49.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id588" statutenumber="79-1601"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id590">79-1601</statuteno><catchline id="id591">Private, denominational,
or parochial schools, teachers, and other individuals; laws applicable;
election not to meet accreditation or approval requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) through (6) of this section,
all private, denominational, and parochial schools in the State of Nebraska
and all teachers employed or giving instruction in such schools shall be subject
to and governed by the provisions of the general school laws of the state
so far as the same apply to grades, qualifications, and certification of teachers
and promotion of students. All private, denominational,
and parochial schools shall have adequate equipment and supplies, shall be
graded the same, and shall have courses of study for each grade conducted
in such schools substantially the same as those given in the public schools which the students would attend
in the absence of such private, denominational, or parochial schools.</para>
<para>(2) All private, denominational, or parochial schools shall
either comply with the accreditation or approval requirements prescribed in
section 79-318 or, for those schools which elect not to meet accreditation
or approval requirements, the requirements prescribed in section 79-318 and
subsections (2) through (6) of this section. Standards and procedures for
approval and accreditation shall be based upon the program of studies, guidance
services, the number and preparation of teachers in relation to the curriculum
and enrollment, instructional materials and equipment, science facilities
and equipment, library facilities and materials, and health and safety factors
in buildings and grounds. Rules and regulations which govern standards and
procedures for private, denominational, and parochial schools which elect,
pursuant to the procedures prescribed in subsections (2) through (6) of this
section, not to meet state accreditation or approval requirements shall be
based upon evidence that such schools offer a program of instruction leading
to the acquisition of basic skills in the language arts, mathematics, science,
social studies, and health. Such rules and regulations may include a provision
for the visitation of such schools and regular achievement testing of students
attending such schools in order to insure that such schools are offering instruction
in the basic skills listed in this subsection. Any arrangements for visitation
or testing shall be made through a parent representative of each such school.
The results of such testing may be used as evidence that such schools are
offering instruction in such basic skills but shall not be used to measure,
compare, or evaluate the competency of students at such schools.</para>
<para>(3) The provisions of subsections (3) through (6) of this
section shall apply to any private, denominational, or parochial school in
the State of Nebraska which elects not to meet state accreditation or approval
requirements. Elections pursuant to such subsections shall be effective when
a statement is received by the Commissioner of Education signed by the parents
or legal guardians of all students attending such private,
denominational, or parochial school, stating that (a) either specifically
(i) the requirements for approval and accreditation required by law and the
rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the State Board of Education
violate sincerely held religious beliefs of the parents or legal guardians
or (ii) the requirements for approval and accreditation required by law and
the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the State Board of Education
interfere with the decisions of the parents or legal guardians in directing the student's education, (b) an authorized representative
of such parents or legal guardians will at least annually submit to the Commissioner
of Education the information necessary to prove that the requirements of subdivisions
(4)(a) through (c) of this section are satisfied, (c) the school offers the
courses of instruction required by subsections (2), (3), and (4) of this section,
and (d) the parents or legal guardians have satisfied themselves that individuals
monitoring instruction at such school are qualified to monitor instruction
in the basic skills as required by subsections (2), (3), and (4) of this section
and that such individuals have demonstrated an alternative competency to monitor
instruction or supervise students pursuant to subsections
(3) through (6) of this section.</para>
<para>(4) Each such private, denominational, or parochial school
shall (a) meet minimum requirements relating to health, fire, and safety standards
prescribed by state law and the rules and regulations of the State Fire Marshal,
(b) report attendance pursuant to section 79-201, (c) maintain a sequential
program of instruction designed to lead to basic skills in the language arts,
mathematics, science, social studies, and health, and (d) comply with the
immunization requirements in section 79-217 if the statement signed by the
parents or legal guardians indicate a nonreligious reason pursuant to subdivision
(3)(a)(ii) of this section for the student attending a private, denominational,
or parochial school which elects not to meet state accreditation or approval
requirements. The State Board of Education shall establish procedures for
receiving information and reports required by subsections (3) through (6)
of this section from authorized parent representatives who may act as agents
for parents or legal guardians of students attending such school and for individuals
monitoring instruction in the basic skills required by subsections (2), (3),
and (4) of this section.</para>
<para>(5) Individuals employed or
utilized by schools which elect not to meet state accreditation
or approval requirements shall not be required to meet the certification requirements
prescribed in sections 79-801 to 79-815 but shall either (a) take appropriate
subject matter components of a nationally recognized teacher competency examination
designated by the State Board of Education as (i) including the appropriate
subject matter areas for purposes of satisfying the requirements of subsections
(3) and (4) of this section and (ii) a nationally recognized examination or
(b) offer evidence of competence to provide instruction in the basic skills
required by subsections (3) and (4) of this section pursuant to informal methods
of evaluation which shall be developed by the State Board of Education. Such
evidence may include educational transcripts, diplomas, and other information
regarding the formal educational background of such individuals. Information
concerning test results, transcripts, diplomas, and other evidence of formal
education may be transmitted to the State Department of Education by authorized
representatives of parents or legal guardians. The results of such testing
or alternative evaluation of individuals who monitor the instruction of students
attending such schools may be used as evidence of whether or not such schools
are offering adequate instruction in the basic skills prescribed in subsections
(2), (3), and (4) of this section but shall not be used to prohibit any such
school from employing such individuals. Failure of a monitor, who is tested
for the purpose of satisfying in whole or in part the requirements of subsections
(3) through (6) of this section, to attain a score equal to or exceeding both
the state or national average score or rating on appropriate subject matter
components of recognized teacher competency examinations designated by the
State Board of Education may be by itself sufficient proof that such school
does not offer adequate instruction in the basic skills prescribed in subsections
(3) and (4) of this section.</para>
<para>(6) The demonstration of competency to monitor instruction
in a private, denominational, or parochial school which has elected not to
meet state accreditation or approval requirements shall in no way constitute
or be construed to grant a license, permit, or certificate to teach in the
State of Nebraska. Any school which elects not to meet state accreditation
or approval requirements and does not meet the requirements of subsections
(2) through (6) of this section shall not be deemed a school for purposes
of section 79-201, and the parents or legal guardians of any students attending
such school shall be subject to prosecution pursuant to such section or any
statutes relating to habitual truancy.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 155, &#167; 1, p. 346; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 53, &#167; 1(h), p. 230; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6508f; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-1906; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-1913; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 506, p. 864; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 928, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1701; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1004; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 49.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Admission to public college or university,</emphasis> see section 85-607.</para><para><emphasis>Identification of students,</emphasis> home school duties, see section 43-2007.</para><para><emphasis>Religious beliefs,</emphasis> conflict with required immunizations, see section 79-221.</para><para><emphasis>Sales and use tax exemption,</emphasis> see section 77-2704.12.</para><para><emphasis>Student transfer,</emphasis> access to student files or records, see section 79-2,105.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Requirement of minimal school standards did not infringe upon constitutional rights of parents of school children. Meyerkorth v. State, 173 Neb. 889, 115 N.W.2d 585 (1962).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>