<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id207">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id209" statutenumber="79-1011"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1011</statuteno><catchline id="id212">Support grants for consolidation; qualification;
requirements; payment.</catchline><para>(1) To support school districts which consolidate, support grants
shall be paid to reorganized Class III school districts resulting
from consolidations which meet the requirements of this section. This section
shall only apply to consolidations with an effective date after April 3, 2014.</para>
<para>(2) To qualify for support
grants under this section, the consolidation must be approved
for support grants by the State
Committee for the Reorganization of School Districts. Consolidating school
districts shall file an application with the state committee on or before
June 15, 2014, or within thirty days
following the issuance of the boundary change order pursuant to subsection
(1) of section 79-479, whichever is later. The state committee shall approve
or disapprove support grants within thirty
days after receipt of the application.</para>
<para>(3) For support
grants to be approved by the state committee, a reorganization
study, including efficiency, demographic, curriculum, facility, financial,
and community components, must be completed prior to the reorganization. If
a study containing such elements has been completed and the study indicates
that the reorganization will most likely result in more efficiency in the
delivery of educational services or greater educational opportunities, the
state committee may approve support
grants.</para>
<para>(4) The amount of the support grant for each qualifying consolidation shall
equal one hundred twenty-five thousand dollars multiplied
by the number of school districts that are consolidating into the new reorganized
Class III school district.</para>
<para>(5) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, support grants shall be calculated as of August
2 immediately preceding the first
full school fiscal year the consolidation will be in effect and
shall be paid directly to the reorganized Class
III district from the School District Reorganization Fund. The
payments shall be made in ten as nearly as possible equal payments on the
last business day of each month, beginning in September and ending the following
June. If
the total amount of support
grants for that school fiscal year exceeds the amount in the School
District Reorganization Fund, the support
grants shall be reduced proportionately so that the total amount
of support
grants equals the amount of funds so appropriated. For support grants approved for school
fiscal year 2014-15, an amount equal to any reduction in such support grants
for such school fiscal year shall be paid from the amount available in the
School District Reorganization Fund for school fiscal year 2015-16 prior to
the payment of any support grants approved for school fiscal year 2015-16
and shall not be reduced unless the total for support grants approved for
school fiscal year 2014-15 exceeds the total amount available in the School
District Reorganization Fund for the combination of school fiscal years 2014-15
and 2015-16. The support grants shall not be included in local
system formula resources as calculated under section 79-1018.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB967, &#167; 15.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>