<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1130"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1130</statuteno><catchline>Transportation services; legislative intent; State Department of Education; duties; cooperative arrangement.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that transportation services for children with disabilities prescribed in section 79-1129 shall be provided in the most cost-efficient manner consistent with the goal of providing free appropriate special education to all such children. The Legislature finds that educational service units and special education cooperatives created by school districts and recognized by the State Department of Education are in a unique position to improve the coordination and efficiency of transportation services in all areas of the state. It is the intent of the Legislature to authorize and encourage school districts, educational service units, and special education cooperatives to jointly plan, coordinate, and, where feasible, provide transportation services for children with disabilities. The State Department of Education shall review and approve, approve with modifications, or disapprove all transportation applications to ensure the implementation of the most cost-efficient transportation system, consistent with the goal of providing free appropriate special education to all children.</para><para>(2) School districts, educational service units, and special education cooperatives created by school districts and recognized by the State Department of Education are authorized to jointly plan, coordinate, and, where feasible, provide special education transportation services prescribed in section 79-1129. Any educational service unit or special education cooperative may enter into a cooperative arrangement with a school board or board of education of a school district for the provision of such transportation services. Such arrangement shall be approved by the State Department of Education, and upon approval of the arrangement the educational service unit or special education cooperative providing the transportation services shall be eligible to receive direct reimbursement for such services pursuant to section 79-1144.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 942, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1986, &#167; 43-607.02; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 367, &#167; 23; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3323; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 812; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>