<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id7">
<sectno id="id8" opdate=" ">Sec. 7.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id9" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1007.10"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id11">79-1007.10</statuteno><catchline id="id12">Cost growth
factor; computation.</catchline><para>(1) For state aid calculated for all
school fiscal years except school fiscal years 2009-10 through 2013-14, the
cost growth factor shall equal the sum of: (a) One; plus (b) the
basic allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal
year in which the aid is to be distributed; plus (c) the
basic allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal
year immediately preceding the school fiscal year in which the aid is to be
distributed; plus (d) one percent.</para>
<para>(2)(a) For
state aid calculated for school fiscal year 2009-10, the cost growth factor
shall equal the sum of: (i) One; plus (ii) the basic allowable growth rate
pursuant to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal year in which the aid is
to be distributed; plus (iii) the basic allowable growth rate pursuant to
section 79-1025 for the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school
fiscal year in which the aid is to be distributed; plus (iv) one and five-tenths
percent.</para><para>(b) For state aid calculated for school fiscal year 2010-11, the
cost growth factor shall equal the sum of: (i) One; plus (ii) the basic allowable
growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal year in which
the aid is to be distributed; plus (iii) the basic allowable growth rate pursuant
to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school
fiscal year in which the aid is to be distributed; plus (iv) two percent.</para>
<para>(c) For state
aid calculated for school fiscal years 2011-12 through 2013-14, the cost growth
factor shall equal the sum of: (i) One; plus (ii) the basic allowable growth
rate pursuant to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal year in which the aid
is to be distributed; plus (iii) the basic allowable growth rate pursuant
to section 79-1025 for the school fiscal year immediately preceding the school
fiscal year in which the aid is to be distributed; plus (iv) one and five-tenths
percent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB21, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>