<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id78">
<sectno id="id79">Sec. 9.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id80" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1073"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id82">79-1073</statuteno><catchline id="id83">General fund
property tax receipts; learning community coordinating council; certification;
division; distribution; property
tax refund or in lieu of property tax reimbursement; proportionality.</catchline><para>On or before September 1 for each year, each learning community
coordinating council shall determine the expected amounts to be distributed
by the county treasurers to each member school district from general fund
property tax receipts pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of section 77-3442 and
shall certify such amounts to each member school district, the county treasurer
for each county containing territory in the learning community, and the State
Department of Education. Such property tax receipts shall be divided among
member school districts proportionally based on the difference of the school
district's formula need calculated pursuant to section 79-1007.11 minus the
sum of the state aid certified pursuant to section 79-1022 and the other actual
receipts included in local system formula resources pursuant to section 79-1018.01
for the school fiscal year for which the distribution is being made.</para>
<para>Each time the county treasurer distributes property tax receipts
from the common general fund levy to member school districts, the amount to
be distributed to each district shall be proportional based on the total amounts
to be distributed to each member school district for the school fiscal year. Each time the county treasurer certifies
a property tax refund pursuant to section 77-1736.06 based on the common general
fund levy for member school districts or any entity issues an in lieu of property
tax reimbursement based on the common general fund levy for member school
districts, including amounts paid pursuant to sections 70-651.01 and 79-1036,
the amount to be certified or reimbursed to each district shall be proportional
on the same basis as property tax receipts from such levy are distributed
to member school districts.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>