<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1108.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1108.02</statuteno><catchline>Learners with high ability; curriculum programs; funding.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning with school fiscal year 1998-99, the Legislature shall appropriate funds to be distributed by the department pursuant to subsections (2) and (3) of this section to local systems as defined in section 79-1003 annually on or before October 15. It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate, for FY1998-99, six million dollars and, for FY1999-00 and each fiscal year thereafter, the amount of the previous year's appropriation increased by the percentage growth in identified participating students plus the basic allowable growth rate in section 79-1025, to carry out this section.</para><para>(2) For school fiscal years through 2000-01, five percent of the appropriation under subsection (1) of this section shall be reserved for distribution as grants to local systems for startup costs as defined by the State Board of Education. The funds distributed pursuant to this subsection shall be distributed based on a pro rata share of the eligible costs submitted in grant applications.</para><para>(3) Local systems may apply to the department for base funds and matching funds pursuant to this section to be spent on approved accelerated or differentiated curriculum programs. Each eligible local system shall receive one-tenth of one percent of the appropriation as base funds plus a pro rata share of the remainder of the appropriation based on identified students participating in an accelerated or differentiated curriculum program, up to ten percent of the prior year's fall membership as defined in section 79-1003, as matching funds. Eligible local systems shall:</para><para>(a) Provide an approved accelerated or differentiated curriculum program for students identified as learners with high ability;</para><para>(b) Provide funds from other sources for the approved accelerated or differentiated curriculum program greater than or equal to fifty percent of the matching funds received pursuant to this subsection;</para><para>(c) Provide an accounting of the funds received pursuant to this section, funds required by subdivision (b) of this subsection, and the total cost of the program on or before August 1 of the year following the receipt of funds in a manner prescribed by the department, not to exceed one report per year;</para><para>(d) Provide data regarding the academic progress of students participating in the accelerated or differentiated curriculum program in a manner prescribed by the department, not to exceed one report per year; and</para><para>(e) Include identified students from Class I districts that are part of the local system in the accelerated or differentiated curriculum program.</para><para>If a local system will not be providing the necessary matching funds pursuant to subdivision (b) of this subsection, the local system shall request a reduction in the amount received pursuant to this subsection such that the local system will be in compliance with such subdivision. Local systems not complying with the requirements of this subsection shall not be eligible local systems in the following year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1229, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>