<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id269" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="79-1028.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1028.02</statuteno><catchline>School fiscal years 2009-10 and
2010-11; American Recovery and Reinvestment Act percentage; school district
allocation; computation; school district; duties.</catchline><para>For each
of school fiscal years 2009-10 and 2010-11, the American Recovery and Reinvestment
Act percentage shall equal the amount of funding from the federal American
Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 to be distributed through the Tax Equity
and Educational Opportunities Support Act for such school fiscal year divided
by the total equalization aid to be distributed pursuant to the Tax Equity
and Educational Opportunities Support Act for such school fiscal year. For
each school district, the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act allocation
shall equal the equalization aid to be distributed to the school district
for such school fiscal year multiplied by the American Recovery and Reinvestment
Act percentage for such school fiscal year. Such allocation shall only be
distributed upon filing of an application signed by the superintendent and
school board president of a school district and filed with the department
by the superintendent of such school district, which application meets the
requirements of the federal American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009
and is approved by the Governor or his or her designee. A school district
shall account for, report, and spend such allocation as required by the federal
American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009. Such allocation shall not
be considered a special grant fund and shall be considered state aid for all
purposes except as otherwise provided in this section and the federal American
Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009. Such
allocation shall not be adjusted in the final calculation of state aid pursuant
to section 79-1065. Such allocation shall be included in the total state aid
which may be adjusted pursuant to section 79-1065. Expenditures of such allocation
shall be considered expenditures from the general fund of the school district
and shall be included in general fund operating expenditures.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB18, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>