<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1605</statuteno><catchline>Private, denominational, or parochial schools; inspection by public school official; when required.</catchline><para>The superintendent of the school district in which any private, denominational, or parochial school is located, which school is not otherwise inspected by an area or diocesan representative holding a Nebraska certificate to administer, shall inspect such schools and report to the proper officers any evidence of failure to observe any of the provisions of sections 79-1601 to 79-1607. The Commissioner of Education, when in his or her judgment it is deemed advisable, may appoint a public school official other than such superintendent, including a member of the State Department of Education, for such inspections. Such appointee shall hold a Nebraska certificate to administer. The State Board of Education shall require the superintendents and appointed public school officials to make such inspections at least twice a year, and the school officers of such schools and the teachers giving instruction in such schools shall permit such inspection and assist and cooperate in the making of the same.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 155, &#167; 6, p. 349; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 53, &#167; 1(m), p. 231; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6508k; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-1911; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-1918; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 510, p. 865; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 254, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 395, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 441, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-1705; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1008; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 45. </para></source><annotation><para>This section did not violate constitutional provision respecting freedom of religion. Meyerkorth v. State, 173 Neb. 889, 115 N.W.2d 585 (1962).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>