<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id503">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id505" statutenumber="79-1128"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1128</statuteno><catchline id="id508">Special education
programs; school district; provide; manner; use of funds; failure to offer
acceptable program; effect.</catchline><para>The special education
programs required by section 79-1127 may be provided by any school district,
by contracting with another school district or service agency, or by some
combination of school districts, an educational service unit, combination
of educational service units, the local or regional office of intellectual disability, any program approved
by the State of Nebraska, or any combination thereof, except that only nonsectarian
services shall be considered for approval by the State of Nebraska. Any program
receiving funds under the Special Education Act shall not use such funds to
match state funds under the provisions of other programs. The members of the
school board of any school district not offering continuous special education
programs acceptable to the State Board of Education shall be in violation
of the law. No state funds shall be paid to any school district as long as
such violation exists, but no deduction shall be made from any funds required
by the Constitution of Nebraska to be paid to such district.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 403, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 863, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 761, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 443, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 43-642; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 367, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3321; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 810; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 346, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 47.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>