
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id300" statutenumber="79-1029"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1029</statuteno><catchline id="id303">Budget authority for general fund budget of expenditures; vote to exceed; procedure.</catchline><para>A school district may exceed the budget authority for the general fund budget of expenditures prescribed in section 79-1023 by an amount approved by a majority of legal voters voting on the issue at a primary, general, or special election called for such purpose upon the recommendation of the board or upon the receipt by the county clerk or election commissioner of a petition requesting an election, signed by at least five percent of the legal voters of the district. The recommendation of the board or the petition of the legal voters shall include the amount by which the board would increase its general fund budget of expenditures for the ensuing school year over and above the budget authority for the general fund budget of expenditures prescribed in section 79-1023. The county clerk or election commissioner shall place the question on the primary or general election ballot or call for a special election on the issue after the receipt of such board recommendation or legal voter petition. The election shall be held pursuant to the Election Act or section 77-3444, and all costs for a special election shall be paid by the district. A vote to exceed the budget authority for the general fund budget of expenditures prescribed in section 79-1023 may be approved on the same question as a vote to exceed the levy limits provided in section 77-3444.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1059, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 608; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 299, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3820; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 675; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 345, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 989, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1213, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB235, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 63. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>