<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1005.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1005.01</statuteno><catchline>State aid calculation generally;
income tax receipts; disbursement.</catchline><para>For state aid calculated
for all school fiscal years except school fiscal years 2002-03 through 2007-08:</para>
<para>(1) An amount equal to the amount appropriated to the School District
Income Tax Fund for distribution in school fiscal year 1992-93 shall be disbursed
as option payments as determined under section 79-1009 and as allocated income
tax funds as determined in this section and sections 79-1008.01, 79-1015.01,
79-1017.01, and 79-1018.01, except as provided in section 79-1008.02. Funds
not distributed as allocated income tax funds due to minimum levy adjustments
shall not increase the amount available to local systems for distribution
as allocated income tax funds;</para>
<para>(2) Not later than November 15 of each year, the Tax Commissioner shall
certify to the department for the preceding tax year the income tax liability
of resident individuals for each local system. The 1996 income tax liability
of resident individuals of Class I districts that are affiliated with multiple
high school districts shall be divided between local systems based on the
percentage of the Class I district's valuation affiliated with each high school
district; and</para>
<para>(3) Using the data certified by the Tax Commissioner pursuant to subdivision
(2) of this section, the department shall calculate the allocation percentage
and each local system's allocated income tax funds. The allocation percentage
shall be an amount equal to the amount appropriated to the School District
Income Tax Fund for distribution in school fiscal year 1992-93 minus the total
amount paid for option students pursuant to section 79-1009 and, for aid calculated
for school fiscal year 2010-11, minus twenty million
dollars with the difference divided by the aggregate statewide income tax
liability of all resident individuals certified pursuant to subdivision (2)
of this section. Each local system's allocated income tax funds shall be calculated
by multiplying the allocation percentage times the local system's income tax
liability certified pursuant to subdivision (2) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1998, Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 149, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 898, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1093, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167;  11; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB5, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>November 21, 2009</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>