<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id272">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id274" statutenumber="79-1102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1102</statuteno><catchline id="id277">Early Childhood
Training Center; established; purpose; duties; statewide training program;
established.</catchline><para>(1) An Early Childhood Training
Center shall be established within the State Department of Education. The
purpose of the center is to train individuals who provide education and development
activities for infants and young children and their parents. The center, taking
into consideration existing public and private training efforts, shall provide
support and assistance to schools and public and private providers of early
childhood education services in developing training programs for staff. The center, in consultation with the Department
of Health and Human Services, shall approve training that is used to satisfy
child care licensing criteria for required training, annual inservice training,
and training needed for participation or advancement in the quality rating
and improvement system established pursuant to the Step Up to Quality Child
Care Act. The center, taking into consideration existing public
and private training efforts, shall also provide clearinghouse information
and publications on available early childhood education training opportunities
throughout the state.</para>
<para>(2) The center shall establish a statewide training program
to support the development of parent education programs in local communities.
The goal of this project is to train individuals who will be able to work
with public and private providers of early childhood services to establish
parent education programs in their communities.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 567, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-3702; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 784; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB231, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB967, &#167; 20.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Step Up to Quality Child Care Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1952.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>