<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id176">
<sectno id="id177" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 16.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id178" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-1007.23"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id180">79-1007.23</statuteno><catchline id="id181">Instructional
time allowance; calculation.</catchline><para>For state aid calculated
for school fiscal year 2009-10 and each school fiscal year thereafter:</para>
<para>(1) The department shall calculate an instructional time
allowance for each district which
submits the information required for the calculation on a form prescribed
by the department on or before October 15 of the school fiscal year preceding
the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated. The instructional
time allowance shall be equal to the product of the formula students
of such district multiplied by the instructional time factor for such district
multiplied by eighty-five percent of the statewide average general fund operating
expenditures per formula student;</para>
<para>(2) The instructional time factor shall equal the difference
of the ratio of the district's average hours of instruction for each full-time
student during the regular school year for the most recently available complete
data year divided by: (a) For state aid calculated for school fiscal year
2009-10, the comparison group average hours of instruction for each full-time
student during the regular school year for the most recently available complete
data year minus one; or (b) for state aid calculated for school fiscal year
2010-11 and each school fiscal year thereafter, the statewide average hours
of instruction for each full-time student during the regular school year for
the most recently available complete data year  minus one, except that if
the result is less than zero, the instructional time factor shall equal zero;</para>
<para>(3) For school fiscal years 2009-10 and 2010-11, the comparison
group average hours of instruction for each full-time student shall be an
average of the averages for all school districts in the comparison group.
The average hours of instruction shall be defined by the department and shall
not include extracurricular activities outside of the regular school day or
time designated for students to eat lunch. The statewide average hours of
instruction for each full-time student shall be an average of the averages
for all school districts; and</para>
<para>(4) For school fiscal year 2011-12 and each school fiscal
year thereafter, the average hours of instruction shall be defined by the
department and shall be based on scheduled time for courses and the number
of students participating in such courses as reported to the department for
the most recently available complete data year. Hours of instruction shall
not include extracurricular activities outside of the regular school day or
time designated for students to eat lunch. The statewide average hours of
instruction for each student shall be an average of the averages for all school
districts.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB5, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167;  16.</para><operativedate>July 15, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>