<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-10,114" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,114</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Class III or IV school district; property; sale; proceeds of sale; use.</catchline><para id="id00">No school property of any kind belonging to any Class III or IV school district shall be sold by the school board or board of education except at a regular meeting of the board and with an affirmative recorded vote of at least two-thirds of all the members of the board. Proceeds of sale of school property sold as provided in this section may be held separately from other funds of the school district and may be used for any school purpose as the board may determine, including, but not limited to, acquiring sites for school buildings or teacherages and purchasing existing buildings for use as school buildings or teacherages, including the sites upon which such buildings are located, and the erection, alteration, equipping, and furnishing of school buildings or teacherages.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, subdivision XIV, &#167; 21, p. 383; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6968; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6602; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 79-2520; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 79-2523; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 256, &#167; 208, p. 759; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 524, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-521; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 760; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 78. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Affirmative recorded vote of at least two-thirds of all the members of the board at a regular meeting is mandatory. Hand v. School Dist. of City of Sidney, 140 Neb. 874, 2 N.W.2d 313 (1942).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>