<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id78" statutenumber="79-1003.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1003.01</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Summer school allowance; summer school student units; calculations.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall calculate a summer school allowance for each district which submits the information required for the calculation on a form prescribed by the department on or before October 15 of the school fiscal year preceding the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated. For aid calculated for school fiscal years through school fiscal year 2013-14, the summer school allowance shall be equal to two and one-half percent of the summer school student units for such district multiplied by eighty-five percent of the statewide average general fund operating expenditures per formula student. For aid calculated for school fiscal year 2014-15 and each school fiscal year thereafter, the summer school allowance shall be equal to the lesser of two and one-half percent of the product of the summer school student units for such district multiplied by eighty-five percent of the statewide average general fund operating expenditures per formula student or the summer school and early childhood summer school expenditures that are paid for with noncategorical funds generated by state or local taxes as reported on the annual financial report for the most recently available data year and that are not included in other allowances.</para><para>(2) Summer school student units shall be calculated for each student enrolled in summer school as defined in section 79-536 in a school district who attends such summer school for at least twelve days in the most recently available complete data year, whether or not the student is in the membership of the school district. The initial number of units for each such student shall equal the sum of the ratios, each rounded down to the nearest whole number, of the number of days for which the student attended summer school classes in such district for at least three hours and less than six hours per day divided by twelve days and of two times the number of days for which the student attended summer school classes in such district for six or more hours per day divided by twelve days.</para><para>(3) Each school district shall receive an additional summer school student unit for each summer school student unit attributed to remedial math or reading programs. Each school district shall also receive an additional summer school student unit for each summer school student unit attributed to a student who in the school year immediately preceding summer school either (a) qualified for free lunches or free milk and attended a school that uses information collected from parents and guardians to determine such qualifications or (b) attended a school that provides free meals to all students pursuant to the community eligibility provision.</para><para>(4) Beginning with state aid calculated for school fiscal year 2012-13, summer school student units shall be calculated for each student who was both enrolled in the most recently available complete data year in a summer session of an early childhood education program for which a qualified early childhood education fall membership greater than zero has been calculated for the school fiscal year for which aid is being calculated and eligible to attend kindergarten in the fall immediately following such summer session. The initial number of units for each such early childhood education student shall equal the sum of the ratios, each rounded down to the nearest whole number, of the number of days for which the student attended the summer session in such district for at least three hours and less than six hours per day divided by twelve days and of two times the number of days for which the student attended the summer session in such district for six or more hours per day divided by twelve days. The initial summer school student units for early childhood education students shall be multiplied by six-tenths. Instructional hours included in the calculation of the qualified early childhood education fall membership or the qualified early childhood education average daily membership shall not be included in the calculation of the summer school allowance.</para><para>(5) Each school district shall receive an additional six-tenths of a summer school student unit for each early childhood education student unit attributed to an early childhood education student who is either qualified for free lunches or free milk based on information collected from parents and guardians to determine such qualifications or is registered to attend a school in the school year immediately following such summer that provides free meals to all students pursuant to the community eligibility provision.</para><para>(6) This section does not prevent school districts from requiring and collecting fees for summer school or summer sessions of early childhood education programs, except that summer school student units shall not be calculated for school districts which collect fees for summer school from students who qualify for free or reduced-price lunches under United States Department of Agriculture child nutrition programs or who attended, or are registered to attend, a school in the school year immediately following such summer that provides free meals to all students pursuant to the community eligibility provision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB235, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB407, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB525, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>