<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id42" statutenumber="79-1225"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1225</statuteno><catchline id="id45">Governing board;
tax; levy; limitation; exception; proceeds; when remitted.</catchline><para>(1)
After the adoption of its budget statement, the board for each educational
service unit, except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, may levy
a tax in the amount which it requires under its adopted budget statement to
be received from taxation. The levy shall be subject to the limits established
by section 77-3442. The amount of such levy shall be certified by the secretary
of the educational service unit board to the county board of equalization
of each county in which any part of the geographical area of the educational
service unit is located on or before September 20 of each year. Such tax shall
be levied and assessed in the same manner as other property taxes and entered
on the books of the county treasurer. The proceeds of such tax, as collected,
shall be remitted to the treasurer of the board on or before the fifteenth
day of each month or more frequently as provided in section 77-1759.</para>
<para>(2) For fiscal year 2013-14 and each fiscal year thereafter, only an
educational service unit which has four or more member school
districts or an educational
service unit composed of a single Class IV or Class V school district may
levy a tax on the taxable value of the taxable property within the geographic
boundaries of the educational service unit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 504, &#167; 10, p. 1612; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 47, p. 700; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 746, &#167; 7, p. 2813; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 391, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 178, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 248; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 599, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 201; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 172; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 452, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 34; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1995, &#167; 79-2210; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 942; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 141, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 287, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 386, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB446, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Tax is authorized by this section to be levied for educational service units by the board, and is constitutional. Frye v. Haas, 182 Neb. 73, 152 N.W.2d 121 (1967).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>