
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id433"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-1005" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1005</statuteno><catchline>Community achievement plan aid; new community achievement plan adjustment; calculation.</catchline><para>(1) For school fiscal year 2017-18 and each school fiscal year thereafter, the department shall determine the community achievement plan aid to be paid to each school district that will participate in a community achievement plan approved by the State Board of Education pursuant to section 79-2122 for such school fiscal year. For the first two school fiscal years a school district will participate in such plan, a new community achievement plan adjustment equal to the community achievement aid shall be included in the calculation of formula need for such school district. For all other school fiscal years, a community achievement plan allowance equal to the community achievement aid shall be included in the calculation of formula need for school districts qualifying for community achievement plan aid. Community achievement plan aid shall be included as a formula resource pursuant to section 79-1017.01.</para><para>(2) Community achievement plan aid shall equal 0.4643 percent of the product of the statewide average general fund operating expenditures per formula student multiplied by the total formula students for all of the member school districts in such learning community. The community achievement plan aid for each learning community shall be divided proportionally among the member school districts based on the sum of two percent of the poverty allowance calculated pursuant to section 79-1007.06, two percent of the limited English proficiency allowance calculated pursuant to section 79-1007.08, and, for school districts with poverty students greater than forty percent of the formula students, except as otherwise provided in this section, three percent of the product of the statewide average general fund operating expenditures per formula student multiplied by the difference of the poverty students minus forty percent of the formula students for such school district.</para><para>(3) For school fiscal year 2017-18, community achievement plan aid and a new community achievement plan adjustment shall be calculated for school districts that are members of a learning community and shall be included in formula resources pursuant to section 79-1017.01 in such amount regardless of the status of the approval of a community achievement plan, but community achievement plan aid shall not be paid to such school districts until a community achievement plan for such learning community is approved by the state board. If a community achievement plan is not approved for such learning community prior to September 1, 2017, the adjustment and aid calculated pursuant to this section shall be removed for the final calculation of state aid pursuant to section 79-1065 for school fiscal year 2017-18 and such amount shall be subtracted from the state aid appropriated by the Legislature for the determination of the local effort rate pursuant to section 79-1015.01 for the final calculation of state aid for school fiscal year 2017-18.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>