<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id209">
<sectno id="id210" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id211" statutenumber="79-1014"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id213">79-1014</statuteno><catchline id="id214">Limited English
proficiency plan; submission required; when; review; approval; elements required;
appeal.</catchline><para>(1) On or before October 15 of
each year, each school district designating a maximum limited English proficiency
allowance greater than zero dollars shall submit a limited English proficiency
plan for the next school fiscal year to the department and to the learning
community coordinating council of any learning community of which the school
district is a member. On or before the immediately following December 1, (a)
the department shall approve or disapprove such plans for school districts
that are not members of a learning community, based on the inclusion of the
elements required pursuant to this section and (b) the learning community
coordinating council, and, as to the applicable portions thereof, each achievement
subcouncil, shall approve or disapprove such plan for school districts that
are members of such learning community, based on the inclusion of such elements.
On or before the immediately following December 5, each learning community
coordinating council shall certify to the department the approval or disapproval
of the limited English proficiency plan for each member school district.</para>
<para>(2) In order to be approved pursuant to this section, a limited
English proficiency plan must include an explanation of how the school district
will address the following issues for such school fiscal year:</para>
<para>(a) Identification of students with limited English proficiency;</para>
<para>(b) Instructional approaches;</para>
<para>(c) Assessment of such students' progress toward mastering
the English language; and</para>
<para>(d) An evaluation to determine the effectiveness of the elements
of the limited English proficiency plan.</para>
<para>(3) The state board shall establish a procedure for appeal
of decisions of the department and of learning community coordinating councils
to the state board for a final determination.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>