<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1840"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1840</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; secured by trust agreement; contents; expenses; how treated.</catchline><para>In the discretion of the authority, any bonds issued under the Nebraska Elementary and Secondary School Finance Authority Act may be secured by a trust agreement by and between the authority and an incorporated trustee or trustees which may be any trust company or bank having the powers of a trust company within the state. Such trust agreement or the resolution providing for the issuance of such bonds may pledge or assign the revenue to be received or proceeds of any contract or contracts pledged and may convey or mortgage the project or any portion thereof.</para><para>Any pledge or assignment made by the authority pursuant to this section shall be valid and binding from the time that the pledge or assignment is made, and the revenue so pledged and thereafter received by the authority shall immediately be subject to the lien of such pledge or assignment without physical delivery thereof or any further act. The lien of such pledge or assignment shall be valid and binding against all parties having claims of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise against the authority irrespective of whether such parties have notice thereof.</para><para>The resolution or any trust agreement by which a pledge is created or an assignment made shall be filed or recorded in the records of the authority and with the Secretary of State and, in the case of a project, in each county in which the project is located.</para><para>Such trust agreement or resolution providing for the issuance of such bonds may contain such provisions for protecting and enforcing the rights and remedies of the bondholders as may be reasonable and proper, not in violation of law, or provided for in the act.</para><para>Any bank or trust company incorporated under the laws of this state which acts as a depository of the proceeds of the bonds, any revenue, or other money shall furnish such indemnifying bonds or pledge such securities as may be required by the authority.</para><para>Any such trust agreement may set forth the rights and remedies of the bondholders and of the trustee or trustees and may restrict the individual right of action by bondholders. Any such trust agreement or resolution may contain such other provisions as the authority may deem reasonable and proper for the security of the bondholders.</para><para>All expenses incurred in carrying out the provisions of such trust agreement or resolution may be treated as a part of the cost of the operation of a project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 809, &#167; 40. </para></source></law></legaldoc>