<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id159"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-11,160"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-11,160</statuteno><catchline>Mental health first aid training program; establish; training requirements; lottery funds; use.</catchline><para>(1) The State Department of Education shall establish a mental health first aid training program for teachers and other personnel employed by a school district or an educational service unit participating in a grant under subsection (2) of section 79-1054.</para><para>(2) The mental health first aid training is to be delivered by trainers who are properly certified by a national organization for behavioral health to provide training meeting the requirements of this section. The program shall also provide an opportunity for teachers and other designated personnel to complete the training necessary to become certified by a national organization for behavioral health to provide mental health first aid training to other teachers and designated personnel.</para><para>(3) Mental health first aid training shall include training on:</para><para>(a) The skills, resources, and knowledge necessary to assist students in crisis to connect with appropriate local mental health care services;</para><para>(b) Mental health resources, including the location of local community mental health centers; and</para><para>(c) Action plans and protocols for referral to such resources.</para><para>(4) A recipient of mental health first aid training shall also receive instruction in preparation to:</para><para>(a) Safely de-escalate crisis situations;</para><para>(b) Recognize the signs and symptoms of mental illness, including such psychiatric conditions as major clinical depression and anxiety disorders; and</para><para>(c) Timely refer a student to mental health services in the early stages of the development of a mental disorder to avoid subsequent behavioral health care and to enhance the effectiveness of mental health services. Except as provided in section 43-2101, any such referral shall be approved by the student's parent or guardian.</para><para>(5) It is the intent of the Legislature that the mental health first aid training program under this section shall be funded using lottery funds under section 9-812.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB852, &#167; 2. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>