<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id6" statutenumber="79-10,110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-10,110</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Health and safety
modifications, qualified zone academy, or American Recovery and Reinvestment
Act of 2009 purpose; school board; powers and duties; hearing; tax levy authorized;
issuance of bonds authorized.</catchline><para>(1) After making
a determination that an actual or potential environmental hazard or accessibility
barrier exists, that a life safety code violation exists, or that expenditures
are needed for indoor air quality or mold abatement and prevention within
the school buildings or grounds under its control, a school board may make
and deliver to the county clerk of such county in which any part of the school
district is situated, not later than the date provided in section 13-508,
an itemized estimate of the amounts necessary to be expended for the abatement
of such environmental hazard, for accessibility barrier elimination, or for
modifications for life safety code violations, indoor air quality, or mold
abatement and prevention in such school buildings or grounds. The board shall
designate the particular environmental hazard abatement project, accessibility
barrier elimination project, or modification for life safety code violations,
indoor air quality, or mold abatement and prevention for which the tax levy
provided for by this section will be expended, the period of years, which
shall not exceed ten years, for which the tax will be levied for such project,
and the estimated amount
of the levy for each year of the period based
on the taxable valuation of the district at the time of issuance.</para>
<para>(2) After a public hearing, a school board may undertake any
qualified capital purpose in any qualified zone academy under its control
and may levy a tax as provided in this section to repay a qualified zone academy
bond issued for such undertaking. The board shall designate: (a) The particular
qualified capital purpose for which the qualified zone academy bond was issued
and for which the tax levy provided for by this section will be expended;
(b) the period of years for which the tax will be levied to repay such qualified
zone academy bond, not exceeding the maturity term for such qualified
zone academy bond established pursuant to federal law or, for any such bond
issued prior to May 20, 2009, fifteen years; and (c) the estimated amount of the levy for each year of
the period based on the taxable
valuation of the district at the time of issuance. The hearing
required by this subsection shall be held only after notice of such hearing
has been published for three consecutive weeks prior to the hearing in a legal
newspaper published or of general circulation in the school district.</para>
<para>(3) After a public hearing, a school board may undertake any American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose and
may levy a tax to repay any American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009
bond issued for such undertaking.
The board shall designate: (a) The American
Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose for which the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act
of 2009 bond will be issued and for which the tax levy provided
by this section will be expended; (b) the period of years for which the tax
will be levied to repay such American
Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 bond, not exceeding the maturity term for
the type of American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 bond established
pursuant to federal law or, if no such term is established, thirty years;
and (c) the estimated amount
of the levy for each year of such period based
on the taxable valuation of the district at the time of issuance.
Prior to the public hearing, the school board shall prepare an itemized estimate
of the amounts necessary to be expended for the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose. The
hearing required by this subsection shall be held only after notice of such
hearing has been published for three consecutive weeks prior to the hearing
in a legal newspaper published or of general circulation in the school district.</para>
<para>(4) The board may designate more than one project under subsection
(1) of this section, more than one qualified capital purpose under subsection
(2) of this section, or more than one American Recovery and Reinvestment Act
of 2009 purpose under subsection (3) of this section  and levy a tax pursuant
to this section for each such project, qualified capital purpose, or American
Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose, concurrently or consecutively,
as the case may be, if the aggregate levy in each year and the duration of
each such levy will not exceed the limitations specified in this section.
Each levy for a project, a qualified capital purpose, or an American Recovery
and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose which is authorized by this section may
be imposed for such duration as the board specifies, notwithstanding the contemporaneous
existence or subsequent imposition of any other levy for another project,
qualified capital purpose, or American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009
purpose imposed pursuant to this section and notwithstanding the subsequent
issuance by the district of bonded indebtedness payable from its general fund
levy.</para>
<para>(5) The county clerk shall levy such taxes, not to exceed
five and one-fifth cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation for
Class II, III, IV, V, and VI districts, and not to exceed the limits set for
Class I districts in section 79-10,124, on the taxable property of the district
necessary to (a) cover the environmental hazard abatement or accessibility
barrier elimination project costs or costs for modification for life safety
code violations, indoor air quality, or mold abatement and prevention itemized
by the board pursuant to subsection (1) of this section and (b) repay any
qualified zone academy bonds or American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of
2009 bonds pursuant to subsection (2) or (3) of this section. Such taxes shall
be collected by the county treasurer at the same time and in the same manner
as county taxes are collected and when collected shall be paid to the treasurer
of the district and used to cover the project costs.</para>
<para>(6) If such board operates grades nine through twelve as part
of an affiliated school system, it shall designate the fraction of the project
or undertaking to be conducted for the benefit of grades nine through twelve.
Such fraction shall be raised by a levy placed upon all of the taxable value
of all taxable property in the affiliated school system pursuant to subsection
(2) of section 79-1075. The balance of the project or undertaking to be conducted
for the benefit of grades kindergarten through eight shall be raised by a
levy placed upon all of the taxable value of all taxable property in the district
which is governed by such board. The combined rate for both levies in the
high school district, to be determined by such board, shall not exceed five
and one-fifth cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable value.</para>
<para>(7) Each board which submits an itemized estimate shall establish
an environmental hazard abatement and accessibility barrier elimination project
account, a life safety code modification project account, an indoor air quality
project account, or a mold abatement and prevention project account, each
board which undertakes a qualified capital purpose shall establish a qualified
capital purpose undertaking account, within the qualified capital purpose
undertaking fund, and each board which undertakes an American Recovery and
Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose shall establish an American Recovery and
Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose undertaking account. Taxes collected pursuant
to this section shall be credited to the appropriate account to cover the
project or undertaking costs. Such estimates may be presented to the county
clerk and taxes levied accordingly.</para>
<para>(8) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Abatement includes, but is not limited to, any inspection
and testing regarding environmental hazards, any maintenance to reduce, lessen,
put an end to, diminish, moderate, decrease, control, dispose of, or eliminate
environmental hazards, any removal or encapsulation of environmentally hazardous
material or property, any related restoration
or replacement of material or property, any related architectural and engineering
services, and any other action to reduce or eliminate environmental hazards
in the school buildings or on the school grounds under the board's control,
except that abatement does not include the encapsulation of any material containing
more than one percent friable asbestos;</para>
<para>(b) Accessibility barrier means anything which impedes entry
into, exit from, or use of any building or facility by all people;</para>
<para>(c) Accessibility barrier elimination includes, but is not
limited to, inspection for and removal of accessibility barriers, maintenance
to reduce, lessen, put an end to, diminish, control, dispose of, or eliminate
accessibility barriers, related restoration or replacement of facilities or
property, any related architectural and engineering services, and any other
action to eliminate accessibility barriers in the school buildings or grounds
under the board's control;</para>
<para>(d) American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 bond means
any type or form of bond permitted by the federal American Recovery and Reinvestment
Act of 2009, as such act or bond may be amended and supplemented, including
the federal Hiring
Incentives to Restore Employment Act, as amended and supplemented, for use
by schools, except qualified zone academy bonds;</para>
<para>(e) American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose
means any construction of a new public school facility or the acquisition
of land on which such a facility is to be constructed or any expansion, rehabilitation,
modernization, renovation, or repair of any existing school facilities financed
in whole or in part with an American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009
bond;</para>
<para>(f) Environmental hazard means any contamination of the air,
water, or land surface or subsurface caused by any substance adversely affecting
human health or safety if such substance has been declared hazardous by a
federal or state statute, rule, or regulation;</para>
<para>(g) Modification for indoor air quality includes, but is not
limited to, any inspection and testing regarding indoor air quality, any maintenance
to reduce, lessen, put an end to, diminish, moderate, decrease, control, dispose
of, or eliminate indoor air quality problems, any related restoration or replacement of material
or related architectural and engineering services, and any other action to
reduce or eliminate indoor air quality problems or to enhance air quality
conditions in new or existing school buildings or on school grounds under
the control of a school board;</para>
<para>(h) Modification for life safety code violation includes,
but is not limited to, any inspection and testing regarding life safety codes,
any maintenance to reduce, lessen, put an end to, diminish, moderate, decrease,
control, dispose of, or eliminate life safety hazards, any related restoration or replacement of material
or property, any related architectural and engineering services, and any other
action to reduce or eliminate life safety hazards in new or existing school
buildings or on school grounds under the control of a school board;</para>
<para>(i) Modification for mold abatement and prevention includes,
but is not limited to, any inspection and testing regarding mold abatement
and prevention, any maintenance to reduce, lessen, put an end to, diminish,
moderate, decrease, control, dispose of, or eliminate mold problems, any related restoration or replacement
of material or related architectural and engineering services, and any other
action to reduce or eliminate mold problems or to enhance air quality conditions
in new or existing school buildings or on school grounds under the control
of a school board;</para>
<para>(j) Qualified capital purpose means (i) rehabilitating or
repairing the public school facility in which the qualified zone academy is
established or (ii) providing equipment for use at such qualified zone academy;</para>
<para>(k) Qualified zone academy has the meaning found in (i) 26
U.S.C. 1397E(d)(4), as such section existed on October 3, 2008, for qualified
zone academy bonds issued on or before such date, and (ii) 26 U.S.C. 54E(d)(1),
as such section existed on October 4, 2008, for qualified zone academy bonds
issued on or after such date;</para>
<para>(l) Qualified zone academy allocation means the allocation
of the qualified zone academy bond limitation by the State Department of Education
to the qualified zone academies pursuant to (i) 26 U.S.C. 1397E(e)(2), as
such section existed on October 3, 2008, for allocations relating to qualified
zone academy bonds issued on or before such date, and (ii) 26 U.S.C. 54E(c)(2),
as such section existed on October 4, 2008, for allocations relating to qualified
zone academy bonds issued on or after such date; and</para>
<para>(m) Qualified zone academy bond has the meaning found in (i)
26 U.S.C. 1397E(d)(1), as such section existed on  October 3, 2008, for such
bonds issued on or before such date, and (ii) 26 U.S.C. 54E(a), as such section
existed on and after October 4, 2008, for such bonds issued on or after such
date, as such section or bonds may be amended or supplemented.</para>
<para>(9) Accessibility barrier elimination project costs includes,
but is not limited to, inspection, maintenance, accounting, emergency services,
consultation, or any other action to reduce or eliminate accessibility barriers.</para>
<para>(10)(a) For
the purpose of paying amounts necessary for the abatement of environmental
hazards, for accessibility
barrier elimination, for modifications for life
safety code violations, indoor air quality, or mold
abatement and prevention, for
a qualified capital purpose, or for an American Recovery and Reinvestment
Act of 2009 purpose, the board may borrow money, establish a sinking fund,
 and issue bonds and other evidences of indebtedness of the district, which
bonds and other evidences of indebtedness shall be secured by and payable
from an irrevocable pledge by the district of amounts received in respect
of the tax levy provided for by this section and any other funds of the district
available therefor. Bonds issued
for a qualified capital purpose or an American Recovery and Reinvestment Act
of 2009 purpose shall be limited to the type or types of bonds authorized
for each purpose in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, respectively. Bonds
and other evidences of indebtedness issued by a district pursuant to this
subsection shall not constitute a general obligation of the district or be
payable from any portion of its general fund levy.</para>
<para>(b) A district may exceed
the maximum levy of five and one-fifth cents per one hundred dollars of taxable
valuation authorized by subsections (5) and (6) of this section in any year
in which (i) the taxable valuation of the district is lower than the taxable
valuation in the year in which the district last issued bonds pursuant to
this section and (ii) such maximum levy is insufficient to meet the combined
annual principal and interest obligations for all bonds issued pursuant to
this section. The amount generated from a district's levy in excess of the
maximum levy upon the taxable valuation of the district shall not exceed the
combined annual principal and interest obligations for such bonds minus the
amount generated by levying the maximum levy upon the taxable valuation of
the district and minus any federal payments or subsidies associated with such
bonds.</para><para>(11) The total principal amount of
bonds for modifications to correct life safety code violations, for indoor
air quality problems, for mold abatement and prevention, or for an American
Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 purpose  which may be issued pursuant
to this section shall not exceed the total amount specified in the itemized
estimate described in subsections (1) and (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(12) The total principal amount of qualified zone academy
bonds which may be issued pursuant to this section for qualified capital purposes
with respect to a qualified zone academy shall not exceed the qualified zone
academy allocation granted to the board by the department. The total amount
that may be financed by qualified zone academy bonds pursuant to this section
for qualified purposes with respect to a qualified zone academy shall not
exceed seven and one-half million dollars statewide in a single year. In any
year that the Nebraska qualified zone academy allocations exceed seven and
one-half million dollars for qualified capital purposes to be financed with
qualified zone academy bonds issued pursuant to this section, (a) the department
shall reduce such allocations proportionally such that the statewide total
for such allocations equals seven and one-half million dollars and (b) the
difference between the Nebraska allocation and seven and one-half million
dollars shall be available to qualified zone academies for requests that will
be financed with qualified zone academy bonds issued without the benefit of
this section.</para>
<para>Nothing in this section directs the State Department of Education
to give any preference to allocation requests that will be financed with qualified
zone academy bonds issued pursuant to this section.</para>
<para>(13) The State Department of Education shall establish procedures
for allocating bond authority to school boards as may be necessary pursuant
to an American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 bond.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 624, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 405, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 212, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1073, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 487, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 706, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 348, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1310, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-4,207; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 756; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 817; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 710, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 240, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 568, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 67, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 540, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB633, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>