<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-1244"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-1244</statuteno><catchline>Power to borrow money; conditions; authorization to accept loans from state or federal government.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any educational service unit may borrow money to the amount of seventy percent of the unexpended balance of total anticipated receipts of the general fund for the current fiscal year and the following fiscal year. Total anticipated receipts of the general fund for the current fiscal year and the following fiscal year means a sum equal to the total of (i) the anticipated receipts from the current existing levy multiplied by two, (ii) the anticipated receipts from the state for core services and technology infrastructure for the current fiscal year and the following fiscal year, (iii) the anticipated receipts from the United States for the current fiscal year and the following fiscal year, and (iv) the anticipated receipts from other sources for the current fiscal year and the following fiscal year.</para><para>(b) Any educational service unit may execute and deliver in evidence thereof its promissory notes which it is hereby authorized and empowered to make and negotiate, bearing a rate of interest set by the educational service unit board and maturing not more than two fiscal years from the date thereof. Such notes, before they are negotiated, shall be presented to the treasurer of the educational service unit and registered by him or her and shall be payable out of the funds collected by such educational service unit in the order of their registry after the payment of prior registered warrants but prior to the payment of any warrant subsequently registered, except that if both warrants and notes are registered, the total of such registered notes and warrants shall not exceed one hundred percent of the unexpended balance of the total anticipated receipts of the general fund of such educational service unit for the current fiscal year and the following fiscal year. For the purpose of making such calculation, such total anticipated receipts shall not include any anticipated receipts against which the educational service unit has borrowed and issued notes pursuant to this section in either the current or the immediately preceding fiscal year.</para><para>(2) In addition to the authority granted by subsection (1) of this section, any educational service unit may accept interest-free or low-interest loans from the state or federal government and may execute and deliver in evidence thereof its promissory notes maturing not more than twenty years from the date of execution.</para><para>(3) In addition to the authority granted by subsections (1) and (2) of this section, any educational service unit may enter into loan agreements for the purpose of borrowing money from financial institutions, including banks, in amounts not in excess of seventy percent of the unexpended balance of its current existing levy. As evidence of such borrowing, an educational service unit may execute and deliver one or more written loan agreements but shall not be required to execute and deliver separate promissory notes for each borrowing under such agreements. Money borrowed pursuant to such agreements shall bear interest at such rate or rates and shall become due and be repaid as provided in such agreements. Any such agreement shall provide for repayment in full at least once each fiscal year and shall be for a term not exceeding one fiscal year. Any such agreement shall be registered upon books kept by the treasurer of the educational service unit, and money borrowed pursuant to such agreement shall be paid out of funds collected upon the current existing levy prior to the payment of any warrant or note registered subsequent to any such loan agreement. If an educational service unit has any such loan agreement or agreements outstanding and has warrants or notes registered, as described in subsection (1) of this section, the total amount (a) of borrowings pursuant to such loan agreement or agreements and (b) of registered notes and warrants shall not exceed one hundred percent of the unexpended balance of the current existing levy.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to exempt an educational service unit from the terms and conditions contained in sections 10-701 to 10-716.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 5, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>