<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id382">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id384"  statutenumber="79-1007.21"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id386">79-1007.21</statuteno><catchline id="id387">Two-year
new school adjustment; school district; application; department; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) For school fiscal year 2009-10 and each school fiscal
year thereafter, school districts may apply to the department for a two-year
new school adjustment, on a form prescribed by the department, on or before
October 15 of the school fiscal year
immediately preceding the school fiscal year for which the first-year new
school adjustment would be included in the calculation of state aid. Such
form shall require evidence of recent and expected student growth, evidence
that a new building or the expansion or remodeling of an existing building
is being completed to provide additional student capacity to accommodate such
growth and not to replace an existing building, evidence that the school fiscal
year for which the district would receive the first-year adjustment will be
the first full school fiscal year for which students will utilize such additional
capacity, and evidence of the estimated additional student capacity to be
provided by the project. On or before the immediately following December 1,
the department shall approve the estimated additional capacity for use in
the adjustment, approve a modified estimated additional capacity for use in
the adjustment, or deny the application based on the requirements of this
section, the evidence submitted on the application, and any other information
provided by the department. Each approval shall include an approved estimated
additional student capacity for the new building. The state board shall establish
procedures for appeal of decisions of the department to the state board for
final determination.</para>
<para>(2) The first-year new school adjustment for each approved
district shall equal the school district's basic funding per formula student
multiplied by twenty percent of the approved estimated additional student
capacity. The second-year new school adjustment for each approved district
shall equal the school district's basic funding per formula student multiplied
by ten percent of the approved estimated additional student capacity.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>