<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-2603"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2603</statuteno><catchline>Approved reading assessment; school district administer.</catchline><para>(1) Each school district shall administer an approved reading assessment three times during the school year to all students in kindergarten through grade three, except for any student receiving specialized instruction for limited English proficiency who has been receiving such instruction for less than two years, any student receiving special education services for whom such assessment would conflict with the individualized education plan, and any student receiving services under a plan pursuant to the requirements of section 504 of the federal Rehabilitation Act of 1973, 29 U.S.C. 794, or Title II of the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, 42 U.S.C. 12131 to 12165, as such acts and sections existed on January 1, 2021, for whom such assessment would conflict with such section 504 or Title II plan. The first administration of such assessment for kindergarten students shall occur within the first forty-five calendar days that school is in session of each school year and for all other grades within the first thirty calendar days that school is in session of each school year.</para><para>(2) For purposes of the Nebraska Reading Improvement Act, an approved reading assessment means an assessment of student reading skills approved by the State Department of Education which:</para><para>(a) Measures progress toward proficiency in the reading skills assessed pursuant to subsection (5) of section 79-760.03 on the statewide assessment of reading for grade three;</para><para>(b) Is valid and reliable;</para><para>(c) Is aligned with academic content standards for reading adopted by either the State Board of Education pursuant to section 79-760.01 or the school district administering such assessment pursuant to section 79-760.02;</para><para>(d) Allows teachers access to results in a reasonable time period as established by the department, not to exceed fifteen contract days; and</para><para>(e) Is commercially available and complies with requirements established by the department.</para><para>(3) On or before March 1, 2019, and on or before each March 1 thereafter, the department shall make public the list of approved reading assessments for the subsequent school year and the threshold level of performance for each such assessment. A student performing below the threshold level shall be identified as having a reading deficiency for purposes of the Nebraska Reading Improvement Act.</para><para>(4) Diagnostic assessments used within a supplemental reading intervention program do not require department approval.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1081, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 48. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>