<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id35"  statutenumber="79-2404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2404</statuteno><catchline>Failure to file approved contract
or contract amendment; Commissioner of Education; withhold funds; duties;
county treasurer; duty.</catchline><para>If the school board of any school district or the board
of any educational service unit fails to timely file a copy of an approved
contract, or contract amendment, for superintendent services or educational
service unit administrator services with the State Department of Education
as required in section 79-2403, the Commissioner of Education, after notice
to the board president and either the superintendent or educational service
unit administrator and an opportunity to be heard, shall direct that any state
aid granted pursuant to the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support
Act to the school district or core services and technology infrastructure
funds granted pursuant to section 79-1241.03 to the educational service unit
be withheld until such time as the contract or amendment is received by the
department. In addition, the commissioner shall direct each county treasurer
of a county with territory in the school district or educational service unit
to withhold all money belonging to the school district or educational service
unit until such time as the commissioner notifies such county treasurer of
receipt of such contract or amendment. Each such county treasurer shall withhold
such money. For school districts that are members of learning communities,
a determination of school money belonging to the school district shall be
based on the proportionate share of property tax receipts allocated to the
school district pursuant to section 79-1073 in addition to the other property
tax receipts belonging to the school district. If the board does not comply
with this section prior to October 1 following the school fiscal year for
which the state aid or core services and technology infrastructure funding
was calculated, the funds shall revert to the General Fund. The amount of
any reverted funds shall be included in data provided to the Governor, the
Appropriations Committee of the Legislature, and the Education Committee of
the Legislature in accordance with section 79-1031.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB470, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>