<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id155">
<sectno id="id156">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id157" statutenumber="79-2115"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id159">79-2115</statuteno><catchline id="id160">Learning community
funds; use; learning community coordinating council; powers and duties; pilot
project; audits.</catchline><para>(1) Learning community funds distributed pursuant to section
79-2103 may be used by the learning community coordinating council receiving
the funds for:</para>
<para>(a) The administration and operation of the learning community;</para>
<para>(b) The administration, operations, and programs of elementary
learning centers pursuant to sections 79-2112 to 79-2114;</para>
<para>(c) Supplements for extended hours to teachers in elementary
schools in which at least thirty-five percent of the students attending the
school who reside in the attendance area of such school qualify for free or
reduced-price lunches;</para>
<para>(d) Transportation for parents of elementary students who
qualify for free or reduced-price lunches to school functions of such students
in elementary schools;</para>
<para>(e) Up to six social workers to provide services through
the elementary learning centers; and</para>
<para>(f) Pilot projects authorized pursuant to section 79-2104.</para>
<para>(2) Each learning community coordinating council shall adopt
policies and procedures for granting supplements for extended hours and for
providing transportation for parents if any such funds are to be used for
such purposes. An example of a pilot project that could receive such funds
would be a school designated as Jump Start Center focused on providing intensive
literacy services for elementary students with low reading scores.</para>
<para>(3) Each learning community coordinating
council shall provide for financial audits of elementary learning centers and
pilot projects.  A
learning community coordinating council shall serve as the recipient of private
funds donated to support any elementary learning center or pilot project receiving
funds from
such learning community coordinating council and shall assure that the use
of such private funds is included in the financial audits required pursuant
to this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167;  24; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167;  18.</para><effectivedate>April 6, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>