<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-2605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2605</statuteno><catchline>Supplemental reading intervention program; school district; duties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Each school district shall provide a supplemental reading intervention program for the purpose of ensuring that students can read at or above grade level at the end of third grade. School districts may work collaboratively with a reading specialist at the State Department of Education, with educational service units, with learning communities, or through interlocal agreements to develop and provide such supplemental reading intervention programs. Each supplemental reading intervention program shall be:</para><para id="id00">(a) Provided to any student identified as having a reading deficiency;</para><para id="id00">(b) Implemented during regular school hours in addition to regularly scheduled reading instruction unless otherwise agreed to by a parent or guardian; and</para><para>(c) Made available as a summer reading program between each school year for any student who has been enrolled in grade one, grade two, or grade three or in a higher grade and is identified as continuing to have a reading deficiency at the conclusion of the school year preceding such summer reading program. Such summer reading program may be (i) held in conjunction with existing summer programs in the school district, (ii) held in a community reading program not affiliated with the school district, or (iii) offered online.</para><para>(2) The supplemental reading intervention program may also include:</para><para id="id00">(a) Reading intervention practices that are evidence-based;</para><para>(b) Diagnostic assessments to identify specific skill-based strengths and weaknesses a student may have;</para><para>(c) Frequent monitoring of student progress throughout the school year with instruction adjusted accordingly;</para><para>(d) Intensive intervention using strategies selected from the following list to match the weaknesses identified in the diagnostic assessment:</para><para>(i) Development in phonemic awareness, phonics, fluency, vocabulary, and reading comprehension;</para><para>(ii) Explicit and systematic instruction with detailed explanations, extensive opportunities for guided practice, and opportunities for error corrections and feedback; or</para><para>(iii) Daily targeted individual or small-group reading intervention based on student needs as determined by diagnostic assessment data subject to planned extracurricular school activities;</para><para>(e) Strategies and resources to assist with reading skills at home, including parent-training workshops and suggestions for parent-guided home reading; or</para><para>(f) Access to before-school or after-school supplemental reading intervention with a teacher or tutor who has specialized training in reading intervention.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1081, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 49. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>