<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id00" statutenumber="79-2607"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2607</statuteno><catchline>State Department of Education; professional learning system; regional coaches; powers and duties; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Evidence-based reading instruction means instruction in reading that is in alignment with scientifically based reading research and does not include the three-cueing system model of reading instruction; and</para><para>(b) Three-cueing system model of reading instruction is an approach to foundational skills instruction that involves the use of three different types of instructional cues which include semantic, syntactic, and graphophonic.</para><para>(2)(a) The State Department of Education shall develop and implement a professional learning system to help provide sustained professional learning and training regarding evidence-based reading instruction for teachers who teach children from four years of age through third grade at an approved or accredited school and teachers employed by an early childhood education program approved by the State Board of Education. The professional learning system shall include information and tips for teachers related to helping children and families work with local family literacy centers to strengthen home and family literacy programs and better instruct children in reading.</para><para>(b) Approved or accredited elementary schools and early childhood education programs approved by the State Board of Education shall ensure that teachers who teach children from four years of age through third grade are aware of the professional learning system and are adequately trained regarding evidence-based reading instruction to effectively instruct students in reading.</para><para>(3) The State Department of Education shall work with educational service units to provide regional coaches to approved or accredited elementary schools to provide assistance and job-embedded training relating to evidence-based reading instruction to teachers who teach students in kindergarten through third grade.</para><para>(4) On or before September 30 of each year, the Commissioner of Education shall file a report electronically with the Clerk of the Legislature relating to the status and use of the professional learning system implemented pursuant to this section.</para><para>(5) It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate two million dollars from the Education Future Fund for each fiscal year beginning with fiscal year 2024-25 through fiscal year 2026-27 to the State Department of Education to provide regional coaches and job-embedded training relating to evidence-based reading instruction pursuant to subsection (2) or (3) of this section.</para><para>(6) The State Department of Education may provide technical assistance as needed to assist school boards in carrying out the Nebraska Reading Improvement Act.</para><para>(7) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1081, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1284, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>