<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id144" statutenumber="79-2111"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2111</statuteno><catchline id="id147">Elementary learning center facilities; focus school or program capital projects; tax levy; repayment of funds; interest; waiver.</catchline><para>(1) A learning community may levy a maximum levy pursuant to subdivision (2)(f) of section 77-3442 for elementary learning center facility leases, for remodeling of leased elementary learning center facilities, and for up to fifty percent of the estimated costs for focus school or program capital projects approved pursuant to this section. The proceeds from such levy shall be used for elementary learning center facility leases, for remodeling of leased elementary learning center facilities, and to reduce the bonded indebtedness required for approved projects by up to fifty percent of the estimated cost of the approved project. The funds used for reductions of bonded indebtedness shall be transferred to the school district for which the project was approved and shall be deposited in such school district's special building fund for use on such project.</para><para>(2) The learning community may approve pursuant to this section funding for capital projects which will include the purchase, construction, or remodeling of facilities for a focus school or program designed to meet the requirements of section 79-769. Such approval shall include an estimated cost for the project and shall state the amount that will be provided by the learning community for such project.</para><para>(3) If, within the ten years following receipt of the funding for a capital project pursuant to this section, a school district receiving such funding uses the facility purchased, constructed, or remodeled with such funding for purposes other than those stated to qualify for the funds, the school district shall repay such funds to the learning community with interest at the rate prescribed in section 45-104.02 accruing from the date the funds were transferred to the school district's building fund as of the last date the facility was used for such purpose as determined by the learning community coordinating council or the date that the learning community coordinating council determines that the facility will not be used for such purpose or that such facility will not be purchased, constructed, or remodeled for such purpose. Interest shall continue to accrue on outstanding balances until the repayment has been completed. The remaining terms of repayment shall be determined by the learning community coordinating council. The learning community coordinating council may waive such repayment if the facility is used for a different focus school or program for a period of time that will result in the use of the facility for qualifying purposes for a total of at least ten years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 67. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>