<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id165">
<sectno id="id166">Sec. 16.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id167" statutenumber="79-2112"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id169">79-2112</statuteno><catchline id="id170">Elementary
learning center; elementary learning center executive director; qualifications; assistants
and employees.</catchline><para>(1) Elementary learning centers
shall serve as visionary resource centers for enhancing the academic success
of elementary students, particularly those students who face challenges in
the educational environment due to factors such as poverty, limited English
skills, and mobility. Each learning community coordinating council shall provide
for a system of elementary learning centers to be administered by an elementary
learning center executive director.</para>
<para>(2) The elementary learning center executive director shall
be appointed by the learning community coordinating council. The executive
director shall be a person well equipped to work with populations in poverty
and to analyze effective methods for assisting and encouraging such populations
to access the programs offered by elementary learning centers. The
elementary learning center executive director shall receive such salary as
is set by the learning community coordinating council.</para>
<para>(3) The elementary learning center executive director may
select, appoint, and compensate as he or she sees fit, within the amount provided
by the learning community coordinating council, such noncertificated assistants
and noncertificated employees as he or she deems necessary to discharge the
responsibilities under sections 79-2112 to 79-2114. Such assistants and employees
shall be subject to the control and supervision of the elementary learning
center executive director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 16.</para><effectivedate>April 6, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>