<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-2118"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2118</statuteno><catchline>Diversity plan; contents; approval;
report.</catchline><para>(1) Each learning community, together with its member
school districts, shall develop a diversity plan to provide educational opportunities
pursuant to sections 79-769 and 79-2110 in each subcouncil district
designed to attract students from diverse backgrounds, which plan may be revised
from time to time. The initial diversity plan shall be completed by December
31 of the year the initial learning community coordinating council for the
learning community takes office. The goal of the diversity plan shall be to
annually increase the socioeconomic diversity of enrollment at each grade
level in each school building within the learning community until such enrollment
reflects the average socioeconomic diversity of the entire enrollment of the
learning community.</para>
<para>(2) Each diversity plan for a learning community shall include specific
provisions relating to each subcouncil district within
such learning community. The specific provisions relating to each subcouncil district shall be approved by both
the achievement subcouncil for such district and by the learning community
coordinating council.</para>
<para>(3) The learning community coordinating council shall report to the
Education Committee of the Legislature on or before December 1 of each even-numbered
year on the diversity and changes in diversity at each grade level in each
school building within the learning community and on the academic achievement
for different demographic groups in each school building within the learning
community.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>