
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id40" statutenumber="79-2113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2113</statuteno><catchline id="id43">Elementary learning center; establishment; achievement subcouncil; plan; powers and duties; location of facilities.</catchline><para>(1) On or before the second June 1 immediately following the establishment of a new learning community, the learning community coordinating council shall establish at least one elementary learning center for each twenty-five elementary schools in which either at least thirty-five percent of the students attending the school who reside in the attendance area of such school qualify for free or reduced-price lunches or free meals are provided to all students pursuant to the community eligibility provision. The council shall determine how many of the initial elementary learning centers shall be located in each subcouncil district on or before September 1 immediately following the establishment of a new learning community.</para><para>(2) Each achievement subcouncil shall submit a plan to the learning community coordinating council for any elementary learning center in its subcouncil district and the services to be provided by such elementary learning center. In developing the plan, the achievement subcouncil shall seek input from community resources and collaborate with such resources in order to maximize the available opportunities and the participation of elementary students and their families. An achievement subcouncil may, as part of such plan, recommend services be provided through contracts with, or grants to, entities other than school districts to provide some or all of the services. Such entities may include collaborative groups which may include the participation of a school district. An achievement subcouncil may also, as part of such plan, recommend that the elementary learning center serve as a clearinghouse for recommending programs provided by school districts or other entities and that the elementary learning center assist students in accessing such programs. The plans for the initial elementary learning centers shall be submitted by the achievement subcouncils to the coordinating council on or before January 1 immediately following the establishment of a new learning community.</para><para>(3) Each elementary learning center shall have at least one facility that is located in an area with a high concentration of poverty. Such facility may be owned or leased by the learning community, or the use of the facility may be donated to the learning community. Programs offered by the elementary learning center may be offered in such facility or in other facilities, including school buildings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB525, &#167; 28. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>