
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id282"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-2803"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2803</statuteno><catchline>Purple star school; annual designation; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) The State Board of Education may annually designate any school as a purple star school if such school applies for such designation in the manner prescribed by the board and meets the qualifications in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) To qualify as a purple star school, a school shall:</para><para>(a) Designate a staff member as a military liaison, whose duties shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(i) Identifying military-connected students enrolled in the school;</para><para>(ii) Serving as a point of contact in the school for military-connected students and their families;</para><para>(iii) Determining the appropriate school services available to military-connected students; and</para><para>(iv) Assisting in the coordination of school programs relevant to military-connected students;</para><para>(b) Maintain an easily accessible web page on the school's website that includes resources for military-connected students and their families, including information regarding:</para><para>(i) Relocation to, enrollment at, registration at, and transferring records to the school;</para><para>(ii) Academic planning, course sequences, and advanced classes available at the school;</para><para>(iii) Counseling and other support services available for military-connected students enrolled at the school; and</para><para>(iv) Contact information for the military liaison designated under subdivision (2)(a) of this section and the duties of the military liaison under such subdivision;</para><para>(c) Maintain a transition program led by students, where appropriate, that assists military-connected students in transitioning into the school;</para><para>(d) Offer professional development for staff members on issues related to military-connected students; and</para><para>(e) Do at least one of the following:</para><para>(i) Post a resolution showing support for military-connected students and their families on the school's website;</para><para>(ii) Recognize April as the Military Child Month or November as Military Family Month with relevant events hosted by the school; or</para><para>(iii) Partner with a local military installation that provides opportunities for active duty military members to volunteer at the school, speak at an assembly, or host field trips for students.</para><para>(3) A public school may partner with its school district to comply with requirements under subdivision (2)(b), (d), or (e) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB5, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>