<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools"  statutenumber="79-2103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2103</statuteno><catchline>State Department of Education; learning community funds; distribution.</catchline><para>The State Department of Education shall provide learning community funds to learning communities pursuant to this section. Learning community funds shall be distributed to each qualified learning community on or before January 30 of the school fiscal year during which the learning community is established and on or before September 15 of each school fiscal year thereafter in an amount equal to the product of the ratio of the amount appropriated for learning community funds divided by the sum of the number of formula students in all learning communities that will be established during such fiscal year plus two times the number of formula students in all other learning communities for the calculation of state aid for member school districts for such school fiscal year multiplied by the number of such formula students in the learning community for learning communities that will be established in such school fiscal year or two times the number of such formula students for all other learning communities. It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate for each fiscal year up to an amount equal to five hundred thousand dollars for each learning community to be established in such fiscal year plus one million dollars for each learning community that will be in the first full fiscal year for such learning community in such fiscal year plus the amount appropriated in the prior year for all other learning communities increased by the basic allowable growth rate described in section 79-1025.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 105; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 39.</para></source></law></legaldoc>