<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id267">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id269" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="79-2104.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2104.02</statuteno><catchline id="id272">Learning
community coordinating council; use of funds; report.</catchline><para>Each
learning community coordinating council shall use any funds received after
January 15, 2011, pursuant to section 79-1241.03 for evaluation and research
pursuant to plans developed by the learning community coordinating council
with assistance from the educational service unit coordinating council <?Pub Caret?>and
adjusted on an ongoing basis. The evaluation shall be conducted by one or
more other entities or individuals who are not employees of the learning community
and shall measure progress toward the goals and objectives of the learning
community, which goals and objectives shall include reduction of excessive absenteeism of students in the member
school districts of the learning community and closing academic
achievement gaps based on socioeconomic status, and the effectiveness of the
approaches used by the learning community or pilot project to reach such goals
and objectives. Any research conducted pursuant to this section shall also
be related to such goals and objectives. After the first full year of operation,
each learning community shall report evaluation and research results to the
Education Committee of the Legislature on or before December 1 of each year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB333, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 21.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB333, section 16, with LB463, section 21, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB333 became effective March 16, 2011. Changes made by LB463 became operative May 12, 2011.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>