<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id468"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-2701" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2701</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings and declarations.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds and declares that:</para><para>(1) Our public school children, faculty, and staff are entitled to be safe in schools when they attend school and study or work;</para><para>(2) Schools have an interest in keeping students safe;</para><para>(3) The interest of schools in keeping students safe may include the presence of school resource officers or security guards if a school district determines such resources are necessary to keep schools safe;</para><para>(4) Parents and guardians of students have a vested interest in being informed of school discipline matters involving their children and to be notified as soon as possible if their children are contacted in response to a possible law violation, questioned, searched, cited, or arrested by a peace officer working with school officials;</para><para>(5) A comprehensive and clear memorandum of understanding between law enforcement and school officials will delineate the roles and responsibilities of school resource officers, security guards, and school officials to balance the interests of safety for students and school staff in relation to parental rights, student success, and family integrity, with the goal that an increased law enforcement presence at schools will not result in a disparate impact on students in federally identified demographic categories; and</para><para>(6) Schools have a duty to respond to and manage disciplinary issues. The primary role of school resource officers and security officers should be to enhance safety with the understanding that school resource officers also work to prevent and respond to law violations and serve as a community resource for students, parents, and school staff.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB390, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>