
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id116">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id118"  statutenumber="79-2110.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2110.01</statuteno><catchline>Open enrollment students; how
treated; disability; transportation services.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of all duties, entitlements,
and rights established by law, including special education as provided in
section 79-1127, open enrollment students shall be treated as resident students
of the open enrollment school district. In determining eligibility for extracurricular
activities as defined in section 79-2,126, the open enrollment student shall
be treated similarly to other students who transfer into the school from another
public, private, denominational, or parochial school.</para>
<para>(2) For open
enrollment students verified as having a disability as defined in section
79-1118.01, the transportation services set forth in section 79-1129 shall
be provided by the open enrollment school district. The State Department of
Education shall reimburse each learning community school district for special
education programs provided to open enrollment students in accordance with
section 79-1142. The resident school district of an open enrollment student
shall be exempted from the payment responsibility set forth in section 79-1140.
For purposes of the calculation to determine reimbursement pursuant to section
79-1142, the open enrollment school district shall include the adjusted average
per pupil cost as defined in section 79-1114 of the open enrollment school
district.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes
of the Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act, open enrollment
students shall not be counted as formula students by the resident school district
and shall be counted by the open enrollment school district.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 33.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Tax Equity and Educational Opportunities Support Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>