<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id287" statutenumber="79-2104.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2104.02</statuteno><catchline id="id290">Learning community coordinating council; use of funds; report.</catchline><para>Each learning community coordinating council shall use any funds received pursuant to section 79-1241.03 for evaluation of programs related to the community achievement plan developed with the assistance of the student achievement coordinator or other department staff designated by the Commissioner of Education and evaluation and research regarding the progress of the learning community pursuant to plans developed by the learning community coordinating council with assistance from the Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council and adjusted on an ongoing basis. The evaluation regarding the progress of the learning community shall be conducted by one or more other entities or individuals who are not employees of the learning community and shall measure progress toward the goals and objectives of the learning community, which goals and objectives shall include reduction of excessive absenteeism of students in the member school districts of the learning community and closing academic achievement gaps based on socioeconomic status, and the effectiveness of the approaches used by the learning community or pilot project to reach such goals and objectives. Any research conducted pursuant to this section shall also be related to such goals and objectives or programs related to the community achievement plan. Each learning community shall report evaluation and research results electronically to the Education Committee of the Legislature on or before February 1 of each year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB333, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 162; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB410, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1081, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 46. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>