<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id509"><amendatorysection statutenumber="79-2702" chaptername="Schools"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2702</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 79-2701 to 79-2704, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Department means the State Department of Education;</para><para>(2) Law enforcement agency means an agency or department of this state or of any political subdivision of this state that is responsible for the prevention and detection of crime, the enforcement of the penal, traffic, or highway laws of this state or any political subdivision of this state, and the enforcement of arrest warrants. Law enforcement agency includes a police department, an office of a town marshal, an office of a county sheriff, the Nebraska State Patrol, and any department to which a deputy state sheriff is assigned as provided in section 84-106;</para><para>(3) Peace officer has the same meaning as in section 28-109;</para><para>(4) School resource officer means any peace officer who is assigned, as his or her primary duty, to any school district to provide law enforcement and security services to any public elementary or secondary school and does not mean a peace officer responding to a call for service, providing proactive enforcement, providing law enforcement or traffic direction for a school-related event, or providing temporary services as a school resource officer when the assigned school resource officer is not available;</para><para>(5) Security agency means a contractor that employs security guards used by a school district; and</para><para>(6) Security guard means a person who is contracted or employed by a security agency to protect buildings and people and who does not have law enforcement authority or the power to arrest under any apparent authority in the jurisdiction where such person is contracted or employed as a security guard. A security guard may be an off-duty peace officer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB390, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>