<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id231">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" id="id233" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="79-2204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2204</statuteno><catchline>State Council on Educational Opportunity
for Military Children; created; members; terms; expenses; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The State
Council on Educational Opportunity for Military Children is created within
the department. The council shall consist of:</para>
<para>(a) The following
ex officio members:</para><para>(i) The Commissioner of Education;</para><para>(ii) The chairperson of
the Education Committee of the Legislature, who shall serve as a nonvoting
member of the council;</para><para>(iii) The compact commissioner appointed pursuant to section 79-2205;
and</para><para>(iv) The military family education liaison, who shall serve as
a member of the council after his or her appointment pursuant to subsection
(3) of this section; and</para><para>(b) The following members appointed by the State Board of Education:</para>
<para>(i) The superintendent
of a school district that has a high concentration of children of military
families; and</para><para>(ii) A representative of a military installation located in this
state.</para><para>(2) The members of the council appointed by the State Board of
Education shall serve three-year terms. Vacancies in the council shall be
filled in the same manner as the initial appointments. The members of the
council shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided
in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(3) The council shall have the following
duties:</para><para>(a) To advise the department with regard to the state's participation
in and compliance with the Interstate Compact on Educational Opportunity for
Military Children; and</para><para>(b) To appoint a military family education liaison to assist families
and the state in implementing the compact.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB575, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>