<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id292">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id294" statutenumber="79-2118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2118</statuteno><catchline id="id297">Diversity plan;
contents; approval; report.</catchline><para>(1) Each learning
community, together with its member school districts, shall develop a diversity
plan to provide educational opportunities pursuant to sections 79-769 and
79-2110 in each subcouncil district designed to attract students from diverse
backgrounds, which plan may be revised from time to time. The initial diversity
plan shall be completed by December 31 of the year the initial learning community
coordinating council for the learning community takes office. The goal of
the diversity plan shall be to annually increase the socioeconomic diversity
of enrollment at each grade level in each school building within the learning
community until such enrollment reflects the average socioeconomic diversity
of the entire enrollment of the learning community.</para>
<para>(2) Each diversity plan for a learning community shall include
specific provisions relating to each subcouncil district within such learning
community. The specific provisions relating to each subcouncil district shall
be approved by both the achievement subcouncil for such district and by the
learning community coordinating council.</para>
<para>(3) The learning community coordinating council shall report
electronically to the Education Committee of the Legislature on or before January 1 of each odd-numbered year
on the diversity and changes in diversity at each grade level in each school
building within the learning community and on the academic achievement for
different demographic groups in each school building within the learning community.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 163; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB410, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>