<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Schools" id="id49" statutenumber="79-2117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>79-2117</statuteno><catchline id="id52">Learning community coordinating council; achievement subcouncil; membership; meeting; hearing; duties.</catchline><para>Each learning community coordinating council shall have an achievement subcouncil for each subcouncil district. Through January 4, 2017, each achievement subcouncil shall consist of the three voting coordinating council members representing the subcouncil district plus any nonvoting coordinating council members choosing to participate who represent a school district that has territory within the subcouncil district. The voting coordinating council members shall also be the voting members on the achievement subcouncil. On and after January 5, 2017, each achievement subcouncil shall consist of the two learning community coordinating council members representing the subcouncil district. Each achievement subcouncil shall meet as necessary but shall meet and conduct a public hearing within its subcouncil district at least once each school year. Each achievement subcouncil shall:</para><para>(1) Develop a diversity plan recommendation for the territory in its subcouncil district that will provide educational opportunities which will result in increased diversity in schools in the subcouncil district;</para><para>(2) Administer elementary learning centers in cooperation with the elementary learning center executive director;</para><para>(3) Receive community input and complaints regarding the learning community and academic achievement in the subcouncil district; and</para><para>(4) Hold public hearings at its discretion in its subcouncil district in response to issues raised by residents of the subcouncil district regarding the learning community, a member school district, and academic achievement in the subcouncil district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1081, &#167; 19. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>