
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id250"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-3110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>79-3110</statuteno><catchline>Mapping data; school board or governing authority; policy; powers and duties; costs.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Mapping data means maps relating to a school building or school property with data for an efficient emergency response to such school building or school property that meets the requirements of this section; and</para><para>(b) Public safety agency means a local, county, or state agency consisting of members who serve a public or governmental agency or political subdivision in an official capacity, with or without compensation, as either peace officers, firefighters, or emergency care providers as defined in section 38-1206.04.</para><para>(2)(a) A school board of a school district or a governing authority of an approved or accredited private, denominational, or parochial school in this state may vote to adopt a policy in accordance with this section to provide mapping data to public safety agencies for use in response to emergencies.</para><para>(b) A school board or a governing authority that adopts such a policy shall provide mapping data in an electronic or digital format to assist public safety agencies in responding to an emergency at a school.</para><para>(c) The mapping data shall, at a minimum, meet all of the following requirements:</para><para>(i) Be compatible with and able to be integrated into software platforms used by public safety agencies that provide emergency services to the specific school for which the data is provided without requiring:</para><para>(A) The purchase of additional software by such public safety agencies; or</para><para>(B) The integration of third-party software to view the data;</para><para>(ii) Be a finished map product in a file format easily accessible using a standard or open-source file reader, depending on the needs of the school and the public safety agency;</para><para>(iii) Be provided in a printable format;</para><para>(iv) Be verified for accuracy, during production and annually, through a walk-through of the school campus;</para><para>(v) Give an indication of what direction is true north;</para><para>(vi) Include accurate floor plans overlaid on accurate, verified aerial imagery of the school campus;</para><para>(vii) Contain site-specific labeling that matches the structure of school buildings, including room labels, hallway names, external door or stairwell numbers, locations of hazards, key utility locations, key boxes, automated external defibrillators, and trauma kits using standard labeling rules set by the State Department of Education;</para><para>(viii) Contain site-specific labeling that matches the school grounds, including parking areas, athletic fields, surrounding roads, and neighboring properties using standard labeling rules set by the State Department of Education; and</para><para>(ix) Be overlaid with a grid and coordinates.</para><para>(3) The school board of each school district and the governing authority of each approved or accredited private, denominational, or parochial school that adopts a policy in accordance with this section shall annually (a) certify to the appropriate public safety agencies that the mapping data required to be provided under subsection (2) of this section is accurate or (b) if such information has changed, provide the appropriate public safety agencies with updated mapping data.</para><para>(4) A school board of a school district that adopts a policy in accordance with this section may apply to the State Department of Education in a manner prescribed by the Commissioner of Education for a grant to cover the costs of providing payment to vendors on behalf of the school district to facilitate the implementation of mapping data in accordance with this section for such school district. Such application shall include a copy of the appropriate school policy, an estimate from a vendor on the cost of providing such mapping data that meets the requirements of subdivision (2)(c) of this section, and any other information the department may require.</para><para>(5)(a) An approved or accredited private, denominational, or parochial school may apply to and contract with the appropriate educational service unit in the school's geographical area in a manner prescribed by the educational service unit for purposes of covering the costs of facilitating mapping data in accordance with this section.</para><para>(b) An educational service unit may apply to the State Department of Education, in a manner prescribed by the Commissioner of Education, for a grant to cover the costs of providing payments to vendors on behalf of an approved or accredited private, denominational, or parochial school which contracts with such educational service unit to facilitate the implementation of mapping data in accordance with this section for such school. The educational service unit shall include with such application the information provided to the educational service unit by the school, which shall include a copy of the appropriate school policy, an estimate from a vendor on the cost of providing such mapping data that meets the requirements of subdivision (2)(c) of this section, and any other information the department may require.</para><para>(6) It is the intent of the Legislature that grants awarded pursuant to this section shall be funded from the School Emergency Response Mapping Fund.</para><para>(7) The State Board of Education may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 88. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>