<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id286"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-3803"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>79-3803</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Stand With Women Act:</para><para>(1) Athletic association means a corporation, association, or organization which has as one of its primary purposes the sponsoring or administration of extracurricular interscholastic athletic contests or competitions;</para><para>(2) Boy means an adolescent human male;</para><para>(3) Female means an individual who naturally has, had, will have, or would have, but for a congenital anomaly or intentional or unintentional disruption, the reproductive system that at some point produces, transports, and utilizes eggs for fertilization. Female includes a woman and a girl;</para><para>(4) Girl means an adolescent human female;</para><para>(5) Male means an individual who naturally has, had, will have, or would have, but for a congenital anomaly or intentional or unintentional disruption, the reproductive system that at some point produces, transports, and utilizes sperm for fertilization. Male includes a man and a boy;</para><para>(6) Man means an adult human male;</para><para>(7) Postsecondary educational institution means a university, college, or community college located in Nebraska that is a member institution of an accrediting body recognized by the United States Department of Education;</para><para>(8) Private school means any private, denominational, or parochial school offering instruction in elementary or high school grades;</para><para>(9) Public school means any public school offering instruction in elementary or high school grades;</para><para>(10) Sex means an individual's sex, either male or female; and</para><para>(11) Woman means an adult human female.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB89, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law></legaldoc>