<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id485"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-3703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>79-3703</statuteno><catchline>College Pathway Program; eligible providers; grants; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) The State Department of Education shall develop and administer the College Pathway Program to provide grants on or after July 1, 2024, to eligible providers to provide services in accordance with subsection (2) of this section to underrepresented and low-income students in high school and postsecondary education.</para><para>(2) A provider is eligible for a grant pursuant to the College Pathway Program Act if the provider offers, exclusively to underrepresented and low-income students, educational services that provide materials, services, and supports to help a student graduate from high school, apply for admission to a postsecondary institution, and complete the requirements to receive an associate degree or a baccalaureate degree. Such educational services may include:</para><para>(a) Assistance and tutorials which help students in completing applications for a college or university, including applying for aid through the Free Application for Federal Student Aid or other scholarships;</para><para>(b) Assistance and materials which help students take the appropriate high school classes in an area or field of study a student is interested in and any classes necessary for a student to gain acceptance at a postsecondary institution or complete the requirements and take the appropriate postsecondary education classes to receive an associate degree or a baccalaureate degree; and</para><para>(c) Any other services specified pursuant to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the State Board of Education.</para><para>(3) Eligible providers may apply to the State Department of Education for a grant on forms and in a manner prescribed by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>