<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id233"><amendatorysection chaptername="Schools" statutenumber="79-3605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>79-3605</statuteno><catchline>Mental health training grant program; State Department of Education; duties; grant; application.</catchline><para>(1) The State Department of Education shall establish a mental health training grant program. The department shall award mental health training grants from any money available in the Mental Health Training Cash Fund. A grantee shall be a school district or an educational service unit.</para><para>(2) Each applicant for a mental health training grant shall describe in the application the training to be provided under the grant on:</para><para>(a) The skills, resources, and knowledge necessary to assist students in crisis to connect with appropriate local mental health services;</para><para>(b) Mental health resources, including, but not limited to, the location of local community mental health centers; and</para><para>(c) Action plans and protocols for referral to such resources.</para><para>(3) Each application for a mental health training grant shall also include in the application a description of how the training to be provided under the grant will prepare recipients of such training to:</para><para>(a) Safely de-escalate crisis situations;</para><para>(b) Recognize the signs and symptoms of mental illness, including, but not limited to, schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, major clinical depression, and anxiety disorders; and</para><para>(c) Timely refer a student to available mental health services in the early stages of the development of a mental disorder to avoid the need for subsequent behavioral health care and to enhance the effectiveness of mental health services.</para><para>(4) The State Board of Education may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section, including, but not limited to, application procedures, selection procedures, and annual reporting procedures.</para><para>(5) Grants received pursuant to this section shall be considered special grant funds under section 79-1003.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>