<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id965">
<sectno id="id966">Sec. 101.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Weights and Measures" id="id967" statutenumber="89-1,100"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id969">89-1,100</statuteno><catchline id="id970">Weights and
Measures Administrative Fund; created; use; investment; fees, penalties, and
other money; lien.</catchline><para>The director shall collect
registration, permit, laboratory, test, and inspection fees, penalties, and
money required to be reimbursed as provided for in the Weights and Measures
Act and shall remit such funds to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer
shall credit such funds to the Weights and Measures Administrative Fund, which
fund is hereby created. All fees, penalties, and reimbursements collected
pursuant to the act and credited to the fund shall be appropriated to the
uses of the department to aid in defraying the expenses of administering the
act, except that transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.
Any unexpended balance in the Weights
and Measures Administrative Fund at the close of any biennium
shall, when reappropriated, be available for the uses and purposes of the
fund for the succeeding biennium. Any money in the fund available for investment
shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska
Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The registration,
permit, laboratory, test, and inspection fees, penalties, and money required
to be reimbursed as provided for in the Weights and Measures Act shall constitute
a lien on the weighing and measuring devices or standards required to be registered
or approved for use in this state until such fees, penalties, and reimbursements
are paid. The director may sue for such fees, penalties, and reimbursements
and may seek to foreclose on any lien in the name of the state. The county
attorney of the county in which the device is located or the Attorney General's
office shall, upon the request of the director, take appropriate action to
establish and foreclose on any such lien.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1413, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 17, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 356, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 142; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 541, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 161, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 101.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>