<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fraud" statutenumber="36-708"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>36-708</statuteno><catchline>Remedies of creditors.</catchline><para>(a) In an action for relief against a transfer or obligation under the Uniform Fraudulent Transfer Act, a creditor, subject to the limitations in section 36-709, may obtain:</para><para>(1) avoidance of the transfer or obligation to the extent necessary to satisfy the creditor's claim;</para><para>(2) an attachment or other provisional remedy against the asset transferred or other property of the transferee in accordance with the procedure prescribed by Chapter 25, article 10;</para><para>(3) subject to applicable principles of equity and in accordance with applicable rules of civil procedure:</para><para>(i) an injunction against further disposition by the debtor or a transferee, or both, of the asset transferred or of other property;</para><para>(ii) appointment of a receiver to take charge of the asset transferred or of other property of the transferee; or</para><para>(iii) any other relief the circumstances may require.</para><para>(b) If a creditor has obtained a judgment on a claim against the debtor, the creditor, if the court so orders, may levy execution on the asset transferred or its proceeds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 423, &#167; 8.</para></source><annotation><para>Pursuant to subsection (a)(1) of this section, the Uniform Fraudulent Transfer Act requires some nexus between the claim upon which an individual's creditor status depends and the purpose for which that individual seeks to set aside a fraudulent transfer. Reed v. Reed, 275 Neb. 418, 747 N.W.2d 18 (2008).</para><para>An appeal of a district court's determination that a transfer of an asset was not in violation of the Uniform Fraudulent Transfer Act is equitable in nature. Parker v. Parker, 268 Neb. 187, 681 N.W.2d 735 (2004).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>