<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id5" statutenumber="32-713"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-713</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Presidential electors; notice of appointment; meeting; pledge.</catchline><para>(1) The certificates of appointment for presidential electors shall be served by the Governor on each person appointed. The Governor shall notify the presidential electors to be at the meeting location designated by the Governor at noon on the first Tuesday after the second Wednesday in December after appointment and report to the Governor at the designated meeting location as being in attendance. The Governor shall serve the certificates of appointment by registered or certified mail. In submitting this state's certificate of ascertainment as required by 3 U.S.C. 5, the Governor shall certify this state's presidential electors, include a security feature for purposes of verifying the authenticity of the certificate, and state in the certificate that:</para><para>(a) The presidential electors will serve as presidential electors unless a vacancy occurs in the office of presidential elector before the end of the meeting at which the presidential electors cast their votes, in which case a substitute presidential elector will fill the vacancy; and</para><para>(b) If a substitute presidential elector is appointed to fill a vacancy, the Governor will submit an amended certificate of ascertainment stating the names on the final list of this state's presidential electors.</para><para>(2) The presidential electors shall convene at 2 p.m. of such Tuesday at the meeting location designated by the Governor. Each presidential elector shall execute the following pledge: As a presidential elector duly selected (or appointed) for this position, I agree to serve and to mark my ballots for President and Vice President for the presidential and vice-presidential candidates who received the highest number of votes in the state if I am an at-large presidential elector or the highest number of votes in my congressional district if I am a congressional district presidential elector.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 213; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 36. </para></source><annotation><para>Governor appoints presidential electors in accordance with return of state canvassing board. State ex rel. Beeson v. Marsh, 150 Neb. 233, 34 N.W.2d 279 (1948).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>