<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id102">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id104" statutenumber="32-902"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>32-902</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Voting instructions;
voting information; posting.</catchline><para>(1) The election
commissioner or county clerk shall cause instructions for the guidance of
registered voters in preparing their ballots to be printed in large, clear
type on cards in English. He or she shall furnish at least five such cards
to each polling place in each precinct at the same time and in the same manner
as the printed ballots. The judges or clerks of election shall post such cards
in each voting booth on the day of election. The card shall contain full instructions
on preparing and casting ballots, including how to cast a write-in vote. The
form and contents of the cards shall be approved by the Secretary of State.</para>
<para>(2) The election commissioner or county clerk shall cause
voting information to be posted in each polling place on the day of election.
The voting information shall include the following information as approved
by the Secretary of State:</para>
<para>(a) Information regarding the date of the election and the
hours during which polling places will be open;</para>
<para>(b) Instructions for voters who registered to vote pursuant to section 32-304 or by
mail and first-time voters;</para>
<para>(c) General information on voting rights under applicable
federal and state laws, including information on the right of an individual
to cast a provisional ballot and instructions on how to contact the appropriate
officials if these rights are alleged to have been violated; and</para>
<para>(d) General information on federal and state laws regarding
prohibitions on acts of fraud and misrepresentation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 245; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 358, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB661, &#167; 13.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Statutory provisions regulating the conduct of an election are directory only when they are not essential to a fair election and they are not made mandatory by the statute itself. Boyer v. Aden, 241 Neb. 1, 486 N.W.2d 22 (1992).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>