<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id117">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id119" statutenumber="32-608"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>32-608</statuteno><catchline id="id122">Filing fees;
payment; amount; not required; when; refund; when allowed.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) or (5) of this section,
a filing fee shall be paid by or on behalf of each candidate prior to filing
for office. For candidates who file in the office of the Secretary of State
as provided in subdivision (1) of section 32-607, the filing fee shall be
paid to the Secretary of State who shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer
for credit to the Election Administration Fund. For candidates for any city
or village office, the filing fee shall be paid to the city or village treasurer
of the city or village in which the candidate resides. For candidates who
file in the office of the election commissioner or county clerk, the filing
fee shall be paid to the election commissioner or county clerk in the county
in which the office is sought. The election commissioner or county clerk shall
remit the fee to the county treasurer. The fee shall be placed in the general
fund of the county, city, or village. No candidate filing forms shall be filed
until the proper payment or the proper receipt showing the payment of such
filing fee is presented to the filing officer. On the day of the filing deadline,
the city or village treasurer's office shall remain open to receive filing
fees until the hour of the filing deadline.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (4) or (5) of this section,
the filing fees shall be as follows:</para>
<para>(a) For the office of United States Senator, state officers,
including members of the Legislature, Representatives in Congress, county
officers, and city or village officers, except the mayor or council members
of cities having a home rule charter, a sum equal to one percent of the annual
salary as of November 30 of the year preceding the election for
the office for which he or she files as a candidate;</para>
<para>(b) For directors of public power and irrigation districts
in districts receiving annual gross revenue of forty million dollars or more,
twenty-five dollars, and in districts receiving annual gross revenue of less
than forty million dollars, ten dollars;</para>
<para>(c) For directors of reclamation districts, ten dollars;
and</para>
<para>(d) For Regents of the University of Nebraska, members of
the State Board of Education, and directors of metropolitan utilities districts,
twenty-five dollars.</para>
<para>(3) All declared write-in candidates shall pay the filing
fees that are required for the office at the time that they present the write-in
affidavit to the filing officer. Any undeclared write-in candidate who is
nominated or elected by write-in votes shall pay the filing fee required for
the office within ten days after the canvass of votes by the county canvassing
board and shall file the receipt with the person issuing the certificate of
nomination or the certificate of election prior to the certificate being issued.</para>
<para>(4) No filing fee shall be required for any candidate filing
for an office in which a per diem is paid rather than a salary or for which
there is a salary of less than five hundred dollars per year. No filing fee
shall be required for any candidate for membership on a school board, on the
board of an educational service unit, on the board of governors of a community
college area, on the board of directors of a natural resources district, or
on the board of trustees of a sanitary and improvement district.</para>
<para>(5) No filing fee shall be required of any candidate completing
an affidavit requesting to file for elective office in forma pauperis. A pauper
shall mean a person whose income and other resources for maintenance are found
under assistance standards to be insufficient for meeting the cost of his
or her requirements and whose reserve of cash or other available resources
does not exceed the maximum available resources that an eligible individual
may own. Available resources shall include every type of property or interest
in property that an individual owns and may convert into cash except:</para>
<para>(a) Real property used as a home;</para>
<para>(b) Household goods of a moderate value used in the home;
and</para>
<para>(c) Assets to a maximum value of three thousand dollars used
by a recipient in a planned effort directed towards self-support.</para>
<para>(6) If any candidate dies prior to an election, the spouse
of the candidate may file a claim for refund of the filing fee with the proper
governing body prior to the date of the election. Upon approval of the claim
by the proper governing body, the filing fee shall be refunded.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 176; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 896, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 802, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 537, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 323, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 12.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2015</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Where no objection was made within three days after the nominating papers had been filed, the failure to present a county treasurer's receipt to the Secretary of State, as required by this section, did not invalidate the nomination. State ex rel. Maupin v. Amsberry, 104 Neb. 550, 178 N.W. 176 (1920).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>