<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id14" statutenumber="32-933"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>32-933</statuteno><catchline id="id17">New or former
resident; vote for President and Vice President; when eligible; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any person listed in this subsection shall be eligible
as a new resident to vote for President and Vice President of the United States
at the statewide general election but for no other offices:</para>
<para>(a) Any citizen of the United States who is at least the constitutionally
prescribed age of a voter and who comes into Nebraska after the voter registration
period is closed pursuant to section 32-302 for the purpose of making Nebraska
his or her place of residence; and</para>
<para>(b) Any registered voter who moves from one county to another
county within Nebraska after the close of the voter registration period.</para>
<para>(2) Any registered voter who moves from Nebraska to another
state or to the District of Columbia for the purpose of making such new location
his or her place of residence after the close of the voter registration period
for such location shall be eligible as a former resident to vote for President
and Vice President of the United States at the statewide general election
but for no other offices.</para>
<para>(3) Any person described in subsection (1) of this section
shall cast his or her ballot in the office of the election commissioner or
county clerk at any time between the close of the voter registration period
and the close of the polls on election day. Such ballots shall be available
after the close of the voter registration period. Ballots for former residents
under subsection (2) of this section shall be available thirty days
prior to the election. The ballots may be voted in the office of the election
commissioner or county clerk at any time between thirty days
prior to the election and the close of the polls on election day, or the ballots
may be mailed to the office and counted if they arrive before the close of
the polls on election day.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 276; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 935, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB271, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>