<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-628"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-628</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Petitions; requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1) All petitions prepared or filed pursuant to the Election Act or
any petition which requires the election commissioner or county clerk to verify
signatures by utilizing the voter registration register shall provide a space
at least two and one-half inches long for written signatures, a space at least
two inches long for printed names, and sufficient space for date of birth
and street name and number, city or village, and zip code. Lines on each petition
shall not be less than one-fourth inch apart. Petitions may be designed in
such a manner that lines for signatures and other information run the length
of the page rather than the width. Petitions shall provide for no more than
twenty signatures per page.</para>
<para>(2) For the purpose of preventing fraud, deception, and misrepresentation,
every sheet of every petition containing signatures shall have upon it, above
the signatures, the statements contained in this subsection, except that a
petition for recall of an elected official shall also have the additional
information specified in subsection (2) of section 32-1304. The statements
shall be printed in boldface type in substantially the following form:</para>
<para>WARNING TO PETITION SIGNERS&#8212;VIOLATION OF ANY OF THE FOLLOWING PROVISIONS
OF LAW MAY RESULT IN THE FILING OF CRIMINAL CHARGES: Any person who signs
any name other than his or her own to any petition or who is not qualified
to sign the petition shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. Any person
who falsely swears to a circulator's affidavit on a petition, who accepts
money or other things of value for signing a petition, or who offers money
or other things of value in exchange for a signature upon any petition shall
be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para>
<para>(3) Every sheet of a petition which contains signatures shall have upon
it, below the signatures, an affidavit as provided in this subsection, except
that the affidavit for a petition for recall of an elected official shall
also include the additional language specified in subsection (3) of section
32-1304. The affidavit shall be in substantially the following form:</para>
<para>
<table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<?PubTbl tgroup rth="0.00pt" clmarg="0.00pt" crmarg="0.00pt"?>
<colspec align="right" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="col2" colwidth="2.77*"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">STATE OF NEBRASKA )</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">ss.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">COUNTY OF ....... )</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>
<para>..........................., (name of circulator) being first duly sworn,
deposes and says that he or she is the circulator of this petition containing
.......... signatures, that he or she is at least eighteen years of age, that each person
whose name appears on the petition personally signed the petition in the presence
of the affiant, that the date to the left of each signature is the correct
date on which the signature was affixed to the petition and that the date
was personally affixed by the person signing such petition, that the affiant
believes that each signer has written his or her name, street and number or
voting precinct, and city, village, or post office address correctly, that
the affiant believes that each signer was qualified to sign the petition,
and that the affiant stated to each signer the object of the petition as printed
on the petition before he or she affixed his or her signature to the petition.</para>
<para>Circulator ...........................</para>
<para>Address ..............................</para>
<para>Subscribed and sworn to before me, a notary public, this ...... day
of ......... 20.... at ..............., Nebraska.</para>
<para>Notary Public ...........................</para>
<para>(4) Each sheet of a petition shall have upon its face and in plain view
of persons who sign the petition a statement in letters not smaller than sixteen-point
type in red print on the petition. If the petition is circulated by a paid
circulator, the statement shall be as follows: This petition is circulated
by a paid circulator. If the petition is circulated by a circulator who is
not being paid, the statement shall be as follows: This petition is circulated
by a volunteer circulator.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 196; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 337, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 460, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 234, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1054, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 444, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB39, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB759, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (3) of this section, petition circulators are not required to read the object statement of the petition to signatories verbatim. Chaney v. Evnen, 307 Neb. 512, 949 N.W.2d 761 (2020).</para><para>The portion of this section which reads "Any circulator circulating petitions under sections 32-702 to 32-713 shall not be hired and salaried for the express purpose of circulating petitions" violates the first amendment and is for that reason void and of no force or effect. State v. Radcliffe, 228 Neb. 868, 424 N.W.2d 608 (1988).</para><para>Where actual and exact date on which the signature of an elector was signed is readily apparent, the omission or faulty rendition of the date should be treated as a clerical or technical error. State ex rel. Morris v. Marsh, 183 Neb. 521, 162 N.W.2d 262 (1968).</para><para>When a certificate of a circulator has been impeached by proof of fraud, all signatures appearing on any petition circulated by him must be rejected until proved genuine. Barkley v. Pool, 103 Neb. 629, 173 N.W. 600 (1919).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>