<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-538"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>32-538</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City with city manager plan of government; city council; members; nomination and election; terms.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) In a city which adopts the city manager plan of government pursuant to the City Manager Plan of Government Act, the city council members shall be nominated at the statewide primary election and elected at the statewide general election.</para><para id="id00">(2) City council members shall be elected from the city at large unless the city council by ordinance provides for the election of all or some of the city council members by wards, the number and boundaries of which are provided for in section 16-104. City council members shall serve for terms of four years or until their successors are elected and qualified. The city council members shall meet the qualifications found in sections 19-613 and 19-613.01.</para><para id="id00">(3) The first election under an ordinance changing the number of city council members or their manner of election shall take place at the next statewide primary and general elections. City council members whose terms of office expire after the election shall continue in office until the expiration of the terms for which they were elected and until their successors are elected and qualified. At the first election under an ordinance changing the number of city council members or their manner of election, one-half or the bare majority of city council members elected at large, as the case may be, who receive the highest number of votes shall serve for four years and the other or others, if needed, for two years. At such first election, one-half or the bare majority of city council members, as the case may be, who are elected by wards shall serve for four years and the other or others, if needed, for two years, as provided in the ordinance. If only one city council member is to be elected at large at such first election, such member shall serve for four years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 134; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 71, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 730, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 240; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 184. </para><operativedate>November 14, 2020</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>City Manager Plan of Government Act,</emphasis> see section 19-601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>