<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-308"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-308</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Registration list;
verification; voter registration application; Department of Motor Vehicles;
duties; registration; when; confidentiality; persons
involved in registration; status.</catchline><para>(1) The Secretary
of State and the Director of Motor Vehicles shall enter into an agreement
to match information in the computerized statewide voter registration list
with information in the data base of the Department of Motor Vehicles to the
extent required to enable each such official to verify the accuracy of the
information provided on applications for voter registration. The Director
of Motor Vehicles shall enter into an agreement with the Commissioner of Social
Security under section 205(r)(8) of the federal Social Security Act, 42 U.S.C.
405(r)(8), as such section existed on April 17, 2003, for purposes of the
Election Act.</para>
<para>(2) The Department of Motor Vehicles, with the assistance
of the Secretary of State, shall prescribe a voter registration application
which may be used to register to vote or change his or her address for voting
purposes at the same time an elector applies for an original or renewal motor
vehicle operator's license, an original or renewal state identification card,
or a replacement thereof.
The voter registration application shall contain the information required
pursuant to section 32-312 and shall be designed so that it does not require
the duplication of information in the application for the motor vehicle operator's
license or state identification card, except that it may require a second
signature of the applicant. The department and the Secretary of State shall
make the voter registration application available to any person
applying for an operator's license or state identification card. The
application shall be completed at the office of the department by the close
of business on the third Friday preceding any election to be registered to
vote at such election. A registration application received after the deadline
shall not be processed by the election commissioner or county clerk until
after the election.</para>
<para>(3) The Department
of Motor Vehicles, in conjunction with the Secretary of State, shall develop
a process to electronically transmit voter registration application information
received under subsection (2) of this section to the election commissioner
or county clerk of the county in which the applicant resides within the time
limits prescribed in subsection (4) of this section. The Director of Motor
Vehicles shall designate an implementation date for the process which shall
be on or before January 1, 2016.</para><para>(4) The voter registration application information
shall be transmitted to the election commissioner or county clerk of the county
in which the applicant resides not later than ten days after receipt, except
that if the voter registration application information is received within
five days prior to the third Friday preceding any election, it shall be transmitted
not later than five days after its original submission. Any information on
whether an applicant registers or declines to register and the location of
the office at which he or she registers shall be confidential and shall only
be used for voter registration purposes.</para><para>(5) For each voter registration application
for which information is transmitted electronically pursuant to this section,
the Secretary of State shall obtain a copy of the electronic representation
of the applicant's signature from the Department of Motor Vehicles' records
of his or her motor vehicle operator's license or state identification card
for purposes of voter registration. Each voter registration application electronically
transmitted under this section shall include information provided by the applicant
that includes whether the applicant is a citizen of the United States, whether
the applicant is of sufficient age to register to vote, the applicant's residence
address, the applicant's postal address if different from the residence address,
the date of birth of the applicant, the party affiliation of the applicant
or an indication that the applicant is not affiliated with any political party,
the applicant's motor vehicle operator's license number, the applicant's previous
registration location by city, county, or state, if applicable, and the applicant's
signature.</para><para>(6) State
agency personnel involved in the voter registration process pursuant
to this section and section 32-309 shall not be considered deputy registrars
or agents or employees of the election commissioner or county clerk.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 357, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB661, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB777, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
