<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-907"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-907</statuteno><catchline>Polling places; accessibility requirements; Secretary of State; duties; training manual; training.</catchline><para>(1) All polling places shall be accessible to all registered voters and shall be in compliance with the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, as amended, and the federal Help America Vote Act of 2002, as amended. In addition, all polling places shall be modified or relocated to architecturally barrier-free buildings to provide unobstructed access to such polling places by people with physical limitations as required by this section. At least one voting booth shall be so constructed as to provide easy access for people with limitations, shall accommodate a wheelchair, and shall have a cover or barrier to provide privacy. The modifications required by this section may be of a temporary nature to provide such unobstructed access only on election day.</para><para>(2) All polling places shall meet the requirements of the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, as amended, and the federal Help America Vote Act of 2002, as amended, including, but not limited to, requirements for:</para><para>(a) Parking;</para><para>(b) An exterior route to an accessible entrance;</para><para>(c) Polling place entrances;</para><para>(d) The route from the entrance into the voting area;</para><para>(e) Voting areas, including, but not limited to, a sign (i) that indicates that assistance is available, (ii) that contains the contact telephone number approved by the Secretary of State, and (iii) posted with visible lettering that is two inches, plus one-eighth inch per foot of viewing distance more than one hundred eighty inches from viewing points;</para><para>(f) Ramps;</para><para>(g) Lifts; and</para><para>(h) Elevators.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State shall develop, print, and make publicly available a training manual regarding accessibility requirements of the Election Act, the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, as amended, and the federal Help America Vote Act of 2002, as amended.</para><para>(4) The Secretary of State shall include in the biennial training for election commissioners and county clerks current standards for accessibility. All poll workers shall receive training regarding accessibility between appointment and serving at an election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 250; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 46. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>