<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id35" statutenumber="32-209"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-209</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Chief deputy election
commissioner; qualifications; appointment; oath; bond;
duties.</catchline><para>(1) The election commissioner in counties
having a population of more than one hundred thousand inhabitants shall appoint
a chief deputy election commissioner in the manner provided in section 32-210.
The chief deputy election commissioner shall be a member of a different political
party than the election commissioner, shall be a registered voter in the county
and of the party he or she is to represent, and shall be a resident of such
county for at least one year.</para>
<para>(2) The chief deputy election commissioner shall hold office
until the term of the election commissioner expires.</para>
<para>(3) Before
entering upon his or her duties, the chief deputy election commissioner shall
take and subscribe an oath in the form provided in section 11-101.01.</para>
<para>(4) The chief deputy election
commissioner shall give bond to the State of Nebraska in the sum of five thousand
dollars with security to be approved by the Governor conditioned on the faithful
performance of the duties of such office.</para>
<para>(5) The chief deputy election
commissioner shall perform duties assigned by the election commissioner. In
the absence of the election commissioner, the chief deputy election commissioner
shall perform all the duties of the election commissioner consistent with
the policies and procedures established by the election commissioner. The
chief deputy election commissioner shall also be responsible for carrying
out any directions properly made and given by the election commissioner prior
to his or her absence.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 226, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>Deputy election commissioner is required to be a member of a political party other than the one with which the election commissioner affiliates. State ex rel. Williams v. Moorhead, 96 Neb. 559, 148 N.W. 552 (1914), reversing 95 Neb. 80, 144 N.W. 1055 (1914).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>