<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id30">
<sectno id="id31" opdate="July 1, 2013">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id32" statutenumber="32-519"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id34">32-519</statuteno><catchline id="id35">County assessor;
election; when required; terms; qualifications; partisan ballot.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in section
22-417, at the statewide general election in 1990 and each four
years thereafter, a county assessor shall be elected in each county having
a population of more than three thousand five hundred inhabitants and more
than one thousand two hundred tax returns. The county assessor shall serve
for a term of four years.</para>
<para>(2) The county board of any county shall order the submission
of the question of electing a county assessor in the county to the registered
voters of the county at the next statewide general election upon presentation
of a petition to the county board (a) conforming to the provisions of section
32-628, (b) not less than sixty days before any statewide general election,
(c) signed by at least ten percent of the registered voters of the county
secured in not less than two-fifths of the townships or precincts of the county,
and (d) asking that the question be submitted to the registered voters in
the county. The form of submission upon the ballot shall be as follows: For
election of county assessor; Against election of county assessor. If a majority
of the votes cast on the question are against the election of a county assessor
in such county, the duties of the county assessor shall be performed by the
county clerk and the office of county assessor shall either cease with the
expiration of the term of the incumbent or continue to be abolished if no
such office exists at such time. If a majority of the votes cast on the question
are in favor of the election of a county assessor, the office shall continue
or a county assessor shall be elected at the next statewide general election.</para>
<para>(3) The county assessor shall meet the qualifications found
in sections 23-3202 and 23-3204. The county assessor shall be elected on the
partisan ballot.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 115; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB121, &#167; 4.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2013</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Under this section, the office of county assessor in a county which has elected to abolish it, continues only during the incumbency of the county assessor then holding office, and immediately upon his resignation, the county clerk becomes ex officio county assessor. Hatcher &amp; Co. v. Gosper County, 95 Neb. 543, 145 N.W. 993 (1914).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>