<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-555" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-555</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City, village, county, or school district; failure to redistrict; county attorney or election commissioner; duties; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, if the governing board of any city, village, county, or school district which nominates or elects members to the board by district or ward fails to draw district boundaries by the date established in subsection (1) of section 32-553 or subsection (4) of section 32-554, the county attorney of the county in which the board is located shall file an action in the district court for the purpose of ordering the board to draw district boundaries. If within six months after the receipt of such order the board does not comply, the members of the board shall be subject to removal and the court shall order the Secretary of State to draw district boundaries in accordance with the most recent federal decennial census. Any vacancy resulting from such removal from office shall be filled as provided by law.</para><para>(2) If the county attorney fails to file the action required by subsection (1) of this section, he or she shall be subject to removal from office. If the county attorney fails to file such action, any citizen within the jurisdiction of the governing board may file the action. The court shall order the board to pay any costs and attorney's fees involved in such action.</para><para>(3) If an election commissioner required to draw district boundaries for any county having more than four hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census pursuant to sections 23-151 and 32-553 fails to do so, the election commissioner shall be subject to (a) suit by the county attorney for the purpose of ordering the drawing of district boundaries, (b) removal from office pursuant to section 32-214 for failure to comply with an order to draw district boundaries within six months of receipt of such order, and (c) suit by any citizen for the purpose of ordering the drawing of district boundaries and shall be obligated to pay any costs and attorney's fees involved in any such action.</para><para>(4) If the county board of any county having more than four hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census fails to complete the process of drawing district boundaries as provided for in sections 23-151 and 32-553, the procedures set forth in subdivision (3)(b) of section 23-151 shall be followed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 151; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 595, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 71, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB742, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>