<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id36" statutenumber="32-312"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>32-312</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Registration application; contents.</catchline><para>The registration application prescribed by the Secretary of State pursuant to section 32-304 or 32-311.01 shall provide the instructional statements and request the information from the applicant as provided in this section.</para><para>CITIZENSHIP&#8212;"Are you a citizen of the United States of America?" with boxes to check to indicate whether the applicant is or is not a citizen of the United States.</para><para>AGE&#8212;"Are you at least eighteen years of age or will you be eighteen years of age on or before the first Tuesday following the first Monday of November of this year?" with boxes to check to indicate whether or not the applicant will be eighteen years of age or older on election day.</para><para>WARNING&#8212;"If you checked 'no' in response to either of these questions, do not complete this application.".</para><para>NAME&#8212;the name of the applicant giving the first and last name in full, the middle name in full or the middle initial, and the maiden name of the applicant, if applicable.</para><para>RESIDENCE&#8212;the name and number of the street, avenue, or other location of the dwelling where the applicant resides if there is a number. If the registrant resides in a hotel, apartment, tenement house, or institution, such additional information shall be included as will give the exact location of such registrant's place of residence. If the registrant lives in an incorporated or unincorporated area not identified by the use of roads, road names, or house numbers, the registrant shall state the section, township, and range of his or her residence and the corporate name of the school district as described in section 79-405 in which he or she is located.</para><para>POSTAL ADDRESS&#8212;the address at which the applicant receives mail if different from the residence address.</para><para>ADDRESS OF LAST REGISTRATION&#8212;the name and number of the street, avenue, or other location of the dwelling from which the applicant last registered.</para><para>TELEPHONE NUMBERS&#8212;the telephone number of the applicant at work and at home. At the request of the applicant, a designation shall be made that the telephone number is an unlisted number, and such designation shall preclude the listing of the applicant's telephone number on any list of voter registrations.</para><para>EMAIL ADDRESS&#8212;an email address of the applicant. At the request of the applicant, a designation shall be made that the email address is private, and such designation shall preclude the listing of the applicant's email address on any list of voter registrations.</para><para>DRIVER'S LICENSE NUMBER OR LAST FOUR DIGITS OF SOCIAL SECURITY NUMBER&#8212;if the applicant has a Nebraska driver's license, the license number, and if the applicant does not have a Nebraska driver's license, the last four digits of the applicant's social security number.</para><para>DATE OF APPLICATION FOR REGISTRATION&#8212;the month, day, and year when the applicant presented himself or herself for registration, when the applicant completed and signed the registration application if the application was submitted by mail or delivered to the election official by the applicant's personal messenger or personal agent, or when the completed application was submitted if the registration application was completed pursuant to section 32-304.</para><para>PLACE OF BIRTH&#8212;show the state, country, kingdom, empire, or dominion where the applicant was born.</para><para>DATE OF BIRTH&#8212;show the date of the applicant's birth. The applicant shall be at least eighteen years of age or attain eighteen years of age on or before the first Tuesday after the first Monday in November to have the right to register and vote in any election in the present calendar year.</para><para>REGISTRATION TAKEN BY&#8212;show the signature of the authorized official or staff member accepting the application pursuant to section 32-309 or 32-310 or at least one of the deputy registrars taking the application pursuant to section 32-306, if applicable.</para><para>PARTY AFFILIATION&#8212;show the party affiliation of the applicant as Democrat, Republican, or Other ........ or show no party affiliation as Nonpartisan. (Note: If you wish to vote in both partisan and nonpartisan primary elections for state and local offices, you must indicate a political party affiliation on the registration application. If you register without a political party affiliation (nonpartisan), you will receive only the nonpartisan ballots for state and local offices at primary elections. If you register without a political party affiliation, you may vote in partisan primary elections for congressional offices.)</para><para>OTHER&#8212;information the Secretary of State determines will assist in the proper and accurate registration of the voter.</para><para>Immediately following the spaces for inserting information as provided in this section, the following statement shall be printed:</para><para>To the best of my knowledge and belief, I declare under penalty of election falsification that:</para><para>(1) I live in the State of Nebraska at the address provided in this application;</para><para>(2) I have not been convicted of a felony or, if convicted, it has been at least two years since I completed my sentence for the felony, including any parole term;</para><para>(3) I have not been officially found to be non compos mentis (mentally incompetent); and</para><para>(4) I am a citizen of the United States.</para><para>Any registrant who signs this application knowing that any of the information in the application is false shall be guilty of a Class IV felony under section 32-1502 of the statutes of Nebraska. The penalty for a Class IV felony is up to two years imprisonment and twelve months post-release supervision, a fine of up to ten thousand dollars, or both.</para><para>APPLICANT'S SIGNATURE&#8212;require the applicant to affix his or her signature to the application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1037; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 357, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 359, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 53, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB661, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 5. </para></source><annotation><para>When performing the duties required by this section, registration officials act ministerially and are required to record the answers as given by the applicants and determine the latter's status as qualified voters in accordance with their answers. State ex rel. Williams v. Moorhead, 96 Neb. 559, 148 N.W. 552 (1914), reversing 95 Neb. 80, 144 N.W. 1055 (1914).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>