<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id477"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id53" statutenumber="32-405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>32-405</statuteno><catchline id="id56">Special election; when held.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise specifically provided:</para><para>(a) Any special election under the Election Act shall be held on the first Tuesday following the second Monday of the selected month, except that if such day falls upon a legal holiday, the election shall be held on the first Tuesday following the first Monday of the selected month;</para><para>(b) No special election shall be held under the Election Act in March, April, May, June, October, November, or December of an even-numbered year unless it is held in conjunction with the statewide primary or general election; and</para><para>(c) No special election shall be held under the Election Act in August or September of an even-numbered year except as provided in section 32-564 and except for a special election by a political subdivision pursuant to section 13-519 to exceed an applicable allowable growth percentage or section 77-3444 to exceed a property tax levy limit in section 77-3442.</para><para>(2) A special election for a Class I, II, III, IV, or V school district which is located in whole or in part in a county in which a city of the primary or metropolitan class is located may be held in conjunction with the primary or general election for a city of the primary or metropolitan class which is governed by a home rule charter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 521, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1055, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB521, &#167; 33. </para><operativedate>May 31, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>