<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-612</statuteno><catchline>Change of political party affiliation; requirements for candidacy; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) A change of political party affiliation by a registered voter so as to affiliate with the political party named in the candidate filing form or in an affidavit as a write-in candidate pursuant to section 32-615 after the first Friday in December prior to the statewide primary election shall not be effective to meet the requirements of section 32-610 or 32-611 or subsection (4) of this section, except that any person may change his or her political party affiliation after the first Friday in December prior to the statewide primary election to become a candidate of a new political party which has successfully completed the petition process required by section 32-716.</para><para>(2) No registered voter, candidate, or proposed candidate shall swear falsely as to political party affiliation or shall swear that he or she affiliates with two or more political parties. Any candidate who swears falsely as to political party affiliation or swears that he or she affiliates with two or more political parties shall not be the candidate of such party and shall not be entitled to assume the office for which he or she filed even if he or she receives a majority or plurality of the votes therefor at the following general election.</para><para>(3) The name of a candidate shall not appear printed on more than one political party ballot. A candidate who is a registered voter of one political party shall not accept the nomination of another political party.</para><para>(4) In order to count write-in votes on a political party ballot in the primary election, the candidate who receives the votes must be a registered voter of that political party unless the political party allows candidates not affiliated with the party by not adopting a rule under section 32-702.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 180; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB646, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>A candidate for a newly formed political party need not comply with the provisions of this section. State ex rel. Chambers v. Beermann, 229 Neb. 696, 428 N.W.2d 883 (1988).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>