<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-623"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-623</statuteno><catchline>Declination of nomination; deadline; notice, to whom given, vacancy, how filled.</catchline><para>If any person nominated for elective office notifies the filing officer with whom the candidate filing form or other acceptance of nomination was filed by filing a statement, in writing and duly acknowledged, that he or she declines such nomination on or before September 1 before the election, the person's name shall not be printed on the ballot, but no declination shall be effective after such date. The filing officer shall inform one or more persons whose names are attached to the nomination if the candidate was nominated by a political party convention or committee or, if nominated at a primary election, the chairperson or secretary of the campaign or political party committee of his or her political party if there is one and, if not, at least three of the prominent members of the candidate's political party in the state that such candidate has declined the nomination by mailing or delivering to them personally notice of such fact, and three days shall be given such party committee or convention to nominate a person to fill such vacancy. In lieu of filing a declination with the Secretary of State, the person so nominated may file a declination with the election commissioner or county clerk in the county in which he or she resides. Any election commissioner or county clerk receiving such a declination shall within five days after its receipt forward a copy of the written declination statement to the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State shall make notifications required by this section for all individuals for whom he or she receives a copy of the written declination statement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 191. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former law question as to the right of an applicant for a place on a party ballot at a primary election to withdraw less than thirty days preceding the election was raised but not decided. State ex rel. Johnson v. Marsh, 120 Neb. 297, 232 N.W. 104 (1930).</para><para>Under former law declinations of nominations, filed after the time provided by the statute, were valid if the certificates of nomination to fill the vacancy were filed within the time prior to the election that was prescribed by the statute. State ex rel. Eastham v. Dewey, 73 Neb. 396, 102 N.W. 1015 (1904).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>