<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-939"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-939</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska resident residing outside the state or country; members of Nebraska National Guard in active service; registration to vote; application for ballot; when; elector and citizen outside the country; register to vote or voting; form.</catchline><para>(1) As provided in section 32-939.02, the persons listed in this subsection who are residents of Nebraska and who reside outside of Nebraska or the United States or are members of the Nebraska National Guard ordered into the active service of the state or of the United States shall be allowed to simultaneously register to vote and make application for ballots for all elections in a calendar year through the use of the Federal Post Card Application or a personal letter which includes the same information as appears on the Federal Post Card Application:</para><para>(a) Members of the armed forces of the United States or the United States Merchant Marine, and their spouses and dependents residing with them who are absent from the state;</para><para>(b) Members of the Nebraska National Guard ordered into the active service of the state or of the United States;</para><para>(c) Citizens temporarily residing outside of the United States and the District of Columbia; and</para><para>(d) Overseas citizens.</para><para>(2)(a) As provided in section 32-939.02, a person who is the age of an elector and a citizen of the United States residing outside the United States, who has never resided in the United States, who has not registered to vote in any other state of the United States, and who has a parent registered to vote within this state shall be eligible to register to vote and vote in one county in which either one of his or her parents is a registered voter.</para><para>(b) A person registering to vote or voting pursuant to this subsection shall sign and enclose with the registration application and with the ballot being voted a form provided by the election commissioner or county clerk substantially as follows: I am the age of an elector and a citizen of the United States residing outside the United States, I have never resided in the United States, I have not registered to vote in any other state of the United States, and I have a parent registered to vote in ......... County, Nebraska. I hereby declare, under penalty of election falsification, a Class IV felony, that the statements above are true to the best of my knowledge.</para><para>THE PENALTY FOR ELECTION FALSIFICATION IS IMPRISONMENT FOR UP TO TWO YEARS AND TWELVE MONTHS POST-RELEASE SUPERVISION OR A FINE NOT TO EXCEED TEN THOUSAND DOLLARS, OR BOTH.</para><para>(Signature of Voter) ..............................</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 282; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 727, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 401, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB951, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB499, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 32. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>