<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id71" statutenumber="32-615"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>32-615</statuteno><catchline id="id74">Write-in candidate; requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection
(2) of this section, any candidate engaged in or pursuing a write-in
campaign shall file a notarized affidavit of his or her intent together with
the receipt for any filing fee with the filing officer as provided in section
32-608 no earlier than December 1 and no later than ten days prior to the
election.</para>
<para>(2) For any county office elected pursuant
to sections 32-517 to 32-529 which is subject to subdivision (1)(b) of section
32-811, a candidate may engage in or pursue a write-in campaign if he or she
files a notarized affidavit of his or her intent together with the receipt
for the filing fee with the filing officer as provided in section 32-608 on
or before March 3 of the year of the statewide primary election. If such an
affidavit is filed as prescribed, the election commissioner or county clerk
shall place that county office on the statewide primary election ballot with
the names of the candidate properly filed for the nomination of the applicable
political party and a line for write-in candidates.</para>
<para>(3) A candidate who has been
defeated as a candidate in the primary election or defeated as a write-in
candidate in the primary election shall not be eligible as a write-in candidate
for the same office in the general election unless (a) a vacancy on the ballot exists pursuant
to section 32-625 or (b) the
candidate was a candidate for an office described in sections 32-512 to 32-550
and the candidate lost the election as a result of a determination pursuant
to section 32-1122 in the case of a tie vote.</para>
<para>(4) A candidate who files
a notarized affidavit shall be entitled to all write-in votes for the candidate
even if only the last name of the candidate has been written if such last
name is reasonably close to the proper spelling.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 183; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 251, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 537, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB56, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB144, &#167; 2.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB56, section 1, with LB144, section 2, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB56 became effective February 19, 2014. Changes made by LB144 became effective July 18, 2014.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>