<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id5" statutenumber="32-811"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>32-811</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Political subdivisions; certain county officers; political
party convention delegates; names not on ballot; when.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If the names of candidates
properly filed for nomination at the primary election for directors of natural
resources districts, directors of public power districts, members of airport
authority boards elected pursuant to sections 32-547 to 32-549, members of
the boards of governors of community college areas, members of the boards
of Class III or Class V school districts which nominate candidates at a primary
election, and officers of cities of the first or second class and cities having
a city manager plan of government do not exceed two candidates for each position
to be filled, any such candidates shall be declared nominated and their names
shall not appear on any primary election ballots.</para>
<para>(b) If the number of candidates properly
filed for the nomination of a political party at the primary election for
any county officer elected pursuant to sections 32-517 to 32-529 does not
exceed the number of candidates to be nominated by that party for that office,
any such properly filed candidates shall be declared nominated and their names
shall not appear on any primary election ballots.</para>
<para>(c) The official abstract
of votes kept by the county or state shall show the names of such candidates
with the statement Nominated Without Opposition. The election commissioner
or county clerk shall place the names of such automatically nominated candidates
on the general election ballot as provided in section 32-814 or 32-815.</para>
<para>(2) Candidates shall not appear on the ballot in the primary
election for the offices listed in subsection (2) of section 32-606.</para>
<para>(3) If the number of candidates for delegates to a county
or national political party convention are the same in number or less than
the number of candidates to be elected, the names shall not appear on the
primary election ballot and those so filed shall receive a certificate of
election.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 232; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 194, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 15, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB878, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1035, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB56, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>