<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id94">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id96" statutenumber="32-903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-903</statuteno><catchline id="id99">Precincts; creation;
requirements; election commissioner or county clerk; powers and duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The election commissioner or county clerk shall create
precincts composed of compact and contiguous territory within the boundary
lines of legislative districts. The precincts shall contain not less than
seventy-five nor more than one thousand seven
hundred fifty registered voters based on the number of voters
voting at the last statewide general election, except that a precinct may
contain less than seventy-five registered voters if in the judgment of the
election commissioner or county clerk it is necessary to avoid creating an
undue hardship on the registered voters in the precinct. The election commissioner
or county clerk shall create precincts based on the number of votes cast at
the immediately preceding presidential election or the current list of registered
voters for the precinct. The election commissioner or county clerk shall revise
and rearrange the precincts and increase or decrease them at such times as
may be necessary to make the precincts contain as nearly as practicable not
less than seventy-five nor more than one thousand seven hundred fifty registered voters voting
at the last statewide general election. The election commissioner or county
clerk shall, when necessary and possible, readjust precinct boundaries to
coincide with the boundaries of cities, villages, and school districts which
are divided into districts or wards for election purposes. The election commissioner
or county clerk shall not make any precinct changes in precinct boundaries
or divide precincts into two or more parts between the statewide primary and
general elections unless he or she has been authorized to do so by the Secretary
of State. If changes are authorized, the election commissioner or county clerk
shall notify each state and local candidate affected by the change.</para>
<para>(2) The election commissioner or county clerk may alter and
divide the existing precincts, except that when any city of the first class
by ordinance divides any ward of such city into two or more voting districts
or polling places, the election commissioner or county clerk shall establish
precincts or polling places in conformity with such ordinance. No such alteration
or division shall take place between the statewide primary and general elections
except as provided in subsection (1) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) All precincts and polling places may be consolidated
for the use of electronic voting systems into fewer and larger precincts as
deemed necessary and advisable by the election commissioner or county clerk.
Such precincts, consolidated for electronic voting systems only, may have
as many registered voters therein as deemed advisable in the interest of economy
and efficiency. At least one electronic voting device shall be provided for
every five hundred registered voters voting in the consolidated precinct or
polling place at the immediately preceding general election.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 246; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 358, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 401, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
