<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id5" statutenumber="32-504"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>32-504</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Congressional districts; numbers; boundaries; established by maps; Clerk of Legislature;
Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Based on the 2010 Census of Population by the United States
Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, the State of Nebraska is hereby
divided into three districts for electing Representatives in the Congress
of the United States, and each district shall be entitled to elect one representative.</para>

<para>(2) The numbers
and boundaries of the districts are designated and established by maps identified
and labeled as maps CON11-30001-1, CON11-30001A, CON11-30001-2, CON11-30001-3,
CON11-30001-3A, filed with the Clerk of the Legislature, and incorporated
by reference as part of Laws 2011, LB704.</para><para>(3)(a) The Clerk of the Legislature shall
transfer possession of the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section
to the Secretary of State on May 27, 2011<?Pub Caret?>.</para>
<para>(b) When questions
of interpretation of district boundaries arise, the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section in possession of the Secretary of State shall serve as
the indication of the legislative intent in drawing the district boundaries.</para>
<para>(c) Each election
commissioner or county clerk shall obtain copies of the maps referred to in
subsection (2) of this section for the election commissioner's or clerk's
county from the Secretary of State.</para><para>(d) The Secretary of State shall also have
available for viewing on his or her web site the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section identifying the boundaries for the districts.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 851, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB704, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>May 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>This act does not violate the one person, one vote standard, and is constitutional. Exon v. Tiemann, 279 F.Supp. 609 (D. Neb. 1968).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
