<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-546.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-546.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Learning community coordinating council; members; election; appointment; vacancies; terms; per diem; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) Each learning community shall be governed by a learning community coordinating council. Through January 4, 2017, each council shall consist of eighteen voting members, with twelve members elected on a nonpartisan ballot from six numbered subcouncil districts created pursuant to section 32-555.01 and with six members appointed from such subcouncil districts pursuant to this section. Beginning January 5, 2017, each learning community coordinating council shall consist of twelve members elected on a nonpartisan ballot from six numbered subcouncil districts created pursuant to section 32-555.01. Members elected at the general election in 2014 shall continue to serve until the terms for which they were elected expire, and such members may run for reelection. Each voter shall be allowed to cast votes for one candidate at both the primary and general elections to represent the subcouncil district in which the voter resides. The four candidates receiving the most votes at the primary election shall advance to the general election. The two candidates receiving the most votes at the general election shall be elected. A candidate shall reside in the subcouncil district for which he or she is a candidate. Coordinating council members shall be elected on the nonpartisan ballot.</para><para>(2) The initial elected members shall be nominated at the statewide primary election and elected at the statewide general election immediately following the certification of the establishment of the learning community, and subsequent members shall be nominated at subsequent statewide primary elections and elected at subsequent statewide general elections. Except as provided in this section, such elections shall be conducted pursuant to the Election Act.</para><para>(3) Vacancies in office for elected members shall occur as set forth in section 32-560. Whenever any such vacancy occurs, the remaining elected members of such council shall appoint an individual residing within the geographical boundaries of the subcouncil district for the balance of the unexpired term.</para><para>(4) Members elected to represent odd-numbered districts in the first election for the learning community coordinating council shall be elected for two-year terms. Members elected to represent even-numbered districts in the first election for the learning community coordinating council shall be elected for four-year terms. Members elected in subsequent elections shall be elected for four-year terms and until their successors are elected and qualified.</para><para>(5) The appointed members shall be appointed in November of each even-numbered year through 2014 after the general election. Appointed members shall be school board members of school districts in the learning community either elected to take office the following January or continuing their current term of office for the following two years. For learning communities to be established prior to July 21, 2016, pursuant to orders issued pursuant to section 79-2102, the Secretary of State shall hold a meeting of the school board members of the school districts in such learning community to appoint one member from such school boards to represent each of the subcouncil districts on the coordinating council of such learning community. For subsequent appointments, the current appointed members of the coordinating council shall hold a meeting of the school board members of such school districts to appoint one member from such school boards to represent each of the subcouncil districts on the coordinating council of the learning community. The appointed members shall be selected by the school board members of the school districts in the learning community who reside in the subcouncil district to be represented pursuant to a secret ballot, shall reside in the subcouncil district to be represented, and shall be appointed for two-year terms and until their successors are appointed and qualified.</para><para>(6) Vacancies in office for appointed members shall occur upon the resignation, death, or disqualification from office of an appointed member. Disqualification from office shall include ceasing membership on the school board for which membership qualified the member for the appointment to the learning community coordinating council or ceasing to reside in the subcouncil district represented by such member of the learning community coordinating council. Whenever such vacancy occurs, the remaining appointed members shall hold a meeting of the school board members of the school districts in such learning community to appoint a member from such school boards who lives in the subcouncil district to be represented to serve for the balance of the unexpired term.</para><para>(7) Through January 4, 2017, each learning community coordinating council shall also have a nonvoting member from each member school district which does not have either an elected or an appointed member who resides in the school district on the council. Such nonvoting members shall be appointed by the school board of the school district to be represented to serve for two-year terms, and notice of the nonvoting member selected shall be submitted to the Secretary of State by such board prior to December 31 of each even-numbered year through 2014. Each such nonvoting member shall be a resident of the appointing school district and shall not be a school administrator employed by such school district. Whenever a vacancy occurs, the school board of such school district shall appoint a new nonvoting member and submit notice to the Secretary of State and to the learning community coordinating council.</para><para>(8) Members of a learning community coordinating council shall take office on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January following their election, except that members appointed to fill vacancies shall take office immediately following administration of the oath of office. Each voting member shall be eligible for reimbursement of reasonable expenses related to service on the learning community coordinating council. Each nonvoting member shall be eligible for reimbursement of reasonable expenses related to service on the learning community coordinating council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB937, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>