<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id152"><amendatorysection statutenumber="32-613.01" chaptername="Elections"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>32-613.01</statuteno><catchline>President; nominating petition; form.</catchline><para>In addition to the requirements of section 32-613, the form of a petition for partisan candidates for President of the United States shall be substantially as follows:</para><para>Petition for Office of President of the United States</para><para>Name of Candidate: ............</para><para>Residence Address: ............</para><para>City, State, and Zip Code: ............</para><para>Party Affiliation: ............</para><para>To the Honorable ............, Secretary of State for the State of Nebraska:</para><para>We, the undersigned residents of the State of Nebraska and the county of ............, respectfully demand that the above-named candidate be placed on the ballot at the primary election to be held on the .... day of ......... 20...., and each for himself or herself says:</para><para>I have personally signed this petition on the date opposite my name;</para><para>I am a registered voter of the State of Nebraska and the county of ............ and am qualified to sign this petition and am affiliated with the appropriate political party or I will be so registered, qualified, and affiliated on or before the date on which this petition is filed with the Secretary of State; and</para><para>My printed name, date of birth, street and number or voting precinct, and city, village, or post office address are correctly written after my signature.</para><para>(Here follow numbered lines for signature, printed name, date of birth, date, street and number or voting precinct, and city, village, or post office address.)</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB521, &#167; 40. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>