<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-620"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>32-620</statuteno><catchline>President and Vice President; candidates;
certification; new political party; how treated; requirements; nonpartisan status; filing; application; contents.</catchline>
<para>(1) Partisan
candidates for the offices of President and Vice President of the United States
on the general election ballot shall be certified to the Governor and Secretary
of State by the national nominating convention as provided by law.</para>
<para>(2) Candidates for the offices
of President and Vice President of the United States of newly established
political parties may obtain general election ballot position by filing with
the Secretary of State an application containing:</para>
<para>(a) The name or names to be printed on the ballot;</para>
<para>(b) The name of the political party;</para>
<para>(c) The written consent of the designated vice-presidential candidate
to have his or her name printed on the ballot; and</para>
<para>(d) The names and addresses of the persons who will represent the applicant
as presidential elector candidates together with the written consent of such
persons to become candidates.</para>
<para>(3) Candidates for the
offices of President and Vice President of the United States of nonpartisan
status may obtain general election ballot position by filing with the Secretary
of State:</para><para>(a)
An application containing:</para><para>(i) The name or names to be printed on the ballot;</para>
<para>(ii) The status of the
candidacy as nonpartisan;</para><para>(iii)
The written consent of the designated vice-presidential candidate to have
his or her name printed on the ballot; and</para><para>(iv) The names and addresses of the persons who will
represent the applicant as presidential elector candidates together with the
written consent of such persons to become candidates; and</para>
<para>(b) A petition signed by not
less than two thousand five hundred registered voters. Such petitions shall
conform to the requirements of section 32-628 and shall be
filed with the Secretary of State by August 1 in the year of the presidential
general election.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 188; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB349, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>This statute is unconstitutional as relates to requirements for independent candidates for President and Vice President of United States. MacBride v. Exon, 558 F.2d 443 (8th Cir. 1977).</para><para>Although Nebraska's statutes unconstitutionally deny an independent candidate access to appear on the ballot in presidential elections, the court directed the independent be included upon a determination he was a serious candidate, truly independent, with a satisfactory level of community support. McCarthy v. Exon, 424 F.Supp. 1143 (D. Neb. 1976).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>