<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">32-604</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Multiple office
holding; when allowed.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in
subsection (2) or (4) of this section, no person shall be precluded from being
elected or appointed to or holding an elective office for the reason that
he or she has been elected or appointed to or holds another elective office.</para>
<para>(2) No person serving as a member of the Legislature or in
an elective office described in Article IV, section 1 or 20, or Article VII,
section 3 or 10, of the Constitution of Nebraska shall simultaneously serve
in any other elective office, except that such a person may simultaneously
serve in another elective office which is filled at an election held in conjunction
with the annual meeting of a public body.</para>
<para>(3) Whenever an incumbent serving as a member of the Legislature
or in an elective office described in Article IV, section 1 or 20, or Article
VII, section 3 or 10, of the Constitution of Nebraska assumes another elective
office, except an elective office filled at an election held in conjunction
with the annual meeting of a public body, the office first held by the incumbent
shall be deemed vacant.</para>
<para>(4) No person serving in a high elective office shall simultaneously
serve in any other high elective office, except that a county attorney may
serve as the county attorney for more than one county if appointed under subsection
(2) of section 23-1201.01.</para>
<para>(5) Notwithstanding subsection (4)
of this section, any person holding more than one high elective office upon July 15, 2010, shall be entitled
to serve the remainder of all terms for which he or she was elected or appointed.</para>
<para>(6) For purposes of this section, (a) elective office has
the meaning found in section 32-109 and includes an office which is filled
at an election held in conjunction with the annual meeting of a public body
created by an act of the Legislature but does not include a member of a learning
community coordinating council appointed pursuant to subsection (5) or (7)
of section 32-546.01 and (b) high elective office means a member of the Legislature,
an elective office described in Article IV, section 1 or 20, or Article VII,
section 3 or 10, of the Constitution of Nebraska, or a county, city, community college area, learning
community, or school district elective office.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 172; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 221, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 84, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB951, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>