<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-211</statuteno><catchline>Election commissioner; counties having 20,000 to 100,000 inhabitants; chief deputy; appointment; qualifications; terms; vacancy; elimination of office.</catchline><para>The office of election commissioner may be created for each county having a population of not less than twenty thousand nor more than one hundred thousand inhabitants. Such office may be created by resolution of the county board establishing such office, and the election commissioner shall be appointed by the county board. The appointment of a chief deputy election commissioner shall be at the option of the county board. If a chief deputy election commissioner is appointed, he or she shall be a member of a different political party than the election commissioner. The election commissioner and chief deputy election commissioner shall be registered voters, residents of such county for at least one year, and of good moral character and integrity and capacity. The election commissioner and chief deputy election commissioner shall serve for terms of four years from the date of their initial appointment or until their successors have been appointed and qualified. The county board may by resolution eliminate the office of election commissioner at the end of a term or upon a vacancy in the office. The county board shall not appoint any county official who is serving an elected term to the office of election commissioner or chief deputy election commissioner. If a vacancy occurs in either office, the county board shall appoint an election commissioner or chief deputy election commissioner to serve for the unexpired term.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 226, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>