<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-913"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>32-913</statuteno><catchline>Precinct list of registered voters; sign-in register; preparation and use.</catchline><para>(1) The clerks of election shall have a list of registered voters of the precinct and a sign-in register at the polling place on election day. The list of registered voters shall be used for guidance on election day and may be in the form of a computerized, typed, or handwritten list or precinct registration cards. Registered voters of the precinct shall place and record their signature in the sign-in register before receiving any ballot. The list of registered voters and the sign-in register may be combined into one document at the discretion of the election commissioner or county clerk including, beginning July 1, 2019, by the use of an electronic poll book. If a combined document is used, a clerk of election may list the names of the registered voters in a separate book in the order in which they voted.</para><para>(2) Within twenty-four hours after the polls close in the precinct, the precinct inspector or one of the judges of election shall deliver the precinct list of registered voters and the precinct sign-in register to the election commissioner or county clerk. The election commissioner or county clerk shall file and preserve the list and register. No member of a receiving board who has custody or charge of the precinct list of registered voters and the precinct sign-in register shall permit the list or register to leave his or her possession from the time of receipt until he or she delivers them to another member of the receiving board or to the precinct inspector or judge of election for delivery to the election commissioner or county clerk.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 256; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 358, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB44, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1065, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>