<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-603"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-603</statuteno><catchline>Candidacy for two or more elected offices at same election; prohibited; exception; filing officer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) No candidate for member of the Legislature or an elective office described in Article IV, section 1 or 20, or Article VII, section 3 or 10, of the Constitution of Nebraska shall be eligible to file as a candidate, to petition on the ballot as a candidate, to accept a nomination by a political party or by party convention, caucus, or committee to fill a vacancy, or to be a declared write-in candidate for more than one elective office to be filled at the same election except for the position of delegate to a county, state, or national political party convention. No candidate for any other high elective office as defined in subsection (6) of section 32-604 shall be eligible to file as a candidate, to petition on the ballot as a candidate, to accept a nomination by a political party or by party convention, caucus, or committee to fill a vacancy, or to be a declared write-in candidate for more than one high elective office to be filled at the same election. Any such person who has filed for a high elective office shall withdraw such filing prior to filing for any other elective office to be filled at the same election except for the position of delegate to a county, state, or national political party convention. Any such person who has won a nomination in a primary election and who is nominated to any additional offices by a write-in vote or by a political party convention or committee shall decline one of the nominations pursuant to section 32-623 and shall do so within seven days after receiving any subsequent nomination. If the candidate fails to take such action, any subsequent nomination shall be declared void. Any filing made in violation of this section shall be void, and the Secretary of State, election commissioner, or county clerk shall not place the name of any person on the ballot for any office for which such person filed in violation of this section.</para><para>(2) If a filing officer determines that a candidate has filed for more than one office in violation of subsection (1) of this section, the filing officer shall notify the Secretary of State, the Secretary of State shall determine the order of the filings and notify the candidate that the subsequent filing is invalid, and the candidate's name shall not be printed on the ballot for such office. The Secretary of State shall notify the filing officers of the counties involved of the action taken on such subsequent filing.</para><para>(3) When the name of a candidate appears on the ballot for more than one office during an election in violation of subsection (1) of this section, the filing officer when possible shall correct the error by removing the candidate's name from the ballot and reprinting corrected ballots. When it is not possible to print a corrected set of ballots in time for the election, all votes cast for such candidate as a candidate for the subsequent office appearing on the ballot shall not be counted, and no certificate of nomination or election shall be issued to such candidate for such subsequent office.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 171; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 221, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>If an individual files to run for two offices in the same general election contrary to the provisions of this section, the second filing by inference withdraws the first. State ex rel. Chambers v. Beermann, 229 Neb. 696, 428 N.W.2d 883 (1988).</para><para>This section applies to general, not primary, elections. State ex rel. Chambers v. Beermann, 229 Neb. 696, 428 N.W.2d 883 (1988).</para><para>This section prohibits an individual from running for reelection to the Nebraska Legislature and for the U.S. Senate in the same general election. State ex rel. Chambers v. Beermann, 229 Neb. 696, 428 N.W.2d 883 (1988).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>