<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-529"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-529</statuteno><catchline>County board of supervisors; districts; terms; qualifications; partisan ballot.</catchline><para>At the first general election after the adoption of township organization by a county, one supervisor shall be elected in each supervisor district. Thereafter one supervisor shall be elected in each odd-numbered supervisor district at the general election two years after the first general election and each four years thereafter, and one supervisor shall be elected in each even-numbered supervisor district at the general election four years after the first general election and each four years thereafter. Each county supervisor shall be nominated and elected by the registered voters of the district from which he or she is elected. Except for supervisors first elected after the county has adopted township organization, the term of each county supervisor shall be four years or until his or her successor is elected and qualified. The county supervisors shall meet the qualifications found in section 23-268. The county supervisors shall be elected on the partisan ballot.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 125. </para></source><annotation><para>County supervisors are elected for four years, but have staggered terms of office. Foote v. County of Adams, 163 Neb. 406, 80 N.W.2d 179 (1956).</para><para>The 1891 amendment to the election laws did not repeal or change the laws relating to the election of township officers or temporary organization, but merely provided for future elections. Albert v. Twohig, 35 Neb. 563, 53 N.W. 582 (1892).</para><para>This section, as enacted in 1879, referred to the first general election after the adoption of township organization at which the county officers named were to be elected. State ex rel. Crossley v. Hedlund, 16 Neb. 566, 20 N.W. 876 (1884).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>