<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id19" statutenumber="32-305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>32-305</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Deputy registrar;
application; training; when; oath; violation; effect.</catchline><para>(1)
Any registered voter may apply to the election commissioner or county clerk
to be appointed as a deputy registrar for the purpose of registering voters.
The application form shall be prescribed by the election commissioner, county
clerk, or Secretary of State. The
election commissioner or county clerk shall make training available for deputy
registrars in the county he or she serves. The deputy registrar
shall notify the election commissioner or county clerk of the location and
time of proposed voter registration and the names and party affiliations of
the deputy registrars. The election commissioner or county clerk,
at his or her discretion, may approve or disapprove the deputy registrar's
plans for voter registration and shall notify the deputy registrar of such
decision.</para>
<para>(2) Any person appointed as a deputy registrar shall attend
a training session conducted by an election commissioner or county clerk.
A person who attends and successfully completes a training session after January
1, 1995, shall be qualified as a deputy registrar for any county in the state
and shall receive a certificate verifying successful completion of the training
and indicating his or her qualification as a deputy registrar to conduct registration
in any county in the state.</para>
<para>(3) Before entering upon his or her duties, the deputy registrar
shall take and subscribe to the following oath:</para>
<para>You do solemnly swear that you will support the Constitution
of the United States and the Constitution of Nebraska and will faithfully
and impartially perform the duties of the office of deputy registrar according
to law and to the best of your ability.</para>
<para>(4) In
order to remain qualified to conduct voter registration as a deputy registrar
in any county in this state, a deputy registrar shall complete a training
session at least once every three years unless the Secretary of
State determines that substantial changes have occurred in the voter registration
process requiring additional training. The training session may vary in length
but shall not exceed four hours. The Secretary of State shall inspect and
review all training programs, procedures, and practices to assure that they
relate to the position of a deputy registrar and his or her duties.</para>
<para>(5) Any deputy registrar who violates any registration procedure,
rule, regulation, or guideline may have his or her status as a deputy registrar
revoked by the election commissioner, county clerk, or Secretary of State.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
