<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-704"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-704</statuteno><catchline>Candidates; delegate or alternate
delegate to national convention; filing form; contents; Secretary of State;
duties.</catchline><para>Any
person seeking to be elected as a delegate or alternate delegate to the national
convention of a political party shall submit a filing form under this section
regardless of the method of election used by the political party. The
filing form for nomination of a candidate for election as a delegate or alternate delegate to the
national convention of a political party shall (1) contain a statement of commitment to a candidate for
the office of President of the United States or that he or she is uncommitted,
(2) include a pledge swearing to support the candidate for
President of the United States to which the candidate for delegate or alternate
delegate to the national convention is committed until (a) such
candidate receives less than thirty-five percent of the votes for nomination
by such convention or releases the delegate from such commitment or
(b) two convention nominating ballots have been taken, and (3) be filed with
the Secretary of State. No filing form for nomination shall be accepted unless
signed by the candidate. The Secretary of State shall prescribe the filing
form for nomination.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 204; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1048, &#167; 8.</para></source><annotation><para>The expression of a preference for President by those voting at primary election does not control presidential electors, and is only morally binding on delegates to national party conventions. State ex rel. Nebraska Rep. State C. Com. v. Wait, 92 Neb. 313, 138 N.W. 159 (1912), 43 L.R.A.N.S. 282 (1912).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>