<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id19"  statutenumber="32-304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>32-304</statuteno><catchline>Registration of electors electronically; application process; application; contents; Secretary of State; Department of Motor Vehicles; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Secretary of State in conjunction with the Department of Motor Vehicles shall implement a registration application process which may be used statewide to register to vote and update voter registration records electronically using the Secretary of State's web site. An applicant who has a valid Nebraska motor vehicle operator's license or state identification card may use the application process to register to vote or to update his or her voter registration record with changes in his or her personal information or other information related to his or her eligibility to vote. For each electronic application, the Secretary of State shall obtain a copy of the electronic representation of the applicant's signature from the Department of Motor Vehicles' records of his or her motor vehicle operator's license or state identification card for purposes of voter registration and electronic poll books.</para><para>(2) The application shall contain substantially all the information provided in section 32-312 and the following informational statements:</para><para>(a) An applicant who submits this application electronically is affirming that the information in the application is true. Any applicant who submits this application electronically knowing that any of the information in the application is false shall be guilty of a Class IV felony under section 32-1502 of the statutes of Nebraska. The penalty for a Class IV felony is up to two years imprisonment and twelve months post-release supervision, a fine of up to ten thousand dollars, or both;</para><para>(b) An applicant who submits this application electronically is agreeing to the use of his or her digital signature from the Department of Motor Vehicles' records of his or her motor vehicle operator's license or state identification card for purposes of voter registration;</para><para>(c) To vote at the polling place on election day, the completed application must be submitted on or before the third Friday before the election and prior to midnight on such Friday; and</para><para>(d) The election commissioner or county clerk will, upon receipt of the application for registration, send an acknowledgment of registration to the applicant indicating whether the application is proper or not.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB661, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1038, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1065, &#167; 4. </para><note>Changes made by LB1038 became effective April 18, 2018. Changes made by LB1065 became operative July 1, 2019.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>