<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-553"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-553</statuteno><catchline>Political subdivision; redistrict; when; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) When any political subdivision except a public power district nominates or elects members of the governing board by districts, such districts shall be substantially equal in population as determined by the most recent federal decennial census. Any such political subdivision which has districts in place on the date the census figures used in drawing district boundaries for the Legislature are required to be submitted to the state by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, shall, if necessary to maintain substantial population equality as required by this subsection, have new district boundaries drawn within six months after the passage and approval of the legislative bill providing for reestablishing legislative districts. Any such political subdivision in existence on the date the census figures used in drawing district boundaries for the Legislature are required to be submitted to the state by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, and which has not established any district boundaries shall establish district boundaries pursuant to this section within six months after such date. If the deadline for drawing or redrawing district boundary lines imposed by this section is not met, the procedures set forth in section 32-555 shall be followed.</para><para>(2) The governing board of each such political subdivision shall be responsible for drawing its own district boundaries and shall, as nearly as possible, follow the precinct lines created by the election commissioner or county clerk after each federal decennial census, except that the election commissioner of any county in which a Class IV or V school district is located shall draw district boundaries for such school district as provided in this section and section 32-552.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 595, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 71, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>This section does not limit redrawing of district boundaries to only once every 10 years. Chambers v. Lautenbaugh, 263 Neb. 920, 644 N.W.2d 540 (2002).</para><para>Read together, section 32-552 and this section authorize an election commissioner to draw or adjust the boundaries of school districts following a federal decennial census only as is necessary to maintain substantial population equality within the districts. Section 32-552 and this section do not authorize an election commissioner to take into account political considerations when adjusting boundaries following a federal decennial census. State ex rel. Steinke v. Lautenbaugh, 263 Neb. 652, 642 N.W.2d 132 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>