<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-331"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-331</statuteno><catchline>Confidential records; procedure.</catchline><para>A registered voter may file an affidavit with the election commissioner or county clerk to have the information relating to his or her name, residence address, and telephone number remain confidential. If the registered voter is a program participant under the Address Confidentiality Act, the affidavit shall state that fact. If the registered voter is not a program participant under the act, the affidavit shall state that the county court or district court has issued an order upon a showing of good cause that a life-threatening circumstance exists in relation to the voter or a member of his or her household. The registered voter shall vote under sections 32-938 to 32-951 in elections held after the filing of the affidavit. To terminate the affidavit and withdraw the confidential designation, the registered voter shall notify the election commissioner or county clerk in writing. The registered voter shall provide a valid mailing address to be used in place of the residence address for election, research, and government purposes. If the registered voter is a program participant under the Address Confidentiality Act, the mailing address shall be as provided in the act. The election commissioner or county clerk may use the mailing address or the word "confidential" or a similar designation in place of the residence address in producing any list, roster, or register required under the Election Act. Those records declared confidential under this section shall be kept in a separate file from the other registered voter information. A county, election commissioner, or county clerk shall be liable in an action for negligence as a result of the disclosure of the confidential information if there is a showing of gross negligence or willfulness.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 514, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 228, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Address Confidentiality Act,</emphasis> see section 42-1201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>