<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-606"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-606</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Candidate filing form; filing period.</catchline><para>(1) Any candidate may place his or her name on the primary election ballot by filing a candidate filing form prescribed by the Secretary of State as provided in section 32-607. Except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section, if a candidate for an elective office is an incumbent of any elective office, the filing period for filing the candidate filing form shall be between January 5 and February 15 prior to the date of the primary election. No incumbent who resigns from elective office prior to the expiration of his or her term shall file for any office after February 15 of that election year. All other candidates shall file for office between January 5 and March 1 prior to the date of the primary election. A candidate filing form and a copy of payment of the filing fee, if applicable, may be transmitted by facsimile for the offices listed in subdivision (1) of section 32-607 if (a) the transmission is received in the office of the filing officer by the filing deadline and (b) the original filing form and payment of the filing fee, if applicable, is mailed to the filing officer with a legible postmark bearing a date on or prior to the filing deadline and is in the office of the filing officer no later than seven days after the filing deadline.</para><para>(2) Any candidate for a township office in a county under township organization, the board of trustees of a village, the board of directors of a reclamation district, the county weed district board, the board of directors of a public power district receiving annual gross revenue of less than forty million dollars, or the board of an educational service unit may place his or her name on the general election ballot by filing a candidate filing form prescribed by the Secretary of State as provided in section 32-607. Except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section, if a candidate for an elective office is an incumbent of any elective office, the filing period for filing the candidate filing form shall be between January 5 and July 15 prior to the date of the general election. No incumbent who resigns from elective office prior to the expiration of his or her term shall file for any office after July 15 of that election year. All other candidates shall file for office between January 5 and August 1 prior to the date of the general election. A candidate filing form may be transmitted by facsimile for the offices listed in subdivision (1) of section 32-607 if (a) the transmission is received in the office of the filing officer by the filing deadline and (b) the original filing form is mailed to the filing officer with a legible postmark bearing a date on or prior to the filing deadline and is in the office of the filing officer no later than seven days after the filing deadline.</para><para>(3) Any city having a home rule charter may provide for filing deadlines for any person desiring to be a candidate for the office of council member or mayor.</para><para>(4) If a candidate for an elective office was appointed to an elective office to fill a vacancy after the deadline for an incumbent to file a candidate filing form in subsection (1) or (2) of this section but before the deadline for all other candidates, the candidate may file a candidate filing form for any office on or before the deadline for all other candidates.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 967, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 802, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB550, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB125, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1055, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB285, &#167; 10. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former act candidate was required to file not less than forty days before the primary election. Fitzgerald v. Kuppinger, 163 Neb. 286, 79 N.W.2d 547 (1956).</para><para>City councilman could file for office of member of Legislature within time herein prescribed. State ex rel. Strom v. Marsh, 162 Neb. 593, 77 N.W.2d 163 (1956).</para><para>Under the statute, a candidate's nominating papers must be actually received and filed in the proper office before the time for filing has expired. State ex rel. Wood v. Marsh, 120 Neb. 296, 232 N.W. 103 (1930).</para><para>Under former law this section required that all nominating papers be filed at least forty days before the primary election, and the time for filing cannot be extended by custom or practice so as to include nominating papers postmarked before but not received until after the time for filing had expired. State ex rel. Smith v. Marsh, 120 Neb. 287, 232 N.W. 99 (1930), 72 A.L.R. 285 (1930).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>