<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-949"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-949</statuteno><catchline>Ballot for early voting; registered voter; duties.</catchline><para>(1) After a ballot for early voting is received by a voter and before placing any marks thereon, the voter shall note whether there are any voting marks on the ballot and whether there is a signature or initials on the ballot in the space provided for the election official's signature or initials. If there are any voting marks or no signature or initials, the ballot shall be returned immediately to the election commissioner or county clerk. If there are no such marks, the voter shall cause the ballot to be marked. If the ballot is voted in the office of the election commissioner or county clerk, the registered voter shall return the ballot and identification envelope to the election commissioner or county clerk or an employee of the election commissioner or county clerk who shall deposit the ballot into a ballot box and place the identification envelope in a secure container.</para><para>(2) If the voter is mailing or otherwise delivering the ballot to the election commissioner or county clerk, the voter shall:</para><para>(a) Place the marked ballot in the identification envelope received for that purpose in such a manner that the signature of the issuing officer on the ballot is visible;</para><para>(b) Complete and sign the voter's oath on the outside of the identification envelope under the penalty of election falsification;</para><para>(c) Enclose, in the identification envelope or separately in the return envelope if one has been provided, his or her completed registration application if one was provided pursuant to section 32-945 or 32-946, a copy of his or her identification document if such identification has been requested, and the oath completed and signed by a voter without a residence address if required pursuant to section 32-946;</para><para>(d) Ensure that the identification envelope or return envelope is sealed; and</para><para>(e) Mail, deliver, or cause to be delivered the envelope containing the ballots and any required materials to the election commissioner or county clerk from whom it was received.</para><para>(3) All postage costs related to returning such ballots and required materials, if any, to the election commissioner or county clerk shall be paid by the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 292; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 50. </para></source></law></legaldoc>