<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-223"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>32-223</statuteno><catchline>Receiving board; members; requirements; inspectors; clerk of election; appointment.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in the Election Act, the election commissioner shall appoint a precinct inspector and a receiving board to consist of at least two judges and two clerks of election for each precinct. The election commissioner may appoint district inspectors to aid the election commissioner in the performance of his or her duties and supervise a group of precincts on election day.</para><para>(2) The election commissioner may allow persons serving on a receiving board as judges and clerks of election and precinct inspectors to serve for part of the time the polls are open and appoint other judges and clerks of election and precinct inspectors to serve on the same receiving board for the remainder of the time the polls are open.</para><para>(3) On each receiving board at any one time, one judge and one clerk of election shall be registered voters of the political party casting the highest number of votes in the county for Governor or for President of the United States in the immediately preceding general election, and one judge and one clerk of election shall be registered voters of the political party casting the next highest number of votes in the county for Governor or for President of the United States in the immediately preceding general election, except that one judge or clerk of election may be a registered voter who is not affiliated with either of such parties. If a third judge is appointed, such judge shall be a registered voter of the political party casting the highest number of votes in the county for Governor or for President of the United States in the immediately preceding general election. All precinct and district inspectors shall be divided between all political parties as nearly as practicable in proportion to the number of votes cast in such county at the immediately preceding general election for Governor or for President of the United States by the parties, respectively.</para><para>(4) The election commissioner may appoint a person who is at least sixteen years old but is not eligible to register to vote as a clerk of election. Such clerk of election shall meet the requirements of subsection (3) of section 32-221, except that such clerk shall not be required to be a registered voter. No more than one clerk of election appointed under this subsection shall serve at any precinct. A clerk of election appointed under this subsection shall be considered a registered voter who is not affiliated with a political party for purposes of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1054, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 357, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 358, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 32. </para><operativedate>September 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>