<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="32-939.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>32-939.02</statuteno><catchline>Person residing outside the country; ballot for early voting; request; use of Federal Post Card Application or personal letter; special ballot; use of Federal Write-In Absentee Ballot; Secretary of State; duties; oath.</catchline><para>(1) Upon request for a ballot, a ballot for early voting shall be forwarded to each voter meeting the criteria of section 32-939 at least forty-five days prior to any election.</para><para>(2) An omission of required information, except the political party affiliation of the applicant, may prevent the processing of an application for and mailing of ballots. The request for any ballots and a registration application shall be sent to the election commissioner or county clerk of the county of the applicant's residence. The request may be sent at any time in the same calendar year as the election, except that the request shall be received by the election commissioner or county clerk not later than the third Friday preceding an election to vote in that election. If an applicant fails to indicate his or her political party affiliation on the application, the applicant shall be registered as nonpartisan.</para><para>(3) A person described in section 32-939 may register to vote through the use of the Federal Post Card Application or a personal letter which includes the same information as appears on the Federal Post Card Application and may simultaneously make application for ballots for all elections in a calendar year. The person may indicate a preference for ballots and other election materials to be delivered via facsimile transmission or electronic mail by indicating such preference on the Federal Post Card Application. If the person indicates such a preference, the election commissioner or county clerk shall accommodate the voter's preference.</para><para>(4) If the ballot for early voting has not been printed in sufficient time to meet the request and special requirements of a voter meeting the criteria of section 32-939, the election commissioner or county clerk may issue a special ballot at least sixty days prior to an election to such a voter upon a written request by such voter requesting the special ballot. For purposes of this subsection, a special ballot means a ballot prescribed by the Secretary of State which contains the titles of all offices being contested at such election and permits the voter to vote by writing in the names of the specific candidates or the decision on any issue. The election commissioner or county clerk shall include with the special ballot a complete list of the nominated candidates and issues to be voted upon by the voter which are known at the time of the voter's request.</para><para>(5) Any person meeting the criteria in section 32-939 may cast a ballot by the use of the Federal Write-In Absentee Ballot. The Federal Write-In Absentee Ballot may be used for all elections. If a person casting a ballot using the Federal Write-In Absentee Ballot is not a registered voter, the information submitted in the Federal Write-In Absentee Ballot transmission envelope shall be treated as a voter registration application.</para><para>(6)(a) Any person requesting a ballot under this section may receive and return the ballot and the oath prescribed in subdivision (b) of this subsection using any method of transmission authorized by the Secretary of State.</para><para>(b) An oath shall be delivered with the ballot and shall be in a form substantially as follows:</para><para>VOTER'S OATH</para><para>I, the undersigned voter, declare that the ballot or ballots contained no voting marks of any kind when I received them, and I caused the ballot or ballots to be marked.</para><para>To the best of my knowledge and belief, I declare under penalty of election falsification that:</para><para>(a) I, .................., am a registered voter in .................. County;</para><para>(b) I have voted the ballot and am returning it in compliance with Nebraska law; and</para><para>(c) I have not voted and will not vote in this election except by this ballot.</para><para>ANY PERSON WHO SIGNS THIS FORM KNOWING THAT ANY OF THE INFORMATION IN THE FORM IS FALSE SHALL BE GUILTY OF ELECTION FALSIFICATION, A CLASS IV FELONY UNDER SECTION 32-1502 OF THE STATUTES OF NEBRASKA. THE PENALTY FOR ELECTION FALSIFICATION IS IMPRISONMENT FOR UP TO TWO YEARS AND TWELVE MONTHS POST-RELEASE SUPERVISION OR A FINE NOT TO EXCEED TEN THOUSAND DOLLARS, OR BOTH.</para><para>I also understand that failure to sign below will invalidate my ballot.</para><para>Signature ........................................</para><para>(7) The Secretary of State shall develop a process for a person casting a ballot under this section to check the status of his or her ballot via the Internet or a toll-free telephone call.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB951, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>