<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id92">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id94" statutenumber="32-325"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>32-325</statuteno><catchline id="id97">Update of voter
registration record; deadline; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A registration
application completed and signed by a registered voter seeking to update his
or her voter registration record shall be completed in person at or delivered
or mailed to the office of the election commissioner or county clerk or submitted pursuant to section 32-304
to the Secretary of State. To avoid additional requirements at
the polling place pursuant to section 32-914.01, 32-914.02, or 32-915, an
application to update a voter registration record must be:</para>
<para>(a) Completed or delivered by the applicant in person at the
office of the election commissioner or county clerk on or before the deadline
prescribed in section 32-302; or</para>
<para>(b) Delivered by a personal messenger or personal agent, submitted pursuant to section 32-304, or
mailed so that it is received by the election commissioner or county clerk
on or before the deadline prescribed in section 32-321.</para>
<para>(2) After verifying the signature on the previous registration
of the registered voter, the election commissioner or county clerk shall make
the change of name, party affiliation, or address on all pertinent election
records. The election commissioner or county clerk shall send an acknowledgment
card to the registered voter indicating that the change of registration has
been completed and shall include the address of the registered voter's new
polling place.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB661, &#167; 12.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>