<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id225"><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-622.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-622.01</statuteno><catchline>Candidate; name change; documentation required; objection; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who has filed for elective office pursuant to subsection (1) of section 32-606 whose legal name has changed since filing may change the name to appear on the ballot to reflect the person's changed legal name by March 1 before the primary election. The candidate shall provide any documentation verifying the legal name change to the filing officer by March 1.</para><para>(2) Any person who has filed for elective office pursuant to subsection (2) of section 32-606 or a nominee for elective office for the general election whose legal name has changed since filing may change the name to appear on the ballot to reflect the person's changed legal name by September 1 before the general election. The candidate shall provide any documentation verifying the legal name change to the filing officer by September 1.</para><para>(3) Any objection to a name change pursuant to subsection (1) or (2) of this section may be made and passed upon in the same manner as an objection to a candidate filing form pursuant to section 32-624, except that any objection pursuant to this subsection shall be made within seven days after the documentation verifying the legal name change is provided to the filing officer.</para><para>(4) Any candidate may file a name change on or before the filing deadline, and such name change shall conform to the requirements of subdivision (1)(b) of section 32-607. Any objection to a name change pursuant to this subsection may be made pursuant to subsection (3) of section 32-607.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 30. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>