<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-221"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-221</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Inspectors and judges and clerks of election; appointment; term; qualifications; vacancy; failure to appear; removal.</catchline><para>(1) The election commissioner shall appoint precinct and district inspectors, judges of election, and clerks of election to assist the election commissioner in conducting elections on election day. In counties with a population of less than four hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census, judges and clerks of election and inspectors shall be appointed at least thirty days prior to the statewide primary election, shall hold office for terms of two years or until their successors are appointed and qualified for the next statewide primary election, and shall serve at all elections in the county during their terms of office. In counties with a population of four hundred thousand or more inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census, judges and clerks of election shall be appointed at least thirty days prior to the first election for which appointments are necessary and shall serve for at least four elections.</para><para>(2) Judges and clerks of election may be selected at random from a cross section of the population of the county. All qualified citizens shall have the opportunity to be considered for service. All qualified citizens shall fulfill their obligation to serve as judges or clerks of election as prescribed by the election commissioner. No citizen shall be excluded from service as a result of discrimination based upon race, color, religion, sex, national origin, or economic status. No citizen shall be excluded from service unless excused by reason of ill health or other good and sufficient reason.</para><para>(3) All persons appointed shall be of good repute and character, be able to read and write the English language, and except as otherwise provided in subsections (4), (5), and (6) of section 32-223, be registered voters in the county. No candidate at an election shall be appointed as a judge or clerk of election or inspector for such election other than a candidate for delegate to a county, state, or national political party convention.</para><para>(4) If a vacancy occurs in the office of judge or clerk of election or inspector, the election commissioner shall fill such vacancy in accordance with section 32-223. If any judge or clerk of election or inspector fails to appear at the hour appointed for the opening of the polls, the remaining officers shall notify the election commissioner, select a registered voter to serve in place of the absent officer if so directed by the election commissioner, and proceed to conduct the election. If the election commissioner finds that a judge or clerk of election or inspector does not possess all the qualifications prescribed in this section or if any judge or clerk of election or inspector is guilty of neglecting the duties of the office or of any official misconduct, the election commissioner shall remove the person and fill the vacancy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 357, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB742, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 12. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>