<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-610"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-610</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Partisan elections; candidate; requirements.</catchline><para>No person shall be allowed to file a candidate filing form as a partisan candidate or to have his or her name placed upon a primary election ballot of a political party if subsection (2) of section 32-720 applies to the political party. For any other political party, no person shall be allowed to file a candidate filing form as a partisan candidate or to have his or her name placed upon a primary election ballot of a political party unless (1) he or she is a registered voter of the political party if required pursuant to section 32-702 and (2)(a) the political party has at least ten thousand persons affiliated as indicated by voter registration records in Nebraska or (b) at one of the two immediately preceding statewide general elections, (i) a candidate nominated by the political party polled at least five percent of the entire vote in the state in a statewide race or (ii) a combination of candidates nominated by the political party for a combination of districts that encompass all of the voters of the entire state polled at least five percent of the vote in each of their respective districts. A candidate filing form filed in violation of this section shall be void.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 178; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1035, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1048, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB34, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Names of candidates for President and Vice President cannot be placed on ballot unless appropriate action is taken by political party organized in this state. State ex rel. Beeson v. Marsh, 150 Neb. 233, 34 N.W.2d 279 (1948).</para><para>A candidate is not entitled to have his name placed upon the primary ballot unless his party polled the vote required by this section at the last election, or is a newly formed party. State ex rel. Nelson v. Marsh, 123 Neb. 423, 243 N.W. 277 (1932).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>