<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-538"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>32-538</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City with city manager plan of government; city council; members; wards; terms; change in number; procedure.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) In a city which adopts the city manager plan of government pursuant to the City Manager Plan of Government Act, the number of city council members shall be determined by the class and population of the city. In cities having one thousand or more but not more than forty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, there shall be five members, and in cities having more than forty thousand but less than two hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, there shall be seven members, except that in cities having between twenty-five thousand and forty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the city council may by ordinance provide for seven members. Council members shall be elected from the city at large unless the city council by ordinance provides for the election of all or some of its council members by wards, the number and boundaries of which are provided for in section 16-104. Council members shall serve for terms of four years or until their successors are elected and qualified. The council members shall meet the qualifications found in sections 19-613 and 19-613.01.</para><para id="id00">The first election under an ordinance changing the number of council members or their manner of election shall take place at the next regular city election. Council members whose terms of office expire after the election shall continue in office until the expiration of the terms for which they were elected and until their successors are elected and qualified. At the first election under an ordinance changing the number of council members or their manner of election, one-half or the bare majority of council members elected at large, as the case may be, who receive the highest number of votes shall serve for four years and the other or others, if needed, for two years. At such first election, one-half or the bare majority of council members, as the case may be, who are elected by wards shall serve for four years and the other or others, if needed, for two years, as provided in the ordinance. If only one council member is to be elected at large at such first election, such member shall serve for four years.</para><para id="id00">(2) Commencing with the statewide primary election in 1976, and every two years thereafter, those candidates whose terms will be expiring shall be nominated at the statewide primary election and elected at the statewide general election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 134; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 71, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 730, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 240. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate><crossreference><para><emphasis>City Manager Plan of Government Act,</emphasis> see section 19-601.</para></crossreference></source></law>
</legaldoc>