<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>32-301</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Registration list; registration of electors; registration records; how kept; use on election day.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The Secretary of State shall implement, in a uniform and nondiscriminatory manner, a single, uniform, official, centralized, interactive computerized statewide voter registration list defined, maintained, and administered at the office of the Secretary of State that contains the name and registration information of every legally registered voter in the state and assigns a unique identifier to each legally registered voter in the state. The computerized list shall serve as the single system for storing and managing the official list of registered voters throughout the state and shall comprise the voter registration register. The computerized list shall be coordinated with other agency data bases within the state and shall be available for electronic access by election commissioners and county clerks. The computerized list shall serve as the official voter registration list for the conduct of all elections under the Election Act. The Secretary of State shall provide such support as may be required so that election commissioners and county clerks are able to electronically enter voter registration information obtained by such officials on an expedited basis at the time the information is received. The Secretary of State shall provide adequate technological security measures to prevent unauthorized access to the computerized list.</para><para id="id00">(2) The election commissioner or county clerk shall provide for the registration of the electors of the county. Upon receipt of a voter registration application in his or her office from an eligible elector, the election commissioner or county clerk shall enter the information from the application in the voter registration register and may create an electronic image, photograph, microphotograph, or reproduction in an electronic digital format to be used as the voter registration record. The election commissioner or county clerk shall provide a precinct list of registered voters for each precinct for the use of judges and clerks of election in their respective precincts on election day. An electronically prepared list of registered voters in a form prescribed by the Secretary of State shall meet the requirements for a precinct list of registered voters.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 234, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 357, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>