<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-573"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>32-573</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska; vacancy; how filled.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) When a vacancy occurs in the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, the office shall be filled by the Governor. The Governor shall appoint a suitable person possessing the qualifications necessary for a member of the Board of Regents.</para><para id="id00">(2)(a) If the vacancy occurs during the first year of the term or before February 1 during a calendar year in which a statewide general election will be held, the appointee shall serve until the first Thursday following the first Tuesday in January following such general election and at such general election a member of the Board of Regents shall be elected to serve the unexpired term if any.</para><para id="id00">(b) If the vacancy occurs on or after February 1 during a calendar year in which a statewide general election will be held and if the term vacated expires on the first Thursday following the first Tuesday in January following such general election, the appointee shall serve the unexpired term.</para><para id="id00">(c) If the vacancy occurs on or after February 1 during a calendar year in which a statewide general election will be held and if the term vacated extends beyond the first Thursday following the first Tuesday in January following such general election, the appointee shall serve until the first Thursday following the first Tuesday in January following the second general election next succeeding his or her appointment and at such election a member of the Board of Regents shall be elected to serve the unexpired term if any.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 181, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>