<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id16" statutenumber="32-552"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-552</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Election districts; adjustment of boundaries; when; procedure; Class IV school district; Class V school district; election districts.</catchline><para>(1) At least five months prior to an election, the governing board of any political subdivision requesting the adjustment of the boundaries of election districts shall provide to the election commissioner or county clerk (a) written notice of the need and necessity of his or her office to perform such adjustments and (b) a revised election district boundary map that has been approved by the requesting political subdivision's governing board and subjected to all public review and challenge ordinances of the political subdivision.</para><para>(2) After each federal decennial census, the election commissioner of the county in which the greater part of a Class IV school district is situated shall, subject to review by the school board, divide the school district into seven numbered districts, substantially equal in population as determined by the most recent federal decennial census. The election commissioner shall consider the location of schools within the district and their boundaries. The election commissioner shall adjust the boundaries of the election districts, subject to final review and adjustment by the school board, to conform to changes in the territory and population of the school district and also following each federal decennial census. Except when specific procedures are otherwise provided, section 32-553 shall apply to all Class IV school districts.</para><para>(3) For purposes of election of members to the board of education of a Class V school district, such school district shall be divided into nine numbered election districts of compact and contiguous territory and of as nearly equal population as may be practical. Each election district shall be entitled to one member on the board of education of such Class V school district. After each federal decennial census, the election commissioner of the county in which the greater part of a Class V school district is situated shall divide the school district into nine numbered districts of compact and contiguous territory and of as nearly equal population as may be practical. The election commissioner shall adjust the boundaries of such districts, subject to final review and adjustment by the school board, to conform to changes in the territory of the school district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 148; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 935, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB125, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1055, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB285, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 20. </para></source><annotation><para>Read together, this section and section 32-553 authorize an election commissioner to draw or adjust the boundaries of school districts following a federal decennial census only as is necessary to maintain substantial population equality within the districts. This section and section 32-553 do not authorize an election commissioner to take into account political considerations when adjusting boundaries following a federal decennial census. State ex rel. Steinke v. Lautenbaugh, 263 Neb. 652, 642 N.W.2d 132 (2002).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>