<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-504</statuteno><catchline>Congressional districts; enumerated.</catchline><para>Based on the 2000 Census of Population by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, the State of Nebraska is hereby divided into three districts for electing Representatives in the Congress of the United States, and each district shall be entitled to elect one representative. The limits and designations of the three districts shall be as follows:</para><para>(1) The first district shall contain the counties of Richardson, Nemaha, Otoe, Cass, Johnson, Pawnee, Gage, Lancaster, Saunders, Seward, Butler, Dodge, Washington, Colfax, Madison, Burt, Stanton, Cuming, Thurston, Wayne, Dixon, and Dakota, that part of Sarpy County not included in the second district, and that part of Cedar County beginning at the intersection of the Cedar-Dixon County line and the northern boundary of Precinct 7, follow such boundary west to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from 574th Avenue, south along such line to 574th Avenue, south on 574th Avenue to 886th Road, west on 886th Road to State Highway 57, north on State Highway 57 to 887th Road, west on 887th Road to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from 570th Avenue, south along such line to 570th Avenue, south on 570th Avenue to 884th Road, west on 884th Road to 566th Avenue, south on 566th Avenue to Bow Creek, follow Bow Creek west to 883rd Road, west on 883rd Road to 564th Avenue, south on 564th Avenue to 882nd Road, south on 882nd Road to 564th Avenue, south on 564th Avenue and continuing south along a north-south line extending south from 564th Avenue to 564th Avenue, south on 564th Avenue to 870th Road, west on 870th Road to 564th Avenue, south on 564th Avenue to the Cedar-Wayne County line, east along the Cedar-Wayne County line to the Cedar-Dixon County line, and north along the Cedar-Dixon County line to the point of beginning;</para><para>(2) The second district shall contain Douglas County and that part of Sarpy County beginning at the intersection of the Douglas-Sarpy County line and South 156th Street, south on South 156th Street to Giles Road, east on Giles Road to South 132nd Street, south on South 132nd Street to State Highway 370, east on State Highway 370 to the western boundary of the Papillion-La Vista Public School District, follow such boundary south to Schram Road, east on Schram Road to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from South 120th Street, south along such line to the intersection of an east-west line extending west from Maass Road, east along such line to South 114th Street, north on South 114th Street to Schram Road, east on Schram Road to the southern corporate limits of the city of Papillion, follow the southern corporate limits of the city of Papillion east to State Highway 370, east on State Highway 370 to South 72nd Street, south on South 72nd Street to Capehart Road, east on Capehart Road to South 60th Street, south on South 60th Street and continuing south along a north-south line extending south from South 60th Street to Platteview Road, east on Platteview Road to Dyson Hollow Road, north on Dyson Hollow Road to the southern boundary of the Bellevue Public School District, follow such boundary east to U.S. Highway 75, south on U.S. Highway 75 to the Sarpy-Cass County line, east along the Sarpy-Cass County line to the Nebraska-Iowa state line, north along the Nebraska-Iowa state line to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, and west along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the point of beginning; and</para><para>(3) The third district shall contain the counties of Jefferson, Saline, Thayer, Fillmore, York, Polk, Platte, Pierce, Knox, Antelope, Boone, Nance, Merrick, Hamilton, Clay, Nuckolls, Webster, Adams, Hall, Howard, Greeley, Wheeler, Holt, Boyd, Garfield, Valley, Sherman, Buffalo, Kearney, Franklin, Harlan, Phelps, Furnas, Gosper, Dawson, Custer, Loup, Blaine, Keya Paha, Rock, Brown, Cherry, Thomas, Logan, Lincoln, Frontier, Red Willow, Hitchcock, Hayes, McPherson, Hooker, Grant, Arthur, Keith, Perkins, Chase, Dundy, Deuel, Garden, Sheridan, Cheyenne, Morrill, Box Butte, Dawes, Sioux, Scotts Bluff, Banner, and Kimball and that part of Cedar County not included in the first district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 851, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>This act does not violate the one person, one vote standard, and is constitutional. Exon v. Tiemann, 279 F.Supp. 609 (D. Neb. 1968).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>