<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id25" statutenumber="32-942"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>32-942</statuteno><catchline id="id28">Registered voter anticipating absence on election day; right to vote; method; voter present in county; voting place; person registering to vote and requesting a ballot at same time; treatment of ballot.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) of this section, a registered voter of this state who anticipates being absent from the county of his or her residence on the day of any election may appear in person before the election commissioner or county clerk not more than thirty days prior to the day of election and obtain his or her ballot. The registered voter shall vote the ballot in the office of the election commissioner or county clerk or shall return the ballot to the office not later than the closing of the polls on the day of the election. A registered voter who is present in the county on the day of the election and who chooses to vote on the day of the election shall vote at the polling place assigned to the precinct in which he or she resides unless he or she is returning a ballot for early voting or voting pursuant to section 32-943.</para><para>(2) If a person registers to vote and requests a ballot at the same time under this section, he or she shall (a)(i) present one of the address confirmation documents as prescribed in subdivision (1)(a) of section 32-318.01, (ii) present proof that he or she is a member of the armed forces of the United States who by reason of active duty has been absent from his or her place of residence where the member is otherwise eligible to vote, is a member of the United States Merchant Marine who by reason of service has been away from his or her place of residence where the member is otherwise eligible to vote, is a spouse or dependent of a member of the armed forces of the United States or United States Merchant Marine who has been absent from his or her place of residence due to the service of that member, or resides outside the United States and but for such residence would be qualified to vote in the state if the state was the last place in which the person was domiciled before leaving the United States, or (iii) state that he or she is elderly or handicapped and has requested to vote by alternative means other than by casting a ballot at his or her polling place on election day or (b) vote a ballot which is placed in an envelope with the voter's name and address and other necessary identifying information and kept securely for counting as provided in this subsection. This subsection does not extend the deadline for voter registration specified in section 32-302. A ballot cast pursuant to subdivision (b) of this subsection shall be rejected and shall not be counted if the acknowledgment of registration sent to the registrant pursuant to section 32-322 is returned as undeliverable for a reason other than clerical error within ten days after it is mailed, otherwise after such ten-day period, the ballot shall be counted.</para><para>(3) This section applies only to a person who appears in person to obtain a ballot as provided in subsection (1) of this section and does not apply to a ballot mailed to a voter pursuant to section 32-945.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 285; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 935, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB499, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB271, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB565, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 21. </para><operativedate>August 30, 2015</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>