<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-312.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-312.03</statuteno><catchline>Registration application; identity confirmation; identifying number.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding other deficiencies that may cause an application for registration to be rejected, failure of the applicant to provide his or her Nebraska driver's license number or last four digits of his or her social security number shall not cause the application to be rejected.</para><para>(2) If the election commissioner or county clerk is able to verify at least one of the numbers against a record available from the Department of Motor Vehicles bearing the applicant's same name, residence address, and date of birth, that number will be entered into the applicant's voter registration record.</para><para>(3) If the applicant's Nebraska driver's license number or the last four digits of the applicant's social security number are confirmed in such a manner, the acknowledgment of registration sent to the registrant pursuant to section 32-322 shall advise the registrant of the number confirmed and the addition of the number to the registrant's voter registration record. The acknowledgment shall advise the registrant to contact the election commissioner or county clerk if the registrant has reason to believe that the number added to his or her voter registration record is incorrect or invalid.</para><para>(4) If the applicant for registration does not have a Nebraska driver's license or a social security number or if the applicant's Nebraska driver's license or social security number cannot be confirmed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the unique identifying number generated and assigned to the applicant's voter registration record in the voter registration register shall be used to identify the registrant for voter registration purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc>