<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-805"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-805</statuteno><catchline>Ballots; preparation; contents; posting.</catchline><para>The election commissioner or county clerk shall prepare the necessary ballots for every election in which candidates for elective office are certified to or filed with the election commissioner or county clerk or whenever any question is to be submitted to a vote of the registered voters of any locality and not to the state generally. The ballots shall be printed in English and in any other language required pursuant to the Voting Rights Act Language Assistance Amendments of 1992. If a question is submitted to the registered voters of any city or village alone, the city or village clerk shall provide the necessary ballots. Sample ballots shall be prepared for each precinct and shall be the same as the official ballots for the precinct. The official ballot shall be headed with the words Official Ballot, and the sample ballot shall be headed with the words Sample Ballot. All official and sample ballots shall be in the possession of the election commissioner, county clerk, or city or village clerk at least ten days before the election and subject to inspection by the candidates or their agents. One set of sample ballots shall be posted in the office of the election commissioner or county clerk not later than ten days prior to the election. Two sample ballots shall be posted at each polling place in each precinct on the morning of election day by the judges and clerks of election at or near the polling place. Additional sample ballots may be printed. No person other than an election commissioner, county clerk, or city or village clerk shall print or cause to be printed or distributed any ballot marked Official Ballot.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 226. </para></source><annotation><para>The arrangement of party names on the ballot is a matter within the discretion of the county clerk provided that each candidate is given the designation to which he is entitled. Woods v. State ex rel. McNerney, 44 Neb. 430, 63 N.W. 23 (1895).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>