<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-217"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-217</statuteno><catchline>Election commissioner, chief deputy election commissioner, and employees; county employees; salaries; how paid.</catchline><para>The election commissioner and the chief deputy election commissioner shall be county employees for the purposes of salary and benefit plans. All employees of the office of the election commissioner shall be county employees and subject to the county personnel system. The county board shall set the salaries of the election commissioner and chief deputy election commissioner at least sixty days prior to the expiration of the term of office of the election commissioner holding office. The salary shall become effective as soon as such salary may become operative under the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>In counties having a population of more than two hundred thousand inhabitants, the salary of the election commissioner shall be at least ten thousand five hundred dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund and the salary of the chief deputy election commissioner shall be at least nine thousand dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund.</para><para>In counties having a population of more than one hundred fifty thousand and not more than two hundred thousand inhabitants, the salary of the election commissioner shall be at least seven thousand five hundred dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund and the salary of the chief deputy election commissioner shall be at least six thousand dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund.</para><para>In counties having a population of more than one hundred thousand and not more than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants, the salary of the election commissioner shall be at least nine thousand five hundred dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund and the salary of the chief deputy election commissioner shall be at least eight thousand five hundred dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund.</para><para>In counties having a population of not more than one hundred thousand inhabitants, the salary of the election commissioner shall be at least six thousand five hundred dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund and the salary of the chief deputy election commissioner shall be at least five thousand dollars annually payable in periodic installments out of the county general fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>