<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-318.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-318.01</statuteno><catchline>Identification documents; required, when.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as provided by subsection (2) of this section, a person who registers to vote by mail after January 1, 2003, and has not previously voted in an election within the state shall present a photographic identification which is current and valid or a copy of a utility bill, bank statement, government check, paycheck, or other government document which is dated within the sixty days immediately prior to the date of presentation and which shows the same name and residence address of the person provided on the registration application in order to avoid identification requirements at the time of voting pursuant to section 32-914 or 32-947.</para><para>(b) Such documentation may be presented at the time of application for registration, after submission of the application for registration, or at the time of voting. The documentation must be received by the election commissioner or county clerk not later than 6 p.m. on the second Friday preceding the election to avoid additional identification requirements at the time of voting at the polling place if the voter votes in person. If the voter is voting using a ballot for early voting, the documentation must be received by the election commissioner or county clerk prior to the date on which the ballot is mailed to the voter to avoid additional identification requirements at the time of voting. Documentation received after the ballot has been mailed to the voter but not later than the deadline for the receipt of ballots specified in subsection (2) of section 32-908 will be considered timely for purposes of determining the applicant's eligibility to vote in the election.</para><para>(c) Such documentation may be presented in person, by mail, or by facsimile transmission.</para><para>(d) Failure to present such documentation may result in the ballot not being counted pursuant to verification procedures prescribed in sections 32-1002 and 32-1027.</para><para>(2) A person who registers to vote by mail after January 1, 2003, and has not previously voted in an election within the state shall not be required to present identification if he or she:</para><para>(a) Has provided his or her Nebraska driver's license number or the last four digits of his or her social security number and the election commissioner or county clerk verifies the number provided pursuant to subsection (2) of section 32-312.03;</para><para>(b) Is a member of the armed forces of the United States who by reason of active duty is absent from his or her place of residence where the member is otherwise eligible to vote;</para><para>(c) Is a member of the United States Merchant Marine who by reason of service is away from his or her place of residence where the member is otherwise eligible to vote;</para><para>(d) Is a spouse or dependent of a member of the armed forces of the United States or United States Merchant Marine who is absent from his or her place of residence due to the service of that member;</para><para>(e) Resides outside the United States and but for such residence would be qualified to vote in the state if the state was the last place in which the person was domiciled before leaving the United States; or</para><para>(f) Is elderly or handicapped and has requested to vote by alternative means other than by casting a ballot at his or her polling place on election day.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 566, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 19. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>