<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id14" statutenumber="32-630"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-630</statuteno><catchline id="id17">Petitions; signers and circulators; duties; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Each person who signs a petition shall, at the time of and in addition to signing, personally affix the date, print his or her last name and first name in full, and affix his or her date of birth and address, including the street and number or a designation of a rural route or voting precinct and the city or village or a post office address. A person signing a petition may use his or her initials in place of his or her first name if such person is registered to vote under such initials.</para><para>(2) Each circulator of a petition shall personally witness the signatures on the petition and shall sign the circulator's affidavit.</para><para>(3) No person shall:</para><para>(a) Sign any name other than his or her own to any petition;</para><para>(b) Knowingly sign his or her name more than once for the same petition effort or measure;</para><para>(c) Sign a petition if he or she is not a registered voter and qualified to sign the same except as provided in section 32-1404;</para><para>(d) Falsely swear to any signature upon any such petition;</para><para>(e) Accept money or other thing of value for signing any petition; or</para><para>(f) Offer money or other thing of value in exchange for a signature upon any petition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 198; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 460, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 444, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB39, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB367, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 34. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2024</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Where petition circulator has sworn to properly executed statutory form of affidavit that he is qualified voter, presumption raises that he is qualified elector; presumption does not disappear simply because full Christian name is not signed. State ex rel. Morris v. Marsh, 183 Neb. 521, 162 N.W.2d 262 (1968).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>