<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id85">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id87" statutenumber="32-811"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>32-811</statuteno><catchline id="id90">Political subdivisions;
political party convention delegates; names not on ballot; when.</catchline>
<para>(1) If the names of candidates properly filed for nomination
at the primary election for directors of natural resources districts, directors
of public power districts, directors of reclamation districts, members of
the boards of governors of community college areas, members of the boards
of Class III or Class V school
districts which nominate candidates at a primary election, and officers of
cities of the first or second class and cities having a city manager plan
of government do not exceed two candidates for each position to be filled,
any such candidates shall be declared nominated and their names shall not
appear on any primary election ballots. The official abstract of votes kept
by the county or state shall show the names of such candidates with the statement
Nominated Without Opposition. The election commissioner or county clerk shall
place the names of such automatically nominated candidates on the general
election ballot as provided in section 32-814.</para>
<para>(2) Candidates shall not appear on the ballot in the primary
election for the board of directors in public power districts receiving annual
gross revenue of less than forty million dollars, for county weed district
boards, and for the board of trustees in villages.</para>
<para>(3) If the number of candidates for delegates to a county
or national political party convention are the same in number or less than
the number of candidates to be elected, the names shall not appear on the
primary election ballot and those so filed shall receive a certificate of
election.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 232; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 194, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 15, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
