<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-809"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>32-809</statuteno><catchline>Statewide primary election; official
ballot; form; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The form of the official ballot
at the statewide primary election shall be prescribed by the Secretary of
State. At the top of the ballot and over all else shall be printed in boldface
type the name of the political party, ....... Official Ballot, Primary Election
20.. . Each division containing the names of the office and a list of candidates
for such office shall be separated from other groups by a bold line. The ballot
shall list at-large candidates and subdistrict candidates under appropriate
headings.</para>
<para>(2) All proposals for constitutional amendments, candidates for delegates
to the national political party conventions, and candidates on the nonpartisan
ballot shall be submitted on a ballot where bold lines separate one office
or issue from another. Proposals for constitutional amendments proposed by
the Legislature shall be placed on the ballot as provided in sections 49-201
to 49-211. Each candidate for delegate to the national political party convention
shall have his or her preference for the candidacy for the office of President
of the United States or the fact that he or she is uncommitted shown on the
ballot in parenthesis and indented on the line immediately below the name
of the candidate. All constitutional amendments shall be placed on a separate
ballot when a paper ballot is used which requires the ballot after being voted
to be folded before being deposited in a ballot box. When an optical-scan
ballot is used which requires a ballot envelope or sleeve in which the ballot
after being voted is placed before being deposited in a ballot box, constitutional
amendments may be printed on either side of the ballot and shall be separated
from other offices or issues by a bold line. Constitutional amendments so
arranged shall constitute a separate ballot.</para>
<para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in section
32-811, the statewide primary election ballot shall contain the
name of every candidate filing or
recognized under subsection
(1) of section 32-606 and sections 32-611, 32-613,
and 32-614 and no other names. No name of a candidate for member
of the Legislature or an elective office described in Article IV, section
1, of the Constitution of Nebraska shall appear on any ballot or any series
of ballots at any primary election more than once except for the names of
candidates for the office of delegate to a county, state, or national political
party convention. When two or more of the last names of candidates for the
same office at the primary election are the same in spelling or sound, the
official ballots may, on the request of any such candidate, have his or her
address printed immediately below his or her name in capital and lowercase
letters in lightface type of the same size as the type in which the name of
the candidate is printed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 230; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 358, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB878, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>