<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-701"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-701</statuteno><catchline>Political party; file delegate selection
plan; contents; President; preference vote.</catchline><para>(1) Each political party which is organized in Nebraska
shall file a copy of the party's plan for selecting delegates and alternate
delegates to the party's national convention with the Secretary of State on
or before December 1 of the calendar year prior to each presidential election
year and shall include a summary of the contents of the plan. The delegate
selection plan shall:</para><para>(a)
Require that at least eighty percent of the delegates and alternate delegates
are committed to a candidate for President of the United States based on the
results of a caucus or the primary election;</para><para>(b) Specify whether the delegates
and alternate delegates are committed to a candidate for President of the
United States based on the results of (i) a caucus system which is open to
all Nebraska residents who are affiliated with the party for purposes of registering
to vote in Nebraska, (ii) election at the statewide primary election, or (iii)
a combination of the methods listed in subdivisions (i) and (ii) of this subdivision;</para>
<para>(c) Specify how the delegates
and alternate delegates are committed for purposes of voting for candidates
for President of the United States based on the results of the caucus or primary
election; and</para><para>(d)
Provide that the delegates and alternate delegates are either awarded to the
winner of the caucus or primary election or awarded proportionally, based
on the number of votes received by each presidential candidate at the caucus
or primary election, to each presidential candidate who received at least
fifteen percent of the votes for the nomination.</para><para>(2) When candidates for the
office of President of the United States are to be nominated, every registered
voter of a political party shall have the opportunity to vote his or her preference
on his or her party nominating ballot for his or her choice for one person
to be the candidate of his or her political party for President of the United
States by writing the name of the person of his or her choice for President
in the blank space to be left upon the ballot for such purpose and making
a cross or mark in the square or oval opposite the written name or by making
a cross or mark in the square or oval opposite the printed name of the person
of his or her choice.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 201; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1048, &#167; 5.</para></source><annotation><para>The expression of a preference for President by those voting at primary election does not control presidential electors, and is only morally binding on delegates to national party conventions. State ex rel. Nebraska Rep. State C. Com. v. Wait, 92 Neb. 313, 138 N.W. 159 (1912), 43 L.R.A.N.S. 282 (1912).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>