<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-950.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-950.01</statuteno><catchline>Secure ballot drop-box; requirements; election commissioner or county clerk; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If an election commissioner or county clerk maintains a secure ballot drop-box for voters to deposit completed ballots, the election commissioner or county clerk shall ensure that the secure ballot drop-box:</para><para>(a) Is securely fastened to the ground or a concrete slab connected to the ground;</para><para>(b) Is secured by a lock that can only be opened by the election commissioner or county clerk or by an election official designated by the election commissioner or county clerk; and</para><para>(c) Complies with the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 and is accessible as determined by the election commissioner or county clerk.</para><para>(2) The election commissioner or county clerk shall inform the Secretary of State of each secure ballot drop-box's location no later than forty-two days prior to any statewide primary or general election.</para><para>(3) Except for a secure ballot drop-box for an election conducted under section 32-960, the election commissioner or county clerk or an election official designated by the election commissioner or county clerk shall open each secure ballot drop-box no later than the sixth Friday prior to any statewide primary or general election and no later than the fourth Friday prior to any special election. For any statewide primary or general election, each secure ballot drop-box shall remain accessible to voters until the deadline for the receipt of ballots as provided in section 32-908. For any special election, at least one secure ballot drop-box shall remain accessible to voters until the deadline for the receipt of ballots as provided in section 32-954.</para><para>(4) After a secure ballot drop-box is made available for depositing ballots, the election commissioner or county clerk shall ensure that ballots deposited in such secure ballot drop-box are collected and returned to the office of the election commissioner or county clerk at least once during each business day.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 48. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>