<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-627"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>32-627</statuteno><catchline>Partisan office; vacancy on ballot;
how filled.</catchline><para>(1) If a vacancy on the ballot arises for any
partisan office except President and Vice President of the United States before
a general election, the vacancy shall be filled by the majority vote of the
proper committee of the same political party. If the vacancy exists for an
office serving only a particular district of the state, only those members
of the political party committee who reside within that district shall participate
in selecting the candidate to fill the vacancy. No vacancy on the ballot shall
be deemed to have occurred if a political party makes no nomination of a candidate
at the primary election for the office. If a vacancy on the ballot arises
for Governor, the vacancy shall be filled by the majority vote of the proper
committee of the same political party, and the candidate for Governor shall
select a person of the same political party to be the candidate for Lieutenant
Governor on the general election ballot. If a vacancy on the ballot arises
for the Lieutenant Governor on or before September 1, the candidate for Governor
shall select a new candidate for Lieutenant Governor in the same manner as
required in section 32-619.01.</para>
<para>(2) The chairperson and secretary of the executive committee for the
political party shall make and file with the filing officer a certificate
setting forth the cause of the vacancy, the name of the person so nominated,
the office for which he or she was nominated, the name of the person for which
the new nominee is to be substituted, the place of residence of the person
so nominated, the street and number of the residence or place of business
of the person so nominated if such person resides in a city, and the name
of the political party with which the person so nominated affiliates which
such committee represents. The certificate shall be signed by the chairperson
and secretary with the name and places of their residences and sworn to by
them before some officer authorized to administer oaths. If there is no executive
committee of the political party or
in lieu of the executive committee filling such vacancy, a mass convention of
the political party may fill the vacancy and the
chairperson and secretary of such convention shall make and file with the
filing officer a certificate in form and manner substantially as is required
to be filed by the chairperson and secretary of the executive committee under
this subsection. The certificate shall be filed by September 1 for a general
election and have the same force and effect as the candidate filing form provided
for in section 32-607. The filing fee charged to candidates for such offices
shall accompany the filing of the certificate.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 195; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 768, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB503, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>