<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-801"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-801</statuteno><catchline>Official ballot; certifications required.</catchline><para>At least fifty days before any statewide primary or general election, the Secretary of State shall transmit in ballot form to each election commissioner or county clerk a certification of the candidates, offices, and issues that appear on the state ballot. The certification prior to the primary election shall name the office to be filled, the length of the term, the number of candidates to be voted for, the name of each candidate for whom candidate filing forms or petitions have been filed in the office of the Secretary of State and who is entitled to be voted for at such primary election, and the party affiliation or nonpartisan status of each candidate. A separate statement of the city or village of residence of each candidate shall be included with the certification, but the city or village of residence shall not appear on the official ballot. The certification prior to the general election shall name the office to be filled, the length of the term, the number of candidates to be voted for, the name of each candidate who was nominated at the primary election or who filed by petition as shown by the records in the office of the Secretary of State and who is entitled to be voted for at the general election, and the party affiliation or nonpartisan status of each candidate for partisan offices.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 222; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 72. </para></source><annotation><para>The Secretary of State is required to certify to the counties which issues will be on the ballot at least 50 days before the election. State ex rel. Bellino v. Moore, 254 Neb. 385, 576 N.W.2d 793 (1998).</para><para>Unless there is some designation of office on a ballot, the ballot is void, but technical accuracy in the designation is not essential. State ex rel. Valentine v. Griffey, 5 Neb. 161, 31 L.E.2d 890 (1876).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>