<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-915.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-915.03</statuteno><catchline>Provisional voter identification verification envelope; required; when; certification.</catchline><para>(1) A registered voter shall fill out a provisional voter identification verification envelope if:</para><para>(a)(i) The voter fails to produce valid photographic identification at the polling place; and</para><para>(ii) The voter's name appears on the precinct list of registered voters for the polling place or the voter has voted a provisional ballot as provided in section 32-915;</para><para>(b) The voter fails to produce valid photographic identification at the time of voting early in person at the office of the election commissioner or county clerk; or</para><para>(c) The voter has a reasonable impediment preventing the voter from obtaining valid photographic identification or the voter's name appears on the precinct list of registered voters for the polling place with a notation that the voter has a religious objection to being photographed.</para><para>(2) Each voter casting a ballot using a provisional voter identification verification envelope shall enclose the ballot in an envelope marked provisional voter identification verification and shall, by signing the certification on the front of the envelope or a separate form attached to the envelope, certify to the following facts:</para><para>(a) My name is ............;</para><para>(b) I am registered to vote at ............;</para><para>(c) I did not present valid photographic identification as required by law or I have a reasonable impediment preventing me from obtaining valid photographic identification;</para><para>(d) I am eligible to vote in this election and have not voted and will not vote in this election except by this ballot; and</para><para>(e) I acknowledge that my ballot will not be counted if:</para><para>(i) I do not present valid photographic identification to my county election office on or before the Tuesday after the election; or</para><para>(ii) I have a reasonable impediment that prevents me from obtaining valid photographic identification and:</para><para>(A) I do not complete a reasonable impediment certification; or</para><para>(B) My county election official cannot verify the signature on my reasonable impediment certification.</para><para>(3) The voter shall sign the certification under penalty of election falsification. The following statements shall be on the front of the envelope or on the attached form: By signing the front of this envelope or the attached form you are certifying to the information contained on this envelope or the attached form under penalty of election falsification. Election falsification is a Class IV felony and may be punished by up to two years imprisonment and twelve months post-release supervision, a fine of up to ten thousand dollars, or both.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB514, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 43. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>