<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id16" statutenumber="32-552"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>32-552</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Election districts; adjustment of boundaries; when; procedure; Class IV school district; Class V school district; districts.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided by subsection (4) of this section, at least five months prior to an election, the governing board of any political subdivision requesting the adjustment of the boundaries of election districts shall provide to the election commissioner or county clerk (a) written notice of the need and necessity of his or her office to perform such adjustments and (b) a revised election district boundary map that has been approved by the requesting political subdivision's governing board and subjected to all public review and challenge ordinances of the political subdivision.</para><para>(2) After the next federal decennial census, the election commissioner of the county in which the greater part of a Class IV school district is situated shall, subject to review by the school board, divide the school district into seven numbered districts, substantially equal in population as determined by the most recent federal decennial census. The election commissioner shall consider the location of schools within the district and their boundaries. The election commissioner shall adjust the boundaries of the election districts, subject to final review and adjustment by the school board, to conform to changes in the territory and population of the school district and also following each federal decennial census. Except when specific procedures are otherwise provided, section 32-553 shall apply to all Class IV school districts.</para><para>(3) For purposes of election of members to the board of education of a Class V school district:</para><para>(a)(i) The Legislature hereby divides such school district into nine numbered election districts of compact and contiguous territory and of as nearly equal population as may be practical. Each election district shall be entitled to one member on the board of education of such Class V school district. The Legislature adopts the official population figures and maps from the 2010 Census Redistricting (Public Law 94-171) TIGER/Line Shapefiles published by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census. The numbers and boundaries of the election districts are designated and established by a map identified and labeled as OPS-13-002, filed with the Clerk of the Legislature, and incorporated by reference as part of Laws 2013, LB125. Such districts are drawn using the boundaries of the Class V school district as they existed on February 12, 2013; (ii) the Clerk of the Legislature shall transfer possession of the map referred to in subdivision (a)(i) of this subsection to the Secretary of State and the election commissioner of the county in which the greater part of the school district is situated on February 12, 2013; (iii) when questions of interpretation of such election district boundaries arise, the map referred to in subdivision (a)(i) of this subsection in possession of such election commissioner shall serve as the indication of the legislative intent in drawing the election district boundaries; and (iv) the Secretary of State and such election commissioner shall also have available for viewing on his or her website the map referred to in subdivision (a)(i) of this subsection identifying the boundaries for such election districts; and</para><para>(b) After the next federal decennial census, the election commissioner of the county in which the greater part of a Class V school district is situated shall divide the school district into nine numbered districts of compact and contiguous territory and of as nearly equal population as may be practical. The election commissioner shall adjust the boundaries of such districts, subject to final review and adjustment by the school board, to conform to changes in the territory of the school district and also following each federal decennial census.</para><para>(4) Following the release of the 2020 Census of Population data by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, as required by Public Law 94-171, the governing board of any political subdivision requesting the adjustment of the boundaries of election districts shall provide to the election commissioner or county clerk (a) written notice of the need and necessity of his or her office to perform such adjustments and (b) a revised election district boundary map that has been approved by the requesting political subdivision's governing board and subjected to all public review and challenge ordinances of the political subdivision by December 30, 2021.</para><para>(5) The Secretary of State may grant additional days upon request of the political subdivision if precinct maps are not delivered to the political subdivision by November 1, 2021, or for an extraordinary circumstance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 148; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 935, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB125, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1055, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB285, &#167; 8. </para></source><annotation><para>Read together, this section and section 32-553 authorize an election commissioner to draw or adjust the boundaries of school districts following a federal decennial census only as is necessary to maintain substantial population equality within the districts. This section and section 32-553 do not authorize an election commissioner to take into account political considerations when adjusting boundaries following a federal decennial census. State ex rel. Steinke v. Lautenbaugh, 263 Neb. 652, 642 N.W.2d 132 (2002).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>