<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id6" statutenumber="32-512"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>32-512</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Public power district;
public power and irrigation district; board of directors; nonpartisan ballot;
terms; qualifications; qualified voters.</catchline><para>(1) After
the selection of the original board of directors of a public power district
as provided for in sections 70-803 and 70-805 or a district as provided for
in sections 70-604 and 70-609, their successors shall be nominated and elected
on the nonpartisan ballot, except that in districts receiving annual gross
revenue of less than forty million dollars, the candidates for the board of
directors shall not appear on the ballot in the primary election. The term
of each elected director shall be not more than six years or until his or
her successor is elected and qualified. Candidates for the board of directors
shall meet the qualifications found in sections 70-610 and 70-619.</para>
<para>(2) Registered voters residing within the chartered territory
and registered voters duly certified in accordance with section 70-604.03
shall be qualified to vote in the district as certified pursuant to section
70-611. The registered voters of a subdivision created under subsection (1) of section 70-612 may only cast
their ballots for candidates for directors to be elected from such subdivision
and for candidates for directors to be elected at large from the whole district. The registered voters of a subdivision
created under subsection (2) or (3) of section 70-612 may only cast their
ballots for candidates for directors to be elected from such subdivision.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB646, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>