<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id58">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id60" statutenumber="32-525"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-525</statuteno><catchline id="id63">County surveyor;
election; when required; terms; qualifications; question of electing county surveyor; county board; powers;
form of ballot; partisan ballot.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in
section 22-417 and except for
counties which vote not to elect the county surveyor as provided in subsection
(2) or (4) of this section, a county surveyor on either a full-time
or part-time basis, as determined by the county board in accordance with section
23-1901, shall be elected in each county having a population of less than
one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants at the statewide general election in
1990 and each four years thereafter.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except
as provided in section 22-417 and in subsection (3) of this section, in each
county having a population of less than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants,
the question of electing a county surveyor in the county shall be submitted
to the registered voters of the county at the statewide general election in
2020. The form of submission upon the ballot shall be as follows: For election
of county surveyor; Against election of county surveyor.</para>
<para>(b) If a majority
of the votes cast on the question are against the election of a county surveyor
in such county, the office of county surveyor shall cease as an elected office
with the expiration of the term of the incumbent or shall remain as it exists
if no elected official holds that office. In such counties, the office shall
be filled as provided in subsection (2) of section 23-1901.01.</para>
<para>(c) If a majority
of the votes cast on the question are in favor of the election of a county
surveyor, the office shall continue to be elected as provided in subsection
(1) of this section or, if no elected county surveyor is in office, a county
surveyor shall be elected at the next statewide general election as provided
in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) If a county having a population of less
than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants has an elected county surveyor
in office on January 1, 2020, the county board may, prior to February 1, 2020,
following a public hearing, adopt a resolution to continue to elect the county
surveyor for the county and not to submit the question pursuant to subsection
(2) of this section.</para><para>(4)(a) Beginning in 2021, in each county having a population of
less than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants, the county board shall submit
the question of electing a county surveyor in the county to the registered
voters of the county at the next statewide general election if (i) the county
board, by majority vote of all the members of the county board, adopts a resolution
on or before September 1 prior to the next statewide general election to submit
the question to the voters or (ii) a petition conforming to section 32-628
asking for the submission of the question to the voters is presented to the
election commissioner or county clerk on or before September 1 prior to the
next statewide general election signed by at least ten percent of the registered
voters of the county. The election commissioner or county clerk shall verify
the signatures pursuant to section 32-631 and place the question on the ballot
if he or she determines that at least ten percent of the registered voters
of the county have signed the petition.</para><para>(b) The form of submission upon the ballot
shall be as follows: For election of county surveyor; Against election of
county surveyor.</para><para>(c) If a majority of the votes cast on the question are against
the election of a county surveyor in such county, the office of county surveyor
shall cease as an elected office with the expiration of the term of the incumbent
or shall remain as it exists if no elected official holds that office. In
such counties, the office shall be filled as provided in subsection (2) of
section 23-1901.01.</para><para>(d) If a majority of the votes cast on the question are in favor
of the election of a county surveyor, the office shall continue to be elected
as provided in subsection (1) of this section or, if no elected county surveyor
is in office, a county surveyor shall be elected at the next statewide general
election as provided in subsection (1) of this section.</para>
<para>(5) The term of the county
surveyor shall be four years or until his or her successor is elected and
qualified. The county surveyor shall meet the qualifications found in sections
23-1901 and 23-1901.01. The county surveyor shall be elected on the partisan
ballot.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 121; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>