<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1549"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1549</statuteno><catchline>Citation in lieu of arrest; Supreme Court; powers; prosecution; procedure; failure to appear; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A peace officer may issue a citation in lieu of arrest for any offense which is a misdemeanor under the Election Act. The citation may be served in the same manner as an arrest warrant, in the same manner as a summons in a civil action, or by certified mail.</para><para>(2) To achieve uniformity, the Supreme Court may prescribe the form of citation. The citation shall include a description of the crime or offense charged, the time and place at which the person cited is to appear, a warning that failure to appear in accordance with the command of the citation is a punishable offense, and such other matter as the court deems appropriate, but shall not include a place for the cited person's social security number. The court may provide that a copy of the citation shall constitute the complaint filed in the trial court.</para><para>(3) When a citation is used by a peace officer, he or she shall enter on the citation all required information, including the name and address of the cited person, the offense charged, and the time and place the person cited is to appear in court. Unless the person cited requests an earlier date, the time of appearance shall be at least three days after the issuance of the citation. One copy of the citation shall be delivered to the person cited, and a duplicate thereof shall be signed by such person, giving his or her promise to appear at the time and place stated in the citation. Such person shall be released from custody upon signing the citation. As soon as practicable, the copy signed by the person cited shall be delivered to the prosecuting attorney.</para><para>(4) At least twenty-four hours before the time set for the appearance of the cited person, the prosecuting attorney shall issue and file a complaint charging such person with an offense or such person shall be released from the obligation to appear as specified. A person cited pursuant to this section may waive his or her right to trial. The Supreme Court may prescribe uniform rules for such waivers.</para><para>(5) Anyone may use a credit card authorized by the court in which the person is cited as a means of payment of his or her fine and costs.</para><para>(6) Any person failing to appear or otherwise comply with the command of a citation shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 448; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 82, &#167; 16. </para></source></law></legaldoc>