<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1606.01" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1606.01</statuteno><catchline>Preelection campaign statement; filing; contents; late filing fee; civil penalty.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to campaign statements required according to the schedule in section 49-1459, a candidate who files an affidavit under subdivision (5)(a) of section 32-1604 shall file a third preelection campaign statement with the commission so that it is received by the commission not later than the sixth day before the election. The closing date for a campaign statement filed under this section shall be the eighth day before the election. Campaign statements filed under this section shall be subject to the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act in all matters not in conflict with this section.</para><para>(2) The campaign statement shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) The filing committee's name, address, and telephone number and the full name, residential and business addresses, and telephone numbers of its committee treasurer; and</para><para>(b) Under the heading RECEIPTS, the total amount of contributions received during the period covered by the campaign statement; under the heading EXPENDITURES, the total amount of expenditures made during the period covered by the campaign statement; and the cumulative amount of those totals for the election period. If a loan was repaid during the period covered by the campaign statement, the amount of the repayment shall be subtracted from the total amount of contributions received. Forgiveness of a loan shall not be included in the totals. Payment of a loan by a third party shall be recorded and reported as a contribution by the third party but shall not be included in the totals. In-kind contributions or expenditures shall be listed at fair market value and shall be reported as both contributions and expenditures.</para><para>(3) All information in the campaign statement filed under this section shall also be included in the postelection campaign statement filed under subdivision (1)(c) of section 49-1459.</para><para>(4) Any person who fails to file a campaign statement with the commission under this section shall pay to the commission a late filing fee of twenty-five dollars for each day the campaign statement remains not filed in violation of this section, not to exceed seven hundred fifty dollars. In addition, if a candidate fails to file the statement required by this section within the prescribed time resulting in any abiding candidate not receiving public funds as described in subsection (6) of section 32-1604 or resulting in a delay in the receipt of such funds, the commission shall assess a civil penalty of not less than two thousand dollars and not more than three times (a) the amount of public funds the abiding candidate received after the delay or (b) the amount of public funds the abiding candidate would have received if the campaign statement had been filed within the prescribed time.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 188, &#167; 7.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act,</emphasis> see section 49-1401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>