<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id174">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id176" statutenumber="32-1306"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1306</statuteno><catchline id="id179">Filing clerk;
notification required; recall election; when held; failure to order; effect.</catchline>
<para>(1) If the recall petition is found to be sufficient, the
filing clerk shall notify the official whose removal is sought and the governing
body of the affected political subdivision that sufficient signatures have
been gathered. Notification of the official sought to be removed may be by
any method specified in section 25-505.01 or, if notification cannot be made
with reasonable diligence by any of the methods specified in section 25-505.01,
by leaving such notice at the official's usual place of residence and mailing
a copy by first-class mail to the official's last-known address.</para>
<para>(2) The governing body of the political subdivision shall
order an election to be held not less than thirty nor more than seventy-five days after the notification of
the official whose removal is sought under subsection (1) of this section,
except that if any other election is to be held in that political subdivision
within ninety days after such notification, the governing body of the political
subdivision shall provide for the holding of the recall election on the same
day. All resignations shall be tendered as provided in section 32-562. If
the official whose removal is sought resigns before the recall election is
held, the governing body may cancel the recall election if the governing body
notifies the election commissioner or county clerk of the cancellation at
least sixteen days prior to the election, otherwise the recall election shall
be held as scheduled.</para>
<para>(3) If the governing body of the political subdivision fails
or refuses to order a recall election within the time required, the election
may be ordered by the district court having jurisdiction over a county in
which the elected official serves. If a filing clerk is subject to a recall
election, the Secretary of State shall conduct the recall election.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 379; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 820, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB312, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 13.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>