<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1608.01" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1608.01</statuteno><catchline>Rules and regulations; filings; methods authorized; authentication procedures.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to provide for the reporting of expenditures by candidates of any public funds received pursuant to the Campaign Finance Limitation Act and for the keeping of records with respect to the expenditure of such funds.</para><para>(2) The commission shall accept any affidavit required to be filed under the act by hand delivery, facsimile transmission, express delivery service, or any other written means of communication. If the filing is made by a means which does not include the original signature of the affiant, an affidavit which includes the original signature shall be filed with the commission within fourteen days after the initial filing.</para><para>(3) The commission may adopt procedures for the digital and electronic filing of any document required to be submitted under the Campaign Finance Limitation Act other than documents required to be notarized. Any procedures for digital filing shall comply with the provisions of section 86-611. The commission may adopt authentication procedures to be used as a verification process for documents filed digitally or electronically. Compliance with authentication procedures adopted by the commission shall have the same validity as a signature on any document.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 587, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 188, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Commission,</emphasis> defined, see section 49-1412.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>