<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1604.01" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1604.01</statuteno><catchline>Candidates for covered elective office; affidavit; late filing fee; violation of act; when.</catchline><para>(1) Each candidate for a covered elective office listed in subdivision (1)(a) of section 32-1603 shall file either an affidavit to abide under subsection (4) of section 32-1604 or an affidavit not to abide and an affidavit stating a reasonable estimate of his or her maximum expenditures under subdivision (5)(a) of section 32-1604 with the Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission within ten days after a candidate committee is required to be formed pursuant to sections 49-1413, 49-1445, and 49-1449 and on or before the first day of each election period thereafter unless the candidate has not filed and will not file to seek election or reelection or has withdrawn his or her filing to seek election or reelection. Each candidate for a covered elective office listed in subdivision (1)(b) of section 32-1603 shall file either an affidavit to abide under subsection (4) of section 32-1604 or an affidavit not to abide and an affidavit stating a reasonable estimate of his or her maximum expenditures under subdivision (5)(a) of section 32-1604 with the Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission within ten days after a candidate committee is required to be formed pursuant to sections 49-1413, 49-1445, and 49-1449 or within ten days after the office is designated as a covered elective office under section 32-1611, whichever is later, unless the candidate has not filed and will not file to seek election or reelection or has withdrawn his or her filing to seek election or reelection. If a candidate is not required to form a candidate committee, the candidate is not required to file an affidavit under section 32-1604.</para><para>(2) An affidavit to abide under subsection (4) of section 32-1604 and an affidavit not to abide and an affidavit stating a reasonable estimate of his or her maximum expenditures under subdivision (5)(a) of section 32-1604 shall be filed on forms prescribed by the commission.</para><para>(3) A candidate who fails to file an affidavit as required by this section shall pay to the commission a late filing fee of twenty-five dollars for each day the affidavit remains not filed in violation of this section, not to exceed seven hundred fifty dollars.</para><para>(4) It shall be a violation of the Campaign Finance Limitation Act for a candidate for a covered elective office who has filed an affidavit to abide under subsection (4) of section 32-1604 to exceed the spending limitations prescribed in section 32-1604.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 420, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 188, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>