<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1118</statuteno><catchline>Legislature; recount; petition; bond; Secretary of State; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The apparent loser at a general election for a seat in the Legislature may secure a recount of the ballots cast at such election by filing a petition for a recount in duplicate with the Secretary of State no later than the fourth Monday after the election. The petition shall be accompanied by a corporate surety bond in the penal sum of two thousand five hundred dollars conditioned for the payment of costs pursuant to section 32-1116 if the recount fails to change the results of the election. If at any stage of the recount the amount of the bond becomes inadequate, the Secretary of State may order an increase in the amount of such bond.</para><para>(2) The Secretary of State shall, by certified or registered mail, give notice of the filing of a petition under this section not later than the day following the filing of the petition and deliver a copy of the petition to the declared winner. The Secretary of State shall also, by the most practicable means of communication, direct the election commissioner or county clerk of each county involved to deliver the ballot boxes to the office of the election commissioner or county clerk designated by the Secretary of State no later than the following Monday.</para><para>(3) After the ballot boxes have been received at the designated office, they shall be opened and the ballots for member of the Legislature shall be recounted under the supervision of the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State may employ such persons as may be necessary to conduct the recount and fix their compensation.</para><para>(4) The Secretary of State shall, on or before December 20, certify the results of the recount to each of the parties to the recount and to the Clerk of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 361. </para></source></law></legaldoc>