<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1012"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1012</statuteno><catchline>Centralized location; partial returns; when; designation of location; counting procedure.</catchline><para>(1) In counties using optical scanners to count the ballots at a centralized location, the election commissioner or county clerk may arrange to have partial returns delivered, properly locked or sealed, to the centralized location or locations at any time desired after the opening of the polls if at least twenty-five ballots have been cast since any prior delivery of ballots. The election commissioner or county clerk shall designate the location or locations for counting the ballots and may designate a location or locations in any county. Upon completion of the count, the ballots shall be conveyed under supervision of the election commissioner or county clerk to the office of such official. If for any reason it becomes impracticable to count all or a part of the ballots with optical scanners, the election commissioner or county clerk may direct that the ballots be counted manually following as closely as possible the provisions governing the manual counting of ballots.</para><para>(2) In counties using optical scanners to count the ballots at polling places, the election commissioner or county clerk may arrange to have partial returns delivered, properly locked, sealed, or digitally secured, to the election office at any time desired after the opening of the polls if at least twenty-five ballots have been cast since any prior delivery of partial returns. The election commissioner or county clerk shall designate polling places as locations for counting the ballots. Upon completion of the count, the ballots shall be conveyed under supervision of the election commissioner or county clerk to the office of such official. If for any reason it becomes impracticable to count all or a part of the ballots with optical scanners, the election commissioner or county clerk may direct that the ballots be counted manually following as closely as possible the provisions governing the manual counting of ballots.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 306; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 358, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 55. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>