<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id149"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1122</statuteno><catchline>Recount; tie vote; determination of winner.</catchline><para>(1) If a recount after a primary election results in any two or more persons having an equal and the highest number of votes for the same nomination for the same county, city, village, or school district office, the county canvassing board shall, in the presence of the candidates or their representatives, determine by lot which of the candidates shall be nominated. The election commissioner or county clerk shall notify such candidates by certified mail to appear at his or her office on a given day and hour to determine the same before the county canvassing board. If a candidate or candidate's representative fails to appear at the given day and hour, a person designated by the election commissioner or county clerk shall participate in the candidate's stead. The election commissioner or county clerk shall make a certificate of nomination for the person so nominated and shall cause such certificate to be delivered to the person entitled thereto.</para><para>(2) If a recount after a general or special election results in any two or more persons having an equal and the highest number of votes for the same county, city, village, or school district office, the county canvassing board shall, in the presence of the candidates or their representatives, determine by lot which of the candidates shall be elected. The election commissioner or county clerk shall notify such candidates by certified mail to appear at his or her office on a given day and hour to determine the same before the county canvassing board. If a candidate or candidate's representative fails to appear at the given day and hour, a person designated by the election commissioner or county clerk shall participate in the candidate's stead. The election commissioner or county clerk shall make a certificate of election for the person so elected and shall cause such certificate to be delivered to the person entitled thereto.</para><para>(3) If a recount after a primary election results in any two or more persons having an equal and the highest number of votes for nomination to an office canvassed by the board of state canvassers, the board shall decide by lot which of such persons is nominated.</para><para>(4) If a recount after a general or special election results in any two or more persons having an equal and the highest number of votes for the office of the Governor, Secretary of State, Auditor of Public Accounts, State Treasurer, Attorney General, or other officer elected to an executive department, the Legislature shall choose one of such persons for the office. If the office involved in the recount is the office of the Governor, the Lieutenant Governor shall be the candidate for Lieutenant Governor chosen by the person selected by the Legislature as Governor.</para><para>(5) If a recount after a general or special election results in any two or more persons having an equal and the highest number of votes for an office canvassed by the board of state canvassers, the board shall decide by lot which of such persons is elected, except officers elected to the executive department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 365; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 253, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 768, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB521, &#167; 75. </para><operativedate>May 31, 2025</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Upon determination there existed tie votes between two candidates for same office, cause remanded with directions that county canvassing board resolve disputed election under provisions of this section. Dugan v. Vlach, 195 Neb. 81, 237 N.W.2d 104 (1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>