<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1602" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1602</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that the cost of running for statewide offices and legislative seats has risen greatly and that many qualified candidates are excluded from the democratic system as a result of such rising cost. The Legislature further finds that the United States Supreme Court has indicated that any limitation on campaign expenditures must be entered into voluntarily and that the utilization of public financing of campaigns is a constitutionally permissible way in which to encourage candidates to adopt voluntary campaign spending limitations. The Legislature further finds that using public funds to assist in the financing of campaigns for certain statewide offices and legislative seats, in conjunction with voluntary campaign spending limitations, will increase the number of qualified candidates able to run for office. The Legislature further finds that in order for the public financing system to function properly in service of the state's interests, every candidate, regardless of whether or not that candidate seeks or is entitled to public funds, must make timely filings as required by the Campaign Finance Limitation Act.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds that there are compelling state interests in preserving the integrity of the electoral process in state elections by ensuring that these elections are free from corruption and the appearance of corruption; in providing the electorate with information that will assist them with electoral decisions; and in gathering the data necessary to permit administration and to detect violations of the act. The Legislature further finds that these ends can be achieved only if (a) reasonable limits are placed on the amount of campaign contributions from certain sources, (b) the sources of funding and the use of that funding in campaigns are fully disclosed within the time periods prescribed by the act, and (c) public funds are provided to candidates who voluntarily accept spending limitations and otherwise comply with conditions for such funding under the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 556, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 420, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 188, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>