<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id155" statutenumber="32-1203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1203</statuteno><catchline id="id158">Political subdivisions; election expenses; duties; determination of charge.</catchline><para>(1) Each city, village, school district, public power district, sanitary and improvement district, metropolitan utilities district, fire district, natural resources district, community college area, learning community coordinating council, educational service unit, hospital district, reclamation district, and library board shall pay for the costs of nominating and electing its officers as provided in subsection (2), (3), or (4) of this section. If a special issue is placed on the ballot at the time of the statewide primary or general election by any political subdivision, the political subdivision shall pay for the costs of the election as provided in subsection (2), (3), or (4) of this section. The districts listed in this subsection shall furnish to the Secretary of State and election commissioner or county clerk any maps and additional information which the election commissioner or county clerk may require in the proper performance of their duties in the conduct of elections and certification of results.</para><para>(2) The charge for each primary and general election shall be determined by (a) ascertaining the total cost of all chargeable costs as described in section 32-1202, (b) dividing the total cost by the number of precincts participating in the election to fix the cost per precinct, (c) prorating the cost per precinct by the inked ballot inch in each precinct for each political subdivision, and (d) totaling the cost for each precinct for each political subdivision, except that the minimum charge for each primary and general election for each political subdivision shall be one hundred dollars.</para><para>(3) In lieu of the charge determined pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the election commissioner or county clerk may charge public power districts the fee for election costs set by section 70-610.</para><para>(4) In lieu of the charge determined pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the election commissioner or county clerk may bill school districts directly for the costs of an election held under section 10-703.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 368; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1067, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 27. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>