<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20"><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id22" statutenumber="32-1031"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1031</statuteno><catchline id="id25">County canvassing
board; canvass of votes; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) After counting
the ballots under section 32-1027, the county canvassing board shall proceed
with the official canvass of votes cast on election day. If in the process
of canvassing the votes for any candidate or measure in any precinct the election
commissioner or county clerk or the canvassing board determines that there
is an obvious error in the certification of the votes, the error shall be
corrected. The county canvassing board may open the ballots-cast container
and recount the ballots for any candidate or any measure which appears to
be in error. If the county canvassing board finds and corrects any such error,
it shall make the correction entry in the precinct sign-in register, the precinct
list of registered voters, and the official summary or summaries of votes
cast and shall attach a letter of explanation to each book where the correction
was made. The letter shall be signed by all members of the county canvassing
board.</para>
<para>(2) When it has been determined that the returns in all precincts
are correct, the county canvassing board shall provide
a record of the results to the election commissioner or county
clerk either in a ledger or
by using a computer printout. The election commissioner or county clerk shall
preserve the record of the results for the period of time specified
by the State Records Administrator pursuant to the Records Management Act,
and then it may be transferred to the State Archives of the Nebraska State
Historical Society for permanent preservation.</para>
<para>(3) Any recesses or adjournments of the county canvassing
board shall be to a fixed time and publicly announced. When a recess is called,
all ballots that have not been counted and all other supplies shall be placed
in a fireproof safe or other suitable location which is locked until such
board reconvenes.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 325; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1035, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Records Management Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1220.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>