<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-1308"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1308</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Recall election; results; effect; vacancies; how filled.</catchline><para>(1) If a majority of the votes cast at a recall election are against the removal of the official named on the ballot or the election results in a tie, the official shall continue in office for the remainder of his or her term but may be subject to further recall attempts as provided in section 32-1309.</para><para>(2) If a majority of the votes cast at a recall election are for the removal of the official named on the ballot, he or she shall, regardless of any technical defects in the recall petition, be deemed removed from office unless a recount is ordered. If the official is deemed removed, the removal shall result in a vacancy in the office which shall be filled as provided in this section and sections 32-567 to 32-570, 32-574, and 32-606.01.</para><para>(3) If the election results show a margin of votes equal to one percent or less between the removal or retention of the official in question, the Secretary of State, election commissioner, or county clerk shall order a recount of the votes cast unless the official named on the ballot files a written statement with the filing officer that he or she does not want a recount.</para><para>(4) If there are vacancies in the offices of one-half or more of the members of any governing body at one time due to the recall of such members, a special election to fill such vacancies shall be conducted as expeditiously as possible by the Secretary of State, election commissioner, or county clerk. Candidates for the special election shall file a candidate filing form pursuant to section 32-606.01.</para><para>(5) No official who is removed at a recall election or who resigns after the initiation of the recall process shall be appointed to fill the vacancy resulting from his or her removal or the removal of any other member of the same governing body during the remainder of his or her term of office.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 381; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 58. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>