<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1302"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1302</statuteno><catchline>Officials subject to recall.</catchline><para>(1) Except for trustees of sanitary and improvement districts, any elected official of a political subdivision and any elected member of the governing bodies of cities, villages, counties, irrigation districts, natural resources districts, public power districts, school districts, community college areas, educational service units, hospital districts, and metropolitan utilities districts may be removed from office by recall pursuant to sections 32-1301 to 32-1309. A trustee of a sanitary and improvement district may be removed from office by recall pursuant to sections 31-786 to 31-793.</para><para>(2) If due to reapportionment the boundaries of the area served by the official or body change, the recall procedure and special election provisions of sections 32-1301 to 32-1309 shall apply to the registered voters within the boundaries of the new area.</para><para>(3) The recall procedure and special election provisions of such sections shall apply to members of the governing bodies listed in subsection (1) of this section, other than sanitary and improvement districts, who are elected by precinct, district, or subdistrict of the political subdivision. Only registered voters of such member's precinct, district, or subdistrict may sign a recall petition or vote at the recall election. The recall election shall be held within the member's precinct, district, or subdistrict. When an elected member is nominated by precinct, district, or subdistrict in the primary election and elected at large in the general election, the recall provisions shall apply to the registered voters at the general election.</para><para>(4) The recall procedure and special election provisions shall apply to the mayor and members of the city council of municipalities with a home rule charter notwithstanding any contrary provisions of the home rule charter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 375; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 874, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>