<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-1524"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1524</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Electioneering; circulation of petitions; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Electioneering means the deliberate, visible display or audible or physical dissemination of information for the purpose of advocating for or against:</para><para>(i) Any candidate on the ballot for the election at which such display or dissemination is occurring;</para><para>(ii) Any elected officeholder of a state constitutional office or federal office at the time of the election at which such display or dissemination is occurring;</para><para>(iii) Any political party on the ballot for the election at which such display or dissemination is occurring; or</para><para>(iv) Any measure on the ballot for the election at which such display or dissemination is occurring; and</para><para>(b) Information includes:</para><para>(i) Such a candidate's name, likeness, logo, or symbol;</para><para>(ii) Such a ballot measure's number, title, subject matter, logo, or symbol;</para><para>(iii) A button, hat, pencil, pen, shirt, sign, or sticker containing information prohibited by this section;</para><para>(iv) Audible information prohibited by this section; and</para><para>(v) Literature or any writing or drawing referring to a candidate, officeholder, or ballot measure described in subdivision (a) of this subsection.</para><para>(2) No judge or clerk of election or precinct or district inspector shall do any electioneering while acting as an election official.</para><para>(3) No person shall do any electioneering or circulate petitions within any polling place or any building designated for voters to cast ballots by the election commissioner or county clerk pursuant to the Election Act while the polling place or building is set up for voters to cast ballots or within two hundred feet of any such polling place or building except as otherwise provided in subsection (5) of this section.</para><para>(4) No person shall do any electioneering within two hundred feet of any secure ballot drop-box.</para><para>(5) Subject to any local ordinance, a person may display yard signs on private property within two hundred feet of a polling place or building designated for voters to cast ballots if the property is not under common ownership with the property on which the polling place or building is located.</para><para>(6) Any person violating this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 423; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 940, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB874, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 49. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>