<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1401</statuteno><catchline>Initiative petition; form.</catchline><para>The form of a petition for initiating any law or any amendment to the Constitution of Nebraska shall comply with the requirements of sections 32-628 and 32-1403 and shall be substantially as follows:</para><para>Initiative Petition</para><para>The object of this petition is to .......................... (Print a concise statement in large type of the legal effect of the filing of the petition and the object sought to be secured by submitting the measure to the voters).</para><para>To the Honorable ............................, Secretary of State for the State of Nebraska:</para><para>We, the undersigned residents of the State of Nebraska and the county of ............, respectfully demand that the following proposed law (or amendment to the Constitution of Nebraska as the case may be) shall be referred to the registered voters of the state for their approval or rejection at the general election to be held on the .... day of ........ 20...., and each for himself or herself says:</para><para>I have personally signed this petition on the date opposite my name;</para><para>I am a registered voter of the State of Nebraska and county of .......... and am qualified to sign this petition or I will be so registered and qualified on or before the date on which this petition is required to be filed with the Secretary of State; and</para><para>My printed name, date of birth, street and number or voting precinct, and city, village, or post office address are correctly written after my signature.</para><para>(Here follow numbered lines for signature, printed name, date of birth, date, street and number or voting precinct, and city, village, or post office address.)</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 383; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 460, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 813, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional amendments proposed by Legislature,</emphasis> procedure, see sections 49-201 to 49-211.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>