<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1522"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1522</statuteno><catchline>Ballots and other election documents; prohibited acts; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) A judge or clerk of election, a printer, or any other person entrusted with the custody or delivery of ballots, blanks, list of voters book and official summary of votes cast, card of instructions, or other required papers who knowingly and willfully (a) unlawfully opens or permits to be opened any sealed packages containing ballots, (b) gives or delivers to any person not lawfully entitled thereto an official ballot, or (c) unlawfully misplaces or carries away, negligently loses, permits to be taken away from him or her, fails to deliver, or destroys any such package of ballots or any ballot, blank, list of voters book and official summary of votes cast, card of instructions, or other required paper shall be guilty of a Class III felony.</para><para>(2) Any printer employed to print the official ballots or any person engaged in printing the same who knowingly and willfully (a) prints or causes or permits to be printed any official ballots printed otherwise than the copy for the same furnished by the election commissioner or county clerk, (b) prints any false or fraudulent ballots, (c) appropriates any of such ballots to himself or herself or gives, delivers, or knowingly permits any of such ballots to be taken by any person other than the election commissioner or county clerk, or (d) seals up or causes or permits to be sealed up or delivers to the election commissioner or county clerk a less number of ballots than the number endorsed thereon shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Any person who knowingly has in his or her possession any official ballot illegally obtained or attempts to vote any ballot other than the official ballot lawfully obtained shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 421. </para></source></law></legaldoc>