<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" statutenumber="32-1525"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1525</statuteno><catchline>Polling and interviews; poll watchers; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall conduct an exit poll, a public opinion poll, or any other interview with voters on election day seeking to determine voter preference within twenty feet of the entrance of any polling place or, if inside the polling place or building, within one hundred feet of any voting booth.</para><para>(2)(a) No poll watcher shall interfere with any voter in the preparation or casting of such voter's ballot or prevent any election worker from performing the worker's duties.</para><para>(b) A poll watcher shall not provide assistance to a voter as described in section 32-918 unless selected by the voter to provide assistance as provided in section 32-918.</para><para>(c) A poll watcher shall not engage in electioneering as defined in section 32-1524 while engaged in observing at a polling place.</para><para>(d) A poll watcher shall maintain a distance of at least eight feet from the sign-in table, the sign-in register, the polling booths, the ballot box, and any ballots which have not been cast, except that if the polling place is not large enough for a distance of eight feet, the judge of election shall post a notice of the minimum distance the poll watcher must maintain from the sign-in table, the sign-in register, the polling booths, the ballot box, and any ballots which have not been cast. The posted notice shall be clearly visible to the voters and shall be posted prior to the opening of the polls on election day. The minimum distance shall not be determined to exclude a poll watcher from being in the polling place.</para><para>(3) Any person violating this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 424; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1055, &#167; 18. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>