<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id176" statutenumber="32-1306"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1306</statuteno><catchline id="id179">Filing officer; notification required; recall election; when held.</catchline><para>(1) If the recall petition is found to be sufficient, the filing officer shall notify the official whose removal is sought and the governing body of the affected political subdivision that sufficient signatures have been gathered. Notification of the official sought to be removed shall be by any method specified in section 25-505.01 or, if notification cannot be made with reasonable diligence by any of the methods specified in section 25-505.01, by leaving such notice at the official's usual place of residence and mailing a copy by first-class mail to the official's last-known address.</para><para>(2) The governing body of the political subdivision shall, within twenty-one days after receipt of the notification from the filing officer pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, order an election. The date of the election shall be the first available date that complies with section 32-405 and that can be certified to the election commissioner or county clerk at least fifty days prior to the election, except that if any other election is to be held in that political subdivision within ninety days after such notification, the governing body of the political subdivision shall provide for the holding of the recall election on the same day.</para><para>(3) All resignations shall be tendered as provided in section 32-562. If the official whose removal is sought resigns before the recall election is held, the governing body may cancel the recall election if the governing body notifies the election commissioner or county clerk of the cancellation on or before the fourth Thursday prior to the election, otherwise the recall election shall be held as scheduled.</para><para>(4) If a filing officer is subject to a recall election, the Secretary of State shall conduct the recall election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 379; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 820, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB312, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB449, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1055, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 57. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>