<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Elections" id="id00" statutenumber="32-1524"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>32-1524</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Electioneering; dissemination of information or materials; circulation of petitions; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No judge or clerk of election or precinct or district inspector shall do any electioneering or disseminate information or materials advertising or advocating for or against any ballot measure while acting as an election official.</para><para>(2) No person shall do any electioneering, disseminate information or materials advertising or advocating for or against any ballot measure, or circulate petitions within any polling place or any building designated for voters to cast ballots by the election commissioner or county clerk pursuant to the Election Act while the polling place or building is set up for voters to cast ballots or within two hundred feet of the entrances to any such polling place or building except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(3) No person shall do any electioneering or disseminate information or materials advertising or advocating for or against any ballot measure within two hundred feet of any secure ballot drop-box.</para><para>(4) Subject to any local ordinance, a person may display yard signs on private real property within two hundred feet of a polling place or building designated for voters to cast ballots or a secure ballot drop-box if the property is not under common ownership with the property on which the polling place, building, or secure ballot drop-box is located.</para><para>(5) Any person violating this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 423; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 940, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB874, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 61. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>