
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" id="id5" statutenumber="1-111"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id7">1-111</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Fees, costs, and
penalties; collection; Certified Public Accountants Fund; created; use; investment;
civil penalties; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) All fees collected
under the Public Accountancy Act and all costs collected under subdivision
(8) of section 1-148 shall be remitted by the board to the State Treasurer
for credit to the Certified Public Accountants Fund which is hereby created.
Such fund shall, if and when specifically appropriated by the Legislature
during any biennium for that purpose, be paid out from time to time by the
State Treasurer upon warrants drawn by the Director of Administrative Services
on vouchers approved by the board, and such board and expense thereof shall
not be supported or paid from any other fund of the state. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund
at the direction of the Legislature through June 30, 2011. Any
money in the Certified Public Accountants Fund available for investment shall
be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) The board shall remit civil penalties collected under
subdivision (5) of section 1-148 to the State Treasurer for distribution in
accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 1, &#167; 6, p. 57; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 1, &#167; 1, p. 61; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 24, p. 2356; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 957, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>