<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="September 1, 2010">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" statutenumber="1-136"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-136</statuteno><catchline>Public accountant; permits; issuance;
fees; failure to renew; effect; inactive list.</catchline><para>(1) Permits
to engage in the practice of public accountancy in this state shall be issued
by the board to (a) persons who are holders of the certificate of certified
public accountant issued under sections 1-114 to 1-124 and who have met the
experience requirements of section 1-136.02, (b) partnerships
and limited liability companies of certified public accountants registered
under section 1-126, and (c) corporations registered under section 1-134
as long as all offices of such certificate holders or registrants in this
state for the practice of public accountancy are maintained and registered
as required under section 1-135.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except as provided in the case of permits subject to subdivision
(2)(b) of this section, the board shall charge an annual permit fee as established
by the board not to exceed one hundred fifty dollars. All permits subject
to this subdivision shall expire on June 30 of each year and may be renewed
annually for a period of one year by certificate holders and registrants in
good standing upon payment of an annual renewal fee as established by the
board not to exceed one hundred fifty dollars. The board may prorate the fee
for any permit subject to this subdivision issued for less than one year.</para>
<para>(b) The board shall charge a biennial permit fee as established by the
board not to exceed three hundred dollars for permits issued under subdivision (1)(a) of this section. All permits
subject to this subdivision shall expire on June 30 of the first calendar
year after the calendar year of issuance in which the age of the certificate
holder or the registrant becomes divisible by two, and may be renewed biennially
for a period of two years by certificate holders and registrants in good standing
upon payment of a biennial renewal fee as established by the board not to
exceed three hundred dollars. The board may prorate the fee for any permit
subject to this subdivision issued for less than two years.</para>
<para>(3) Failure of a certificate holder or registrant to apply for a permit
within (a) three years from the expiration date of the permit last obtained
or renewed or (b) three years from the date upon which the certificate holder
or registrant was issued a certificate or registration if no permit was ever
issued to such person shall deprive him or her of the right to issuance or
renewal of a permit unless the board, in its discretion, determines such failure
to have been excusable. In such case the renewal fee or the fee for the issuance
of the original permit, as the case may be, shall be such amount as established
by the board not to exceed three hundred dollars.</para>
<para>(4) Any certificate holder or registrant who has not lost his or her
right to issuance or renewal of a permit and who is not actively engaged in
the practice of public accountancy in this state may file a written application
with the board to be classified as inactive. A person so classified shall
not be issued a permit or be deemed the holder of a permit but shall be carried
upon an inactive roll to be maintained by the board upon the payment of an
inactive fee as established by the board not to exceed fifty percent of the
fee charged persons actively engaged in the practice of public accountancy
as provided in this section. A person so classified shall not be deprived
of the right to the issuance or renewal of a permit and may, upon application
to the board and upon payment of the current permit fee, be issued a current
permit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 1, &#167; 31, p. 65; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 1, &#167; 1, p. 57; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 961, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 290, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 278, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 92, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 473, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 869, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 214, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 17.</para></source><annotation><para>A public accountancy "certificate holder or registrant who has not lost his or her right to issuance or renewal of a permit," who may be classified as inactive pursuant to subsection (4) of this section, is a person who is otherwise entitled to issuance of a permit under the requirements set forth in the Public Accountancy Act. Forget v. State, 265 Neb. 488, 658 N.W.2d 271 (2003).</para></annotation> </law>
</legaldoc>