<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" statutenumber="1-136.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>1-136.02</statuteno><catchline>Public accountant; permit; when issued.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The board shall issue a permit under subdivision (1)(a) of section 1-136 to a holder of a certificate as a certified public accountant when such holder has completed:</para><para>(i) A postbaccalaureate degree and one year of experience;</para><para>(ii) A baccalaureate degree plus an additional thirty credit hours of education and one year of experience; or</para><para>(iii) A baccalaureate degree and two years of experience.</para><para>(b) The degree required under this subsection shall be conferred by a college or university accredited by an accrediting agency recognized by the United States Department of Education or a similar agency as determined to be acceptable by the board. The degree program shall include the accounting subject areas or equivalent to be determined by the board.</para><para>(c) The experience acquired to satisfy the requirement under this subsection shall be satisfactory to the board and shall include providing any type of service or advice involving the use of accounting, attest, compilation, management advisory, financial advisory, tax, or consulting skills. The experience shall be under the supervision of an active certified public accountant who is the holder of a permit issued under subdivision (1)(a) of section 1-136 or the equivalent issued by another state. The experience may be gained through employment in public practice, government, industry, or academia as acceptable to the board.</para><para>(2) The board shall issue a permit under subdivision (1)(a) of section 1-136 to a holder of a reciprocal certificate issued under section 1-124 upon a showing that:</para><para>(a) The applicant meets all current requirements in this state for issuance of a permit at the time the application is made; and</para><para>(b) At the time of the application for a permit, the applicant, within the ten years immediately preceding application, met the experience requirement in subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 290, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 41, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB24, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB27, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB853, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB56, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB854, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB718, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>