<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="September 1, 2010">Sec. 19.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" statutenumber="1-136.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>1-136.02</statuteno><catchline>Permit; when issued.</catchline>
<para>(1) The board shall issue a permit under subdivision (1)(a) of section
1-136 to a holder of a certificate as a certified public accountant when such
holder has had:</para>
<para>(a) Two years of public accounting experience satisfactory to the board,
in any state, (i) in practice as a certified public accountant, (ii) in employment as a staff accountant
by anyone engaging in the practice of public accountancy, or (iii) in any
combination of either of such types of experience;</para>
<para>(b) Three years of auditing experience satisfactory to the board in
the office of the Auditor of Public Accounts or in the Department of Revenue;
or</para>
<para>(c) Experience gained through employment by the federal government as
a special agent or an internal revenue agent in the Internal Revenue Service,
a degree from a college or university of recognized standing, and certification
by a District Director of Internal Revenue that such person has had at least
three and one-half years of field experience as a special agent or internal
revenue agent.</para>
<para>(2) The board shall issue a permit under subdivision (1)(a) of section
1-136 to a holder of a reciprocal certificate issued under section 1-124 upon
a showing that:</para>
<para>(a) He or she meets all current requirements in this state for issuance
of a permit at the time the application is made; and</para>
<para>(b) At the time of the application for a permit the applicant, within
the ten years immediately preceding application, has had at least two years'
experience in the practice of public accountancy as a sole proprietor or as
a staff accountant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 290, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 41, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB24, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>