<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" statutenumber="1-126"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-126</statuteno><catchline>Certified public accountant; partnership
or limited liability company; registration; requirements.</catchline><para>A
partnership or limited liability company engaged in this state in the practice
of public accountancy may register with the board as a partnership or limited
liability company of certified public accountants if it meets the following
requirements:</para>
<para>(1) At least one partner of the partnership or member of the limited
liability company shall be a certified public accountant of this state in
good standing;</para>
<para>(2) Each partner of the partnership who is a certified public accountant
or member of the limited liability company who is a certified public accountant
personally engaged within this state in the practice of public accountancy
as a partner or member thereof shall be a certified public accountant of this
state in good standing;</para>
<para>(3) Each partner of the partnership who is a certified public accountant
or member of the limited liability company who is a certified public accountant
shall be a certified public accountant of some state in good standing; and</para>
<para>(4) Each resident manager in charge of an office of the partnership
or limited liability company in this state shall be a certified public accountant
of this state in good standing.</para>
<para>An application for such registration shall be made upon the affidavit
of a general partner of such partnership or a member of such limited liability
company who is a certified public accountant of this state in good standing.
The board shall in each case determine whether the applicant is eligible for
registration.</para>
<para>A partnership or limited liability company which is so registered and
which holds a permit issued under subdivision (1)(b) of
section 1-136 may use the words certified public accountants or the abbreviation
C.P.A.'s in connection with its partnership or limited liability company name.</para>
<para>Notification shall be given to the board, pursuant to board rules and
regulations, regarding the admission to or withdrawal of a partner from any
partnership or a member from any limited liability company so registered.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 1, &#167; 21, p. 61; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 957, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>