<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" statutenumber="1-106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>1-106</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Public Accountancy Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Board means the Nebraska State Board of Public Accountancy;</para><para>(2) Certificate means a certificate issued under sections 1-114 to 1-124;</para><para>(3) Firm means a partnership, limited liability company, or corporation engaged in the practice of public accountancy in this state entitled to register with the board or a proprietorship engaged in the practice of public accountancy in this state;</para><para>(4) Partnership includes, but is not limited to, a limited liability partnership;</para><para>(5) Peer review means a review of one or more aspects of the professional work of a firm that either or both performs attest engagements or performs compilations by an active certified public accountant who is the holder of a permit issued under subdivision (1)(a) of section 1-136 or the equivalent issued by another state and who is not affiliated with the firm being reviewed;</para><para>(6) Permit means a permit to engage in the practice of public accountancy in this state issued under section 1-136;</para><para>(7) Practice privilege means the privilege of an accountant to practice public accountancy or hold himself or herself out as a certified public accountant in this state in accordance with section 1-125.01;</para><para>(8) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, or any territory or insular possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States; and</para><para>(9) Temporary practice privilege means the privilege of a foreign accountant to temporarily practice public accountancy in this state in accordance with section 1-125.02.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 1, &#167; 1, p. 55; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB159, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>