<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="September 1, 2010">Sec. 21.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Accountants" statutenumber="1-137"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-137</statuteno><catchline>Individual certificates, practice privilege, temporary practice
privilege, registration, and permits; disciplinary action; grounds.</catchline>
<para>After notice and hearing as provided in sections 1-140 to 1-149, the
board may take disciplinary action as provided in section 1-148 for any one
or any combination of the following causes:</para>
<para>(1) Fraud or deceit in obtaining a certificate as a certified public accountant or the practice privilege or temporary practice privilege,
registration, or a permit under the Public Accountancy Act;</para>
<para>(2) Dishonesty, fraud, or gross negligence in the practice of public
accountancy;</para>
<para>(3) Violation of any of the provisions of sections 1-151 to 1-161;</para>
<para>(4) Violation of a rule of professional conduct adopted and promulgated
by the board under the authority granted by the act;</para>
<para>(5) Conviction of a felony under the laws of any state or of the United
States;</para>
<para>(6) Conviction of any crime, an element of which is dishonesty or fraud,
under the laws of any state or of the United States;</para>
<para>(7) Cancellation, revocation, suspension, or refusal to renew authority
to practice as a certified public accountant or a public accountant in any
other state, for any cause other than failure to pay a registration fee in
such other state;</para>
<para>(8) Suspension or revocation of the right to practice before any state
or federal agency; or</para>
<para>(9) Failure of a certificate holder or registrant to obtain a permit
issued under section 1-136, within either (a) three years from the expiration
date of the permit last obtained or renewed by the certificate holder or registrant
or (b) three years from the date upon which the certificate holder or registrant
was issued his or her certificate or registration if no permit was ever issued
to him or her, unless under section 1-136 such failure was excused by the
board pursuant to section 1-136.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 1, &#167; 32, p. 66; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 92, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 41, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 114, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB31, &#167; 21.</para></source><annotation><para>When a certified public accountant is an officer and shareholder of a corporation, the accountant's actions related to the corporation may reflect adversely on the accountant's fitness to practice as a certified public accountant and be subject to discipline by the Board of Public Accountancy. Zwygart v. State, 273 Neb. 406, 730 N.W.2d 103 (2007).</para><para>The power to revoke the certificate of a certified public accountant is in the State Board of Public Accountancy, not in the executive director. Bohling v. State Bd. of Pub. Accountancy, 243 Neb. 666, 501 N.W.2d 714 (1993).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>