<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id300"><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-605.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>45-605.01</statuteno><catchline>Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry; licensure and registration; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Effective October 1, 2020, or within one year after the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry is capable of processing licenses issued under the Collection Agency Act, whichever is later, the board, upon its discretion, may require licensees under the act to be licensed and registered through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. In order to carry out this requirement, the board may participate in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. For this purpose, the board may establish, by adopting and promulgating rules and regulations or by order, requirements as necessary. The requirements may include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) Any information as deemed necessary by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry;</para><para>(b) The payment of fees to apply for or renew a license provided for in sections 45-606 and 45-620 and any processing fee allowed under this section through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry;</para><para>(c) The setting or resetting, as necessary, of renewal processing or reporting dates; and</para><para>(d) Amending or surrendering a license or any other such activities as the board deems necessary for participation in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(2) In order to fulfill the purposes of the Nebraska Collection Agency Act, the board may establish relationships or contracts with the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry or other entities designated by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry to collect and maintain records and process transaction fees or other fees related to licensees or other persons subject to the act. The board may allow such system to collect licensing fees on behalf of the board and allow such system to collect a processing fee for the services of the system directly from each licensee or applicant for a license.</para><para>(3) The board shall regularly report enforcement actions and other relevant information to the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(4) The board shall establish a process whereby applicants and licensees may challenge information entered into the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry by the board.</para><para>(5) The board shall ensure that the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry adopts a privacy, data security, and breach of security of the system notification policy. The board shall make available upon written request a copy of the contract between the board and the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry pertaining to the breach of security of the system provisions.</para><para>(6) Upon written request, the board shall provide the most recently available audited financial report of the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>