<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="45-728"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-728</statuteno><catchline>License; application; form; fee; use
of nationwide registry.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for a license shall
apply on a form prescribed by the director.</para>
<para>(2) The application for a license as a mortgage loan originator shall
be accompanied by an application fee of one hundred fifty dollars, plus the
cost of the criminal history background check required by subsection (3) of
this section and any processing fee allowed under subsection (2) of section
45-748.</para>
<para>(3) In connection with an application for licensing as a mortgage loan
originator, the applicant shall, at a minimum, furnish to the Nationwide Mortgage
Licensing System and Registry information concerning the applicant's identity,
including the following:</para>
<para>(a) Fingerprints for submission to the Federal Bureau of Investigation
and any other governmental agency or entity authorized to receive such information
for a state, national, and international criminal history background check;
and</para>
<para>(b) Personal history and experience in a format prescribed
by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry, including the submission
of authorization for the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry
and the director to obtain the following:</para>
<para>(i) An independent credit report obtained from a consumer reporting
agency described in 15 U.S.C. 1681a(p), as such
section existed on January 1, 2010; and</para>
<para>(ii) Information related to any administrative, civil, or criminal findings
by any governmental jurisdiction.</para>
<para>(4) For the purposes of this section and in order to reduce the points
of contact which the Federal Bureau of Investigation may have to maintain
for purposes of subdivisions (3)(a) and (3)(b)(ii) of this section, the director
may use the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry as a channeling
agent for requesting information from and distributing information to the
United States Department of Justice or any other governmental agency.</para>
<para>(5) For the purposes of this section and in order to reduce the points
of contact which the director may have to maintain for purposes of subdivisions
(3)(b)(i) and (3)(b)(ii) of this section, the director may use the Nationwide
Mortgage Licensing System and Registry as a channeling agent for requesting
and distributing information to and from any source so directed by the director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB892, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>