<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-191.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-191.08</statuteno><catchline>Director; enforcement powers.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The director in his or her discretion may make such investigations within or without this state as necessary to determine whether any person has violated or is about to violate sections 45-189 to 45-191.11 or to aid in the enforcement of such sections or in the adopting or promulgating of rules, regulations, and forms under such sections. In the discretion of the director, the actual expense of any such investigation may be charged to any person who is the subject of such investigation.</para><para>(b) The department may publish information concerning any violation of such sections or any rule, regulation, or order of the department.</para><para>(c) For purposes of any investigation or proceeding under such sections, the director or any officer designated by him or her may administer oaths and affirmations, subpoena witnesses, compel their attendance, take evidence, and require the production of any books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, agreements, or other documents or records which the director deems relevant or material to the inquiry.</para><para>(2)(a) In case of contumacy by or refusal to obey a subpoena issued to any person, any court of competent jurisdiction, upon application by the director, may issue an order to that person requiring him or her to appear before the director or an officer designated by the director to produce documentary evidence or to give evidence touching on a matter under investigation or in question. Any failure to obey an order of the court may be punished by the court as a contempt of court.</para><para>(b) The request for order of compliance may be addressed to either (i) the district court of Lancaster County or the district court in the county where service may be obtained on the person refusing to testify or produce, if the person is within this state, or (ii) the appropriate district court of this state having jurisdiction over the person refusing to testify or produce, if the person is outside this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 270, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 