<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-191.09"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>45-191.09</statuteno><catchline>Director; summary cease and desist order; when; other enforcement measures; collection of fines and costs; hearing; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) The director may summarily order a loan broker to cease and desist from acting as a loan broker or from the use of certain forms or practices relating to the loan broker's activities if the order is in the public interest and the director finds:</para><para>(a) The disclosure statement on file is incomplete in any material respect or contains any statement which was, in light of the circumstances under which it was made, false or misleading with respect to any material fact;</para><para>(b) The loan broker has willfully violated or willfully failed to comply with any provision of sections 45-189 to 45-191.11;</para><para>(c) There has been a substantial failure to comply with any of the provisions of such sections;</para><para>(d) The continued use of certain forms or practices relating to the loan broker's activity would constitute a misrepresentation, deceit, or fraud upon the consumer; or</para><para>(e) Any person identified in the required disclosure statement has been convicted of an offense described in subdivision (2)(i)(i) of section 45-191.01 or is subject to an order or has had a civil judgment entered against him or her as described in subdivision (2)(i)(ii) or (2)(i)(iii) of section 45-191.01 and the involvement of such person in the loan broker's business creates an unreasonable risk to prospective borrowers.</para><para>(2) If the director believes, whether or not based upon an investigation conducted under section 45-191.08, that any person or loan broker has engaged in or is about to engage in any act or practice constituting a violation of any provision of sections 45-189 to 45-191.11 or any rule, regulation, or order under such sections, the director may:</para><para>(a) Issue a cease and desist order;</para><para>(b) Impose a fine not to exceed one thousand dollars per violation, in addition to costs of the investigation; or</para><para>(c) Initiate an action in any court of competent jurisdiction to enjoin such acts or practices and to enforce compliance with such sections or any order under such sections.</para><para>(3) Upon a proper showing a permanent or temporary injunction, restraining order, or writ of mandamus shall be granted. The director shall not be required to post a bond.</para><para>(4)(a) Any fines and costs imposed pursuant to this section shall be in addition to all other penalties imposed by the laws of this state. The department shall collect the fines and costs and remit them to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit the costs to the Securities Act Cash Fund and distribute the fines in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(b) If a person fails to pay the fine or costs of the investigation referred to in this subsection, a lien in the amount of the fine and costs may be imposed upon all of the assets and property of such person in this state and may be recovered by suit by the department. Failure of the person to pay a fine and costs shall constitute a separate violation of sections 45-189 to 45-191.11.</para><para>(5) Upon entry of an order pursuant to this section, the director shall promptly notify all persons to whom such order is directed that it has been entered and of the reasons for such order and that any person to whom the order is directed may request a hearing in writing within fifteen business days of the issuance of the order. Upon receipt of a written request, the matter shall be set down for hearing to commence within thirty business days after the receipt unless the parties consent to a later date or the hearing officer sets a later date for good cause. If a hearing is not requested within fifteen business days from the issuance of the order and none is ordered by the director, the order shall automatically become final and shall remain in effect until it is modified or vacated by the director. If a hearing is requested or ordered, the director, after notice and hearing, shall enter his or her written findings of fact and conclusions of law and may affirm, modify, or vacate the order.</para><para>(6) The director may vacate or modify a cease and desist order if he or she finds that the conditions which caused its entry have changed or that it is otherwise in the public interest to do so.</para><para>(7) Any person aggrieved by a final order of the director may appeal the order. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 270, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 24. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>