<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-601"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>45-601</statuteno><catchline>Act, how cited; collection agency; license required; violation; penalty; foreign agency; communication authorized.</catchline><para>Sections 45-601 to 45-622 shall be known and may be cited as the Collection Agency Act.</para><para>No person, firm, corporation, or association shall conduct or operate a collection agency or do a collection agency business as defined in the act until he, she, or it has secured a license as provided in the act. Any person, firm, corporation, or association conducting or operating such a collection agency or doing such a collection agency business without a license shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor for each day that such unlawful business is conducted. Any officer or agent of a firm, corporation, or association who personally participates in any violation of the act shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para><para>Nothing contained in this section shall be construed to require a regular employee of a collection agency duly licensed as such in this state to procure a collection agency license.</para><para>Nothing in the act shall be construed to prohibit a person, firm, corporation, or association regulated as a collection agency in another state and residing in another state from communicating with a debtor in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 500, &#167; 1, p. 1592; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 299; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 81-8,158; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 471, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 261, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 25. </para><operativedate>November 14, 2020</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Exemptions from Credit Services Organization Act,</emphasis> see section 45-803.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Failure to report and pay collections made within specified time justified revocation of license. State ex rel. Hartman v. Weiss, 181 Neb. 685, 150 N.W.2d 264 (1967).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>