<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="45-724"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-724</statuteno><catchline>Surety bond; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, an applicant
for a mortgage banker license or registration shall file with the department
a surety bond in the amount of one hundred thousand dollars, furnished by
a surety company authorized to do business in the State of Nebraska. The surety
bond also shall cover all mortgage loan originators who are employees or independent
agents of the applicant. The bond shall be for the use of the State of Nebraska
and any Nebraska resident who may have claims or causes of action against
the applicant or against an individual who is a mortgage loan originator employed
by, or in an independent agent relationship with, the applicant. Submission
of a rider to an existing bond indicating that the required coverage is outstanding
and evidencing the beneficiaries required in this subsection shall
satisfy the requirements of this section. The bond or a substitute bond shall
remain in effect during all periods of licensing or registration.</para>
<para>(2) Upon filing of the mortgage report of condition required by section
45-726, a mortgage banker licensee or registrant shall maintain or increase
its surety bond to reflect the total dollar amount of the closed residential
mortgage loans originated in this state in the preceding calendar year in accordance with the following
table. A licensee or registrant may
decrease its surety bond in accordance with the following table if the surety
bond required is less than the amount of the surety bond on file with the
department.</para>
<para><table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1.24*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="0.76*" />
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Dollar Amount of Closed </entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Residential Mortgage Loans</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Surety Bond Required</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$0.00 to $5,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$100,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$5,000,000.01 to $10,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$125,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$10,000,000.01 to $25,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$150,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Over $25,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$200,000.00</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></para>
<para>(3) Should the department determine that a mortgage banker licensee
or registrant does not maintain a surety bond in the amount required by subsection
(2) of this section, the department shall give written notification to the
mortgage banker licensee or registrant requiring him, her, or it to increase
the surety bond within thirty days to the amount required by subsection (2)
of this section.</para>
<para>(4) At any time the director may require the filing of a new or supplemental
bond in the form as provided in subsection (1) of this section if he or she
determines that the bond filed under subsection
(1) or (2) of this section is exhausted or is inadequate for any
reason, including the financial condition of the licensee, the registrant, or the applicant for a license or registration. The new
or supplemental bond shall not exceed one million dollars.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 272, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 217, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 218, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2008, &#167; 45-709; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB892, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>