<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="45-727"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-727</statuteno><catchline>Mortgage loan originator; license
required; loan processor or underwriter; license required.</catchline><para>(1) An individual, unless specifically
exempted from the Residential Mortgage Licensing Act under section 45-703,
shall not engage in, or offer to engage in, the business of a mortgage loan
originator with respect to any residential real estate or dwelling located
or intended to be located in this state without first obtaining and maintaining
annually a license under the act. Each licensed mortgage loan originator shall
obtain and maintain a valid unique identifier issued by the Nationwide Mortgage
Licensing System and Registry.</para>
<para>(2) In order to facilitate
an orderly transition to licensing and minimize disruption in the mortgage
marketplace, the effective date for subsection (1) of this section is July
31, 2010.</para><para>(3)
An independent agent shall not engage in the activities as a loan processor
or underwriter unless such independent agent loan processor or underwriter
obtains and maintains a license under subsection (1) of this section. Each
independent agent loan processor or underwriter licensed as a mortgage loan
originator shall obtain and maintain a valid unique identifier issued by the
Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(4) For the purposes of implementing
an orderly and efficient licensing process, the director may adopt and promulgate
licensing rules or regulations and interim procedures for licensing and acceptance
of applications. For previously registered or licensed individuals, the director
may establish expedited review and licensing procedures.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>