
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-606</statuteno><catchline>License; application; fees; financial statement; form.</catchline><para>(1) Any person, firm, corporation, or association desiring to engage in this state in the collection business under the Collection Agency Act shall make written and sworn application for such license to the board upon a form to be prescribed by the board, which application shall be accompanied by an investigation fee of not to exceed two hundred fifty dollars and any processing fee allowed under section 45-605.01. The amount of the investigation fee shall be fixed by the board and shall not exceed the amount actually necessary to sustain the administration and enforcement of the act. Such application shall be accompanied by a duly verified financial statement of the applicant in form prescribed by the board. The Secretary of State shall remit the fees received pursuant to this section to the State Treasurer for credit to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para><para>(2) The board may require applicants to utilize the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry or an entity designated by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry for the processing of applications and fees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 500, &#167; 10, p. 1596; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 639, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 81-8,167; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 471, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 206, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 261, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 14. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB909, section 28, with LB910, section 14, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB909 became operative November 14, 2020. Changes made by LB910 became operative July 1, 2021.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>