<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id00" statutenumber="45-921"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-921</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Alleged violations; director; powers and duties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The director may examine or investigate complaints about or reports of alleged violations of the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act or any rule, regulation, or order of the director thereunder. The director may order the actual cost of such examination or investigation to be paid by the person who is the subject of the examination or investigation, whether the alleged violator is licensed or not.</para><para id="id00">(2) The director may publish information concerning any violation of the act or any rule, regulation, or order of the director under the act.</para><para id="id00">(3) For purposes of any investigation, examination, or proceeding under the act, the director may administer oaths and affirmations, subpoena witnesses, compel their attendance, take evidence, and require the production of any books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, agreements, or other documents or records which the director deems relevant or material to the examination, investigation, or proceeding.</para><para id="id00">(4) In the case of contumacy by or refusal to obey a subpoena issued to any person, the district court of Lancaster County, upon application by the director, may issue an order requiring such person to appear before the director and to produce documentary evidence if so ordered to give evidence on the matter under investigation or in question. Failure to obey the order of the court may be punished by the court as contempt.</para><para id="id00">(5) Upon receipt by a licensee of a notice of investigation or inquiry request for information from the department, the licensee shall respond within twenty-one calendar days. Each day a licensee fails to respond as required by this subsection shall constitute a separate violation.</para><para id="id00">(6) If the director finds, after notice and opportunity for hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, that any person has violated subsection (5) of this section, the director may order such person to pay (a) an administrative fine of not more than two thousand dollars for each separate violation and (b) the costs of investigation. The department shall remit fines collected under this subsection to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para id="id00">(7) If a person fails to pay an administrative fine and the costs of investigation ordered pursuant to subsection (6) of this section, a lien in the amount of such fine and costs may be imposed upon all assets and property of such person in this state and may be recovered in a civil action by the director. The lien shall attach to the real property of such person when notice of the lien is filed and indexed against the real property in the office of the register of deeds in the county where the real property is located. The lien shall attach to any other property of such person when notice of the lien is filed against the property in the manner prescribed by law. Failure of the person to pay such fine and costs shall constitute a separate violation of the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB194, &#167; 16. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>