<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id977"><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" statutenumber="45-356"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-356</statuteno><catchline>Acquisition of licensee; notice; filing fee; director; duties; disapproval; grounds; notice; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) No person acting personally or as an agent shall acquire control of any licensee under the Nebraska Installment Sales Act without first (a) giving thirty days' notice to the department on a form prescribed by the department of such proposed acquisition and (b) paying a filing fee of one hundred fifty dollars and any processing fee allowed under subsection (2) of section 45-354.</para><para>(2) The director, upon receipt of such notice, shall act upon the acquisition within thirty days, and unless he or she disapproves of the proposed acquisition within such period of time, the acquisition shall become effective on the thirty-first day after receipt without the director's approval, except that the director may extend the thirty-day period an additional thirty days if, in his or her judgment, any material information submitted is substantially inaccurate or the acquiring party has not furnished all the information required by the department.</para><para>(3) An acquisition may become effective prior to the expiration of the disapproval period if the director issues written notice of his or her intent not to disapprove the action.</para><para>(4)(a) The director may disapprove any proposed acquisition if:</para><para>(i) The financial condition of any acquiring person is such as might jeopardize the financial stability of the acquired licensee;</para><para>(ii) The character and general fitness of any acquiring person or of any of the proposed management personnel indicate that the acquired installment sales licensee would not be operated honestly, fairly, or efficiently within the purpose of the Nebraska Installment Sales Act; or</para><para>(iii) Any acquiring person neglects, fails, or refuses to furnish all information required by the department.</para><para>(b) The director shall notify the acquiring party in writing of disapproval of the acquisition. The notice shall provide a statement of the basis for the disapproval.</para><para>(c) Within fifteen business days after receipt of written notice of disapproval, the acquiring party may make a written request for a hearing on the proposed acquisition in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department under the Administrative Procedure Act. The director shall, by order, approve or disapprove the proposed acquisition on the basis of the record made at the hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB778, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>