<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-905"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-905</statuteno><catchline>Application for license; form; contents; criminal history record information check.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for a license shall submit an application, under oath, to the director on forms prescribed by the director. The forms shall contain such information as the director may prescribe, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(a) The applicant's financial condition;</para><para>(b) The qualifications and business history of the applicant and of its officers, directors, shareholders, partners, or members;</para><para>(c) Whether the applicant or any of its officers, directors, shareholders, partners, or members have ever been convicted of any (i) misdemeanor involving any aspect of a delayed deposit services business or any business of a similar nature or (ii) felony;</para><para>(d) Whether the applicant or any of its officers, directors, shareholders, partners, or members have ever been permanently or temporarily enjoined by a court of competent jurisdiction from engaging in or continuing any conduct or practice involving any aspect of a delayed deposit services business or any business of a similar nature;</para><para>(e) A description of the applicant's proposed method of doing business; and</para><para>(f) If the applicant is an individual, the applicant's social security number.</para><para>(2) The director shall cause a criminal history record information check to be conducted of the applicant, its officers, directors, shareholders, partners, or members. The direct cost of the criminal history record information check shall be paid by the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 119. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 