<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id78"  statutenumber="45-907"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>45-907</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Application; notice of filing; publication; hearing; investigation; costs.</catchline><para>(1) When an application for a delayed deposit services business license has been accepted by the director as substantially complete, notice of the filing of the application shall be published by the director for three successive weeks in a legal newspaper published in or of general circulation in the county where the applicant proposes to operate the delayed deposit services business. A public hearing shall be held on each application except as provided in subsection (2) of this section. The date for hearing shall not be less than thirty days after the last publication. Written protest against the issuance of the license may be filed with the department by any person not less than five days before the date set for hearing. The director, in his or her discretion, may grant a continuance. The costs of the hearing shall be paid by the applicant. The director may investigate the propriety of the issuance of a license to the applicant. The costs of such investigation shall be paid by the applicant.</para><para>(2) The director may waive the hearing requirements of subsection (1) of this section if (a) the applicant has held and operated under a license to engage in the delayed deposit services business in Nebraska pursuant to the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act for at least three calendar years immediately prior to the filing of the application, (b) no written protest against the issuance of the license has been filed with the department within fifteen days after publication of a notice of the filing of the application one time in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where the applicant proposes to operate the delayed deposit services business, and (c) in the judgment of the director, the experience, character, and general fitness of the applicant warrant the belief that the applicant will comply with the act.</para><para>(3) The expense of any publication made pursuant to this section shall be paid by the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB194, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>