<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id474"><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-905.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-905.01</statuteno><catchline>Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry; licensees; requirements; director; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) On and after January 1, 2021, licensees under the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act are required to be licensed and registered through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. In order to carry out this requirement, the department is authorized to participate in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. For this purpose, the director may establish requirements as necessary by adopting and promulgating rules and regulations or by order. The requirements may include, but are not limited to:</para><para>(a) Background checks of applicants and licensees, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(i) Fingerprints of any principal officer, director, partner, member, or sole proprietor submitted to the Federal Bureau of Investigation and any other governmental agency or entity authorized to receive such information for a state, national, and international criminal history record information check;</para><para>(ii) Checks of civil or administrative records;</para><para>(iii) Checks of an applicant's or a licensee's credit history; or</para><para>(iv) Any other information as deemed necessary by the director;</para><para>(b) The payment of fees to apply for or renew a license through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry;</para><para>(c) The setting or resetting, as necessary, of renewal processing or reporting dates; and</para><para>(d) Amending or surrendering a license or any other such activities as the director deems necessary for participation in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(2) In order to fulfill the purposes of the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act, the department may contract with the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry or other entities designated by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry to collect and maintain records and process transaction fees or other fees related to applicants, licensees, or other persons subject to the act. The department may allow such system to collect licensing fees on behalf of the department and may allow such system to collect a processing fee for the services of the system directly from each applicant or licensee.</para><para>(3) The director shall regularly report enforcement actions and other relevant information to the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(4) The director shall establish a process whereby applicants and licensees may challenge information entered by the director into the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(5) The department shall ensure that the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry adopts a privacy, data security, and breach of security of the system notification policy. The director shall make available upon written request a copy of such policy and the contract between the department and the system.</para><para>(6) Upon written request the department shall provide the most recently available audited financial report of the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(7) The director may use the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry as a channeling agent for requesting information from and distributing information to the United States Department of Justice or any other governmental agency in order to reduce the points of contact which the Federal Bureau of Investigation may have to maintain for purposes of subsection (5) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 39. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>