  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-1,113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1,113</statuteno><catchline>Action or defense based on credit agreement; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A debtor or a creditor may not maintain an action or assert a defense in an action based on a credit agreement unless the credit agreement is in writing, expresses consideration, sets forth the relevant terms and conditions of the credit agreement, and is signed by the creditor and by the debtor.</para><para>(2) Subsection (1) of this section shall not apply to (a) credit extended on an account as defined in section 4-104, Uniform Commercial Code, (b) loans initiated by credit card or other type of transaction card, or (c) credit agreements as defined in subdivision (1)(a)(ii) of section 45-1,112 unless the creditor, at the time of the initial loan of money or grant or extension of credit, has given to the debtor a written notice, signed or initialed by the debtor, which contains substantially the following language: A credit agreement must be in writing to be enforceable under Nebraska law. To protect you and us from any misunderstandings or disappointments, any contract, promise, undertaking, or offer to forebear repayment of money or to make any other financial accommodation in connection with this loan of money or grant or extension of credit, or any amendment of, cancellation of, waiver of, or substitution for any or all of the terms or provisions of any instrument or document executed in connection with this loan of money or grant or extension of credit, must be in writing to be effective.</para><para>(3) This section shall not be construed to limit or bar the recovery of money owed or collateral securing a loan in any way.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 606, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1199, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>The credit agreement statute of frauds is not coextensive with the general statute of frauds with all the common-law exceptions. Synergy4 Enters. v. Pinnacle Bank, 290 Neb. 241, 859 N.W.2d 552 (2015).</para><para>This section supersedes the common-law theory of promissory estoppel insofar as it applies to unwritten credit agreements or oral promises to loan money or extend credit. Synergy4 Enters. v. Pinnacle Bank, 290 Neb. 241, 859 N.W.2d 552 (2015).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 