<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-807"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-807</statuteno><catchline>Written statement to buyer; contents; credit services organization; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Before executing a contract or agreement with or receiving money or other valuable consideration from a buyer, a credit services organization shall provide the buyer with a written statement containing:</para><para>(a) A complete and detailed description of the services to be performed by the credit services organization for the buyer and the total cost of the services;</para><para>(b) A statement explaining the buyer's right to proceed against the surety bond or surety account required by section 45-805;</para><para>(c) The name and address of the surety company that issued the bond or the name and address of the depository and the trustee and the account number of the surety account;</para><para>(d) A complete and accurate statement of the buyer's right to review any file on the buyer maintained by a consumer reporting agency as provided by the Fair Credit Reporting Act, 15 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.;</para><para>(e) A statement that the buyer's file is available for review at no charge on request made to the consumer reporting agency within thirty days after the date of receipt of notice that credit has been denied and that the buyer's file is available for a minimal charge at any other time;</para><para>(f) A complete and accurate statement of the buyer's right to dispute directly with the consumer reporting agency the completeness or accuracy of any item contained in a file on the buyer maintained by the consumer reporting agency;</para><para>(g) A statement that accurate information cannot be permanently removed from the files of a consumer reporting agency;</para><para>(h) A complete and accurate statement of when consumer information becomes obsolete and of when consumer reporting agencies are prevented from issuing reports containing obsolete information; and</para><para>(i) A complete and accurate statement of the availability of nonprofit credit counseling services.</para><para>(2) The credit services organization shall maintain on file, for a period of two years after the date the statement is provided, an exact copy of the statement, signed by the buyer, acknowledging receipt of the statement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 292, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>