<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="45-734"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>45-734</statuteno><catchline>Mortgage loan originator license;
inactive status; duration; renewal; reactivation.</catchline><para>(1) A mortgage
loan originator whose license is placed on inactive status under this section
shall not act as a mortgage loan originator in this state until such time
as the license is reactivated.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall place a mortgage loan originator license on
inactive status upon the occurrence of one of the following:</para>
<para>(a) Upon receipt of a notice from either the licensed mortgage banker,
registrant, installment loan company, or mortgage loan originator that the
mortgage loan originator's relationship as an employee or independent agent
of a licensed mortgage banker or installment loan company has been terminated;</para>
<para>(b) Upon the cancellation of the employing licensed mortgage banker's
license pursuant to section 45-742 or upon the cancellation of the employing
installment loan company's license pursuant to subdivision (3)(b) of section
45-1033 for failure to maintain the required surety bond;</para>
<para>(c) Upon the voluntary surrender of the employing licensed mortgage
banker's license pursuant to section 45-742 or upon the voluntary surrender
of the employing installment loan company's license pursuant to section 45-1032;</para>
<para>(d) Upon the expiration of the employing licensed mortgage banker's
license pursuant to section 45-742 or upon the expiration of the employing
installment loan company's license pursuant to subdivision (3)(a) of section
45-1033 if such mortgage loan originator has renewed his or her license pursuant
to section 45-732;</para>
<para>(e) Upon the revocation or suspension of the employing licensed mortgage
banker's license pursuant to section 45-742 or upon the revocation or suspension
of the employing installment loan company's license pursuant to subsection
(1) of section 45-1033; or</para>
<para>(f) Upon the cancellation, surrender, or expiration of the employing
registrant's registration with the department.</para>
<para>(3) If a mortgage loan originator license becomes inactive under this
section, the license shall remain inactive until the license expires, the
licenseholder surrenders the license, the license is revoked or suspended
pursuant to section 45-742, or the license is reactivated.</para>
<para>(4) A mortgage loan originator who holds an inactive mortgage loan originator
license may renew such inactive license if he or she remains otherwise eligible
for renewal pursuant to section 45-732 except for being covered by a surety
bond pursuant to subdivision (1)(f) of section 45-729. Such renewal shall
not reactivate the license.</para>
<para>(5) The department has the authority to reactivate
a mortgage loan originator license upon receipt of a notice pursuant to section
45-735 that the mortgage loan originator licensee has been hired as a mortgage
loan originator by a licensed mortgage banker, registrant, or installment
loan company and if such mortgage loan originator meets
the conditions for licensing at the time the reactivation notice is received,
including, but not limited to, coverage by a surety bond pursuant
to subdivision (1)(f) of section 45-729.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB965, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>