<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id160">
<sectno id="id161" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" id="id162" statutenumber="45-346.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id164">45-346.01</statuteno><catchline id="id165">Licensee;
move of place of business; maintain minimum net worth; bond; existing licensee;
how treated.</catchline><para>(1) A licensee may move its place
of business from one place to another within a county without obtaining a
new license if the licensee gives written notice thereof to the director at
least ten days prior to such move.</para>
<para>(2) A licensee shall maintain the minimum net worth as required
by section 45-346 while a license issued under the Nebraska Installment Sales
Act is in effect. The minimum net worth shall be proven by an annual audit
conducted by a certified public accountant. A licensee shall submit a copy
of the annual audit to the director as required by section 45-348 or upon written request of
the director. If a licensee fails to maintain the required minimum
net worth, the Department of Banking and Finance may issue a notice of cancellation
of the license in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para>
<para>(3) The surety bond or a substitute bond as required by section
45-346 shall remain in effect while a license issued under the Nebraska Installment
Sales Act is in effect. If a licensee fails to maintain a surety bond or substitute
bond, the licensee shall immediately cease doing business and surrender the
license to the department. If the licensee does not surrender the license,
the department may issue a notice of cancellation of the license in lieu of
revocation proceedings.</para>
<para>(4) Until October 1, 2008, a licensee licensed prior to September
1, 2007, may operate with no net worth or bonding requirement as provided
for at the time such licensee was originally licensed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>