<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-621"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>45-621</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Collection Agency Fund; created;
use; investment; transfer.</catchline><para>(1) All fees collected under the Collection Agency Act shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to a special fund to be known as the Nebraska
Collection Agency Fund. The board may use the fund as may be necessary for
the proper administration and enforcement of the act. The fund shall be paid
out only on proper vouchers approved by the board and upon warrants issued
by the Director of Administrative Services and countersigned by the State
Treasurer as provided by law. All fees and expenses of the Attorney General
in representing the board pursuant to the act shall be paid out of such fund.
Transfers from the fund to the
Election Administration Fund or the General Fund may be made at
the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Nebraska Collection Agency
Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) On or before July
5, 2013, the State Treasurer shall transfer one hundred thousand dollars from
the Nebraska Collection Agency Fund to the Election Administration Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 500, &#167; 25, p. 1603; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 53, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 81-8,182; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 471, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 206, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 261, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 541, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 21.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>