<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt"  statutenumber="45-354"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-354</statuteno><catchline>Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System
and Registry; department; participation; requirements; director; duties; department;
duties.</catchline><para>(1)
Effective January 1, 2013, or within one hundred eighty days after the Nationwide
Mortgage Licensing System and Registry is capable of accepting licenses issued
under the Nebraska Installment Sales Act, whichever is later, the department
shall require such licensees under the act to be licensed and registered through
the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. In order to carry out
this requirement, the department is authorized to participate in the Nationwide
Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. For this purpose, the department may
establish, by adopting and promulgating rules and regulations or by order,
requirements as necessary. The requirements may include, but not be limited
to:</para>
<para>(a) Background
checks of applicants and licensees, including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(i) Criminal history
through fingerprint or other databases;</para><para>(ii) Civil or administrative records;</para>
<para>(iii) Credit history;
or</para><para>(iv)
Any other information as deemed necessary by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing
System and Registry;</para><para>(b) The payment of fees to apply for or renew a license
through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry;</para>
<para>(c) Compliance
with prelicensure education and testing and continuing education;</para>
<para>(d) The setting
or resetting, as necessary, of renewal processing or reporting dates; and</para>
<para>(e) Amending or
surrendering a license or any other such activities as the director deems
necessary for participation in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and
Registry.</para><para>(2)
In order to fulfill the purposes of the Nebraska Installment Sales Act, the
department is authorized to establish relationships or contracts with the
Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry or other entities designated
by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry to collect and maintain
records and process transaction fees or other fees related to licensees or
other persons subject to the act. The department may allow such system to
collect licensing fees on behalf of the department and allow such system to
collect a processing fee for the services of the system directly from each
licensee or applicant for a license.</para><para>(3) The director is required to regularly report enforcement
actions and other relevant information to the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing
System and Registry subject to the provisions contained in section 45-355.</para>
<para>(4) The director
shall establish a process whereby applicants and licensees may challenge information
entered into the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry by the
director.</para><para>(5)
The department shall ensure that the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System
and Registry adopts a privacy, data security, and breach of security of the
system notification policy. The director shall make available upon written
request a copy of the contract between the department and the Nationwide Mortgage
Licensing System and Registry pertaining to the breach of security of the
system provisions.</para><para>(6)
The department shall upon written request provide the most recently available
audited financial report of the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB965, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>