<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id217"><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" statutenumber="45-360"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>45-360</statuteno><catchline>Preauthorized loans; authorized; billing cycle.</catchline><para>(1) Licensees holding an active installment loan license may make preauthorized loans. Preauthorized loan means a loan made by a licensee pursuant to an agreement between the licensee and the borrower whereby:</para><para>(a) The licensee may permit the borrower to obtain advances of money from the licensee from time to time or the licensee may advance money on behalf of the borrower from time to time as directed by the borrower;</para><para>(b) The amount of each advance and permitted charge and cost is debited to the borrower's account and payments and other credits are credited to the same account;</para><para>(c) The charges are computed on the unpaid principal balance or balances of the account from time to time;</para><para>(d) The borrower has the privilege of paying the account in full at any time or, if the account is not in default, in monthly installments or fixed or determinable amounts as provided in the agreement; and</para><para>(e) The loan agreement expressly states that it covers preauthorized loans. Preauthorized loan does not mean a transaction, resulting in either a credit or a debit to the borrower's account, which is initiated by the use or application of a plastic, metal, or other type of credit or transaction card.</para><para>(2) For purposes of computations relating to preauthorized loans made pursuant to the Nebraska Installment Loan and Sales Act, billing cycle means the time interval between periodic billing dates. A billing cycle shall be considered monthly if the closing date of the cycle is the same date each month or does not vary by more than four days from such date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB474, &#167; 81. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>