<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-101.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-101.04</statuteno><catchline>General interest rate; maximum;
when not applicable.</catchline><para>The limitation on the rate of interest
provided in section 45-101.03 shall not apply to:</para>
<para>(1) Other rates of interest authorized for loans made by any licensee
or permittee operating under a license or permit duly issued by the Department
of Banking and Finance pursuant to the Credit Union Act, the Nebraska Installment
Loan Act, subsection (4) of section 8-319, or sections 8-815 to 8-829;</para>
<para>(2) Loans made to any corporation, partnership, limited liability company,
or trust;</para>
<para>(3) The guarantor or surety of any loan to a corporation, partnership,
limited liability company, or trust;</para>
<para>(4) Loans made when the aggregate principal amount of the indebtedness
is twenty-five thousand dollars or more of the borrower to any one financial
institution, licensee, or permittee;</para>
<para>(5) Loans insured, guaranteed, sponsored, or participated in, either
in whole or part, by any agency, department, or program of the United States
or state government;</para>
<para>(6) Loans or advances of money, repayable on demand, which are made
solely upon securities, as defined in subdivision (15) of section 8-1101,
pledged as collateral for such repayment and in which such loans or advances
are used by the borrower only for the purchase of securities as so defined.
It shall be lawful to contract for and receive any rate of interest on such
transaction as the parties thereto may expressly agree;</para>
<para>(7) Interest charges made on open credit accounts by a person who sells
goods or services on credit when the interest charges do not exceed one and
one-third percent per month for any charges which remain unpaid for more than
thirty days following rendition of the statement of account;</para>
<para>(8) A minimum charge of ten dollars per loan which may be charged by
the lender in lieu of all interest charges;</para>
<para>(9) Loans described in subsection (4) of section 8-319 made by a state
or federal savings and loan association at a rate not to exceed nineteen percent
per annum;</para>
<para>(10) Loans made primarily for business or agricultural purposes or secured
by real property when such loans are made (a) by a licensee, registrant, or
permittee operating under a license, registration, or permit duly issued by
the Department of Banking and Finance except for licensees operating under
the Nebraska Installment Loan Act, (b) by any financial institution insured
by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or the National Credit Union
Administration, or (c) by any insurance company organized under the laws of
this state and subject to regulation by the Department of Insurance;</para>
<para>(11) Loans secured solely by real property when such loans are (a) made
by licensees operating under the Nebraska Installment Loan Act and (b) made
to finance or refinance the purchase of the property or construction on or
improvements to the property, if the Department of Banking and Finance has
the authority to examine such loans for compliance with sections 45-101.02
and 45-101.03. A licensee making a loan pursuant to this subdivision may obtain
an interest in any fixtures attached to such real property and any insurance
proceeds payable in connection with such real property or the loan;</para>
<para>(12) Loans secured by a reverse mortgage pursuant to section 45-702.01;</para>
<para>(13) Interest charges made on any goods or services sold under an installment
contract pursuant to the Nebraska Installment Sales Act. Subject to section
45-338, it shall be lawful to contract for and receive any rate of interest
on such contract as the parties may expressly agree to in writing; or</para>
<para>(14) Fees which may be charged by a licensee for services pursuant to
the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 349, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 616, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 390, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 276, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 279, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 623, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 143, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 795, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 272, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 263; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 216, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 30; </para>
<para>Laws 1994, LB 979, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 397, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 335, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB892, &#167;  2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credit Union Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1701.</para><para><emphasis>Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 45-901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Installment Loan Act,</emphasis> see section 45-1001.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Installment Sales Act,</emphasis> see section 45-334.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A corporation may agree to pay any rate of interest by an agreement in writing which sets out the amount or rate charged. Such interest is not usurious. Classen v. Becton, Dickinson &amp; Co., 214 Neb. 543, 334 N.W.2d 644 (1983).</para><para>The exemptions specified in subdivisions (2), (3), and (4) of this section exempt the specified transactions from the installment loan act, sections 8-435 et seq., as well as from the interest rate limitations of section 45-101.03. McCaul v. American Savings Co., 213 Neb. 841, 331 N.W.2d 795 (1983).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>