<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="45-729"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>45-729</statuteno><catchline>Issuance of mortgage loan originator
license; director; findings required; denial; notice; appeal; application deemed abandoned; when; effect.</catchline>
<para>(1) The director shall not issue a mortgage loan originator license
unless the director makes at a minimum the following findings:</para>
<para>(a) The applicant has never had a mortgage loan originator license revoked
in any governmental jurisdiction, except that a subsequent formal vacation
of such revocation shall not be deemed a revocation;</para>
<para>(b) The applicant has not been convicted of, or pleaded guilty or nolo
contendere or its equivalent to, in a domestic, foreign, or military court:</para>
<para>(i) A misdemeanor under any state or federal law which involves dishonesty
or fraud or which involves any aspect of the business of a mortgage banker,
depository institution, or installment loan company unless such individual
has received a pardon for such conviction or
such conviction has been expunged, except that the director may consider the
underlying crime, facts, and circumstances of a pardoned or expunged conviction
in determining the applicant's eligibility for a license pursuant to subdivision
(c) of this subsection; or</para>
<para>(ii) Any felony under state or federal law unless such individual has
received a pardon for such conviction or
such conviction has been expunged, except that the director may consider the
underlying crime, facts, and circumstances of a pardoned or expunged conviction
in determining the applicant's eligibility for a license pursuant to subdivision
(c) of this subsection;</para>
<para>(c) The applicant has demonstrated financial responsibility, character,
and general fitness such as to command the confidence of the community and
to warrant a determination that the mortgage loan originator will operate
honestly, fairly, and efficiently within the purposes of the Residential Mortgage
Licensing Act. For purposes of this subsection, an individual has shown that
he or she is not financially responsible when he or she has shown a disregard
in the management of his or her own financial condition. The director may
consider the following factors in making a determination as to financial responsibility:</para>
<para>(i) The applicant's current outstanding judgments except judgments solely
as a result of medical expenses;</para>
<para>(ii) The applicant's current outstanding tax liens or other government
liens and filings;</para>
<para>(iii) The applicant's foreclosures within the past three years; and</para>
<para>(iv) A pattern of seriously delinquent accounts within the past three
years by the applicant;</para>
<para>(d) The applicant has completed the prelicensing education requirements
described in section 45-730;</para>
<para>(e) The applicant has passed a written test that meets the test requirement
described in section 45-731; and</para>
<para>(f) The applicant is covered by a surety bond as required pursuant to
section 45-724 or a supplemental surety bond as required pursuant to section
45-1007.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If the director determines
that a mortgage loan originator license application should be denied, the
director shall notify the applicant in writing of the denial and of the reasons
for the denial.</para>
<para>(b) The director shall not
deny an application for a mortgage loan originator license because of the
failure to submit information required under the act or rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated under the act without first giving the applicant an
opportunity to correct the deficiency by supplying the missing information.</para>
<para>(c) If an applicant for
a mortgage loan originator license does not complete his or her license application
and fails to respond to a notice or notices from the department to correct
the deficiency or deficiencies for a period of one hundred twenty days or
more after mailing of the initial notice after initial filing of the application,
the department may deem the application as abandoned and may issue a notice
of abandonment of the application to the applicant in lieu of proceedings
to deny the application.</para><para>(d) A
decision of the director denying a mortgage loan originator license application
pursuant to the Residential Mortgage Licensing Act may
be appealed. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure
Act and rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department.</para>
<para>(3) A mortgage loan originator license shall not be assignable.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB965, &#167; 15.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>