<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-191.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>45-191.01</statuteno><catchline>Loan brokerage agreement; written disclosure statement; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to a borrower signing a loan brokerage agreement, the loan broker shall give the borrower a written disclosure statement. The cover sheet of the disclosure statement shall have printed, in at least ten-point boldface capital letters, the title DISCLOSURES REQUIRED BY NEBRASKA LAW. The following statement, printed in at least ten-point type, shall appear under the title:</para><para>THE STATE OF NEBRASKA HAS NOT REVIEWED AND DOES NOT APPROVE, RECOMMEND, ENDORSE, OR SPONSOR ANY LOAN BROKERAGE AGREEMENT. THE INFORMATION CONTAINED IN THIS DISCLOSURE DOCUMENT HAS NOT BEEN VERIFIED BY THE STATE. IF YOU HAVE QUESTIONS, SEEK LEGAL ADVICE BEFORE YOU SIGN A LOAN BROKERAGE AGREEMENT.</para><para>Only the title and the statement shall appear on the cover sheet.</para><para>(2) The body of the disclosure statement shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) The name, street address, and telephone number of the loan broker, the names under which the loan broker does, has done, or intends to do business, the name and street address of any parent or affiliated company, and the electronic mail and Internet address of the loan broker, if any;</para><para>(b) A statement as to whether the loan broker does business as an individual, a partnership, a corporation, or another organizational form, including identification of the state of incorporation or formation;</para><para>(c) How long the loan broker has done business;</para><para>(d) The number of loan brokerage agreements the loan broker has entered into in the previous twelve months;</para><para>(e) The number of loans the loan broker has obtained for borrowers in the previous twelve months;</para><para>(f) A description of the services the loan broker agrees to perform for the borrower;</para><para>(g) The conditions under which the borrower is obligated to pay the loan broker. This disclosure shall be in boldface type;</para><para>(h) The names, titles, and principal occupations for the past five years of all officers, directors, or persons occupying similar positions responsible for the loan broker's business activities;</para><para>(i) A statement whether the loan broker or any person identified in subdivision (h) of this subsection:</para><para>(i) Has been convicted of a felony or misdemeanor or pleaded nolo contendere to a felony or misdemeanor charge if such felony or misdemeanor involved fraud, embezzlement, fraudulent conversion, or misappropriation of property;</para><para>(ii) Has been held liable in a civil action by final judgment or consented to the entry of a stipulated judgment if the civil action alleged fraud, embezzlement, fraudulent conversion, or misappropriation of property or the use of untrue or misleading representations in an attempt to sell or dispose of real or personal property or the use of unfair, unlawful, or deceptive business practices; or</para><para>(iii) Is subject to any currently effective injunction or restrictive order relating to business activity as the result of an action brought by a public agency or department including, but not limited to, action affecting any vocational license; and</para><para>(j) Any other information the director requires.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 270, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB184, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>