<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-805"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-805</statuteno><catchline>Surety bond or surety account; requirements; action on surety; depository; Secretary of State; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) A credit services organization conducting business in this state shall obtain a surety bond or establish a surety account which complies with this section. The bond or account shall be in the amount of one hundred thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) If a surety bond is obtained, the bond shall be issued by a surety company authorized to do business in this state and a copy of the bond shall be filed with the Secretary of State. If a surety account is established, the account shall be established and maintained at a federally insured bank or savings and loan association located in this state and notification of the depository, the trustee, and the account number shall be filed with the Secretary of State.</para><para>(3) The bond or account shall be in favor of the state for the benefit of any person who is damaged by any violation of the Credit Services Organization Act. The bond or account shall also be in favor of any person damaged by such a violation.</para><para>(4) Any person claiming against the bond or account for a violation of the act may maintain an action at law against the credit services organization and against the surety or trustee. The surety or trustee shall be liable only for damages awarded under section 45-810. The aggregate liability of the surety or trustee to all persons damaged by a credit services organization's violation of the act shall not exceed the amount of the bond or account.</para><para>(5) A depository holding money in a surety account under the act shall not convey money in the account to the credit services organization that established the account or a representative of the credit services organization unless the credit services organization or representative presents a statement issued by the Secretary of State indicating that subsection (6) of this section has been satisfied in relation to the account. The Secretary of State may conduct investigations and require submission of information as necessary to enforce this subsection.</para><para>(6) The bond or account shall be maintained until two years after the date that the credit services organization ceases operation in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 292, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>