<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-337"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-337</statuteno><catchline>Insurance; policy; cancellation; premium refund; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The amount, if any, included for insurance, which may be purchased by the holder of the contract, shall not exceed the applicable premium rates chargeable in accordance with filings, if any, with the Department of Insurance. If dual interest insurance on the goods is purchased by the holder it shall, within thirty days after execution of the installment contract, send or cause to be sent to the buyer a policy or policies or certificate of insurance, written by an insurance company authorized to do business in this state, clearly setting forth the amount of the premium, the kind or kinds of insurance, the coverages, and all the terms and conditions of the contract or contracts of insurance.</para><para>(2) If any insurance is canceled or the premium adjusted during the term of the installment contract, any refund of the insurance premium plus the unearned time-price differential thereon received by the holder shall be credited by the holder to the last maturing installment of the contract except to the extent applied toward payment for similar insurance protecting the interests of the buyer and the holder or either of them.</para><para>(3) If any insurance is canceled due to the payment of all sums for which the buyer is liable under an installment contract, the holder of the installment contract shall, upon receipt of payment of all sums due, send notice to the buyer within fifteen business days of the name, address, and telephone number of the insurance company which issued the insurance contract or the party responsible for any refund, and notice that the buyer may be eligible for a refund. A copy of such notice shall be retained by the holder of the installment contract. This subsection does not apply if the holder of the loan contract previously credited the refund of the insurance premium to the loan contract or otherwise refunded the insurance premium to the buyer.</para><para>(4) The holder may also purchase nonfiling insurance and charge a reasonable fee. The fee shall not exceed the amount of fees and charges prescribed by law which would have been paid to public officials for filing, perfecting, releasing, and satisfying any lien or security interest in the goods or services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 268, &#167; 4, p. 759; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 94, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 