<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-915"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>45-915</statuteno><catchline>Licensee; principal place of business; change of location; branch offices; approval required; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, a licensee, on or before December 31, 2020, may offer a delayed deposit services business only at an office designated as its principal place of business in the application. A licensee may change the location of its designated principal place of business with the prior written approval of the director. The director may establish forms and procedures for determining whether the change of location should be approved.</para><para>(2) On or before December 31, 2020, a licensee may operate branch offices only in the same county in which the licensee's designated principal place of business is located. The licensee may establish a branch office or change the location of a branch office with the prior written approval of the director. The director may establish forms and procedures for determining whether an original branch or branches or a change of location of a branch should be approved.</para><para>(3) On or after January 1, 2021, a licensee shall designate an office in Nebraska as its principal place of business. A licensee may change the location of its designated principal place of business with the prior written approval of the director. The director may establish forms and procedures for determining whether the change of location should be approved.</para><para>(4) On or after January 1, 2021, a licensee may operate branch offices in Nebraska. The licensee may establish a branch office or change the location of a branch office with the prior written approval of the director. The director may establish forms and procedures for determining whether an original branch or branches or a change of location of a branch should be approved.</para><para>(5) A licensee may offer a delayed deposit services business only at an office designated as its principal place of business and any branch office established pursuant to this section.</para><para>(6) A fee of one hundred fifty dollars and any processing fee allowed under subsection (2) of section 45-905.01 shall be submitted with each request made pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 43. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>