<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id162" statutenumber="45-346.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>45-346.01</statuteno><catchline id="id165">Licensee; move of main office; notice to director; maintain minimum net worth; bond.</catchline><para>(1) A licensee may move its main office from one place to another without obtaining a new license if the licensee gives notice thereof to the director through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry at least thirty days prior to such move.</para><para>(2) A licensee shall notify the director through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry at least thirty days prior to the occurrence of any of the following:</para><para>(a) The establishment of a new branch office. Notice of each such establishment shall be accompanied by a fee of one hundred dollars and any processing fee allowed under subsection (2) of section 45-354;</para><para>(b) The relocation or closing of an existing branch office; or</para><para>(c) A change of name, trade name, or doing business as designation.</para><para>(3) A licensee shall maintain the minimum net worth as required by section 45-346 while a license issued under the Nebraska Installment Sales Act is in effect. The minimum net worth shall be proven by an annual audit conducted by a certified public accountant. A licensee shall submit a copy of the annual audit to the director as required by section 45-348 or upon written request of the director. If a licensee fails to maintain the required minimum net worth, the department may issue a notice of cancellation of the license in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para><para>(4) The surety bond or a substitute bond as required by section 45-346 shall remain in effect while a license issued under the Nebraska Installment Sales Act is in effect. If a licensee fails to maintain a surety bond or substitute bond, the licensee shall immediately cease doing business and surrender the license to the department. If the licensee does not surrender the license, the department may issue a notice of cancellation of the license in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB965, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB355, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>