<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id00"  statutenumber="45-919"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>45-919</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Acts prohibited.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) No licensee shall:</para><para id="id00">(a) At any one time hold from any one maker more than two checks;</para><para id="id00">(b) At any one time hold from any one maker a check or checks in an aggregate face amount of more than five hundred dollars;</para><para id="id00">(c) Hold or agree to hold a check for more than thirty-four days. A check which is in the process of collection for the reason that it was not negotiable on the day agreed upon shall not be deemed as being held in excess of the thirty-four-day period;</para><para id="id00">(d) Require the maker to receive payment by a method which causes the maker to pay additional or further fees and charges to the licensee, an affiliate of the licensee, or any other person;</para><para id="id00">(e) Accept a check as repayment, refinancing, or any other consolidation of a check or checks held by the same licensee;</para><para id="id00">(f) Except as provided in section 45-919.01, renew, roll over, defer, or in any way extend a delayed deposit transaction by allowing the maker to pay less than the total amount of the check and any authorized fees or charges. This subdivision shall not prevent a licensee that agreed to hold a check for less than thirty-four days from agreeing to hold the check for an additional period of time no greater than the thirty-four days it would have originally been able to hold the check if (i) the extension is at the request of the maker, (ii) no additional fees are charged for the extension, and (iii) the delayed deposit transaction is completed as required by subdivision (1)(c) of this section. The licensee shall retain written or electronic proof of compliance with this subdivision. If a licensee fails, or is unable, to provide such proof to the department upon request, there shall be a rebuttable presumption that a violation of this subdivision has occurred and the department may pursue any remedies or actions available to it under the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act;</para><para id="id00">(g) Enter into another delayed deposit transaction with the same maker on the same business day as the completion of a delayed deposit transaction unless prior to entering into the transaction the maker and the licensee verify on a form prescribed by the department that completion of the prior delayed deposit transaction has occurred. The licensee shall retain written proof of compliance with this subdivision. If a licensee fails, or is unable, to provide such proof to the department upon request, there shall be a rebuttable presumption that a violation of this subdivision has occurred and the department may pursue any remedies or actions available to it under the act;</para><para>(h) Charge, collect, or receive any finance charges, fees, interest, or similar charges for loan brokerage, insurance, or any other ancillary products;</para><para>(i) Negotiate or present a paper check for payment unless the check is endorsed with the actual business name of the licensee;</para><para>(j) Engage, in connection with a delayed deposit transaction, in unfair or deceptive practices or advertising under the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act to engage in any act that limits or restricts the application of the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act, including, but not limited to, making transactions disguised as personal property, personal sales, or leaseback transactions, or disguise transaction proceeds as cash rebated for the pretextual installment sale of goods and services; or</para><para>(k) Attempt to deposit or negotiate a check after two consecutive failed collection attempts unless the licensee has obtained a new, written payment authorization from the maker.</para><para>(2) No licensee, affiliate of a licensee, or any other person, including a person operating as a credit services organization, shall charge, collect, or receive any finance charges, fees, interest, or similar charges that would cause a maker to pay an amount in excess of or in addition to those permitted under the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act in connection with a delayed deposit transaction, including, but not limited to, charges for loan brokerage, insurance, or any other ancillary products.</para><para id="id00">(3) For purposes of this section, (a) completion of a delayed deposit transaction means the licensee has presented a maker's check for payment to a financial institution as defined in section 8-101.03 or the maker redeemed the check by paying the full amount of the check in cash to the licensee and (b) licensee shall include (i) a person related to the licensee by common ownership or control, (ii) a person in whom such licensee has any financial interest of ten percent or more, or (iii) any employee or agent of the licensee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 155; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB194, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 87-306.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>