<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-191.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-191.04</statuteno><catchline>Loan brokerage agreement; requirements; right to cancel.</catchline><para>(1) A loan brokerage agreement shall be in writing and shall be signed by the loan broker and the borrower. The loan broker shall furnish the borrower a copy of such signed loan brokerage agreement at the time the borrower signs it.</para><para>(2) The borrower has the right to cancel a loan brokerage agreement for any reason at any time within five business days after the date the parties sign the agreement. The loan brokerage agreement shall set forth the borrower's right to cancel and the procedures to be followed when an agreement is canceled.</para><para>(3) A loan brokerage agreement shall set forth in at least ten-point type, or handwriting of at least equivalent size, the following:</para><para>(a) The terms and conditions of payment;</para><para>(b) A full and detailed description of the acts or services the loan broker will undertake to perform for the borrower;</para><para>(c) The loan broker's principal business address, telephone number, and electronic mail and Internet address, if any, and the name, address, telephone number, and electronic mail and Internet address, if any, of its agent in the State of Nebraska authorized to receive service of process;</para><para>(d) The business form of the loan broker, whether a corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or otherwise; and</para><para>(e) The following notice of the borrower's right to cancel the loan brokerage agreement pursuant to this section:</para><para>"You have five business days in which you may cancel this agreement for any reason by mailing or delivering written notice to the loan broker. The five business days shall expire on ................... (last date to mail or deliver notice), and notice of cancellation should be mailed to .......................................... (loan broker's name and business street address). If you choose to mail your notice, it must be placed in the United States mail properly addressed, first-class postage prepaid, and postmarked before midnight of the above date. If you choose to deliver your notice to the loan broker directly, it must be delivered to the loan broker by the end of the normal business day on the above date. Within five business days after receipt of the notice of cancellation, the loan broker shall return to you all sums paid by you to the loan broker pursuant to this agreement."</para><para>The notice shall be set forth immediately above the place at which the borrower signs the loan brokerage agreement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 270, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB184, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>