<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" id="id172" statutenumber="45-348"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>45-348</statuteno><catchline id="id175">License; renewal;
licensee; duties; fee; voluntary surrender of license.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, every licensee
shall, on or before the first day of October, pay to the director a fee of one hundred fifty dollars for each
license held as a license fee for the succeeding year and any processing fee allowed under subsection (2) of section
45-354 and submit such information as the director may require
to indicate any material change in the information contained in the original
application or succeeding renewal applications, including a copy of the licensee's
most recent annual audit.</para>
<para>(2) Licenses which expire
on October 1, 2012, shall be renewed until December 31, 2013, upon compliance
with subsection (1) of this section. For such renewals, the fee shall be one
and three-twelfths of the fees required under subsection (1) of this section.
A license renewed on or after January 1, 2013, shall remain in full force
and effect until the next succeeding December 31.</para><para>(3) A licensee may voluntarily surrender a license
at any time by delivering to the director written notice of the surrender.
The department shall
issue a notice of cancellation of the license following such surrender.</para>
<para>(4) If a licensee fails to
renew its license and does not voluntarily surrender the license pursuant
to this section, the department may issue a notice of expiration of the license
to the licensee in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 268, &#167; 15, p. 765; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB965, &#167; 6.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>