<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id00" statutenumber="45-902"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>45-902</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">For purposes of the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act:</para><para>(1) Annual percentage rate means an annual percentage rate as determined under section 107 of the federal Truth in Lending Act, 15 U.S.C. 1606, as such section existed on January 1, 2018, and includes all fees, interest, and charges contained in a delayed deposit service contract, except for charges permitted for the presentation of instruments that are not negotiable under subdivision (1)(a)(v) of section 45-917 or returned unpaid under section 45-918.01;</para><para id="id00">(2) Check means any check, draft, or other instrument for the payment of money. Check also means an authorization to debit an account electronically;</para><para>(3) Default means a maker's failure to repay a delayed deposit transaction in compliance with the terms contained in a delayed deposit service agreement;</para><para id="id00">(4) Delayed deposit services business means any person who for a fee (a) accepts a check dated subsequent to the date it was written or (b) accepts a check dated on the date it was written and holds the check for a period of days prior to deposit or presentment pursuant to an agreement with or any representation made to the maker of the check, whether express or implied;</para><para>(5) Department means the Department of Banking and Finance;</para><para id="id00">(6) Director means the Director of Banking and Finance or his or her designee;</para><para id="id00">(7) Financial institution has the same meaning as in section 8-101.03;</para><para id="id00">(8) Licensee means any person licensed under the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act;</para><para>(9) Maker means an individual who receives the proceeds of a delayed deposit transaction; and</para><para id="id00">(10) Person means an individual, proprietorship, association, joint venture, joint stock company, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability company, business corporation, nonprofit corporation, or any group of individuals however organized.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 154; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB194, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>