<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id181"  statutenumber="45-922"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>45-922</statuteno><catchline id="id184">Licensee; disciplinary actions; failure to renew.</catchline><para>(1) The director may, following a hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, suspend or revoke any license issued pursuant to the Delayed Deposit Services Licensing Act if he or she finds:</para><para>(a) A licensee or any of its officers, directors, partners, or members has knowingly violated the act or any rule, regulation, or order of the director thereunder;</para><para>(b) A fact or condition existing which, if it had existed at the time of the original application for such license, would have warranted the director to refuse to issue such license;</para><para>(c) A licensee has abandoned its place of business for a period of thirty days or more;</para><para>(d) A licensee or any of its officers, directors, partners, or members has knowingly subscribed to, made, or caused to be made any false statement or false entry in the books and records of any licensee, has knowingly subscribed to or exhibited false papers with the intent to deceive the department, has failed to make a true and correct entry in the books and records of such licensee of its business and transactions in the manner and form prescribed by the department, or has mutilated, altered, destroyed, secreted, or removed any of the books or records of such licensee without the written approval of the department or as provided in section 45-925; or</para><para>(e) A licensee has knowingly violated a voluntary consent or compliance agreement which had been entered into with the director.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in this section, a license shall not be revoked or suspended except after notice and a hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(3)(a) If a licensee fails to renew its license as required by section 45-910 and does not voluntarily surrender the license pursuant to section 45-911, the department may issue a notice of expiration of the license to the licensee in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para><para>(b) If a licensee fails to maintain a surety bond as required by section 45-906, the department may issue a notice of cancellation of the license in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para><para>(4) Revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration of a license shall not impair or affect the obligation of a preexisting lawful contract between the licensee and any person, including a maker of a check.</para><para>(5) Revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration of a license shall not affect civil or criminal liability for acts committed before the revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration or liability for fines levied against the licensee or any of its officers, directors, shareholders, partners, or members, pursuant to section 45-925, for acts committed before the revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 967, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 106; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB194, &#167; 17. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>