<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id564"><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" statutenumber="45-1304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1304</statuteno><catchline>State Treasurer; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) On or before October 1, 2025, and on or before October 1 of each year thereafter for as long as medical debt relief coordinators are fulfilling their contractual obligations under the Medical Debt Relief Act, the State Treasurer shall submit an annual report regarding the program in accordance with this section.</para><para>(2) Each report under this section shall contain the following information for the most recently completed fiscal year:</para><para>(a) The amount of medical debt purchased and discharged under the program;</para><para>(b) The number of eligible residents who received medical debt relief under the program;</para><para>(c) The characteristics of such eligible residents as described in subdivision (3)(c)(iv) of section 45-1303;</para><para>(d) The number of such eligible residents whose income was calculated at one hundred percent, one hundred fifty percent, and two hundred percent of the federal poverty guidelines;</para><para>(e) The number and characteristics of the health care providers from whom medical debt was purchased and discharged;</para><para>(f) The number and characteristics of the medical debt relief coordinators contracted with for the purposes of purchasing and discharging medical debt; and</para><para>(g) The number of private individuals and private entities that made a contribution to the Medical Debt Relief Fund and the total amount of such contributions.</para><para>(3) Each report under this section shall be submitted electronically to the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB937, &#167; 46. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>