<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id18" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="45-1103" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1103</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Guaranteed Asset Protection Waiver Act:</para><para>(1) Borrower means a debtor, retail buyer, or lessee under a finance agreement;</para><para>(2) Creditor means:</para><para>(a) The lender in a loan or credit transaction involving a motor vehicle;</para><para>(b) The lessor in a lease transaction involving a motor vehicle;</para><para>(c) Any retail seller of motor vehicles that provides credit to retail buyers of such motor vehicles if such entities comply with the provisions of the act; or</para><para>(d) The assignees of any of the foregoing to whom the credit obligation is payable;</para><para>(3) Creditor's designee means a person other than the creditor that performs administrative or operational functions pursuant to a guaranteed asset protection waiver program;</para><para>(4) Finance agreement means a loan, credit transaction, lease, or retail installment sales contract for the purchase or lease of a motor vehicle;</para><para>(5) Financial institution has the same meaning as in section 8-101.03;</para><para>(6) Free-look period means the period of time from the effective date of the guaranteed asset protection waiver until the date the borrower may cancel the contract without penalty, fees, or costs to the borrower. This period of time must not be shorter than thirty days;</para><para>(7) Guaranteed asset protection waiver means a contractual agreement wherein a creditor or the creditor's designee agrees, for a separate charge, to cancel or waive all or part of amounts due on a borrower's finance agreement in the event of a total physical damage loss as determined by the insurer issuing the motor vehicle insurance policy subject to the terms of the waiver or unrecovered theft as determined by the insurer issuing the motor vehicle insurance policy subject to the terms of the waiver of the motor vehicle, which agreement must be part of, or a separate addendum to, the finance agreement. If a borrower does not have motor vehicle insurance, the creditor or the creditor's designee will accept a report prepared pursuant to insurance industry standards by a qualified inspector declaring the motor vehicle a total loss or a law enforcement report declaring the motor vehicle an unrecovered theft. Nothing in the act shall be construed to require the waiver to pay more than the amount that would have been paid if the borrower had motor vehicle insurance at the time of loss;</para><para>(8) Motor vehicle means self-propelled or towed vehicles designed for personal or commercial use, including, but not limited to, automobiles, trucks, motorcycles, recreational vehicles, all-terrain vehicles, snowmobiles, campers, boats, personal watercraft, and motorcycle, boat, camper, and personal watercraft trailers; and</para><para>(9) Person includes an individual, company, association, organization, partnership, business trust, corporation, and every form of legal entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB571, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 157. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>