<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id102"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" id="id104" statutenumber="45-1006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id106">45-1006</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Installment loans; application hearing; protest; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) When an application for an original installment loan license has been accepted by the director as substantially complete, notice of the filing of the application shall be published by the department three successive weeks in a legal newspaper published in or of general circulation in the county where the applicant proposes to operate the business of lending money. A public hearing shall be held on each application except as provided in subsection (2) of this section. The date for hearing shall not be less than thirty days after the last publication. Written protest against the issuance of the license may be filed with the department by any person not less than five days before the date set for hearing. The director, in his or her discretion, may grant a continuance. The costs of the hearing shall be paid by the applicant. The director may deny any application for license after hearing. The director shall, in his or her discretion, make examination and inspection concerning the propriety of the issuance of a license to any applicant. The cost of such examination and inspection shall be paid by the applicant.</para><para>(2) The director may waive the hearing requirements of subsection (1) of this section if (a) the applicant has held, and operated under, a license to engage in the business of lending money in Nebraska pursuant to the Nebraska Installment Loan Act for at least one calendar year immediately prior to the filing of the application, (b) no written protest against the issuance of the license has been filed with the department within fifteen days after publication of a notice of the filing of the application one time in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where the applicant proposes to operate the business of lending money, and (c) in the judgment of the director, the experience, character, and general fitness of the applicant warrant the belief that the applicant will comply with the Nebraska Installment Loan Act.</para><para>(3) The expense of any publication made pursuant to this section shall be paid by the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 90, &#167; 11, p. 349; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 45-139; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 45-118; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 555, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 25; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2000, &#167; 45-118; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 25.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>