<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-1013"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1013</statuteno><catchline>Installment loans; license; renewal;
fees; relocation of place of business; procedure; hearing; fee.</catchline><para>(1) For the annual renewal of an original license
under the Nebraska Installment Loan Act, the licensee shall file with the
department a fee of two hundred fifty dollars and a renewal application containing
such information as the director may require to indicate any material change
in the information contained in the original application or succeeding renewal
applications.</para>
<para>(2) For the relocation of
its place of business, a licensee shall file with the department a fee of
one hundred fifty dollars and an application containing such information as
the director may require to determine whether the relocation should be approved.
Upon receipt of the fee and application, the director shall publish a notice
of the filing of the application in a newspaper of general circulation in
the county where the licensee proposes to relocate. If the director receives
any substantive objection to the proposed relocation within fifteen days after
publication of such notice, he or she shall hold a hearing on the application
in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and the rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated under the act. The expense of any publication required
by this section shall be paid by the applicant licensee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 90, &#167; 6, p. 347; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 45-134; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 45-126; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 39, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 599, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 555, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1998), &#167; 45-126; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB279, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>