<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt"  statutenumber="45-1007"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1007</statuteno><catchline>Installment loans; license; bond.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section, a license shall not
be issued until the applicant gives to the department a bond in the penal
sum of fifty thousand dollars to be executed by the applicant and a surety
company authorized to do business in the State of Nebraska, conditioned for
the faithful performance by the applicant, as a licensee, of the duties and
obligations pertaining to the business of lending money and the prompt payment
of any judgment recovered against the applicant, as a licensee, under the
Nebraska Installment Loan Act.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except as provided
in subsection (3) of this section, a licensee who employs or enters into an
independent agent agreement with an individual required to obtain a mortgage
loan originator license pursuant to the Residential Mortgage Licensing Act
shall maintain the surety bond required by subsection (1) of this section
and a supplemental surety bond. The supplemental surety bond posted by such
licensee shall cover all mortgage loan originators who are employees or independent
agents of such licensee. The supplemental surety bond shall be for the use
of the State of Nebraska and any Nebraska resident who may have claims or
causes of action against such licensee arising from a transaction involving
a residential mortgage loan, as defined in section 45-702, or against an individual
who is a mortgage loan originator employed by, or in an independent agent
relationship with, the licensee. The initial amount of the supplemental surety
bond shall be one hundred thousand dollars.</para><para>(b) Upon filing of the mortgage report of condition
required by section 45-1018, a licensee shall maintain or increase its supplemental
surety bond to reflect the total dollar amount of the closed residential mortgage
loans originated in this state in the preceding year in accordance with the
following table. A licensee may decrease its supplemental surety bond in accordance
with the following table if the supplemental surety bond required is less
than the amount of the supplemental surety bond on file with the department.</para>
<para><table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">

<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1.24*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="0.76*" />
<tbody>
<row>

<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Dollar
Amount of Closed </entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
</row>
<row>

<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Residential
Mortgage Loans</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Surety
Bond Required</entry>
</row>
<row>

<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$0.00
to $5,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$100,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>

<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$5,000,000.01
to $10,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$125,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>

<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$10,000,000.01
to $25,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$150,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>

<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Over
$25,000,000.00</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$200,000.00</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></para>
<para>(3)(a) A person who has
been issued multiple licenses pursuant to section 45-1010 and who employs
or enters into an independent agent agreement with an individual required
to obtain a mortgage loan originator license pursuant to the Residential Mortgage
Licensing Act shall maintain a surety bond for each license that he, she,
or it holds as required in subsection (1) of this section and shall also post
one supplemental surety bond which shall cover all licenses held by such person.
The supplemental surety bond posted by such person shall cover all mortgage
loan originators who are employees or independent agents of such person. The
supplemental surety bond shall be for the use of the State of Nebraska and
any Nebraska resident who may have claims or causes of action against such
person arising from a transaction involving a residential mortgage loan or
against an individual who is a mortgage loan originator employed by, or in
an independent agent relationship with, the person. The amount of such supplemental
surety bond shall be as follows:</para><para>(i) The initial supplemental surety bond shall be
in the amount of one hundred thousand dollars; and</para><para>(ii) Upon filing of the mortgage
report of condition required by section 45-1018, the person's supplemental
surety bond shall be maintained in accordance with subdivision (2)(b) of this
section. For purposes of calculating the amount of the bond that is required,
the total dollar amount of the closed loans shall include all residential
mortgage loans in this state closed by the person.</para><para>(b) A person who holds both one
or more installment loan licenses pursuant to the Nebraska Installment Loan
Act and a mortgage banker license pursuant to the Residential Mortgage Licensing
Act shall not be required to post and maintain a supplemental surety bond
if such person meets the following conditions:</para><para>(i) The person maintains a surety
bond as provided in subsection (1) of this section for each installment loan
license he, she, or it holds;</para><para>(ii) The person maintains a mortgage banker surety
bond as provided in section 45-724; and</para><para>(iii) The mortgage banker surety bond covers all transactions
involving residential mortgage loans, including such transactions done pursuant
to the person's installment loan license or licenses.</para><para>(4) Should the department determine
that a licensee does not maintain a supplemental surety bond in the amount
required by subsection (2) or (3) of this section, the department shall give
written notification to the licensee requiring him, her, or it to increase
the surety bond within thirty days to the amount required by subsection (2)
or (3) of this section.</para><para>(5) The
bond or a substitute bond required
by subsection (1) of this section shall remain in effect or the
licensee shall immediately cease making loans and the license shall be canceled
by the director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 90, &#167; 31, p. 357; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 45-157; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 45-119; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 555, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1998), &#167; 45-119; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 218, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 42.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Residential Mortgage Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 45-701.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>