<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-1033"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1033</statuteno><catchline>License; administrative fine; disciplinary
actions; failure to renew.</catchline><para>(1) The director may, following
a hearing under the Administrative Procedure Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by
the department under the act, suspend or revoke any license issued
pursuant to the Nebraska Installment Loan Act. The director may also impose
an administrative fine on the licensee for each separate violation of the
act. The director may take one or more of these actions if the director finds:</para>
<para>(a) The licensee has materially violated or demonstrated a continuing
pattern of violating the Nebraska Installment Loan Act or rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated under the act, any order issued under the act, or
any other state or federal law applicable to the conduct of its business;</para>
<para>(b) A fact or condition exists which, if it had existed at the time
of the original application for the license, would have warranted the director
to deny the application;</para>
<para>(c) The licensee has violated a voluntary consent or compliance agreement
which had been entered into with the director;</para>
<para>(d) The licensee has knowingly provided or caused to be provided to
the director any false or fraudulent representation of a material fact or
any false or fraudulent financial statement or suppressed or withheld from
the director any information which, if submitted by the licensee, would have
resulted in denial of the license application;</para>
<para>(e) The licensee has refused to permit an examination by the director
of the licensee's business, records, and accounts pursuant to subsection (1)
of section 45-1017 or refused or failed to comply with subsection (2) of section
45-1017 or failed to make any report required under section 45-1018. Each
day the licensee continues in violation of this subdivision constitutes a
separate violation;</para>
<para>(f) The licensee has failed to maintain records as required by the director
following written notice. Each day the licensee continues in violation of
this subdivision constitutes a separate violation;</para>
<para>(g) The licensee knowingly has employed any individual or knowingly
has maintained a contractual relationship with any individual acting as an
agent, if such individual has been convicted of, pleaded guilty to, or was
found guilty after a plea of nolo contendere to (i) a misdemeanor under any
state or federal law which involves dishonesty or fraud or which involves
any aspect of the mortgage banking business, financial institution business,
or installment loan business or (ii) any felony under state or federal law;</para>
<para>(h) The licensee has violated the written restrictions or conditions
under which the license was issued;</para>
<para>(i) The licensee, or if the licensee is a business entity, one of the
officers, directors, members, partners, or controlling shareholders, was found
guilty after a plea of nolo contendere to (i) a misdemeanor under any state
or federal law which involves dishonesty or fraud or which involves any aspect
of the mortgage banking business, financial institution business, or installment
loan business or (ii) any felony under state or federal law; or</para>
<para>(j) The licensee knowingly
has employed any individual or knowingly has maintained a contractual relationship
with any individual acting as an agent, if such individual is conducting activities
requiring a mortgage loan originator license in this state without first obtaining
such license.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in this section,
a license shall not be revoked or suspended except after notice and a hearing
in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by
the department under the act.</para>
<para>(3)(a) If a licensee fails to renew its license as required by subsection
(1) of section 45-1013 and does not voluntarily surrender the license pursuant
to section 45-1032, the department may issue a notice of expiration of the
license to the licensee in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para>
<para>(b) If a licensee fails to maintain a surety bond as required by section
45-1007, the department may issue a notice of cancellation of the license
in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para>
<para>(4) Revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration of a license
shall not impair or affect the obligation of a preexisting lawful contract
between the licensee and any person, including a borrower.</para>
<para>(5) Revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration of a license
shall not affect civil or criminal liability for acts committed before the
revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration or liability for any fines
which may be imposed against the licensee or any of its officers, directors,
shareholders, partners, or members pursuant to this section or section 45-1069
for acts committed before the surrender.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 218, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 49.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>