<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, And Debt" statutenumber="45-1026" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1026</statuteno><catchline>Installment loans; insurance upon security; licensee may require; restrictions; refunds; when.</catchline><para>(1) The following types of insurance or one or more of the following types of insurance may be written in connection with loans made by licensees under the Nebraska Installment Loan Act:</para><para>(a) Fire, theft, windstorm, or comprehensive, including fire, theft, and windstorm, fifty dollars or more deductible collision, and bodily injury liability and property damage liability upon motor vehicles;</para><para>(b) Fire and extended-coverage insurance upon real property;</para><para>(c) Fire and extended-coverage insurance upon tangible personal property, limited to the principal amount of the loan;</para><para>(d) Involuntary unemployment or job protection insurance. In the event of a renewal of a loan contract, this type of insurance shall be canceled and a refund of the unearned premium credited or made before new insurance of this type may be rewritten. Such insurance shall not be required as a condition precedent to the making of such loan; and</para><para>(e) Life, health, and accident insurance or any of them, except that the amount of such insurance shall not exceed the total amount to be repaid under the loan contract and the term shall not extend beyond the final maturity date of the loan contract. In the event of a renewal of a loan contract, this type of insurance shall be canceled and a refund of the unearned premium credited or made before new insurance of this type may be written in connection with such loan. Such insurance shall not be required as a condition precedent to the making of such loan.</para><para>(2) In addition to the types of insurance written under subsection (1) of this section by licensees under the act, any other type of insurance or motor club service as defined in section 44-3707 may be provided for the benefit of a licensee's borrower or the borrower's immediate family whether or not in connection with a loan, except that such insurance or motor club service shall not be required as a condition precedent to the making of any loan. Nothing in this subsection alters or eliminates any insurance licensing requirements or certificate of authority requirements under the Motor Club Services Act.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding sections 45-1024 and 45-1025, any gain or advantage, in the form of commission or otherwise, to the licensee or to any employee, affiliate, or associate of the licensee from such insurance or motor club service or the sale thereof shall not be deemed to be an additional or further charge in connection with the loan contract. The insurance premium or motor club service contract fee may be collected from the borrower or financed through the loan contract at the time the loan is made.</para><para>(4)(a) Insurance permitted under this section shall be obtained through a duly licensed insurance agent, agency, or broker. Premiums shall not exceed those fixed by law or current applicable manual rates. Insurance written, as authorized by this section, may contain a mortgage clause or other appropriate provision to protect the insurable interest of the licensee.</para><para>(b) Motor club services permitted under this section shall be obtained through a motor club which holds a certificate of authority under the Motor Club Services Act.</para><para>(5) In the event of a renewal of a loan contract, any insurance or motor club service sold pursuant to this section shall be canceled and (a) a refund of the unearned premium or motor club service contract fee credited or made before new insurance or motor club service of the same type as that being canceled may be rewritten or (b) the holder of the loan contract shall send notice to the buyer within fifteen business days after cancellation of the name, address, and telephone number of the insurance company or motor club which issued the insurance contract or motor club service contract or the party responsible for any refund and notice that the buyer may be eligible for a refund. A copy of such notice shall be retained by the holder of the loan contract.</para><para>(6) If any insurance or motor club service sold pursuant to this section is canceled or the premium or motor club service contract fee adjusted during the term of the loan contract, any refund of the insurance premium or motor club service contract fee plus the unearned interest thereon received by the holder shall be credited by the holder to the loan contract or otherwise refunded, except to the extent applied toward payment for similar insurance or motor club service protecting the interests of the buyer and the holder or either of them.</para><para>(7) If any insurance or motor club service sold pursuant to this section is canceled due to the payment of all sums for which the buyer is liable under a loan contract, the holder of the loan contract shall, upon receipt of payment of all sums due, send notice to the buyer within fifteen business days after payment of the sums due of the name, address, and telephone number of the insurance company or motor club which issued the insurance contract or motor club service contract or the party responsible for any refund and notice that the buyer may be eligible for a refund. A copy of such notice shall be retained by the holder of the loan contract. This subsection does not apply if the holder of the loan contract previously credited the refund of the insurance premium or motor club service contract fee to the loan contract or otherwise refunded the insurance premium or motor club service contract fee to the buyer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 90, &#167; 17, p. 351; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 45-145; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 45-139; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 155, &#167; 3, p. 491; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1094, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 555, &#167; 19; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1998), &#167; 45-139; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 51. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Club Services Act,</emphasis> see section 44-3701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Charges made under this section are permitted to be included in an installment loan. Berg v. Midwest Laundry Equipment Corp., 178 Neb. 770, 135 N.W.2d 457 (1965).</para><para>Charges for life, health, and accident insurance as a condition for making loan were violation of act. State ex rel. Beck v. Associates Discount Corp., 162 Neb. 683, 77 N.W.2d 215 (1956).</para><para>Insurance premium is a proper item to be included in loan. Underwriters Acceptance Corp. v. Dunkin, 152 Neb. 550, 41 N.W.2d 855 (1950).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>