<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Interest, Loans, and Debt" statutenumber="45-1055"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>45-1055</statuteno><catchline>Writing evidencing borrower's obligation; form; copies; fee; licensee; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The licensee shall give to the borrower a copy of any writing evidencing a loan if the writing requires or provides for the signature of the borrower. The writing evidencing the borrower's obligation to pay under a loan shall contain a clear and conspicuous notice in form and content substantially as follows:</para><para>NOTICE TO CONSUMER: 1. Do not sign this paper before you read it. 2. You are entitled to a copy of this paper. 3. You may prepay the unpaid balance at any time without penalty and may be entitled to receive a refund of unearned charges in accordance with law.</para><para>(2) Upon written request of a borrower, the licensee shall provide a written statement of the dates and amounts of payments made and the amounts of any default and deferment charges assessed preceding the month in which the request is received and the total amount unpaid as the end of the period covered by the statement and a copy of the loan agreement, security agreement, and a facsimile of any insurance certificate issued as part of the transaction, if applicable. The licensee may charge a reasonable fee for such copies, not to exceed fifty cents per page.</para><para>(3) The licensee shall answer in writing, within ten business days after receipt, any written request for payoff information from the borrower or the borrower's representative. This service shall be provided without charge to the borrower, except that when such information is provided upon request within sixty days after the fulfillment of a previous request, a processing fee of up to ten dollars may be charged.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 87, &#167; 18; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1998), &#167; 45-185; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 65. </para></source></law></legaldoc>