<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-503</statuteno><catchline>Requisition by county clerk.</catchline><para>The county clerk of each county shall make a requisition upon the Secretary of State for copies of the session laws and the journal of the Legislature for the use of the county of which he or she is clerk. The county clerk shall make the requisition for session laws based on the classification of the county by population as provided in section 23-1114.01. A Class 1 county may request a maximum of three sets, a Class 2 county may request a maximum of five sets, a Class 3 county may request a maximum of seven sets, a Class 4 county may request a maximum of ten sets, a Class 5 county may request a maximum of twelve sets, a Class 6 county may request a maximum of twenty sets, and a Class 7 county may request a maximum of twenty-five sets. The county clerk shall make a requisition for less than the maximum amount authorized if he or she finds that a lesser amount is sufficient for the needs of the county. The county clerk shall make a requisition for one copy of the journal of the Legislature. The Secretary of State shall forward the session laws and journal to each county by the most expeditious and economic means and in print or electronic format as he or she determines, upon recommendation by the Clerk of the Legislature and approval of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1907, c. 78, &#167; 2, p. 289; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3735; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3128; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 49-503; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 49-503; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 572, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 534, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 