<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id540"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id195" statutenumber="49-801"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>49-801</statuteno><catchline id="id198">Statutes; terms, defined.</catchline><para>Unless the context is shown to intend otherwise, words and phrases in the statutes of Nebraska hereafter enacted are used in the following sense:</para><para>(1) Acquire when used in connection with a grant of power or property right to any person includes the purchase, grant, gift, devise, bequest, and obtaining by eminent domain;</para><para>(2) Action includes any proceeding in any court of this state;</para><para>(3) Attorney means attorney at law;</para><para>(4) Company includes any corporation, partnership, limited liability company, joint-stock company, joint venture, or association;</para><para>(5) Domestic when applied to corporations means all those created by authority of this state;</para><para>(6) Federal refers to the United States;</para><para>(7) Foreign when applied to corporations includes all those created by authority other than that of this state;</para><para>(8) Grantee includes every person to whom any estate or interest passes in or by any conveyance;</para><para>(9) Grantor includes every person from or by whom any estate or interest passes in or by any conveyance;</para><para>(10) Inhabitant shall be construed to mean a resident in the particular locality in reference to which that word is used;</para><para>(11) Land or real estate includes lands, tenements, and hereditaments and all rights thereto and interest therein other than a chattel interest;</para><para>(12) Magistrate includes judge of the county court and clerk magistrate;</para><para>(13) Military or veteran status means a person:</para><para>(a) Is serving active duty service in the armed forces of the United States, including any reserve component or the National Guard;</para><para>(b) Has served on such active duty and was discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions); or</para><para>(c) Is a dependent, as defined in 50 U.S.C. 3911, of a person described in subdivision (13)(a) or (b) of this section;</para><para>(14) Month means calendar month;</para><para>(15) Oath includes affirmation in all cases in which an affirmation may be substituted for an oath;</para><para>(16) Peace officer includes sheriffs, coroners, jailers, marshals, police officers, state highway patrol officers, members of the National Guard on active service by direction of the Governor during periods of emergency, and all other persons with similar authority to make arrests;</para><para>(17) Person includes bodies politic and corporate, societies, communities, the public generally, individuals, partnerships, limited liability companies, joint-stock companies, and associations;</para><para>(18) Personal estate includes money, goods, chattels, claims, and evidences of debt;</para><para>(19) Process means a summons, subpoena, or notice to appear issued out of a court in the course of judicial proceedings;</para><para>(20) Service animal has the same meaning as in 28 C.F.R. 36.104, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2008;</para><para>(21) State when applied to different states of the United States shall be construed to extend to and include the District of Columbia and the several territories organized by Congress;</para><para>(22) Sworn includes affirmed in all cases in which an affirmation may be substituted for an oath;</para><para>(23) The United States includes territories, outlying possessions, and the District of Columbia;</para><para>(24) Violate includes failure to comply with;</para><para>(25) Writ shall signify an order or citation in writing issued in the name of the state out of a court or by a judicial officer; and</para><para>(26) Year means calendar year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 182, &#167; 1, p. 601; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 175, &#167; 2, p. 490; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 255; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 481, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1030, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 303; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB806, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 92. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><annotation><para>In conjunction with section 25-2221 and subsection (13) of this section, a political subdivision has until the end of the last day of the 6-month period after a claimant has filed a tort claim upon which to make a final disposition of such claim. Geddes v. York County, 273 Neb. 271, 729 N.W.2d 661 (2007).</para><para>Unless the context is shown to intend otherwise, action includes any proceeding in a court and only final orders therein are bases for appeals. Grantham v. General Telephone Co., 187 Neb. 647, 193 N.W.2d 449 (1972).</para><para>Term person in statutes includes a corporation. Fosler v. Aden, 175 Neb. 535, 122 N.W.2d 494 (1963).</para><para>The word month is legislatively defined as calendar month. Ruan Transport Corp. v. Peake Inc., 163 Neb. 319, 79 N.W.2d 575 (1956).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>