<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<?APT Element gi="legaldoc"?>
<?APT Element gi="law" attrs="type"?>
<?APT Element gi="section" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="sectno" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="amendatorysection" attrs="amended chaptername id statutenumber"?>
<?APT Element gi="bookinfo"?>
<?APT Element gi="statuteno" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="catchline" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="para"?>
<?APT Element gi="source"?>
<?APT Element gi="effectivedate"?>
<?APT Element gi="annotation"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id193"><sectno id="id194">Sec.
12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id195"
statutenumber="49-801"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno
id="id197">49-801</statuteno><catchline id="id198">Statutes; terms, defined.</catchline><para>Unless
the context is shown to intend otherwise, words and phrases in the statutes
of Nebraska hereafter enacted are used in the following sense:</para><para>(1)
Acquire when used in connection with a grant of power or property right to
any person shall include the purchase, grant, gift, devise, bequest, and obtaining
by eminent domain;</para><para>(2) Action shall include any proceeding in
any court of this state;</para><para>(3) Attorney shall mean attorney at law;</para><para>(4)
Company shall include any corporation, partnership, limited liability company,
joint-stock company, joint venture, or association;</para><para>(5) Domestic
when applied to corporations shall mean all those created by authority of
this state;</para><para>(6) Federal shall refer to the United States;</para><para>(7)
Foreign when applied to corporations shall include all those created by authority
other than that of this state;</para><para>(8) Grantee shall include every
person to whom any estate or interest passes in or by any conveyance;</para><para>(9)
Grantor shall include every person from or by whom any estate or interest
passes in or by any conveyance;</para><para>(10) Inhabitant shall be construed
to mean a resident in the particular locality in reference to which that word
is used;</para><para>(11) Land or real estate shall include lands, tenements,
and hereditaments and all rights thereto and interest therein other than a
chattel interest;</para><para>(12) Magistrate shall include judge of the county
court and clerk magistrate;</para><para>(13) Month shall mean calendar month;</para><para>(14)
Oath shall include affirmation in all cases in which an affirmation may be
substituted for an oath;</para><para>(15) Peace officer shall include sheriffs,
coroners, jailers, marshals, police officers, state highway patrol officers,
members of the National Guard on active service by direction of the Governor
during periods of emergency, and all other persons with similar authority
to make arrests;</para><para>(16) Person shall include bodies politic and
corporate, societies, communities, the public generally, individuals, partnerships,
limited liability companies, joint-stock companies, and associations;</para><para>(17)
Personal estate shall include money, goods, chattels, claims, and evidences
of debt;</para><para>(18) Process shall mean a summons, subpoena, or notice
to appear issued out of a court in the course of judicial proceedings;</para><para>(19)
Service animal shall have the same meaning as in 28 C.F.R. 36.104, as such
regulation existed on January 1, 2008;</para><para>(20) State when applied
to different states of the United States shall be construed to extend to and
include the District of Columbia and the several territories organized by
Congress;</para><para>(21) Sworn shall include affirmed in all cases in which
an affirmation may be substituted for an oath;</para><para>(22) The United
States shall include territories, outlying possessions, and the District of
Columbia;</para><para>(23) Violate shall include failure to comply with;</para><para>(24)
Writ shall signify an order or citation in writing issued in the name of the
state out of a court or by a judicial officer; and</para><para>(25) Year shall
mean calendar year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 182, &#167; 1, p. 601; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 175, &#167; 2, p. 490; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 255; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 481, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1030, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 303; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB806, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>In
conjunction with section 25-2221 and subsection (13) of this section, a political
subdivision has until the end of the last day of the 6-month period after
a claimant has filed a tort claim upon which to make a final disposition of
such claim. Geddes v. York County, 273 Neb. 271, 729 N.W.2d 661 (2007).</para><para>Unless
the context is shown to intend otherwise, action includes any proceeding in
a court and only final orders therein are bases for appeals. Grantham v. General
Telephone Co., 187 Neb. 647, 193 N.W.2d 449 (1972).</para><para>Term person
in statutes includes a corporation. Fosler v. Aden, 175 Neb. 535, 122 N.W.2d
494 (1963).</para><para>The word month is legislatively defined as calendar
month. Ruan Transport Corp. v. Peake Inc., 163 Neb. 319, 79 N.W.2d 575 (1956).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
