<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id178"><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-601"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>49-601</statuteno><catchline>Session laws, journals, statutes; distribution; publication; printing; Clerk of the Legislature; Revisor of Statutes; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Clerk of the Legislature is authorized to distribute the session laws, the journal of the Legislature, and the statutes of the state. The session laws, journal, and statutes may be published in print or electronic format or in both formats.</para><para>(2) The session laws and journal shall be compiled and published by the Clerk of the Legislature after each regular session of the Legislature. The session laws shall contain all the laws passed by the preceding session as well as those passed during any special session since the last regular session. The session laws shall also contain a certified copy of the Constitution of Nebraska as required by section 49-1701. The clerk shall distribute one copy of the session laws and the journal to each member of the Legislature and shall distribute a second copy to any member of the Legislature upon such member's request.</para><para>(3) The Revisor of Statutes shall cause the statutes to be printed pursuant to section 49-704 and the policy described in subsection (4) of this section. The printer shall deliver all completed copies to the Clerk of the Legislature for distribution.</para><para>(4) The Clerk of the Legislature shall provide copies of the session laws, journal, and statutes for distribution to judges, county officers and offices, state officers and agencies, libraries, and other persons pursuant to a policy adopted by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council. The clerk shall distribute such copies by the most expeditious and economic means as the clerk determines pursuant to the policy adopted by the executive board. Any person may send a request to the clerk for printed copies of the session laws, journal, or statutes and shall pay the cost of production and delivery of such copies as such costs are determined by the clerk based on prices prescribed by the executive board pursuant to the policy. The clerk may sell or otherwise dispose of copies determined to be surplus or superseded pursuant to the policy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1236, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2027</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>