<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id6" statutenumber="49-617"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>49-617</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Printing of statutes; distribution of copies.</catchline><para>The Revisor of Statutes shall cause the statutes to be printed. The printer shall deliver all completed copies to the Supreme Court. These copies shall be held and disposed of by the court as follows: Sixty copies to the State Library to exchange for statutes of other states; five copies to the State Library to keep for daily use; not to exceed twenty-five copies to the Legislative Council for bill drafting and related services to the Legislature and executive state officers; as many copies to the Attorney General as he or she has attorneys on his or her staff; as many copies to the Commission on Public Advocacy as it has attorneys on its staff; up to sixteen copies to the State Court Administrator; thirteen copies to the Tax Commissioner; eight copies to the Nebraska Publications Clearinghouse; six copies to the Public Service Commission; four copies to the Secretary of State; three copies to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission; four copies to the Clerk of the Legislature for use in his or her office and three copies to be maintained in the legislative chamber, one copy on each side of the chamber and one copy at the desk of the Clerk of the Legislature, under control of the sergeant at arms; three copies to the Department of Health and Human Services; two copies each to the Governor of the state, the Chief Justice and each judge of the Supreme Court, each judge of the Court of Appeals, the Clerk of the Supreme Court, the Reporter of Decisions, the Commissioner of Labor, the Auditor of Public Accounts, and the Revisor of Statutes; one copy each to the Secretary of State of the United States, each Indian tribal court located in the State of Nebraska, the library of the Supreme Court of the United States, the Adjutant General, the Air National Guard, the Commissioner of Education, the State Treasurer, the Board of Educational Lands and Funds, the Director of Agriculture, the Director of Administrative Services, the Director of Economic Development, the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, the Director-State Engineer, the Director of Banking and Finance, the Director of Insurance, the Director of Motor Vehicles, the Director of Veterans' Affairs, the Director of Natural Resources, the Director of Correctional Services, the Nebraska Emergency Operating Center, each judge of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, each commissioner of the Commission of Industrial Relations, the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, the State Real Estate Commission, the secretary of the Game and Parks Commission, the Board of Pardons, each state institution under the Department of Health and Human Services, each state institution under the State Department of Education, the State Surveyor, the Nebraska State Patrol, the materiel division of the Department of Administrative Services, the personnel division of the Department of Administrative Services, the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Board, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, each of the Nebraska state colleges, each district judge of the State of Nebraska, each judge of the county court, each judge of a separate juvenile court, the Lieutenant Governor, each United States Senator from Nebraska, each United States Representative from Nebraska, each clerk of the district court for the use of the district court, the clerk of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, each clerk of the county court, each county attorney, each county public defender, each county law library, and the inmate library at all state penal and correctional institutions, and each member of the Legislature shall be entitled to two complete sets, and two complete sets of such volumes as are necessary to update previously issued volumes, but each member of the Legislature and each judge of any court referred to in this section shall be entitled, on request, to an additional complete set. Copies of the statutes distributed without charge, as listed in this section, shall be the property of the state or governmental subdivision of the state and not the personal property of the particular person receiving a copy. Distribution of statutes to the library of the College of Law of the University of Nebraska shall be as provided in sections 85-176 and 85-177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 115, &#167; 17, p. 407; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 49-617; </para><para>Laws 1944, Spec. Sess., c. 3, &#167; 5, p. 100; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 185, &#167; 5, p. 612; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 345, &#167; 1, p. 1132; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 210, &#167; 3, p. 743; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 242, &#167; 2, p. 722; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 243, &#167; 3, p. 725; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 415, &#167; 5, p. 1247; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 416, &#167; 8, p. 1266; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 303, &#167; 3, p. 898; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 305, &#167; 1, p. 858; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 325, &#167; 1, p. 863; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 326, &#167; 1, p. 865; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 36, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 254; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1174, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1284, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 1, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 563, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 572, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 595, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 59, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 168, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 498, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 572, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 118; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 14, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 271, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 906, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 278; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 36, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 692, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 241; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1085, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 223; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB472, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB770, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB799, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>