<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-506"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-506</statuteno><catchline>Distribution by Secretary of State.</catchline><para>After the Secretary of State has made the distribution provided by section 49-503, he or she shall deliver additional copies of the session laws and the journal of the Legislature pursuant to this section in print or electronic format as he or she determines, upon recommendation by the Clerk of the Legislature and approval of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>One copy of the session laws shall be delivered to the Lieutenant Governor, the State Treasurer, the Auditor of Public Accounts, the Reporter of the Supreme Court and Court of Appeals, the State Court Administrator, the State Fire Marshal, the Department of Administrative Services, the Department of Agriculture, the Department of Banking and Finance, the State Department of Education, the Department of Environment and Energy, the Department of Insurance, the Department of Labor, the Department of Motor Vehicles, the Department of Revenue, the Department of Transportation, the Department of Veterans' Affairs, the Department of Natural Resources, the Military Department, the Nebraska State Patrol, the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice, each of the Nebraska state colleges, the Game and Parks Commission, the Nebraska Library Commission, the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, the Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission, the Public Service Commission, the State Real Estate Commission, the Nebraska State Historical Society, the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Risk Manager, the Legislative Fiscal Analyst, the Public Counsel, the materiel division of the Department of Administrative Services, the State Records Administrator, the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services, the Tax Equalization and Review Commission, the inmate library at all state penal and correctional institutions, the Commission on Public Advocacy, and the Library of Congress; two copies to the Governor, the Secretary of State, the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, the Commission of Industrial Relations, and the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education, one of which shall be for use by the community colleges; three copies to the Department of Health and Human Services; four copies to the Nebraska Publications Clearinghouse; five copies to the Attorney General; nine copies to the Revisor of Statutes; sixteen copies to the Supreme Court and the Legislative Council; and thirty-five copies to the University of Nebraska College of Law.</para><para>One copy of the journal of the Legislature shall be delivered to the Governor, the Lieutenant Governor, the State Treasurer, the Auditor of Public Accounts, the Reporter of the Supreme Court and Court of Appeals, the State Court Administrator, the Nebraska State Historical Society, the Legislative Fiscal Analyst, the Tax Equalization and Review Commission, the Commission on Public Advocacy, and the Library of Congress; two copies to the Secretary of State, the Commission of Industrial Relations, and the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court; four copies to the Nebraska Publications Clearinghouse; five copies to the Attorney General and the Revisor of Statutes; eight copies to the Clerk of the Legislature; thirteen copies to the Supreme Court and the Legislative Council; and thirty-five copies to the University of Nebraska College of Law. The remaining copies shall be delivered to the State Librarian who shall use the same, so far as required for exchange purposes, in building up the State Library and in the manner specified in sections 49-507 to 49-509.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1907, c. 78, &#167; 6, p. 290; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3738; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3131; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 49-506; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 49-506; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 185, &#167; 4, p. 611; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 243, &#167; 2, p. 725; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 413, &#167; 1, p. 1419; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1284, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 572, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 271, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 906, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 277; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 36, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 534, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 240; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1085, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 222; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 176; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 54. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>