<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id307">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id309" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="49-14,124"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>49-14,124</statuteno><catchline id="id312">Alleged violation;
preliminary investigation by commission; powers; notice.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall, by way of preliminary investigation,
investigate any alleged violation of the Nebraska Political Accountability
and Disclosure Act, or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated thereunder,
upon:</para>
<para>(a) The receipt of a complaint signed under oath which contains
at least a reasonable belief that a violation has occurred;</para>
<para>(b) The recommendation of the executive director; or</para>
<para>(c) The commission's own motion.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of conducting preliminary investigations
under the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure
Act, the commission shall have the powers possessed by the courts of this
state to issue subpoenas, and the district court shall have jurisdiction to
enforce such subpoenas.</para>
<para>(3) The executive director
shall notify any person under investigation by the commission of the investigation
and of the nature of the alleged violation within five days after the commencement
of the investigation.</para>
<para>(4) Within fifteen days after
the filing of a sworn complaint by a person alleging a violation, and every
thirty days thereafter until the matter is terminated, the executive director
shall notify the complainant and the alleged violator of the action taken
to date by the commission together with the reasons for such action or for
nonaction.</para>
<para>(5) Each governing body shall
cooperate with the commission in the conduct of its investigations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 49, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 420, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 578, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 188, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 28.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>