<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1458"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1458</statuteno><catchline>Late contribution; how reported; late filing fee.</catchline><para>(1) A committee which receives a late contribution shall report the contribution to the commission by filing a report within two days after the date of its receipt. The report may be filed by hand delivery, facsimile transmission, telegraph, express delivery service, or any other written means of communication, including electronic means approved by the commission, and need not contain an original signature.</para><para>(2) The report shall include the full name, street address, occupation, employer, and principal place of business of the contributor, the amount of the contribution, and the date of receipt.</para><para>(3) A late contribution shall be reported on subsequent campaign statements without regard to reports filed pursuant to this section.</para><para>(4) Any committee which fails to file a report of late contributions with the commission as required by this section shall pay to the commission a late filing fee of one hundred dollars for each of the first ten days the report remains not filed in violation of this section. After the tenth day, such committee shall pay, for each day the report remains not filed, an additional late filing fee of one percent of the amount of the late contribution which was required to be reported, not to exceed ten percent of the amount of the late contribution which was required to be reported. </para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, late contribution means a contribution of one thousand dollars or more received after the closing date for campaign statements as provided in subdivision (1)(b) of section 49-1459.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1263, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 438, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB434, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>