<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-14,112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-14,112</statuteno><catchline>Commission; members; vacancy; how filled.</catchline><para>(1) When a vacancy occurs by expiration of a term of office or otherwise, which vacancy is subject to an appointment from a list pursuant to the provisions of section 49-14,105, such list shall be submitted to the Governor or the Secretary of State not later than thirty days after such vacancy occurs.</para><para>(2) If the appointment is subject to a list pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of section 49-14,105, and the Legislature is not in session, such list may be submitted by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>(3) The Governor or the Secretary of State shall make his or her appointment within thirty days of receiving the list provided for in section 49-14,105 unless two or more of the individuals whose names appear on the list are unwilling to withdraw from activities or resign from positions as required by section 49-14,114. If such individuals are unwilling to so withdraw or resign, the Governor or the Secretary of State shall notify the provider of the list. Within thirty days after such notification is received, a new list of names of at least five individuals shall be submitted to the Governor or Secretary of State. Such new list shall not include the individuals included in the initial list who were unwilling to withdraw from activities or resign from positions as required by section 49-14,114.</para><para>(4) The Governor or Secretary of State shall appoint an individual from the new list within thirty days of receipt unless two or more of the individuals whose names appear on the second list are unwilling to withdraw from activities or resign from positions as required by section 49-14,114. In such event, the Governor or Secretary of State shall appoint an individual of his or her own choosing within thirty days after the receipt of the new list.</para><para>(5) If the Governor or Secretary of State does not receive the initial list within thirty days of a vacancy, the Governor or Secretary of State may make an appointment of his or her own choosing. If the Governor or Secretary of State does not receive the second list within thirty days after notification to the provider of the list, the Governor or Secretary of State may make an appointment of his or her own choosing.</para><para>(6) All appointments of the Governor or Secretary of State shall be subject to sections 49-14,106 and 49-14,110 and subsection (2) of section 49-14,111.</para><para>(7) No individual appointed to the commission shall serve more than one full six-year term on the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 54, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 534, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 53. </para></source></law></legaldoc>