<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1499.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1499.02</statuteno><catchline>Executive branch; discharge of official duties; potential conflict; actions required.</catchline><para>(1) An official or employee of the executive branch of state government who would be required to take any action or make any decision in the discharge of his or her official duties that may cause financial benefit or detriment to him or her, a member of his or her immediate family, or a business with which he or she is associated, which is distinguishable from the effects of such action on the public generally or a broad segment of the public, shall take the following actions as soon as he or she is aware of such potential conflict or should reasonably be aware of such potential conflict, whichever is sooner:</para><para>(a) Prepare a written statement describing the matter requiring action or decision and the nature of the potential conflict; and</para><para>(b) Deliver a copy of the statement to the commission and to his or her immediate superior, if any, who shall assign the matter to another. If the immediate superior does not assign the matter to another or if there is no immediate superior, the official or employee shall take such action as the commission shall advise or prescribe to remove himself or herself from influence over the action or decision on the matter.</para><para>(2) This section does not prevent such a person from (a) making or participating in the making of a governmental decision to the extent that the individual's participation is legally required for the action or decision to be made or (b) making or participating in the making of a governmental decision if the potential conflict of interest is based upon a business association and the business association exists only as the result of his or her position on a commodity board. A person acting pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection shall report the occurrence to the commission.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, commodity board means only the following:</para><para>(a) Corn Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board;</para><para>(b) Nebraska Dairy Industry Development Board;</para><para>(c) Grain Sorghum Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board;</para><para>(d) Nebraska Wheat Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board;</para><para>(e) Dry Bean Commission;</para><para>(f) Nebraska Potato Development Committee;</para><para>(g) Nebraska Poultry and Egg Development, Utilization, and Marketing Committee; and</para><para>(h) Dry Pea and Lentil Commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB803, &#167; 21. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>