<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id00" renumber="yes"><amendatorysection amended="no" id="id00" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="49-1802" chaptername="Law"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1802</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para id="id00">In the Uniform Unsworn Foreign Declarations Act:</para><para id="id00">(1) Boundaries of the United States means the geographic boundaries of the United States, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, and any territory or insular possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States.</para><para id="id00">(2) Law includes the federal or a state constitution, a federal or state statute, a judicial decision or order, a rule of court, an executive order, and an administrative rule, regulation, or order.</para><para id="id00">(3) Record means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium and is retrievable in perceivable form.</para><para id="id00">(4) Sign means, with present intent to authenticate or adopt a record:</para><para id="id00">(A) to execute or adopt a tangible symbol; or</para><para id="id00">(B) to attach to or logically associate with the record an electronic symbol, sound, or process.</para><para id="id00">(5) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any territory or insular possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States.</para><para id="id00">(6) Sworn declaration means a declaration in a signed record given under oath. The term includes a sworn statement, verification, certificate, and affidavit.</para><para id="id00">(7) Unsworn declaration means a declaration in a signed record that is not given under oath, but is given under penalty of perjury.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB57, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>