<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id369">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id371" statutenumber="49-14,132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>49-14,132</statuteno><catchline id="id374">Filings;
limitation of use.</catchline><para>Information copied from campaign
statements, registration forms, activity reports, statements of financial
interest, and other filings required by the Nebraska Political Accountability
and Disclosure Act shall not be sold or used by any person for the purpose
of soliciting contributions or for commercial purposes, except that (1) the
name and address of any political committee or entity specified in subsection (1)
of section 49-1469 may be used for soliciting contributions from
such committee or
entity and (2) the use of information copied or otherwise obtained
from statements, forms, reports, and other filings required by the act in
newspapers, magazines, books, or other similar communications is permissible
as long as the principal purpose of using such information is not to communicate
any contributor information listed thereon for the purpose of soliciting contributions
or for other commercial purposes.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 132; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 134, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 34.</para></source><annotation><para>Prohibition by this section of use of public information for "other political campaign purposes", as applied in this case, placed an impermissible burden on protected speech and is struck down for being overbroad. Provision in this statute which prohibits use of information for harassment purposes is held to be so vague as to be constitutionally infirm and is therefore struck down. Fowler v. Neb. Account. and Disclosure Comm., 213 Neb. 462, 330 N.W.2d 136 (1983).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>