<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id280">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id282" statutenumber="49-1469"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1469</statuteno><catchline id="id285">Businesses
and organizations; contributions, expenditures, or services; report; contents;
separate segregated political fund; when required.</catchline><para>(1)
A corporation, labor organization, industry, trade, or professional association,
limited liability company, or limited liability partnership, which is organized
under the laws of the State of Nebraska or doing business in this state and
which is not a committee, may:</para>
<para>(a) Make an expenditure;</para>
<para>(b) Make a contribution; and</para>
<para>(c) Provide personal services.</para>
<para>(2) Any such entity shall not be required to file reports
of independent expenditures pursuant to section 49-1467, but if it makes a
contribution or expenditure, or provides personal services, with a value of more than two hundred fifty
dollars, it shall file a report
with the commission within ten days after the end of the calendar month in
which the contribution or expenditure is made or the personal services are
provided. The report shall include:</para>
<para>(a) The nature, date, and value of the contribution or expenditure
and the name of the candidate or committee or a description of the ballot
question to or for which the contribution or expenditure was made; and</para>
<para>(b) A description of any personal services provided, the
date the services were provided, and the name of the candidate or committee
or a description of the ballot question to or for which the personal services
were provided.</para>
<para>(3) Any entity specified in subsection (1) of this section
may not receive contributions unless it establishes and administers a separate
segregated political fund which shall be utilized only in the manner set forth
in sections 49-1469.05 and 49-1469.06.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 535, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 214, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1136, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 587, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1263, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>