<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1483"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1483</statuteno><catchline>Lobbyist and principal; file separate
statements; when; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Every lobbyist who is registered
or required to be registered shall, for each of his or her principals, file electronically a separate
statement for each calendar quarter with the Clerk of the Legislature within
thirty days after the end of each calendar quarter. Every principal employing
a lobbyist who is registered or required to be registered shall file electronically a separate
statement for each calendar quarter with the Clerk of the Legislature within
thirty days after the end of each calendar quarter.</para>
<para>(2) Each statement shall show the following:</para>
<para>(a) The total amount received or expended directly or indirectly for
the purpose of carrying on lobbying activities, with the following categories
of expenses each being separately itemized: (i) Miscellaneous expenses; (ii)
entertainment, including expenses for food and drink as provided in subdivision
(3)(a) of this section; (iii) lodging expenses; (iv) travel expenses; (v)
lobbyist compensation, except that when a principal retains the services of
a person who has only part-time lobbying duties, only the compensation paid
which is reasonably attributable to influencing legislative action need be
reported; (vi) lobbyist expense reimbursement; (vii) admissions to a state-owned
facility or a state-sponsored industry or event as provided in subdivision
(3)(a) of this section; and (viii) extraordinary office expenses directly
related to the practice of lobbying;</para>
<para>(b) A detailed statement of any money which is loaned, promised, or
paid by a lobbyist, a principal, or anyone acting on behalf of either to an
official in the executive or legislative branch or member of such official's
staff. The detailed statement shall identify the recipient and the amount
and the terms of the loan, promise, or payment; and</para>
<para>(c) The total amount expended for gifts, other than admissions to a
state-owned facility or a state-sponsored industry or event, as provided in
subdivision (3)(a) of this section.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Each statement shall disclose the aggregate expenses for entertainment,
admissions, and gifts for each of the following categories of elected officials:
Members of the Legislature; and officials in the executive branch of the state.
Such disclosures shall be in addition to the entertainment expenses reported
under subdivision (2)(a)(ii) of this section, admissions reported under subdivision
(2)(a)(vii) of this section, and gifts reported under subdivision (2)(c) of
this section.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of reporting aggregate expenses for entertainment for
members of the Legislature and officials in the executive branch of the state
as required by subdivision (3)(a) of this section, the reported amount shall
include the actual amounts attributable to entertaining members of the Legislature
and officials in the executive branch of the state. When the nature of an
event at which members of the Legislature are entertained makes it impractical
to determine the actual cost, the cost of entertainment shall be the average
cost per person multiplied by the number of members of the Legislature in
attendance. When the nature of an event at which officials in the executive
branch of the state are entertained makes it impractical to determine the
actual cost, the cost of entertainment shall be the average cost per person
multiplied by the number of officials in the executive branch of the state
in attendance. For purposes of this subdivision, the average cost per person
means the cost of the event divided by the number of persons expected to attend
the event.</para>
<para>(4) The lobbyist shall also file any changes or corrections to the information
set forth in the registration required pursuant to section 49-1480 so as to
reflect the correctness of such information as of the end of each calendar
quarter for which such statement is required by this section.</para>
<para>(5) If a lobbyist does not expect to receive lobbying receipts from
or does not expect to make lobbying expenditures for a principal, the quarterly
statements required by this section as to such principal need not be filed
by the lobbyist if the principal and lobbyist both certify such facts electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature.
A lobbyist exempt from filing quarterly statements pursuant to this section
shall (a) file a statement of activity pursuant to section 49-1488 and (b)
resume or commence filing quarterly statements with regard to such principal
starting with the quarterly period the lobbyist receives lobbying receipts
or makes lobbying expenditures for such principal.</para>
<para>(6) If a principal does not expect to receive lobbying receipts or does
not expect to make lobbying expenditures, the quarterly statements required
pursuant to this section need not be filed by the principal if the principal
and lobbyist both certify such facts electronically to
the Clerk of the Legislature. A principal exempt from filing quarterly statements
pursuant to this section shall commence or resume filing quarterly statements
starting with the quarterly period the principal receives lobbying receipts
or makes lobbying expenditures.</para>
<para>(7) A principal shall report electronically the
name and address of every person from whom it has received more than one hundred
dollars in any one month for lobbying purposes.</para>
<para>(8) For purposes of sections 49-1480 to 49-1492.01, calendar quarter means the first day of January through the thirty-first
day of March, the first day of April through the thirtieth day of June, the
first day of July through the thirtieth day of September, and the first day
of October through the thirty-first day of December.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 162, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 479, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 232, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 872, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1243, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1021, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 70.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>