<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1492.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1492.01</statuteno><catchline>Agency, political subdivision,
or publicly funded postsecondary educational institution; gifts; reporting
requirements; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any agency, political
subdivision, or publicly funded postsecondary educational institution which
gives a gift of an admission to a state-owned facility or a state-sponsored
industry or event to a public official, a member of a public official's staff,
or a member of the immediate family of a public official shall report the
gift on a form prescribed by the commission.</para>
<para>(2) The report shall be filed electronically with
the Clerk of the Legislature within fifteen days after the end of the calendar
quarter in which the gift is given. The report shall include the following:</para>
<para>(a) The identity of the agency, political subdivision, or publicly funded
postsecondary educational institution;</para>
<para>(b) A description of the gift;</para>
<para>(c) The value of the gift; and</para>
<para>(d) The name of the recipient of the gift and the following:</para>
<para>(i) If the recipient is an official in the executive or legislative
branch of state government, the office held by the official and the branch
he or she serves;</para>
<para>(ii) If the recipient is a member of an official's staff in the executive
or legislative branch of state government, his or her job title and the name
of the official; or</para>
<para>(iii) If the recipient is a member of the immediate family of an official
in the executive or legislative branch of state government, his or her relationship
to the official and the name of the official.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section, public official does not include an
elected or appointed official of a political subdivision or school board.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who knowingly and intentionally violates this section
shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1021, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 73.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>