<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1479.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1479.01</statuteno><catchline>Earmarked contribution; requirements; report; late filing fee; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any contribution by a person made on behalf of or to a candidate or committee, including contributions which are in any way earmarked or otherwise directed to the candidate or committee through an intermediary or agent, shall be considered to be a contribution from the person to the candidate or committee.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, earmarked shall mean a designation, instruction, or encumbrance, including those which are direct or indirect, express or implied, or oral or written, which results in any part of a contribution or expenditure, including any in-kind expenditure made in exchange for a contribution, being made to or expended on behalf of a candidate or a committee.</para><para>(3) Any intermediary or agent, other than a committee, which receives an earmarked contribution shall forward the earmarked contribution to the recipient candidate or committee within ten days after receipt of such contribution.</para><para>(4) An intermediary or agent which is not a committee shall file a report of the earmarked contribution with the commission within ten days after receipt of the contribution. Any committee which is an intermediary or agent shall file a report of the earmarked contribution with the commission by the date the next campaign statement is required to be filed. The report of the earmarked contribution filed pursuant to this section shall be on a form prescribed by the commission.</para><para>(5) Any intermediary or agent making an earmarked contribution shall disclose to the recipient of the earmarked contribution the name and address of the intermediary or agent and the actual source of the contribution by providing the recipient with a copy of the report of the earmarked contribution at the time that the earmarked contribution is made.</para><para>(6) Any person or committee which fails to file a report of an earmarked contribution with the commission as required by this section shall pay to the commission a late filing fee of twenty-five dollars for each day the statement remains not filed in violation of this section not to exceed seven hundred fifty dollars.</para><para>(7) Any person who knowingly violates this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 480, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1263, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 28. </para></source></law></legaldoc>