<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1493" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1493</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Individuals required to file a statement of financial interests.</catchline><para>The individuals listed in subdivisions (1) through (13) of this section shall file with the commission a statement of financial interests as provided in sections 49-1496 and 49-1497 for the preceding calendar year on or before March 1 of each year in which such individual holds such a position. An individual who leaves office shall, within thirty days after leaving office, file a statement covering the period since the previous statement was filed. Disclosure of the interest named in sections 49-1496 to 49-1498 shall be made by:</para><para>(1) An individual holding a state executive office as provided in Article IV of the Constitution of Nebraska, including the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Secretary of State, Auditor of Public Accounts, State Treasurer, Attorney General, Tax Commissioner, and heads of such other executive departments as set forth in the Constitution or as may be established by law;</para><para>(2) An individual holding the office of Commissioner of Education, member of the State Board of Education, member of the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska with the exception of student members, or member of the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education;</para><para>(3) A member of the Board of Parole;</para><para>(4) A member of the Public Service Commission;</para><para>(5) A member of the Legislature;</para><para>(6) A member of the board of directors or an officer of a district organized under the provisions of Chapter 70;</para><para>(7) A member of any board or commission of the state or any county which examines or licenses a business or which determines rates for or otherwise regulates a business;</para><para>(8) A member of a land-use planning commission, zoning commission, or authority of the state or any county with a population of more than one hundred thousand inhabitants;</para><para>(9) An elected official of a city of the primary or metropolitan class;</para><para>(10) An elected county official;</para><para>(11) A member of the Nebraska Environmental Trust Board;</para><para>(12) An individual employed at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln in the position of Head Football Coach, Men's Basketball Coach, or Women's Basketball Coach; and</para><para>(13) An official or employee of the state designated by rules and regulations of the commission who is responsible for taking or recommending official action of a nonministerial nature with regard to:</para><para>(a) Contracting or procurement;</para><para>(b) Administering or monitoring grants or subsidies;</para><para>(c) Land-use planning or zoning;</para><para>(d) Inspecting, licensing, regulating, or auditing any person; or</para><para>(e) Any similar action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 214, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 417, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB400, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>