<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id301">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id303" statutenumber="49-1479.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1479.02</statuteno><catchline id="id306">Major out-of-state
contributor; report; contents; applicability; late filing fee.</catchline>
<para>(1) A major out-of-state contributor shall file with the
commission an out-of-state contribution report. An out-of-state contribution
report shall be filed on a form prescribed by the commission within ten days
after the end of the calendar month in which a person becomes a major out-of-state
contributor. For the remainder of the calendar year, a major out-of-state
contributor shall file an out-of-state contribution report with the commission
within ten days after the end of each calendar month in which the contributor
makes a contribution or expenditure.</para>
<para>(2) An out-of-state contribution report shall disclose as
to each contribution or expenditure not previously reported (a) the amount,
nature, value, and date of the contribution or expenditure, (b) the name and
address of the committee, candidate, or person who received the contribution
or expenditure, (c) the name and address of the person filing the report,
and (d) the name, address, occupation, and employer of each person making
a contribution of more than two
hundred dollars in
the calendar year to the person filing the report.</para>
<para>(3) This section shall not apply to (a) a person who files
a report of a contribution or an expenditure pursuant to subsection (2) of
section 49-1469, (b) a person required to file a report or campaign statement
pursuant to section 49-1469.07, (c) a committee having a statement of organization
on file with the commission, or (d) a person or committee registered with
the Federal Election Commission.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who fails to file an out-of-state contribution
report with the commission as required by this section shall pay to the commission
a late filing fee of one hundred dollars for each of the first ten days the
report remains not filed in violation of this section. After the tenth day,
such person shall pay, for each day the report remains not filed, an additional
late filing fee of one percent of the amount of the contributions or expenditures
which were required to be reported, not to exceed ten percent of the amount
of the contributions or expenditures which were required to be reported.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 49, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 15; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 49-1469.04; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB434, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 33.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>