<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1474.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1474.01</statuteno><catchline>Political material; disclaimer requirements; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Except for an individual or individuals acting independently utilizing their own personal resources or as provided in subsection (2) of this section, the person who pays for the production, distribution, or posting of a billboard, placard, poster, pamphlet, or other printed matter relating to a candidate or ballot question shall cause a disclaimer containing the name and street address of the person to appear on such matter. The person who pays for a radio or television advertisement relating to a candidate or ballot question shall cause a disclaimer containing the name of such person to be included in the advertisement, and the radio or television station shall, for a period of at least six months, keep the street address of such person on file and divulge it to any person upon request.</para><para>(2) If a candidate pays for the production, distribution, or posting of a billboard, placard, poster, pamphlet, or other printed material relating to such candidate, then the candidate shall cause a disclaimer containing the name and street address or post office box number of such candidate to appear on such matter. If a candidate pays for a radio or television advertisement relating to such candidate, then the candidate shall cause a disclaimer containing the name of such candidate to be included in the advertisement, and the radio or television station shall, for a period of at least six months, keep the street address or post office box number of such candidate on file and divulge it to any person upon request.</para><para>(3) The size and placement of the disclaimer shall be determined by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. The rules and regulations shall exempt from the disclaimer required by this section windshield stickers, yard signs, bumper stickers, campaign buttons, and balloons and may also exempt other items relating to a candidate or committee which are printed or reproduced at the request of such candidate or committee.</para><para>(4) Any person who knowingly violates the provisions of this section shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 535, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 479, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 637, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 399, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB32, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>