<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id93"><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1479.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1479.03</statuteno><catchline>Foreign national; contribution to ballot question committee; prohibited; exception.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, foreign national means:</para><para>(a) An individual who is not a citizen of the United States or a national of the United States and who is not lawfully admitted for permanent residence;</para><para>(b) A person, other than an individual, organized under the laws of or having its principal place of business in a foreign country;</para><para>(c) A government of a foreign country; or</para><para>(d) A political party or political committee established in a foreign country.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for a foreign national, directly or indirectly, to make a contribution to a ballot question committee or for a ballot question committee to solicit, accept, or receive such a contribution.</para><para>(3) A person, other than an individual, organized under the laws of the United States which is a domestic subsidiary of a foreign national may make a contribution or an expenditure to support or oppose the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question ballot if:</para><para>(a) The person is a discrete entity organized under the laws of any state within the United States and its principal place of business is within the United States;</para><para>(b) The foreign national parent does not finance election-related contributions or expenditures either directly or through such person, including through subsidizing the person's business operations, unless the person can demonstrate by a reasonable accounting method that it has sufficient funds from its own domestic operations to make any contributions or expenditures; and</para><para>(c) All decisions concerning the administration of the person's contributions or expenditures are made by citizens or permanent residents of the United States.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 53. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>