<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id918"><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1474.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1474.03</statuteno><catchline>Campaign advertisement; dissemination; applicability; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies to any election for the following elective offices: Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Secretary of State, State Treasurer, Attorney General, Auditor of Public Accounts, member of the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, member of the State Board of Education, Public Service Commissioner, and member of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Campaign advertisement means a professionally produced visual or audio recording disseminated or caused to be disseminated (i) by a candidate for any elective office listed in this section or by any committee and (ii) for the purpose of supporting or opposing the nomination or election of such a candidate; and</para><para>(b) Professionally produced visual or audio recording does not include a broadcast, rebroadcast, livestreamed, or restreamed live forum, question and answer session, townhall meeting, or interview.</para><para>(3) No campaign advertisement shall be disseminated:</para><para>(a) On television or as a video by means of the Internet unless the campaign advertisement includes closed captioning or the candidate or committee responsible for the campaign advertisement posts a transcript of such campaign advertisement on the candidate's or committee's website; or</para><para>(b) On radio unless the candidate or committee responsible for the campaign advertisement posts a transcript of such campaign advertisement on the candidate's or committee's website.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 52. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>