<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id614"><amendatorysection statutenumber="49-1701" chaptername="Law"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1701</statuteno><catchline>Constitution of Nebraska; Revisor of Statutes; duties; Secretary of State; review; Clerk of the Legislature; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (6) of this section, following each regular session of the Legislature, the Revisor of Statutes shall compile an updated copy of the Constitution of Nebraska, showing all sections as they exist at that time and including notes after the end of each section as follows:</para><para>(a) For each section, the Revisor of Statutes shall provide a note referencing the source of such section and any amendments thereto;</para><para>(b) If a section is declared unconstitutional or inoperative, in whole or in part, by the final judgment of a federal court or the Nebraska Supreme Court, the Revisor of Statutes shall provide a note to that effect. The Attorney General shall assist the Revisor of Statutes in complying with this subdivision by promptly notifying the Revisor of Statutes when any section is declared unconstitutional or inoperative; and</para><para>(c) For any section, the Revisor of Statutes may provide additional notes at his or her discretion.</para><para>(2) The Revisor of Statutes shall, within two days after the Legislature has adjourned sine die, transmit the updated copy of the Constitution of Nebraska as compiled under subsection (1) of this section to the Secretary of State for his or her review to determine whether the updated copy accurately reflects the text of the Constitution of Nebraska as it exists at that time. If the Secretary of State determines that any changes are necessary, he or she shall, within five days after receipt of the updated copy, notify the Revisor of Statutes of the changes. The Revisor of Statutes shall make such changes and then promptly return the updated copy to the Secretary of State for further review. If the Secretary of State determines that no changes are necessary or that all necessary changes have been made by the Revisor of Statutes, the Secretary of State shall certify the updated copy as an accurate reflection of the text of the Constitution of Nebraska as it exists at that time. The Secretary of State shall then transmit the certified copy to the Clerk of the Legislature for distribution no later than ten days after the Legislature has adjourned sine die.</para><para>(3) After receiving the certified copy of the Constitution of Nebraska from the Secretary of State pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the Clerk of the Legislature shall:</para><para>(a) Make the certified copy available in electronic form on the Legislature’s website;</para><para>(b) Include the certified copy in the session laws compiled and published pursuant to section 49-501.01; and</para><para>(c) Print pamphlets of the certified copy for distribution to the public upon request.</para><para>(4) The certified copies printed by the Clerk of the Legislature pursuant to subdivisions (3)(b) and (3)(c) of this section shall constitute the official version of the Constitution of Nebraska and may be cited as prima facie evidence of the law in all courts of this state.</para><para>(5) The Secretary of State shall maintain in his or her office a copy of every edition of the Constitution of Nebraska certified pursuant to this section.</para><para>(6) Following any regular session of the Legislature, if the Revisor of Statutes determines that there have been no changes to the text of the Constitution of Nebraska and no changes to the notes required by subsection (1) of this section, the Revisor of Statutes may decide not to compile an updated copy of the Constitution of Nebraska for that year. If the Revisor of Statutes decides not to compile an updated copy for the year, he or she shall notify the Secretary of State and the Clerk of the Legislature of such fact and the Clerk of the Legislature shall continue to use the most recent year’s certified copy for purposes of subsection (3) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB686, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>