<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id00" statutenumber="49-1494"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1494</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Candidates for elective office; statement of financial interest; filing; time.</catchline><para>(1) An individual who files to appear on the ballot for election to an elective office specified in section 49-1493 shall file a statement of financial interests for the preceding calendar year with the commission as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) Candidates for the elective offices specified in section 49-1493 who qualify other than by filing shall file a statement for the preceding calendar year with the commission within five days after becoming a candidate or being appointed to that elective office.</para><para>(3) If the candidate for an elective office specified in section 49-1493 files to appear on the ballot for election during the calendar year in which the election is held, the candidate shall file a statement of financial interests for the preceding calendar year with the commission on or before March 1 of the year in which the election is held or, if the filing deadline for the elective office is after March 1 of the year in which the election is held, the candidate shall file such statement on or before the filing deadline for the elective office.</para><para>(4) A candidate for an elective office specified in section 49-1493 who fails to file a statement of financial interests as required in subsection (1) or (2) of this section within five days after the deadline in subsection (3) of this section and section 49-1493 shall not appear on the ballot.</para><para>(5) A statement of financial interests shall be preserved for a period of not less than five years by the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 479, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB400, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB451, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB843, &#167; 54. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>