<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1560"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1560</statuteno><catchline>Effectuation and operation of revocation form; general principles.</catchline><para>The following general principles shall in part govern the effectuation and operation of a statutory short form revocation of power of attorney:</para><para>(1) Any competent individual who has effectuated a statutory short form power of attorney or any similar or other document creating and establishing a revocable agency relationship shall be entitled at any time to revoke such power of attorney or such document, to terminate such agency relationship, and to effectuate a statutory short form revocation of power of attorney. The conservator of any principal who has effectuated any such statutory short form or document shall be entitled at any time on behalf of such principal while incompetent to revoke such statutory short form or document, to terminate such agency relationship, and to effectuate a statutory short form revocation of power of attorney on behalf of and for such principal;</para><para>(2) The principal or the conservator of any principal under a statutory short form revocation of power of attorney shall be entitled to modify the content and substance thereof by inclusion of any other appropriate, convenient, or necessary provision or provisions or by use of any other clear and explicit addition or additions;</para><para>(3) No effectuated revocation of power of attorney revoking a statutory short form power of attorney or any similar or other document creating and establishing a revocable agency relationship which has superseded and revoked a previous similar relationship shall be effective or operative to reinstate or revive any such document or any such superseded and revoked relationship. No effectuated revocation of power of attorney shall be subject to revocation so as to reinstate or revive any superseded and revoked power of attorney; and</para><para>(4) When the principal or the conservator of any principal has effectuated a statutory short form revocation of power of attorney revoking a statutory short form power of attorney or any similar or other document creating and establishing a revocable agency relationship which has been filed in or with any public office or otherwise made a matter of public record, the principal or such conservator shall so far as practicable similarly file or make such revocation of power of attorney a matter of public record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 475, &#167; 60. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 