<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id16">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id18" statutenumber="49-14,101.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id20">49-14,101.01</statuteno><catchline id="id21">Financial
gain; gift of travel or lodging; prohibited acts; violation; penalty; permissible activities and uses.</catchline>
<para>(1) A public official or public employee shall not use or
authorize the use of his or her public office or any confidential information
received through the holding of a public office to obtain financial gain,
other than compensation provided by law, for himself or herself, a member
of his or her immediate family, or a business with which the individual is
associated.</para>
<para>(2) A public official or public employee shall not use or
authorize the use of personnel, resources, property, or funds under his or
her official care and control other than in accordance with prescribed constitutional,
statutory, and regulatory procedures or use such items, other than compensation
provided by law, for personal financial gain.</para>
<para>(3) Unless
otherwise restricted by an employment contract, a collective-bargaining agreement,
or a written agreement or policy approved by a government body, a public official
or public employee may use a telecommunication system, a cellular telephone,
an electronic handheld device, or a computer under the control of a government
body for email, text messaging, a local call, or a long-distance call to a
child at home, a teacher, a doctor, a day care center, a baby-sitter, a family
member, or any other person to inform any such person of an unexpected schedule
change or for other essential personal business. Any such communication shall
be kept to a minimum and shall not interfere with the conduct of public business.
A public official or public employee shall be responsible for payment or reimbursement
of charges, if any, that directly result from any such communication. An agency
or government body may establish procedures for reimbursement of charges pursuant
to this subsection.</para><para>(4) A
public official shall not accept a gift of travel or lodging or a gift of
reimbursement for travel or lodging if the gift is made so that a member of
the public official's immediate family can accompany the public official in
the performance of his or her official duties.</para>
<para>(5) A member of the immediate
family of a public official shall not accept a gift of travel or lodging or
a gift of reimbursement for travel or lodging if the gift is made so that
a member of the public official's immediate family can accompany the public
official in the performance of his or her official duties.</para>
<para>(6) This section does not
prohibit the Executive Board of the Legislative Council from adopting policies
that allow a member of the Legislature to install and use with private funds
a telephone line, telephone, and telefax machine in his or her public office
for private purposes.</para>
<para>(7) Except as provided in
section 23-3113, any person violating this section shall be guilty of a Class
III misdemeanor, except that no vote by any member of the Legislature shall
subject such member to any criminal sanction under this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1086, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB626, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>