<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1469.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1469.06</statuteno><catchline>Businesses and organizations; separate segregated political fund; contributions and expenditures; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) All contributions to and expenditures from a separate segregated political fund shall be limited to money or anything of ascertainable value obtained through the voluntary contributions of the employees, officers, directors, stockholders, or members of the corporation, including a nonprofit corporation, labor organization, or industry, trade, or professional association, and the affiliates thereof, under which such fund was established.</para><para>(2) No contribution or expenditure shall be received or made from such fund if obtained or made by using or threatening to use job discrimination or financial reprisals.</para><para>(3) Only expenditures to candidates and committees and independent expenditures may be made from a fund established by a corporation, labor organization, or industry, trade, or professional organization. Such separate segregated political fund may receive and disburse funds for the purpose of supporting or opposing candidates and committees in elections in states other than Nebraska and candidates for federal office and making independent expenditures in such elections if such receipts and disbursements are made in conformity with the solicitation provisions of this section and the corporation, labor organization, or industry, trade, or professional association which establishes and administers such fund complies with the laws of the jurisdiction in which such receipts or disbursements are made.</para><para>(4) The expenses for establishment and administration of a separate segregated political fund of a corporation, labor organization, or industry, trade, or professional association may be paid from the separate segregated political fund of such corporation, labor organization, or industry, trade, or professional association.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc>