<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id13" statutenumber="49-14,101.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-14,101.03</statuteno><catchline>Public official or public employee; incidental or de minimis use of public resources; permissible activities and uses.</catchline><para>(1) Any use of public resources by a public official or public employee which is incidental or de minimis shall not constitute a violation of section 49-14,101.01 or 49-14,101.02.</para><para>(2) For purposes of sections 49-14,101.01 and 49-14,101.02, a resource of government, including a vehicle, shall not be considered a public resource and personal use shall not be prohibited if (a) the use of the resource for personal purposes is part of the public official's or public employee's compensation provided in an employment contract or a written policy approved by a government body and (b) the personal use of the resource as compensation is reported in accordance with the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, and taxes, if any, are paid. If authorized by the contract or policy, the resource may be used whether or not the public official or public employee is engaged in the duties of his or her public office or public employment.</para><para>(3) Use of a government vehicle by a public official or public employee to travel to a designated location or the home of the public official or public employee is permissible when the primary purpose of the travel serves a government purpose and the use is pursuant to a written policy approved by a government body.</para><para>(4) Use of a government Internet network by a member of the Legislature for essential personal business is permissible when the member is serving in the member's official capacity and such use is pursuant to a written policy approved by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>(5) Pursuant to a collective-bargaining agreement, a public facility may be used by a bargaining unit to meet regarding activities of the union or bargaining unit. This section shall not authorize the use of public resources for the purpose of campaigning for or against the nomination or election of a candidate or the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question.</para><para>(6) Nothing in the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act prohibits a public official or public employee from using his or her personal cellular telephone, electronic handheld device, or computer to access a wireless network to which access is provided to the public by a government body.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB626, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB996, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>