<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1494"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1494</statuteno><catchline>Candidates for elective office; statement of financial interest; filing; time; where; effect; supplementary statements.</catchline><para>(1) An individual who files to appear on the ballot for election to an elective office specified in section 49-1493 shall:</para><para>(a) File a statement of financial interests for the preceding calendar year at the same time and with the same official with whom the individual files for office; and</para><para>(b) File a copy of the statement with the commission within five days after filing for office.</para><para>(2) Candidates for the elective offices specified in section 49-1493 who qualify other than by filing shall file a statement for the preceding calendar year with the commission within fifteen days after becoming a candidate or being appointed to that elective office.</para><para>(3) A filing to appear on the ballot shall not be accepted by a filing official unless a statement is properly filed.</para><para>(4) A statement of financial interests shall be preserved for a period of not less than five years by the commission and not less than eighteen months by the officials other than the commission with whom it is filed.</para><para>(5) This section does not apply to a person who has already filed a statement for the preceding calendar year.</para><para>(6) If the candidate for an elective office specified in section 49-1493 files to appear on the ballot for election prior to January 1 of the year in which the election is held, the candidate shall file supplementary statements with the appropriate filing officials on or before April 1 of the year in which the election is held covering the preceding calendar year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 479, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 36. </para></source></law></legaldoc>