<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1499"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1499</statuteno><catchline>Legislature; discharge of official duties; potential conflict; actions required.</catchline><para>(1) A member of the Legislature who would be required to take any action or make any decision in the discharge of his or her official duties that may cause financial benefit or detriment to him or her, a member of his or her immediate family, or a business with which he or she is associated, which is distinguishable from the effects of such action on the public generally or a broad segment of the public, shall take the following actions as soon as he or she is aware of such potential conflict or should reasonably be aware of such potential conflict, whichever is sooner:</para><para>(a) Prepare a written statement describing the matter requiring action or decision and the nature of the potential conflict, and if he or she will not abstain from voting, deliberating, or taking other action on the matter, the statement shall state why, despite the potential conflict, he or she intends to vote or otherwise participate; and</para><para>(b) Deliver a copy of the statement to the commission and to the Speaker of the Legislature who shall cause the statement to be filed with the Clerk of the Legislature to be held as a matter of public record.</para><para>(2) Nothing in this section shall prohibit any member of the Legislature from voting, deliberating, or taking other action on any matter that comes before the Legislature.</para><para>(3) The member of the Legislature may abstain from voting, deliberating, or taking other action on the matter on which the potential conflict exists. He or she may have the reasons for the abstention recorded in the Legislative Journal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 134, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 556, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 434, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 39. </para></source></law></legaldoc>