<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1480.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1480.01</statuteno><catchline>Application for registration; fee; collection; registration renewal.</catchline><para>(1) The Clerk of the Legislature shall collect a fee of two hundred dollars for an application for registration by a lobbyist for each principal if the lobbyist receives or will receive compensation for such lobbying. Except as provided by section 49-1434, a lobbyist who receives compensation shall include an individual who is an employee or member of a principal whose duties of employment, office, or membership include engaging in lobbying activities.</para><para>(2) A fee of fifteen dollars shall be collected for an application by a lobbyist for each principal if the lobbyist is not receiving and will not be receiving compensation for such lobbying. Any lobbyist who receives compensation who did not anticipate receiving such compensation at the time of application for registration shall, within five days of the receipt of any compensation, file an amended registration form which shall be accompanied by an additional fee of one hundred eighty-five dollars for such year.</para><para>(3) The registration of a lobbyist for each of his or her principals may be renewed by the payment of a fee as provided by subsections (1) and (2) of this section. Such fee shall be paid to the Clerk of the Legislature on or before December 31 of each calendar year. The registration of a lobbyist for each of his or her principals shall terminate as of the end of the calendar year for which the lobbyist registered unless the registration is renewed as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 872, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1243, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 30. </para></source></law></legaldoc>