<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Law"  statutenumber="49-1499.07"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1499.07</statuteno><catchline>Executive branch; nepotism prohibited;
restrictions on supervisors; legislative intent for legislative branch and
judicial branch.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Family member means
an individual who is the spouse, child, parent, brother, sister, grandchild,
or grandparent, by blood, marriage, or adoption, of an official or employee
in the executive branch of state government;</para><para>(b) Nepotism means the act of hiring,
promoting, or advancing a family member in state government or recommending
the hiring, promotion, or advancement of a family member in state government,
including initial appointment and transfer to other positions in state government;
and</para><para>(c)
Supervisor means an individual having authority, in the interest of the state,
to hire, transfer, suspend, lay off, recall, promote, discharge, assign, reward,
or discipline employees, responsibility to direct them or to adjust their
grievances, or effectively to recommend any such action, if the exercise of
such authority is not merely of a routine or clerical nature but requires
the use of independent judgment.</para><para>(2) Except as authorized in subsection (5) of this
section, an official or employee in the executive branch of state government
shall not engage in nepotism.</para><para>(3) Except as authorized in subsection (5) of this
section, an official or employee in the executive branch of state government
shall not act as a supervisor to his or her family member.</para>
<para>(4) In addition to the
other penalties authorized under the Nebraska Political Accountability and
Disclosure Act, any person violating this section may be subject to disciplinary
action.</para><para>(5)(a)
The head of an agency may, upon a written showing of good cause, grant an
exception to subsection (2) or (3) of this section. The written showing of
good cause shall be filed with the commission and shall be considered a public
record.</para><para>(b)
An official or employee in the executive branch of state government who becomes
a supervisor to his or her family member other than by means of nepotism shall
notify the head of the agency within seven days of becoming aware of such
situation and may continue to act as a supervisor until the head of the agency
remedies the situation. The head of the agency shall act as soon as practicable.</para>
<para>(6) It is the intent
of the Legislature that the legislative branch and the judicial branch of
state government develop and implement internal policies prohibiting nepotism
and the supervision of a family member.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB322, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>