<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1434" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1434</statuteno><catchline>Principal, lobbyist, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Principal means a person who authorizes a lobbyist to lobby in behalf of that principal.</para><para>(2) Lobbyist means a person who is authorized to lobby on behalf of a principal and includes an officer, agent, attorney, or employee of the principal whose regular duties include lobbying.</para><para>(3) Principal or lobbyist does not include:</para><para>(a) A public official or employee of a branch of state government, except the University of Nebraska, or an elected official of a political subdivision who is acting in the course or scope of his or her office or employment;</para><para>(b) Any publisher, owner, or working member of the press, radio, or television while disseminating news or editorial comment to the general public in the ordinary course of business;</para><para>(c) An employee of a principal or lobbyist whose duties are confined to typing, filing, and other types of clerical office work;</para><para>(d) Any person who limits his or her activities (i) to appearances before legislative committees and who so advises the committee at the time of his or her appearance whom he or she represents or that he or she appears at the invitation of a named member of the Legislature or at the direction of the Governor or (ii) to writing letters or furnishing written material to individual members of the Legislature or to the committees thereof; </para><para>(e) Any individual who does not engage in lobbying for another person as defined in section 49-1438; or</para><para>(f) An employee of a political subdivision whose regular employment duties do not ordinarily include lobbying activities as long as such employee is not additionally compensated for such lobbying activities, other than his or her regular salary, and is not reimbursed for any lobbying expenditures except his or her travel, lodging, and meal expenses and the meal expenses for members of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 162, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 232, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 940, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>