
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id29">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id31" statutenumber="49-14,101.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id33">49-14,101.02</statuteno><catchline id="id34">Public official
or public employee; use of public resources or funds; prohibited acts; exceptions.</catchline>
<para>(1) For purposes of this section, public resources means personnel,
property, resources, or funds under the official care and control of a public
official or public employee.</para>
<para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this section, a public
official or public employee shall not use or authorize the use of public resources
for the purpose of campaigning for or against the nomination or election of
a candidate or the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question.</para>
<para>(3) This section does not prohibit a public official or public
employee from making government facilities available to a person for campaign
purposes if the identity of the candidate or the support for or opposition
to the ballot question is not a factor in making the government facility available
or a factor in determining the cost or conditions of use.</para>
<para>(4) This section does not prohibit a governing body from discussing
and voting upon a resolution supporting or opposing a ballot question or a
public corporation organized under Chapter 70 from otherwise supporting or
opposing a ballot question concerning the sale or purchase of its assets.</para>
<para>(5) This section does not prohibit a public official or a public employee under the direct
supervision of a public official from responding to specific inquiries
by the press or the public as to his or her opinion regarding a ballot question
or from providing information in response to a request for information.</para>
<para>(6) This section does not prohibit a member of the Legislature
from making use of public resources in expressing his or her opinion regarding
a candidate or a ballot question or from communicating that opinion. A member
is not authorized by this section to utilize mass mailings or other mass communications
at public expense for the purpose of campaigning for or against the nomination
or election of a candidate. A member is not authorized by this section to
utilize mass mailings at public expense for the purpose of qualifying, supporting,
or opposing a ballot question.</para>
<para>(7) This subsection
applies to public officials other than members of the Legislature provided
for in subsection (6) of this section. This section does not prohibit, in
the normal course of his or her duties, a public official or a public employee
under the direct supervision of a public official from using public resources
to research and prepare materials to assist the government body for which
the individual is a public official or public employee in determining the
effect of the ballot question on the government body. This section does not
authorize mass mailings, mass duplication, or other mass communications at
public expense for the purpose of qualifying, supporting, or opposing a ballot
question. Mass communications shall not include placing public records demonstrating
the consequences of the passage or defeat of a ballot question affecting the
government body for which the individual is a public official or public employee
on existing websites of such government body.</para><para>(8) Nothing in this section prohibits a public
official from campaigning for or against the qualification, passage, or defeat
of a ballot question or the nomination or election of a candidate when no
public resources are used.</para>
<para>(9) Nothing in this section
prohibits a public employee from campaigning for or against the qualification,
passage, or defeat of a ballot question or the nomination or election of a
candidate when no public resources are used. Except as otherwise provided
in this section, a public employee shall not engage in campaign activity for
or against the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question or the
nomination or election of a candidate while on government work time or when
otherwise engaged in his or her official duties.</para>
<para>(10) This section does not
prohibit an employee of the Legislature from using public resources consistent
with this section for the purpose of researching or campaigning for or against
the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question if the employee
is under the direction and supervision of a member of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(11) Nothing
in this section prohibits a public official or public employee from identifying
himself or herself by his or her official title.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB626, &#167; 5.</para></source><annotation><para>
In order to determine whether there has been a violation of subsection (2) of this section, a court must consider the intent behind the expenditure of public resources. Nebraska Account. &amp; Disclosure Comm. v. Skinner, 288 Neb. 804, 853 N.W.2d 1 (2014).</para><para>Public resources are used "for the purpose of campaigning" when their use is intended to influence public support for or against a particular political candidate, ticket, or measure. Nebraska Account. &amp; Disclosure Comm. v. Skinner, 288 Neb. 804, 853 N.W.2d 1 (2014).</para><para>The language of subsection (2) of this section does not make a distinction between express advocacy and issue advocacy. Nebraska Account. &amp; Disclosure Comm. v. Skinner, 288 Neb. 804, 853 N.W.2d 1 (2014).</para><para>The filming of a city council member in his city office for the purpose of creating a video advertisement for his reelection campaign was not a "use" of resources in violation of this section. Vokal v. Nebraska Acct. &amp; Disclosure Comm., 276 Neb. 988, 759 N.W.2d 75 (2009).</para><para>
This section is penal in nature and must be strictly construed in the context of the object sought to be accomplished, the evils and mischiefs sought to be remedied, and the purpose sought to be served. Vokal v. Nebraska Acct. &amp; Disclosure Comm., 276 Neb. 988, 759 N.W.2d 75 (2009).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
