<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1419"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1419</statuteno><catchline>Expenditure, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Expenditure shall mean a payment, donation, loan, pledge, or promise of payment of money or anything of ascertainable monetary value for goods, materials, services, or facilities in assistance of, or in opposition to, the nomination or election of a candidate or the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question. An offer or tender of an expenditure is not an expenditure if expressly and unconditionally rejected or returned.</para><para>(2) Expenditure shall include a contribution or a transfer of anything of ascertainable monetary value for purposes of influencing the nomination or election of any candidate or the qualification, passage, or defeat of a ballot question.</para><para>(3) Expenditure shall not include:</para><para>(a) An amount paid pursuant to a pledge or promise to the extent the amount was previously reported as an expenditure;</para><para>(b) An expenditure for communication by a person strictly with the person's paid members or shareholders;</para><para>(c) An expenditure for communication on a subject or issue if the communication does not support or oppose a ballot question or candidate by name or clear inference;</para><para>(d) An expenditure by a broadcasting station, newspaper, magazine, or other periodical or publication for any news story, commentary, or editorial in support of or opposition to a candidate for elective office or a ballot question in the regular course of publication or broadcasting; or</para><para>(e) An expenditure for nonpartisan voter registration activities. This subdivision shall not apply if a candidate or a group of candidates sponsors, finances, or is identified by name with the activity. This subdivision shall apply to an activity performed pursuant to the Election Act by an election commissioner or other registration official who is identified by name with the activity.</para><para>(4) Expenditure for purposes of sections 49-1480 to 49-1492.01 shall mean an advance, conveyance, deposit, distribution, transfer of funds, loan, payment, pledge, or subscription of money or anything of value and any contract, agreement, promise, or other obligation, whether or not legally enforceable, to make an expenditure. Expenditure shall not include payments for transportation by lobbyists or the cost of communicating positions from a principal to a lobbyist or from a lobbyist to a principal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 162, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 567; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 49, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>