
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id385" statutenumber="49-14,140"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-14,140</statuteno><catchline id="id388">Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission Cash Fund is hereby created. The fund shall consist of funds received by the commission pursuant to sections 49-1449.01, 49-1470, 49-1480.01, 49-1482, 49-14,123, and 49-14,123.01 and subdivision (4) of section 49-14,126. The fund shall be used by the commission in administering the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act. Any money in the Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para><para>On April 25, 2013, the State Treasurer shall transfer $630,870 from the Campaign Finance Limitation Cash Fund to the Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission Cash Fund to be used for development, implementation, and maintenance of an electronic filing system for campaign statements and other reports under the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act and for making such statements and reports available to the public on the website of the commission. The State Treasurer shall transfer the balance of the Campaign Finance Limitation Cash Fund to the Election Administration Fund on or before July 5, 2013, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 815, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 872, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1243, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB527, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB176, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>