<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id142">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id144" statutenumber="49-1459"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1459</statuteno><catchline id="id147">Campaign statements;
filing schedule; statement of exemption.</catchline><para>(1) Except
as provided in subsection (2) of this section, campaign statements as required
by the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act shall be filed
according to the following schedule:</para>
<para>(a) A first preelection campaign statement shall be filed
not later than the thirtieth day before the election. The closing date for
a campaign statement filed under this subdivision shall be the thirty-fifth
day before the election;</para>
<para>(b) A second preelection campaign statement shall be filed
not later than the tenth day before the election. The closing date for a campaign
statement filed under this subdivision shall be the fifteenth day before the
election; and</para>
<para>(c) A postelection campaign statement shall be filed not
later than the fortieth day following the primary election and the seventieth
day following the general election. The closing date for a postelection campaign statement to be filed under this subdivision after the primary election shall
be the thirty-fifth day following the election. The closing date for a postelection campaign statement to be filed under this subdivision after the general election shall
be December 31 of the year in which the election is held. If all liabilities
of a candidate and committee are paid before the closing date and additional
contributions are not expected, the campaign statement may be filed at any
time after the election, but not later than the dates provided under this
subdivision.</para>
<para>(2) Any committee may file a statement with the commission indicating that
the committee does not expect to receive contributions or make expenditures
of more than one thousand dollars in the calendar year of an election. Such statement shall be
signed by the committee treasurer or the assistant treasurer, and in the case
of a candidate committee, it shall also be signed by the candidate. Such statement shall be
filed on or before the thirtieth day before the election. A committee which
files a statement
pursuant to this subsection is not required to file campaign statements according
to the schedule prescribed in subsection (1) of this section but shall file
a sworn statement of exemption not later than the fortieth day following the
primary election and the seventieth day following the general election stating
only that the committee did not, in fact, receive or expend an amount in excess
of one thousand dollars. If the committee receives contributions or makes
expenditures of more than one thousand dollars during the election year, the
committee is then subject to all campaign filing requirements under subsection
(1) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 535, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 587, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 632, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>The Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act requires candidate committees to file two preelection campaign statements and one postelection campaign statement for both the primary and general elections. Nebraska Legislature on behalf of State v. Hergert, 271 Neb. 976, 720 N.W.2d 372 (2006).
</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>