<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id17" statutenumber="49-1413"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1413</statuteno><catchline id="id20">Committee, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Committee shall mean (a) any combination of two or more
individuals which receives contributions or makes expenditures of five thousand dollars or more in a calendar year
for the purpose of influencing or attempting to influence the action of the
voters for or against the nomination or election of one or more candidates
or the qualification, passage, or defeat of one or more ballot questions or
(b) a person whose primary purpose is to receive contributions or make expenditures
and who receives or makes contributions or expenditures of five thousand dollars or more in a calendar year for the purpose of
influencing or attempting to influence the action of the voters for or against
the nomination or election of one or more candidates or the qualification,
passage, or defeat of one or more ballot questions, except that an individual,
other than a candidate, shall not constitute a committee.</para>
<para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in section 49-1445, a committee
shall be considered formed and subject to the Nebraska Political Accountability
and Disclosure Act upon raising, receiving, or spending five thousand dollars in a calendar
year as prescribed in this section.</para>
<para>(3) A corporation, labor organization, industry, trade, or professional association, limited liability company, or limited
liability partnership is not a committee if it makes expenditures
or provides personal services pursuant to sections 49-1469 to 49-1469.08.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 535, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 230, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 480, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 2.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>