<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id55">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id57" statutenumber="49-1446"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1446</statuteno><catchline id="id60">Committee; treasurer;
depository account; contributions and expenditures; requirements; reports;
commingling funds; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Each
committee shall have a treasurer who is a qualified elector of this state.
A candidate may appoint himself or herself as the candidate committee treasurer.</para>
<para>(2) Each committee shall designate
one account in a financial institution in this state as an official depository
for the purpose of depositing all contributions which it receives in the form
of or which are converted to money, checks, or other negotiable instruments
and for the purpose of making all expenditures. Secondary depositories shall
be used for the sole purpose of depositing contributions and promptly transferring
the deposits to the committee's official depository.</para>
<para>(3) No contribution shall be accepted and no expenditure shall
be made by a committee which has not filed a statement of organization and
which does not have a treasurer. When the office of treasurer in a candidate
committee is vacant, the candidate shall be the treasurer until the candidate
appoints a new treasurer.</para>
<para>(4) No expenditure shall be made by a committee without the
authorization of the treasurer or the assistant treasurer. The contributions
received or expenditures made by a candidate or an agent of a candidate shall
be considered received or made by the candidate committee.</para>
<para>(5) Contributions received by an individual acting in behalf
of a committee shall be reported promptly to the committee's treasurer not
later than five days before the closing date of any campaign statement required
to be filed by the committee and shall be reported to the committee treasurer
immediately if the contribution is received less than five days before the
closing date.</para>
<para>(6) A contribution shall be considered received by a committee
when it is received by the committee treasurer or a designated agent of the
committee treasurer notwithstanding the fact that the contribution is not
deposited in the official depository by the reporting deadline.</para>
<para>(7) Contributions received by a committee shall not be commingled
with any funds of an agent of the committee or of any other person except
for funds received or disbursed by a separate segregated political fund for
the purpose of supporting or opposing candidates and committees in elections
in states other than Nebraska and candidates for federal office, as provided
in section 49-1469.06, including independent expenditures made in such elections.</para>
<para>(8) Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of
a Class IV misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 535, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1136, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 587, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>