<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id212">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id214" statutenumber="49-1455"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1455</statuteno><catchline id="id217">Committee campaign
statement; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The campaign statement
of a committee, other than a political party committee, shall contain the
following information:</para>
<para>(a) The filing committee's name, address, and telephone number
and the full name, residential and business addresses, and telephone numbers
of its committee treasurer;</para>
<para>(b) Under the heading RECEIPTS, the total amount of contributions
received during the period covered by the campaign statement; under the heading
EXPENDITURES, the total amount of expenditures made during the period covered
by the campaign statement; and the cumulative amount of those totals for the
election period. If a loan was repaid during the period covered by the campaign
statement, the amount of the repayment shall be subtracted from the total
amount of contributions received. Forgiveness of a loan shall not be included
in the totals. Payment of a loan by a third party shall be recorded and reported
as a contribution by the third party but shall not be included in the totals.
In-kind contributions or expenditures shall be listed at fair market value
and shall be reported as both contributions and expenditures;</para>
<para>(c) The balance of cash and cash equivalents on hand at the
beginning and the end of the period covered by the campaign statement;</para>
<para>(d) The full name of each individual from whom contributions
totaling more than two
hundred fifty dollars are
received during the period covered by the report, together with the individual's
street address, the amount contributed, the date on which each contribution
was received, and the cumulative amount contributed by that individual for
the election period;</para>
<para>(e) The full name of each person, except those individuals
reported under subdivision (1)(d) of this section, which contributed a total
of more than two
hundred fifty dollars during
the period covered by the report together with the person's street address,
the amount contributed, the date on which each contribution was received,
and the cumulative amount contributed by the person for the election period;</para>
<para>(f) The name of each committee which is listed as a contributor
shall include the full name of the committee's treasurer;</para>
<para>(g) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this
section: The full name and street address of each person to whom expenditures
totaling more than two
hundred fifty dollars were
made, together with the date and amount of each separate expenditure to each
such person during the period covered by the campaign statement; the purpose
of the expenditure; and the full name and street address of the person providing
the consideration for which any expenditure was made if different from the
payee;</para>
<para>(h) The amount and the date of expenditures for or against
a candidate or ballot question during the period covered by the campaign statement
and the cumulative amount of expenditures for or against that candidate or
ballot question for the election period. An expenditure made in support of
more than one candidate or ballot question, or both, shall be apportioned
reasonably among the candidates or ballot questions, or both; and</para>
<para>(i) The total amount of funds disbursed by a separate segregated
political fund, by state, for the purpose of supporting or opposing candidates
and committees in elections in states other than Nebraska and candidates for
federal office, including independent expenditures made in such elections.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section, election period means the
calendar year of the election.</para>
<para>(3) A campaign statement shall include the total amount paid
to individual petition circulators during the reporting period, if any, but
shall not include the name, address, or telephone number of any individual
petition circulator if the only payment made to such individual was for services
as a petition circulator.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1976, LB 987, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1136, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 587, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 420, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB39, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 25.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>