<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-14,101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-14,101</statuteno><catchline>Public official, employee, candidate, and other individuals; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall offer or give to the following persons anything of value, including a gift, loan, contribution, reward, or promise of future employment, based on an agreement that the vote, official action, or judgment of any public official, public employee, or candidate would be influenced thereby:</para><para>(a) A public official, public employee, or candidate;</para><para>(b) A member of the immediate family of an individual listed in subdivision (a) of this subsection; or</para><para>(c) A business with which an individual listed under subdivision (a) or (b) of this subsection is associated.</para><para>(2) No person listed in subsection (1) of this section shall solicit or accept anything of value, including a gift, loan, contribution, reward, or promise of future employment based on an agreement that the vote, official action, or judgment of the public official, public employee, or candidate would be influenced thereby.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in section 23-3113, any person violating this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor, except that no vote by any member of the Legislature shall subject such member to any criminal sanction under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 370, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 548, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1243, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 18. </para></source><annotation><para>This section has not been impliedly repealed by section 28-917. State v. Null, 247 Neb. 192, 526 N.W.2d 220 (1995).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 