<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id200">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id202" statutenumber="49-1445"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1445</statuteno><catchline id="id205">Candidate for
office; candidate committee; slate or team; committee; when formed; violation;
penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A candidate shall form a candidate
committee upon raising, receiving, or expending more than five thousand dollars in a calendar year.</para>
<para>(2) A candidate committee may consist of one member with
the candidate being the member.</para>
<para>(3) A person who is a candidate for more than one office
shall form a candidate committee for an office upon raising, receiving, or
expending more than five
thousand dollars in
a calendar year for that office.</para>
<para>(4) Two or more candidates who campaign as a slate or team
for public office shall form a committee upon raising, receiving, or expending
jointly in any combination more
than five thousand dollars in a calendar year.</para>
<para>(5) The fee to file for office shall not be included in determining
if a candidate has raised, received, or expended more than five thousand dollars in a calendar year.</para>
<para>(6) Any person who violates this section shall be guilty
of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 987, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 535, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 230, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 480, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 601, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 416, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB79, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 24.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2015</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Generally, the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act requires candidates for elective state office to form candidate committees and file campaign statements with the Nebraska Accountability and Disclosure Commission once the candidate has raised, received, or expended $5,000 in a calendar year. Nebraska Legislature on behalf of State v. Hergert, 271 Neb. 976, 720 N.W.2d 372 (2006).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>