<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<?APT Element gi="legaldoc"?>
<?APT Element gi="law" attrs="type"?>
<?APT Element gi="section" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="sectno" attrs="id opdate"?>
<?APT Element gi="amendatorysection" attrs="amended chaptername id statutenumber"?>
<?APT Element gi="bookinfo"?>
<?APT Element gi="statuteno" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="catchline" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="para"?>
<?APT Element gi="source"?>
<?APT Element gi="operativedate"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id4"><sectno id="id5" opdate="January 1, 2009">Section
1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Law" id="id6" statutenumber="49-1474.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">49-1474.02</statuteno><catchline
id="id9">Dissemination of message by telecommunication or electronic means;
requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who makes an expenditure reportable
under the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act to disseminate
by any means of telecommunication a prerecorded message or a recorded message
relating to a candidate or ballot question shall include, immediately preceding
the message, the name of the person making the expenditure. Such messages
shall be disseminated only between the hours of 8 a.m. and 9 p.m. at the location
of the person receiving the messages.</para><para>(2) Any person who makes
an expenditure reportable under the act to disseminate by any means of telecommunication
a message relating to a candidate or ballot question which is not a recorded
message or a prerecorded message shall, immediately upon the request of the
recipient of the message, disclose the name of the person making the expenditure.
If the message is disseminated through an employee or agent of the person
making the expenditure, the employee or agent shall, immediately upon the
request of the recipient of the message, disclose the name of the person making
the expenditure.</para><para>(3) Any person who makes an expenditure reportable
under the act to disseminate by any electronic means, including the Internet
or email, a message relating to a candidate or ballot question shall include
in the message the name of the person making the expenditure.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 49-1446.06; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB720, &#167; 1.</para></source> </law></legaldoc>
