<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Law" statutenumber="49-1499.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>49-1499.04</statuteno><catchline>Political subdivision; employment of family member; when; exception.</catchline><para>(1) An official or employee of a political subdivision may employ or recommend or supervise the employment of an immediate family member if (a) he or she does not abuse his or her official position as described in section 49-1499.05, (b) he or she makes a full disclosure on the record to the governing body of the political subdivision and a written disclosure to the person in charge of keeping records for the governing body, and (c) the governing body of the political subdivision approves the employment or supervisory position.</para><para>(2) No official or employee shall employ an immediate family member (a) without first having made a reasonable solicitation and consideration of applications for such employment, (b) who is not qualified for and able to perform the duties of the position, (c) for any unreasonably high salary, or (d) who is not required to perform the duties of the position.</para><para>(3) No official or employee of a political subdivision shall terminate the employment of another employee so as to make funds or a position available for the purpose of hiring an immediate family member.</para><para>(4) This section does not apply to an immediate family member of an official or employee who (a) was previously employed in a position subject to this section prior to the election or appointment of the official or employee or (b) was employed in a position subject to provisions similar to this section prior to September 1, 2001.</para><para>(5) Prior to, upon, or as soon as reasonably possible after the official date of taking office, a newly elected or appointed official or employee shall make a full disclosure of any immediate family member employed in a position subject to subdivision (4)(a) or (b) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 242, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 242, &#167; 43. </para></source></law></legaldoc>