<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-541"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-541</statuteno><catchline>Board; officers; powers; seal; rules and regulations; conduct of business.</catchline><para>The board shall organize by election of a chairperson and vice-chairperson. The board shall have the power to compel the attendance of witnesses, and the chairperson and vice-chairperson shall have the power to administer oaths. The board shall employ a director who shall keep a record of all proceedings, transactions, communications, and official acts of the board, be custodian of all records, and perform such other duties as the board may require.</para><para>The board shall adopt a seal, which may be either an engraved or ink stamp seal with the words Abstracters Board of Examiners, State of Nebraska, and such other device as the board may desire included, by which it shall authenticate the acts of the board. Copies of all records and papers in the office of the board, certified by the signature of the director and the seal of the board, shall be received in evidence in all cases equally and with like effect as the originals.</para><para>The board may adopt and promulgate such rules and regulations as it shall deem necessary for the proper administration of its powers and duties and the carrying out of the Abstracters Act. Such rules and regulations may provide that, except for hearings on the revocation of certificates issued by the board, the business of the board may be conducted while in session as a body or by correspondence. Such correspondence shall be directed to the director to be incorporated into the records of the board.</para><para>The action of the majority of the members of the board shall be deemed the action of the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 4, p. 1438; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 653, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-512; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 11.</para></source><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>