<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2,112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2,112</statuteno><catchline>Easement; creation; approval by governing body; when required.</catchline><para>(1) A conservation or preservation easement shall be an interest in real property, created by an instrument in which the purpose for the easement is clearly stated. The instrument shall be filed, duly recorded, and indexed in the office of the register of deeds of the county in which the real property subject to the conservation or preservation easement is located.</para><para>(2) No conveyance of a conservation or preservation easement shall be effective until accepted by the holder.</para><para>(3) In order to minimize conflicts with land-use planning, each conservation or preservation easement shall be approved by the appropriate governing body. Such approving body shall first refer the proposed acquisition to and receive comments from the local planning commission with jurisdiction over such property, which shall within sixty days of the referral provide such comments regarding the conformity of the proposed acquisition to comprehensive planning for the area. If such comments are not received within sixty days, the proposed acquisition shall be deemed approved by the local planning commission. If the property is located partially or entirely within the boundaries or zoning jurisdiction of a city or village, approval of the governing body of such city or village shall be required. If such property is located entirely outside the boundaries and zoning jurisdiction of any city or village, approval of the county board shall be required. If the property is located in the Niobrara scenic river corridor as defined in section 72-2006 and is not incorporated within the boundaries of a city or village, the Niobrara Council approval rather than city, village, or county approval shall be required. Approval of a proposed acquisition may be denied upon a finding by the appropriate governing body that the acquisition is not in the public interest when the easement is inconsistent with (a) a comprehensive plan for the area which had been officially adopted and was in force at the time of the conveyance, (b) any national, state, regional, or local program furthering conservation or preservation, or (c) any known proposal by a governmental body for use of the land.</para><para>(4) Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (3) of this section, the state, or any state agency or political subdivision other than a city, village, or county, may accept an easement after first referring the proposed acquisition to and receiving comments from the local planning commission with jurisdiction over the property, which shall within sixty days of the referral provide such comments regarding the conformity of the proposed acquisition to comprehensive planning for the area. If such comments are not received within sixty days, the proposed acquisition shall be deemed approved by the local planning commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 173, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1234, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>