<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id103">
<sectno id="id104">Sec. 9.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id105" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-710.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id107">76-710.04</statuteno><catchline id="id108">Economic
development purpose; restriction on use of eminent domain.</catchline><para>(1) A condemner may not take property through the use of eminent
domain under sections 76-704 to 76-724 if the taking is primarily for an economic
development purpose.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section, economic development purpose
means taking property for subsequent use by a commercial for-profit enterprise
or to increase tax revenue, tax base, employment, or general economic conditions.</para>
<para>(3) This section does not affect the use of eminent domain
for:</para>
<para>(a) Public projects or private projects that make all or
a major portion of the property available for use by the general public or
for use as a right-of-way, aqueduct, pipeline, transmission line, or similar use;</para>
<para>(b) Removing harmful uses of property if such uses constitute
an immediate threat to public health and safety;</para>
<para>(c) Leasing property to a private person who occupies an
incidental part of public property or a public facility, such as a retail
establishment on the ground floor of a public building;</para>
<para>(d) Acquiring abandoned property;</para>
<para>(e) Clearing defective property title;</para>
<para>(f) Taking private property for use by a utility or railroad;</para>
<para>(g) Taking private property based upon a finding of blighted
or substandard conditions under the Community Development Law if the private
property is not agricultural land or horticultural land as defined in section
77-1359; and</para>
<para>(h) Taking
private property for a transmission line to serve a privately developed facility
generating electricity using wind, solar, biomass, or landfill gas. Nothing
in this subdivision shall be construed to grant the power of eminent domain
to a private entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 924, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 9.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community Development Law,</emphasis> see section 18-2101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>