<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2,122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2,122</statuteno><catchline>Real estate closing agents; requirements; exemptions; enforcement; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) To act as a real estate closing agent, a person shall be (a) licensed or regulated by one or more regulating entities or (b) employed by a person or entity regulated by one or more regulating entities, unless employing such person to act as a real estate closing agent is otherwise prohibited by statute, rule, or regulation.</para><para>(2) A person acting as a real estate closing agent shall:</para><para>(a) Have received good funds which are available for disbursement at the time of closing a real estate transaction, except that up to five hundred dollars need not be available for disbursement from good funds;</para><para>(b) Except as provided in section 81-885.21, deposit all funds received on behalf of another person in a trust account controlled by the real estate closing agent in a federally insured financial institution, except that up to five hundred dollars may be paid by one party directly to another party without first being deposited in a trust account controlled by the real estate closing agent; and</para><para>(c) Except as provided in section 81-885.21, disburse closing funds only from the real estate closing agent's trust account in a federally insured financial institution in the form of good funds or in the form of a check drawn from the real estate closing agent's trust account.</para><para>(3) The following real estate transactions are exempt from this section:</para><para>(a) Transactions with a political subdivision which is exercising its power of condemnation or eminent domain;</para><para>(b) Lease or rental transactions; and</para><para>(c) Real estate transactions in which the closing occurs within one business day following another real estate closing and in which one party is a principal to both transactions, but only to the extent that the funds disbursed in the subsequent transaction are drawn upon funds properly received by a real estate closing agent in the prior transaction which were deposited in that real estate closing agent's trust account in a federally insured financial institution or as otherwise provided in section 81-885.21.</para><para>(4) The Attorney General or any county attorney may act to enjoin the performance of real estate closings which violate this section.</para><para>(5) A person acting as a real estate closing agent in violation of this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1275, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 774, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Real Estate License Act,</emphasis> see section 81-885.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 