  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-540"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-540</statuteno><catchline>Abstracters Board of Examiners; membership.</catchline><para>There is hereby created an Abstracters Board of Examiners of five members to be appointed by the Governor to carry out the purposes of and enforce the Abstracters Act. The board shall include three members who shall at all times be active registered abstracters who have engaged in the business of abstracting for at least five years, one member who shall be a lawyer experienced in the area of real estate law, and one member who shall be representative of the public.</para><para>No more than two members of the board shall be appointed from the same county, at least one member shall be appointed from a county having as its largest city a city of the first class, and at least one member shall be appointed from a county having as its largest city a city of the second class. No member of the board shall be employed by the same employer as any other member of the board.</para><para>Each member of the board shall serve for a term of five years and until a successor is appointed and qualified, except that members of the board currently serving on March 26, 1985, shall continue to serve the terms for which they were appointed. The first attorney member of the board whose term expires after March 26, 1985, shall be succeeded by the representative of the public.</para><para>Vacancies created by the death, resignation, or other disability of a board member resulting in the inability to carry out his or her duties shall be filled by appointment by the Governor and such successor shall possess the same qualifications as the member replaced and such member shall, upon qualification, serve the unexpired term of the member whom he or she succeeds. No member of the board shall be appointed to succeed himself or herself.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 3, p. 1437; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 330, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-511; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 