<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-542"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-542</statuteno><catchline>Registration; application; fee; qualifications; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>Any individual desiring to become a registered abstracter shall file an application for registration with the board. Such applicant shall have reached the age of majority, shall not have been convicted of a felony, and shall have at least one year of verified land title-related experience satisfactory to the board. Each applicant for registration shall take the written examination prescribed by section 76-543.</para><para>Such application shall be in a form prepared by the board and shall contain the applicant's social security number and such information as may be necessary to assist the board in determining the qualification of the applicant for registration. Each such application shall be accompanied by (1) an application fee of not less than twenty-five dollars or more than one hundred dollars and (2) an examination fee of not less than twenty-five dollars or more than one hundred dollars. The board shall establish such fees based on the administrative costs of the board.</para><para>Upon receipt of such application the board shall notify the applicant by mail whether the application has been accepted. If the application has not been accepted, the examination fee shall be returned to the applicant. If the application has been accepted, the applicant shall be notified of the time and place of the next scheduled examination.</para><para>The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to establish the experience standards and administer the examination required for registered abstracters.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 11, p. 1440; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 615, &#167; 10, p. 2498; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 330, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 409, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-519; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 202; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1071, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 