<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id173" statutenumber="76-214"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-214</statuteno><catchline id="id176">Deed, memorandum of contract, or land contract; recorded; death certificate filed; statement required; access.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, every grantee who has a deed to real estate recorded and every purchaser of real estate who has a memorandum of contract or land contract recorded shall, at the time such deed, memorandum of contract, or land contract is presented for recording, file with the register of deeds a completed statement as prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. For all deeds and all memoranda of contract and land contracts recorded on and after January 1, 2001, the statement shall not require the social security number of the grantee or purchaser or the federal employer identification number of the grantee or purchaser. This statement may require the recitation of any information contained in the deed, memorandum of contract, or land contract, the total consideration paid, the amount of the total consideration attributable to factors other than the purchase of the real estate itself, and other factors which may influence the transaction. If a death certificate is recorded as provided in subsection (2) of this section, this statement may require a date of death, the name of the decedent, and whether the title is affected as a result of a transfer on death deed, a joint tenancy deed, or the expiration of a life estate or by any other means. This statement shall be signed and filed by the grantee, the purchaser, or his or her authorized agent. The register of deeds shall forward the statement to the county assessor. If the grantee or purchaser fails to furnish the prescribed statement, the register of deeds shall not record the deed, memorandum of contract, or land contract. The register of deeds shall indicate on the statement the book and page or computer system reference where the deed, memorandum of contract, or land contract is recorded and shall immediately forward the statement to the county assessor. The county assessor shall process the statement according to the instructions of the Property Tax Administrator and shall, pursuant to the rules and regulations of the Tax Commissioner, forward the statement to the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(2)(a) The statement described in subsection (1) of this section shall be filed at the time that a certified or authenticated copy of the grantor's death certificate is filed if such death certificate is required to be filed under section 76-2,126 and the conveyance of real estate was pursuant to a transfer on death deed.</para><para>(b) The statement described in subsection (1) of this section shall not be required to be filed at the time that a transfer on death deed is filed or at the time that an instrument of revocation of a transfer on death deed as described in subdivision (a)(1)(B) of section 76-3413 is filed.</para><para>(3) Any person shall have access to the statements at the office of the Tax Commissioner, county assessor, or register of deeds if the statements are available and have not been disposed of pursuant to the records retention and disposition schedule as approved by the State Records Administrator.</para><para>(4) The statement described in subsection (1) of this section shall not be required if the document being recorded is an easement or an oil, gas, or mineral lease, or any subsequent assignment of an easement or such lease, except that such statement shall be required for conservation easements and preservation easements as such terms are defined in section 76-2,111.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 224, &#167; 1, p. 549; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5662; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 76-268; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 76-214; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 456, &#167; 1, p. 1450; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 457, &#167; 1, p. 1451; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 28, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 179, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 679, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 200; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 902, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1275, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 527, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB348, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB536, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB780, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB725, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB535, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Violation of section,</emphasis> penalty, see section 76-215.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The real property transactions eligible for inclusion in the sales file are those transactions for which the statement required by this section is filed. For those transactions initially eligible for inclusion in the sales file, the price to be included in the sales file is the total consideration paid as listed on the statement described in subsection (1) of this section. Shaul v. Lang, 263 Neb. 499, 640 N.W.2d 668 (2002).</para><para>Sales-assessment ratio study was made prior to 1965 amendment to this section. Brandeis Inv. Co. v. State Board of Equalization &amp; Assessment, 181 Neb. 750, 150 N.W.2d 893 (1967).</para><para>Statement of consideration is prima facie evidence thereof but may be rebutted. Sampson v. Sissel, 151 Neb. 521, 38 N.W.2d 341 (1949).</para><para>Where space in deed for recital of consideration was left blank, it was a circumstance taken into consideration in determining question of estoppel. Storz v. Clarke, 117 Neb. 488, 221 N.W. 101 (1928).</para><para>Recitals of consideration in deeds are incompetent as evidence of value. State v. Wright, 105 Neb. 617, 181 N.W. 539 (1921).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>