<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-879"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-879</statuteno><catchline>Public-offering statement; requirements.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in section 76-878 or subsection (b) of this section, a declarant, prior to the offering of any interest in a unit to the public, shall prepare a public-offering statement conforming to the requirements of sections 76-825 to 76-894.</para><para>(b) A declarant may transfer responsibility for preparation of all or a part of the public-offering statement to a successor declarant pursuant to section 76-862 or to a person in the business of selling real estate who intends to offer units in the condominium. In the event of any such transfer, the transferor shall provide the transferee with any information necessary to enable the transferee to fulfill the requirements of subsection (a) of this section.</para><para>(c) Any declarant or other person in the business of selling real estate who offers a unit to a purchaser shall deliver a public-offering statement in the manner prescribed in subsection (a) of section 76-883. The person responsible for preparing all or a part of the public-offering statement is liable for any materially false or intentionally misleading statement set forth therein or any failure to make disclosures required by sections 76-825 to 76-894 with respect to that portion of the public-offering statement which he or she prepared. If a declarant did not prepare any part of a public-offering statement that he or she delivers, he or she is not liable for its contents unless he or she had actual knowledge of the statement or omission or, in the exercise of reasonable care, should have known of the statement or omission. Nothing in sections 76-825 to 76-894 shall prohibit a condominium purchaser from waiving the preparation and delivery of a public-offering statement.</para><para>(d) If a unit is part of a condominium and is part of any other real estate regime in connection with the sale of which the delivery of a public-offering statement is required under the laws of this state, a single public-offering statement conforming to the requirements of sections 76-825 to 76-894 as those requirements relate to all real estate regimes in which the unit is located may be prepared and delivered in lieu of providing two or more public-offering statements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1105, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc>