
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id146">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id148" statutenumber="76-238.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-238.01</statuteno><catchline id="id151">Mortgages;
interest in real estate included; debts that may be secured; future advances; optimal future advance; notice; filing;
limitation.</catchline><para>(1) Any interest in real
property capable of being transferred may be mortgaged to secure (a) existing debts or obligations, (b) debts or obligations created simultaneously
with the execution of the mortgage, (c) future
advances necessary to protect the security, even
though such future advances cause the total indebtedness to exceed the maximum
amount stated in the mortgage, or (d) any future advances to be
made at the option of the parties in
any amount unless, except as otherwise provided under subsection (2) or (3)
of this section, a maximum amount of total indebtedness to be secured is stated
in the mortgage. </para>
<para>(2) Future
advances necessary to protect the security shall include, but not be limited
to, advances for payment of real property taxes, special assessments, prior
liens, hazard insurance premiums, maintenance charges imposed under a condominium
declaration or other covenant, and costs of repair, maintenance, or improvements.
Future advances necessary to protect the security are secured by the mortgage
and have the priority specified in subsection (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except
as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, all items identified in
subsection (1) of this section are equally secured by the mortgage from the
time of filing the mortgage as provided by law and have the same priority
as the mortgage over the rights of all other persons who acquire any rights
in or liens upon the mortgaged real property subsequent to the time the mortgage
was filed.</para><para>(b)(i) The mortgagor or his or her successor in title may limit
the amount of optional future advances secured by the mortgage under subdivision
(1)(d) of this section by filing a notice for record in the office of the
register of deeds of each county in which the mortgaged real property or some
part thereof is situated. A copy of such notice shall be sent by certified
mail to the mortgagee at the address of the mortgagee set forth in the mortgage
or, if the mortgage has been assigned, to the address of the most recent assignee
reflected in a recorded assignment of the mortgage. The amount of such secured
optional future advances shall be limited to not less than the amount actually
advanced at the time of receipt of such notice by the mortgagee.</para>
<para>(ii) If any
optional future advance is made by the mortgagee to the mortgagor or his or
her successor in title after receiving written notice of the filing for record
of any trust deed, mortgage, lien, or claim against such mortgaged real property,
then the amount of such optional future advance shall be junior to such trust
deed, mortgage, lien, or claim. The notice under this subdivision shall be
sent by certified mail to the mortgagee at the address of the mortgagee set
forth in the mortgage or, if the mortgage has been assigned, to the address
of the most recent assignee reflected in a recorded assignment of the mortgage.</para>
<para>(iii) Subdivisions
(b)(i) and (ii) of this subsection shall not limit or determine the priority
of optional future advances as against construction liens governed by section
52-139.</para><para>(4) The reduction to zero
or elimination of the debt evidenced by the instruments authorized in this
section shall not invalidate the operation of this section as to any future
advances unless a notice or release to the contrary is filed for record as
provided by law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 368, &#167; 1, p. 1140; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 913, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 136, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB788, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>The Legislature has fixed the priority of some optional advances at the time mortgage is recorded. Larson Cement Stone Co. v. Redlim Realty Co., 179 Neb. 134, 137 N.W.2d 241 (1965).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>