<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2,110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2,110</statuteno><catchline>Instruments to subdivide real estate; defective; validation; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) After January 1, 1995, no action shall be maintained to set aside, cancel, annul, or declare void or invalid any conveyance, in any manner purporting to subdivide real estate, which has been recorded in the office of the register of deeds of the county in which the real estate is situated for more than five years prior to the commencement of the action on the ground that the conveyance or the recording of the conveyance has failed to comply with any requirement relating to subdivision approval. Unless the conveyance is modified or set aside by an action or proceeding commenced by January 1, 1995, or five years after the date of recording of the conveyance, whichever is later, it shall be conclusively presumed that the conveyance is fully valid notwithstanding any failure to comply with any requirement relating to subdivision approval.</para><para>(2) If any conveyance, in any manner purporting to subdivide real estate, has been or is hereafter recorded in the office of register of deeds of the county in which the real estate is situated and the conveyance or the recording of the conveyance has failed to comply with any requirement relating to subdivision approval and if the conveyance has not been otherwise validated under subsection (1) of this section, any party claiming an interest in such conveyance may file an affidavit with the register of deeds asserting that written notice of the defect in approval has been received by the governmental authority having subdivision approval jurisdiction over such real estate. Upon filing such affidavit, such governmental authority shall have one hundred twenty days from the receipt of such written notice to record an objection in the office of register of deeds in the county in which the real estate is situated, or such conveyance shall be fully valid. If an objection is filed, the conveyance shall not be validated. The objection shall be in the form of a resolution adopted after public hearing. The governmental authority may waive, prospectively waive, or retroactively waive such notice or such one-hundred-twenty-day period, as to a single subdivision or any category of subdivisions.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding the validity of any such conveyance under this section, the subdivider shall not thus be relieved of any penalty lawfully imposed by such governmental authority for the failure to otherwise comply with any requirement relating to subdivision approval. Any conveyance of real estate for the public use shall be valid only upon express approval of such governmental authority. Other than for purposes of validating a conveyance, this section shall not excuse compliance with applicable zoning or subdivision ordinances of the governmental authority having subdivision approval jurisdiction over such real estate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 235, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 188, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>