<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-816" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-816</statuteno><catchline>Board of administrators; records; examination; condominium statement; filing with register of deeds.</catchline><para>(1) The board of administrators or other administrative body specified in the bylaws shall keep or cause to be kept a book with a detailed account, in chronological order, of the receipts and expenditures affecting the condominium property regime and its administration and specifying the maintenance and repair expenses of the common elements and all other expenses incurred. Both the book and the vouchers accrediting the entries made thereupon shall be available for examination by any co-owner or any prospective purchaser at convenient hours on working days that shall be set and announced for general knowledge. Any prospective purchaser must be designated as such by a co-owner in writing. For condominiums created in this state before January 1, 1984, the provision on the records of the administrative body or association in section 76-876 shall apply to the extent necessary in construing the provisions of sections 76-827, 76-829 to 76-831, 76-840, 76-841, 76-869, 76-874, 76-876, 76-884, and 76-891.01, and subdivisions (a)(1) to (a)(6) and (a)(11) to (a)(16) of section 76-860 which apply to events and circumstances which occur after January 1, 1984.</para><para>(2) The association of co-owners and board of administrators, or other administrative body governing the condominium property regime, and its common elements, shall file with the register of deeds of the county in which the condominium is located a condominium statement listing the name of such board or other administrative body and the names and addresses of the current officers of such board or other administrative body. Such filing shall be made every year on or before December 31. The receipt of any legal notice by or service of process on such officer personally or at such officer's filed address shall constitute notice to the board or other administrative body administering the condominium and its common elements. If the board or other administrative body fails to make the filing required by this subsection, the posting of the legal notice or process at the entrance, main office, or other prominent location in the common area of the condominium shall constitute notice to the board or other administrative body until such filing is made.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 429, &#167; 16, p. 1442; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 730, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 478, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB42, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>