<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate=" ">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-547"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>76-547</statuteno><catchline>Certificates; term; renewal; requirements;
fees.</catchline><para>(1) All certificates of authority issued pursuant to
section 76-545 shall expire on April 1 of each even-numbered year irrespective of when issued.
Such certificates shall be renewed, as provided in this section, for a two-year period upon payment of a renewal fee
of not less than fifty dollars or more than four hundred dollars. The board shall establish
such fee based on the administrative costs of the board.</para>
<para>(2) All certificates of registration, including duplicate certificates
of registration, issued pursuant to section 76-543 shall expire on April 1
of each even-numbered year irrespective of when issued. Such certificates
shall be renewed, as provided in this section, for a two-year period upon
payment of a renewal fee of not less than twenty dollars or more than two
hundred dollars. The board shall establish such fee based on the administrative
costs of the board. The board shall not renew the certificate of registration
or duplicate certificate of registration for any registered abstracter who
has failed to complete the professional development requirements set forth
in section 76-544, unless the registered abstracter has shown good cause why
he or she was unable to comply with such requirements. If the board determines
that good cause was shown for not completing the professional development
requirements, the board shall permit the registered abstracter to make up
all outstanding hours of professional development within six months of the
renewal of such certificates. If the hours are not completed in six months,
such certificates shall be revoked.</para>
<para>(3) Thirty to sixty days prior to the expiration date of the certificates,
the board shall cause a notice of expiration and application for renewal,
including a statement for the fee for each certificate, to be mailed to each
of the holders of such certificates. The notice and application shall be in
a form prepared by the board.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 15, p. 1442; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 330, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-523; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1071, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 640, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1051, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>