<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-712"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-712</statuteno><catchline>Condemnation award; certification; filing; state or federal-aid highways; failure to make deposit within sixty days; effect.</catchline><para>Upon deposit of the condemnation award, the court shall prepare and certify under seal a true copy thereof and shall transmit the same to the register of deeds of the county where any real estate or interest therein is condemned and to the county clerk of the county where personal property only is condemned. When real estate or personal property in two or more counties is condemned, a certified copy of the condemnation award shall be filed in each county where any property is situated. The amount of the condemnation award in all condemnation proceedings for the state highway system established by Chapter 39, article 13, or for any highway or urban extension thereof which is a part of the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways as defined in the Federal Aid Highway Act of 1956, and qualified for federal aid thereunder, shall be deposited with the court within sixty days from the filing of the appraisers' award. In such proceedings, if the condemner fails to make such deposit within sixty days from the filing of the appraisers' award, the condemner shall be deemed to have abandoned the condemnation proceeding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 12, p. 455; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 351, &#167; 2, p. 1240; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 370, &#167; 4, p. 1145; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 601, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>Where eminent domain proceeding was pending in which question of abandonment and its effect could be determined, action for declaratory judgment on claimed abandonment should have been dismissed. Zarybnicky v. County of Gage, 196 Neb. 210, 241 N.W.2d 834 (1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 