<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id480"><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2,132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2,132</statuteno><catchline>Required findings; order.</catchline><para>(a) The court may not approve relocation of an easement under the Uniform Easement Relocation Act unless the servient estate owner:</para><para>(1) establishes that the easement is eligible for relocation under section 76-2,129; and</para><para>(2) satisfies the conditions for relocation under section 76-2,130.</para><para>(b) An order under the Uniform Easement Relocation Act approving relocation of an easement must:</para><para>(1) state that the order is issued in accordance with the Uniform Easement Relocation Act;</para><para>(2) recite the recording data of the instrument creating the easement, if any, any amendments, and any notice as described under sections 76-288 to 76-298;</para><para>(3) identify the immediately preceding location of the easement;</para><para>(4) describe in a legally sufficient manner the new location of the easement;</para><para>(5) describe mitigation required of the servient estate owner during relocation;</para><para>(6) refer in detail to the plans and specifications of improvements necessary for the easement holder to enter, use, and enjoy the easement in the new location;</para><para>(7) specify conditions to be satisfied by the servient estate owner to relocate the easement and construct improvements necessary for the easement holder to enter, use, and enjoy the easement in the new location;</para><para>(8) include a provision for payment by the servient estate owner of expenses under section 76-2,133;</para><para>(9) include a provision for compliance by the parties with the obligation of good faith under section 76-2,134; and</para><para>(10) instruct the servient estate owner to record an affidavit, if required under subsection (a) of section 76-2,135, when the servient estate owner substantially completes relocation.</para><para>(c) An order under subsection (b) of this section may include any other provision consistent with the Uniform Easement Relocation Act for the fair and equitable relocation of the easement.</para><para>(d) Before a servient estate owner proceeds with relocation of an easement under the Uniform Easement Relocation Act, the owner must record, in the land records of each jurisdiction where the servient estate is located, a certified copy of the order under subsection (b) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB501, &#167; 69. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>