<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id84">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id86" statutenumber="76-903">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-903</statuteno><catchline id="id89">Design; collection
of tax; refund; procedure; disbursement.</catchline><para>The Tax
Commissioner shall design such stamps in such denominations as in his or her
judgment will be the most advantageous to all persons concerned. When any
deed subject to the tax imposed by section 76-901 is offered for recordation,
the register of deeds shall ascertain and compute the amount of the tax due
thereon and shall collect such amount as a prerequisite to acceptance of the
deed for recordation. If a dispute arises concerning the taxability of the
transfer, the register of deeds shall not record the deed until the disputed
tax is paid. If a disputed tax has been paid, the taxpayer may file for a
refund pursuant to section 76-908. The taxpayer may also seek a declaratory
ruling pursuant to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Department
of Revenue. From each two dollars and twenty-five cents of tax collected pursuant
to section 76-901, the register of deeds shall retain fifty cents to be placed
in the county general fund and shall remit the balance to the State Treasurer
who shall credit ninety-five cents
of such amount to the Affordable Housing Trust Fund, twenty-five cents of such amount to the Site and Building
Development Fund, twenty-five cents of such amount to the Homeless
Shelter Assistance Trust Fund, and thirty cents of such amount to the Behavioral
Health Services Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 463, &#167; 3, p. 1473; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 618, &#167; 2, p. 2505; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 194, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 236, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1192, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 864, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 516, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 40, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB388, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
