<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id205">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id207" statutenumber="76-902">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-902</statuteno><catchline id="id210">Tax; exemptions.</catchline>
<para>The tax imposed by section 76-901 shall not apply to:</para>
<para>(1) Deeds recorded prior to November 18, 1965;</para>
<para>(2) Deeds to property transferred by or to the United States
of America, the State of Nebraska, or any of their agencies or political subdivisions;</para>
<para>(3) Deeds which secure or release a debt or other obligation;</para>
<para>(4) Deeds which, without additional consideration, confirm,
correct, modify, or supplement a deed previously recorded but which do not
extend or limit existing title or interest;</para>
<para>(5)(a) Deeds between spouses,
between ex-spouses for the purpose of conveying any rights to property acquired
or held during the marriage, or between parent and child, without
actual consideration therefor, and (b) deeds to or from a family corporation,
partnership, or limited liability company when all the shares of stock of
the corporation or interest in the partnership or limited liability company
are owned by members of a family, or a trust created for the benefit of a
member of that family, related to one another within the fourth degree of
kindred according to the rules of civil law, and their spouses, for no consideration
other than the issuance of stock of the corporation or interest in the partnership
or limited liability company to such family members or the return of the stock
to the corporation in partial or complete liquidation of the corporation or
deeds in dissolution of the interest in the partnership or limited liability
company. In order to qualify for the exemption for family corporations, partnerships,
or limited liability companies, the property shall be transferred in the name
of the corporation or partnership and not in the name of the individual shareholders,
partners, or members;</para>
<para>(6) Tax deeds;</para>
<para>(7) Deeds of partition;</para>
<para>(8) Deeds made pursuant to mergers, consolidations, sales,
or transfers of the assets of corporations pursuant to plans of merger or
consolidation filed with the office of Secretary of State. A copy of such
plan filed with the Secretary of State shall be presented to the register
of deeds before such exemption is granted;</para>
<para>(9) Deeds made by a subsidiary corporation to its parent
corporation for no consideration other than the cancellation or surrender
of the subsidiary's stock;</para>
<para>(10) Cemetery deeds;</para>
<para>(11) Mineral deeds;</para>
<para>(12) Deeds executed pursuant to court decrees;</para><?Pub Caret?>
<para>(13) Land contracts;</para>
<para>(14) Deeds which release a reversionary interest, a condition
subsequent or precedent, a restriction, or any other contingent interest;</para>
<para>(15) Deeds of distribution executed by a personal representative
conveying to devisees or heirs property passing by testate or intestate succession;</para>
<para>(16) Transfer
on death deeds or revocations of transfer on death deeds;</para>
<para>(17) Certified
or authenticated death certificates pertaining to transfer on death deeds;</para>
<para>(18) Deeds transferring property
located within the boundaries of an Indian reservation if the grantor or grantee
is a reservation Indian;</para>
<para>(19) Deeds transferring property
into a trust if the transfer of the same property would be exempt if the transfer
was made directly from the grantor to the beneficiary or beneficiaries under
the trust. No such exemption shall be granted unless the register of deeds
is presented with a signed statement certifying that the transfer of the property
is made under such circumstances as to come within one of the exemptions specified
in this section and that evidence supporting the exemption is maintained by
the person signing the statement and is available for inspection by the Department
of Revenue;</para>
<para>(20) Deeds transferring property
from a trustee to a beneficiary of a trust;</para>
<para>(21) Deeds which convey property
held in the name of any partnership or limited liability company not subject
to subdivision (5) of this section to any partner in the partnership or member
of the limited liability company or to his or her spouse;</para>
<para>(22) Leases;</para>
<para>(23) Easements; or</para>
<para>(24) Deeds which transfer
title from a trustee to a beneficiary pursuant to a power of sale exercised
by a trustee under a trust deed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 463, &#167; 2, p. 1473; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 619, &#167; 1, p. 2506; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 620, &#167; 1, p. 2507; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 825, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 610, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 815, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 650, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 194, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 795, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1105, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 193, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 481; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 516, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB536, &#167; 35.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>