<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-552"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-552</statuteno><catchline>Disciplinary actions; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>A verified complaint may be filed with the board charging a registered abstracter or a holder of a certificate of authority with a violation of the Abstracters Act. The board on its own motion may also file such a complaint. If a complaint is filed, the board shall immediately notify the abstracter or holder of such certificate of the complaint. The notice shall be in writing and be sent by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested. The notice shall contain a statement of the charges and a copy of the complaint. The notice shall state the time and place of the hearing which shall be not less than twenty nor more than forty days from the date of service of such complaint. The abstracter or holder of such certificate shall be entitled to counsel at any hearing. The board shall cause a transcript of any testimony taken to be made by a reporter or stenographer.</para><para>The decision of the board may be appealed, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 147.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 