<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate=" ">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-545"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>76-545</statuteno><catchline>Business of abstracting; requirements;
certificate of authority; authority; fee.</catchline><para>Any individual
or business entity desiring to engage in the business of abstracting in this
state shall make application to the board for a certificate of authority.
Such application shall be in a form prepared by the board and shall contain
such information as may be necessary to assist the board in determining whether
the applicant has complied with the Abstracters Act. Such application shall
be accompanied by an application fee of not less than twenty-five dollars
or more than two hundred dollars. The board
shall establish such fee based on the administrative costs of the board. The
applicant shall furnish proof that such applicant is or has employed a registered
abstracter and shall provide the name and address of a resident agent for
service of process under the act. When this section has been complied with,
the board shall issue a certificate of authority in such form as it may prescribe,
attesting to the same, and such certificate shall be prominently displayed
in the place of business of the applicant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 14, p. 1442; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 615, &#167; 11, p. 2499; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-522; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1071, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1051, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>