<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-546" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-546</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Temporary certificate of registration; when issued; fee; expiration.</catchline><para id="id00">The board may, upon application to it by (1) any individual succeeding to the ownership of any abstract business by any means other than by purchase or (2) any individual who, by reason of the incapacity of any registered abstracter owner of any abstract business, is required to assume the operation of such business, grant to such individual, without examination, a temporary certificate of registration. The application shall include the applicant's social security number. The fee for such temporary certificate of registration shall be not less than twenty-five or more than one hundred dollars. The board shall establish such fee based on the administrative costs of the board. Such certificate shall expire six months after its date or upon the expiration of sixty days after the next regularly scheduled examination which could be taken by the applicant under the rules and regulations of the board, whichever period is the longer. The board shall notify such applicant by mail of the time and place of such examination.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 13, p. 1441; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 409, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-521; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 203; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB345, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>