<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-886"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-886</statuteno><catchline>Conversion buildings; rights of tenants.</catchline><para>(a) A declarant of a condominium containing conversion buildings, and any person in the business of selling real estate for his or her own account who intends to offer units in such a condominium shall give each of the residential tenants and any residential subtenant in possession of a portion of a conversion building notice of the conversion and provide those persons with the public-offering statement, if any, no later than sixty days before the tenants and any subtenant in possession are required to vacate. The notice must set forth generally the rights of tenants and subtenants under this section and shall be hand delivered to the unit or mailed by prepaid United States mail to the tenant and subtenant at the address of the unit or any other mailing address provided by a tenant. No tenant or subtenant may be required to vacate upon less than sixty days' notice, except by reason of nonpayment of rent, waste, or conduct that disturbs other tenants' peaceful enjoyment of the premises, and the terms of the tenancy may not be altered during that period. Failure to give notice as required by this section is a defense to an action for possession.</para><para>(b) For sixty days after delivery or mailing of the notice described in subsection (a), the person required to give the notice may offer to convey each unit or proposed unit occupied for residential use to the tenant who leases that unit. If such an offer is made and the tenant fails to purchase the unit during the sixty-day period, the offeror may not offer to dispose of an interest in that unit during the following thirty days at a price or on terms more favorable to the offeree than the price or terms offered to the tenant. This subsection does not apply to any unit in a conversion building if that unit will be restricted exclusively to nonresidential use or the boundaries of the converted unit do not substantially conform to the dimensions of the residential unit before conversion.</para><para>(c) If a seller, in violation of subsection (b) of this section, conveys a unit to a purchaser for value who has no knowledge of the violation, recordation of the deed conveying the unit extinguishes any right a tenant may have under subsection (b) of this section to purchase that unit if the deed states that the seller has complied with subsection (b) of this section, but does not affect the right of a tenant to recover damages from the seller for a violation of subsection (b) of this section.</para><para>(d) If a notice of conversion specifies a date by which a unit or proposed unit must be vacated the notice shall constitute a notice to vacate.</para><para>(e) Nothing in this section permits termination of a lease by a declarant in violation of its terms.</para><para>(f) Any tenant may waive any provision of this section by a written instrument executed after the date of notice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 62. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 