<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2,124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2,124</statuteno><catchline>Water resources update notice; Department of Natural Resources; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person transferring ownership of real property not inside the corporate limits of a municipality shall complete and provide to the transferee, at or before the closing of the transfer, a water resources update notice acknowledging (a) whether any surface water rights issued pursuant to Chapter 46, article 2, and in the name of any party other than an irrigation district, public power and irrigation district, or mutual irrigation company are attached to the real property, ownership of which is being transferred, and (b) whether there are any water wells, except water wells used solely for domestic purposes and constructed prior to September 9, 1993, on the real property, ownership of which is being transferred. If the water resources update notice discloses the existence of such surface water rights or such water wells, the transferee shall complete the water resources update notice and shall file it with the Department of Natural Resources within sixty days after recording the deed or other instrument by which the transfer of ownership of real property is made. The department shall use such notice to update ownership of surface water rights and water well registrations as required by sections 46-230 and 46-602.</para><para>(2) The department shall prescribe the form and content of the water resources update notice and shall make such forms available to title insurance companies and other persons as deemed appropriate by the department. The requirement that a water resources update notice be filed with the department or the failure to file such a notice does not affect the recording, legality, or sufficiency of a deed or other instrument evidencing the transfer of ownership of real property.</para><para>(3) The department shall not collect a fee for the filing of the water resources update notices.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 458, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 