<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-217"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-217</statuteno><catchline>Acknowledgment; before whom taken in this state.</catchline><para>The acknowledgment must be made or proved, if in this state, before a judge or clerk of any court, United States Magistrate or notary public therein; but no officer can take any such acknowledgment or proof out of his territorial jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 43, &#167; 3, p. 280; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6198; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5597; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 76-203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 76-217; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 244, &#167; 1, p. 768; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 268. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Authority to take acknowledgments:</emphasis></para><para>Deputy clerks of the district and county courts, see section 24-403.</para><para>Notaries public, see section 64-107.</para><para>Secretary of State, see section 84-507.</para><para><emphasis>Notaries public,</emphasis> generally, see Chapter 64, article 1.</para><para><emphasis>Payment to county treasurer of fees of county officers for taking acknowledgments,</emphasis> see section 33-153.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Certificate of an officer having authority to take acknowledgments cannot be impeached by showing that it was irregularly performed. Bode v. Jussen, 93 Neb. 482, 140 N.W. 768 (1913); Morris v. Linton, 61 Neb. 537, 85 N.W. 565 (1901).</para><para>Officer is disqualified to take acknowledgment when he is interested in transaction. Banking House of A. Castetter v. Stewart, 70 Neb. 815, 98 N.W. 34 (1904); Horbach v. Tyrrell, 48 Neb. 514, 67 N.W. 485 (1896); Hedbloom v. Pierson, 2 Neb. Unof. 799, 90 N.W. 218 (1902); Chadron L. &amp; B. Assn. v. O'Linn, 1 Neb. Unof. 1, 95 N.W. 368 (1901).</para><para>Certificate of acknowledgment cannot be impeached by showing that officer's duty was irregularly performed. Council Bluffs Savings Bank v. Smith, 59 Neb. 90, 80 N.W. 270 (1899).</para><para>Prior to September 7, 1947, United States Commissioner was unauthorized to take acknowledgments. Interstate S. &amp; L. Assn. v. Strine, 58 Neb. 133, 78 N.W. 377 (1899).</para><para>Acknowledgment may be taken by attorney of party in interest. Havemeyer v. Dahn, 48 Neb. 536, 67 N.W. 489 (1896).</para><para>Act of acknowledging officer is ministerial. Horbach v. Tyrrell, 48 Neb. 514, 67 N.W. 485 (1896).</para><para>Acknowledgment is act of one who has executed instrument going before some competent officer and declaring it to be his act or deed. Aultman &amp; Taylor Co. v. Jenkins, 19 Neb. 209, 27 N.W. 117 (1886).</para><para>County clerk is authorized to take acknowledgments. Davis v. Huston, 15 Neb. 28, 16 N.W. 820 (1883).</para><para>Certificate of acknowledgment cannot be impeached except for fraud, collusion, or imposition. Boldt v. Becker, 1 Neb. Unof. 75, 95 N.W. 509 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>