  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-873"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-873</statuteno><catchline>Assessment for common expenses.</catchline><para>(a) Until the association makes a common expense assessment, the declarant shall pay all common expenses. After any assessment has been made by the association, assessments must be made at least annually. After one-third of the members of the executive board are elected by unit owners other than the declarant, assessments shall be based on a budget adopted at least annually by the association.</para><para>(b) Except for assessment under subsections (c), (d), and (e) of this section, all common expenses must be assessed against all the units in accordance with the allocations set forth in the declaration pursuant to subsection (a) of section 76-844. Any past-due common expense assessment or installment thereof bears interest at the rate established by the association not exceeding eighteen percent per year.</para><para>(c) To the extent required by the declaration:</para><para>(1) Any common expense associated with the maintenance, repair, or replacement of a limited common element must be assessed against the units to which that limited common element is assigned, equally, or in any other proportion that the declaration provides;</para><para>(2) Any common expense or portion thereof benefiting fewer than all of the units must be assessed exclusively against the units benefited; and</para><para>(3) The costs of insurance may at the discretion of the association be assessed in proportion to risk and, if reasonably determined, the costs of utilities not separately metered must be assessed in proportion to usage.</para><para>(d) Assessments to pay a judgment against the association pursuant to subsection (a) of section 76-875 may be made only against the units in the condominium at the time the judgment was entered, in proportion to their common expense liabilities.</para><para>(e) If any common expense is caused by the misconduct of any unit owner, the association may assess that expense exclusively against his or her unit.</para><para>(f) If common expense liabilities are reallocated, common expense assessments and any installment thereof not yet due shall be recalculated in accordance with the reallocated common expense liabilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 49. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 