<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-802"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-802</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Condominium Property Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Condominium property regime shall mean a project whereby four or more apartments are separately offered or proposed to be offered for sale;</para><para>(2) Apartment shall mean an enclosed space consisting of one or more rooms occupying all or part of a floor in a building of one or more floors or stories regardless of whether it is designed for residence, for office, for the operation of any industry or business, or for any other type of independent use, if it has a direct exit to a thoroughfare or to a given common space leading to a thoroughfare;</para><para>(3) Co-owner shall mean a person, firm, corporation, partnership, limited liability company, association, trust, or other legal entity, or any combination thereof, which owns an apartment within the building;</para><para>(4) Association of co-owners shall mean all the co-owners as defined in subdivision (3) of this section, but a majority as defined in subdivision (8) of this section shall, except as otherwise provided in the act, constitute a quorum for the adoption of decisions;</para><para>(5) Board of administrators shall mean the governing board of the regime, consisting of not less than three members selected by and from the co-owners;</para><para>(6) General common elements shall mean and include:</para><para>(a) The land or leasehold interest in land on which the building stands;</para><para>(b) The foundations, main walls, roofs, halls, lobbies, stairways, and entrances and exit or communication ways;</para><para>(c) The basements, roofs, yards, and gardens except as otherwise provided or stipulated;</para><para>(d) The premises for the lodging of janitors or persons in charge of the building except as otherwise provided or stipulated;</para><para>(e) The compartments or installations of central services such as power, light, gas, cold and hot water, refrigeration, reservoirs, water tanks and pumps, and the like;</para><para>(f) The elevators, garbage incinerators, and, in general, all devices or installations existing for common use; and</para><para>(g) All other elements of the building rationally of common use or necessary to its existence, upkeep, and safety;</para><para>(7) Limited common elements shall mean and include those common elements which are agreed upon by all the co-owners to be reserved for the use of a certain number of apartments to the exclusion of the other apartments, such as special corridors, stairways and elevators, sanitary services common to the apartments of a particular floor, and the like;</para><para>(8) Majority of co-owners shall mean more than fifty percent of the basic value of the property as a whole, in accordance with the percentages computed in accordance with the provisions of section 76-806;</para><para>(9) Master deed shall mean the deed establishing the condominium property regime;</para><para>(10) Person shall mean an individual, firm, corporation, partnership, limited liability company, association, trust, or other legal entity or any combination thereof;</para><para>(11) Property shall mean and include the land, leasehold interests in land, any building, all improvements and structures thereon, and all easements, rights, and appurtenances belonging thereto or any of them alone;</para><para>(12) To record shall mean to record in accordance with sections 76-237 to 76-257 or other applicable recording statutes;</para><para>(13) Common expense shall mean and include:</para><para>(a) All sums lawfully assessed against the apartment owner;</para><para>(b) Expense of administration, maintenance, repair, or replacement of common elements; and</para><para>(c) Expenses agreed upon as common expenses by the association of co-owners; and</para><para>(14) All pronouns used in the Condominium Property Act shall include the male, female, and neuter genders and include the singular or plural numbers, as the case may be.</para><para>For condominiums created in this state before January 1, 1984, the definitions in section 76-827 shall apply to the extent necessary in construing the provisions of sections 76-827, 76-829 to 76-831, 76-840, 76-841, 76-869, 76-874, 76-876, 76-884, and 76-891.01, and subdivisions (a)(1) through (a)(6) and (a)(11) through (a)(16) of section 76-860 which apply to events and circumstances which occur after January 1, 1984.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 429, &#167; 2, p. 1435; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 730, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 479; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 478, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 361, &#167; 36. </para></source><annotation><para>Where resort homeowners' association purpose was to perform quasi-municipal functions, such as street and sewage system maintenance, its purpose and function are analogous to those of a condominium owners' association. Beaver Lake Assn. v. Beaver Lake Corp., 200 Neb. 685, 264 N.W.2d 871 (1978).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>