<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id416"><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2,141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2,141</statuteno><catchline>Covered real estate; affidavit; required when; form; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, covered real estate means real estate described in 31 C.F.R. 802.211(b)(3).</para><para>(2) Whenever there is a conveyance of covered real estate, the purchaser of the real estate shall complete and sign an affidavit stating that such purchaser is not affiliated with any foreign government or nongovernment person determined to be a foreign adversary pursuant to 15 C.F.R. 7.4.</para><para>(3) The affidavit shall be submitted to the register of deeds of the county in which the covered real estate is located. The register of deeds shall not record any instrument reflecting the conveyance of such real estate until he or she has received such affidavit. The register of deeds shall send a copy of the affidavit to the Attorney General.</para><para>(4) Any person who swears falsely on such an affidavit shall be guilty of a violation of section 28-915.01.</para><para>(5) The responsibility for determining whether an affidavit is required under this section rests solely with the purchaser, and no individual or entity other than the purchaser shall bear any civil or criminal liability under this section. A violation of this section shall not make any title or interest in land invalid or unmarketable.</para><para>(6) The affidavit required under this section shall be in substantially the following form:</para><para><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><?PubTbl tgroup rth="0.00pt" clmarg="0.00pt" crmarg="0.00pt"?><colspec align="right" colname="col1" colwidth="1.0*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="2.77*" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">STATE OF NEBRASKA )</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"> ss.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">COUNTY OF ....... )</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para><para>I, .................. (Purchaser), certify under penalty of perjury that I am not affiliated with any foreign government or nongovernment person determined to be a foreign adversary pursuant to 15 C.F.R. 7.4.</para><para><table frame="none"><tgroup align="center" cols="2"><colspec align="left" colname="col1" colwidth="1.65*" /><colspec align="left" colname="col2" colwidth="1.0*" /><tbody><row><entry>..............................</entry><entry>...............</entry></row><row><entry>Signature of Purchaser</entry><entry>Date</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1120, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>