<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-861"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-861</statuteno><catchline>Executive board; members and officers; powers and duties; condominium statement; filing with register of deeds.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in the declaration, the bylaws, subsection (b) of this section, or other provisions of the Nebraska Condominium Act, the executive board may act in all instances on behalf of the association. In the performance of their duties, the officers and members of the executive board are required to exercise ordinary and reasonable care.</para><para>(b) The executive board may not act on behalf of the association to commence litigation on behalf of the unit owners or the unit owners association, to amend the declaration pursuant to section 76-854, to terminate the condominium pursuant to section 76-855, or to elect members of the executive board or determine the qualifications, powers and duties, or terms of office of executive board members pursuant to subsection (f) of this section, but the executive board may fill vacancies in its membership for the unexpired portion of any term.</para><para>(c) Within thirty days after adoption of any proposed budget for the condominium, the executive board shall provide a summary of the budget to all the unit owners, and shall set a date for a meeting of the unit owners to consider ratification of the budget not less than fourteen nor more than thirty days after mailing of the summary. Unless at that meeting a majority of all votes in the association or any larger vote specified in the declaration reject the budget, the budget is ratified, whether or not a quorum is present. In the event the proposed budget is rejected, the periodic budget last ratified by the unit owners shall be continued until such time as the unit owners ratify a subsequent budget proposed by the executive board.</para><para>(d) Subject to subsection (e) of this section, the declaration may provide for a period of declarant control of the association, during which period a declarant, or persons designated by him or her, may appoint and remove the officers and members of the executive board. Regardless of the period provided in the declaration, a period of declarant control terminates no later than the earlier of: (i) Sixty days after conveyance of ninety percent of the units which may be created to unit owners other than a declarant; or (ii) two years after all declarants have ceased to offer units for sale in the ordinary course of business. A declarant may voluntarily surrender the right to appoint and remove officers and members of the executive board before termination of that period, but in that event he or she may require, for the duration of the period of declarant control, that specified actions of the association or executive board, as described in a recorded instrument executed by the declarant, be approved by the declarant before they become effective. Successor boards following declarant control may not discriminate nor act arbitrarily with respect to units still owned by a declarant or a successor declarant.</para><para>(e) Not later than sixty days after conveyance of fifty percent of the units which may be created to unit owners other than a declarant, at least one member and not less than twenty-five percent of the members of the executive board shall be elected exclusively by unit owners other than the declarant.</para><para>(f) Not later than the termination of any period of declarant control, the unit owners shall elect an executive board of at least three members, at least a majority of whom must be unit owners. The executive board shall elect the officers. The executive board members and officers shall take office upon election.</para><para>(g) Notwithstanding any provision of the declaration or bylaws to the contrary, the unit owners, by a two-thirds vote of all persons present and entitled to vote at any meeting of the unit owners at which a quorum is present, may remove any member of the executive board with or without cause, other than a member appointed by the declarant.</para><para>(h) The association shall file with the register of deeds of the county in which the condominium is located a condominium statement listing the name of the association and the names and addresses of the current officers of the association. Such filing shall be made every year on or before December 31. The receipt of any legal notice by or service of process on such officer personally or at such officer's filed address shall constitute notice to the association. If the association fails to make the filing required by this subsection, the posting of the legal notice or process at the entrance, main office, or other prominent location in the common area of the condominium shall constitute notice to the association until such filing is made.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB42, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 47. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>