<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id508">
<sectno id="id509">Sec. 52.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id510" statutenumber="76-549"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id512">76-549</statuteno><catchline id="id513">Abstracters
Board of Examiners Cash Fund; created; investment; board
members and director; compensation.</catchline><para>(1) All fees collected pursuant
to the Abstracters Act shall be deposited in the state treasury to be credited
to the Abstracters Board of Examiners Cash Fund which is hereby created. All
actual and necessary expenses of the board shall be paid from such fund.</para>
<para>(2) No member of the board
shall receive a salary. Each member of the board shall receive as compensation
for each day or part thereof of actual service while attending meetings or
otherwise engaged upon the business of the board fifty dollars and expenses
incurred in the performance of official duties. The director shall be paid
a salary to be determined by the board.</para>
<para>(3) Transfers
may be made from the Abstracters Board of Examiners Cash Fund to the General
Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Abstracters Board
of Examiners Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 5, p. 1438; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 615, &#167; 6, p. 2497; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 25, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 330, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 147; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 76-513; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 52.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>"Preparing written reports of title to real property" constitutes the "business of abstracting" for purposes of the Abstracters Act only when done in exchange for a fee or other valuable consideration. So construed, the Abstracters Act is not unconstitutionally overbroad on its face. State v. Rabourn, 269 Neb. 499, 693 N.W.2d 291 (2005).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>