<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-890"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-890</statuteno><catchline>Warranties; statute of limitations; judicial proceedings; notice; effect; strict compliance; required.</catchline><para>(a) A judicial proceeding for breach of any obligation arising under section 76-887 or 76-888 must be commenced within two years after the cause of action accrues, but the parties may agree to reduce the period of limitation to not less than one year. With respect to a unit that may be occupied for residential use, an agreement to reduce the period of limitation must be evidenced by an instrument executed by the purchaser. Prior to commencing any judicial proceeding under this section, the person seeking to commence the judicial proceeding must (1) provide written notice of the proposed proceeding and the specific alleged defect or defects to the prospective defendant or defendants and (2) give the prospective defendant or defendants at least three months to cure the alleged defect or defects. If the defect or defects are such that they cannot reasonably be cured within three months, the cure period shall extend as long as the prospective defendant has commenced and is diligently proceeding with repairs. Providing the notice in this section in a manner reasonably understood to inform the prospective defendant of the specific alleged defect or defects shall toll any applicable statute of limitations until the alleged defect or defects are cured. Any proceeding commenced without strict compliance with this section is subject to dismissal for such noncompliance.</para><para>(b) Subject to subsection (c) of this section, a cause of action for breach of warranty, regardless of the purchaser's lack of knowledge of the breach, accrues:</para><para>(1) as to a unit, at the time the purchaser to whom the warranty is first made enters into possession if a possessory interest was conveyed or at the time of acceptance of the instrument of conveyance if a nonpossessory interest was conveyed; and</para><para>(2) as to each common element, at the time the common element is completed or, if later, (i) as to a common element that may be added to the condominium or portion thereof, at the time the first unit therein is conveyed to a bona fide purchaser, or (ii) as to a common element within any other portion of the condominium, at the time the first unit in the condominium is conveyed to a bona fide purchaser.</para><para>(c) If a warranty explicitly extends to future performance or duration of any improvement or component of the condominium, the cause of action accrues at the time the breach is discovered or at the end of the period for which the warranty explicitly extends, whichever is earlier.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 433, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1105, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 52. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>