<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1414" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1414</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms and conditions of rental agreement; death of tenant; removal of personal property; liability.</catchline><para>(1) The landlord and tenant may include in a rental agreement terms and conditions not prohibited by the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act or other rule of law including rent, term of the agreement, and other provisions governing the rights and obligations of the parties.</para><para>(2) In absence of agreement, the tenant shall pay as rent the fair rental value for the use and occupancy of the dwelling unit.</para><para>(3) Rent shall be payable without demand or notice at the time and place agreed upon by the parties. Unless otherwise agreed, rent is payable at the dwelling unit and periodic rent is payable at the beginning of any term of one month or less and otherwise in equal monthly installments at the beginning of each month. Unless otherwise agreed, rent shall be uniformly apportionable from day to day.</para><para>(4) Unless the rental agreement fixes a definite term, the tenancy shall be week to week in case of a roomer who pays weekly rent, and in all other cases month to month.</para><para>(5) Upon request by a landlord, the tenant may provide and routinely update the name and contact information of a person who is authorized by the tenant to enter the tenant's dwelling unit to retrieve and store the tenant's personal property if the tenant dies. Upon the death of a tenant, the landlord shall make a reasonable attempt to contact the authorized person, if any, within ten days after the death. The authorized person shall have twenty days after being contacted by the landlord to notify the landlord that he or she will claim the tenant's property, and he or she will then have twenty days after such notification to remove the tenant's personal property from the dwelling unit or obtain the personal property from where it is being stored. Upon presentation of a valid government-issued identification confirming the identity of the authorized person, the landlord shall grant the authorized person reasonable access to the rented dwelling unit or to where the personal property is being stored if not in the dwelling unit. If the tenant's personal property is not entirely removed from the dwelling unit by an authorized person, the landlord may dispose of the remaining property as prescribed in the Disposition of Personal Property Landlord and Tenant Act. If the landlord allows an authorized person to receive the tenant's personal property as provided by this subsection, the landlord has no further liability to the tenant, the tenant's estate, or the tenant's heirs for lost, damaged, or stolen personal property. If the landlord is unable to contact the authorized person at the address and telephone number provided by the tenant or the authorized person fails to respond to the landlord's notification within twenty days after contact is made, the landlord may dispose of the tenant's personal property as prescribed in the Disposition of Personal Property Landlord and Tenant Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 293, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 7, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB221, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Disposition of Personal Property Landlord and Tenant Act,</emphasis> see section 69-2301.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Ambiguities in a lease should be construed against the person preparing the lease. D &amp; R Realty v. Bender, 230 Neb. 301, 431 N.W.2d 920 (1988).</para><para>Where a substantial portion of leased premises is destroyed or rendered incapable of being used by a lessee, the lessee is entitled to an apportionment of the rental to be paid, in the absence of an expressed assumption of the risk of such destruction. D &amp; R Realty v. Bender, 230 Neb. 301, 431 N.W.2d 920 (1988).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>