<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1427"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1427</statuteno><catchline>Wrongful failure to supply heat, water, hot water, or essential services.</catchline><para>(1) If contrary to the rental agreement or section 76-1419 the landlord deliberately or negligently fails to supply running water, hot water, or heat, or essential services, the tenant may give written notice to the landlord specifying the breach and may:</para><para>(a) Procure reasonable amounts of hot water, running water, heat and essential services during the period of the landlord's noncompliance and deduct their actual and reasonable cost from the rent;</para><para>(b) Recover damages based upon the diminution in the fair rental value of the dwelling unit; or</para><para>(c) Procure reasonable substitute housing during the period of the landlord's noncompliance, in which case the tenant is excused from paying rent for the period of the landlord's noncompliance.</para><para>In addition to the remedy provided in subdivisions (a) and (c), if the failure to supply is deliberate, the tenant may recover the actual and reasonable cost or fair and reasonable value of the substitute housing not in excess of an amount equal to the periodic rent, and in any case under this subsection reasonable attorney's fees.</para><para>(2) If the tenant proceeds under this section, he may not proceed under section 76-1425 as to that breach.</para><para>(3) The rights under this section do not arise until the tenant has given written notice to the landlord or if the condition was caused by the deliberate or negligent act or omission of the tenant, a member of his family, or other person on the premises with his consent. This section is not intended to cover circumstances beyond the landlord's control.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 293, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 