<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1304</statuteno><catchline>Application of sections; exceptions.</catchline><para>Unless the method of disposition is adopted for the purpose of evasion of the provisions of sections 76-1301 to 76-1315, such provisions shall not apply to offers or dispositions of any lot or unit in a retirement subdivision or community by a purchaser for his or her own account in a single or isolated transaction, nor shall such provisions apply to the following:</para><para>(1) Offers or dispositions of evidences of indebtedness secured by a mortgage or deed of trust of real estate;</para><para>(2) Offers or dispositions of securities or units of interest issued by a real estate investment trust regulated under any state or federal statute;</para><para>(3) The sale or lease of real estate under or pursuant to court order;</para><para>(4) The disposition in any manner whatsoever of any unit of public housing under the administrative jurisdiction of a local public housing authority;</para><para>(5) Offers or dispositions of securities currently registered with the Director of Banking and Finance and under the provisions of the Securities Act of Nebraska; and</para><para>(6) Health care facilities licensed by the Department of Health and Human Services under the Health Care Facility Licensure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1311, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 693, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 793; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 148; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 61, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 700.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para><para><emphasis>Securities Act of Nebraska,</emphasis> see section 8-1123.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>