<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1521"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1521</statuteno><catchline>Reports; form; contents; Secretary
of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The report required by section 76-1520
shall be on a form provided by the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State
may incorporate the form with other forms required to be filed by entities
identified in subsection (1) of section 76-1520. If there has been no change
in the information contained in the previous report filed by the reporting
entity, the reporting entity may so indicate in a space provided on the reporting
form for that purpose.</para>
<para>(2) The Secretary of State shall include a list of exemptions to the
prohibitions contained in Article XII, section 8, of the Constitution of Nebraska
and a means by which persons filing the form may indicate, if applicable,
which exemptions apply to the reporting entity. The reporting entity may include
or attach a statement indicating the basis upon which the reporting entity
claims exemption from the prohibitions contained in Article XII, section 8,
of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(3) The Secretary of State shall annually prepare a report indicating
the total number of entities reporting under sections 76-1520 to 76-1524,
the number of entities reporting as a corporation, as a limited partnership,
as a limited liability partnership, as a limited liability company, and as
a trust and the basis upon which the reporting entities claim exemption from
the prohibitions contained in Article XII, section 8, of the Constitution
of Nebraska. The Secretary of State shall deliver the report electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature
on or before January 1 each year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1193, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 134.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>