<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1008" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1008</statuteno><catchline>Notice of default and sale; request for copies; mailing of notice; publication of notice of default; when.</catchline><para>(1) Any person desiring a copy of any notice of default and of any notice of sale under any trust deed may, at any time subsequent to the filing for record of the trust deed and prior to the filing for record of a notice of default thereunder, file for record in the office of the register of deeds of any county in which any part or parcel of the trust property is situated a duly acknowledged request for a copy of any such notice of default and notice of sale. The request shall set forth the name and address of the person or persons requesting copies of such notices and shall identify the trust deed by stating the names of the original parties thereto, the date of filing for record thereof, and the book and page or computer system reference where the same is recorded and shall be in substantially the following form:</para><para>Request is hereby made that a copy of any notice of default and a copy of notice of sale under the trust deed filed for record ............, 20...., and recorded in book .........., page ........, (or computer system reference ........) Records of ............. County, Nebraska, executed by .......... as trustor, in which ............ is named as beneficiary and ............ as trustee, be mailed to .......(insert name)....... at ..........(insert address).......... .</para><para>Signature ..........................</para><para>(2) Not later than ten days after recordation of such notice of default, the trustee or beneficiary or the attorney for the trustee or beneficiary shall mail, by registered or certified mail with postage prepaid, a copy of such notice with the recording date shown thereon, addressed to each person whose name and address is set forth in a request therefor which has been recorded prior to the filing for record of the notice of default, directed to the address designated in such request. At least twenty days before the date of sale, the trustee or the attorney for the trustee shall mail, by registered or certified mail with postage prepaid, a copy of the notice of the time and place of sale, addressed to each person whose name and address is set forth in a request therefor which has been recorded prior to the filing for record of the notice of default, directed to the address designated in such request.</para><para>(3) Each trust deed shall contain a request that a copy of any notice of default and a copy of any notice of sale thereunder shall be mailed to each person who is a party thereto at the address of such person set forth therein, and a copy of any notice of default and of any notice of sale shall be mailed to each such person at the same time and in the same manner required as though a separate request therefor had been filed by each of such persons as provided in this section.</para><para>(4) If no address of the trustor is set forth in the trust deed and if no request for notice by such trustor has been recorded as provided in this section, a copy of the notice of default shall be published at least three times, once a week for three consecutive weeks, in a newspaper of general circulation in each county in which the trust property or some part thereof is situated, such publication to commence not later than ten days after the filing for record of the notice of default.</para><para>(5) No request for a copy of any notice filed for record pursuant to this section nor any statement or allegation in any such request nor any record thereof shall affect the title to trust property or be deemed notice to any person that any person requesting copies of notice of default or of notice of sale has or claims any right, title, or interest in or lien or claim upon the trust property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 451, &#167; 8, p. 1427; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 679, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 999, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1986, Third Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 813, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 54. </para></source><annotation><para>A proper reading of this section provides that unless the person or institution is a party to the trust deed at issue, that person or institution is not entitled to notice unless it is requested under subsection (1) of this section. First Neb. Ed. Credit Union v. U.S. Bancorp, 293 Neb. 308, 877 N.W.2d 578 (2016).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>