<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1498"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1498</statuteno><catchline>Noncompliance by landlord; tenant's rights.</catchline><para>(1) If there is a material noncompliance by the landlord with the rental agreement or a noncompliance with section 76-1492 materially affecting health and safety, the tenant may deliver a written notice to the landlord specifying the acts and omissions constituting the breach and that the rental agreement will terminate upon a date not less than thirty days after receipt of the notice if the breach is not remedied or if reasonable steps to remedy the breach have not been taken in fourteen days. The rental agreement shall terminate and the mobile home space shall be vacated as provided in the notice subject to the following:</para><para>(a) If the breach is remediable by repairs or the payment of damages or otherwise and the landlord adequately remedies the breach or takes reasonable steps to remedy it prior to the date specified in the notice, the rental agreement will not terminate; and</para><para>(b) The tenant may not terminate for a condition caused by the deliberate or negligent act or omission of the tenant, a member of the tenant's family, or other person in the mobile home park with the tenant's consent.</para><para>(2) A tenant may recover damages and obtain injunctive relief for any material noncompliance by the landlord with the rental agreement or section 76-1492.</para><para>(3) The remedy provided in subsection (2) of this section shall be in addition to any right of the tenant arising under subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(4) If the rental agreement is terminated, the landlord shall return any prepaid rent and any rental deposit, less any allowable deductions, recoverable by the tenant under section 76-1485.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 916, &#167; 49. </para></source></law></legaldoc>