  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1238"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1238</statuteno><catchline>Relocation assistance advisory services; available; when; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The head of any displacing agency shall ensure that the relocation assistance advisory services described in subsection (2) of this section are made available to all persons displaced by such agency. If the agency head determines that any person occupying property immediately adjacent to the property where the displacing activity occurs is caused substantial economic injury as a result of the activity, the agency head may make available to such person such advisory services.</para><para>(2) Each relocation assistance advisory program required by this section shall include such measures, facilities, or services as may be necessary or appropriate in order to:</para><para>(a) Determine and make timely recommendations on the needs and preferences, if any, of displaced persons for relocation assistance;</para><para>(b) Provide current and continuing information on the availability, sale prices, and rental charges of comparable replacement dwellings for displaced homeowners and tenants and suitable locations for businesses and farm operations;</para><para>(c) Assure that a person shall not be required to move from a dwelling unless the person has had a reasonable opportunity to relocate to a comparable replacement dwelling except in the case of (i) a major disaster as defined in section 102(2) of the Federal Disaster Relief Act of 1974, (ii) a national emergency declared by the President, or (iii) any other emergency which requires the person to move immediately from the dwelling because continued occupancy of the dwelling by such person constitutes a substantial danger to the health or safety of such person;</para><para>(d) Assist a person displaced from a business or farm operation in obtaining and becoming established in a suitable replacement location;</para><para>(e) Supply (i) information concerning other programs which might assist displaced persons and (ii) technical assistance to such persons in applying for assistance under such programs; and</para><para>(f) Provide other advisory services to displaced persons in order to minimize the hardships of adjusting to relocation.</para><para>(3) The head of a displacing agency shall coordinate the relocation assistance activities performed by such agency with other federal, state, or local governmental activities in the community which could affect the efficient and effective delivery of relocation assistance and related services.</para><para>(4) Notwithstanding section 76-1221, in any case in which a displacing agency acquires property for a program or project, any person who occupies such property on a rental basis after the property is acquired by the displacing agency or for a period subject to termination when the property is needed for the project shall be eligible for advisory services to the extent determined by the displacing agency in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the head of the lead agency which are consistent with regulations adopted and promulgated by the United States Department of Transportation under the Uniform Relocation Assistance and Real Property Acquisition Policies Act of 1970, Public Law 91-646, as amended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 254, &#167; 25. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 