<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1485"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1485</statuteno><catchline>Rental deposit; return; withholdings; considered abandoned property; when.</catchline><para>(1) A landlord shall, within fourteen days from the date of termination of the tenancy, return the rental deposit to the tenant or furnish to the tenant a written statement showing the specific reason for withholding all or any portion of the rental deposit. If no mailing address or delivery instructions are provided by the tenant to the landlord, the landlord shall mail, by first-class mail, the balance of the rental deposit to be returned, if any, and the written statement regarding any amounts withheld to the tenant's last-known mailing address. If the mailing is returned as undeliverable, or if the returned balance of the rental deposit remains outstanding for one year, it shall be considered abandoned property to be reported to the State Treasurer in accordance with the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act. The landlord may withhold from the rental deposit only such amounts as are reasonable:</para><para>(a) To remedy a tenant's default in the payment of rent or of other funds due to the landlord pursuant to the rental agreement; and</para><para>(b) To restore the mobile home space to its condition at the commencement of the tenancy, ordinary wear and tear excepted.</para><para>(2) In an action concerning the rental deposit, the burden of proving, by a preponderance of the evidence, the reason for withholding all or any portion of the rental deposit shall be on the landlord.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 916, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB320, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act,</emphasis> see section 69-1329.</para> </crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>