<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1014.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1014.01</statuteno><catchline>Trust deed; reconveyance required; when; failure to deliver; effect; damages.</catchline><para>When the obligation secured by any trust deed has been satisfied, the beneficiary shall, upon receipt of a written request by the trustor or the trustor's successor in interest or designated representative or by the holder of a junior trust deed or junior mortgage, deliver to the trustor or trustor's successor in interest or designated representative a reconveyance in recordable form duly executed by the trustee. The reconveyance may designate the grantee therein as the person or persons entitled thereto. The beneficiary under such trust deed shall, upon receipt of a written request, deliver to the trustor or his or her successor in interest, as directed in the written request, the trust deed and the note or other evidence of the obligation so satisfied. If a trustee fails or refuses to execute a reconveyance required by the beneficiary, the beneficiary shall appoint a successor trustee that will execute a reconveyance.</para><para>Any beneficiary who fails to deliver such a reconveyance within sixty days after receipt of such written request shall be liable to the trustor or his or her successor in interest, as the case may be, for five thousand dollars or actual damages resulting from such failure, whichever is greater. In any action against the beneficiary or trustee pursuant to this section, the court shall award, in addition to the foregoing amounts, court costs, including reasonable attorney's fees, and may further order the trustee to reconvey the property. Successor in interest of the trustor shall include the current owner of the property and shall also include the person issuing a payoff check in accordance with the terms of a payoff letter from a beneficiary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1275, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 396, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 218, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 