<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1305</statuteno><catchline>Offering or disposition; requirements; right to cancel; escrow.</catchline><para>Unless the retirement subdivision or community lands or the transaction is exempt by section 76-1304:</para><para>(1) No person may offer or dispose of any lot or unit in any retirement subdivision or community located in this state, nor offer or dispose in this state of any lot or unit in any retirement subdivision or community located outside this state prior to the time such subdivision or community is registered in the manner prescribed by sections 76-1301 to 76-1315;</para><para>(2) No person may dispose of any lot or unit in any retirement subdivision or community unless a current public-offering statement is delivered to the prospective purchaser and the prospective purchaser is afforded a reasonable opportunity, under no circumstances less than forty-eight hours, to examine the public-offering statement prior to the disposition;</para><para>(3) A purchaser shall have the right to cancel a contract for disposition within three business days after the date the contract is executed or within three business days after the delivery to the purchaser of the public-offering statement, whichever is later. The right to cancel may not be waived and any attempt to obtain such a waiver is unlawful and shall be considered a violation of sections 76-1301 to 76-1315. A purchaser may cancel the contract by hand delivering or mailing, postage prepaid, a written statement of cancellation to the developer. The cancellation shall be deemed effective upon mailing. Upon cancellation, the developer shall refund to the purchaser within thirty days after receipt of the cancellation notice all payments and other consideration given by the purchaser reduced by the proportion of any benefits the purchaser has actually received by agreement with the developer prior to the effective date of the cancellation. A developer and purchaser shall agree in writing on a specific value for each benefit received by the purchaser for purposes of this section; and</para><para>(4) If in any retirement subdivision or community a purchaser's lot or unit remains subject to any debts or liabilities of the developer or association in connection with the initial construction of the improvements to the retirement subdivision or community, the developer shall hold all payments from purchasers in escrow at a state or federally regulated financial institution located in this state until such time, not to exceed twenty-four months, that the public improvements serving the retirement subdivision or community are substantially completed and secured financing has been obtained by the developer or association (a) in an amount adequate to complete the improvements to the retirement subdivision or community as represented in the statement of record and (b) under such terms as are consistent with the budget stated in the public-offering statement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1311, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 61, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>