  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1722"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1722</statuteno><catchline>Effect of violation on rights of action; attorney's fees; violations; penalties; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) If a developer or any other person subject to the Nebraska Time-Share Act violates any provision thereof or any provision of the project instruments, any person or class of persons damaged or otherwise adversely affected by the violation shall have a claim for appropriate relief, which may be brought in the county where the cause of action or part of the cause of action arose. The court may render any contract entered into in this state in violation of the act void and unenforceable and any money paid under such contract, together with interest at the rate of six percent per annum, may be recovered from the date of such payment or such violation, whichever is later. The court may also award such person or class of persons reasonable attorney's fees.</para><para>(2)(a) Any developer or any other person subject to the act who offers or disposes of a time-share interval without having complied with the act or who violates any provision of the act shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(b) Any person acting as a sales agent without having first obtained a real estate broker or salesperson license shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Whenever, in the judgment of the commission, any person has engaged or is about to engage in any acts or practices which constitute or will constitute a violation of the act, the Attorney General may maintain an action in the name of the State of Nebraska, in the district court of the county wherein such violation or threatened violation occurred, to abate and temporarily and permanently enjoin such acts and practices and to enforce compliance with the provisions of the act. The plaintiff shall not be required to give any bond nor shall any court costs be adjudged against the plaintiff.</para><para>(4) The commission by and through its director may prefer a complaint for violation of the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 945, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 68, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 