<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1738"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1738</statuteno><catchline>Registration; exemptions; exception.</catchline><para>No registration with the commission shall be required in the case of:</para><para>(1) Any transfer of a time-share interval by any time-share interval owner other than the developer or his or her agent;</para><para>(2) Any disposition pursuant to court order;</para><para>(3) A disposition by a government or governmental agency;</para><para>(4) A disposition by foreclosure or deed in lieu of foreclosure;</para><para>(5) A disposition of a time-share interval in a time-share project situated wholly outside this state if all solicitations, negotiations, offerings, and contacts took place wholly outside this state and the contract was executed wholly outside this state;</para><para>(6) A gratuitous transfer of a time-share interval;</para><para>(7) Group reservations made for fifteen or more people as a single transaction between a hotel and travel agent or travel groups for hotel accommodations when deposits are made and held for more than three years in advance; or</para><para>(8) Any offering, other than through an individual while located in this state, of a time-share interval for a time-share project situated wholly outside this state if the offer states that the time-share interval is in compliance with the law of the jurisdiction in which the time-share interval is located.</para><para>A reservation pursuant to section 76-1727 may be taken as a result of an exempt offering if the time-share program is registered prior to entering into any binding agreement with a purchaser, unless otherwise provided by the Nebraska Time-Share Act. For the purposes of subdivision (5) of this section and the act, an exempt offer is an offering.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 945, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 68, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 