<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id340"><amendatorysection statutenumber="76-1431.01" chaptername="Real Property"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1431.01</statuteno><catchline>Tenant; victim of an act of domestic violence; release from rental agreement; conditions; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A tenant who is a victim of an act of domestic violence or whose household member is a victim of an act of domestic violence may obtain a release from a rental agreement if the tenant or household member has:</para><para>(a) Obtained a protective order, restraining order, or other similar relief which applies to the perpetrator of the act of domestic violence; or</para><para>(b) Obtained certification confirming domestic violence as set forth in subdivision (5)(a)(iii) of section 76-1431.</para><para>(2) To obtain a release from a rental agreement under this section, the tenant shall:</para><para>(a) Provide to the landlord a copy of the documentation described in subsection (1) of this section; and</para><para>(b) Provide to the landlord a written notice containing:</para><para>(i) The date on which the tenant wishes the release to be effective. Such date shall be at least fourteen days after the date the tenant provides the documentation and written notice and no more than thirty days after such date; and</para><para>(ii) The names of any household members to be released in addition to the tenant.</para><para>(3) The tenant shall remain liable for rent for the month in which the tenant terminated the rental agreement.</para><para>(4) A tenant and any household member who is released from a rental agreement pursuant to this section:</para><para>(a) Are not liable for rent or damages to the premises incurred after the release date; and</para><para>(b) Are not subject to any fee solely because of termination of the rental agreement.</para><para>(5) Other tenants who are parties to the rental agreement, other than household members of a tenant released under this section, are not released pursuant to this section from their obligations under the rental agreement or the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act.</para><para>(6) A tenant who is a perpetrator of an act of domestic violence may not obtain a release from a rental agreement under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB320, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>