<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1228"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1228</statuteno><catchline>Payment to displaced person; amount.</catchline>
<para>(1) Whenever
a program or project to be undertaken by a displacing agency will result in
the displacement of any person, the head of the displacing agency shall provide
for the payment to the displaced person of:</para>
<para>(a) Actual reasonable expenses in moving himself
or herself and his or her family, business, farm operation, or other personal
property;</para>
<para>(b) Actual direct losses of tangible personal
property as a result of moving or discontinuing a business or farm operation,
but not to exceed an amount equal to the reasonable expenses that would have
been required to relocate such property, as determined by the head of the
agency;</para>
<para>(c) Actual reasonable expenses in searching
for a replacement business or farm;
and</para>
<para>(d) Actual reasonable expenses necessary to
reestablish at its new site a displaced farm, nonprofit organization, or small
business as defined by criteria established by the lead agency which are consistent
with regulations adopted and promulgated by the United States Department of
Transportation under the Uniform Relocation Assistance and Real Property Acquisition
Policies Act of 1970, 42
U.S.C. 4601 et seq., as amended, but not to exceed ten thousand
dollars.</para>
<para>(2) The lead agency may
adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing a reasonable maximum
payment under subdivision (1)(c) of this section which are consistent with
regulations adopted by the United States Department of Transportation under
the Uniform Relocation Assistance and Real Property Acquisition Policies Act
of 1970, 42 U.S.C. 4601 et seq., as amended.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 254, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB167, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>