<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1231"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1231</statuteno><catchline>Owner; displacement from dwelling; additional payment; amount.</catchline><para>In addition to payments otherwise authorized by the Relocation Assistance Act, the head of the displacing agency shall make an additional payment not to exceed twenty-two thousand five hundred dollars to any displaced person who is displaced from a dwelling actually owned and occupied by such displaced person for at least one hundred and eighty days prior to the initiation of negotiations for the acquisition of the property. Such additional payment shall include the following elements:</para><para>(1) The amount, if any, which, when added to the acquisition cost of the dwelling acquired by the displacing agency, equals the reasonable cost of a comparable replacement dwelling;</para><para>(2) The amount, if any, which will compensate such displaced person for any increased interest costs and other debt service costs which such person is required to pay for financing the acquisition of any comparable replacement dwelling. Such amount shall be paid only if the dwelling acquired by the displacing agency was encumbered by a bona fide mortgage which was a valid lien on such dwelling for at least one hundred eighty days immediately prior to the initiation of negotiations for the acquisition of such dwelling;</para><para>(3) Reasonable expenses incurred by such displaced person for evidence of title, recording fees, and other closing costs incident to the purchase of the replacement dwelling but not including prepaid expenses; and</para><para>(4) The amount, if any, which will compensate such displaced person for the increase in property taxes resulting from the relocation for a period of three years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 254, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc>