<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1233</statuteno><catchline>Renter; displacement from dwelling; additional payment; requirements; use.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to amounts otherwise authorized by the Relocation Assistance Act, the head of a displacing agency shall make a payment to or for any displaced person displaced from any dwelling not eligible to receive a payment under section 76-1231 which dwelling was actually and lawfully occupied by such displaced person for at least ninety days immediately prior to (a) the initiation of negotiations for acquisition of such dwelling or (b) in any case in which displacement is not a direct result of acquisition, such other event as the head of the lead agency shall prescribe by rules and regulations which are consistent with regulations adopted and promulgated by the United States Department of Transportation under the Uniform Relocation Assistance and Real Property Acquisition Policies Act of 1970, Public Law 91-646, as amended. Such payment shall consist of the amount necessary to enable such person to lease or rent for a period not to exceed forty-two months a comparable replacement dwelling, but the payment shall not exceed five thousand two hundred fifty dollars. At the discretion of the head of the displacing agency, a payment under this subsection may be made in periodic installments. Computation of a payment under this subsection to a low-income displaced person for a comparable replacement dwelling shall take into account such person's income.</para><para>(2) Any person eligible for a payment under subsection (1) of this section may elect to apply such payment to a downpayment on and other incidental expenses pursuant to the purchase of a decent, safe, and sanitary replacement dwelling. Such person may, at the discretion of the head of the displacing agency, be eligible under this subsection for the maximum payment allowed under subsection (1) of this section, except that in the case of a displaced homeowner who has owned and occupied the displacement dwelling for at least ninety days but not more than one hundred eighty days immediately prior to the initiation of negotiations for the acquisition of such dwelling, such payment shall not exceed the payment such person would otherwise have received under section 76-1231 had the person owned and occupied the displacement dwelling one hundred eighty days immediately prior to the initiation of such negotiations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 254, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 