<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1734"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1734</statuteno><catchline>Application for registration; contents; fees; certificate of registration; report; investigation.</catchline><para>(1) An application for registration shall contain the public-offering statement, a brief description of the property, copies of time-share instruments, a certified, audited financial statement fully and fairly disclosing the current financial condition of the developer, and any documents referred to therein and such other information as may be required by the commission. In lieu of a certified, audited financial statement of the developer, the commission may accept a current audited consolidated financial statement which includes the financial condition of the developer and is accompanied by a statement from the developer's parent organization, in a form approved by the commission, that guarantees the developer's performance on any obligation under the Nebraska Time-Share Act or as contracted by the developer.</para><para>(2) Such application shall be accompanied by a filing fee of two hundred dollars plus five dollars for each twenty-five time-share intervals or portions thereof. If the application is approved, the commission shall issue a certificate of registration to the applicant. After issuance of a certificate, an annual fee of fifty dollars plus five dollars for each twenty-five time-share intervals or fraction thereof computed on the number of time-share intervals in the original application shall be due and payable on or before January 1 of each year. The annual fee for each time-share program shall not exceed one thousand five hundred dollars. Failure to remit annual fees when due shall automatically cancel the certificate, but otherwise such certificate shall remain in full force and effect if the commission determines from satisfactory investigation that such certificate should be renewed.</para><para>(3) Before issuing the renewal certificate each year, the certificate holder shall furnish to the commission, on or before January 1 of each year, an annual report of all purchases and reservations made by the developer or its agents to any person with a residence, primary place of business, or mailing address in this state and any other information requested by the commission. The annual report shall (a) include the amount of any deposit required to be made in connection with the purchase or reservation of a time-share interval from the developer and (b) cover the twelve-month period ending October 31 immediately preceding the annual report.</para><para>(4) The commission shall thoroughly investigate all matters relating to the application and may require a personal inspection of the real estate by a person or persons designated by it. All expenses incurred by the commission in investigating such real estate and the proposed sale thereof in this state shall be borne by the applicant and the commission shall require a deposit sufficient to cover such expenses prior to incurring such expenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 945, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 68, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 845, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>