<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1419"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1419</statuteno><catchline>Landlord to maintain fit premises.</catchline><para>(1) The landlord shall:</para><para>(a) Substantially comply, after written or actual notice, with the requirements of the applicable minimum housing codes materially affecting health and safety;</para><para>(b) Make all repairs and do whatever is necessary, after written or actual notice, to put and keep the premises in a fit and habitable condition;</para><para>(c) Keep all common areas of the premises in a clean and safe condition;</para><para>(d) Maintain in good and safe working order and condition all electrical, plumbing, sanitary, heating, ventilating, air conditioning, and other facilities and appliances, including elevators, supplied or required to be supplied by him or her;</para><para>(e) Provide and maintain appropriate receptacles and conveniences for the removal of ashes, garbage, rubbish, and other waste incidental to the occupancy of the dwelling unit and arrange for their removal from the appropriate receptacle; and</para><para>(f) Supply running water and reasonable amounts of hot water at all times and reasonable heat except where the building that includes the dwelling unit is not required by law to be equipped for that purpose, or the dwelling unit is so constructed that heat or hot water is generated by an installation within the exclusive control of the tenant and supplied by a direct public utility connection.</para><para>If there exists a minimum housing code applicable to the premises, the landlord's maximum duty under this section shall be determined by subdivision (1)(a) of this section. The obligations imposed by this section are not intended to change existing tort law in the state.</para><para>(2) The landlord and tenant of a single-family residence may agree that the tenant perform the landlord's duties specified in subdivisions (1)(e) and (1)(f) of this section and also specified repairs, maintenance tasks, alterations, and remodeling, but only if the transaction is in writing, for good consideration, entered into in good faith and not for the purpose of evading the obligations of the landlord.</para><para>(3) The landlord and tenant of a dwelling unit other than a single-family residence may agree that the tenant is to perform specified repairs, maintenance tasks, alterations, or remodeling only if:</para><para>(a) The agreement of the parties is entered into in good faith and not for the purpose of evading the obligations of the landlord and is set forth in a separate writing signed by the parties and supported by adequate consideration; and</para><para>(b) The agreement does not diminish or affect the obligation of the landlord to other tenants in the premises.</para><para>(4) Notwithstanding any provision of the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act, a landlord may employ a tenant to perform the obligations of the landlord.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 293, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 7, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>This section of the Uniform Residential Landlord Tenant Act does not change existing tort law. Tighe v. Cedar Lawn, Inc., 11 Neb. App. 250, 649 N.W.2d 520 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 