<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1416"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1416</statuteno><catchline>Security deposits; prepaid rent.</catchline><para>(1) A landlord may not demand or receive security, however denominated, in an amount or value in excess of one month's periodic rent, except that a pet deposit not in excess of one-fourth of one month's periodic rent may be demanded or received when appropriate, but this subsection shall not be applicable to housing agencies organized or existing under the Nebraska Housing Agency Act.</para><para>(2) Upon termination of the tenancy, property or money held by the landlord as prepaid rent and security may be applied to the payment of rent and the amount of damages which the landlord has suffered by reason of the tenant's noncompliance with the rental agreement or section 76-1421. The balance, if any, and a written itemization shall be delivered or mailed to the tenant within fourteen days after the date of termination of the tenancy. If no mailing address or instructions are provided by the tenant to the landlord, the landlord shall mail, by first-class mail, the balance of the security deposit to be returned, if any, and a written itemization of the amount of the security deposit not returned to the tenant's last-known mailing address. If the mailing is returned as undeliverable, or if the returned balance of the security deposit remains outstanding for one year, it shall be considered abandoned property to be reported and paid to the State Treasurer in accordance with the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act.</para><para>(3) If the landlord fails to comply with subsection (2) of this section, the tenant may recover the property and money due him or her, court costs, and reasonable attorney's fees. In addition, if the landlord's failure to comply with subsection (2) of this section is willful and not in good faith, the tenant may recover an amount equal to one month's periodic rent or two times the amount of the security deposit, whichever is less, as liquidated damages.</para><para>(4) This section does not preclude the landlord or tenant from recovering other damages to which he or she may be entitled under the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act. However, a tenant shall not be liable for damages directly related to the tenant's removal from the premises by order of any governmental entity as a result of the premises not being fit for habitation due to the negligence or neglect of the landlord.</para><para>(5) The holder of the landlord's interest in the premises at the time of the termination of the tenancy is bound by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 293, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 105, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 7, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB433, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB532, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Housing Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1572.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act,</emphasis> see section 69-1329.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The mandatory attorney fees provisions of the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act include fees for pro bono work. Black v. Brooks, 285 Neb. 440, 827 N.W.2d 256 (2013).</para><para>Where there is no written agreement obligating the client to pay an attorney fee award to the pro bono organization, the proper remedy to avoid a windfall to the prevailing party is to award the fee directly to the pro bono organization. Black v. Brooks, 285 Neb. 440, 827 N.W.2d 256 (2013).</para><para>The 14-day limitation language in subsection (2) of this section refers to the time allowed the landlord to return the deposit, not the time in which a demand must be made by the vacating tenant. Hilliard v. Robertson, 253 Neb. 232, 570 N.W.2d 180 (1997).</para><para>Under subsection (3) of this section, in order to recover a deposit plus an attorney fee, tenant must establish that landlord did not comply with a demand for return of the security deposit. Mason v. Schumacher, 231 Neb. 929, 439 N.W.2d 61 (1989).</para><para>Where a tenant prevails in an action under subsection (2) of this section against the tenant's landlord, the tenant is entitled to recover reasonable attorney fees under subsection (3) of this section as a matter of right; it is not at the discretion of the trial court. However, in order to recover fees under subsection (3) of this section, the tenant must present evidence of the tenant's attorney fees such that a trial court can make a meaningful award. Lomack v. Kohl-Watts, 13 Neb. App. 14, 688 N.W.2d 365 (2004).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>