<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1522"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1522</statuteno><catchline>Failure to report; false report; effect; Secretary of State; duties; reinstatement; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Failure to report the information required by section 76-1520 or the filing of false information shall be cause for dissolution or cancellation of registration of the corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, or limited liability company or revocation of authority to transact business in this state in the manner provided in this section.</para><para>(2) If the Secretary of State has reason to believe a corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, or limited liability company required to report pursuant to section 76-1520 has failed to report, or has filed a false or incomplete report, the Secretary of State shall send to the registered agent of such entity by certified mail a notice stating that if the defect is not corrected within sixty days after receipt of notice the entity shall be dissolved or its registration shall be canceled.</para><para>(3) If the Secretary of State determines that the entity has not corrected the defect upon the expiration of sixty days after notice of failure to report, false reporting, or incomplete reporting, the entity shall be dissolved or its registration canceled. Notice of such cancellation shall be sent by certified mail to the registered agent of the entity.</para><para>(4) A business entity dissolved or canceled pursuant to this section may have its existence reinstated at any time by submitting a report as required by sections 76-1520 to 76-1524 correcting the defect for which it was dissolved and paying a reinstatement fee of one hundred dollars to the Secretary of State. Any fees received pursuant to this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Corporation Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1193, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 