<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1906"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1906</statuteno><catchline>Redemption of redemptive homestead; when allowed.</catchline><para>(1) In an action against protected real estate for the foreclosure of any mortgage or trust deed described in section 76-1904 with respect to which no waiver or disclaimer of the right to make a designation of homestead has been made or is otherwise binding in accordance with section 76-1905, if any part of the homestead of the mortgagor or trustor is included in a decree directing a sale of the mortgaged premises or trust property, the mortgagor or trustor may request redemption of his or her redemptive homestead. Such request shall be made in a petition signed and sworn to by the mortgagor or trustor and filed in the foreclosure action not later than twenty days after entry of the decree of foreclosure.</para><para>(2) In any proceeding against protected real estate involving the exercise of a power of sale by a trustee under a trust deed described in section 76-1904 with respect to which no waiver or disclaimer of the right to make a designation of homestead has been made or is otherwise binding in accordance with section 76-1905, if any part of the homestead of the trustor is included in the notice of default filed in accordance with section 76-1006, the trustor may request redemption of his or her redemptive homestead. Such request shall be made in a petition signed and sworn to by the trustor and filed in the district court of the county where the trust property is located not later than two months following recordation of the notice of default.</para><para>(3) If protected real estate of a judgment debtor is subject to the lien of a judgment entered on or after November 21, 1986, and if no waiver or disclaimer of the right to make a designation of homestead is binding in accordance with section 76-1905, the judgment debtor may request redemption of his or her redemptive homestead. Such request shall be made in a petition signed and sworn to by the judgment debtor and filed in the district court of the county where the redemptive homestead is located not later than the date of the last publication of the notice required by section 25-1529.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, Third Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 43, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 