  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1520"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1520</statuteno><catchline>Interest in real estate used for farming or ranching; reports required.</catchline><para>(1) A person serving as the president, a general partner, any other officer, or an authorized representative of a corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, or limited liability company or a corporate trustee of a trust shall report to the Secretary of State:</para><para>(a) Any interest in real estate held by the corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or trust used for farming or ranching in this state as defined under Article XII, section 8, of the Constitution of Nebraska;</para><para>(b) Any activity or enterprise performed, conducted, or engaged in by the corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or trust defined as farming or ranching in this state under Article XII, section 8, of the Constitution of Nebraska; and</para><para>(c) Whether the corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or trust contracts with others engaged in farming or ranching for the care or production of agricultural commodities, including livestock.</para><para>(2) The reports required by this section shall be open to the public.</para><para>(3) For purposes of sections 76-1520 to 76-1524, interest in real estate used for farming or ranching includes legal, beneficial, and other interests, including interests held by a corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or trust in a general partnership holding real estate used for farming or ranching, but does not include an interest in real estate used for farming or ranching acquired by a corporation, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, or trust by process of law in the collection of debts or by any procedures for the creation or enforcement of a lien, encumbrance, or claim on the real estate, whether created by mortgage or otherwise.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1193, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 