<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1431"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1431</statuteno><catchline>Noncompliance; failure to pay rent; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act, if there is a noncompliance with section 76-1421 materially affecting health and safety or a material noncompliance by the tenant with the rental agreement or any separate agreement, the landlord may deliver a written notice to the tenant specifying the acts and omissions constituting the breach and that the rental agreement will terminate upon a date not less than thirty days after receipt of the notice if the breach is not remedied in fourteen days, and the rental agreement shall terminate as provided in the notice subject to the following. If the breach is remediable by repairs or the payment of damages or otherwise and the tenant adequately remedies the breach prior to the date specified in the notice, the rental agreement will not terminate. If substantially the same act or omission which constituted a prior noncompliance of which notice was given recurs within six months, the landlord may terminate the rental agreement upon at least fourteen days' written notice specifying the breach and the date of termination of the rental agreement.</para><para>(2) If rent is unpaid when due and the tenant fails to pay rent within three days after written notice by the landlord of nonpayment and his or her intention to terminate the rental agreement if the rent is not paid within that period of time, the landlord may terminate the rental agreement.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act, the landlord may recover damages and obtain injunctive relief for any noncompliance by the tenant with the rental agreement or section 76-1421. If the tenant's noncompliance is willful, the landlord may recover reasonable attorney's fees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 293, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 7, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 