  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1726"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1726</statuteno><catchline>Commission; notice of suspension; conditions; cease and desist order; revocation order.</catchline><para>(1) The commission, after notice and hearing, may issue a notice of suspension if any of the following conditions exist:</para><para>(a) Any representation in any document or information filed with the commission is false or misleading;</para><para>(b) Any developer or agent of the developer has engaged or is engaging in any unlawful act or practice;</para><para>(c) Any developer or agent of the developer has disseminated or caused to be disseminated orally or in writing any false or misleading promotional materials in connection with a time-share program;</para><para>(d) Any developer or agent of the developer has concealed, diverted, or disposed of any funds or assets of any person in a manner impairing rights of purchasers of time-share intervals in the time-share program;</para><para>(e) Any developer or agent of the developer has failed to perform any stipulation or agreement made to induce the commission to issue an order relating to the time-share program; or</para><para>(f) Any developer or agent of the developer has otherwise violated any provision of the Nebraska Time-Share Act or the commission's rules and regulations or orders.</para><para>(2) The commission may issue a cease and desist order if the developer has not registered the time-share program as required by the act.</para><para>(3) The commission, after notice and hearing, may issue an order revoking the registration of a time-share program upon determination that a developer or agent of the developer has failed to comply with a notice of suspension issued by the commission affecting the time-share program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 945, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 68, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 