 <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1909" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1909</statuteno><catchline>Redemption; payment by petitioner; failure to pay; effect; petitioner's equity; use; when allowed.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, an order confirming a requested homestead redemption shall direct the petitioner to pay into the court not later than ten days from the entry of such order a cash amount equal to the current market value of the redemptive homestead as found and determined by the court in its confirmation order. If the petitioner fails to make such payment, the court shall, upon its own motion or the motion of any party to the action, vacate the confirmation order, and all of the protected real estate shall then be subject to sale as provided by law, free of any redemptive or other right of the petitioner otherwise existing under the Farm Homestead Protection Act. The filing of a petition requesting redemption on the basis of the payment of a cash amount equal to the current market value of the redemptive homestead shall not constitute a waiver of any stay in effect or available to the petitioner under section 25-1506.</para><para>(2) Redemption based upon the petitioner's equity in the protected real estate shall be permitted when requested in the prayer of the petition and when the court specifically finds and determines in its confirmation order that the sum of all liens upon the protected real estate is equal to eighty-five percent or less of the current market value of that portion of the protected real estate exclusive of the redemptive homestead. If the court finds that the petitioner has sufficient equity as required by this subsection, the payment otherwise required by subsection (1) of this section shall be waived by the court in its order confirming the redemption. The filing of a petition requesting redemption on the basis of the petitioner's equity in the protected real estate as provided in this subsection shall constitute a waiver of any stay in effect or available to the petitioner under section 25-1506.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, Third Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc>