<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1904</statuteno><catchline>Mortgage or trust deed; designation of homestead; waiver or disclaimer; reservation of right to designate.</catchline><para>(1) In any mortgage or trust deed executed on or after November 21, 1986, upon agricultural land, the mortgagor or trustor may make a designation of homestead in the body of such mortgage or trust deed.</para><para>(2) In any mortgage or trust deed executed on or after November 21, 1986, upon agricultural land, if no (a) designation of homestead is made pursuant to subsection (1) of this section or (b) waiver or disclaimer given in accordance with subsection (3) of this section, such mortgage or trust deed shall be construed as affording to the mortgagor or trustor a reservation of right to defer his or her designation of homestead until such time as a decree of foreclosure is entered upon such mortgage or trust deed or a trustee's notice of default is filed for record pursuant to section 76-1006.</para><para>(3)(a) On or after November 21, 1986, prior to the execution of any mortgage or trust deed upon agricultural land, the mortgagor or trustor may disclaim in writing his or her right to make a designation of homestead. The disclaimer shall contain a statement by the mortgagor or trustor that no part of his or her homestead is presently or in the future will be situated upon the real estate described in the mortgage or trust deed and that the mortgagor or trustor understands that if he or she establishes a homestead on any part of the real estate during the time the mortgage or trust deed remains unsatisfied and a lien upon the real estate, there shall be no right to make a designation of homestead in the event of a foreclosure or trustee's sale upon such mortgage or trust deed. Such written disclaimer shall be set forth as a preface to the mortgage or trust deed and shall be filed for record as a part of the mortgage or trust deed in the office of the register of deeds. Failure by the mortgagee or trustee to file a written disclaimer as provided in this subdivision shall nullify any purported disclaimer by the mortgagor or trustor of his or her right to make a designation of homestead.</para><para>(b) On and after November 21, 1986, prior to the execution of any mortgage or trust deed upon agricultural land, the mortgagor or trustor may waive by written acknowledgment his or her right to make a designation of homestead. The written acknowledgment shall contain a statement that the mortgagor or trustor understands that he or she has the right to make a designation of homestead in the mortgage or trust deed and the execution of such acknowledgment constitutes the waiver of rights otherwise available for the purpose of affording the mortgagor or trustor the opportunity to retain his or her homestead in the event of a default upon such mortgage or trust deed. Such written acknowledgment shall be set forth as a preface to the mortgage or trust deed and shall be filed for record as a part of the mortgage or trust deed in the office of the register of deeds. Failure by the mortgagee or trustee to file a written acknowledgment as provided in this subdivision shall nullify any purported waiver by the mortgagor or trustor of his or her right to make a designation of homestead.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, Third Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>