<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1307"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1307</statuteno><catchline>Public-offering statement; contents.</catchline><para>(1) A public-offering statement shall disclose fully and accurately the physical characteristics of the retirement subdivision or community. The proposed public-offering statement submitted to the agency shall be in a form prescribed by its rules and shall as a minimum include the following:</para><para>(a) The name and principal address of the developer;</para><para>(b) A general description of the retirement subdivision or community stating the total number of lots, parcels, units, or interests in the offering;</para><para>(c) The significant terms of any encumbrances, easements, liens, and restrictions, including zoning and other regulations affecting such lands and each unit or lot, and a statement of all existing taxes and existing or proposed special taxes or assessments which affect such lands;</para><para>(d) A statement of the use for which the property is offered;</para><para>(e) Information concerning improvements, including hospitals, health and recreational facilities of any kind, streets, water supply, levees, drainage control systems, irrigation systems, sewage disposal facilities and customary utilities, and the estimated cost, date of completion, and responsibility for construction and maintenance of existing and proposed improvements which are referred to in connection with the offering or disposition of any interest in the retirement subdivision or community;</para><para>(f) A statement that audited financial statements or prospective financial statements, or both if applicable, for the developer and any association are on file with the agency;</para><para>(g) A statement, if applicable, of the association's ability to incur debt secured by a lot or unit after it has been disposed of to a purchaser;</para><para>(h) A statement, if applicable, of any affiliation of the association or developer with a for-profit or nonprofit organization and the nature of the affiliation and the extent to which the affiliate organization is responsible for the financial and contractual obligations of the association;</para><para>(i) A statement, if applicable, of the policy of the association with regard to any health or financial conditions upon which the association may require a purchaser to relinquish occupancy of a lot or unit;</para><para>(j) If a purchaser will be required to pay a periodic payment that is subject to change by the association for the purpose of expenses and liabilities of the association, a detailed current budget or projected budget of the expenses and liabilities of the association, the assumptions upon which the budget or expected budget is based, including the number of units or lots assumed under the budget to be paying such periodic payments, and if any secured debt, the effect on monthly payments if less than the assumed number of units or lots are disposed of to purchasers;</para><para>(k) A description of the insurance coverage or a statement that there is no insurance coverage provided for the benefit of the retirement subdivision or community;</para><para>(l) A statement describing the purchaser's cancellation rights; and</para><para>(m) Additional information required by the agency to assure full and fair disclosure to prospective purchasers.</para><para>(2) The public-offering statement shall not be used for any promotional purposes before registration of the retirement subdivision or community and afterwards only if it is used in its entirety. No person may advertise or represent that the agency approves or recommends the retirement subdivision or community lands or disposition thereof. No portion of the public-offering statement may be underscored, italicized, or printed in larger or heavier or different color type than the remainder of the statement unless the agency requires or permits it.</para><para>(3) The agency may require the developer to alter or amend the proposed public-offering statement in order to assure full and fair disclosure to prospective purchasers, and no change in the plan of disposition or development of the retirement subdivision or community may be made after registration without notifying the agency and without making an appropriate amendment to the public-offering statement. A public-offering statement is not current unless all amendments are incorporated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1311, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 61, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 