<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-1902" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-1902</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in the Farm Homestead Protection Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Designation of homestead shall mean a sworn written statement by an individual mortgagor, trustor, or judgment debtor which describes his or her homestead, executed on or after November 21, 1986. Such statement shall include a legal description of the homestead. If only a portion of the homestead will be encumbered by the mortgage, trust deed, or judgment lien with respect to which a designation is made, then such portion so encumbered shall also be identified by proper legal description. If the homestead or the encumbered portion of the homestead is not separately described in its entirety in the mortgage or trust deed with respect to which a designation is made, or cannot be accurately described as a fractional part of a section, the designation shall be accompanied by a survey which includes a metes and bounds description with reference to established datum. The survey and description shall be prepared by and bear the signature and seal of a professional land surveyor. The designation shall include statements by the individual mortgagor, trustor, or judgment debtor that (a) he or she resides in a dwelling house located upon the homestead, (b) all appurtenances to such dwelling and an adequate supply of potable water and an adequate system of sewage disposal exist upon the homestead, (c) both the water supply and sewage disposal system are located entirely upon the homestead and neither will require access to or an easement across any part of the nondesignated agricultural land encumbered by such mortgage or trust deed, (d) both the homestead and the nonhomestead real estate encumbered by such mortgage or trust deed have existing legal access to a public roadway, and (e) provide a complete listing of all structures and other improvements situated on the portion of the homestead so encumbered, together with a representation that such structures and improvements are within the homestead boundary and do not encroach upon any of the nonhomestead real estate encumbered by such mortgage or trust deed;</para><para>(2) Agricultural land shall mean a parcel of land larger than twenty acres not located in any incorporated city or village which is owned by an individual and used in farming operations carried on by the owner at any time within the preceding three-year period for the production of farm products as defined in section 9-102, Uniform Commercial Code. Agricultural land shall include wasteland lying within or contiguous to and in common individual ownership with land used in farming operations for the production of farm products;</para><para>(3) Homestead shall mean a parcel of agricultural land encumbered in whole or in part by the lien of a mortgage, trust deed, or judgment, for which a designation of homestead has been made pursuant to the Farm Homestead Protection Act, and which possesses all of the attributes legally requisite to its selection by the mortgagor, trustor, or judgment debtor as his or her homestead under Chapter 40, except that the value limitation of section 40-101 shall not be construed to limit or impede any such designation;</para><para>(4) Protected real estate shall mean agricultural land which is encumbered by the lien of a judgment entered or a mortgage or trust deed executed on or after November 21, 1986, which lien is of a first and paramount priority over any other lien except a tax lien; and</para><para>(5) Redemptive homestead shall mean that portion of any protected real estate for which an owner has made a designation of homestead as provided in the Farm Homestead Protection Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, Third Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB102, &#167; 10. </para><operativedate>September 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>