<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" id="id00" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" statutenumber="76-2227.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2227.01</statuteno><catchline>Real property associate; applicant; qualifications; fingerprints; national criminal history record check; scope of practice; limit on activities.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify for a credential as a real property associate, an applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Be at least nineteen years of age;</para><para>(b)(i)(A) Hold a high school diploma or a certificate of high school equivalency or have education acceptable to the Real Property Appraiser Board; and</para><para>(B) Have successfully completed and passed examination for no fewer than ninety class hours in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education courses as prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board and complete the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course. The fifteen-hour course shall be taught by a Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Instructor who is certified by the Appraiser Qualifications Board and who is a state-certified appraiser in good standing. The qualifying education courses shall be conducted by an accredited degree-awarding community college, college, or university, an appraisal society, institute, or association, a state or federal agency or commission, a proprietary school, or such other education provider as may be approved by the Real Property Appraiser Board, and shall be, at a minimum, fifteen class hours in length. Each course shall be conducted in a classroom and not online or by correspondence. Each course shall include an examination pertinent to the material presented; or</para><para>(ii) Hold a bachelor's degree or higher in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university that has had all or part of its curriculum approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as required core curriculum. If the degree in real estate as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board does not satisfy all required qualifying education for credentialing, the remaining class hours shall be completed in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(i)(B) of this section; and</para><para>(c) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the Real Property Appraiser Board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the Real Property Appraiser Board.</para><para>(2) The scope of practice of a real property associate shall be limited to valuation services not requiring a credential as a trainee real property appraiser, licensed residential real property appraiser, certified residential real property appraiser, or certified general real property appraiser under the Real Property Appraiser Act.</para><para>(3) A real property associate shall not advertise or hold himself or herself out to the general public as a real property appraiser.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB731, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>April 7, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>