<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id101" statutenumber="76-2228.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2228.01</statuteno><catchline id="id104">Trainee real property appraiser; applicant; qualifications; fingerprints; national criminal history record check; upgraded credential; requirements; scope of practice.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify for a credential as a trainee real property appraiser, an applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Be at least nineteen years of age;</para><para>(b)(i)(A) If submitting an application on or before December 31, 2025, have successfully completed and passed examination for no fewer than seventy-five class hours in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board. Each course shall include a proctored, closed-book examination pertinent to the material presented. Except for the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course, which shall be completed within the two-year period immediately preceding submission of the application, all class hours shall be completed within the five-year period immediately preceding submission of the application; or</para><para>(B) If submitting an application after December 31, 2025, have successfully completed and passed examination for no fewer than eighty-three class hours in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board. Each course shall include a proctored, closed-book examination pertinent to the material presented. Except for the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course, which shall be completed within the two-year period immediately preceding submission of the application, all class hours shall be completed within the five-year period immediately preceding submission of the application; or</para><para>(ii) Hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university that has had all or part of its curriculum approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as required core curriculum or the equivalent as determined by the Appraiser Qualifications Board. The degree shall be conferred within the five-year period immediately preceding submission of the application. If the degree in real estate or equivalent as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board does not satisfy all required qualifying education for credentialing, the remaining class hours shall be completed in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education pursuant to subdivision (b)(i) of this subsection;</para><para>(c) As prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board, successfully complete a Real Property Appraiser Board-approved supervisory real property appraiser and trainee course within one year immediately preceding the date of application; and</para><para>(d) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the Real Property Appraiser Board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the Real Property Appraiser Board.</para><para>(2) Prior to engaging in real property appraisal practice, a trainee real property appraiser shall submit a written request for supervisory real property appraiser approval on a form approved by the board. The request for supervisory real property appraiser approval may be made at the time of application or any time after approval as a trainee real property appraiser.</para><para>(3) To qualify for an upgraded credential, a trainee real property appraiser shall satisfy the appropriate requirements as follows:</para><para>(a) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the Real Property Appraiser Board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the Real Property Appraiser Board; and</para><para>(b) Within the twenty-four months following approval of the applicant's education and experience by the Real Property Appraiser Board for an upgraded credential, pass an appropriate examination approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board for that upgraded credential, prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board, and administered by a contracted testing service. Successful completion of examination shall be valid for twenty-four months.</para><para>(4) To qualify for a credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser, a trainee real property appraiser shall:</para><para>(a) Successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than seventy-five additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(ii) of section 76-2230; and</para><para>(b) Meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(c) of section 76-2230.</para><para>(5) To qualify for a credential as a certified residential real property appraiser, a trainee real property appraiser shall:</para><para>(a) Meet the postsecondary educational requirements pursuant to subdivisions (1)(b) and (c) of section 76-2231.01;</para><para>(b)(i) If submitting an application on or before December 31, 2025, successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than one hundred twenty-five additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(d)(ii) of section 76-2231.01; or</para><para>(ii) If submitting an application after December 31, 2025, successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than one hundred seventeen additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(d)(ii) of section 76-2231.01; and</para><para>(c) Meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(e) of section 76-2231.01.</para><para>(6) To qualify for a credential as a certified general real property appraiser, a trainee real property appraiser shall:</para><para>(a) Meet the postsecondary educational requirements pursuant to subdivisions (1)(b) and (c) of section 76-2232;</para><para>(b)(i) If submitting an application on or before December 31, 2025, successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than two hundred twenty-five additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(d)(ii) of section 76-2232; or</para><para>(ii) If submitting an application after December 31, 2025, successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than two hundred seventeen additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(d)(ii) of section 76-2232; and</para><para>(c) Meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(e) of section 76-2232.</para><para>(7) The scope of real property appraisal practice for the trainee real property appraiser shall be limited to real property appraisal practice assignments that the supervisory certified real property appraiser is permitted to engage in by his or her current credential and that the supervisory real property appraiser is competent to engage in.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB714, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB731, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB77, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB23, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB992, &#167; 8. </para><effectivedate>March 13, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>