<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id00" renumber="yes"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id322" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2233.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2233.02</statuteno><catchline id="id325">Credential; expiration; renewal; fees; random fingerprint audit program.</catchline><para>(1) A credential issued under the Real Property Appraiser Act other than a temporary credential shall remain in effect until December 31 of the designated year unless surrendered, revoked, suspended, or canceled prior to such date. To renew a valid credential, the credential holder shall file an application on a form approved by the board and pay the appropriate renewal fee in an amount established by the board pursuant to section 76-2241. The credential holder shall also pay the criminal history record check fee in an amount established by the board pursuant to section 76-2241 for maintenance of the random fingerprint audit program to the board not later than November 30 of the designated year. A credential may be renewed for one year or two years. In every second year of the two-year continuing education period, as specified in section 76-2236, evidence of completion of continuing education requirements shall accompany renewal application or be on file with the board prior to renewal.</para><para>(2) The board shall establish a number of credential holders to be selected at random to submit, along with the application for renewal, two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the board.</para><para>(3) If a credential holder fails to apply and meet the requirements for renewal by November 30 of the designated year, such credential holder may obtain a renewal of such credential by satisfying all of the requirements for renewal and paying the appropriate late processing fee in an amount established by the board pursuant to section 76-2241 if such late renewal takes place prior to July 1 of the following year. A credential holder selected at random to submit fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprints that has applied and met all other requirements for renewal prior to November 30 of the designated year shall not pay a late processing fee if fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprints are received prior to November 30 of the designated year. If a credential holder that first obtained his or her credential at the current level on or after November 1 fails to apply and meet the requirements for renewal by December 31 of the designated year, such credential holder may obtain a renewal of such credential by satisfying all the requirements for renewal and paying a late processing fee if such late renewal takes place prior to July 1 of the following year. The board may refuse to renew any credential if the credential holder has continued to perform real property appraisal activities or other related activities in this state following the expiration of his or her credential. If a credential is not renewed prior to July 1, a credential holder shall reapply for credentialing and meet the current requirements in place at the time of application, except as provided in section 76-2233.03.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 54. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>