<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id377" statutenumber="76-2241"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2241</statuteno><catchline id="id380">Fees.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall charge and collect appropriate fees for its services under the Real Property Appraiser Act as follows:</para><para>(a) A credential application fee of no more than two hundred dollars;</para><para>(b) An examination fee of no more than three hundred dollars. The board may direct applicants to pay the fee directly to a third party who has contracted to administer the examination;</para><para>(c) An initial and renewal credentialing fee, other than temporary credentialing, of no more than three hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(d) A late processing fee of no more than twenty-five dollars for each month or portion of a month the fee is late;</para><para>(e) A temporary credential application fee for a licensed residential real property appraiser, a certified residential real property appraiser, or a certified general real property appraiser of no more than one hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(f) A temporary credentialing fee of no more than one hundred dollars for a licensed residential real property appraiser, certified residential real property appraiser, or certified general real property appraiser holding a temporary credential under the act;</para><para>(g) An inactive credential application fee of no more than one hundred dollars;</para><para>(h) An inactive credentialing fee of no more than three hundred dollars;</para><para>(i) A duplicate proof of credentialing fee of no more than twenty-five dollars;</para><para>(j) A certificate of good standing fee of no more than ten dollars; and</para><para>(k) A criminal history record check fee of no more than one hundred dollars.</para><para>(2) All fees for credentialing through reciprocity shall be the same as those paid by others pursuant to this section.</para><para>(3) In addition to the fees set forth in this section, the board may collect and transmit to the appropriate federal authority any fees established under the provisions of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989. The board may establish such fees as it deems appropriate for special examinations and other services provided by the board.</para><para>(4) All fees and other revenue collected pursuant to the Real Property Appraiser Act shall be remitted by the board to the State Treasurer for credit to the Real Property Appraiser Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB714, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB731, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB992, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>