<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id96"><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Real Property" id="id98"  statutenumber="76-2807"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2807</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of satisfaction; recording; effect; wrongful recording; remedy; liability; designation of authority; recording.</catchline><para>(1) A certificate of satisfaction complying with the Nebraska Security Instrument Satisfaction Act is evidence of the facts contained in it, shall be accepted for recording in the county in which the security instrument is recorded, and, upon recording, operates as a satisfaction of the security interest described in the certificate of satisfaction. If a security instrument is recorded in more than one county and a certificate of satisfaction is recorded in one of them, a certified copy of the certificate of satisfaction may be recorded in another county with the same effect as the original.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, in addition to any other remedy provided by law, a closing agent wrongfully or erroneously recording a certificate of satisfaction under this section shall be liable to the secured creditor for actual damages caused by the recording of the certificate of satisfaction and reasonable attorney's fees and costs.</para><para>(b) A closing agent that records a certificate of satisfaction of a security instrument wrongfully or erroneously is not liable if the closing agent complied in good faith with the act.</para><para>(c) If a certificate of satisfaction is executed and recorded by a title insurance agent pursuant to a designation of authority, the title insurer making such designation shall be liable to a secured creditor for the wrongful or erroneous recording of the certificate of satisfaction by such designee, to the same extent as provided under subdivisions (a) and (b) of this subsection.</para><para>(d) A single designation of authority may be recorded in the office of the register of deeds in any county in which a certificate of satisfaction may be recorded. The register of deeds shall record such designation of authority upon payment of the required fees. When the designation of authority is recorded, the register of deeds shall index such instrument under the name of the title insurance agent designated in the instrument in the manner provided for miscellaneous instruments relating to real estate. A separate designation of authority shall not be necessary for each certificate of satisfaction. Such authority shall continue until a revocation of the designation of authority is recorded in the county where the designation of authority was recorded.</para><para>(3) The recording of a certificate of satisfaction does not itself extinguish the liability of any person liable for payment of the underlying obligation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB386, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 