<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id00" statutenumber="76-2218"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2218</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Two-year continuing education period, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) through (6) of this section, two-year continuing education period means the period of twenty-four months commencing on January 1 and completed on December 31 of the following year.</para><para>(2) For a new real property appraiser credentialed prior to July 1 pursuant to section 76-2228.01, 76-2230, 76-2231.01, or 76-2232, two-year continuing education period means the period commencing on the date of initial credentialing and completed on December 31 of the following year.</para><para>(3) For a new real property appraiser credentialed on or after July 1 pursuant to section 76-2228.01, 76-2230, 76-2231.01, or 76-2232, two-year continuing education period means the period of twenty-four months commencing on January 1 of the year following the date of initial credentialing.</para><para>(4) For a new real property appraiser credentialed pursuant to section 76-2233 who held a valid credential of the same class to engage in real property appraisal practice under the laws of another jurisdiction on January 1 of the year in which the credential was issued by the board, two-year continuing education period means the period of twenty-four months commencing on January 1 of the year in which the credential was issued by the board.</para><para>(5) For a new real property appraiser credentialed pursuant to section 76-2233 who (a) did not hold a valid credential of the same class to engage in real property appraisal practice under the laws of another jurisdiction on January 1 of the year in which the credential was issued by the board and (b) was credentialed pursuant to section 76-2233 prior to July 1, two-year continuing education period means the period commencing on the date of initial credentialing and completed on December 31 of the following year.</para><para>(6) For a new real property appraiser credentialed pursuant to section 76-2233 who (a) did not hold a valid credential of the same class to engage in real property appraisal practice under the laws of another jurisdiction on January 1 of the year in which the credential was issued by the board and (b) was credentialed pursuant to section 76-2233 on or after July 1, two-year continuing education period means the period of twenty-four months commencing on January 1 of the year following the date of initial credentialing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB707, &#167; 52. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>