<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2321"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2321</statuteno><catchline>Excavation; notice; contents; commencement.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not commence any excavation without first giving notice to every operator. An excavator's notice to the center shall be deemed notice to all operators. An excavator's notice to operators shall be ineffective for purposes of this subsection unless given to the center. Notice to the center shall be given at least two full business days, but no more than ten business days, before commencing the excavation, except notice may be given more than ten business days in advance when the excavation is a road construction, widening, repair, or grading project provided for in sections 70-311 to 70-313 and 86-708 to 86-710. An excavator may commence work before the elapse of two full business days when (a) notice to the center has been given as provided by this subsection and (b) all the affected operators have notified the excavator that the location of all the affected operator's underground facilities have been marked or that the operators have no underground facilities in the location of the proposed excavation.</para><para>(2) The notice required pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall include (a) the name and telephone number of the person making the notification, (b) the name, address, and telephone number of the excavator, (c) the location of the area of the proposed excavation, including the range, township, section, and quarter section, unless the area is within the corporate limits of a city or village, in which case the location may be by street address, (d) the date and time excavation is scheduled to commence, (e) the depth of excavation, (f) the type and extent of excavation being planned, including whether the excavation involves tunneling or horizontal boring, and (g) whether the use of explosives is anticipated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 421, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 496.</para></source><annotation><para>The exception to the notice requirement in subsection (1) of this section applies only to certain "road construction, widening, repair, or grading project" undertaken by counties and townships, and does not apply to state road construction projects. Galaxy Telecom v. J.P. Theisen &amp; Sons, 265 Neb. 270, 656 N.W.2d 444 (2003).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 