<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2239" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2239</statuteno><catchline>Investigations; authorized; disciplinary action; complaint; procedure; hearing.</catchline><para>The board may, upon its own motion, and shall, upon the written complaint of any aggrieved person, cause an investigation to be made with respect to an alleged violation of the Real Property Appraiser Act by any credential holder or applicant for credentialing under the act. The board may revoke or suspend the credential or otherwise discipline a credential holder or deny any application for any of the acts or omissions set forth in section 76-2238. Violation of the act or the rules and regulations during a period of probation shall cause immediate execution of a suspension penalty. Upon receipt of information indicating that a credential holder may have violated any provision of the act, the board shall make an investigation of the facts to determine whether or not there is evidence of a violation. If technical assistance is required, the board may contract with or use qualified individuals or companies.</para><para>If an investigation indicates that a credential holder may have violated a provision of the act, the board may offer the credential holder an opportunity to voluntarily and informally discuss the alleged violation before the board. The board may enter into consent agreements or negotiate settlements. If an investigation indicates that a credential holder has violated a provision of the act, a formal complaint shall be prepared by the board and served upon the credential holder. The complaint shall require the credential holder to file an answer within thirty days of the date of service. In responding to a complaint, the credential holder may admit the allegations of the complaint, deny the allegations of the complaint, or plead otherwise. Failure to make a timely response shall be deemed an admission of the allegations of the complaint. Upon receipt of an answer to the complaint, the director or chairperson of the board shall set a date, time, and place for an administrative hearing on the complaint. The date of the hearing shall not be less than thirty nor more than one hundred twenty days from the date that the answer is filed unless such date is extended for good cause.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 61. </para></source></law></legaldoc>