<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2422"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2422</statuteno><catchline>Written agreements for brokerage
services; when required.</catchline><para>(1) All written agreements for brokerage
services on behalf of a seller, landlord, buyer, or tenant shall be entered
into by the designated broker on behalf of that broker and affiliated licensees,
except that the designated broker may authorize affiliated licensees in writing
to enter into the written agreements on behalf of the designated broker. A
copy of a written agreement for brokerage services shall be left with the
client or clients.</para>
<para>(2) Before engaging in any of the activities enumerated in subdivision
(2) of section 81-885.01, a designated broker intending to establish a single
agency relationship with a seller or landlord shall enter into a written agency
agreement with the party to be represented. Except as provided in section 76-2422.01,
the agreement shall include a licensee's duties and responsibilities
specified in section 76-2417, the terms of compensation, a fixed date of expiration
of the agreement, and whether an offer of subagency may be made to any other
designated broker, except that if a licensee is a limited seller's agent for
a builder, the terms of compensation may be established for a specific new
construction property on or before the builder's acceptance of a contract
to sell.</para>
<para>(3) Before or while engaging in any of the acts enumerated in subdivision
(2) of section 81-885.01, a designated broker acting as a single agent for
a buyer or tenant may enter into a written agency agreement with the party
to be represented. The agreement shall include a licensee's duties and responsibilities
specified in section 76-2418, the terms of compensation, a fixed date of expiration
of the agreement, and whether an offer of subagency may be made to any other
designated broker.</para>
<para>(4) Before engaging in any of the activities enumerated in subdivision
(2) of section 81-885.01, a designated broker intending to act as a dual agent
shall obtain the written consent of the seller and buyer or landlord and tenant
permitting the designated broker to serve as a dual agent. The consent shall
include a licensee's duties and responsibilities specified in section 76-2419.
The requirements of this subsection are met as to a seller or landlord if
the written agreement entered into with the seller or landlord complies with
this subsection. The requirements of this subsection are met as to a buyer
or tenant if a consent or buyer's or tenant's agency agreement is signed by
a potential buyer or tenant which complies with this subsection. The consent
of the buyer or tenant does not need to refer to a specific property and may
refer generally to all properties for which the buyer's or tenant's agent
may also be acting as a seller's or landlord's agent and would be a dual agent.
If a licensee is acting as a dual agent with regard to a specific property,
the seller and buyer or landlord and tenant shall confirm in writing the dual-agency
status and the party or parties responsible for paying any compensation prior
to or at the time a contract to purchase property or a lease or letter of
intent to lease is entered into for the specific property.</para>
<para>(5) Before engaging in any of the activities enumerated in subdivision
(2) of section 81-885.01, a designated broker intending to act as a subagent
shall enter into a written contract with the primary designated broker for
the client. If a designated broker has made a unilateral offer of subagency,
another designated broker can enter into the subagency relationship by the
act of disclosing to the customer that he or she is a subagent of the client.</para>
<para>(6) Before engaging in any of the activities enumerated in subdivision
(2) of section 81-885.01, a designated broker who intends to establish an
agency relationship with any party or parties to a transaction in which the
designated broker's duties and responsibilities exceed those contained in
sections 76-2417 and 76-2418 shall enter into a written agency agreement with
a party or parties to the transaction to perform services on their behalf.
The agreement shall specify the agent's duties and responsibilities, including
any duty of confidentiality, and the terms of compensation. Any agreement
under this subsection shall be subject to the common-law requirements of agency
applicable to real estate licensees.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 883, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 863, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 88, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB25, &#167; 9.</para></source><annotation><para>One of the enumerated activities covered by subsection (6) of this section is the exchange of property, based on the plain language of section 81-885.01(2). McCully, Inc. v. Baccaro Ranch, 279 Neb. 443, 778 N.W.2d 115 (2010).</para><para>This section does not act as a statute of frauds. McCully, Inc. v. Baccaro Ranch, 279 Neb. 443, 778 N.W.2d 115 (2010).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
