<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id00" renumber="yes"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id149" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2236.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2236.01</statuteno><catchline id="id152">Use of titles; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1)(a) No person other than a real property associate shall assume or use the title real property associate or any title, designation, or abbreviation likely to create the impression of credentialing as a real property associate by this state.</para><para>(b) No person other than a licensed residential real property appraiser shall assume or use the title licensed residential real property appraiser or any title, designation, or abbreviation likely to create the impression of credentialing as a licensed residential real property appraiser by this state.</para><para>(c) No person other than a certified residential real property appraiser shall assume or use the title certified residential real property appraiser or any title, designation, or abbreviation likely to create the impression of credentialing as a certified residential real property appraiser by this state.</para><para>(d) No person other than a certified general real property appraiser shall assume or use the title certified general real property appraiser or any title, designation, or abbreviation likely to create the impression of credentialing as a certified general real property appraiser by this state.</para><para>(e) No person other than a trainee real property appraiser shall assume or use the title trainee real property appraiser or any title, designation, or abbreviation likely to create the impression of credentialing as a trainee real property appraiser by this state.</para><para>(2) A real property appraiser shall state whether he or she is a licensed residential real property appraiser, certified residential real property appraiser, certified general real property appraiser, or trainee real property appraiser and include his or her board-issued credential number whenever he or she identifies himself or herself as a real property appraiser, including on all reports which are signed individually or as cosigner.</para><para>(3) The terms real property associate, licensed residential real property appraiser, certified residential real property appraiser, certified general real property appraiser, and trainee real property appraiser may only be used to refer to a person who is credentialed as such under the Real Property Appraiser Act and may not be used following or immediately in connection with the name or signature of a corporation, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability company, firm, or group or in such manner that it might be interpreted as referring to a corporation, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability company, firm, or group or to anyone other than the credential holder. This subsection shall not be construed to prevent a credential holder from signing a report on behalf of a corporation, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability company, firm, or group if it is clear that only the person holds the credential and that the corporation, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability company, firm, or group does not.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 491; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2014, &#167; 76-2229; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 57. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>