<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id176" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2223"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2223</statuteno><catchline id="id179">Real Property Appraiser
Board; powers and duties; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The
Real Property Appraiser Board shall administer and enforce the Real Property
Appraiser Act and may:</para>
<para>(a) Receive applications for credentialing under the act, process such
applications and regulate the issuance of credentials to qualified applicants,
and maintain a directory of the names and addresses of persons who receive
credentials under the act;</para>
<para>(b) Hold meetings, public hearings, informal conferences, and administrative
hearings, prepare or cause to be prepared specifications for all appraiser
classifications, solicit bids and enter into contracts with one or more testing
services, and administer or contract for the administration of examinations
approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board in such places and at such
times as deemed appropriate;</para>
<para>(c) Develop the specifications for credentialing examinations, including
timing, location, and security necessary to maintain the integrity of the
examinations;</para>
<para>(d) Review the procedures and criteria of a contracted testing service
to ensure that the testing meets with the approval of the Appraiser Qualifications
Board;</para>
<para>(e) Collect all fees required or permitted by the act. The Real Property
Appraiser Board shall remit all such receipts to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Real Property Appraiser Fund. In addition, the board may collect and
transmit to the appropriate federal authority any fees established under the
Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, as the
act existed on January 1, 2012;</para>
<para>(f) Establish appropriate administrative procedures for disciplinary
proceedings conducted pursuant to the Real Property Appraiser Act;</para>
<para>(g) Issue subpoenas to compel the attendance of witnesses and the production
of books, documents, records, and other papers, administer oaths, and take
testimony and require submission of and receive evidence concerning all matters
within its jurisdiction. In case of disobedience of a subpoena, the Real Property
Appraiser Board may make application to the district court of Lancaster County
to require the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of
documentary evidence. If any person fails to obey an order of the court, he
or she may be punished by the court as for contempt thereof;</para>
<para>(h) Deny, censure, suspend, or revoke an application or credential if
it finds that the applicant or credential holder has committed any of the
acts or omissions set forth in section 76-2238 or otherwise violated the act.
Any disciplinary matter may be resolved through informal disposition pursuant
to section 84-913;</para>
<para>(i) Take appropriate disciplinary action against a credential holder
if the Real Property Appraiser Board determines that a credential holder has
violated any provision of the act or the Uniform Standards of Professional
Appraisal Practice;</para>
<para>(j) Enter into consent decrees and issue cease and desist orders upon
a determination that a violation of the act has occurred;</para>
<para>(k) Promote research and conduct studies relating to the profession
of real property appraisal, sponsor real property appraisal educational activities,
and incur, collect fees for, and pay the necessary expenses in connection
with activities which shall be open to all credential holders;</para>
<para>(l) Establish and adopt minimum standards for appraisals as required
under section 76-2237;</para>
<para>(m) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the act.
The rules and regulations may include provisions establishing minimum standards
for schools, courses, and instructors. The rules and regulations shall be
adopted pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act; and</para>
<para>(n) Do all other things necessary to carry out the Real Property Appraiser
Act.</para>
<para>(2) The Real Property Appraiser Board shall also administer and enforce
the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB714, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>March 8, 2012</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 76-3201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>