<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id157" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2229.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2229.01</statuteno><catchline id="id160">Credential
as a registered real property appraiser; applicant; qualifications; upgraded
credential; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify for a credential
as a registered real property appraiser, an applicant shall:</para>
<para>(a) Be at least nineteen years of age;</para>
<para>(b) Hold a high school diploma or a certificate of high school equivalency
or have education acceptable to the board;</para>
<para>(c) Have successfully completed no fewer than ninety class hours in
board-approved courses of study which relate to appraisal and which include
the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice
Course as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as of January 1, 2012, or the equivalent of the course as approved
by the Real Property Appraiser Board. The courses of study shall be conducted
by an accredited, degree-awarding university, college, or community college,
an appraisal society, institute, or association, or such other educational
provider as may be approved by the Real Property Appraiser Board and shall
be, at a minimum, fifteen class hours in length. Each course of study shall
include an examination pertinent to the material presented;</para>
<para>(d) Within the twelve months following approval of the applicant by
the Real Property Appraiser Board, pass an examination approved by the Appraiser
Qualifications Board as of January 1, 2012, and administered by
a contracted testing service which demonstrates that the applicant has:</para>
<para>(i) Knowledge of technical terms commonly used in or related to appraisal
and the writing of appraisal reports;</para>
<para>(ii) Knowledge of depreciation theories, cost estimating, methods of
capitalization, market data analysis, appraisal mathematics, and economic
concepts applicable to real estate;</para>
<para>(iii) An understanding of the basic principles of land economics, appraisal
processes, and problems encountered in the gathering, interpreting, and processing
of data involved in the valuation of real property;</para>
<para>(iv) Knowledge of the appraisal of various types of and interests in
real property for various functions and purposes;</para>
<para>(v) An understanding of basic real estate law;</para>
<para>(vi) An understanding of the types of misconduct for which disciplinary
proceedings may be initiated;</para>
<para>(vii) An understanding of the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal
Practice;</para>
<para>(viii) An understanding of the recognized methods and techniques necessary
for the development and communication of a credible appraisal; and</para>
<para>(ix) Knowledge of such other principles and procedures as may be appropriate
to produce a credible appraisal; and</para>
<para>(e) Not have been convicted of any felony or, if so convicted, have
had his or her civil rights restored.</para>
<para>(2) To qualify for an upgraded credential, a registered real property
appraiser shall satisfy at least one of the appropriate requirements as follows:</para>
<para>(a) For a credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser,
he or she shall (i) complete sixty additional hours of designated core curriculum
education and (ii) meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision
(1)(d) of section 76-2230;</para>
<para>(b) For a credential as a certified residential real property appraiser,
he or she shall (i) complete one hundred ten additional hours of designated
core curriculum education, (ii) meet the experience requirements pursuant
to subdivision (1)(d) of section 76-2231.01, and (iii) meet the postsecondary
educational requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(i) or (ii) of section
76-2231.01; or</para>
<para>(c) For a credential as a certified general real property appraiser,
he or she shall (i) complete two hundred twenty-five additional hours of designated
core curriculum education, (ii) meet the experience requirements pursuant
to subdivision (1)(d) of section 76-2232, and (iii) meet the postsecondary
educational requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(i) or (ii) of section
76-2232.</para>
<para>(3) The application for registration shall include the applicant's social
security number and such other information as the Real Property Appraiser
Board may require.</para>
<para>(4) The scope of practice of a registered real property appraiser shall
be limited to the appraisal of noncomplex property having one, two, three,
or four residential units having a transaction value of less than two hundred
fifty thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(5) An applicant shall receive no more than three successive annual
renewals for credentialing as a registered real property appraiser. Notwithstanding
any other provision of section 76-2228 to the contrary, the board shall not
approve any initial application for credentialing as a registered real property
appraiser on and after January 1, 2012.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 204; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB714, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>