<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id948"><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2333"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2333</statuteno><catchline>Underground Excavation Safety Committee; created; members; appointment; expenses; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning September 1, 2024, the Underground Excavation Safety Committee is created. The committee shall consist of the following members: (a) The State Fire Marshal or the State Fire Marshal's designee, (b) three representatives of operators, (c) three representatives of excavators, and (d) one alternate representative of operators and one alternate representative of excavators. An alternate representative described in subdivision (d) of this subsection shall only participate in a committee meeting if a corresponding representative described in subdivision (b) or (c) of this subsection has declared a conflict of interest and recused himself or herself from participation in a matter before the committee or is otherwise unavailable for a committee meeting. In such instance, the chairperson shall notify the alternate representative to serve in the place of the recused or absent representative for any meeting related to such particular conflict or for the duration of such absence.</para><para>(2) The representative members shall be appointed by the Governor. The Governor shall appoint one of the three initial representatives of operators described in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, one of the three initial representatives of excavators described in subdivision (1)(c) of this section, and both alternate representatives described in subdivision (1)(d) of this section for two-year terms. The other initial representatives shall be appointed for four-year terms. All succeeding terms shall be for four years. A representative member may be reappointed at the end of such member's term. If there is a vacancy on the committee, the Governor shall appoint a member to serve the remainder of the unexpired term of the vacating member. All representative members shall be subject to approval by the Legislature.</para><para>(3) The committee shall select from among its members a chairperson. The committee shall not select an alternate representative to serve as chairperson. The committee shall govern its procedures pursuant to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the State Fire Marshal. No representative member shall receive any compensation for services rendered as a member of the committee but may be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(4) The committee shall meet not less than monthly and also at such other times and at such places as may be established by the chairperson. The committee may meet by videoconference with approval of a majority of the committee members. Any action taken by the committee shall require a majority vote of the members.</para><para>(5)(a) The committee shall (i) review investigations completed pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of section 76-2325, (ii) determine based on such review whether any person has committed any violation described in subdivision (2)(b) of section 76-2325, and (iii) determine the appropriate civil penalty, if any, to be assessed for such violation consistent with subdivision (2)(b)(ii) of section 76-2325.</para><para>(b) No member of the committee who participated in an investigation conducted under subdivision (2)(a) of section 76-2325 shall participate in a hearing upon any question in which such member or any business with which such member is associated is a party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB683, &#167; 8. </para><effectivedate>May 27, 2023</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>