<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id137">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id139" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2228.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2228.02</statuteno><catchline>Trainee real property appraiser;
direct supervision; supervisory appraiser; qualifications; disciplinary action;
effect; appraisal experience log.</catchline><para>(1) Each trainee real property appraiser's experience shall
be subject to direct supervision by a supervisory appraiser. To qualify as
a supervisory appraiser, a real property appraiser shall:</para>
<para>(a) Be a certified
residential real property appraiser or certified general real property appraiser
in good standing;</para><para>(b) Have held a certified real property appraiser credential for
a minimum of three years immediately preceding the date of the written request
for approval as supervisory appraiser;</para><para>(c) Have not successfully completed disciplinary
action by the board or any other jurisdiction, which action limited the real
property appraiser's legal eligibility to engage in real property appraisal
activity within three years immediately preceding the date the written request
for approval as supervisory appraiser is submitted by the applicant or trainee
real property appraiser on a form approved by the board;</para>
<para>(d) As prescribed
by rule or regulation of the board, have successfully completed a board-approved
seven-hour supervisory appraiser and trainee course within two years immediately
preceding the date the written request for approval as supervisory appraiser
is submitted by the applicant or trainee real property appraiser on a form
approved by the board; and</para><para>(e) Certify that he or she understands
his or her responsibilities and obligations under the Real Property Appraiser
Act as a supervisory appraiser and applies his or her signature to the written
request for approval as supervisory appraiser submitted by the applicant or
trainee real property appraiser.</para><para>(2) The supervisory appraiser shall be
responsible for the training and direct supervision of the trainee real property
appraiser's experience by:</para><para>(a) Accepting responsibility for the report
by applying his or her signature and certifying that the report is in compliance
with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice;</para>
<para>(b) Reviewing
the trainee real property appraiser reports; and</para><para>(c) Personally inspecting
each appraised property with the trainee real property appraiser as is consistent
with his or her scope of practice until the supervisory appraiser determines
that the trainee real property appraiser is competent in accordance with the
competency rule of the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice.</para>
<para>(3) A certified
real property appraiser disciplined by the board or any other appraiser regulatory
agency in another jurisdiction, which discipline may or may not have limited
the real property appraiser's legal eligibility to engage in real property
appraisal activity, shall not be eligible as a supervisory appraiser as of
the date disciplinary action was imposed against the appraiser by the board
or any other appraiser regulatory agency. The certified real property appraiser
shall be considered to be in good standing and eligible as a supervisory appraiser
upon the successful completion of disciplinary action that does not limit
the real property appraiser's legal eligibility to engage in real property
appraisal activity, or three years after the successful completion of disciplinary
action that limits the real property appraiser's legal eligibility to engage
in real property appraisal activity.</para><para>(4) The trainee real property appraiser
may have more than one supervisory appraiser, but a supervisory appraiser
may not supervise more than three trainee real property appraisers at one
time.</para><para>(5) As prescribed by rule or regulation of the board, an appraisal
experience log shall be maintained jointly by the supervisory appraiser and
the trainee real property appraiser.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 16.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>