<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id34" statutenumber="76-2325"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2325</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Violations; civil penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who violates section 76-2320, 76-2320.01, 76-2320.02, 76-2321, 76-2322, 76-2323, 76-2326, 76-2330, or 76-2331 shall be subject to a civil penalty as follows:</para><para>(a) For a violation by an excavator or an operator related to a gas or hazardous liquid underground pipeline facility or a fiber optic telecommunications facility, an amount not to exceed ten thousand dollars for each violation for each day the violation persists, up to a maximum of five hundred thousand dollars; and</para><para>(b) For a violation by an excavator or an operator related to any other underground facility, an amount not to exceed five thousand dollars for each day the violation persists, up to a maximum of fifty thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) An action to recover a civil penalty shall be brought by the Attorney General or a prosecuting attorney on behalf of the State of Nebraska in any court of competent jurisdiction of this state. The trial shall be before the court, which shall consider the nature, circumstances, and gravity of the violation and, with respect to the person found to have committed the violation, the degree of culpability, the absence or existence of prior violations, whether the violation was a willful act, any good faith attempt to achieve compliance, and such other matters as justice may require in determining the amount of penalty imposed. All penalties shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 421, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB930, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 97; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB462, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>