<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id00" renumber="yes"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id90" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2227"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2227</statuteno><catchline id="id93">Credentials; application; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Applications for credentials, including authorization to take the appropriate examination, and for renewal of credentials shall be made in writing to the board on forms approved by the board. The payment of the appropriate fee in an amount established by the board pursuant to section 76-2241 shall accompany all applications.</para><para>(2) Applications for credentials, including initial and renewal applications, shall include the applicant's social security number and such other information as the board may require.</para><para>(3) At the time of filing an initial or renewal application for credentials, the applicant shall sign a pledge that he or she has read and will comply with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice. Each applicant shall also certify that he or she understands the types of misconduct for which disciplinary proceedings may be initiated.</para><para>(4) Credentials shall be issued only to persons who have a good reputation for honesty, trustworthiness, integrity, and competence to perform assignments in such manner as to safeguard the interest of the public and only after satisfactory proof of such qualification has been presented to the board upon request and a completed application has been approved.</para><para>(5) Credentials shall be issued only to persons who have demonstrated a general knowledge of Nebraska law as it pertains to real property appraisal activity.</para><para>(6) No credential shall be issued to a person other than an individual.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 490; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 44. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>