<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id331" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2236"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2236</statuteno><catchline id="id334">Continuing education; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Every credential holder shall furnish evidence to the board that he or she has satisfactorily completed no fewer than twenty-eight hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year continuing education period. The continuing education period begins on January 1 of the next year for any credential holder who first obtained his or her credential at the current level on or after July 1. Hours of satisfactorily completed approved continuing education activities cannot be carried over from one two-year continuing education period to another. Evidence of successful completion of such continuing education activities for the two-year continuing education period, including passing examination if applicable, shall be submitted to the board in the manner prescribed by the board. No continuing education activity shall be less than two hours in duration. A person who holds a temporary credential does not have to meet any continuing education requirements in the Real Property Appraiser Act.</para><para>(2) No more than fourteen hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year continuing education period shall be taken online or by correspondence. All online courses shall conform to the Appraiser Qualifications Board's criteria.</para><para>(3) As prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board and at least once every two years, the seven-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Update Course as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as of January 1, 2016, or the equivalent of the course as approved by the Real Property Appraiser Board, shall be included in the continuing education requirement of each credential holder. The seven-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Update Course or an equivalent of the course as approved by the board shall:</para><para>(a) Be taken in a classroom and not online or by correspondence;</para><para>(b) Be approved by the board as a continuing education activity for the duration the course is approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as of January 1, 2016; and</para><para>(c) Be taught by an instructor certified by the Appraiser Qualifications Board to teach the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice and who is a state-certified appraiser in good standing.</para><para>(4) As prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board and at least once every four years, but not more than every two years, a report writing update course of at least seven hours, as approved by the board, shall be included in the continuing education requirement of each credential holder. The report writing update course shall be taken in a classroom and not online or by correspondence.</para><para>(5) A continuing education activity conducted in another jurisdiction in which the activity is approved to meet the continuing education requirements for renewal of a credential in such other jurisdiction shall be accepted by the board if that jurisdiction has adopted and enforces standards for such continuing education activity that meet or exceed the standards established by the Real Property Appraiser Act and the rules and regulations of the board.</para><para>(6) The board may adopt a program of continuing education for individual credentials as long as the program is compliant with the Appraiser Qualifications Board's criteria specific to continuing education.</para><para>(7) No more than fourteen hours may be approved by the Real Property Appraiser Board as continuing education in each two-year continuing education period for participation, other than as a student, in appraisal educational processes and programs, which includes teaching, program development, authorship of textbooks, or similar activities that are determined by the board to be equivalent to obtaining continuing education. Evidence of participation shall be submitted to the board upon completion of the appraisal educational process or program. No preapproval will be granted for participation in appraisal educational processes or programs.</para><para>(8) Qualifying education, as approved by the board, successfully completed by a credential holder to fulfill the class-hour requirement to upgrade to a higher classification than his or her current classification, shall be approved by the board as continuing education.</para><para>(9) Qualifying education, as approved by the board, taken by a credential holder not to fulfill the class-hour requirement to upgrade to a higher classification, shall be approved by the board as continuing education if the credential holder completes the examination.</para><para>(10) A board-approved seven-hour supervisory appraiser and trainee course successfully completed by a certified real property appraiser for approval as a supervisory appraiser shall be approved by the board as continuing education no more than once during each two-year continuing education period.</para><para>(11) The Real Property Appraiser Board shall approve continuing education activities and instructors which it determines would protect the public by improving the competency of credential holders.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 29, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB714, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB731, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>