<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id34" statutenumber="76-2325"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2325</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Violations; civil penalty; investigation; State Fire Marshal; committee; duties; hearing; civil penalty; costs.</catchline><para>(1) Until September 1, 2024:</para><para>(a) Any person who violates section 76-2320, 76-2320.01, 76-2320.02, 76-2321, 76-2322, 76-2323, 76-2326, 76-2330, or 76-2331 shall be subject to a civil penalty as follows:</para><para>(i) For a violation by an excavator or an operator related to a gas or hazardous liquid underground pipeline facility or a fiber optic telecommunications facility, an amount not to exceed ten thousand dollars for each violation for each day the violation persists, up to a maximum of five hundred thousand dollars; and</para><para>(ii) For a violation by an excavator or an operator related to any other underground facility, an amount not to exceed five thousand dollars for each day the violation persists, up to a maximum of fifty thousand dollars; and</para><para>(b) An action to recover a civil penalty shall be brought by the Attorney General or a prosecuting attorney on behalf of the State of Nebraska in any court of competent jurisdiction of this state. The trial shall be before the court, which shall consider the nature, circumstances, and gravity of the violation and, with respect to the person found to have committed the violation, the degree of culpability, the absence or existence of prior violations, whether the violation was a willful act, any good faith attempt to achieve compliance, and such other matters as justice may require in determining the amount of penalty imposed. All penalties shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(2) Beginning September 1, 2024:</para><para>(a)(i) When the State Fire Marshal has reason to believe that any person has committed any violation described in subdivision (b) of this subsection, the State Fire Marshal may conduct an investigation to determine the facts and circumstances of such alleged violation and, if conducted, shall give prior notice of such investigation by first-class mail or electronic mail to such person.</para><para>(ii) When any person other than the State Fire Marshal has reason to believe that any violation described in subdivision (b) of this subsection has occurred, such person may submit information to the State Fire Marshal regarding such violation on a form prescribed by the State Fire Marshal. Upon receipt of such information, the State Fire Marshal may conduct an investigation to determine the facts and circumstances of such alleged violation and, if conducted, shall give prior notice of such investigation by first-class mail or electronic mail to both the person being investigated and the person who submitted the information to the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(iii) The State Fire Marshal shall refer the findings of the investigation to the committee for its determination. Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (2)(a)(iv) of this section, the committee shall issue a written determination stating findings of fact, conclusions of law, and the civil penalty, if any, to be assessed for such violation and serve a copy of the written determination by personal service or by certified mail, return receipt requested, upon such person. If the State Fire Marshal's investigation was commenced based on information provided pursuant to subdivision (2)(a)(ii) of this section, a copy of the written determination shall also be delivered by first-class mail to the person providing such information.</para><para>(iv) If the committee determines that the civil penalty to be assessed for any violation exceeds the amount described in subdivision (2)(b)(iv) of this section, the committee shall refer the matter, together with the State Fire Marshal's findings and the committee's written determination, to the Attorney General for prosecution pursuant to subdivision (2)(b)(v) of this section.</para><para>(v) Not later than thirty days after receipt of the committee's written determination, any party may submit a written request to the State Fire Marshal for a hearing on the matter. The committee shall then appoint a hearing officer to conduct such hearing and set a hearing date and provide written notice of hearing to the parties at least thirty days prior to the date of the hearing. Such notice shall contain the name, address, and telephone number of the hearing officer, a copy of the written determination upon which the hearing shall be held, and the date, time, and place of hearing. The notice of hearing may be served by personal service or by certified mail. If no hearing is requested in answer to the written determination by the person found to have committed any violation as described in subdivision (b) of this subsection, or if a request for a hearing is withdrawn, such person shall pay any civil penalty assessed within thirty days after receipt of the written determination or within thirty days after cancellation of the hearing, whichever is applicable.</para><para>(vi) In the preparation and conduct of the hearing, the hearing officer shall have the power, on the hearing officer's own motion or upon the request of any party, to compel the attendance of any witness and the production of any documents by subpoena to ensure a fair hearing. The hearing officer may administer oaths and examine witnesses and receive any evidence pertinent to the determination of the matter. Any witnesses so subpoenaed shall be entitled to the same fees as prescribed by law in judicial proceedings in the district court of this state in a civil action and mileage at the same rate provided in section 81-1176 for state employees.</para><para>(vii) A party may appear at the hearing with or without the assistance of counsel to present testimony, examine witnesses, and offer evidence. A stenographic record of all testimony and other evidence received at the hearing shall be made and preserved pending final disposition of the matter.</para><para>(viii) Unless all requests for hearing are withdrawn prior to the hearing, following the hearing the hearing officer shall prepare written findings of fact and conclusions of law, and based on such findings of fact and conclusions of law, the committee shall affirm, modify, or reverse the written determination issued under subdivision (2)(a)(iii) of this section and issue a final order. The committee's final order may include an assessment of costs incurred in conducting the hearing, including the costs of the hearing officer and compelling the attendance of witnesses, and assess such costs against the parties. Any party aggrieved by the final order of the committee may appeal the decision, and such appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act; and</para><para>(b)(i) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(b)(ii) of this section, any person who violates section 76-2320, 76-2320.01, 76-2320.02, 76-2321, 76-2322, 76-2323, 76-2326, 76-2330, or 76-2331 or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the State Fire Marshal pursuant to section 76-2319 shall be subject to a civil penalty as follows:</para><para>(A) For a violation by an excavator or an operator related to a gas or hazardous liquid underground pipeline facility or a fiber optic telecommunications facility, an amount not to exceed ten thousand dollars for each violation for each day the violation persists, up to a maximum of five hundred thousand dollars; and</para><para>(B) For a violation by an excavator or an operator related to any other underground facility, an amount not to exceed five thousand dollars for each day the violation persists, up to a maximum of fifty thousand dollars.</para><para>(ii) In addition to or in lieu of assessing a civil penalty as provided in subdivision (i) of this subsection, the committee may order that a violator take and complete continuing education regarding compliance with the One-Call Notification System Act. Such continuing education shall be approved by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(iii) When imposing a civil penalty, the committee shall consider the nature, circumstances, and gravity of the violation and, with respect to the person found to have committed the violation, the degree of culpability, the absence or existence of prior violations, whether the violation was a willful act, any good faith attempt to achieve compliance, and such other matters as justice may require.</para><para>(iv) The committee shall not assess a civil penalty that is more than ten thousand dollars per violation. The violator shall pay the costs of the investigation as billed by the State Fire Marshal. The State Fire Marshal shall remit such paid costs to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund from which the costs were expended.</para><para>(v) As provided in subdivision (2)(a)(iv) of this section, for any investigation in which a civil penalty in excess of the amount described in subdivision (2)(b)(iv) of this section is deemed justified by the committee, the committee shall refer such matter to the Attorney General or a prosecuting attorney who shall bring an action on behalf of the State of Nebraska to recover such penalty in any court of competent jurisdiction of this state. The trial shall be before the court, which shall consider the nature, circumstances, and gravity of the violation and, with respect to the person found to have committed the violation, the degree of culpability, the absence or existence of prior violations, whether the violation was a willful act, any good faith attempt to achieve compliance, and such other matters as justice may require in determining the amount of penalty imposed.</para><para>(vi) Costs incurred by the investigation conducted pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section may be sought as part of any judgment against a violator. The State Fire Marshal shall remit any such recovered costs to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund from which the costs were expended.</para><para>(vii) All civil penalties collected pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 421, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB930, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 97; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB462, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB683, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>