<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id129">
<sectno id="id130" opdate=" ">Sec. 10.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id131" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2228.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id133">76-2228.01</statuteno><catchline id="id134">Trainee
real property appraiser; applicant; qualifications; upgraded credential; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify
for a credential as a trainee real property appraiser, an applicant shall:</para>
<para>(a) Be at least nineteen years of age;</para>
<para>(b) Hold a high school diploma or a certificate of high school
equivalency or have education acceptable to the board;</para>
<para>(c) Have successfully completed no fewer than seventy-five
class hours in board-approved courses of study which relate to appraisal and
which include completion of the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of
Professional Appraisal Practice Course as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications
Board as of January 1, 2010,
or the equivalent of the course as approved by the Real Property Appraiser
Board. The fifteen-hour course shall be taught by a Uniform Standards
of Professional Appraisal Practice Instructor who is certified by the Appraiser
Qualifications Board and who is a state-certified appraiser in good standing.
The courses of study shall be conducted by an accredited, degree-awarding university, college, or community college, an appraisal
society, institute, or association, a state or federal agency or commission,
a proprietary school, or such other educational provider as may be approved
by the Real Property Appraiser Board and
shall be, at a minimum, fifteen class hours in length. Each course shall include
an examination pertinent to the material presented. The applicant shall have
completed the class hours within the five-year period immediately preceding
submission of the application and shall have completed the fifteen-hour National
Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course within the two-year
period immediately preceding submission of the application;</para>
<para>(d) Be subject to direct supervision by a supervising appraiser
or appraisers who are certified residential real property appraisers or certified
general real property appraisers in good standing. The supervising appraiser
shall be responsible for the training and direct supervision of the trainee
by accepting responsibility for the appraisal report by signing and certifying
the report is in compliance with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal
Practice, reviewing the trainee appraisal reports, and personally inspecting
each appraised property with the trainee as
is consistent with his or her scope of practice until the supervising
appraiser determines the trainee is competent in accordance with the competency
rule of the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice. The trainee
shall maintain an appraisal log for each supervising appraiser in accordance
with standards set by rule and regulation of the board; and</para>
<para>(e) Not have been convicted of any felony or, if so convicted,
have had his or her civil rights restored.</para>
<para>(2) To qualify
for an upgraded credential, a trainee real property appraiser shall satisfy
at least one of the appropriate requirements as follows:</para>
<para>(a) For a
credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser, he or she shall
(i) complete seventy-five additional hours of designated core curriculum education
and (ii) meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(d) of
section 76-2230;</para><para>(b) For a credential as a certified residential real property appraiser,
he or she shall (i) complete one hundred twenty-five additional hours of designated
core curriculum education, (ii) meet the experience requirements pursuant
to subdivision (1)(d) of section 76-2231.01, and (iii) meet the postsecondary
educational requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(i) or (ii) of section
76-2231.01; or</para><para>(c) For a credential as a certified general real property appraiser,
he or she shall (i) complete two hundred twenty-five additional hours of designated
core curriculum education, (ii) meet the experience requirements pursuant
to subdivision (1)(d) of section 76-2232, and (iii) meet the postsecondary
educational requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(i) or (ii) of section
76-2232.</para><para>(3) If a trainee real property
appraiser remains in the classification in excess of two years, the trainee
shall be required in the third and successive years to successfully complete
no fewer than fourteen hours of instruction in courses or seminars for each
year of the period preceding the renewal and shall have completed the seven-hour
National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Update Course,  as the course existed on January 1, 2010,
or the equivalent of the course as approved by the Real Property Appraiser
Board, at a minimum of every two years. The courses of study shall
be conducted by an accredited,
degree-awarding university, college, or community college, an appraisal society, institute,
or association, a state or federal agency or commission, a proprietary school,
or such other educational provider as may be approved by the board. Credit
may be granted for educational offerings and for participation other than
as a student as approved by the board.</para>
<para>(4) The application for a
credential as a trainee real property appraiser shall include the applicant's
social security number and such other information as the board may require.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 10.</para><effectivedate>April 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>