<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id17" statutenumber="76-2323"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2323</statuteno><catchline id="id20">Underground facilities;
mark or identify.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receipt of the information
contained in the notice pursuant to section 76-2321, an operator shall advise
the excavator of the approximate location of underground facilities in the
area of the proposed excavation by marking or identifying the location of
the underground facilities with stakes, flags, paint, or any other clearly
identifiable marking or reference point and
shall indicate if the underground facilities are subject to section 76-2331.
The location of the underground facility given by the operator shall be within
a strip of land eighteen inches on either side of the marking or identification
plus one-half of the width of the underground facility. If in the opinion
of the operator the precise location of a facility cannot be determined and
marked as required, the operator shall provide all pertinent information and
field locating assistance to the excavator at a mutually agreed to time. The
location shall be marked or identified using color standards prescribed by
the center. The operator shall respond no later than two business days after
receipt of the information in the notice or at a time mutually agreed to by
the parties.</para>
<para>(2) The marking or identification shall be done in a manner
that will last for a minimum of five business days on any nonpermanent surface
and a minimum of ten business days on any permanent surface. If the excavation
will continue for longer than five business days, the operator shall remark
or reidentify the location of the underground facility upon the request of
the excavator. The request for remarking or reidentification shall be made
through the center.</para>
<para>(3) An operator who determines that it does not have any underground
facility located in the area of the proposed excavation shall notify the excavator
of the determination prior to the date of commencement of the excavation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 421, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB930, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>