<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id366">
<sectno id="id367" opdate=" ">Sec. 24.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id368" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2249"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id370">76-2249</statuteno><catchline id="id371">Directory of
appraisers; information; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) The
board may prepare a printed directory
showing the name and place of business of credential holders under the Real
Property Appraiser Act. Copies of the directory shall be made available to
the public at such reasonable price per copy as may be fixed by the board
and shall be provided to federal authorities as required by the Financial
Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, as the act existed
on January 1, 2010.</para>
<para>(2) The board shall provide without charge to any credential
holder under the act a set of rules and regulations adopted and promulgated
by the board and any other information which the board deems important in
the area of real property appraisal in the State of Nebraska. The information
may be printed in a booklet, a pamphlet, or any other form the board determines
appropriate. The board may update such material as often as it deems necessary.
The board may provide such material to any other person upon request and may
charge a fee for the material. The fee shall be reasonable and shall not exceed
any reasonable or necessary costs of producing the material for distribution.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 842, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167;  16; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167;  24.</para><effectivedate>April 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>