<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id300">
<sectno id="id301" opdate=" ">Sec. 19.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id302" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2236"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id304">76-2236</statuteno><catchline id="id305">Continuing
education; requirements.</catchline><para>Every credential holder
shall furnish evidence to the board that he or she has satisfactorily completed
no fewer than twenty-eight hours of approved continuing education activities
in each two-year continuing education period. Hours of satisfactorily completed
approved continuing education activities cannot be carried over from one two-year
continuing education period to another. As prescribed by rule or regulation of the board and
at least once every two years, the seven-hour National Uniform Standards of
Professional Appraisal Practice Update Course as approved by the Appraiser
Qualifications Board as of
January 1, 2010, or the equivalent of the course as approved by the Real Property
Appraiser Board, shall be included in the continuing education
requirement of each credential holder. As
prescribed by rule or regulation of the Real Property Appraiser Board and
at least once every four years, a seven-hour report writing update course
shall be included in the continuing education requirement of each credential
holder. The Real Property Appraiser Board shall
approve continuing education activities which it determines would protect
the public by improving the competency of credential holders. Evidence of
completion of such continuing education activities for the two-year continuing
education period may be submitted to the board as each activity is completed.
A person who holds a temporary or
reciprocal credential shall not have to meet any continuing education
requirements in this state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 29, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167;  19.</para><effectivedate>April 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>