<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id193" statutenumber="76-2230"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2230</statuteno><catchline id="id196">Credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser; applicant; qualifications; fingerprints; national criminal history record check; upgraded credential; requirements; scope of practice.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify for a credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser, an applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Be at least nineteen years of age;</para><para>(b) Hold a high school diploma or a certificate of high school equivalency or have education acceptable to the Real Property Appraiser Board;</para><para>(c)(i) Have successfully completed and passed examination for no fewer than one hundred fifty class hours in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board and completed the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course. Each course shall include a proctored, closed-book examination pertinent to the material presented; or</para><para>(ii) Hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university that has had all or part of its curriculum approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as required core curriculum or the equivalent as determined by the Appraiser Qualifications Board. If the degree in real estate or equivalent as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board does not satisfy all required qualifying education for credentialing, the remaining class hours shall be completed in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education pursuant to subdivision (c)(i) of this subsection;</para><para>(d)(i) Have no fewer than one thousand hours of experience as prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board. The required experience shall be acceptable to the Real Property Appraiser Board and subject to review and determination as to conformity with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice. The experience shall have occurred during a period of no fewer than six months; or</para><para>(ii) Successfully complete a PAREA program. If the PAREA program does not satisfy all required experience for credentialing, the remaining experience hours shall be completed pursuant to subdivision (d)(i) of this subsection;</para><para>(e) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the Real Property Appraiser Board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the Real Property Appraiser Board; and</para><para>(f) Within the twelve months following approval of the applicant's education and experience by the Real Property Appraiser Board, pass a licensed residential real property appraiser examination, certified residential real property appraiser examination, or certified general real property appraiser examination, approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board, prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board, and administered by a contracted testing service.</para><para>(2) To qualify for an upgraded credential, a licensed residential real property appraiser shall satisfy the appropriate requirements as follows:</para><para>(a) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the Real Property Appraiser Board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the Real Property Appraiser Board; and</para><para>(b) Within the twelve months following approval of the applicant's education and experience by the Real Property Appraiser Board for an upgraded credential, pass an appropriate examination approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board for that upgraded credential, prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board, and administered by a contracted testing service.</para><para>(3) To qualify for a credential as a certified residential real property appraiser, a licensed residential real property appraiser shall:</para><para>(a)(i) Meet the postsecondary educational requirements pursuant to subdivisions (1)(b) and (c) of section 76-2231.01; or</para><para>(ii)(A) Have held a credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser for a minimum of five years; and</para><para>(B) Not have been subject to a nonappealable disciplinary action by the board or any other jurisdiction, which action limited the real property appraiser's legal eligibility to engage in real property appraisal practice within five years immediately preceding the date of application for the certified residential real property appraiser credential;</para><para>(b) Successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than fifty additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(d)(ii) of section 76-2231.01; and</para><para>(c) Meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(e) of section 76-2231.01.</para><para>(4) To qualify for a credential as a certified general real property appraiser, a licensed residential real property appraiser shall:</para><para>(a) Meet the postsecondary educational requirements pursuant to subdivisions (1)(b) and (c) of section 76-2232;</para><para>(b) Successfully complete and pass proctored, closed-book examinations for no fewer than one hundred fifty additional class hours in board-approved qualifying education courses conducted by education providers as prescribed by rules and regulations of the board, or hold a degree in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university or equivalent pursuant to subdivision (1)(d)(ii) of section 76-2232; and</para><para>(c) Meet the experience requirements pursuant to subdivision (1)(e) of section 76-2232.</para><para>(5) An appraiser holding a valid licensed residential real property appraiser credential shall satisfy the requirements for the trainee real property appraiser credential for a downgraded credential.</para><para>(6) The scope of practice for a licensed residential real property appraiser shall be limited to real property appraisal practice concerning noncomplex residential real property or real estate having no more than four units, if any, with a transaction value of less than one million dollars and complex residential real property or real estate having no more than four units, if any, with a transaction value of less than four hundred thousand dollars. The appraisal of subdivisions for which a development analysis or appraisal is necessary is not included in the scope of practice for a licensed residential real property appraiser.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 29, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 205; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB714, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB731, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB77, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB23, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB707, &#167; 54. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>