<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2602" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2602</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>In the Uniform Environmental Covenants Act:</para><para>(1) Activity and use limitations means restrictions or obligations created under the act with respect to real property.</para><para>(2) Agency means the Department of Environment and Energy or any other Nebraska or federal agency that determines or approves the environmental response project pursuant to which the environmental covenant is created.</para><para>(3) Common interest community means a condominium, cooperative, or other real property with respect to which a person, by virtue of the person's ownership of a parcel of real property, is obligated to pay property taxes or insurance premiums, or for maintenance, or improvement of other real property described in a recorded covenant that creates the common interest community.</para><para>(4) Environmental covenant means a servitude arising under an environmental response project that imposes activity and use limitations.</para><para>(5) Environmental response project means a plan or work performed for environmental remediation of real property and conducted:</para><para>(A) Under a federal or state program governing environmental remediation of real property, including the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act;</para><para>(B) Incident to closure of a solid or hazardous waste management unit, if the closure is conducted with approval of an agency; or</para><para>(C) Under a state voluntary cleanup program authorized by the Remedial Action Plan Monitoring Act.</para><para>(6) Holder means the grantee of an environmental covenant as specified in subsection (a) of section 76-2603.</para><para>(7) Person means an individual, corporation, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, limited liability company, association, joint venture, public corporation, government, governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or any other legal or commercial entity.</para><para>(8) Record, used as a noun, means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium and is retrievable in perceivable form.</para><para>(9) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any territory or insular possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 298, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 94. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1501.</para><para><emphasis>Remedial Action Plan Monitoring Act,</emphasis> see section 81-15,181.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>