<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno>Sec. 21.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Real Property" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2721"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2721</statuteno><catchline>Homeowner; right to cancel equity purchase contract; limitation; when effective.</catchline><para>(1)(a) In addition to any right of rescission available under state or federal law, a homeowner has the right to cancel an equity purchase contract until midnight of the third business day following the day on which the homeowner signs a contract that complies with the Nebraska Foreclosure Protection Act or until noon on the last business day before the foreclosure sale of the residence in foreclosure, whichever occurs first.</para><para>(b) There shall be no right to cancel under the act with regard to any equity purchase contract executed on or after noon of the last business day before the foreclosure sale of the residence in foreclosure, if the homeowner first agrees to enter into an equity purchase contract with the equity purchaser on or after noon of the last business day before the foreclosure sale.</para><para>(2) Cancellation occurs when a homeowner personally delivers written notice of cancellation to the address specified in the equity purchase contract or upon deposit of such notice in the United States mail, properly addressed, with postage prepaid.</para><para>(3) A notice of cancellation given by a homeowner need not take the particular form as provided with the equity purchase contract and, however expressed, is effective if it indicates the intention of the homeowner not to be bound by the equity purchase contract.</para><para>(4) In the absence of any written notice of cancellation from a homeowner, the execution by the homeowner of a deed or other instrument of conveyance of an interest in the residence in foreclosure to the equity purchaser after the expiration of the rescission period creates a rebuttable presumption that the homeowner did not cancel the equity purchase contract.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB123, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>