<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id299" statutenumber="76-2233"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2233</statuteno><catchline id="id302">Reciprocity; credential; issuance; when; applicant; duties; fingerprints; national criminal history record check; verification of status.</catchline><para>(1) A person currently credentialed to engage in real property appraisal practice concerning real estate and real property under the laws of another jurisdiction may qualify for a credential through reciprocity as a licensed residential real property appraiser, a certified residential real property appraiser, or a certified general real property appraiser by complying with all of the provisions of the Real Property Appraiser Act relating to the appropriate classification of credentialing.</para><para>(2) An applicant under this section may qualify for a credential if, in the determination of the board:</para><para>(a) The requirements for credentialing in the applicant's jurisdiction of practice specified in an application for credentialing meet or exceed the minimum requirements of the Real Property Appraiser Qualification Criteria as adopted and promulgated by the Appraiser Qualifications Board of The Appraisal Foundation; and</para><para>(b) The regulatory program of the applicant's jurisdiction of practice specified in an application for credentialing is determined to be effective in accordance with Title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989 by the Appraisal Subcommittee of the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council.</para><para>(3) The status of an applicant's jurisdiction of practice specified in an application for credentialing through reciprocity shall be verified through the most recent Compliance Review Report issued by the Appraisal Subcommittee of the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council. In the case that findings pertaining to the adoption or implementation of the Real Property Appraiser Qualification Criteria indicate that one or more credentialing requirements do not meet or exceed the Real Property Appraiser Qualification Criteria as promulgated by the Appraiser Qualifications Board of The Appraisal Foundation, the board may request evidence from the jurisdiction of practice or the Appraisal Subcommittee of the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council showing that progress has been made to mitigate the findings in the Compliance Review Report.</para><para>(4) To qualify for a credential through reciprocity, the applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the board;</para><para>(b) Submit an irrevocable consent that service of process upon him or her may be made by delivery of the process to the director of the board if the plaintiff cannot, in the exercise of due diligence, effect personal service upon the applicant in an action against the applicant in a court of this state arising out of the applicant's activities as a real property appraiser in this state; and</para><para>(c) Comply with such other terms and conditions as may be determined by the board.</para><para>(5) The credential status of an applicant under this section, including current standing and any disciplinary action imposed against his or her credentials, shall be verified through the National Registry of the Appraisal Subcommittee of the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1153, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 208; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1011, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB717, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB731, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB741, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 78. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>