<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id279">
<sectno id="id280" opdate=" ">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id281" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-2233.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id283">76-2233.01</statuteno><catchline id="id284">Nonresident;
temporary credential; issuance; when.</catchline><para>A nonresident
may obtain a temporary credential as a licensed residential real property appraiser, a certified
residential real property appraiser, or a certified general real property
appraiser to perform a contract relating to the appraisal of real estate or
real property in this state. To qualify for the issuance of a temporary credential,
an applicant shall:</para>
<para>(1) Submit an application on a form approved by the board;</para>
<para>(2) Submit an irrevocable consent that service of process
upon him or her may be made by delivery of the process to the director of
the board if the plaintiff cannot, in the exercise of due diligence, effect
personal service upon the applicant in an action against the applicant in
a court of this state arising out of the applicant's activities in this state;</para>
<para>(3) Submit evidence that he or she is credentialed as a licensed
or certified appraiser of real estate and real property and is currently in
good standing in the jurisdiction of residency, along with his or her social
security number and such other information as the board may require;</para>
<para>(4) Certify that disciplinary proceedings are not pending
against the applicant in the applicant's state of domicile or in any other
jurisdiction or state the nature of any pending disciplinary proceedings;
and</para>
<para>(5) Pay an application fee in an amount established by the
board.</para>
<para>A temporary credential issued under this section shall be
expressly limited to a grant of authority to perform the appraisal work required
by the contract for appraisal services in this state. Each temporary credential
shall expire upon the completion of the appraisal work required by the contract
for appraisal services or upon the expiration of a period of six months from
the date of issuance, whichever occurs first. A temporary credential may be
renewed for one additional six-month period.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 203, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1107, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 162, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 778, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB186, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 17.</para><effectivedate>April 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>