<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-2115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2115</statuteno><catchline>Salesperson registration; application; contents; denial, suspension, or revocation; grounds; renewal; fee.</catchline><para>(1) A salesperson may apply for registration by filing with the commission an application which includes the following information:</para><para>(a) A statement detailing whether the applicant within the past five years has been convicted of any misdemeanor or felony involving theft, fraud, or dishonesty or whether the applicant has been enjoined from, had any civil penalty assessed for, or been found to have engaged in any violation of any law designed to protect consumers; and</para><para>(b) A statement describing the applicant's employment history for the past five years and whether any termination of employment during the last five years was occasioned by any theft, fraud, or act of dishonesty.</para><para>(2) Each application for initial registration shall provide to the commission as part of the application a recent photograph of the applicant.</para><para>(3) The commission may deny a salesperson's application for registration or suspend or revoke his or her registration if the commission finds that the order is necessary for the protection of purchasers or owners of membership camping contracts or that the registrant or applicant within the past five years:</para><para>(a) Has been convicted of any misdemeanor or felony involving theft, fraud, or act of dishonesty or has been enjoined from, had any civil penalty assessed for, or been found to have engaged in any violation of any law designed to protect consumers;</para><para>(b) Has violated any material provision of the Membership Campground Act; or</para><para>(c) Has engaged in fraudulent or deceitful practices in any industry involving sales to consumers.</para><para>(4) Registration shall be effective for a period of one year. Registration shall be renewed annually by the filing of a form prescribed by the commission for such purpose. The registration application or the renewal application shall be accompanied by a fee of fifty dollars and shall automatically become effective upon the expiration of seven business days following filing with the commission unless:</para><para>(a) The application has been denied under subsection (3) of this section;</para><para>(b) The commission allows the registration to become effective on an earlier date; or</para><para>(c) The applicant or registrant consents to delay of the effective date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 656, &#167; 15. </para></source></law></legaldoc>