<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id00" renumber="yes"><amendatorysection amended="no" id="id00" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" statutenumber="76-2227.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2227.01</statuteno><catchline>Real property associate; applicant; qualifications; fingerprints; national criminal history record check; examination; scope of practice; limit on activities.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify for a credential as a real property associate, an applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Be at least nineteen years of age;</para><para>(b)(i)(A) Hold a high school diploma or a certificate of high school equivalency or have education acceptable to the Real Property Appraiser Board; and</para><para>(B) Have successfully completed and passed examination for no fewer than ninety class hours in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education courses as prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board and complete the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course. The fifteen-hour course shall be taught by a Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Instructor who is certified by the Appraiser Qualifications Board and who is a state-certified appraiser in good standing. The qualifying education courses shall be conducted by an accredited degree-awarding community college, college, or university, an appraisal society, institute, or association, a state or federal agency or commission, a proprietary school, or such other education provider as may be approved by the Real Property Appraiser Board, and shall be, at a minimum, fifteen class hours in length. Each course shall be conducted in a classroom and not online or by correspondence. Each course shall include an examination pertinent to the material presented; or</para><para>(ii) Hold a bachelor's degree or higher in real estate from an accredited degree-awarding college or university that has had all or part of its curriculum approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board as required core curriculum. If the degree in real estate as approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board does not satisfy all required qualifying education for credentialing, the remaining class hours shall be completed in Real Property Appraiser Board-approved qualifying education pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(i)(B) of this section;</para><para>(c) Certify that he or she has not surrendered an appraiser credential, or any other registration, license, or certification, held for any other regulatory agency or in any other jurisdiction, in lieu of disciplinary action pending or threatened within the five-year period immediately preceding the date of application;</para><para>(d) Certify that his or her appraiser credential, or any other registration, license, or certification, held for any other regulatory agency or in any other jurisdiction, has not been revoked or suspended within the five-year period immediately preceding the date of application;</para><para>(e) Not have been convicted of, including a conviction based upon a plea of guilty or nolo contendere:</para><para>(i) Any felony or, if so convicted, has had his or her civil rights restored;</para><para>(ii) Any crime of fraud, dishonesty, breach of trust, money laundering, misrepresentation, or deceit involving real estate, financial services, or in the making of an appraisal within the five-year period immediately preceding the date of application; or</para><para>(iii) A crime which is related to the qualifications, functions, or duties of a real property appraiser within the five-year period immediately preceding the date of application;</para><para>(f) Certify that no civil judicial actions, including dismissal with settlement, in connection with real estate, financial services, or in the making of an appraisal have been brought against him or her within the five-year period immediately preceding the date of application;</para><para>(g) Demonstrate character and general fitness such as to command the confidence and trust of the public;</para><para>(h) Submit two copies of legible ink-rolled fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the Real Property Appraiser Board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. A fingerprint-based national criminal history record check shall be conducted through the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check to be carried out by the Real Property Appraiser Board; and</para><para>(i) Within the twelve months following approval of the applicant's education by the Real Property Appraiser Board, pass a licensed residential real property appraiser examination, certified residential real property appraiser examination, or certified general real property appraiser examination, approved by the Appraiser Qualifications Board, prescribed by rules and regulations of the Real Property Appraiser Board, and administered by a contracted testing service.</para><para>(2) Except for the fifteen-hour National Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice Course, all class hours shall be completed within the five-year period immediately preceding submission of the application.</para><para>(3) The scope of practice of a real property associate shall be limited to valuation services not requiring a credential as a trainee real property appraiser, licensed residential real property appraiser, certified residential real property appraiser, or certified general real property appraiser under the Real Property Appraiser Act.</para><para>(4) A real property associate shall not advertise or hold himself or herself out to the general public as a real property appraiser.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 45. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>