<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="REAL PROPERTY" id="id00" statutenumber="76-2233.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-2233.03</statuteno><catchline>Credential; inactive status; application; prohibited acts; reinstatement; expiration; reapplication.</catchline><para>(1) A credential holder may request that his or her credential be placed on inactive status for a period not to exceed two years. Such requests shall be submitted to the board on an application form prescribed by the board. The payment of the appropriate fee in an amount established by the board pursuant to section 76-2241 shall accompany all applications for requests of inactive status.</para><para>(2) A credential holder whose credential is placed on inactive status shall not:</para><para>(a) Assume or use any title, designation, or abbreviation likely to create the impression that such person holds an active credential issued by the board; or</para><para>(b) Engage in real property appraisal practice or act as a credentialed real property appraiser.</para><para>(3) A credential holder whose credential is placed on inactive status may make a request to the board that such credential be reinstated to active status on an application form prescribed by the board. The payment of the appropriate fee in an amount established by the board pursuant to section 76-2241 shall accompany all applications for reinstatement of a credential.</para><para>(4) A credential holder's application for reinstatement shall include evidence that he or she has met the continuing education requirements as specified in section 76-2236 while the credential was on inactive status.</para><para>(5) If a credential holder's credential expires during the inactive period, an application for renewal of the credential shall accompany the application for reinstatement. All requirements for renewal specified in section 76-2233.02 shall be met, except for the requirement to pay a late processing fee for applications received after November 30 of the designated year.</para><para>(6) If a credential holder fails to reinstate his or her credential to active status prior to the completion of the two-year period, his or her credential will return to the status as if the credential was not placed on inactive status. If a credential holder's credential is expired at the completion of the two-year period, the credential holder shall reapply for credentialing and meet the current requirements in place at the time of application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB139, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB741, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 81. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>