<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id90">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id92" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-3415"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3415</statuteno><catchline>Effect of transfer on death deed
at transferor's death.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in the transfer on death
deed, in this section, or in sections 30-2313 to 30-2319 or section 30-2354,
on the death of the transferor, the following rules apply to property that
is the subject of a transfer on death deed and owned by the transferor at
death:</para>
<para>(1) Subject
to subdivision (2) of this subsection, the interest in the property is transferred
to the designated beneficiary in accordance with the deed;</para>
<para>(2) The interest
of a designated beneficiary is contingent on the designated beneficiary surviving
the transferor by one hundred twenty hours. If the deed provides for a different
survival period, the deed shall determine the survival requirement for designated
beneficiaries. The interest of a designated beneficiary that fails to survive
the transferor by one hundred twenty hours or as otherwise provided in the
deed shall be treated as if the designated beneficiary predeceased the transferor;</para>
<para>(3) Subject
to subdivision (4) of this subsection, concurrent interests are transferred
to the beneficiaries in equal and undivided shares with no right of survivorship;
and</para><para>(4) If the transferor has identified two or more designated beneficiaries
to receive concurrent interests in the property, the share of one which fails
for any reason is transferred to the other, or to the others in proportion
to the interest of each in the remaining part of the property held concurrently.</para>
<para>(b) A beneficiary
takes the property subject to all conveyances, encumbrances, assignments,
contracts, mortgages, liens, and other interests to which the property is
subject at the transferor's death.</para><para>(c) If a transferor is a joint owner and
is:</para><para>(1) Survived by one or more other joint owners, the property that
is the subject of a transfer on death deed belongs to the surviving joint
owner or owners with right of survivorship; or</para><para>(2) The last surviving
joint owner, the transfer on death deed of the last surviving joint owner
transferor is effective.</para><para>(d) A transfer on death deed transfers
property without covenant or warranty of title even if the deed contains a
contrary provision.</para><para>(e) If after recording a transfer on death deed the transferor
is divorced or his or her marriage is dissolved or annulled, the divorce,
dissolution, or annulment revokes any disposition or appointment of property
made by the transfer on death deed to the former spouse unless the transfer
on death deed expressly provides otherwise. Property prevented from passing
to a former spouse under a transfer on death deed because of revocation by
divorce, dissolution, or annulment passes as if the former spouse failed to
survive the transferor. A decree of separation which does not terminate the
status of husband and wife is not a divorce for purposes of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB536, &#167; 15.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>