<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id123"><?Pub Caret?>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id125" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="76-3215"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3215</statuteno><catchline>Payment of fees; appraiser added
to appraiser panel; removal; complaint; hearing; board; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Each appraisal
management company registered in this state, except in cases of noncompliance
with the conditions of the engagement, shall make payment of fees to an appraiser
for the completion of an appraisal or valuation assignment within sixty days
after the date on which the appraiser transmits or otherwise provides the
completed appraisal report or valuation assignment to the appraisal management
company or its assignee.</para>
<para>(2) Except within the
first ninety days after an appraiser is first added to the appraiser panel
of an appraisal management company, an appraisal management company may not
remove the appraiser from the appraiser panel of the appraisal management
company or otherwise refuse to assign requests for appraisal services to an
appraiser on the appraiser panel without:</para><para>(a) Notifying the appraiser in writing
of the reasons why the appraiser is being removed from the appraiser panel
of the appraisal management company; and</para><para>(b) Providing an opportunity for the appraiser
to respond to the notification from the appraisal management company.</para>
<para>(3) An appraiser
who is removed from the appraiser panel of an appraisal management company
may file a complaint with the board for a review of the decision of the appraisal
management company. The scope of the board's review in any such case is limited
to determining that the appraisal management company has complied with subsection
(2) of this section and whether a violation of the Real Property Appraiser
Act has occurred.</para><para>(4) If an appraiser files a complaint against an appraisal management
company pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, the board shall adjudicate
the complaint within one hundred eighty days after the filing of the complaint.</para>
<para>(5) If, after
opportunity for hearing and review, the board determines that an appraisal
management company acted improperly in removing the appraiser from the appraiser
panel, the board shall:</para><para>(a) Provide written findings to the involved parties;</para>
<para>(b) Provide
an opportunity for the appraisal management company and the appraiser to respond
to the findings; and</para><para>(c) Make recommendations for action.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 15.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Real Property Appraiser Act,</emphasis> see section 76-2201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>