<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id226"><amendatorysection statutenumber="76-3203.01" chaptername="Real Property"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3203.01</statuteno><catchline>Appraiser panel; removal; notice; reconsideration of removal.</catchline><para>(1) Only AMC appraisers considered to be in good standing in all jurisdictions in which an active credential is held shall be included on an appraisal management company’s appraiser panel.</para><para>(2) An appraisal management company shall remove any AMC appraiser from its appraiser panel within thirty days after receiving notice that the AMC appraiser:</para><para>(a) Is no longer considered to be in good standing in one or more jurisdictions in which he or she holds an active credential or equivalent;</para><para>(b) The AMC appraiser’s credential or equivalent has been refused, denied, canceled, or revoked; or</para><para>(c) The AMC appraiser has surrendered his or her credential or equivalent in lieu of revocation.</para><para>(3) Pursuant to subdivision (5)(c) of section 76-3202, an appraiser panel shall include each AMC appraiser as of the earliest date on which such person was accepted by the appraisal management company:</para><para>(a) For consideration for future assignments in covered transactions or for secondary mortgage market participants in connection with covered transactions; or</para><para>(b) For engagement to perform one or more appraisals on behalf of a creditor for a covered transaction or for a secondary mortgage market participant in connection with covered transactions.</para><para>(4) Any AMC appraiser included on an appraisal management company’s appraiser panel pursuant to subsection (3) of this section shall remain on such appraiser panel until the date on which the appraisal management company:</para><para>(a) Sends written notice to the AMC appraiser removing him or her from the appraiser panel. Such written notice shall include an explanation of the action taken by the appraisal management company;</para><para>(b) Receives written notice from the AMC appraiser requesting that he or she be removed from the appraiser panel. Such written notice shall include an explanation of the action requested by the AMC appraiser; or</para><para>(c) Receives written notice on behalf of the AMC appraiser of the death or incapacity of the AMC appraiser. Such written notice shall include an explanation on behalf of the AMC appraiser.</para><para>(5) Upon receipt of notice that he or she has been removed from the appraisal management company’s appraiser panel, an AMC appraiser shall have thirty days to provide a response to the appraisal management company that removed the AMC appraiser from its appraiser panel. Upon receipt of the AMC appraiser’s response, the appraisal management company shall have thirty days to reconsider the removal and provide a written response to the AMC appraiser.</para><para>(6) If an AMC appraiser is removed from an appraisal management company’s appraiser panel pursuant to subsection (4) of this section, nothing shall prevent the appraisal management company at any time during the twelve months after removal from the appraiser panel from considering such person for future assignments in covered transactions or for secondary mortgage market participants in connection with covered transactions, or for engagement to perform one or more appraisals on behalf of a creditor for a covered transaction or for a secondary mortgage market participant in connection with covered transactions. If such consideration or engagement takes place, the removal shall be deemed not to have occurred and such person shall be deemed to have been included on the appraiser panel without interruption.</para><para>(7) Any AMC appraiser included on an appraisal management company’s appraiser panel engaged in appraisal practice or real property appraisal activity as a result of an assignment provided by an appraisal management company shall be free from inappropriate influence and coercion as required by the appraisal independence standards established under section 129E of the federal Truth in Lending Act, as such section existed on January 1, 2018, including the requirements for payment of a reasonable and customary fee to AMC appraisers when the appraisal management company is engaged in providing appraisal management services.</para><para>(8) An appraisal management company shall select an AMC appraiser from its appraiser panel for an assignment who is independent of the transaction and who has the requisite education, expertise, and experience necessary to competently complete the assignment for the particular market and property type.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB17, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>