<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id26">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" id="id28" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="76-3410"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3410</statuteno><catchline id="id31">Transfer on death
deed; essential elements and formalities; warning; limitation on action to set aside transfer.</catchline><para>(a) A transfer on death deed:</para>
<para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (2) of this
subsection, must contain the essential elements and formalities of a properly
recordable inter vivos deed;</para>
<para>(2) Must state that the transfer to the designated beneficiary
is to occur at the transferor's death;</para>
<para>(3) Must contain the warnings provided in subsection (b) of
this section; and</para>
<para>(4) Must be recorded (i) within thirty days after being executed
as required in section 76-3409, (ii) before the transferor's death, and (iii)
in the public records in the office of the register of deeds of the county
where the property is located.</para>
<para>(b)(1) A transfer on death deed shall contain the following
warnings:</para>
<para>WARNING: The property transferred remains subject to inheritance
taxation in Nebraska to the same extent as if owned by the transferor at death.
Failure to timely pay inheritance taxes is subject to interest and penalties
as provided by law.</para>
<para>WARNING: The designated beneficiary is personally liable,
to the extent of the value of the property transferred, to account for medicaid
reimbursement to the extent necessary to discharge any such claim remaining
after application of the assets of the transferor's estate. The designated
beneficiary may also be personally liable, to the extent of the value of the
property transferred, for claims against the estate, statutory allowances
to the transferor's surviving spouse and children, and the expenses of administration
to the extent needed to pay such amounts by the personal representative.</para>
<para>WARNING: The Department of Health and Human Services may require
revocation of this deed by a transferor, a transferor's spouse, or both a
transferor and the transferor's spouse in order to qualify or remain qualified
for medicaid assistance.</para>
<para>(2) No recorded transfer on death deed shall be invalidated
because of any defects in the wording of the warnings required by this subsection.</para>
<para>(c) No action
may be commenced to set aside a transfer on death deed, based on failure to
comply with the requirement of disinterested witnesses pursuant to section
76-3409, more than ninety days after the date of death of the transferor or,
if there is more than one transferor, more than ninety days after the date
of death of the last surviving transferor.</para><para>(d) Notwithstanding subsection (c) of this section,
an action to set aside a transfer on death deed, based on failure to comply
with the requirement of disinterested witnesses pursuant to section 76-3409,
in which the transferor or, if there is more than one transferor, the last
surviving transferor, has died prior to May 8, 2013, shall be commenced by
the later of (1) ninety days after the date of death of the transferor or,
if there is more than one transferor, ninety days after the date of death
of the last surviving transferor, or (2) ninety days after May 8, 2013.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB536, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB345, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>