<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-3203.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3203.02</statuteno><catchline>Federally regulated appraisal management company; report; board; fees; powers.</catchline><para>(1) A federally regulated appraisal management company must report all information required to be submitted to the Appraisal Subcommittee pursuant to Title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, the AMC rule, and any policy or rule established by the Appraisal Subcommittee related to its operation in this state, including, but not limited to, the collection of information related to ownership limitations.</para><para>(2) The board may collect and transmit to the Appraisal Subcommittee any fees established by the Appraisal Subcommittee pursuant to Title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, the AMC rule, and any policy or rule established by the Appraisal Subcommittee required for inclusion on the AMC Registry, and collect any fees as deemed appropriate by the board for services provided as related to a federally regulated appraisal management company's operation in this state.</para><para>(3) Nothing in the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act shall prevent issuance by the board of a registration to a federally regulated appraisal management company.</para><para>(4) Except for a federally regulated appraisal management company that holds a registration issued by the board, section 76-3202, and this section, a federally regulated appraisal management company is exempt from the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB17, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB989, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>