<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id108">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id110"  statutenumber="76-3417"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3417</statuteno><catchline>Liability for creditor claims and
statutory allowances.</catchline><para>(a) If other assets of the estate of the transferor are
insufficient to pay all claims against the transferor's estate, statutory
allowances to the transferor's surviving spouse and children, and the expenses
of administration, a transfer under the Nebraska Uniform Real Property Transfer
on Death Act subjects the beneficiary to personal liability as provided in
this section to the extent needed to pay all claims against the transferor's
estate, statutory allowances to the transferor's surviving spouse and children,
and the expenses of administration.</para>
<para>(b)(1) A beneficiary
who receives property through a transfer on death deed upon the death of the
transferor is liable to account to the personal representative of the transferor's
estate for a proportionate share of the fair market value of the equity in
the interest received to the extent necessary to discharge the claims and
allowances described in subsection (a) of this section remaining unpaid after
application of the transferor's estate. For purposes of this subdivision (b)(1),
the fair market value shall be determined as of the date of death of the transferor.
For purposes of this subdivision (b)(1), the beneficiary's proportionate share
means the proportionate share of all nonprobate transfers recovered by the
personal representative for the payment of the claims and allowances under
the Nebraska Uniform Real Property Transfer on Death Act and sections 30-2726,
30-2743, and 30-3850. </para><para>(2) A proceeding to assert the liability for claims against the
estate and statutory allowances may not be commenced unless the personal representative
has received a written demand by the surviving spouse, a creditor, a child,
or a person acting for a child of the transferor. The proceeding must be commenced
within one year after the death of the transferor.</para><para>(c) A beneficiary against
whom a proceeding to account is brought may join as a party to the proceeding
a surviving party or beneficiary of any other transfer on death deed for the
same transferor or any other asset of the transferor subject to sections 30-2726,
30-2743, and 30-3850.</para><para>(d) Assets recovered by the personal representative pursuant to
this section shall be administered as part of the transferor's estate.</para>
<para>(e) Nothing
in this section shall be construed to limit the rights of creditors under
other laws of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB536, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>