<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-3503" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3503</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Radon Resistant New Construction Act:</para><para>(1) Active radon mitigation system means a family of radon mitigation systems involving mechanically driven soil depressurization, including subslab depressurization, drain tile depressurization, block wall depressurization, and submembrane depressurization. Active radon mitigation system is also known as active soil depressurization;</para><para>(2) Building contractor means any individual, corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or other business entity that engages in new construction;</para><para>(3) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(4) New construction means any original construction of a single-family home or a multifamily dwelling, including apartments, group homes, condominiums, and townhouses, or any original construction of a building used for commercial, industrial, educational, or medical purposes. New construction does not include additions to existing structures or remodeling of existing structures;</para><para>(5) Passive radon mitigation system means a pipe installed in new construction that relies solely on the convective flow of air upward for soil gas depressurization and may consist of multiple pipes routed through conditioned space from below the foundation to above the roof;</para><para>(6) Radon mitigation specialist means an individual who is licensed by the department as a radon mitigation specialist in accordance with the Radiation Control Act; and</para><para>(7) Radon resistant new construction means construction that utilizes design elements and construction techniques that passively resist radon entry and prepare a building for an active postconstruction mitigation system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB9, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB130, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Radiation Control Act,</emphasis> see section 71-3519.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>