<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id137"  statutenumber="76-3216" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3216</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited acts; board; violations; enforcement actions; fine; considerations; report required.</catchline><para>(1) It is unlawful for a person to directly or indirectly engage in or attempt to engage in business as an appraisal management company or to advertise or hold itself out as engaging in or conducting business as an appraisal management company in this state without first obtaining a registration or by meeting the requirements as a federally regulated appraisal management company.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 76-3204, any person who, directly or indirectly for another, offers, attempts, or agrees to perform all actions described in subdivision (5) of section 76-3202 or any action described in subdivision (6) of such section, shall be deemed an appraisal management company within the meaning of the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act, and such action shall constitute sufficient contact with this state for the exercise of personal jurisdiction over such person in any action arising out of the act.</para><para>(3) The board may issue a cease and desist order against any person who violates this section by performing any action described in subdivision (5) or (6) of section 76-3202 without the appropriate registration. Such order shall be final ten days after issuance unless such person requests a hearing pursuant to section 76-3217. The board may, through the Attorney General, obtain an order from the district court for the enforcement of the cease and desist order.</para><para>(4) To the extent permitted by any applicable federal legislation or regulation, the board may censure an appraisal management company, conditionally or unconditionally suspend or revoke its registration, or levy fines or impose civil penalties not to exceed five thousand dollars for a first offense and not to exceed ten thousand dollars for a second or subsequent offense, if the board determines that an appraisal management company is attempting to perform, has performed, or has attempted to perform any of the following:</para><para>(a) A material violation of the act;</para><para>(b) A violation of any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the board; or</para><para>(c) Procurement of a registration for itself or any other person by fraud, misrepresentation, or deceit.</para><para>(5) In order to promote voluntary compliance, encourage appraisal management companies to correct errors promptly, and ensure a fair and consistent approach to enforcement, the board shall endeavor to impose fines or civil penalties that are reasonable in light of the nature, extent, and severity of the violation. The board shall also take action against an appraisal management company's registration only after less severe sanctions have proven insufficient to ensure behavior consistent with the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act. When deciding whether to impose a sanction permitted by subsection (4) of this section, determining the sanction that is most appropriate in a specific instance, or making any other discretionary decision regarding the enforcement of the act, the board shall consider whether an appraisal management company:</para><para>(a) Has an effective program reasonably designed to ensure compliance with the act;</para><para>(b) Has taken prompt and appropriate steps to correct and prevent the recurrence of any detected violations; and</para><para>(c) Has independently reported to the board any significant violations or potential violations of the act prior to an imminent threat of disclosure or investigation and within a reasonably prompt time after becoming aware of the occurrence of such violations.</para><para>(6) Any violation of appraisal-related laws or rules and regulations, and disciplinary action taken against an appraisal management company, shall be reported to the Appraisal Subcommittee as required by Title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, the AMC final rule, and any policy or rule established by the Appraisal Subcommittee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB17, &#167; 17. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>