
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id13" renumber="yes"><amendatorysection id="id15" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-3504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3504</statuteno><catchline>Radon Resistant New Construction Task Force; created; members; meetings; expenses; duties.</catchline><para id="id16">(1) The Radon Resistant New Construction Task Force is created. The task force shall consist of the chief medical officer of the Division of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services as designated in section 81-3115 or his or her designee, who shall serve as the chairperson of the task force, and the following additional members to be appointed by the Governor:</para><para id="id18">(a) Three representatives of home builders' associations in Nebraska, each from a different congressional district;</para><para id="id19">(b) A representative of a home inspectors' association in Nebraska;</para><para id="id20">(c) Two representatives of commercial construction associations, one of whom must have experience related to large-scale projects and one of whom must have experience related to medium-scale to small-scale projects;</para><para id="id21">(d) A representative of a Nebraska realtors' organization;</para><para id="id22">(e) A representative of a respiratory disease organization;</para><para id="id23">(f) A representative of a cancer research and prevention organization;</para><para>(g) A representative of the League of Nebraska Municipalities;</para><para id="id25">(h) Three community public health representatives, each from a different congressional district;</para><para id="id26">(i) A professional engineer as defined in section 81-3422;</para><para id="id27">(j) An architect as defined in section 81-3404; and</para><para>(k) A representative with expertise in residential or commercial building codes.</para><para id="id28">(2) The task force shall meet at the call of the chairperson. The appointed members of the task force shall serve without compensation but shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The department shall provide staff and support for the operation of the task force.</para><para id="id29">(3) The task force shall develop minimum standards for radon resistant new construction and shall recommend such minimum standards to the Governor, to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature, and to the Urban Affairs Committee of the Legislature. In developing such minimum standards, the task force shall:</para><para>(a) Design the minimum standards so that they may be enforced by a county, city, or village as part of its local building code;</para><para>(b) Consider Appendix F of the International Residential Code for One- and Two-Family Dwellings, 2012 edition, published by the International Code Council; and</para><para>(c) Consider including the following provisions in such minimum standards:</para><para>(i) A requirement that the installation of an active radon mitigation system only be performed by a building contractor or his or her subcontractors or by a radon mitigation specialist;</para><para>(ii) A requirement that the installation of radon resistant new construction only be performed by a building contractor or his or her subcontractors or by a radon mitigation specialist; and</para><para>(iii) A requirement that only a building contractor or his or her subcontractors or a radon mitigation specialist be allowed to install a radon vent fan or upgrade a passive new construction pipe to an active radon mitigation system.</para><para id="id30">(4) The task force shall provide its recommendations by April 15, 2018. The task force and this section terminate on May 1, 2018.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB9, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>