<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection id="id15" chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-3504" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3504</statuteno><catchline>Radon resistant new construction; minimum standards.</catchline><para>Except as provided in section 76-3505, new construction built after September 1, 2019, in the State of Nebraska that is intended to be regularly occupied by people shall be built using radon resistant new construction. Such construction shall meet the following minimum standards:</para><para>(1) Sumps:</para><para>(a) A sump pit open to soil or serving as the termination point for subslab or exterior drain tile loops shall be covered with a gasketed or otherwise sealed lid;</para><para>(b) A sump used as the suction point in a subslab depressurization system shall have a lid designed to accommodate the vent pipe; and</para><para>(c) A sump used as a floor drain shall have a lid equipped with a trapped inlet;</para><para>(2) A passive subslab depressurization system shall be installed during construction in basement or slab-on-grade buildings, including the following components:</para><para>(a) Vent pipe:</para><para>(i)(A) A minimum three-inch diameter acrylonitrile butadiene styrene (ABS), polyvinyl chloride (PVC), or equivalent gas-tight pipe shall be embedded vertically into the subslab permeable material before the slab is cast. A "T" fitting or equivalent method shall be used to ensure that the pipe opening remains within the subslab permeable material; or</para><para>(B) A minimum three-inch diameter ABS, PVC, or equivalent gas-tight pipe shall be inserted directly into an interior perimeter drain tile loop or through a sealed sump cover where the sump is exposed to the subslab or connected to it through a drainage system;</para><para>(ii) The pipe shall be extended up through the building floors and terminate at least twelve inches above the surface of the roof in a location at least ten feet away from any window or other opening into the conditioned spaces of the building that is less than two feet below the exhaust point and ten feet from any window or other opening in adjoining or adjacent buildings; and</para><para>(iii) In buildings where interior footings or other barriers separate the subslab gas-permeable material, each area shall be fitted with an individual vent pipe. Vent pipes shall connect to a single vent that terminates above the roof or each individual vent pipe shall terminate separately above the roof. All exposed and visible interior radon vent pipes shall be identified with at least one label on each floor and in accessible attics. Such label shall read: Radon Reduction System; and</para><para>(3) Power source: In order to provide for future installation of an active radon mitigation system, an electrical circuit terminated in an approved box shall be installed during construction in the attic or other anticipated location of vent pipe fans.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB9, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB130, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>