<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id84">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id86" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="76-3207"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>76-3207</statuteno><catchline>Applicant for registration; fingerprint
submission; criminal history record check; costs.</catchline><para>(1) An appraisal management company applying
for registration in this state shall not:</para>
<para>(a) In whole
or in part, directly or indirectly, be owned by any person who has had an
appraiser license or certificate in this state or in any other state refused,
denied, canceled, surrendered in lieu of revocation, or revoked; and</para>
<para>(b) Be more
than ten percent owned by a person who is not of good moral character, which
for purposes of this section shall require that such person has not been convicted
of, or entered a plea of nolo contendere to, a felony relating to the appraisal
practice or any crime involving fraud, misrepresentation, or moral turpitude.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of subdivision
(1)(b) of this section, each individual owner of more than ten percent of
an appraisal management company shall, at the time an application for registration
as an appraisal management company is made, submit two copies of legible ink-rolled
fingerprint cards or equivalent electronic fingerprint submissions to the
board for delivery to the Nebraska State Patrol in a form approved by both
the Nebraska State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. The board
shall pay the Nebraska State Patrol the costs associated with conducting a
fingerprint-based national criminal history record check through the Nebraska
State Patrol and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with such record check
to be carried out by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 7.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>