<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id47">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id49" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="76-3203"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo>
<statuteno>76-3203</statuteno><catchline>Registration; application; contents;
form; surety bond; renewal.</catchline><para>(1) It is unlawful for a person to directly or indirectly
engage in or attempt to engage in business as an appraisal management company
or to advertise or hold itself out as engaging in or conducting business as
an appraisal management company in this state without first obtaining a registration
issued by the board.</para>
<para>(2) An application
for the registration required by subsection (1) of this section shall include
the following information:</para><para>(a) The name of the person seeking registration
and any other name or names, if any, under which it will do business in this
state;</para><para>(b) The business address of the person seeking registration;</para>
<para>(c) The telephone
contact information of the person seeking registration;</para>
<para>(d) If the
person seeking registration is not a corporation that is domiciled in this
state, the name and contact information for the person's agent for service
of process in this state;</para><para>(e) The name, address, and contact information for any person that
owns ten percent or more of the person seeking registration;</para>
<para>(f) The name,
address, and contact information for one controlling person designated as
the main contact for all communication between the person seeking registration
and the board;</para><para>(g) A certification that the person seeking registration has a system
and process in place to verify that an appraiser selected to the appraiser
panel of the person seeking registration holds a license or certification
in good standing in this state pursuant to the Real Property Appraiser Act;</para>
<para>(h) A certification
that the person seeking registration requires appraisers completing appraisal
services at the person's request to comply with the Uniform Standards of Professional
Appraisal Practice, including the requirements for geographic and product
competence;</para><para>(i) A certification that the person seeking registration has a system
in place to verify that only licensed or certified appraisers are used for
federally related transactions;</para><para>(j) A certification that the person seeking
registration has a system in place to require that appraisals are conducted
independently and free from inappropriate influence and coercion as required
by the appraisal independence standards established under section 129E of
the federal Truth in Lending Act, as amended, including the requirements for
payment of a reasonable and customary fee to appraisers when the appraisal
management company is providing appraisal services for a consumer credit transaction
secured by the principal dwelling of a consumer;</para><para>(k) A certification that
the person seeking registration maintains a detailed record of each request
for appraisal services that it receives and the appraiser that performs the
residential real estate appraisal services for the appraisal management company;</para>
<para>(l) If the
person seeking registration is a nonresident, an irrevocable consent for service
of process, if required pursuant to section 76-3205; and</para>
<para>(m) Any other
information required by the board which is reasonably necessary to implement
the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act.</para>
<para>(3) An applicant
for registration as an appraisal management company in this state shall submit
to the board an application on a form or forms prescribed by the board.</para>
<para>(4) An applicant for
registration as an appraisal management company in this state shall furnish
to the board, at the time of making application, a surety bond in the amount
of twenty-five thousand dollars. The surety bond required under this subsection
shall be issued by a bonding company or insurance company authorized to do
business in this state, and a copy of the bond shall be filed with the board.
The bond shall be in favor of the state for the benefit of any person who
is damaged by any violation of the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration
Act. The bond shall also be in favor of any person damaged by such a violation.
Any person claiming against the bond for a violation of the act may maintain
an action at law against the appraisal management company and against the
surety. The aggregate liability of the surety to all persons damaged by a
violation of the act by an appraisal management company shall not exceed the
amount of the bond. The bond shall be maintained until one year after the
date that the appraisal management company ceases operation in this state.</para>
<para>(5) A registration
issued pursuant to the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration
Act shall be valid for two years after the date on which it is issued. An
application for the renewal of a registration shall include substantially
similar information required for the initial registration as provided in subsection
(2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Real Property Appraiser Act,</emphasis> see section 76-2201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>