<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id154"><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" statutenumber="76-3802"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3802</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>In the Uniform Unlawful Restrictions in Land Records Act:</para><para>(1) Amendment means a document that removes an unlawful restriction.</para><para>(2) Document means a record recorded or eligible to be recorded in land records.</para><para>(3) Governing instrument means a document recorded in land records that:</para><para>(A) establishes a governing body responsible for management of common areas or facilities used by more than one owner of a property interest affected by the document; and</para><para>(B) requires contribution, enforceable by a lien on a separate property interest, of a share of taxes, insurance premiums, maintenance, or improvement of, or services or other expenses for the common benefit of, the real property described in the document.</para><para>(4) Index means a system that enables a search for a document in land records.</para><para>(5) Land records means documents and indexes maintained by a recorder.</para><para>(6) Owner means a person that has a fee interest in real property.</para><para>(7) Person means an individual, estate, business or nonprofit entity, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or other legal entity.</para><para>(8) Record, used as a noun, means information:</para><para>(A) inscribed on a tangible medium; or</para><para>(B) stored in an electronic or other medium and retrievable in perceivable form.</para><para>(9) Recorder means an officer authorized under other law of this state to accept a document for recordation in land records.</para><para>(10) Remove means eliminate any apparent or purportedly continuing effect on title to real property.</para><para>(11) Unlawful restriction means a prohibition, restriction, covenant, or condition in a document that purports to interfere with or restrict the transfer, use, or occupancy of real property:</para><para>(A) on the basis of race, color, religion, national origin, sex, familial status, disability, or other personal characteristics; and</para><para>(B) in violation of other law of this state or federal law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB21, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>