<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="76-3112"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3112</statuteno><catchline>Receiver of fee; record document;
contents; amendment; payee failure to comply; effect; affidavit; recording;
effect.</catchline><para>(1)
For a private transfer fee obligation in existence prior to March 11, 2011,
the receiver of the fee shall, within thirty days after March 11, 2011, or
before any transfer of real property subject to the private transfer fee,
whichever period is shorter, record against the real property subject to the
private transfer fee obligation a separate document in the register of deeds
office of the county in which the real property is located that meets all
of the following requirements:</para>
<para>(a) The title
of the document shall be "Notice of Private Transfer Fee Obligation" in at
least fourteen-point, boldface type;</para><para>(b) The amount, if the private transfer fee is a flat
amount, or the percentage of the sales price constituting the cost of the
private transfer fee, or such other basis by which the private transfer fee
is to be calculated;</para><para>(c) The date or circumstances under which the private
transfer fee obligation expires, if any;</para><para>(d) The purpose for which the funds from the private
transfer fee obligation will be used;</para><para>(e) The name of the person to whom funds are to be
paid and specific contact information regarding where the funds are to be
sent;</para><para>(f)
The acknowledged signature of the payee; and</para><para>(g) The legal description
of the real property purportedly burdened by the private transfer fee obligation.</para>
<para>(2) The person
to whom the private transfer fee is to be paid may file an amendment to the
notice of private transfer fee obligation containing new contact information,
but such amendment must contain the recording information of the notice of
private transfer fee obligation which it amends and the legal description
of the property burdened by the private transfer fee obligation.</para>
<para>(3) If the payee
fails to comply fully with subsection (1) of this section, the grantor of
any real property burdened by the private transfer fee obligation may proceed
with the transfer of any interest in the real property to any grantee and
in so doing shall be deemed to have acted in good faith and shall not be subject
to any obligations under the private transfer fee obligation. In such event,
any transfer of the real property thereafter shall be free and clear of the
private transfer fee and private transfer fee obligation.</para>
<para>(4) If the payee
fails to provide a written statement of the private transfer fee payable within
thirty days after the date of a written request for the same sent to the address
shown in the notice of private transfer fee obligation, then the grantor,
on recording of the affidavit required under subsection (5) of this section,
may transfer any interest in the real property to any grantee without payment
of the private transfer fee and shall not be subject to any further obligations
under the private transfer fee obligation. In such event, any transfer of
the real property shall be free and clear of the private transfer fee and
private transfer fee obligation.</para><para>(5) An affidavit stating the facts enumerated under
subsection (6) of this section shall be recorded in the office of the register
of deeds in the county in which the real property is situated prior to or
simultaneously with a transfer pursuant to subsection (4) of this section
of real property unburdened by a private transfer fee obligation. An affidavit
filed under this subsection shall state that the affiant has actual knowledge
of, and is competent to testify to, the facts in the affidavit and shall include
the legal description of the real property burdened by the private transfer
fee obligation, the name of the owner of such real property at the time of
the signing of such affidavit, a reference by recording information to the
instrument of record containing the private transfer fee obligation, and an
acknowledgment that the affiant is testifying under penalty of perjury.</para>
<para>(6) When recorded,
an affidavit as described in subsection (5) of this section shall constitute
prima facie evidence that:</para><para>(a) A request for the written statement of the private
transfer fee payable in order to obtain a release of the fee imposed by the
private transfer fee obligation was sent to the address shown in the notification;
and</para><para>(b)
The entity listed on the notice of private transfer fee obligation failed
to provide the written statement of the private transfer fee payable within
thirty days after the date of the notice sent to the address shown in the
notification.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB26, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>