<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id148"  statutenumber="76-3217" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3217</statuteno><catchline>Violations; disciplinary hearings; notice; procedure; costs.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall conduct disciplinary hearings for any violation of the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(2) Before the board may censure, suspend, or revoke the registration of, or levy a fine or civil penalty against, an appraisal management company, the board shall notify the appraisal management company in writing of any charges made under the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration Act at least twenty days prior to the date set for the hearing and shall permit the appraisal management company an opportunity to be heard in person or by counsel. The notice shall be satisfied by personal service on the contact person of the appraisal management company or agent for service of process in this state or by sending the notice by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the address of the contact person of the appraisal management company that is on file with the board.</para><para>(3) Any hearing pursuant to this section shall be heard by a hearing officer at a time and place prescribed by the board. The hearing officer may make findings of fact and shall deliver such findings to the board. The board shall take such disciplinary action as it deems appropriate, subject to the limitations contained within section 76-3216. Costs incurred for an administrative hearing, including fees of counsel, the hearing officer, court reporters, investigators, and witnesses, shall be taxed as costs in such action as the board may direct.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB17, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>