<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id135">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Real Property" id="id137" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="76-3216"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>76-3216</statuteno><catchline>Board; violations; enforcement actions;
fine; considerations.</catchline><para>(1) To the extent permitted by any applicable federal legislation
or regulation, the board may censure an appraisal management company, conditionally
or unconditionally suspend or revoke the registration issued to the appraisal
management company under the Nebraska Appraisal Management Company Registration
Act, or levy fines or impose civil penalties not to exceed five thousand dollars
for a first offense and not to exceed ten thousand dollars for a second or
subsequent offense, if the board determines that an appraisal management company
is attempting to perform, has performed, or has attempted to perform any of
the following:</para>
<para>(a) A material
violation of the act;</para><para>(b) A violation of any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated
by the board; or</para><para>(c) Procurement of a registration for itself or any other person
by fraud, misrepresentation, or deceit.</para><para>(2) In order to promote voluntary compliance,
encourage appraisal management companies to correct errors promptly, and ensure
a fair and consistent approach to enforcement, the board shall endeavor to
impose fines or civil penalties that are reasonable in light of the nature,
extent, and severity of the violation. The board shall also take action against
an appraisal management company's registration only after less severe sanctions
have proven insufficient to ensure behavior consistent with the Nebraska Appraisal
Management Company Registration Act. When deciding whether to impose a sanction
permitted by subsection (1) of this section, determining the sanction that
is most appropriate in a specific instance, or making any other discretionary
decision regarding the enforcement of the act, the board shall consider whether
an appraisal management company:</para><para>(a) Has an effective program reasonably
designed to ensure compliance with the act;</para><para>(b) Has taken prompt and appropriate steps
to correct and prevent the recurrence of any detected violations; and</para>
<para>(c) Has independently
reported to the board any significant violations or potential violations of
the act prior to an imminent threat of disclosure or investigation and within
a reasonably prompt time after becoming aware of the occurrence of such violations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB410, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>