<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="constitution">
<section>
<sectno></sectno>
<constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="III-24">
    <bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo>
<articlesectno>III-24</articlesectno>
<catchline>Games of chance, lotteries, and gift enterprises; restrictions; use of state lottery proceeds; parimutuel wagering on horseraces; bingo games; laws relating to games of chance, applicability.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in this section, the Legislature shall not authorize any game of chance or any lottery or gift enterprise when the consideration for a chance to participate involves the payment of money for the purchase of property, services, or a chance or admission ticket or requires an expenditure of substantial effort or time.</para>
<para>(2) The Legislature may authorize and regulate a state lottery pursuant to subsection (3) of this section and other lotteries, raffles, and gift enterprises which are intended solely as business promotions or the proceeds of which are to be used solely for charitable or community betterment purposes without profit to the promoter of such lotteries, raffles, or gift enterprises.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The Legislature may establish a lottery to be operated and regulated by the State of Nebraska. The proceeds of the lottery shall be appropriated by the Legislature for the costs of establishing and maintaining the lottery and for the following purposes, as directed by the Legislature:</para>
<para>(i) The first five hundred thousand dollars after the payment of prizes and operating expenses shall be transferred to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund;</para>
<para>(ii) Forty-four and one-half percent of the money remaining after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund to be used as provided in the Nebraska Environmental Trust Act;</para>
<para>(iii) Forty-four and one-half percent of the money remaining after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be used for education as the Legislature may direct;</para>
<para>(iv) Ten percent of the money remaining after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Nebraska State Fair Board if the most populous city within the county in which the fair is located provides matching funds equivalent to ten percent of the funds available for transfer. Such matching funds may be obtained from the city and any other private or public entity, except that no portion of such matching funds shall be provided by the state. If the Nebraska State Fair ceases operations, ten percent of the money remaining after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the General Fund; and</para>
<para>(v) One percent of the money remaining after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund.</para>
<para>(b) No lottery game shall be conducted as part of the lottery unless the type of game has been approved by a majority of the members of the Legislature.</para>
    <para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit (a) the enactment of laws providing for the licensing and regulation of wagering on the results of horseraces, wherever run, either within or outside of the state, by the parimutuel method, when such wagering is conducted by licensees within a licensed racetrack enclosure or (b) the enactment of laws providing for the licensing and regulation of bingo games conducted by nonprofit associations which have been in existence for a period of five years immediately preceding the application for license, except that bingo games cannot be conducted by agents or lessees of such associations on a percentage basis.</para><para>(5) This section shall not apply to any law which is enacted contemporaneously with the adoption of this subsection or at any time thereafter and which provides for the licensing, authorization, regulation, or taxation of all forms of games of chance when such games of chance are conducted by authorized gaming operators within a licensed racetrack enclosure.</para>
</constitutionalsection>
</section>
<source>
<para>Neb. Const. art. III, sec. 21 (1875); </para>
<para>Amended 1934, Initiative Measure No. 332; </para>
<para>Amended 1958, Initiative Measure No. 302; </para>
<para>Amended 1962, Laws 1961, c. 248, sec. 1, p. 735; </para>
<para>Amended 1968, Laws 1967, c. 307, sec. 1, p. 832; </para>
<para>Amended 1988, Laws 1988, LR 15, sec. 1; </para>
<para>Amended 1992, Laws 1991, LR 24CA, sec. 1; </para>
<para>Amended 2004, Laws 2004, LR 209CA, sec. 1; </para><para>Amended 2020, Initiative Measure No. 429.</para></source>
<crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Environmental Trust Act,</emphasis> see section 81-15,167.</para></crossreference>
<annotation>
<para>This provision plainly requires that parimutuel wagering on horses must be conducted by an entity licensed to do so and must be conducted by licensees at a racetrack enclosure which is licensed to operate horse races. Wagering that occurs in a detached facility, one that is by definition outside a licensed racetrack enclosure, cannot logically occur within a licensed racetrack enclosure as required by this provision. State ex rel. Stenberg v. Douglas Racing Corp., 246 Neb. 901, 524 N.W.2d 61 (1994).</para>
<para>Free replays are things of value and when obtained on a gambling device constitute property. State ex rel. Spire v. Strawberries, Inc., 239 Neb. 1, 473 N.W.2d 428 (1991).</para>
<para>"Proceeds" means net proceeds and "promoter" means only the person or organization legally responsible for operating a lottery, not each employee thereof. State v. City Betterment Corp., 197 Neb. 575, 250 N.W.2d 601 (1977).</para>
<para>Where registration was required to participate in drawing for prize, the element of consideration was present to constitute a lottery. State ex rel. Line v. Grant, 162 Neb. 210, 75 N.W.2d 611 (1956).</para>
<para>Pinball machine was prohibited as game of chance. Baedaro v. Caldwell, 156 Neb. 489, 56 N.W.2d 706 (1953).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
