<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="IV-25"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>IV-25</articlesectno><catchline>Salaries of officials; fees.</catchline><para>The officers provided for in this article shall receive such salaries as may be provided by law. Such officers, or such other officers as may be provided for by law, shall not receive for their own use any fees, costs, or interest upon public money in their hands. All fees that may hereafter be payable by law for services performed, or received by an officer provided for in this article, by virtue of his office shall be paid forthwith into the state treasury.</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. V, sec. 24 (1875); </para><para>Amended 1920, Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, No. 13; </para><para>Transferred by Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, art. IV, sec. 25; </para><para>Amended 1956, Laws 1955, c. 193, sec. 1, p. 555. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former law, salary of executive officer could not be changed more than once in eight years. State ex rel. Laughlin v. Johnson, 156 Neb. 671, 57 N.W.2d 531 (1953).</para><para>County officer is required to perform the duties of his office for the compensation allowed him by statute. Hoctor v. State, 141 Neb. 329, 3 N.W.2d 558 (1942).</para><para>During temporary absence of Governor from state, Lieutenant Governor is entitled only to salary fixed by law for the office of Lieutenant Governor and not for office of Governor. Johnson v. Johnson, 141 Neb. 239, 3 N.W.2d 414 (1942).</para><para>Salary of State Railway Commissioner is subject to garnishment under statute in force at time he was candidate and elected to office. Department of Banking v. Foe, 136 Neb. 422, 286 N.W. 264 (1939).</para><para>Nebraska State Board of Agriculture was not a public agency so as to require funds to be paid into state treasury. Crete Mills v. Nebraska State Board of Agriculture, 132 Neb. 244, 271 N.W. 684 (1937).</para><para>Act providing for refunding of excess grain inspection fees is not in conflict herewith. Bollen v. Price, 129 Neb. 342, 261 N.W. 689 (1935).</para><para>Occupancy by Governor of mansion provided by state is not a perquisite of office or other compensation. State v. Sheldon, 78 Neb. 552, 111 N.W. 372 (1907).</para><para>Constitution modified all previous statutes so as to require all fees to be paid in advance into the treasury. State v. Home Insurance Co., 59 Neb. 524, 81 N.W. 443 (1900); State v. Moore, 56 Neb. 82, 76 N.W. 474 (1898); Moore v. State, 53 Neb. 831, 74 N.W. 319 (1898).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>