<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="constitution">
<section>
<sectno></sectno>
<constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="VIII-1A">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<articlesectno>VIII-1A</articlesectno>
<catchline>Levy of property tax for state purposes; prohibition.</catchline>
<para>The state shall be prohibited from levying a property tax for state purposes.</para>
</constitutionalsection>
</section>
<source>
<para>Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 1A (1954); </para>
<para>Adopted 1954, Laws 1954, Sixty-sixth Extraordinary Session, c. 5, sec. 1, p. 65; </para>
<para>Amended 1966, Initiative Measure No. 301. </para></source>
<annotation><para><emphasis>1. Not unconstitutional</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Unconstitutional</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Not unconstitutional</emphasis></para><para>Section 77-3442(2)(b) was enacted for substantially local purposes, and therefore it does not violate the prohibition under this provision against a property tax for a state purpose. Sarpy Cty. Farm Bureau v. Learning Community, 283 Neb. 212, 808 N.W.2d 598 (2012).</para><para>Section 79-1073 was enacted for substantially local purposes, and therefore, it does not violate the prohibition under this provision against a property tax for a state purpose. Sarpy Cty. Farm Bureau v. Learning Community, 283 Neb. 212, 808 N.W.2d 598 (2012).</para><para>The Class VI school system tax levy set forth in section 79-1078 (formerly section 79-438.13) is not a levy for state purposes and therefore does not violate this provision. Swanson v. State, 249 Neb. 466, 544 N.W.2d 333 (1996).</para><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of this provision of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para><para>Statutory provisions requiring counties to pay cost of maintaining a county court, prosecuting criminal law violations, and conducting state and national elections do not contravene the constitutional provision which prohibits property tax by state. State ex rel. Meyer v. County of Banner, 196 Neb. 565, 244 N.W.2d 179 (1976).</para><para>Statute authorizing or requiring a local subdivision to levy a property tax for local fire protection purposes does not contravene this section. R-R Realty Co. v. Metropolitan Utilities Dist., 184 Neb. 237, 166 N.W.2d 746 (1969).</para><para>County levies to support institutional patients in state facilities not violative of this section. Craig v. Board of Equalization of Douglas County, 183 Neb. 779, 164 N.W.2d 445 (1969).</para><para><emphasis>2. Unconstitutional</emphasis></para>
<para>A property tax in furtherance of compliance with an interstate compact is, for purposes of analysis under this provision, a property tax levied by the State for state purposes. Garey v. Nebraska Dept. of Nat. Resources, 277 Neb. 149, 759 N.W.2d 919 (2009).</para>
<para>Section 2-3225(1)(d) violates the prohibition against levying a property tax for state purposes found in this provision and is therefore unconstitutional. Garey v. Nebraska Dept. of Nat. Resources, 277 Neb. 149, 759 N.W.2d 919 (2009).</para><para>Where the state assumes control and the primary burden of financial support of a statewide system under provisions of the Nebraska Technical Community College Act, the property tax under section 79-2626 is for a state purpose under this Article. State ex rel. Western Nebraska Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 192 Neb. 201, 219 N.W.2d 454 (1974).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para>
<para>Where state and local purposes are commingled, the crucial issue turns upon a determination of whether the controlling purposes are state or local. Counties may be required to pay attorney's fees for one appointed to defend an indigent defendant. Kovarik v. County of Banner, 192 Neb. 816, 224 N.W.2d 761 (1975).</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
