<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="V-20"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>V-20</articlesectno><catchline>Officers in this Article; tenure; residence; duties; compensation.</catchline><para>All officers provided for in this Article shall hold their offices until their successors shall be qualified and they shall respectively reside in the district or county from which they shall be selected. All officers, when not otherwise provided for in this Article, shall perform such duties and receive such compensation as may be prescribed by law.</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. VI, sec. 20 (1875); </para><para>Amended 1920, Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, No. 15; </para><para>Transferred by Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, art. V, sec. 20; </para><para>Amended 1962, Laws 1961, c. 252, sec. 2(2), p. 742; </para><para>Amended 1970, Laws 1969, c. 419, sec. 1, p. 1432. </para></source><annotation><para>Elections for police judge must be held along with general election of other constitutional officers. State ex rel. McDermott v. Reilly, 94 Neb. 232, 142 N.W. 923 (1913), rehearing denied 94 Neb. 238, 143 N.W. 200 (1913); State ex rel. Benson v. Mayor and Council of the City of Hastings, 91 Neb. 304, 135 N.W. 1028 (1912).</para><para>Term includes period for which incumbent may hold over until his successor has qualified. State ex rel. Polk v. Galusha, 74 Neb. 188, 104 N.W. 197 (1905).</para><para>The term of a constitutional officer can neither be extended nor shortened by legislative act. State ex rel. Gordon v. Moores, 70 Neb. 48, 96 N.W. 1011 (1903); State ex rel. Wheeler v. Stuht, 52 Neb. 209, 71 N.W. 941 (1897).</para><para>Office of police judge falls within provisions of this section. State ex rel. Gordon v. Moores, 61 Neb. 9, 84 N.W. 399 (1900).</para><para>Territorial jurisdiction of justice of the peace is precinct for which he was elected or appointed, but judgment rendered in any other precinct is not void for that reason alone. Jones v. Church of the Holy Trinity, 15 Neb. 81, 17 N.W. 362 (1883).</para><para>District judge is state, not county, officer. Jones v. York County, 26 F.2d 623 (8th Cir. 1928).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>