<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="IV-8"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>IV-8</articlesectno><catchline>Special sessions.</catchline><para>The Governor may, on extraordinary occasions, convene the Legislature by proclamation, stating therein the purpose for which they are convened, and the Legislature shall enter upon no business except that for which they were called together.</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. V, sec. 8 (1875); </para><para>Transferred by Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, art. IV, sec. 8. </para></source><annotation><para>Under this section the Governor may, during the Legislature's special session convened pursuant to a gubernatorial proclamation, submit by an appropriate amended proclamation any additional subjects for valid legislation to be enacted at such special session of the Legislature. Jaksha v. State, 222 Neb. 690, 385 N.W.2d 922 (1986).</para><para>Amendments to Liquor Control Act, made by chapter 5, Seventy-fourth Extraordinary Session of the Legislature, were unconstitutional because not within Governor's call. Arrow Club, Inc. v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 177 Neb. 686, 131 N.W.2d 134 (1964).</para><para>Governor's call of special session of the Legislature was sufficient. State Securities Co. v. Ley, 177 Neb. 251, 128 N.W.2d 766 (1964).</para><para>Amendments made to election laws at the 1944 extraordinary session of the Legislature were within the scope of the proclamation of the Governor calling the session. State ex rel. Baldwin v. Strain, 152 Neb. 763, 42 N.W.2d 796 (1950).</para><para>Special session can transact no business except that included in objects of proclamation, calling the session. Statement in proclamation asking for revision or amendment of general incorporation law will include in its scope the regulation, control and government of railroad companies. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. Wolfe, 61 Neb. 502, 86 N.W. 441 (1901).</para><para>Proclamation calling special session may be revoked by Governor. People ex rel. Tennant v. Parker, 3 Neb. 409 (1873).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>