<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="constitution">
<section>
<sectno></sectno>
<constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="I-28">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<articlesectno>I-28</articlesectno>
<catchline>Crime victims; rights enumerated; effect; Legislature; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) A victim of a crime, as shall be defined by law, or his or her guardian or representative shall have: The right to be informed of all criminal court proceedings; the right to be present at trial unless the trial court finds sequestration necessary for a fair trial for the defendant; and  the right to be informed of, be present at, and make an oral or written statement at sentencing, parole, pardon, commutation, and conditional release proceedings. This enumeration of certain rights for crime victims shall not be construed to impair or deny others provided by law or retained by crime victims.</para>
<para>(2) The Legislature shall provide by law for the implementation of the rights granted in this section. There shall be no remedies other than as specifically provided by the Legislature for the enforcement of the rights granted by this section.</para>
<para>(3) Nothing in this section shall constitute a basis for error in favor of a defendant in any criminal proceeding, a basis for providing standing to participate as a party to any criminal proceeding, or a basis to contest the disposition of any charge.</para>
</constitutionalsection>
</section>
<source>
<para>Neb. Const. art. I, sec. 28 (1996); </para>
<para>Adopted 1996, Laws 1995, LR 21CA, sec. 1. </para>
</source>
<annotation><para>This provision is not self-executing. Legislative action is necessary to provide for the implementation of the rights provided herein. State ex rel. Lamm v. Nebraska Bd. of Pardons, 260 Neb. 1000, 620 N.W.2d 763 (2001).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc>
