<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="VII-13"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>VII-13</articlesectno><catchline>State colleges; government; board; name; selection; duties; compensation.</catchline><para>The general government of the state colleges as now existing, and such other state colleges as may be established by law, shall be vested, under the direction of the Legislature, in a board of seven members to be styled as designated by the Legislature, six of whom shall be appointed by the Governor, with the advice and consent of the Legislature, two each for a term of two, four, and six years, and two each biennium thereafter for a term of six years, and the Commissioner of Education shall be a member ex officio. The duties and powers of the board shall be prescribed by law, and the members thereof shall receive no compensation for the performance of their duties, but may be reimbursed their actual expenses incurred therein.</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 13 (1920); </para><para>Adopted 1920, Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, No. 25; </para><para>Transferred by Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, art. VII, sec. 13; </para><para>Amended 1952, Laws 1951, c. 164, sec. 2(4), p. 646; </para><para>Amended 1968, Laws 1967, c. 315, sec. 1, p. 845. </para></source><annotation><para>Board of Education of State Normal Schools was established in 1920. State ex rel. Johnson v. Hagemeister, 161 Neb. 475, 73 N.W.2d 625 (1955).</para><para>Teacher, head of department in state normal school, dismissed by president without action by board, is entitled to test, by quo warranto, the right of teacher employed to take his place. Eason v. Majors, 111 Neb. 288, 196 N.W. 133 (1923).</para><para>Upon showing that college administrative body acted from honest conviction upon belief facts showed it was for best interests of the school, and there was no showing that act was arbitrary or generated by ill will, fraud, coercion, or other such motives, court will not interfere. Levitt v. Board of Trustees of Nebraska State Colleges, 376 F.Supp. 945 (D. Neb. 1974).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>