<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN"
 "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="constitution">
<section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution"
statutenumber="XVIII-1">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<articlesectno>XVIII-1</articlesectno>
<catchline>Statement of intent.</catchline>
<para>The people of the State of Nebraska want to amend the United States
Constitution to establish term limits on Congress that will ensure representation
in Congress by true citizen lawmakers. The President of the United States
is limited by the XXII Amendment to the United States Constitution to two
terms in office. Governors in forty states are limited to two terms or less.
 Voters have established term limits for over two thousand state legislators
as well as over seventeen thousand local officials across the country. Nevertheless,
Congress has ignored our desire for term limits not only by proposing excessively
long terms for its own members but also by utterly refusing to pass an amendment
for genuine congressional term limits. Congress has a clear conflict of interest
in proposing a term limits amendment to the United States Constitution. A
majority of both Republicans and Democrats in the 104th Congress voted against
a constitutional amendment containing the term limits passed by a wide margin
of Nebraska voters. The people, not Congress, should set term limits. We
hereby establish as the official position of the citizens and State of Nebraska
that our elected officials should enact by constitutional amendment congressional
term limits of three terms in the United States House of Representatives and
of two terms in the United States Senate.</para>
<para>The career politicians dominating Congress have a conflict of interest
that prevents Congress from being what the founders intended, the branch of
government closest to the people. The politicians have refused to heed the
will of the people for term limits; they have voted to dramatically raise
their own pay; they have provided lavish million-dollar pensions for themselves;
and they have granted themselves numerous other privileges at the expense
of the people. Most importantly, members of Congress have enriched themselves
while running up huge deficits to support their spending. They have put the
government nearly $5,000,000,000,000.00 (five trillion dollars) in debt, gravely
threatening the future of our children and grandchildren.</para>
<para>The corruption and appearance of corruption brought about by political
careerism is destructive to the proper functioning of the first branch of
our representative government. Congress has grown increasingly distant from
the people of the states. The people have the sovereign right and compelling
interest in creating a citizen Congress that will more effectively protect
our freedom and prosperity. This interest and right may not effectively be
served in any way other than that proposed by this initiative.</para>
<para>We hereby state our intention on behalf of the people of Nebraska, that
this initiative lead to the adoption of the following amendment to the United
States Constitution:</para>
<para>CONGRESSIONAL TERM LIMITS AMENDMENT TO</para>
<para>THE UNITED STATES CONSTITUTION</para>
<para>Section 1. No person shall serve in the office of United States Representative
for more than three terms, but upon ratification of this amendment no person
who has held the office of United States Representative or who then holds
the office shall serve for more than two additional terms.</para>
<para>Section 2. No person shall serve in the office of United States Senator
for more than two terms, but upon ratification of this amendment no person
who has held the office of United States Senator or who then holds the office
shall serve for more than one additional term.</para>
<para>Section 3. This article shall have no time limit within which it must
be ratified to become operative upon the ratification of the legislatures
of three-fourths of the several states.</para><para>Therefore, we the people of the State
of Nebraska, have chosen to amend the Constitution of Nebraska to inform voters
regarding incumbent and nonincumbent federal and state candidates' support
for the congressional term limits amendment provided for in this section.</para>
</constitutionalsection></section>
<source>
<para>Neb. Const. art. XVIII, sec. 1 (1996); </para>
<para>Adopted 1996, Initiative Measure No. 409. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
