<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="XVIII-3"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>XVIII-3</articlesectno><catchline>Nonincumbent candidates; Term Limits Pledge; ballot notation; when.</catchline><para>(1) Nonincumbent candidates for the United States Senate, the United States House of Representatives, and the Legislature should be given an opportunity to take a "Term Limits Pledge" regarding term limits each time they file to run for such offices. Any such person who declines to take the "Term Limits Pledge" shall have the information "DECLINED TO PLEDGE TO SUPPORT TERM LIMITS" printed adjacent to his or her name on every primary and general election ballot.</para><para>(2) The "Term Limits Pledge" shall be offered to nonincumbent candidates for the United States Senate, the United States House of Representatives, and the Legislature until a constitutional amendment which limits the number of terms of United States Senators to no more than two and United States Representatives to no more than three has become part of our United States Constitution.</para><para>(3) The "Term Limits Pledge" that each nonincumbent candidate, set forth in subsections (1) and (2) of this section, shall be offered is as follows: I support term limits and pledge to use all my legislative powers to enact the proposed constitutional amendment to the United States Constitution set forth in Article XVIII, section 1, of this Constitution. If elected, I pledge to vote in such a way that the designation "DISREGARDED VOTERS INSTRUCTION ON TERM LIMITS" will not appear adjacent to my name.</para><para>......................... Signature of Candidate</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. XVIII, sec. 3 (1996); </para><para>Adopted 1996, Initiative Measure No. 409. </para><note>This section is an unconstitutional infringement on the right to vote in violation of Article V of the Constitution of the United States. Miller v. Moore, 169 F.3d 1119 (8th Cir. 1999).</note></source><annotation><para>This section is an unconstitutional infringement on the right to vote. Miller v. Moore, 169 F.3d 1119 (8th Cir. 1999).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
