<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="constitution">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="XIII-4">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<articlesectno>XIII-4</articlesectno>
<catchline>Nonprofit enterprise development; powers of counties and municipalities.</catchline><para>Notwithstanding any other
provision in this Constitution, the Legislature may authorize any county,
city, or village to acquire, own, develop, and lease or finance real and personal
property, other than property used or to be used for sectarian instruction
or study or as a place for devotional activities or religious worship, to
be used, during the term of any revenue bonds issued, only by nonprofit enterprises
as determined by law and to issue revenue bonds for the purpose of defraying
the cost of acquiring and developing or financing such property by construction,
purchase, or otherwise. Such bonds shall not become general obligation bonds
of the governmental subdivision by which such bonds are issued, and such governmental
subdivision shall have no authority to impose taxes for the payment of such
bonds. Notwithstanding the provisions of Article VIII, section 2, of this
Constitution, the acquisition, ownership, development, use, or
financing of any real or personal property pursuant to the provisions of this
section shall not affect the imposition of any taxes or the exemption therefrom
by the Legislature pursuant to this Constitution. The acquiring, owning, developing,
and leasing or financing of such property shall be deemed for a public purpose,
but the governmental subdivision shall not have the right to acquire such
property for the purposes specified in this section by condemnation. The principal
of and interest on any bonds issued may be secured by a pledge of the lease
and the revenue therefrom and by mortgage upon such property. No such governmental
subdivision shall have the power to operate any such property as a business
or in any manner except as the lessor thereof.</para></constitutionalsection>
</section>
<source><para>Neb. Const. art. XIII, sec. 4 (2010); Adopted 2010, Laws 2010, LR295CA, sec. 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
