<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="XV-1"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>XV-1</articlesectno><catchline>Official oath; refusal; disqualification.</catchline><para>Executive and judicial officers and members of the legislature, before they enter upon their official duties shall take and subscribe the following oath, or affirmation. "I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will support the constitution of the United States, and the constitution of the State of Nebraska, and will faithfully discharge the duties of .......... according to the best of my ability, and that at the election at which I was chosen to fill said office, I have not improperly influenced in any way the vote of any elector, and have not accepted, nor will I accept or receive, directly or indirectly, any money or other valuable thing from any corporation, company or person, or any promise of office, for any official act or influence (for any vote I may give or withhold on any bill, resolution, or appropriation)." Any such officer or member of the legislature who shall refuse to take the oath herein prescribed, shall forfeit his office, and any person who shall be convicted of having sworn falsely to, or of violating his said oath shall forfeit his office, and thereafter be disqualified from holding any office of profit or trust in this state unless he shall have been restored to civil rights.</para>
</constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. XIV, sec. 1 (1875); </para><para>Transferred by Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, art. XV, sec. 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Violation of judicial oath aggravates offense of disregarding oath as a lawyer. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Conover, 166 Neb. 132, 88 N.W.2d 135 (1958).</para><para>County judge is required to take oath of constitutional officers. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Wiebusch, 153 Neb. 583, 45 N.W.2d 583 (1951).</para><para>Exact form of oath to be taken by executive and judicial officers and members of Legislature is prescribed. State ex rel. Johnson v. Chase, 147 Neb. 758, 25 N.W.2d 1 (1946).</para><para>A judicial officer is required to take and subscribe to the oath prescribed by this section. Duffy v. State ex rel. Edson, 60 Neb. 812, 84 N.W. 264 (1900).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>