<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="XI-1"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>XI-1</articlesectno><catchline>Subscription to stock prohibited; exception.</catchline><para>No city, county, town, precinct, municipality, or other subdivision of the state shall ever become a subscriber to the capital stock, or owner of such stock, or any portion or interest therein of any railroad, or private corporation, or association, except that, notwithstanding any other provision of this Constitution, the Legislature may authorize the investment of public endowment funds by any city which is authorized by this Constitution to establish a charter, in the manner required of a prudent investor who shall act with care, skill, and diligence under the prevailing circumstance and in such investments as the governing body of such city, acting in a fiduciary capacity for the exclusive purpose of protecting and benefiting such investment, may determine, subject to such limitations as the Legislature may by statute provide.</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. XI, sec. 1 (1875); </para><para>Transferred in 1907, art. XIa, sec. 1; </para><para>Transferred by Constitutional Convention, 1919-1920, art. XI, sec. 1; </para><para>Amended 2008, Laws 2007, LR6CA, sec. 1. </para></source><annotation><para>This Article and section of the Nebraska Constitution prohibits the deposit of funds by subdivisions of the State of Nebraska in mutual savings and loan associations, whether federal or state chartered, except those funds authorized under Article XV, section 17(2), of the Constitution of Nebraska. Nebraska League of S. &amp; L. Assns. v. Mathes, 201 Neb. 122, 266 N.W.2d 720 (1978).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>