<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="constitution"><section><sectno></sectno><constitutionalsection chaptername="Constitution" statutenumber="XVIII-5"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><articlesectno>XVIII-5</articlesectno><catchline>Ballot notation; Secretary of State; duties; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) The Secretary of State shall be responsible to make an accurate determination as to whether a candidate for the United States Senate, the United States House of Representatives, or the Legislature shall have placed adjacent to his or her name on the election ballot the information "DISREGARDED VOTERS INSTRUCTION ON TERM LIMITS" or "DECLINED TO PLEDGE TO SUPPORT TERM LIMITS."</para><para>(2) The Secretary of State shall consider timely submitted public comments prior to making the determination required in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State, in accordance with subsection (1) of this section, shall determine and declare what information, if any, shall appear adjacent to the name of each incumbent member of Congress if he or she was to be a candidate in the next election. In the case of United States Representatives and United States Senators, this determination and declaration shall be made in a fashion necessary to ensure the orderly printing of primary and general election ballots with allowance made for all legal action provided in subsections (5) and (6) of this section, and shall be based upon his or her action during his or her current term of office and any action taken in any concluded term, if such action was taken after the determination and declaration was made by the Secretary of State in a previous election. In the case of incumbent members of the Legislature, this determination and declaration shall be made not later than thirty days after the end of the regular session following each general election, and shall be based upon legislative action in the previous regular session.</para><para>(4) The Secretary of State shall determine and declare what information, if any, will appear adjacent to the names of nonincumbent candidates for Congress and the Legislature, not later than five business days after the deadline for filing for the 
office.</para><para>(5) If the Secretary of State makes the determination that the information "DISREGARDED VOTERS INSTRUCTION ON TERM LIMITS" or "DECLINED TO PLEDGE TO SUPPORT TERM LIMITS" shall not be placed on the ballot adjacent to the name of a candidate for the United States Senate, the United States House of Representatives, or the Legislature, any elector may appeal such decision within five business days to the Nebraska Supreme Court as an original action or shall waive any right to appeal such decision; in which case the burden of proof shall be upon the Secretary of State to demonstrate by clear and convincing evidence that the candidate has met the requirements set forth in this article and therefore should not have the information "DISREGARDED VOTERS INSTRUCTION ON TERM LIMITS" or "DECLINED TO PLEDGE TO SUPPORT TERM LIMITS" printed on the ballot adjacent to the candidate's name.</para><para>(6) If the Secretary of State determines that the information "DISREGARDED VOTERS INSTRUCTION ON TERM LIMITS" or "DECLINED TO PLEDGE TO SUPPORT TERM LIMITS" shall be placed on the ballot adjacent to a candidate's name, the candidate or any elector may appeal such decision within five business days to the Nebraska Supreme Court as an original action or shall waive any right to appeal such decision; in which case the burden of proof shall be upon the candidate or any elector to demonstrate by clear and convincing evidence that the candidate should not have the information "DISREGARDED VOTERS INSTRUCTION ON TERM LIMITS" or "DECLINED TO PLEDGE TO SUPPORT TERM LIMITS" printed on the ballot adjacent to the candidate's name.</para><para>(7) The Nebraska Supreme Court shall hear the appeal provided for in subsection (5) of this section and issue a decision within sixty days. The Nebraska Supreme Court shall hear the appeal provided for in subsection (6) of this section and issue a decision not later than sixty-one days before the date of the 
election.</para></constitutionalsection></section><source><para>Neb. Const. art. XVIII, sec. 5 (1996); </para><para>Adopted 1996, Initiative Measure No. 409. </para><note>This section is an unconstitutional infringement on the right to vote in violation of Article V of the Constitution of the United States. Miller v. Moore, 169 F.3d 1119 (8th Cir. 1999).</note></source><annotation><para>This section violates Article V of the U.S. Constitution and is an unconstitutional infringement on the right to vote. Miller v. Moore, 169 F.3d 1119 (8th Cir. 1999).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>