<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Negotiable Instruments" statutenumber="62-301"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>62-301</statuteno><catchline>Holidays, enumerated; federal holiday schedule observed; exceptions; bank holidays.</catchline><para>(1) For the purposes of the Uniform Commercial Code and section 62-301.01, the following days shall be holidays: New Year's Day, January 1; Birthday of Martin Luther King, Jr., the third Monday in January; President's Day, the third Monday in February; Arbor Day, the last Friday in April; Memorial Day, the last Monday in May; Independence Day, July 4; Labor Day, the first Monday in September; Columbus Day, the second Monday in October; Veterans Day, November 11, and the federally recognized holiday therefor, or either of them; Thanksgiving Day, the fourth Thursday in November; the day after Thanksgiving; and Christmas Day, December 25. If any such holiday falls on Sunday, the following Monday shall be a holiday. If the date designated by the state for observance of any legal holiday enumerated in this section, except Veterans Day, is different from the date of observance of such holiday pursuant to a federal holiday schedule, the federal holiday schedule shall be observed.</para><para>(2) Any bank doing business in this state may, by a brief written notice at, on, or near its front door, fully dispense with or restrict, to such extent as it may determine, the hours within which it will be open for business.</para><para>(3) Any bank may close on Saturday if it states such fact by a brief written notice at, on, or near its front door. When such bank will, in observance of such a notice, not be open for general business, such day shall, with respect to the particular bank, be the equivalent of a holiday as fully as if such day were listed in subsection (1) of this section, and any act authorized, required, or permitted to be performed at, by, or with respect to such bank which will, in observance of such notice, not be open for general business, acting in its own behalf or in any capacity whatever, may be performed on the next succeeding business day and no liability or loss of rights on the part of any person shall result from such delay.</para><para>(4) Any bank which, by the notice provided for by subsection (3) of this section, has created the holiday for such bank may, without destroying the legal effect of the holiday for it and solely for the convenience of its customers, remain open all or part of such day in a limited fashion by treating every transaction with its customers on such day as though the transaction had taken place immediately upon the opening of such bank on the first following business day.</para><para>(5) Whenever the word bank is used in this section it includes building and loan association, savings and loan association, credit union, savings bank, trust company, investment company, and any other type of financial institution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1905, c. 83, art. 18, &#167; 195, p. 434; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 69, &#167; 1, p. 306; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5512; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 98, &#167; 1, p. 241; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 186, &#167; 1, p. 698; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4805; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 62-1706; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 187, &#167; 1, p. 755; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 62-1706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 62-301; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 252, &#167; 1, p. 789; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 204, &#167; 1, p. 761; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 224, &#167; 1, p. 790; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 395, &#167; 1, p. 1239; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 844, &#167; 2, p. 3180; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 34, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 729, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 218, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 855, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 825, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 909, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1094, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 32. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Banks,</emphasis> days considered legal holidays, see section 8-1,129.</para><para><emphasis>Thanksgiving,</emphasis> proclamation by Governor, see section 84-104.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Status as a holiday under this section has no effect upon court procedure. Taylor Dairy Products Co. v. Owen, 139 Neb. 603, 298 N.W. 332 (1941).</para><para>Judicial sale may be held on Lincoln's Birthday. Reid v. Keys, 112 Neb. 242, 199 N.W. 533 (1924).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 