  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Negotiable Instruments" statutenumber="62-303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>62-303</statuteno><catchline>Tuition notes or contracts of business colleges; requirements; limitation upon negotiation.</catchline><para>It shall be unlawful for any proprietor, officer, agent or representative of any business college, or the business or commercial department of any school doing business within the State of Nebraska, or without the state when operating or soliciting within the state, to contract for or receive for tuition or scholarship a negotiable note or negotiable contract, unless such negotiable note or notes or negotiable contract shall have printed in red ink prominently and legibly and in twenty-four point bold type diagonally across the face thereof, and above the signatures thereto, the words negotiable note given for tuition if a note, or the words negotiable contract note given for tuition and scholarship, if a contract, and unless a copy of said instrument shall be delivered to the makers thereof at the time of signing the same. It shall be unlawful for any such proprietor, agent or representative of any such school or department to sell or dispose of any such negotiable note or negotiable contract note, received in payment for tuition or scholarship, prior to three days from the entrance and personal registration of the student, for whom the same was purchased, in the matriculation register at the place of the location of the school or department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 220, &#167; 1, p. 489; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4807; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 62-1708; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 62-303; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 212, &#167; 1, p. 693. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Private postsecondary career school,</emphasis> contracts and evidence of indebtedness, see section 85-1645 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Foreign corporation soliciting and carrying on business in this state cannot enforce contract entered into and valid in another state if contract growing out of transaction is contrary to local laws. Refrigeration &amp; Air Conditioning Institute, Inc. v. Hilyard, 146 Neb. 42, 18 N.W.2d 548 (1945).</para><para>Note for tuition for linotype school was void where makers were not furnished with copy of note. Mergenthaler Linotype Co. v. McNamee, 125 Neb. 71, 249 N.W. 92 (1933).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 