
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-913"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-913</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Zoning laws and regulations; enforcement; violations; penalties; actions.</catchline><para id="id00">The city council or village board of trustees may provide by ordinance for the enforcement of sections 19-901 to 19-915 and of any ordinance, regulation, or restriction made thereunder. A violation of such sections or of such ordinance or regulation is hereby declared to be a misdemeanor, and such city council or village board of trustees may provide for the punishment thereof by fine not exceeding one hundred dollars for any one offense, recoverable with costs, or by imprisonment in the county jail for a term not to exceed thirty days. Each day such violation continues after notice of violation is given to the offender may be considered a separate offense. In case any building or structure is erected, constructed, reconstructed, altered, repaired, converted, or maintained, or any building, structure, or land is used in violation of sections 19-901 to 19-915 or of any ordinance or other regulation made under such sections, the proper local authorities of the municipality, in addition to other remedies, may institute any appropriate action or proceedings to prevent such unlawful erection, construction, reconstruction, alteration, repair, conversion, maintenance, or use, to restrain, correct, or abate such violation, to prevent the occupancy of such building, structure, or land, or to prevent any illegal act, conduct, business, or use in or about such premises.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 43, &#167; 10, p. 187; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-910; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-913; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 80. </para></source><annotation><para>Injunction authorized in addition to other remedies for violation of zoning laws. City of Imperial v. Raile, 187 Neb. 404, 191 N.W.2d 442 (1971).</para><para>City may maintain action for mandatory injunction to compel removal of structure erected in violation of zoning ordinance. City of Beatrice v. Williams, 172 Neb. 889, 112 N.W.2d 16 (1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>