<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>19-103</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para id="id00">There is hereby created the City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund. Amounts credited to the fund pursuant to section 77-2602 shall, upon appropriation by the Legislature, be first expended to support the design and development of the redevelopment projects within the riverfront redevelopment plan designated for the area along the Missouri River generally north of Interstate 480 to Interstate 680 by the city of Omaha, except that each fiscal year there shall be no distribution from the fund until the finance director of the city certifies that other funds have been encumbered for that calendar year by the city to pay the cost of the combined sewer separation program project east of Seventy-second Street in the city of Omaha. Such certification shall be required only until such sewer separation project is completed or until no cigarette tax money is available to the fund. The amount certified shall be at least seven million dollars each calendar year until 2007 and at least four million dollars each calendar year thereafter. The sewer separation project has such a significant impact on the health and welfare of such a large percentage of the population and on public health in general that the project is a matter of statewide concern. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para id="id00">No distribution from the fund shall be made unless the city of the metropolitan class provides matching funds equal to the ratio of one dollar for each three dollars of the state distribution. Funds derived from any state source may not be utilized as matching funds for purposes of this section.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer the unobligated balance in the City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund to the General Fund on July 1, 2017, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible, on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. On July 8, 2017, the City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund shall terminate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 657, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 20. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>