<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-415"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-415</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Mayor; city council members; powers and duties; heads of departments.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) In cities under the commission plan of government containing at least forty thousand and less than four hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the city council shall consist of the mayor who shall be superintendent of the department of public affairs, one city council member to be superintendent of the department of accounts and finances, one city council member to be superintendent of the department of public safety, one city council member to be superintendent of the department of streets and public improvements, and one city council member to be superintendent of the department of parks and public property.</para><para id="id00">(2) In cities under the commission plan of government containing at least two thousand and less than forty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the city council shall consist of the mayor who shall be commissioner of the department of public affairs and public safety, one city council member to be commissioner of the department of streets, public improvements, and public property, one city council member to be commissioner of the department of public accounts and finances, one city council member to be commissioner of the department of public works, and one city council member to be commissioner of the department of parks and recreation.</para><para id="id00">(3) In all cities described in this section, the commissioner of the department of accounts and finances shall be vice president of the city council and shall, in the absence or inability of the mayor to serve, perform the duties of the mayor. In case of vacancy in the office of mayor by death or otherwise, the vacancy shall be filled as provided in section 32-568.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 24, &#167; 12, p. 160; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5299; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4522; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 141, &#167; 8, p. 352; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-412; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-415; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 89, &#167; 1, p. 299; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 112, &#167; 6, p. 523; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 281, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 514; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 329; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB820, &#167; 4. </para>
</source></law>
</legaldoc>