
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-929"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-929</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Planning commission; city council or village board of trustees; powers and duties; appeal.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Except as provided in sections 19-930 to 19-933, the planning commission of a city of the first class, city of the second class, or village shall (a) make and adopt plans for the physical development of the city or village, including any areas outside its boundaries which in the commission's judgment bear relation to the planning of such city or village and including a comprehensive development plan as defined by section 19-903, (b) prepare and adopt such implemental means as a capital improvement program, subdivision regulations, building codes, and a zoning ordinance in cooperation with other interested municipal departments, and (c) consult with and advise public officials and agencies, public utilities, civic organizations, educational institutions, and citizens with relation to the promulgation and implementation of the comprehensive development plan and its implemental programs. The commission may delegate authority to any such group to conduct studies and make surveys for the commission, make preliminary reports on its findings, and hold public hearings before submitting its final reports. The city council or village board of trustees shall not take final action on matters relating to the comprehensive development plan, capital improvements, building codes, subdivision development, annexation of territory, or zoning until it has received the recommendation of the planning commission if such commission in fact has been created and is existent. The city council or village board of trustees shall by ordinance set a reasonable time within which the recommendation from the planning commission is to be received. A recommendation from the planning commission shall not be required for subdivision of existing lots and blocks whenever all required public improvements have been installed, no new dedication of public rights-of-way or easements is involved, and such subdivision complies with the ordinance requirements concerning minimum areas and dimensions of such lots and blocks, if the city council or village board of trustees has designated, by ordinance, an agent pursuant to section 19-916.</para><para id="id00">(2) The planning commission may, with the consent of the city council or village board of trustees, in its own name (a) make and enter into contracts with public or private bodies, (b) receive contributions, bequests, gifts, or grant funds from public or private sources, (c) expend the funds appropriated to it by the city or village, (d) employ agents and employees, and (e) acquire, hold, and dispose of property.</para><para id="id00">The planning commission may on its own authority make arrangements consistent with its program, conduct or sponsor special studies or planning work for any public body or appropriate agency, receive grants, remuneration, or reimbursement for such studies or work, and at its public hearings, summon witnesses, administer oaths, and compel the giving of testimony.</para><para id="id00">(3) The planning commission may grant conditional uses or special exceptions to property owners for the use of their property if the city council or village board of trustees has, through a zoning ordinance or special ordinance, generally authorized the commission to exercise such powers and has approved the standards and procedures adopted by the commission for equitably and judiciously granting such conditional uses or special exceptions. The granting of a conditional use permit or special exception shall only allow property owners to put their property to a special use if it is among those uses specifically identified in the zoning ordinance as classifications of uses which may require special conditions or requirements to be met by the owners before a use permit or building permit is authorized. The power to grant conditional uses or special exceptions shall be the exclusive authority of the commission, except that the city council or village board of trustees may choose to retain for itself the power to grant conditional uses or special exceptions for those classifications of uses specified in the zoning ordinance. The city council or village board of trustees may exercise such power if it has formally adopted standards and procedures for granting such conditional uses or special exceptions in a manner that is equitable and will promote the public interest. An appeal of a decision by the commission or the city council or village board of trustees regarding a conditional use or special exception shall be made to the district court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 39, &#167; 6, p. 177; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 18-2106; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-1306; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 85, &#167; 2, p. 269; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 186, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 71, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 18-1306; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 207, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 209, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 630, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 95. </para></source><annotation><para>A city of the first class is not required to obtain a recommendation from the planning commission before proceeding with annexation. City of Parkview v. City of Grand Island, 188 Neb. 267, 196 N.W.2d 197 (1972).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>