<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-414"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-414</statuteno><catchline>Council; departments; assignment of duties.</catchline><para>The executive and administrative powers, authorities, and duties in such cities shall be distributed into and among departments as follows:</para><para>In metropolitan cities, (1) department of public affairs, (2) department of accounts and finances, (3) department of police, sanitation, and public safety, (4) department of fire protection and water supply, (5) department of street cleaning and maintenance, (6) department of public improvements, and (7) department of parks and public property;</para><para>In primary cities, (1) department of public affairs, (2) department of accounts and finances, (3) department of public safety, (4) department of streets and public improvements, and (5) department of parks and public property; and</para><para>In cities containing two thousand or more and not more than forty thousand population, (1) department of public affairs and public safety, (2) department of accounts and finances, (3) department of streets, public improvements, and public property, (4) department of public works, and (5) department of parks and recreation.</para><para>The council shall provide, as nearly as possible, the powers and duties to be exercised and performed by, and assign them to, the appropriate departments. It may prescribe the powers and duties of all officers and employees of the city and may assign particular officers, or employees, to more than one of the departments, may require any officer or employee to perform duties in two or more of the departments, and may make such other rules and regulations as may be necessary or proper for the efficient and economical management of the business affairs of the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 24, &#167; 11, p. 159; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 21, &#167; 7, p. 92; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5298; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4521; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 141, &#167; 7, p. 351; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-411; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-414; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 55, &#167; 3, p. 179; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 281, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>The general plan of the commission form of government has been followed in Lincoln under the home rule charter. Eppley Hotels Co. v. City of Lincoln, 133 Neb. 550, 276 N.W. 196 (1937).</para><para>The fact that an officer had been in the habit of employing men in the past does not override the provision of the statute unless it had previously been agreed to by the city commissioner. Scott v. City of Lincoln, 104 Neb. 546, 178 N.W. 203 (1920).</para><para>The power to fix salaries of police officers and members of the fire department in cities of the metropolitan class was not included in this section. Adams v. City of Omaha, 101 Neb. 690, 164 N.W. 714 (1917).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>