
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-901"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-901</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Zoning regulations; power to adopt; when; comprehensive development plan; planning commission; reports and hearings; purpose; validity of plan; not applicable; when.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) For the purpose of promoting health, safety, morals, or the general welfare of the community, the city council of a city of the first class or city of the second class or the village board of trustees of a village may adopt zoning regulations which regulate and restrict the height, number of stories, and size of buildings and other structures, the percentage of lots that may be occupied, the size of yards, courts, and other open spaces, the density of population, and the location and use of buildings, structures, and land for trade, industry, residence, or other purposes. For a city of the first class as described in subdivision (3) of section 19-5503, such regulations shall comply with the Municipal Density and Missing Middle Housing Act.</para><para id="id00">(2) Such powers shall be exercised only after the city council or village board of trustees has established a planning commission, received from its planning commission a recommended comprehensive development plan as defined in section 19-903, adopted such comprehensive development plan, and received the specific recommendation of the planning commission on the adoption or amendment of zoning regulations. The planning commission shall make a preliminary report and hold public hearings on its recommendations regarding the adoption or repeal of the comprehensive development plan and zoning regulations and shall hold public hearings thereon before submitting its final report to the city council or village board of trustees. Amendments to the comprehensive plan or zoning regulations shall be considered at public hearings before submitting recommendations to the city council or village board of trustees.</para><para id="id00">(3) A comprehensive development plan as defined in section 19-903 which has been adopted and not rescinded by a city council or village board of trustees prior to May 17, 1967, shall be deemed to have been recommended and adopted in compliance with the procedural requirements of this section when, prior to the adoption of the plan by the city council or village board of trustees, a recommendation thereon had been made to the city council or village board of trustees by a zoning commission in compliance with the provisions of section 19-906, as such section existed prior to its repeal by Laws 1967, c. 92, section 7, or by a planning commission appointed under the provisions of Chapter 19, article 9, regardless of whether the planning commission had been appointed as a zoning commission.</para><para id="id00">(4) The requirement that a planning commission be appointed and a comprehensive development plan be adopted shall not apply to cities of the first class, cities of the second class, and villages which have legally adopted a zoning ordinance prior to May 17, 1967, and which have not amended the zoning ordinance or zoning map since May 17, 1967. Such city or village shall appoint a planning commission and adopt the comprehensive plan prior to amending the zoning ordinance or zoning map.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 43, &#167; 1, p. 182; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-901; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 131, &#167; 8, p. 509; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 19-901; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-901; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 65, &#167; 1, p. 289; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 92, &#167; 1, p. 283; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 93, &#167; 1, p. 288; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 508, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 95, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 71, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB866, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Municipal Density and Missing Middle Housing Act,</emphasis> see section 19-5501.</para> </crossreference><annotation><para>When a legislative body does not specify the manner in which a comprehensive development plan is to be adopted, it is assumed that such plan may be effectively adopted via resolution. Smith v. City of Papillion, 270 Neb. 607, 705 N.W.2d 584 (2005).</para><para>Zoning powers granted to villages under section 19-901, R.R.S.1943, shall be exercised only after the municipal legislative body has appointed a planning commission, received from its planning commission a recommended comprehensive development plan as defined in section 19-903, R.R.S.1943, adopted such comprehensive development plan, and received the specific recommendation of the planning commission on the adoption or amendment of zoning regulations. Village of McGrew v. Steidley, 208 Neb. 726, 305 N.W.2d 627 (1981).</para><para>Plaintiff was not entitled to an injunction enjoining defendant from erecting a fire station in violation of a zoning ordinance. Witzel v. Village of Brainard, 208 Neb. 231, 302 N.W.2d 723 (1981).</para><para>Adoption, amendment, supplement, or change of regulations and restrictions under comprehensive development plan shall not become effective until after a public hearing of which notice has been given. Stec v. Countryside of Hastings, Inc., 190 Neb. 733, 212 N.W.2d 561 (1973).</para><para>Cities of the first class have authority to regulate and restrict the use of land located within boundaries of the city. City of Grand Island v. Ehlers, 180 Neb. 331, 142 N.W.2d 770 (1966).</para><para>This section was not applicable to zoning act relating to first class cities only. Schlientz v. City of North Platte, 172 Neb. 477, 110 N.W.2d 58 (1961).</para><para>Action of city council in zoning or rezoning must have a foundation in promoting health, safety, morals, or general welfare of the community. Weber v. City of Grand Island, 165 Neb. 827, 87 N.W.2d 575 (1958).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>