<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-701"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>19-701</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Public utility; condemnation; election; resubmission.</catchline><para id="id00">Whenever the qualified electors of any city of the primary class, city of the first class, city of the second class, or village shall vote at any general or special election to acquire and appropriate, by an exercise of the power of eminent domain, any waterworks, waterworks system, electric light plant, electric light and power plant, heating plant, street railway, or street railway system, located or operating within or partly within and partly without such city or village, together with real and personal property needed or useful in connection therewith, if the main part of such works, plant, or system be within such city or village and even though a franchise for the construction and operating of any such works, plant, or system may or may not have expired, then such city or village shall possess and have the power and authority, by an exercise of the power of eminent domain to appropriate and acquire, for the public use of such city or village, any such works, plant, railway, pipelines, or system. If any public utility properties supplying different kinds of service to such city or village are operated as one unit and under one management, the right to acquire and appropriate, as provided in sections 19-701 to 19-707, shall cover and extend to the entire property and not to any divided or segregated part thereof, and the duly constituted authorities of such city or village shall have the power to submit such question or proposition, in the usual manner, to the qualified electors of such city or village at any general city or village election or at any special city or village election and may submit the proposition in connection with any city or village special election called for any other purpose, and the votes cast thereon shall be canvassed and the result found and declared as in any other city or village election. Such city or village authorities shall submit such question at any such election whenever a petition asking for such submission, signed by the legal voters of such city or village equaling in number fifteen percent of the votes cast at the last general city or village election, and filed in the city clerk's or village clerk's office at least sixty days before the election at which the submission is presented, but if the question of acquiring any particular plant or system has been submitted once, the same question shall not again be submitted to the voters of such city or village until two years shall have elapsed from and after the date of the findings by the board of appraisers regarding the value of the property and the city's or village's rejection of such question.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 188, &#167; 1, p. 422; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4600; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-701; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 122; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 19-708; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-701; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 56, &#167; 1, p. 183; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 384, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 57. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Constitutionality</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Election</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Constitutionality</emphasis></para><para>Act held constitutional. May v. City of Kearney, 145 Neb. 475, 17 N.W.2d 448 (1945); City of Mitchell v. Western Public Service Co., 124 Neb. 248, 246 N.W. 484 (1933).</para><para>Constitutionality of this and succeeding sections authorizing condemnation of property of public utility sustained. Central Electric &amp; Gas Co. v. City of Stromsburg, 192 F.Supp. 280 (D. Neb. 1960).</para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para>Where the Supreme Court enjoined a city and its officials from issuing bonds for purpose of raising money to tender an award in proceedings to condemn property of power company, city could not proceed further until another election was held. City of Kearney v. Consumers Public Power Dist., 146 Neb. 29, 18 N.W.2d 437 (1945).</para><para>Proceeding in Supreme Court to vacate appointment of members of court of condemnation is not within jurisdiction of Supreme Court. Consumers Public Power Dist. v. City of Sidney, 144 Neb. 6, 12 N.W.2d 104 (1945).</para><para>Condemnation proceeding was not a civil action subject to removal to federal court. Village of Walthill v. Iowa Electric L. &amp; P. Co., 228 F.2d 647 (8th Cir. 1956).</para><para><emphasis>3. Election</emphasis></para><para>Proposition of acquisition of gas plant was properly submitted to voters. Talbott v. City of Lyons, 171 Neb. 186, 105 N.W.2d 918 (1960).</para><para>Notice of election was sufficient. Central Electric &amp; Gas Co. v. City of Stromsburg, 289 F.2d 217 (8th Cir. 1961).</para><para>Ballot title submitting question of proposition to acquire complete gas system was sufficient. Iowa Electric Light &amp; Power Co. v. City of Lyons, 166 F.Supp. 676 (D. Neb. 1958), affirmed 265 F.2d 273 (1959).</para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>All property, and not segregated portions, must be taken. Consumers Public Power Dist. v. Eldred, 146 Neb. 926, 22 N.W.2d 188 (1946).</para><para>Authority of court of condemnation is limited to determination of just compensation. Kansas-Nebraska Nat. Gas Co. v. Village of Deshler, 192 F.Supp. 303 (D. Neb. 1960).</para><para>Village could not acquire by eminent domain gas distribution system only. Village of Walthill v. Iowa Electric Light &amp; Power Co., 125 F.Supp. 859 (D. Neb. 1954).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>