
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-903</statuteno><catchline>Comprehensive development plan; requirements; regulations and restrictions made in accordance with plan; considerations.</catchline><para>The regulations and restrictions authorized by sections 19-901 to 19-915 shall be in accordance with a comprehensive development plan which shall consist of both graphic and textual material and shall be designed to accommodate anticipated long-range future growth which shall be based upon documented population and economic projections. The comprehensive development plan shall, among other possible elements, include:</para><para>(1) A land-use element which designates the proposed general distributions, general location, and extent of the uses of land for agriculture, housing, commerce, industry, recreation, education, public buildings and lands, and other categories of public and private use of land;</para><para>(2) The general location, character, and extent of existing and proposed major roads, streets, and highways, and air and other transportation routes and facilities;</para><para>(3) The general location, type, capacity, and area served of present and projected or needed community facilities including recreation facilities, schools, libraries, other public buildings, and public utilities and services;</para><para>(4) When a new comprehensive plan or a full update to an existing comprehensive plan is developed, an energy element which: Assesses energy infrastructure and energy use by sector, including residential, commercial, and industrial sectors; evaluates utilization of renewable energy sources; and promotes energy conservation measures that benefit the community. This subdivision shall not apply to villages; and</para><para>(5)(a) When next amended after January 1, 1995, an identification of sanitary and improvement districts, subdivisions, industrial tracts, commercial tracts, and other discrete developed areas which are or in the future may be appropriate subjects for annexation and (b) a general review of the standards and qualifications that should be met to enable the municipality to undertake annexation of such areas. Failure of the plan to identify subjects for annexation or to set out standards or qualifications for annexation shall not serve as the basis for any challenge to the validity of an annexation ordinance.</para><para>Regulations adopted pursuant to sections 19-901 to 19-915 shall be designed to lessen congestion in the streets; to secure safety from fire, panic, and other dangers; to promote health and the general welfare; to provide adequate light and air; to prevent the overcrowding of land; to secure safety from flood; to avoid undue concentration of population; to facilitate the adequate provision of transportation, water, sewerage, schools, parks, and other public requirements; to protect property against blight and depreciation; to protect the tax base; to secure economy in governmental expenditures; and to preserve, protect, and enhance historic buildings, places, and districts.</para><para>Such regulations shall be made with reasonable consideration, among other things, for the character of the district and its peculiar suitability for particular uses and with a view to conserving the value of buildings and encouraging the most appropriate use of land throughout such municipality.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 43, &#167; 3, p. 183; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-903; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-903; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 430, &#167; 2, p. 1318; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 92, &#167; 2, p. 283; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 630, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB997, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB731, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Adoption, amendment, supplement, or change of regulations and restrictions under comprehensive development plan shall not become effective until after a public hearing of which notice has been given. Stec v. Countryside of Hastings, Inc., 190 Neb. 733, 212 N.W.2d 561 (1973).</para><para>Municipal code and ordinance did not constitute a comprehensive plan contemplated by this section. City of Milford v. Schmidt, 175 Neb. 12, 120 N.W.2d 262 (1963).</para><para>Zoning regulations must be made in accordance with comprehensive plan. Weber v. City of Grand Island, 165 Neb. 827, 87 N.W.2d 575 (1958).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>