<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-409" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>19-409</statuteno><catchline>City council members; candidates; terms.</catchline><para>(1) In a city under the commission plan of government, the two candidates for city council member receiving the highest number of votes at the primary election shall be placed upon the official ballot for such position at the statewide general election. If no candidates appeared on the primary election ballot or if the city council waived the primary election under section 19-405, all persons filing pursuant to section 19-405 shall be the only candidates whose names shall be placed upon the official ballot for such position at the statewide general election.</para><para>(2) Terms for city council members under the commission plan of government shall begin on the date of the first regular meeting of the city council in December following the statewide general election. The changes made to this section by Laws 1999, LB 250, shall not change the staggering of the terms of city council members in cities that have adopted the commission plan of government prior to January 1, 1999.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 24, &#167; 7, p. 155; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 21, &#167; 3, p. 88; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5294; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4517; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 141, &#167; 5, p. 348; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-407; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-409; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 112, &#167; 4, p. 522; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 327, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 512; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 250, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 16. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The provision that the only candidates whose names shall be placed upon the official ballot at the city election means that these are the only candidates whose names shall be printed on the official ballot, and there is no prohibition against any voter inserting the names of such other persons as he may desire to vote for. State ex rel. Zeilinger v. Thompson, 134 Neb. 739, 279 N.W. 462 (1938).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>