<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-616"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-616</statuteno><catchline>Appointive or elected official; compensation; no change during term of office.</catchline><para>The annual compensation of the mayor and a council member in cities adopting sections 19-601 to 19-648 shall be payable quarterly in equal installments and shall be fixed by the council. The emoluments of any appointive or elective officer shall not be increased or diminished during the term for which such officer was elected or appointed, except that when there are officers elected or appointed to the council, or a board or commission having more than one member and the terms of one or more members commence and end at different times, the compensation of all members of such council, board, or commission may be increased or diminished at the beginning of the full term of any member thereof. No person who has resigned or vacated any office shall be eligible to the same during the time for which such person was elected or appointed when, during the same time, the emoluments have been increased. For each absence from regular meetings of the council, unless authorized by a two-thirds vote of all members thereof, there shall be deducted a sum equal to two percent of such annual salary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 208, &#167; 17, p. 501; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4554; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-617; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-616; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 113, &#167; 1, p. 515; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1054, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Vacancies,</emphasis> how filled, see sections 19-3101 and 32-560 to 32-573.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>