<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-104</statuteno><catchline>Bonds authorized; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Cities of the primary class and cities of the metropolitan class may by ordinance issue their bonds and refunding bonds to finance and refinance the acquisition, construction, improving, and equipping of the projects authorized by sections 19-101 to 19-103 and provide for the payment of the same as specified in this section. Bonds, except refunding bonds, authorized by this section may only be issued once, and such issuance must occur within two years after July 1, 2001. An issuer shall be permitted to pledge the amounts on deposit or to be deposited in the City of the Primary Class Development Fund or the City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund, as applicable, as and when appropriated by the Legislature, to the registered owners of any bonds issued to finance the acquisition, construction, improving, or equipping of projects as approved in sections 19-101 to 19-103 as long as the lien of such pledge does not attach until funds are actually deposited into the issuer's respective fund, and in no event shall such a pledge be construed as an obligation of the Legislature to appropriate such funds. Any such pledge shall be valid and binding from the time when the pledge is made. The money so pledged and thereafter received by the issuer or deposited into its respective fund shall immediately be subject to the lien of such pledge without any physical delivery thereof or further act, and the lien of any such pledge shall be valid and binding as against all parties having claims of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise against the issuer, irrespective of whether the parties have notice thereof. Neither the ordinance nor any other instrument by which a pledge is created need be recorded.</para><para>(2) Such bonds may be sold by the issuer in such manner and for such price as the mayor and city council determine, at a discount, at par, or at a premium, at private negotiated sale or at public sale. The bonds shall have a stated maturity of fifteen years or less and shall bear interest at such rate or rates and otherwise be issued by ordinance adopted by the mayor and city council with such other terms and provisions as are established, permitted, or authorized by applicable state laws, notwithstanding any provisions of a home rule charter. In addition to the pledge of the amounts on deposit or to be deposited in the City of the Primary Class Development Fund or the City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund, as the case may be and as appropriate, permitted by subsection (1) of this section, such bonds may also be secured as to payment in whole or in part by a pledge, as shall be determined by the issuer, (a) from the income, proceeds, and revenue, if any, of the facilities financed with proceeds of such bonds, and (b) from its revenue and income, including its sales, use, or occupation tax revenue, fees, or receipts, as may be determined by the issuer. The issuer may further secure such bonds by a mortgage or deed of trust encumbering all or any portion of the facilities financed with the proceeds of such bonds and by a bond insurance policy or other credit support facility. No general obligation bonds, except refunding bonds, shall be issued until authorized by a majority of the issuer's electors voting on the question as to the issuance of the bonds at a statewide regular primary election or at a special election duly called for such purpose.</para><para>(3) The face of all such bonds shall plainly state that the bonds and the interest thereon shall not constitute nor give rise to an indebtedness, obligation, or pecuniary liability of the state nor a charge against the general credit, revenue, or taxing power of the state. Bonds issued in accordance with the provisions of this section are declared to be issued for an essential public and governmental purpose and, together with interest thereon and income therefrom, shall be exempt from all state income taxes.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, general obligation bond means any bond or refunding bond which is payable from the proceeds of an ad valorem tax.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 657, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>