<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>19-102</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City of the Primary Class Development Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para id="id00">There is hereby created the City of the Primary Class Development Fund. Amounts credited to the fund pursuant to section 77-2602 shall, upon appropriation by the Legislature, be first expended to support the design and development of the Antelope Valley project and financing costs related thereto for the Antelope Valley Study as outlined in the Environmental Impact Statement and Comprehensive Plan Amendment 94-60 to the 1994 Lincoln/Lancaster County Comprehensive Plan. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para id="id00">No distribution from the fund shall be made unless the city of the primary class provides matching funds equal to the ratio of one dollar for each three dollars of the state distribution. Funds derived from any state source may not be utilized as matching funds for purposes of this section.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer the unobligated balance in the City of the Primary Class Development Fund to the General Fund on July 1, 2017, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible, on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. On July 8, 2017, the City of the Primary Class Development Fund shall terminate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 657, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>