<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Particular Classes" statutenumber="19-409"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-409</statuteno><catchline>Council members; excise members; candidates; terms.</catchline><para>(1) The two candidates receiving the highest number of votes at the primary election shall be placed upon the official ballot for such position at the statewide general election. If no candidates appeared on the primary election ballot or if the council waived the primary election under section 19-405, all persons filing pursuant to section 19-405 shall be the only candidates whose names shall be placed upon the official ballot for such position at the statewide general election.</para><para>(2) If excise members are to be elected, the six candidates receiving the highest number of votes for excise members at the primary election or all candidates, if there are less than six on the primary election ballot or if no primary election is held, shall be the only candidates whose names shall be placed upon the official ballot for excise members at the statewide general election in any such city.</para><para>(3) Terms for council members shall begin on the date of the first regular meeting of the council in December following the statewide general election. The terms of council members holding office on August 28, 1999, shall be extended to the first regular meeting of the council in December following the statewide general election. The changes made to this section by Laws 1999, LB 250, shall not change the staggering of the terms of council members in cities that have adopted the commission plan of government prior to January 1, 1999.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 24, &#167; 7, p. 155; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 21, &#167; 3, p. 88; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5294; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4517; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 141, &#167; 5, p. 348; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-407; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-409; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 112, &#167; 4, p. 522; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 327, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 512; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 250, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>The provision that the only candidates whose names shall be placed upon the official ballot at the city election means that these are the only candidates whose names shall be printed on the official ballot, and there is no prohibition against any voter inserting the names of such other persons as he may desire to vote for. State ex rel. Zeilinger v. Thompson, 134 Neb. 739, 279 N.W. 462 (1938).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>