<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-417" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>19-417</statuteno><catchline>Offices and boards; creation; discontinuance.</catchline><para>The city council in a city under the commission plan of government shall have power to discontinue any employment or abolish any office at any time, when, in the judgment of the city council, such employment or office is no longer necessary. The city council shall have power, at any time and at any meeting, to create any office or board it deems necessary, including the office of city manager, and fix salaries. The city council may create a board of three or more members composed of other officers of the city and confer upon such board any power not required to be exercised by the city council itself. The city council may require such officers to serve upon any such board and perform the services required of it with or without any additional pay for such additional service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 24, &#167; 14, p. 162; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5301; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 35, &#167; 1, p. 116; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4524; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-414; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-417; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>For reasons of economy or lack of public necessity for services of a policeman, the city authorities may, when they see fit, terminate his employment, and he has no right to a statutory hearing upon the question of whether the public welfare requires a continuance of a full police force, or whether or not the revenues available are adequate for the payment of his salary. Rooney v. City of Omaha, 105 Neb. 447, 181 N.W. 143 (1920).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>