<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-902"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>19-902</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Zoning regulations; uniformity; manufactured homes; certain codes excepted.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) For any or all of the purposes designated in section 19-901, the city council or village board of trustees may divide the municipality into districts of such number, shape, and area as may be deemed best suited to carry out the purposes of sections 19-901 to 19-915 and may regulate and restrict the erection, construction, reconstruction, alteration, repair, or use of buildings, structures, or land within such districts. All such regulations shall be uniform for each class or kind of buildings throughout each district, but the regulations applicable to one district may differ from those applicable to other districts. For a city of the first class as described in subdivision (3) of section 19-5503, such regulations shall comply with the Municipal Density and Missing Middle Housing Act. If a regulation affects the Niobrara scenic river corridor as defined in section 72-2006 and is not incorporated within the boundaries of the municipality, the Niobrara Council shall act on the regulation as provided in section 72-2010.</para><para id="id00">(2)(a) The city council or village board of trustees shall not adopt or enforce any zoning ordinance or regulation which prohibits the use of land for a proposed residential structure for the sole reason that the proposed structure is a manufactured home if such manufactured home bears an appropriate seal which indicates that it was constructed in accordance with the standards of the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles, the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act, or the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development. The city council or village board of trustees may require that a manufactured home be located and installed according to the same standards for foundation system, permanent utility connections, setback, and minimum square footage which would apply to a site-built, single-family dwelling on the same lot. The city council or village board of trustees may also require that manufactured homes meet the following standards:</para><para id="id00">(i) The home shall have no less than nine hundred square feet of floor area;</para><para id="id00">(ii) The home shall have no less than an eighteen-foot exterior width;</para><para id="id00">(iii) The roof shall be pitched with a minimum vertical rise of two and one-half inches for each twelve inches of horizontal run;</para><para id="id00">(iv) The exterior material shall be of a color, material, and scale comparable with those existing in residential site-built, single-family construction;</para><para id="id00">(v) The home shall have a nonreflective roof material which is or simulates asphalt or wood shingles, tile, or rock; and</para><para id="id00">(vi) The home shall have wheels, axles, transporting lights, and removable towing apparatus removed.</para><para id="id00">(b) The city council or village board of trustees may not require additional standards unless such standards are uniformly applied to all single-family dwellings in the zoning district.</para><para id="id00">(c) Nothing in this subsection shall be deemed to supersede any valid restrictive covenants of record.</para><para id="id00">(3) For purposes of this section, manufactured home shall mean (a) a factory-built structure which is to be used as a place for human habitation, which is not constructed or equipped with a permanent hitch or other device allowing it to be moved other than to a permanent site, which does not have permanently attached to its body or frame any wheels or axles, and which bears a label certifying that it was built in compliance with national Manufactured Home Construction and Safety Standards, 24 C.F.R. 3280 et seq., promulgated by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development, or (b) a modular housing unit as defined in section 71-1557 bearing a seal in accordance with the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act.</para><para id="id00">(4) Subdivision regulations and building, plumbing, electrical, housing, fire, or health codes or similar regulations and the adoption thereof shall not be subject to sections 19-901 to 19-915.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 43, &#167; 2, p. 183; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-902; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-902; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 298, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 313, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 511, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1234, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB866, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Municipal Density and Missing Middle Housing Act,</emphasis> see section 19-5501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1555.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles,</emphasis> see section 71-4601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>