<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-909"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-909</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of adjustment; appeals to board; record on appeal; hearing; stays.</catchline><para id="id00">Appeals to the board of adjustment may be taken by any person aggrieved or by any officer, department, board, or bureau of the municipality affected by any decision of the administrative officer. Such appeal shall be taken within a reasonable time, as provided by the rules of the board of adjustment, by filing with the officer from whom the appeal is taken and with the board of adjustment a notice of appeal specifying the grounds for such appeal. The officer from whom the appeal is taken shall forthwith transmit to the board of adjustment all the papers constituting the record upon which the action appealed from was taken. An appeal stays all proceedings in furtherance of the action appealed from, unless the officer from whom the appeal is taken certifies to the board of adjustment, after the notice of appeal shall have been filed with him or her, that by reason of facts stated in the certificate a stay would, in his or her opinion, cause imminent peril to life or property. In such case proceedings shall not be stayed otherwise than by a restraining order which may be granted by the board of adjustment or by a court of record on application on notice to the officer from whom the appeal is taken and on due cause shown. The board of adjustment shall fix a reasonable time for the hearing of the appeal, give public notice thereof, as well as due notice to the parties in interest, and decide the same within a reasonable time. Upon the hearing any party may appear in person or by agent or by attorney.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 43, &#167; 7, p. 185; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-907; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-909; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 75. </para></source><annotation><para>Procedural rules detailed in statutes and city zoning ordinance need not be further adopted by a board of adjustment. South Maple Street Assn. v. Board of Adjustment of City of Chadron, 194 Neb. 118, 230 N.W.2d 471 (1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>