<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id110">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id112" statutenumber="19-916"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id114">19-916</statuteno><catchline id="id115">Additions; subdivision or platting; procedure;
rights and privileges of inhabitants; powers of legislative body; approval
required; effect; filing and
recording.</catchline><para>(1) The local legislative
body shall have power by ordinance to provide the manner, plan, or method
by which land within the corporate limits of any such municipality, or land
within the area designated by a city of the first class pursuant to subsection
(1) of section 16-902 or within the area designated by a city of the second
class or village pursuant to subsection (1) of section 17-1002, may be subdivided,
platted, or laid out, including a plan or system for the avenues, streets,
or alleys to be laid out within or across such land, and to compel the owners
of any such land that are subdividing, platting, or laying out such land to
conform to the requirements of the ordinance and to lay out and dedicate the
avenues, streets, and alleys in accordance with the ordinance as provided
in sections 16-901 to 16-905 and sections 17-1001 to 17-1004. No addition
shall have any validity, right, or privileges as an addition, and no plat
of land or, in the absence of a plat, no instrument subdividing land within
the corporate limits of any such municipality or of any land within the area
designated by a city of the first class pursuant to subsection (1) of section
16-902 or within the area designated by a city of the second class or village
pursuant to subsection (1) of section 17-1002, shall be recorded or have any
force or effect, unless the plat or instrument is approved by the legislative
body, or its designated agent, and the legislative body's or agent's approval
is endorsed on such plat or instrument.</para><para>(2)
The legislative body may designate by ordinance an employee of such city or
village to approve further subdivision of existing lots and blocks whenever
all required public improvements have been installed, no new dedication of
public rights-of-way or easements is involved, and such subdivision complies
with the ordinance requirements concerning minimum areas and dimensions of
such lots and blocks.</para>

<para>(3) All additions laid out contiguous or adjacent to the corporate
limits may be included within the corporate limits and become a part of such
municipality for all purposes whatsoever if
approved by the legislative body of the city or village under this subsection.
The proprietor or proprietors of any land within the corporate limits of any
city of the first or second class or village, or of any land contiguous or
adjacent to the corporate limits, may lay out such land into lots, blocks,
streets, avenues, alleys, and other grounds under the name of .......... Addition
to the City or Village of .........., and shall cause an accurate map or plat
thereof to be made out, designating explicitly the land so laid out and particularly
describing the lots, blocks, streets, avenues, alleys, and other grounds belonging
to such addition. The lots shall be designated by numbers, and streets, avenues,
and other grounds, by names or numbers. Such plat shall be acknowledged before
some officer authorized to take the acknowledgments of deeds, shall contain
a dedication of the streets, alleys, and public grounds therein to the use
and benefit of the public, and shall have appended a survey made by some competent
surveyor with a certificate attached, certifying that he or she has accurately
surveyed such addition and that the lots, blocks, streets, avenues, alleys,
parks, commons, and other grounds are well and accurately staked off and marked.
The addition may become part of the municipality at such time
as the addition is approved by
the legislative body if (a) after giving notice of the time and
place of the hearing as provided in section 19-904, the planning commission
and the legislative body both hold public hearings on the inclusion of the
addition within the corporate limits and (b) the legislative body votes to approve
the inclusion of the addition within the corporate boundaries of the municipality
in a separate vote from the vote approving the addition. Such hearings shall be separate from the public hearings
held regarding approval of the addition. If the legislative body
includes the addition within the corporate limits, the inhabitants of such
addition shall be entitled to all the rights and privileges and shall be subject to all the laws, ordinances,
rules, and regulations of the municipality to which such land is an addition. When such map or plat is made out, acknowledged,
and certified, and has been approved by the local legislative body, the map
or plat shall be filed and recorded in the office of the register of deeds
and county assessor of the county. If the legislative body includes the addition
within the corporate limits, such map or plat shall be equivalent to a deed
in fee simple absolute to the municipality from the proprietor of all streets,
avenues, alleys, public squares, parks, and commons, and of such portion of
the land as is therein set apart for public and municipal use, or is dedicated
to charitable, religious, or educational purposes.</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 6, p. 228; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4811; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3979; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-108; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-112; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 66, &#167; 1, p. 215; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 757, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 16-112; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 71, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 210, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB495, &#167; 9.</para></source><annotation><para>Annexation by city council resolution in compliance with a subdivision ordinance adopted by the city under section 19-916 constitutes a declaration of boundaries of the city by ordinance within the meaning of former section 79-801. The effective date of the city annexation ordinance is the date of the city council resolution of approval. Northwest High School Dist. No. 82 of Hall &amp; Merrick Counties v. Hessel, 210 Neb. 219, 313 N.W.2d 656 (1981).</para><para>One of two methods of annexing territory to a city of the first class is provided by this section. State ex rel. City of Grand Island v. Tillman, 174 Neb. 23, 115 N.W.2d 796 (1962).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>