
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-616"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-616</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Appointive or elected official; compensation; no change during term of office.</catchline><para id="id00">The annual compensation of the mayor and city council members in cities under the city manager plan of government shall be payable quarterly in equal installments and shall be fixed by the city council. The salary of any appointive or elective officer shall not be increased or diminished during the term for which such officer was elected or appointed, except that when there are officers elected or appointed to the city council or a board or commission having more than one member and the terms of one or more members commence and end at different times, the compensation of all members of such city council, board, or commission may be increased or diminished at the beginning of the full term of any member thereof. No person who has resigned or vacated any office shall be eligible to be elected or appointed to such office during the time for which he or she was elected or appointed when, during the same time, the salary has been increased. For each absence from regular meetings of the city council, unless authorized by a two-thirds vote of all members of the city council, there shall be deducted a sum equal to two percent of such annual salary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 208, &#167; 17, p. 501; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4554; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-617; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-616; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 113, &#167; 1, p. 515; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1054, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 47. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Vacancies,</emphasis> how filled, see sections 19-3101 and 32-560 to 32-574.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>