<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-418"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-418</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City council; meetings; quorum.</catchline><para id="id00">In cities under the commission plan of government, the regular meetings of the city council in cities of the metropolitan class shall be held at least once in each week and upon such day and hour as the city council may designate. In all other cities under the commission plan of government having a population of two thousand or more as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the regular meetings of the city council shall be held at such intervals and upon such day and hour as the city council may by ordinance or resolution designate. Special meetings of the city council in any of such cities may be called, from time to time, by the mayor or two city council members, giving notice in such manner as may be fixed or defined by law or ordinance in any of such cities or as shall be fixed by ordinance or resolution by such city council. A majority of such city council shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business, but it shall require a majority vote of the city council in any such city to pass any measure or transact any business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 24, &#167; 15, p. 163; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5302; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4525; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-415; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-418; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 257, &#167; 18, p. 941; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 23. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>