<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Particular Classes" statutenumber="19-1826"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>19-1826</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As
used in the Civil Service Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Commission shall mean a civil service commission created pursuant
to the Civil Service Act, and commissioner shall mean a member of such commission;</para>
<para>(2) Appointing authority shall mean: (a) In a mayor and council form
of government, the mayor with the approval of the council, except to the extent
that the appointing authority is otherwise designated by ordinance to be the
mayor or city administrator; (b) in a commission form of government, the mayor
and city council or village board; (c) in a village form of government, the
village board; and (d) in a city manager plan of government, the city manager;</para>
<para>(3) Appointment shall mean all means of selecting, appointing, or employing
any person to hold any position or employment subject to civil service;</para>
<para>(4) Municipality shall mean all cities and villages specified in subsection
(1) of section 19-1827 having full-time police officers or full-time firefighters;</para>
<para>(5) Governing body shall mean: (a) In a mayor and council form of government,
the mayor and council; (b) in a commission form of government, the mayor and
council or village board; (c) in a village form of government, the village
board; and (d) in a city manager plan of government, the mayor and council;</para>
<para>(6) Full-time police officers shall mean police officers in positions
which require certification by the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center,
created pursuant to section 81-1402, who have the power of arrest, who are
paid regularly by a municipality, and for whom law enforcement is a full-time
career, but shall not include clerical, custodial, or maintenance personnel;</para>
<para>(7) Full-time firefighter shall mean duly appointed firefighters who
are paid regularly by a municipality and for whom firefighting is a full-time
career, but shall not include clerical, custodial, or maintenance personnel
who are not engaged in fire suppression;</para>
<para>(8) Promotion or demotion shall mean changing from one position to another,
accompanied by a corresponding change in current rate of pay;</para>
<para>(9) Position shall mean an individual job which is designated by an
official title indicative of the nature of the work;</para>
<para>(10) Merged commission
shall mean a civil service commission resulting from the merger of two or
more commissions pursuant to section 19-1848;</para><para>(11) Agreement shall mean an agreement
pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act; and</para><para>(12) Existing commission shall mean
a civil service commission of a city of the first class as it existed immediately
prior to the effective creation of a merged commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 29, &#167; 23, p. 138; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-1823; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 48, &#167; 7, p. 236; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 19-1823; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 372, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB943, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>April 2, 2010</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Fully paid fire department means a fire department having members paid regularly by city and devoting their whole time to firefighting. State ex rel. Retchless v. Cook, 181 Neb. 863, 152 N.W.2d 23 (1967).</para><para>By definition contained in this section, employee is required to devote his whole time to firefighting or law enforcement. Dlouhy v. City of Fremont, 175 Neb. 115, 120 N.W.2d 590 (1963).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>