
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-1827"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-1827</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Civil service commission; applicability; members; appointment; compensation; term; removal; appeal; quorum.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) There is hereby created, in cities having a population of more than five thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census and having full-time police officers or full-time firefighters, a civil service commission, except in cities with a population in excess of forty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census which have or may adopt a home rule charter pursuant to sections 2 to 5 of Article XI of the Constitution of Nebraska. Any city or village having a population of five thousand inhabitants or less as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census may adopt the Civil Service Act and create a civil service commission by a vote of the electors of such city or village. If any city of the first class which established a civil service commission decreases in population to less than five thousand, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, and continues to have full-time police officers or full-time firefighters, the civil service commission shall be continued for at least four years, and thereafter continued at the option of the governing body of such city or village. The members of such commission shall be appointed by the appointing authority.</para><para id="id00">(2) The governing body shall by ordinance determine if the commission shall be comprised of three or five members. The members of the civil service commission shall serve without compensation. No person shall be appointed a member of such commission who is not a citizen of the United States, a resident of such city or village for at least three years immediately preceding such appointment, and an elector of the county wherein such person resides. If the commission is comprised of three members, the term of office of such commissioners shall be six years, except that the first three members of such commission shall be appointed for different terms, as follows: One to serve for a period of two years, one to serve for a period of four years, and one to serve for a period of six years. If the commission is comprised of five members, the term of office of such members shall be for five years, except that the first members of such commission shall be appointed for different terms, as follows: One to serve for a period of one year, one to serve for a period of two years, one to serve for a period of three years, one to serve for a period of four years, and one to serve for a period of five years. If the city or village determines by ordinance to change from a three-member commission to a five-member commission, or from a five-member commission to a three-member commission, the members of the commission serving before the effective date of such ordinance shall hold office until reappointed or their successors are appointed.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any member of the civil service commission may be removed from office for incompetency, dereliction of duty, malfeasance in office, or other good cause by the appointing authority, except that no member of the commission shall be removed until written charges have been made, due notice given such member, and a full hearing had before the appointing authority. Any member so removed shall have the right to appeal to the district court of the county in which such commission is located, which court shall hear and determine such appeal in a summary manner. Such an appeal shall be only upon the ground that such judgment or order of removal was not made in good faith for cause, and the hearing on such appeal shall be confined to the determination of whether or not it was so made.</para><para id="id00">(4) The members of the civil service commission shall devote due time and attention to the performance of the duties specified and imposed upon them by the Civil Service Act. Two commissioners in a three-member commission and three commissioners in a five-member commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. Confirmation of the appointment or appointments of commissioners, made under subsection (1) of this section, by any other legislative body shall not be required. At the time of any appointment, not more than two commissioners of a three-member commission, or three commissioners of a five-member commission, including the one or ones to be appointed, shall be registered electors of the same political party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 29, &#167; 1, p. 125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-1801; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 48, &#167; 1, p. 228; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 89, &#167; 5, p. 304; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 291, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 19-1801; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 372, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 122. </para></source><annotation><para>Procedure regulating discharge of city employee in classified civil service is governed by the Nebraska Civil Service Act. Wachtel v. Fremont Civil Service Commission, 190 Neb. 49, 206 N.W.2d 56 (1973).</para><para>This article prescribes civil service for cities having a full paid fire or police department. State ex rel. Retchless v. Cook, 181 Neb. 863, 152 N.W.2d 23 (1967).</para><para>Civil Service Act is applicable to all cities having a full paid fire or police department. Dlouhy v. City of Fremont, 175 Neb. 115, 120 N.W.2d 590 (1963).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>