
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes"  statutenumber="19-1848"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-1848</statuteno><catchline>Merger of commissions; agreement;
applicability of act; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Any two or more cities of the first class which have
civil service commissions may merge their commissions by an agreement.</para>
<para>(2) The agreement shall
state the date of creation of the merged commission. Upon the date of creation
of the merged commission, the existing commissions shall be dissolved without
further action by the governing body. The dissolution of an existing commission
and the resulting loss of authority by the members of the existing commissions
shall not be deemed a removal from office under subsection (3) of section
19-1827. Members of the existing commissions are eligible for appointment
to the merged commission.</para><para>(3)
The Civil Service Act shall be applicable to a merged commission except as
provided in the following provisions:</para><para>(a) A merged commission shall consist of three, five,
seven, or nine members, as provided in the agreement;</para><para>(b) Each city participating in the
agreement shall appoint at least one member to the merged commission;</para>
<para>(c) Each member of such
merged commission shall be a resident of one of the cities participating in
the agreement for at least three years immediately preceding his or her appointment;</para>
<para>(d) The term of office
of each member of the merged commission shall be as provided in the agreement,
except that such term shall not exceed six years. The agreement may provide
for staggered terms of office for the initial members of the merged commission;</para>
<para>(e) At the time of appointment,
not more than four members of a seven-member commission nor more than five
members of a nine-member commission shall be of the same political party;
and</para><para>(f)
The appointing authority for purposes of appointing members to the merged
commission shall be as defined in the act. The agreement shall provide for
the appointing authority for the purpose of exercising all other powers of
the appointing authority as described in the act.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB943, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>