<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-1303"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>19-1303</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Sinking fund; resolution to establish; contents; election; laws governing.</catchline><para id="id00">Before any sinking fund or funds shall be established or before any annual tax shall be levied for planned municipal improvements mentioned in section 19-1302, by a city or village, the city council or village board of trustees shall declare its purpose by resolution to submit to the qualified electors of the city or village at the next general municipal election the proposition to provide such city or village with the specific municipal improvement planned under sections 19-1301 to 19-1304. Such resolution of submission shall, among other things, set forth a clear description of the improvement planned, the estimated cost according to the prevailing costs, the amount of annual levy over a definite period of years, not exceeding ten years, required to provide such cost, and the specific name or designation for the sinking fund sought to be established to carry out the planned improvement, together with a statement of the proposition for placement upon the ballot at such election. Notice of the submission of the proposition, together with a copy of the official ballot containing such proposition, shall be published in its entirety three successive weeks before the day of the election in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the municipality or, if no legal newspaper is in or of general circulation in the municipality, in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the county in which such city or village is located. No such sinking fund shall be established unless the same shall have been authorized by a majority or more of the legal votes of such city or village cast for or against the proposition. If less than a majority of the legal votes favor the establishment of the sinking fund, the planned improvement shall not be made, no annual tax shall be levied therefor, and no sinking fund or sinking funds shall be established in connection therewith, but such resolution of submission shall immediately be repealed. If the proposition shall carry at such election in the manner prescribed in this section, the city council or village board of trustees and its successors in office shall proceed to do all things authorized under such resolution of submission but never inconsistent with sections 19-1301 to 19-1304. The election provided for under this section shall be conducted as provided under the Election Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1939, c. 12, &#167; 3, p. 81; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 19-1303; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-1303; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 59, &#167; 2, p. 217; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 105. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This section does not apply to creating a sinking fund for payment of interest and principal of bonds. Talbott v. City of Lyons, 171 Neb. 186, 105 N.W.2d 918 (1960).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>