<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-1102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>19-1102</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City or village clerk; proceedings of council; publication; contents.</catchline><para id="id00">It shall be the duty of each village or city clerk in every village or city having a population of not more than one hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census to prepare and publish the official proceedings of the village or city board, council, or commission within thirty days after any meeting of the board, council, or commission. The publication shall be in a newspaper in or of general circulation in the village or city, shall set forth a statement of the proceedings of the meeting, and shall also include the amount of each claim allowed, the purpose of the claim, and the name of the claimant, except that the aggregate amount of all payroll claims may be included as one item. Between July 15 and August 15 of each year, the employee job titles and the current annual, monthly, or hourly salaries corresponding to such job titles shall be published. Each job title published shall be descriptive and indicative of the duties and functions of the position. The charge for the publication shall not exceed the rates provided for in section 23-122.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 183, &#167; 1, p. 410; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4376; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-574; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-1102; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 193, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 415, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 30. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>