<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-2203"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>19-2203</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Error in platting; application; order to show cause; contents; publication.</catchline><para id="id00">If it shall appear to the judge of the district court that the application presented pursuant to section 19-2201 is properly filed, he or she shall make an order directing all persons owning real estate or having an interest in real estate situated in such part of such city or village, giving the name of the plat as recorded as well as a general description of the territory affected by the proposed correction and reestablishment of corporate limits, to appear before him or her at a time and place to be specified, not less than four and not more than ten weeks from the time of making such order, to show cause why a decree correcting and reestablishing the corporate limits of such city or village should not be entered. The notice of such order to show cause shall be made by publication in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in such city or village. If there is no legal newspaper in or of general circulation in such city or village, then such notice shall be published in some legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the county in which such city or village is located. The notice shall be published four consecutive weeks in such legal newspaper and shall contain a summary statement of the object and prayer of the application, mention the court where it is filed, and notify the persons interested when they are required to appear and show cause why such decree should not be entered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 60, &#167; 3, p. 191; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 138. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>