<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00"  statutenumber="19-2428"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-2428</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Improvement district; land within agricultural use zone; how treated.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever the city council of a city of the first class or city of the second class or the village board of trustees of a village creates an improvement district as specified in section 19-2427 which includes land adjacent to such city or village and such adjacent land is within an agricultural use zone and is used exclusively for agricultural use, the owners of record title of such adjacent land may apply for a deferral from special assessments pursuant to sections 19-2428 to 19-2431.</para><para id="id00">(2) For purposes of sections 19-2428 to 19-2431:</para><para id="id00">(a) Agricultural use means the use of land as described in section 77-1359, so that incidental use of the land for nonagricultural or nonhorticultural purposes shall not disqualify the land; and</para><para id="id00">(b) Agricultural use zone means designation of any land predominantly for agricultural or horticultural use by any political subdivision pursuant to sections 19-925 to 19-933, Chapter 14, article 4, Chapter 15, article 9, Chapter 16, article 9, Chapter 17, article 10, or Chapter 23, article 1. The primary objective of the agricultural use zoning shall be to preserve and protect agricultural activities and the potential for the agricultural, horticultural, or open use of land. Uses to be allowed on such lands include primarily agricultural-related or horticultural-related uses, and nonagricultural or nonhorticultural industrial, commercial, or residential uses allowed on such lands shall be restricted so that they do not conflict with or detract from this objective.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 94, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 679, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 166. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>