<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-2701"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-2701</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Public utilities; service outside city; authorization; limitation on length of contracts.</catchline><para id="id00">A city of the first class or city of the second class may enter into a contract or contracts to sell electric, water, or sewer service to persons beyond the corporate limits of such city when, in the judgment of the mayor and city council of such a city not having a board of public works or of its board of public works in such a city having such board, it is beneficial to such city to do so. No such contract shall run for a period in excess of twenty-five years. Such city is hereby authorized and empowered to enter into contracts for the furnishing of electric service to persons, firms, associations, and corporations beyond the corporate limits of such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 19, &#167; 1, p. 186; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167;&#167; 4959, 4960; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167;&#167; 4128, 4129; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 43, &#167; 2, p. 188; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167;&#167; 16-657, 16-658; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-685; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 26, &#167; 4, p. 130; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 16-685; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 53, &#167; 1, p. 262; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 170. </para></source><annotation><para>City was given power to contract for the sale of water outside the city limits. Burger v. City of Beatrice, 181 Neb. 213, 147 N.W.2d 784 (1967).</para><para>The provisions of this section were modified by legislative act creating the Nebraska Power Review Board. City of Auburn v. Eastern Nebraska Public Power Dist., 179 Neb. 439, 138 N.W.2d 629 (1965).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>