<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-2418" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>19-2418</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Sidewalks; construct, replace, repair; districts; special assessments; payment.</catchline><para>The mayor and city council or board of trustees shall levy special assessments on the lots and parcels of land abutting on or adjacent to the sidewalk improvements specially benefited thereby in such district in proportion to the benefits, to pay the cost of such improvement. All special assessments shall be a lien on the property on which levied from the date of the levy until paid. The special assessment for the sidewalk improvement shall be levied at one time and shall become delinquent as follows: One-seventh of the total assessment shall become delinquent in ten days after such levy; one-seventh in one year; one-seventh in two years; one-seventh in three years; one-seventh in four years; one-seventh in five years; and one-seventh in six years. Each of such installments, except the first, shall draw interest at the rate of not exceeding the rate of interest specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, from the time of the levy until the installment becomes delinquent. If the installment becomes delinquent, interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, shall be paid thereon as in the case of other special assessments. All such special assessments shall be made and collected in accordance with the procedure established for paving assessments for the particular city or village.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 80, &#167; 2, p. 316; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 933, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 45. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>