<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-3327"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>19-3327</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Offstreet parking; additional authority; notice; hearing; written objections; resolution; procedure.</catchline><para id="id00">Any city of the primary class, city of the first class, or city of the second class, after the creation of an offstreet parking district pursuant to the Offstreet Parking District Act, shall have the power to own, purchase, construct, equip, lease, or operate within such city any offstreet parking facility in addition to any offstreet parking facility contemplated at the time of the creation of the district if the mayor and city council are of the opinion that the district will be benefited thereby. Whenever the city council deems it advisable to own, purchase, construct, equip, lease, or operate such additional facility, the city council shall by resolution set forth the engineer's estimate of the sum of money to be expended in the acquisition of property and the construction of the offstreet parking facility and a description of the facility to be constructed, and if such resolution proposes to acquire by grant, contract, or purchase or through condemnation any offstreet parking facility, the resolution shall state the price and conditions and how such facility shall be acquired, and if assessments are to be levied, the resolution shall state the proposed boundaries of the area in the district in which the special assessments shall be levied. Notice of the time and place of a hearing before the city council on such resolution shall be given by publication one time each week for two weeks in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city. The publication shall contain the entire resolution. The last publication shall not be less than five days nor more than two weeks prior to the date set for such hearing. Not later than the hour set for the hearing, any owner or any person interested in any real property within the proposed area may file with the city clerk written objections to the resolution, the extent of the proposed area, or both, and every person so interested shall have a right to protest on any grounds and to object to his or her real property being included in the area. At such hearing all objections and protests shall be heard and passed upon by the mayor and city council. If the owners of record title representing more than sixty percent of the taxable valuation of all of the taxable real property included in such proposed area and who were such owners at the time the notice of hearing on objections to the creation of the facility was first published file a petition with the city clerk within three days of the date set for the hearing, such resolution shall not be passed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 540, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 564, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 206. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Downtown improvement and parking districts,</emphasis> see section 19-4038.</para><para><emphasis>Offstreet Parking District Act,</emphasis> see section 19-3301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>