<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-3701"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-3701</statuteno><catchline>Ordinances; effective date.</catchline><para>All ordinances for the government of any city of the first or second class or of any village, adopted by the voters of said city after submission to them by either initiative or referendum petition shall become immediately effective thereafter; but no ordinance for the government of any such city or village except as provided in sections 16-405 and 17-613, which has been adopted by such city or village without submission to the voters of such city or village, shall go into effect until fifteen days after the passage of such ordinance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1897, c. 32, &#167; 12, p. 234; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5237; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 96, &#167; 1, p. 238; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4436; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 18-512; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-130; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 282, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For other provisions applicable to ordinances of cities of the first and second class and villages,</emphasis> see sections 16-247, 16-403 to 16-405, 17-613 to 17-616, and 19-604.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Immediate publication of notice of creation of paving district was proper. Freeman v. City of Neligh, 155 Neb. 651, 53 N.W.2d 67 (1952).</para><para>The provisions of this section that "no ordinance for the government of any city shall go into effect until thirty days after the passage of the same" does not apply to issuing a liquor license. Enos v. Hanff, 98 Neb. 245, 152 N.W. 397 (1915).</para><para>An ordinance adopted by the voters under the initiative statute does not "go into effect" until thirty days after it is adopted. Eyre v. Doerr, 97 Neb. 562, 150 N.W. 625 (1915).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>