<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-3318"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>19-3318</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Proposed offstreet parking district; petition; contents; signers; requisite number.</catchline><para id="id00">The owners of the record title of any real property within a given area in any city of the first class or city of the second class representing fifty-five percent of the total taxable valuation of all of the taxable real property within the proposed district to be formed, which district must consist of contiguous lands and lots, may petition the mayor and city council to create a vehicle offstreet parking district by ordinance, which district shall be consecutively numbered, and to acquire property and construct an offstreet parking facility thereon as provided in the Offstreet Parking District Act. For purposes of the act, property separated by streets or alleys shall be deemed to be contiguous.</para><para id="id00">The petition shall contain:</para><para id="id00">(1) A general description of the exterior boundaries of the proposed district;</para><para id="id00">(2) A general statement of the estimated amount of money involved in the acquisition of the land and property and construction of the facility;</para><para id="id00">(3) A general description of the improvements proposed to be made or constructed; and</para><para id="id00">(4) A statement that the petition is filed pursuant to this section.</para><para id="id00">The petition may consist of any number of separate instruments, but a description of the real property represented by each petitioner shall be included either opposite the signature or by separate instrument.</para><para id="id00">When the petition is filed, the city clerk shall check or cause it to be checked. If it is signed by qualified signers representing the required percentage of the total taxable valuation, the city clerk shall make a certificate to that effect and present the petition and certificate to the mayor and city council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 60, &#167; 18, p. 206; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1967, &#167; 16-829; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 88, &#167; 18, p. 447; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 197. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>