<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-4635"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-4635</statuteno><catchline>Court of condemnation; finding of value; procedure; appeal; abandonment; when.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the determination and filing of a finding of the value of the gas system by the court of condemnation, the city shall have the right and power, by resolution adopted by a majority of the members of its governing body, to elect to abandon the proceedings to acquire the gas system by the exercise of the power of eminent domain.</para><para>(2) If the city (a) does not elect to abandon within ninety days after the finding and filing of value or (b) formally notifies the utility by United States registered mail with signature confirmation that its governing body has voted to proceed with the condemnation, the utility owning the gas system may appeal from the finding of value and award by the court of condemnation to the district court.</para><para>(3) The appeal shall be made by filing with the city clerk within twenty days after (a) the expiration of the time given the city to exercise its rights of abandonment or (b) the date of the receipt of the notice of the city's intent to proceed with condemnation, a bond to be approved by the court of condemnation, conditioned for the payment of all costs which may be made on any appeal, and by filing in the district court, within ninety days after such bond is filed, a transcript of the proceedings before the court of condemnation, including the evidence taken before it, certified by the clerk, reporter, and judges of the court of condemnation. The appeal in the district court shall be tried and determined upon the pleadings, proceedings, and evidence in the transcript.</para><para>(4) Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (1) of this section, the city may abandon the proceedings to acquire the gas system by the exercise of the power of eminent domain at any time prior to taking physical possession of the gas system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 384, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>