
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-4031"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-4031</statuteno><catchline>Business improvement district; general business occupation tax; purpose; exceptions; notice; appeal; collection; basis; area within riverfront development district; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to or in place of the special assessments authorized by the Business Improvement District Act, a city may levy a general business occupation tax upon the businesses and users of space within a business improvement district established for acquiring, constructing, maintaining, or operating public offstreet parking facilities and providing in connection therewith other public improvements and facilities authorized by the Business Improvement District Act, for the purpose of paying all or any part of the total cost and expenses of any authorized improvement or facility within the business improvement district. Notice of a hearing on any such tax levied under the Business Improvement District Act shall be given to the businesses and users of space of the business improvement districts, and appeals may be taken, all in the manner provided in section 19-4030.</para><para>(2) After March 27, 2014, any occupation tax imposed pursuant to this section shall make a reasonable classification of businesses, users of space, or kinds of transactions for purposes of imposing such tax, except that no occupation tax shall be imposed on any transaction which is subject to tax under section 53-160, 66-489, 66-489.02, 66-4,140, 66-4,145, 66-4,146, 77-2602, or 77-4008 or which is exempt from tax under section 77-2704.24. The collection of a tax imposed pursuant to this section shall be made and enforced in such a manner as the city council shall by ordinance determine to produce the required revenue. The city council may provide that failure to pay the tax imposed pursuant to this section shall constitute a violation of the ordinance and subject the violator to a fine or other punishment as provided by ordinance.</para><para>(3) If any part of a business improvement district overlaps with a riverfront development district in which a general business occupation tax is already being levied pursuant to section 19-5312, the city creating the business improvement district shall not impose the business improvement district’s occupation tax within the overlapping area.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 251, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 22, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB474, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB97, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 224. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>