<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id00" statutenumber="19-4630"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>19-4630</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Resolution of intent; public hearing.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A resolution of intent to pursue condemnation pursuant to section 19-4628 shall be presented to the governing body of the city at a regular meeting of such governing body. At that meeting the governing body may adopt the resolution of intent and, if it does so, shall set a time at least forty-five days after the date of the meeting at which the resolution of intent was adopted at which time the governing body of the city shall hold a public hearing.</para><para id="id00">(2) At the public hearing, the sole item of business to be conducted shall be the public hearing on the resolution of intent at which the public shall be permitted to comment on the proposed condemnation, the utility shall be permitted to respond to the statements set out in the resolution of intent and any comments made at the public hearing, and the governing body may act as provided in section 19-4631.</para><para id="id00">(3) The city clerk shall transmit a copy of the resolution of intent and notice of the date and time of the public hearing to the utility by United States registered mail with signature confirmation within seven days after the meeting at which the resolution of intent was adopted. At least thirty days prior to the public hearing, the city shall publish notice of the time and place of the public hearing and a summary of the resolution of intent in a legal newspaper published in or of general circulation in the city.</para><para id="id00">(4) The utility may present to the city a description of portions of the gas system which (a) are not described as part of the gas system being condemned by the city and (b) are served through the town border station of the city. The utility may require the city to include in its description of the gas system being condemned any or all of those portions of the system if the proposed condemnation would sever those portions of the system from the utility's distribution facilities and would require the utility to create new infrastructure to link these portions to its existing delivery system outside the city. If the utility chooses to require the city to include additional portions of the gas system in the description of the property being condemned, it shall do so prior to the adjournment of the public hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 384, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 232. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>