<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="CITIES AND VILLAGES; LAWS APPLICABLE TO MORE THAN ONE AND LESS THAN ALL CLASSES" id="id00" statutenumber="19-4029.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>19-4029.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Notice of hearing; manner given; contents.</catchline><para>(1) A notice of hearing for any hearing under sections 19-4029, 19-4029.02, and 19-4029.03 shall be given by (a) one publication of the notice of hearing in a newspaper of general circulation in the city and (b) mailing a copy of the notice of hearing to each owner of taxable property as shown on the latest tax rolls of the county treasurer for such county. If an occupation tax is to be imposed, a copy of the notice of hearing shall also be mailed to each user of space in the proposed district. Publication and mailing shall be completed at least ten days prior to the time of hearing.</para><para>(2) Any notice of hearing for any hearing required by section 19-4029 shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) A description of the boundaries of the proposed district;</para><para>(b) The time and place of a hearing to be held by the city council to consider establishment of the district;</para><para>(c) The proposed public facilities and improvements to be made or maintained within any such district; and</para><para>(d) The proposed or estimated costs for improvements and facilities within the proposed district and the method by which the revenue shall be raised. If a special assessment is proposed, the notice shall also state the proposed method of assessment.</para><para>(3) Any notice of hearing for any hearing required by sections 19-4029.02 and 19-4029.03 shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) A description of the boundaries of the area to be added to the existing business improvement district and a description of the new boundaries of the modified district;</para><para>(b) The time and place of a hearing to be held by the city council to consider establishment of the modified district;</para><para>(c) The new public facilities and improvements, if any, to be made or maintained within any such district; and</para><para>(d) The proposed or estimated costs for new and existing improvements and facilities within the proposed modified district and the method by which the revenue shall be raised. If a special assessment is proposed, the notice shall also state the proposed method of assessment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 251, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 22, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2012), &#167; 19-4025; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB168, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>