<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-4637"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-4637</statuteno><catchline>Voter approval.</catchline><para>(1) A city shall not appropriate a gas system through the exercise of the power of eminent domain without the approval of the registered voters of the city as provided in the Municipal Natural Gas System Condemnation Act.</para><para>(2) At such time as (a) the court of condemnation has finally determined the value of the gas system and no appeal has been perfected to the district court from that determination by the city or the utility, (b) the district court has pronounced its final judgment on the value of the gas system, and neither the utility or city has perfected an appeal to the Supreme Court from such judgment, or (c) the Supreme Court has pronounced its final judgment on the value of the gas system, the governing body of the city may submit to the registered voters of the city at any general or special city election the question of whether the city should acquire the gas system by the exercise of the power of eminent domain at the price established by the court of condemnation, the district court, or the Supreme Court as the case may be. The ballot language shall describe the property to be acquired and the interest in the property being sought and shall recite the cost of the acquisition as adjudged by the court establishing the value of the gas system. The ballot question shall be in the following form:</para><para>Shall the city of (name of city) acquire by the exercise of the power of eminent domain the gas system currently owned by (name of utility) at a total cost of (set out the total dollar amount to be awarded to the utility as determined by the court of condemnation, the district court, or the Supreme Court as the case may be): ....Yes ....No</para><para>(3) The city shall submit the question to the registered voters in the manner prescribed in the Election Act. The question may be placed before the registered voters of the city at any general or special city election called for the purpose and may be submitted in connection with any city special election called for any other purpose. The votes cast on the question shall be canvassed and the result found and declared as prescribed in the Election Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 384, &#167; 14. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>