
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id15"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to More Than One and Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-5406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>19-5406</statuteno><catchline>Registration of property; duty of owner; information required; fee; exemptions.</catchline><para>(1) Owners of vacant property subject to a vacant property registration ordinance adopted pursuant to section 19-5405 shall be required to register such property with the program administrator if the property has been vacant for one hundred eighty days or longer. A vacant property registration ordinance registration form shall be in either paper or electronic form, and the following information shall be required:</para><para>(a) The name, street address, mailing address, telephone number, and, if applicable, the facsimile number and email address of the property owner and his or her agent;</para><para>(b) The street address and parcel identification number of the vacant property;</para><para>(c) The transfer date of the instrument conveying the property to the owner; and</para><para>(d) The date on which the property became vacant.</para><para>(2)(a) A vacant property registration ordinance may require payment of a fee one hundred eighty days after initial registration of the vacant property pursuant to subsection (1) of this section or three hundred sixty days after the property becomes vacant, whichever is sooner, and may require the payment of supplemental registration fees at intervals not more frequently than every six months thereafter for as long as the property remains on the vacant property registration database. The initial registration fee shall be not more than two hundred fifty dollars for a residential property and not more than one thousand dollars for a commercial property. A supplemental registration fee shall be not more than double the previous fee amount, with a maximum supplemental registration fee of ten times the initial registration fee amount. Registration fees may be refundable for the year preceding the date on which the property is no longer vacant.</para><para>(b) A vacant property registration ordinance shall provide an exemption to the registration and fee requirements for vacant property that is advertised in good faith for sale or lease.</para><para>(c) A vacant property registration ordinance may provide exemptions to the registration and fee requirements, including, but not limited to, for vacant property:</para><para>(i) Only considered to be a seasonal residence;</para><para>(ii) Damaged by fire, weather, an act of God, or vandalism;</para><para>(iii) Under construction or renovation;</para><para>(iv) Where the owner is temporarily absent, but who has demonstrated his or her intent to return; and</para><para>(v) Which is subject to divorce, probate, or estate proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB256, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>