<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id610"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to More Than One and Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-5805"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>19-5805</statuteno><catchline>Report.</catchline><para>(1) On or before July 1, 2025, and on or before July 1 of each odd-numbered year thereafter, each city shall electronically submit a report to the Urban Affairs Committee of the Legislature detailing its efforts to eliminate poverty. The report shall encompass the following key components:</para><para>(a) Needs Assessment. Conducting a comprehensive needs assessment to identify challenges in housing, education, health care, employment, access to capital, economic development, and social services in target areas;</para><para>(b) Community Engagement. Involving residents, community organizations, and stakeholders in the planning process to ensure community input;</para><para>(c) Data Analysis. Utilizing data and research to understand root causes of poverty and measure the impact of interventions;</para><para>(d) Education and Job Training. Developing accessible education and job training programs in sectors with growth potential;</para><para>(e) Affordable Housing. Implementing strategies to increase affordable housing options, address homelessness, and promote home ownership;</para><para>(f) Health Care Access. Improving access to quality health care services, including mental health and substance abuse treatment;</para><para>(g) Economic Development. Attracting investments to stimulate local business growth and job creation;</para><para>(h) Transportation and Infrastructure. Investing in transportation options and infrastructure improvements;</para><para>(i) Social Services. Expanding access to social services such as child care, food assistance, and counseling;</para><para>(j) Equity and Inclusion. Promoting equity and inclusivity, and addressing disparities based on race, gender, and other factors;</para><para>(k) Accountability and Evaluation. Establishing metrics for progress tracking and regular evaluations;</para><para>(l) Funding and Resources. Securing funding from various sources, including government grants and private investments;</para><para>(m) Long-Term Sustainability. Developing a long-term sustainability plan to maintain improvements;</para><para>(n) Coordination and Collaboration. Fostering coordination and collaboration among government agencies, nonprofit organizations, and businesses; and</para><para>(o) Public Awareness. Promoting awareness of the city's efforts, goals, and progress through communication and outreach efforts.</para><para>(2) The Urban Affairs Committee of the Legislature may request any city to present its report to the committee at a public hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB840, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>