<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id191">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id193" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="19-5218"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>19-5218</statuteno><catchline>Sale of property as part of foreclosure
proceedings; land bank; powers.</catchline><para>(1)(a) At any sale of real property conducted as part of
foreclosure proceedings under sections 77-1901 to 77-1941, a land bank may:</para>
<para>(i) Bid on
such real property in an amount that the land bank would be willing to pay
for such real property. If a bid is given pursuant to this subdivision, the
bid shall not receive any special treatment by the sheriff conducting the
sale and shall be accepted or rejected in the same manner as any other bid
on such real property; or</para><para>(ii) Give an automatically accepted bid on such real property in
an amount equal to the total amount of taxes, interest, and costs due on the
real property. If an automatically accepted bid is given, it shall be accepted
by the sheriff regardless of any other bids on such real property. An automatically
accepted bid may be given only if the conditions for making such a bid prescribed
by the board pursuant to subsection (11) of section 19-5205 have been met
and only if the land bank has obtained written consent to the tender of an
automatically accepted bid from the holder of a mortgage or the beneficiary
or trustee under a trust deed giving rise to a lien against such real property.
To obtain such written consent, the land bank shall send, by certified mail,
a notice of its intent to make an automatically accepted bid to any such holder
of a mortgage or beneficiary or trustee under a trust deed and shall request
that written consent be given within thirty days. If no response is given
within such thirty-day time period, such holder of a mortgage or beneficiary
or trustee under a trust deed shall be deemed to have given written consent.</para>
<para>(b) If a land
bank's bid pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section is accepted by the
sheriff, the land bank shall pay the sheriff and shall be entitled to a deed
to the real property in accordance with sections 77-1901 to 77-1941.</para>
<para>(2) If a sheriff
attempts to sell real property as part of foreclosure proceedings under sections
77-1901 to 77-1941, there is no bid given at such sale equal to the total
amount of taxes, interest, and costs due thereon, and the real property being
sold lies within a municipality that has created a land bank, then such land
bank shall be deemed to have bid the total amount of taxes, interest, and
costs due thereon and such bid shall be accepted by the sheriff. The land
bank may then discharge and extinguish the liens for delinquent taxes included
in the foreclosure proceedings pursuant to section 19-5216. The land bank
shall then be entitled to a deed to the real property in accordance with sections
77-1901 to 77-1941.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>