<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id36" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="19-5205"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>19-5205</statuteno><catchline>Board; requirements; members; qualifications; vacancy; compensation; meetings; actions of board; liability; automatically accepted bid procedure; reasons.</catchline><para>(1) If a land bank is created by a single municipality, the board of such land bank shall meet the following requirements:</para><para>(a) The board shall consist of:</para><para>(i) Seven voting members appointed by the mayor of the municipality that created the land bank and confirmed by a two-thirds vote of the governing body of such municipality;</para><para>(ii) The planning director of the municipality that created the land bank or his or her designee, as a nonvoting, ex officio member;</para><para>(iii) One member of the governing body of the municipality that created the land bank, appointed by such governing body, as a nonvoting, ex officio member; and </para><para>(iv) Such other nonvoting members as are appointed by the mayor of the municipality that created the land bank;</para><para>(b) The seven voting members of the board shall be residents of the municipality that created the land bank;</para><para>(c) If the governing body of the municipality creating the land bank has any of its members elected by district or ward, then at least one voting member of the board shall be appointed from each such district or ward. Such voting members shall represent, to the greatest extent possible, the racial and ethnic diversity of the municipality creating the land bank;</para><para>(d) The seven voting members of the board shall have, collectively, verifiable skills, expertise, and knowledge in market-rate and affordable residential, commercial, industrial, and mixed-use real estate development, financing, law, purchasing and sales, asset management, economic and community development, and the acquisition of tax sale certificates;</para><para>(e) The seven voting members of the board shall include:</para><para>(i) At least one member representing a chamber of commerce;</para><para>(ii) At least one member with experience in banking;</para><para>(iii) At least one member with experience in real estate development;</para><para>(iv) At least one member with experience as a realtor;</para><para>(v) At least one member with experience in nonprofit or affordable housing; and</para><para>(vi) At least one member with experience in large-scale residential or commercial property rental; and</para><para>(f) A single voting member may satisfy more than one of the requirements provided in subdivision (1)(e) of this section if he or she has the required qualifications. It is not necessary that there be a different member to fulfill each such requirement.</para><para>(2) If a land bank is created by more than one municipality pursuant to an agreement under the Interlocal Cooperation Act, the board of such land bank shall meet the following requirements:</para><para>(a) The board shall consist of:</para><para>(i) An odd number of voting members, totaling at least seven, appointed by the mayors of the municipalities that created the land bank, as mutually agreed to by such mayors, and confirmed by a two-thirds vote of the governing body of each municipality that created the land bank;</para><para>(ii) The planning director of each municipality that created the land bank or his or her designee, as nonvoting, ex officio members;</para><para>(iii) One member of the governing body of each municipality that created the land bank, appointed by the governing body on which such member serves, as nonvoting, ex officio members; and</para><para>(iv) Such other nonvoting members as are appointed by the mayors of the municipalities that created the land bank, as mutually agreed to by such mayors;</para><para>(b) Each voting member of the board shall be a resident of one of the municipalities that created the land bank, with at least one voting member appointed from each such municipality;</para><para>(c) If the governing body of the largest municipality creating the land bank has any of its members elected by district or ward, then at least one voting member of the board shall be appointed from each such district or ward. Such voting members shall represent, to the greatest extent possible, the racial and ethnic diversity of the largest municipality creating the land bank;</para><para>(d) The voting members of the board shall have, collectively, verifiable skills, expertise, and knowledge in market-rate and affordable residential, commercial, industrial, and mixed-use real estate development, financing, law, purchasing and sales, asset management, economic and community development, and the acquisition of tax sale certificates;</para><para>(e) The voting members of the board shall include:</para><para>(i) At least one member representing a chamber of commerce;</para><para>(ii) At least one member with experience in banking;</para><para>(iii) At least one member with experience in real estate development;</para><para>(iv) At least one member with experience as a realtor;</para><para>(v) At least one member with experience in nonprofit or affordable housing; and</para><para>(vi) At least one member with experience in large-scale residential or commercial property rental; and</para><para>(f) A single voting member may satisfy more than one of the requirements provided in subdivision (2)(e) of this section if he or she has the required qualifications. It is not necessary that there be a different member to fulfill each such requirement.</para><para>(3) The members of the board shall select annually from among themselves a chairperson, a vice-chairperson, a treasurer, and such other officers as the board may determine.</para><para>(4) A public official or public employee shall be eligible to be a member of the board.</para><para>(5) A vacancy on the board among the appointed board members shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment.</para><para>(6) Board members shall serve without compensation.</para><para>(7) The board shall meet in regular session according to a schedule adopted by the board and shall also meet in special session as convened by the chairperson or upon written notice signed by a majority of the voting members. The presence of a majority of the voting members of the board shall constitute a quorum.</para><para>(8) Except as otherwise provided in subsections (9) and (11) of this section and in sections 19-5210 and 19-5214, all actions of the board shall be approved by the affirmative vote of a majority of the voting members present and voting.</para><para>(9) Any action of the board on the following matters shall be approved by a majority of the voting members:</para><para>(a) Adoption of bylaws and other rules and regulations for conduct of the land bank's business;</para><para>(b) Hiring or firing of any employee or contractor of the land bank. This function may, by majority vote of the voting members, be delegated by the board to a specified officer or committee of the land bank, under such terms and conditions, and to the extent, that the board may specify;</para><para>(c) The incurring of debt;</para><para>(d) Adoption or amendment of the annual budget; and</para><para>(e) Sale, lease, encumbrance, or alienation of real property, improvements, or personal property with a value of more than fifty thousand dollars.</para><para>(10) Members of a board shall not be liable personally on the bonds or other obligations of the land bank, and the rights of creditors shall be solely against such land bank.</para><para>(11) The board shall adopt policies and procedures to specify the conditions that must be met in order for the land bank to give an automatically accepted bid as authorized in sections 19-5217 and 19-5218. The adoption of such policies and procedures shall require the approval of two-thirds of the voting members of the board. At a minimum, such policies and procedures shall ensure that the automatically accepted bid shall only be given for one of the following reasons:</para><para>(a) The real property substantially meets more than one of the following criteria as determined by two-thirds of the voting members of the board:</para><para>(i) The property is not occupied by the owner or any lessee or licensee of the owner;</para><para>(ii) There are no utilities currently being provided to the property;</para><para>(iii) Any buildings on the property have been deemed unfit for human habitation, occupancy, or use by local housing officials;</para><para>(iv) Any buildings on the property are exposed to the elements such that deterioration of the building is occurring;</para><para>(v) Any buildings on the property are boarded up;</para><para>(vi) There have been previous efforts to rehabilitate any buildings on the property;</para><para>(vii) There is a presence of vermin, uncut vegetation, or debris accumulation on the property;</para><para>(viii) There have been past actions by the municipality to maintain the grounds or any building on the property; or</para><para>(ix) The property has been out of compliance with orders of local housing officials;</para><para>(b) The real property is contiguous to a parcel that meets more than one of the criteria in subdivision (11)(a) of this section or that is already owned by the land bank; or</para><para>(c) Acquisition of the real property by the land bank would serve the best interests of the community as determined by two-thirds of the voting members of the board. In determining whether the acquisition would serve the best interests of the community, the board shall take into consideration the hierarchical ranking of priorities for the use of real property conveyed by a land bank established pursuant to subsection (5) of section 19-5210, if any such hierarchical ranking is established.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB699, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>