<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id349"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to More Than One and Less Than All Classes" statutenumber="19-5704"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>19-5704</statuteno><catchline>Grant; application; contents; eligibility; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning July 1, 2024, an eligible grantee may apply to the Department of Economic Development for a grant under the Municipality Infrastructure Aid Act on forms created by the department.</para><para>(2) To be eligible for a grant under the Municipality Infrastructure Aid Act, an eligible grantee shall include the following in its application:</para><para>(a) The infrastructure improvements that are a part of a redevelopment plan approved under the Community Development Law;</para><para>(b) How the infrastructure improvements would attract and support any new business or business expansion;</para><para>(c) How the infrastructure improvements would provide infrastructure that is sufficient for the new business or business expansion;</para><para>(d) The cost-benefit analysis of the redevelopment plan approved under the Community Development Law; and</para><para>(e) How the new business or business expansion would provide the following:</para><para>(i) The creation of additional jobs in or near the eligible grantee;</para><para>(ii) The creation of high-quality jobs in or near the eligible grantee;</para><para>(iii) Increased business investment in or near the eligible grantee; and</para><para>(iv) Revitalization of rural and other distressed areas of the state.</para><para>(3) A grant shall not be awarded to an eligible grantee if:</para><para>(a) The eligible grantee does not provide a positive cost-benefit analysis of the redevelopment plan approved under the Community Development Law; or</para><para>(b) The eligible grantee does not provide matching funds in the amount of at least twenty-five percent of the amount of the grant.</para><para>(4) An eligible grantee shall not be awarded a grant of more than five million dollars for any single application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB600, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>April 17, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>