<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id142">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To More Than One And Less Than All Classes" id="id144" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="19-5211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>19-5211</statuteno><catchline>Land bank; funding; real property
taxes collected on conveyed property; allocation; notice to county treasurer;
when required.</catchline><para>(1)
A land bank may receive funding through grants and loans from the municipality
or municipalities that created the land bank, from other municipalities, from
the state, from the federal government, and from other public and private
sources.</para>
<para>(2) A land
bank may receive and retain payments for services rendered, for rents and
leasehold payments received, for consideration for disposition of real and
personal property, for proceeds of insurance coverage for losses incurred,
for income from investments, and for any other asset and activity lawfully
permitted to a land bank under the Nebraska Municipal Land Bank Act.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except
as otherwise provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, fifty percent
of the real property taxes collected on real property conveyed by a land bank
pursuant to the laws of this state shall be remitted to the land bank. Such
allocation of property tax revenue shall commence with the first taxable year
following the date of conveyance and shall continue for a period of five years.
Such allocation of property tax revenue shall not occur if such taxes have
been divided under section 18-2147 as part of a redevelopment project under
the Community Development Law, unless the authority, as defined in section
18-2103, enters into an agreement with the land bank for the remittance of
such funds to the land bank.</para><para>(b) A land bank may, by resolution of the board, elect not to receive
the real property taxes described in subdivision (a) of this subsection for
any real property conveyed by the land bank. If such an election is made,
the land bank shall notify the county treasurer of the county in which the
real property is located by filing a copy of the resolution with the county
treasurer, and thereafter the county treasurer shall remit such real property
taxes to the appropriate taxing entities.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 11.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community Development Law,</emphasis> see section 18-2101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>