<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-311.09"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-311.09</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Harassment protection
order; violation; penalty; procedure;
costs; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) Any victim who has been
harassed as defined by section 28-311.02 may file a petition and affidavit
for a harassment protection order as provided in subsection (3) of this section.
Upon the filing of such a petition and affidavit in support thereof, the court may issue a
harassment protection order without bond enjoining the respondent from (a)
imposing any restraint upon the person or liberty of the petitioner, (b) harassing,
threatening, assaulting, molesting, attacking, or otherwise disturbing the
peace of the petitioner, or (c) telephoning, contacting, or otherwise communicating
with the petitioner.</para>
<para>(2) The petition for a harassment protection order shall state
the events and dates of acts constituting the alleged harassment.</para>
<para>(3) A petition for a harassment protection order shall be
filed with the clerk of the district court, and the proceeding may be heard
by the county court or the district court as provided in section 25-2740.</para>
<para>(4) A petition for a harassment protection order filed pursuant
to subsection (1) of this section may not be withdrawn except upon order of
the court. An order issued pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall
specify that it is effective for a period of one year unless otherwise dismissed or modified by the
court. Any person who knowingly violates an order issued pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section after service or
notice as described in subdivision (8)(b) of this section shall
be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(5)(a) Fees to cover costs associated with the filing of a
petition for a harassment protection order or the issuance or service of a
harassment protection order seeking only the relief provided by this section
shall not be charged, except that a court may assess such fees and costs if
the court finds, by clear and convincing evidence, that the statements contained
in the petition were false and that the harassment protection order was sought
in bad faith.</para>
<para>(b) A court may also assess costs associated with the filing
of a petition for a harassment protection order or the issuance or service
of a harassment protection order seeking only the relief provided by this section against
the respondent.</para>
<para>(6) The clerk of the district court shall make available standard
application and affidavit forms for a harassment protection order with instructions
for completion to be used by a petitioner. The clerk and his or her employees
shall not provide assistance in completing the forms. The State Court Administrator
shall adopt and promulgate the standard application and affidavit forms provided
for in this section as well as the standard temporary and final harassment
protection order forms and provide a copy of such forms to all clerks of the
district courts in this state. These standard temporary and final harassment
protection order forms shall be the only such forms used in this state.</para>
<para>(7) Any order issued under subsection (1) of this section
may be issued ex parte without notice to the respondent if it reasonably appears
from the specific facts shown by affidavit of the petitioner that irreparable
harm, loss, or damage will result before the matter can be heard on notice.
If the specific facts included in the affidavit (a) do not show that the petitioner
will suffer irreparable harm, loss, or damage or (b) show that, for any other
compelling reason, an ex parte order should not be issued, the court may forthwith cause
notice of the application to be given to the respondent stating
that he or she may show cause, not more than fourteen days after service, why such order should not be
entered. If such ex parte order is issued without notice to the respondent,
the court shall forthwith cause notice of the petition and order and a form with which to request a show-cause
hearing to be given the respondent stating that, upon service
on the respondent, the order shall remain in effect for a period of one year
unless the respondent shows cause why the order should not remain in effect
for a period of one year. If the respondent wishes to appear
and show cause why the order should not remain in effect for a period of one
year, he or she shall affix his or her current address, telephone number,
and signature to the form and return it to the clerk of the district court
within five days after service upon him or her. Upon receipt of the request
for a show-cause hearing, the court shall immediately schedule a show-cause
hearing to be held within thirty days after the receipt of the request for
a show-cause hearing and shall notify the petitioner and respondent of the
hearing date.</para>
<para>(8)(a) Upon the issuance of
any harassment protection order, the clerk
of the court shall forthwith provide the petitioner, without charge, with
two certified copies of such order. The clerk of the court shall also forthwith
provide the local police department or local law enforcement agency and the
local sheriff's office, without charge, with one copy each of such order and
one copy each of the sheriff's return thereon. The clerk of the court shall
also forthwith provide a copy of the harassment protection order to the sheriff's
office in the county where the respondent may be personally served together
with instructions for service. Upon receipt of the order and instructions
for service, such sheriff's office shall forthwith serve the harassment protection
order upon the respondent and file its return thereon with the clerk of the
court which issued the harassment protection order within fourteen days of
the issuance of the harassment protection order. If any harassment protection
order is dismissed or modified by the court, the clerk of the court shall
forthwith provide the local police department or local law enforcement agency
and the local sheriff's office, without charge, with one copy each of the
order of dismissal or modification.</para>
<para>(b) If the
respondent is present at a hearing convened pursuant to this section and the
harassment protection order is not dismissed, such respondent shall be deemed
to have notice by the court at such hearing that the protection order will
be granted and remain in effect and further service of such notice described
in this subsection shall not be required for purposes of prosecution under
this section. If the respondent has been properly served with the ex parte
order and fails to appear at the hearing, the temporary order shall be deemed
to be granted and remain in effect and the service of the ex parte order will
serve as notice required under this section.</para><para>(9)
A peace officer may, with
or without a warrant, arrest
a person if (a) the officer has probable cause to believe that the person
has committed a violation of a harassment protection order
issued pursuant to this section or a violation of a valid foreign harassment
protection order recognized pursuant to section 28-311.10 and (b) a petitioner
under this section provides the peace officer with a copy of a harassment
protection order or the peace officer determines that such an order exists
after communicating with the local law enforcement agency or a person protected
under a valid foreign harassment protection order recognized pursuant to section
28-311.10 provides the peace officer with a copy of such order.</para>
<para>(10) A peace officer making an arrest pursuant to subsection
(9) of this section shall take such person into custody and take such person
before the
county court or the court which issued the harassment protection order within
a reasonable time. At such time the court shall establish the conditions of
such person's release from custody, including the determination of bond or
recognizance, as the case may be. The court shall issue an order directing
that such person shall have no contact with the alleged victim of the harassment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 218, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB310, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation>
<para>Pursuant to subsection (8) of this section, personal service is an element of the misdemeanor crime of violating a harassment protection order. State v. Graff, 282 Neb. 746, 810 N.W.2d 140 (2011).</para>
<para>A proper form under this section is not a prerequisite for subject matter jurisdiction, and this section does not change the rules of notice pleading generally applicable to civil actions. Mahmood v. Mahmud, 279 Neb. 390, 778 N.W.2d 426 (2010).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>