<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-115"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">28-115</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Criminal offense
against a pregnant woman; enhanced penalty.</catchline><para>(1)
Any person who commits any of the following criminal offenses against a pregnant
woman shall be punished by the imposition of the next higher penalty classification
than the penalty classification prescribed for the criminal offense, unless
such criminal offense is already punishable as a Class IB felony or higher
classification: Assault in the first degree, section 28-308; assault in the
second degree, section 28-309; assault in the third degree, section 28-310;
sexual assault in the first degree, section 28-319; sexual assault in the
second or third degree, section 28-320; sexual assault of a child in the second
or third degree, section 28-320.01; sexual abuse of an inmate or parolee in
the first degree, section 28-322.01; sexual abuse of an inmate or parolee
in the second degree, section 28-322.03; sexual abuse of a protected individual
in the first or second degree, section 28-322.04; domestic assault in the
first, second, or third degree, section 28-323; assault on an officer in the
first degree, section 28-929; assault on an officer in the second degree,
section 28-930; assault on an officer in the third degree, section 28-931;
assault on an officer using a motor vehicle, section 28-931.01; assault by
a confined person, section 28-932;
confined person committing offenses against another person, section 28-933;
proximately causing serious bodily injury while operating a motor vehicle,
section 60-6,198; and sexual assault of a child in the first degree, section
28-319.01.</para>
<para>(2) The prosecution shall allege and prove beyond a reasonable
doubt that the victim was pregnant at the time of the offense.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 57, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB771, &#167;  1.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>