<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-408"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-408</statuteno><catchline>Registration to manufacture or distribute controlled substances; factors considered.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall register an applicant to manufacture or distribute controlled substances included in Schedules I to V of section 28-405 unless the department determines that the issuance of such registration is inconsistent with the public interest. In determining the public interest the department shall consider the following factors:</para><para>(a) Maintenance of effective controls against diversion of particular controlled substances and any Schedule I or II substance compounded therefrom into other than legitimate medical, scientific, or industrial channels;</para><para>(b) Compliance with applicable state and local law;</para><para>(c) Whether the applicant has been convicted of a felony under any law of the United States or of any state or has been convicted of a violation relating to any substance defined in the Uniform Controlled Substances Act as a controlled substance under any law of the United States or any state, except that such fact in itself shall not be an automatic bar to registration;</para><para>(d) Past experience in the manufacture or distribution of controlled substances, and the existence in the applicant's establishment of effective controls against diversion; and</para><para>(e) Such other factors as may be relevant to and consistent with the public health and safety.</para><para>(2) Registration granted under subsection (1) of this section shall not entitle a registrant to manufacture or distribute controlled substances in Schedule I or II of section 28-405 other than those specified in the registration.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in this section and section 28-409, practitioners shall be registered to prescribe, administer, or dispense substances in Schedules II to V of section 28-405 if they are authorized to prescribe, administer, or dispense under the laws of this state. A registration application by a practitioner who wishes to conduct research with Schedule I substances shall be referred to the department for approval or disapproval. Registration to prescribe, administer, or dispense substances in Schedules II to V of section 28-405 or registration for the purpose of bona fide research with Schedule I substances by a practitioner may be denied only on a ground specified in subsection (1) of section 28-409 or if there are reasonable grounds to believe that the applicant will abuse or unlawfully transfer such substances or fail to safeguard adequately his or her supply of such substances against diversion from legitimate medical or scientific use.</para><para>(4) Compliance by manufacturers and distributors with the Controlled Substances Act, 21 U.S.C. 801 et seq., as such act existed on May 1, 2001, respecting registration, excluding fees, shall be deemed compliance with this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 323, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>