<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-907"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-907</statuteno><catchline>False reporting; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the offense of false reporting if he or she:</para><para>(a) Furnishes material information he or she knows to be false to any peace officer or other official with the intent to instigate an investigation of an alleged criminal matter or to impede the investigation of an actual criminal matter;</para><para>(b) Furnishes information he or she knows to be false alleging the existence of the need for the assistance of an emergency medical service or out-of-hospital emergency care provider or an emergency in which human life or property are in jeopardy to any hospital, emergency medical service, or other person or governmental agency;</para><para>(c) Furnishes any information, or causes such information to be furnished or conveyed by electric, electronic, telephonic, or mechanical means, knowing the same to be false concerning the need for assistance of a fire department or any personnel or equipment of such department;</para><para>(d) Furnishes any information he or she knows to be false concerning the location of any explosive in any building or other property to any person; or</para><para>(e) Furnishes material information he or she knows to be false to any governmental department or agency with the intent to instigate an investigation or to impede an ongoing investigation and which actually results in causing or impeding such investigation.</para><para>(2)(a) False reporting pursuant to subdivisions (1)(a) through (d) of this section is a Class I misdemeanor; and</para><para>(b) False reporting pursuant to subdivision (1)(e) of this section is an infraction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 192; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 347, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 907, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 36.</para></source><annotation>
<para><emphasis>1. Elements</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Elements</emphasis></para>
<para>Subsection (1)(a) of this section includes other officials besides police officers who have the authority to investigate actual criminal matters. Nebraska Legislature on behalf of State v. Hergert, 271 Neb. 976, 720 N.W.2d 372 (2006).</para><para>Subsection (1)(a) of this section prohibits a person from furnishing material information he or she knows to be false to any peace officer or other official with the intent to impede the investigation of an actual criminal matter. Nebraska Legislature on behalf of State v. Hergert, 271 Neb. 976, 720 N.W.2d 372 (2006).</para><para>To commit the crime of false reporting one need not actually impede a police investigation, but must furnish false information with the intent to impede the investigation of a criminal matter. State v. Gonzales, 224 Neb. 659, 399 N.W.2d 832 (1987).</para><para>"To impede the investigation of an actual criminal matter" includes the impeding of the gathering of information as to the identity of a defendant named in an arrest warrant. State v. Nissen, 224 Neb. 60, 395 N.W.2d 560 (1986).</para><para>The phrase "the investigation of an actual criminal matter" requires that there be a legitimate and valid investigation of facts which could constitute a predicate criminal offense. State v. Ewing, 221 Neb. 462, 378 N.W.2d 158 (1985).</para><para>The defendant's allegedly false statements to the 911 emergency dispatch service concerning crimes being committed at a certain address were made to a peace officer for purposes of the criminal statute prohibiting false reporting of a criminal matter; although the 911 emergency dispatch service was not a branch of law enforcement, it acted as an intermediary used by the general public to reach peace officers, and statements made to the emergency dispatch service were made with the intent to summon a law enforcement officer to that address. State v. Halligan, 20 Neb. App. 87, 818 N.W.2d 650 (2012).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The purpose of subsection (1)(a) of this section is to prevent the public from willfully furnishing erroneous information to law enforcement officers and thus interfering with the performance of their duties. Interference with an officer's duties includes false statements that impede an officer's gathering of information. Nebraska Legislature on behalf of State v. Hergert, 271 Neb. 976, 720 N.W.2d 372 (2006).</para><para>Evidence was sufficient for juvenile court to find beyond a reasonable doubt that defendant had violated provisions of this section. In re Interest of McManaman, 222 Neb. 263, 383 N.W.2d 45 (1986).</para><para>Purpose of statute is to prevent wasted time and efforts of law enforcement personnel by discouraging public from willfully furnishing erroneous information to law enforcement officers which may interfere with performance of their duties. In re Interest of McManaman, 222 Neb. 263, 383 N.W.2d 45 (1986).</para><para>A local ordinance which did not explicitly require that the false statement be material or be given with the intent to instigate or impede a criminal investigation is not inconsistent with this section where the ordinance does not restrict anything expressly permitted by this section and the provisions are able to coexist. In re Interest of Genevieve C., 13 Neb. App. 665, 698 N.W.2d 462 (2005).</para><para>A person must have reliable knowledge of the principal's identity to be guilty as an accessory under section 28-204. Merely reporting false information about a crime without knowledge of the principal's identity constitutes the misdemeanor of false reporting, as defined by this section. State v. Anderson, 10 Neb. App. 163, 626 N.W.2d 627 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>