<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id25">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id27" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-801"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>28-801</statuteno><catchline id="id30">Prostitution;
penalty; affirmative defense;
immunity from prosecution; law enforcement officer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (5) of
this section, any person who performs, offers, or agrees to perform
any act of sexual contact or sexual penetration, as those terms are defined
in section 28-318, with any person not his or her spouse, in exchange for
money or other thing of value, commits prostitution.</para>
<para>(2) Any person convicted of violating subsection (1) of this
section shall be punished as follows:</para>
<para>(a) If such person has had no prior convictions or has had
one prior conviction, such person shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.
If the court places such person on probation, such order of probation shall
include, as one of its conditions, that such person shall satisfactorily attend
and complete an appropriate mental health and substance abuse assessment conducted
by a licensed mental health professional or substance abuse professional authorized
to complete such assessment; and</para>
<para>(b) If such person has had two or more prior convictions,
such person shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. If the court places
such person on probation, such order of probation shall include, as one of
its conditions, that such person shall satisfactorily attend and complete
an appropriate mental health and substance abuse assessment conducted by a
licensed mental health professional or substance abuse professional authorized
to complete such assessment.</para>
<para>(3) It is an
affirmative defense to prosecution under this section that such person was
a trafficking victim as defined in section 28-830.</para><para>(4) For
purposes of this section, prior conviction
means any conviction on or after July 14, 2006, for violation of subsection
(1) of this section or any conviction on or after July 14, 2006, for violation
of a city or village ordinance relating to prostitution.</para>
<para>(5) If the
law enforcement officer determines, after a reasonable detention for investigative
purposes, that a person suspected of or charged with a violation of subsection
(1) of this section is a person under eighteen years of age, such person shall
be immune from prosecution for a prostitution offense under this section and
shall be subject to temporary custody under section 43-248 and further disposition
under the Nebraska Juvenile Code. A law enforcement officer who takes a person
under eighteen years of age into custody under this section shall immediately
report an allegation of a violation of section 28-831 to the Department of
Health and Human Services which shall commence an investigation within twenty-four
hours under the Child Protection Act.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 157; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 19, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 176, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 116, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1086, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB255, &#167; 2.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2013</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 28-710.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> see section 43-2,129.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>