<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id889"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-316.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-316.01</statuteno><catchline>Sexual abuse by a school employee; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Sexual contact has the same meaning as in section 28-318;</para><para>(b) Sexual penetration has the same meaning as in section 28-318;</para><para>(c) School employee means a person nineteen years of age or older who is employed by a public, private, denominational, or parochial school approved or accredited by the State Department of Education; and</para><para>(d) Student means a person at least sixteen but not more than nineteen years of age enrolled in or attending a public, private, denominational, or parochial school approved or accredited by the State Department of Education, or who was such a person enrolled in or who attended such a school within ninety days of any violation of this section.</para><para>(2) A person commits the offense of sexual abuse by a school employee if a school employee subjects a student in the school to which such employee is assigned for work to sexual penetration or sexual contact, or engages in a pattern or scheme of conduct to subject a student in the school to which such employee is assigned for work to sexual penetration or sexual contact. It is not a defense to a charge under this section that the student consented to such sexual penetration or sexual contact.</para><para>(3) Any school employee who engages in sexual penetration with a student is guilty of sexual abuse by a school employee in the first degree. Sexual abuse by a school employee in the first degree is a Class IIA felony.</para><para>(4) Any school employee who engages in sexual contact with a student is guilty of sexual abuse by a school employee in the second degree. Sexual abuse by a school employee in the second degree is a Class IIIA felony.</para><para>(5) Any school employee who engages in a pattern or scheme of conduct with the intent to subject a student to sexual penetration or sexual contact is guilty of sexual abuse by a school employee in the third degree. Sexual abuse by a school employee in the third degree is a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB881, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>