<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-915.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-915.01</statuteno><catchline>False statement under oath or affirmation; penalty; applicability of section.</catchline><para>(1) A person who makes a false statement under oath or equivalent affirmation, or swears or affirms the truth of such a statement previously made, when he or she does not believe the statement to be true, is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor if the falsification:</para><para>(a) Occurs in an official proceeding; or</para><para>(b) Is intended to mislead a public servant in performing his or her official function.</para><para>(2) A person who makes a false statement under oath or equivalent affirmation, or swears or affirms the truth of such a statement previously made, when he or she does not believe the statement to be true, is guilty of a Class II misdemeanor if the statement is one which is required by law to be sworn or affirmed before a notary or other person authorized to administer oaths.</para><para>(3) Subsections (4) through (7) of section 28-915 shall apply to subsections (1) and (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) This section shall not apply to reports, statements, affidavits, or other documents made or filed pursuant to the Campaign Finance Limitation Act or the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 451, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB464, &#167; 1.</para></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act,</emphasis> see section 49-1401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A person can be convicted of making a false statement under oath when making a statement based on a belief that he or she knows is false. Perjury can be proved either by two witnesses or by one witness, together with material and independently established corroborative facts sufficient to amount to the testimony of another witness. State v. McCaslin, 240 Neb. 482, 482 N.W.2d 558 (1992).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>