<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id123" statutenumber="28-721"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>28-721</statuteno><catchline id="id126">Central registry; record; amend, expunge, or remove; mandatory expungement hearing; waiver; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) At any time, the department may amend, expunge, or remove from the central registry of child protection cases maintained pursuant to section 28-718 any record upon good cause shown and upon notice to the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect.</para><para>(2)(a) If the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect is a minor child who is twelve years of age or older but younger than nineteen years of age, the subject is entered into the central registry of child protection cases maintained under section 28-718, and the case involving that minor child is classified as court substantiated or agency substantiated as provided in section 28-720, the department shall conduct a mandatory expungement hearing within sixty days after the subject receives the notification required under section 28-713.01 unless the subject and the subject's attorney of record, parent, guardian, or guardian ad litem sign and return a waiver form as provided under section 28-713.01 within thirty days after receipt. The department shall not, as guardian, sign a waiver form for any subject in its custody. If such subject remains on the central registry of child protection cases, the department shall conduct a second mandatory expungement hearing within sixty days after the subject's nineteenth birthday unless the subject signs and returns a waiver form as provided under section 28-713.01 within thirty days after receipt.</para><para>(b) The department may conduct the mandatory expungement hearing by any means, including by telephone.</para><para>(c) If a mandatory expungement hearing is held regarding the subject of a report of child abuse or neglect who is a minor child and the subject is entered into the central registry of child protection cases maintained under section 28-718, the subject may make a subsequent request under subsection (1) of this section or section 28-723.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB292, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>