<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id72" statutenumber="28-386"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-386</statuteno><catchline id="id75">Knowing and intentional abuse, neglect, or exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits knowing and intentional abuse, neglect, or exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult if he or she through a knowing and intentional act causes or permits a vulnerable adult or senior adult to be:</para><para>(a) Physically injured;</para><para>(b) Unreasonably confined;</para><para>(c) Sexually abused;</para><para>(d) Exploited;</para><para>(e) Cruelly punished;</para><para>(f) Neglected; or</para><para>(g) Sexually exploited.</para><para>(2) Knowing and intentional abuse, neglect, or exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult is a Class IIIA felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 463, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 364, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1051, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB934, &#167; 9. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Registration of sex offenders,</emphasis> see sections 29-4001 to 29-4014.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The initial step when determining whether this section has been violated is to determine whether the victim was a vulnerable adult. State v. Stubbs, 252 Neb. 420, 562 N.W.2d 547 (1997).</para><para>The initial step when determining if this section has been violated is to determine whether the victim was a vulnerable adult. The State has the burden of proving all essential elements of the crime charged. State v. Janssen, 7 Neb. App. 384, 584 N.W.2d 27 (1998).</para><para>In order to convict someone of the crime of exploitation of a vulnerable adult, there must be a nexus between a vulnerable adult's impairment and the exploitation. State v. Stubbs, 5 Neb. App. 38, 555 N.W.2d 55 (1996).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>