<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<sectno id="id20">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id21" statutenumber="28-326"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id23">28-326</statuteno><catchline id="id24">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 28-325 to 28-345, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Abortion means the use or prescription of any instrument,
medicine, drug, or other substance or device intentionally to terminate the
pregnancy of a woman known to be pregnant with an intention other than to
increase the probability of a live birth, to preserve the life or health of
the child after live birth, or to remove a dead unborn child, and which causes
the premature termination of the pregnancy;</para>
<para>(2) Complications
associated with abortion means any adverse physical, psychological, or emotional
reaction that is reported in a peer-reviewed journal to be statistically associated
with abortion such that there is less than a five percent probability (P &lt;
.05) that the result is due to chance;</para><para>(3) Conception means the fecundation of
the ovum by the spermatozoa;</para><para>(4) Emergency situation means that condition
which, on the basis of the physician's good faith clinical judgment, so complicates
the medical condition of a pregnant woman as to necessitate the immediate
abortion of her pregnancy to avert her death or for which a delay will create
serious risk of substantial impairment of a major bodily function;</para>
<para>(5) Hospital means those institutions
licensed by the Department of Health and Human Services pursuant to the Health
Care Facility Licensure Act;</para>
<para>(6) Negligible
risk means a risk that a reasonable person would consider to be immaterial
to a decision to undergo an elective medical procedure;</para>
<para>(7) Partial-birth
abortion means an abortion procedure in which the person performing the abortion
partially delivers vaginally a living unborn child before killing the unborn
child and completing the delivery. For purposes of this subdivision, the term
partially delivers vaginally a living unborn child before killing the unborn
child means deliberately and intentionally delivering into the vagina a living
unborn child, or a substantial portion thereof, for the purpose of performing
a procedure that the person performing such procedure knows will kill the
unborn child and does kill the unborn child;</para><para>(8) Physician means any person licensed to practice
medicine in this state as provided in  the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para>
<para>(9) Pregnant means that condition
of a woman who has unborn human life within her as the result of conception;</para>
<para>(10) Probable gestational
age of the unborn child means what will with reasonable probability, in the
judgment of the physician, be the gestational age of the unborn child at the
time the abortion is planned to be performed;</para><para>(11) Risk factor associated
with abortion means any factor, including any physical, psychological, emotional,
demographic, or situational factor, for which there is a statistical association
with one or more complications associated with abortion such that there is
less than a five percent probability (P &lt; .05) that such statistical association
is due to chance. Such information on risk factors shall have been published
in any peer-reviewed journals indexed by the United States National Library
of Medicine's search services (PubMed or MEDLINE) or in any journal included
in the Thomson Reuters Scientific Master Journal List not less than twelve
months prior to the day preabortion screening was provided;</para>
<para>(12) Self-induced
abortion means any abortion or menstrual extraction attempted or completed
by a pregnant woman on her own body;</para><para>(13) Ultrasound means the use of ultrasonic
waves for diagnostic or therapeutic purposes, specifically to monitor an unborn
child;</para><para>(14) Viability means that
stage of human development when the unborn child is potentially able to live
more than merely momentarily outside the womb of the mother by natural or
artificial means; and</para>
<para>(15) Woman
means any female human being whether or not she has reached the age of majority.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 316, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 695, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 663, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 110, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 23, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB675, &#167;  1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB594, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Sections 28-326(8), 28-327, 28-333, and 28-343 (1979) regulating abortion were unconstitutional. Womens Services, P.C. v. Thone, 690 F.2d 667 (8th Cir. 1982).</para><para>The portions of this statute which require that a woman seeking an abortion indicate in writing that she has been advised of possible alternatives to abortion and of the abortion procedures to be used, does not unduly burden either the woman's decisionmaking process or her obtaining an abortion and, in view of the state's interest in having the information conveyed, the sections are constitutional. Womens Services, P.C. v. Thone, 483 F.Supp. 1022 (D. Neb. 1979).</para><para>This section, as far as it requires a woman seeking an abortion to indicate that she has been advised of the reasonably possible medical and mental consequences resulting from an abortion, pregnancy, and childbirth, gives a person of ordinary intelligence fair notice as to the subject matter of the statute and is not void for vagueness. Womens Services, P.C. v. Thone, 483 F.Supp. 1022 (D. Neb. 1979).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>