<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-417"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-417</statuteno><catchline>Unlawful acts; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person:</para><para>(a) To omit, remove, alter, or obliterate a symbol required by the federal Controlled Substances Act, 21 U.S.C. 801 et seq., as the act existed on September 1, 2001, or required by the laws of this state;</para><para>(b) To alter, deface, or remove any label affixed to a package of narcotic drugs;</para><para>(c) To refuse or fail to make, keep, or furnish any record, notification, order form, statement, invoice, or information required under the Uniform Controlled Substances Act;</para><para>(d) To refuse any entry into any premises for inspection authorized by the act;</para><para>(e) To keep or maintain any store, shop, warehouse, dwelling house, building, vehicle, boat, aircraft, or place whatever which such person knows or should know is resorted to by persons using controlled substances in violation of the Uniform Controlled Substances Act for the purpose of using such substances or which is used for the keeping or selling of the same in violation of the act;</para><para>(f) To whom or for whose use any controlled substance has been prescribed, sold, or dispensed by a practitioner or the owner of any animal for which any such substance has been prescribed, sold, or dispensed by a veterinarian to possess it in a container other than which it was delivered to him or her by the practitioner; or</para><para>(g) To be under the influence of any controlled substance for a purpose other than the treatment of a sickness or injury as prescribed or administered by a practitioner. In a prosecution under this subdivision, it shall not be necessary for the state to prove that the accused was under the influence of any specific controlled substance, but it shall be sufficient for a conviction under this subdivision for the state to prove that the accused was under the influence of some controlled substance by proving that the accused did manifest physical and physiological symptoms or reactions caused by the use of any controlled substance.</para><para>(2) Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 920, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 273, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 113, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 15. </para></source></law></legaldoc>