<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id53">
<sectno id="id54" opdate=" ">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id55" statutenumber="28-407"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id57">28-407</statuteno><catchline id="id58">Registration required;
exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in
this section, every person who manufactures, prescribes, distributes, administers,
or dispenses any controlled substance within this state or who proposes to
engage in the manufacture, prescribing, administering, distribution, or dispensing
of any controlled substance within this state shall obtain a registration
issued by the department, except that on and after January 1, 2000, health
care providers credentialed by the department and facilities licensed by the
department shall not be required to obtain a separate Nebraska controlled
substances registration upon providing proof of a Federal Controlled Substances
Registration to the department. Federal Controlled Substances Registration
numbers obtained under this section shall not be public information but may
be shared by the department for investigative and regulatory purposes if necessary
and only under appropriate circumstances to ensure against any unauthorized
access to such information.</para>
<para>(2) The following persons shall not be required to register
and may lawfully possess controlled substances under the provisions of the
Uniform Controlled Substances Act:</para>
<para>(a) An agent, or an employee thereof, of any practitioner,
registered manufacturer, distributor, or dispenser of any controlled substance
if such agent is acting in the usual course of his or her business or employment;</para>
<para>(b) A common or contract carrier or warehouse keeper, or an
employee thereof, whose possession of any controlled substance is in the usual
course of his or her business or employment; and</para>
<para>(c) An ultimate user or a person in possession of any controlled
substance pursuant to a medical order issued by a practitioner authorized
to prescribe.</para>
<para>(3) A separate registration shall be required at each principal
place of business of professional practice where the applicant manufactures,
distributes, or dispenses controlled substances, except that no registration
shall be required in connection with the placement of an emergency box within a long-term care facility pursuant
to the provisions of the Emergency Box Drug Act.</para>
<para>(4) The department is authorized to inspect the establishment
of a registrant or applicant for registration in accordance with the rules
and regulations promulgated.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 550, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Emergency Box Drug Act,</emphasis> see section 71-2410.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>