<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-315"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-315</statuteno><catchline>False imprisonment in the second degree; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits false imprisonment in the second degree if he knowingly restrains another person without legal authority.</para><para>(2) In any prosecution under this section, it shall be an affirmative defense that the person restrained (a) was on or in the immediate vicinity of the premises of a retail mercantile establishment and he was restrained for the purpose of investigation or questioning as to the ownership of any merchandise; and (b) was restrained in a reasonable manner and for not more than a reasonable time; and (c) was restrained to permit such investigation or questioning by a police officer, or by the owner of the mercantile establishment, his authorized employee or agent; and (d) that such police officer, owner, employee or agent had reasonable grounds to believe that the person so detained was committing or attempting to commit theft of merchandise on the premises; Provided, nothing in this section shall prohibit or restrict any person restrained pursuant to this section from maintaining any applicable civil remedy if no theft has occurred.</para><para>(3) False imprisonment in the second degree is a Class I misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 30.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Registration of sex offenders,</emphasis> see sections 29-4001 to 29-4014.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Second degree false imprisonment is a lesser-included offense of first degree false imprisonment. State v. Brownell, 11 Neb. App. 68, 644 N.W.2d 166 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>