<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id68" statutenumber="28-414"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>28-414</statuteno><catchline id="id71">Controlled substance;
prescription; transfer; destruction; requirements.</catchline><para>(1)(a)
Except as otherwise provided in this subsection or section 28-412 or when
administered directly by a practitioner to an ultimate user, a controlled
substance listed in Schedule II of section 28-405 shall not be dispensed without
the written prescription bearing the signature of a practitioner authorized
to prescribe. No prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule
II of section 28-405 shall be filled more than six months from the date of
issuance. A prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule II
of section 28-405 shall not be refilled.</para>
<para>(b) In emergency situations as defined by rule and regulation of the
department, a controlled substance listed in Schedule II of section 28-405
may be dispensed pursuant to a facsimile of a written, signed prescription
bearing the word "emergency" or pursuant to an oral prescription reduced to
writing in accordance with subdivision (3)(b) of this section, except for
the prescribing practitioner's signature, and bearing the word "emergency".</para>
<para>(c) In nonemergency situations:</para>
<para>(i) A controlled substance listed in Schedule II of section 28-405 may
be dispensed pursuant to a facsimile of a written, signed prescription if
the original written, signed prescription is presented to the pharmacist for
review before the controlled substance is dispensed, except as provided in
subdivision (1)(c)(ii) or (1)(c)(iii) of this section;</para>
<para>(ii) A narcotic drug listed in Schedule II of section 28-405 may be
dispensed pursuant to a facsimile of a written, signed prescription (A) to
be compounded for direct parenteral administration to a patient for the purpose
of home infusion therapy or (B) for administration to a patient enrolled in
a hospice care program and bearing the words "hospice patient";</para>
<para>(iii) A controlled substance listed in Schedule II of section 28-405
may be dispensed pursuant to a facsimile of a written, signed prescription
for administration to a resident of a long-term care facility; and</para>
<para>(iv) For purposes of subdivisions (1)(c)(ii) and (1)(c)(iii) of this
section, a facsimile of a written, signed prescription shall serve as the
original written prescription and shall be maintained in accordance with subdivision
(3)(a) of this section.</para>
<para>(d)(i) A prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule
II of section 28-405 may be partially filled if the pharmacist does not supply
the full quantity prescribed and he or she makes a notation of the quantity
supplied on the face of the prescription. The remaining portion of the prescription
may be filled within seventy-two hours of the first partial filling. The pharmacist
shall notify the prescribing practitioner if the remaining portion of the
prescription is not or cannot be filled within such period. No further quantity
may be supplied after such period without a new written, signed prescription.</para>
<para>(ii) A prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule II
of section 28-405 written for a patient in a long-term care facility or for
a patient with a medical diagnosis documenting a terminal illness may be partially
filled. Such prescription shall bear the words "terminally ill" or "long-term
care facility patient" on its face. If there is any question whether a patient
may be classified as having a terminal illness, the pharmacist shall contact
the prescribing practitioner prior to partially filling the prescription.
Both the pharmacist and the prescribing practitioner have a corresponding
responsibility to assure that the controlled substance is for a terminally
ill patient. For each partial filling, the dispensing pharmacist shall record
on the back of the prescription or on another appropriate record, uniformly
maintained and readily retrievable, the date of the partial filling, quantity
dispensed, remaining quantity authorized to be dispensed, and the identification
of the dispensing pharmacist. The total quantity of controlled substances
listed in Schedule II which is dispensed in all partial fillings shall not
exceed the total quantity prescribed. A prescription for a Schedule II controlled
substance for a patient in a long-term care facility or a patient with a medical
diagnosis documenting a terminal illness is valid for sixty days from the
date of issuance or until discontinuance of the prescription, whichever occurs
first.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection or when administered
directly by a practitioner to an ultimate user, a controlled substance listed
in Schedule III, IV, or V of section 28-405 shall not be dispensed without
a written or oral medical order. Such medical order is valid for six months
after the date of issuance. Authorization from a practitioner authorized to
prescribe is required to refill a prescription for a controlled substance
listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section 28-405. Such prescriptions shall
not be refilled more than five times within six months after the date of issuance.
Original prescription information for any controlled substance listed in Schedule
III, IV, or V of section 28-405 may be transferred between pharmacies for
purposes of refill dispensing pursuant to section 38-2871.</para>
<para>(b) A controlled substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section
28-405 may be dispensed pursuant to a facsimile of a written, signed prescription.
The facsimile of a written, signed prescription shall serve as the original
written prescription for purposes of this subsection and shall be maintained
in accordance with the provisions of subdivision (3)(c) of this section.</para>
<para>(c) A prescription for a controlled substance listed in Schedule III,
IV, or V of section 28-405 may be partially filled if (i) each partial filling
is recorded in the same manner as a refilling, (ii) the total quantity dispensed
in all partial fillings does not exceed the total quantity prescribed, and
(iii) each partial filling is dispensed within six months after the prescription
was issued.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Prescriptions for all controlled substances listed in Schedule
II of section 28-405 shall be kept in a separate file by the dispensing practitioner
and shall be maintained for a minimum of five years. The practitioner shall
make all such files readily available to the department and law enforcement
for inspection without a search warrant.</para>
<para>(b) All prescriptions for controlled substances listed in Schedule II
of section 28-405 shall contain the name and address of the patient, the name
and address of the prescribing practitioner, the Drug Enforcement Administration
number of the prescribing practitioner, the date of issuance, and the prescribing
practitioner's signature. If the
prescription is for an animal, it shall also state the name and address of
the owner of the animal and the species of the animal.</para>
<para>(c) Prescriptions for all controlled substances listed in Schedule III,
IV, or V of section 28-405 shall be maintained either separately from other
prescriptions or in a form in which the information required is readily retrievable
from ordinary business records of the dispensing practitioner and shall be
maintained for a minimum of five years. The practitioner shall make all such
records readily available to the department and law enforcement for inspection
without a search warrant.</para>
<para>(d) All prescriptions for controlled substances listed in Schedule III,
IV, or V of section 28-405 shall contain the name and address of the patient,
the name and address of the prescribing practitioner, the Drug Enforcement
Administration number of the prescribing practitioner, the date of issuance,
and for written prescriptions, the prescribing practitioner's signature. If
the prescription is for an animal, it shall also state the owner's name and
address and species of the animal.</para>
<para>(e) A registrant who is the owner of a controlled substance may transfer:</para>
<para>(i) Any controlled substance listed in Schedule I or II of section 28-405
to another registrant as provided by law or by rule and regulation of the
department; and</para>
<para>(ii) Any controlled substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section
28-405 to another registrant if such owner complies with subsection (4) of
section 28-411.</para>
<para>(f)(i) The owner of any stock of controlled substances may cause such
controlled substances to be destroyed pursuant to this subdivision when the
need for such substances ceases. Complete records of controlled substances
destruction pursuant to this subdivision shall be maintained by the registrant
for five years from the date of destruction.</para>
<para>(ii) When the owner is a registrant:</para>
<para>(A) Controlled substances listed in Schedule II, III, IV, or V of section
28-405 may be destroyed by a pharmacy inspector, by a reverse distributor,
or by the federal Drug Enforcement Administration. Upon destruction, any forms
required by the administration to document such destruction shall be completed;</para>
<para>(B) Liquid controlled substances in opened containers which originally
contained fifty milliliters or less or compounded liquid controlled substances
within the facility where they were compounded may be destroyed if witnessed
by two individuals credentialed under the Uniform Credentialing Act and designated
by the facility and recorded in accordance with subsection (4) of section
28-411; or</para>
<para>(C) Solid controlled substances in opened unit-dose containers or which
have been adulterated within a hospital where they were to be administered
to patients at such hospital may be destroyed if witnessed by two individuals
credentialed under the Uniform Credentialing Act and designated by the hospital
and recorded in accordance with subsection (4) of section 28-411.</para>
<para>(iii) When the owner is a patient, such owner may transfer the controlled
substances to a pharmacy for immediate destruction by two individuals credentialed
under the Uniform Credentialing Act and designated by the pharmacy.</para>
<para>(iv) When the owner is a resident of a long-term care facility or hospital,
a controlled substance listed in Schedule II, III, IV, or V of section 28-405
shall be destroyed by two individuals credentialed under the Uniform Credentialing
Act and designated by the facility or hospital.</para>
<para>(g) Before dispensing any controlled substance listed in Schedule II,
III, IV, or V of section 28-405, the dispensing practitioner shall affix a
label to the container in which the controlled substance is dispensed. Such
label shall bear the name and address of the pharmacy or dispensing practitioner,
the name of the patient, the date of filling, the consecutive number of the
prescription under which it is recorded in the practitioner's prescription
records, the name of the prescribing practitioner, and the directions for
use of the controlled substance. Unless the prescribing practitioner writes
"do not label" or words of similar import on the original written prescription
or so designates in an oral prescription, such label shall also bear the name
of the controlled substance.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 273, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1122; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB179, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>