<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10"><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id12" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="28-105.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-105.02</statuteno><catchline>Class IA felony; person under eighteen
years; maximum sentence; court consider mitigating factors.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding
any other provision of law, the penalty for any person convicted of a Class
IA felony for an offense committed when such person was under the age of eighteen
years shall be a maximum sentence of not greater than life imprisonment and
a minimum sentence of not less than forty years' imprisonment.</para>
<para>(2) In determining the sentence
of a convicted person under subsection (1) of this section, the court shall
consider mitigating factors which led to the commission of the offense. The
convicted person may submit mitigating factors to the court, including, but
not limited to:</para><para>(a)
The convicted person's age at the time of the offense;</para>
<para>(b) The impetuosity of the
convicted person;</para><para>(c)
The convicted person's family and community environment;</para>
<para>(d) The convicted person's
ability to appreciate the risks and consequences of the conduct;</para>
<para>(e) The convicted person's
intellectual capacity; and</para><para>(f)
The outcome of a comprehensive mental health evaluation of the convicted person
conducted by an adolescent mental health professional licensed in this state.
The evaluation shall include, but not be limited to, interviews with the convicted
person's family in order to learn about the convicted person's prenatal history,
developmental history, medical history, substance abuse treatment history,
if any, social history, and psychological history.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB44, &#167; 2.</para></source>  <annotation><para>Subsection (1) of this section does not apply to persons who committed a Class IA felony offense when they were 18 years of age. State v. Wetherell, 289 Neb. 312, 855 N.W.2d 359 (2014).</para><para>Where a defendant had been sentenced to life imprisonment without the possibility of parole for a crime he committed while under the age of 18 years and that sentence was later determined to be unconstitutional, this section applied to his resentencing. State v. Taylor, 287 Neb. 386, 842 N.W.2d 771 (2014).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>