<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id360"><amendatorysection statutenumber="28-936" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>28-936</statuteno><catchline>Electronic communication device; possession within facility; provided to inmate; penalty; seizure; disposition.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits an offense if he or she intentionally introduces within a facility, or intentionally provides an inmate of a facility with, any electronic communication device. An inmate commits an offense if he or she intentionally procures, makes, or otherwise provides himself or herself with, or has in his or her possession, any electronic communication device.</para><para>(2) This section does not apply to:</para><para>(a) An attorney or an attorney's agent visiting an inmate who is a client of such attorney;</para><para>(b) The Public Counsel or any employee of his or her office;</para><para>(c) A peace officer acting under his or her authority;</para><para>(d) An emergency responder or a firefighter responding to emergency incidents within a facility; or</para><para>(e) Any person acting with the permission of the Director of Correctional Services or in accordance with rules, regulations, or policies of the Department of Correctional Services.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Facility has the same meaning as in section 83-170; and</para><para>(b) Electronic communication device means any device which, in its ordinary and intended use, transmits by electronic means writings, sounds, visual images, or data of any nature to another electronic communication device. Electronic communication device does not include any device provided to an inmate by the Department of Correctional Services.</para><para>(4) A violation of this section is a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(5) An electronic communication device involved in a violation of this section shall be subject to seizure by the Department of Correctional Services or a peace officer, and disposition may be made in accordance with the method of disposition directed for contraband in sections 29-818 and 29-820.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB686, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>