<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-445"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-445</statuteno><catchline>Imitation controlled substance; prohibited acts; determination; penalties; seizure.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who knowingly and intentionally manufactures, distributes, delivers, or possesses with intent to distribute or deliver an imitation controlled substance shall:</para><para>(a) For the first offense, be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor; and</para><para>(b) For the second and all subsequent offenses, be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) In determining whether a substance is an imitation controlled substance the court or other authority concerned shall consider all relevant factors, including but not limited to the following:</para><para>(a) Whether the substance is represented as having an effect similar to or the same as an illicit controlled substance;</para><para>(b) Whether the substance is represented by way of terminology which is deceptively similar to or the same as that describing a particular controlled substance;</para><para>(c) Whether the dosage unit price substantially exceeds the reasonable price of a similar dosage unit of like chemical composition sold over the counter with packaging and labeling approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</para><para>(d) Whether the substance is packaged in a manner and quantity similar to or the same as that commonly used for illicit controlled substances;</para><para>(e) Whether the dosage unit appearance of the substance is deceptively similar to that of a particular controlled substance; and</para><para>(f) Whether the substance is distributed to persons who represent it as a controlled substance, under circumstances which indicate the distributor knows, intends, or should know that his or her distributee is making or will make such representations.</para><para>(3) Any substance possessed, distributed, or delivered in violation of this section shall be subject to seizure and forfeiture as provided in section 28-431.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 406, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>