<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-613"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-613</statuteno><catchline>Commercial bribery and breach of duty to act disinterestedly; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits a Class I misdemeanor if he or she solicits, accepts, or agrees to accept any benefit as consideration for knowingly violating or agreeing to violate a duty of fidelity to which he or she is subject as:</para><para>(a) Agent or employee; or</para><para>(b) Trustee, guardian, or other fiduciary; or</para><para>(c) Lawyer, physician, accountant, appraiser, or other professional advisor; or</para><para>(d) Officer, director, partner, limited liability company member, manager, or other participant in the direction of the affairs of an incorporated or unincorporated association; or</para><para>(e) Duly elected or appointed representative or trustee of a labor organization or employee of a welfare trust fund; or</para><para>(f) Arbitrator or other purportedly disinterested adjudicator or referee.</para><para>(2) A person who holds himself or herself out to the public as being engaged in the business of making disinterested selection, appraisal, or criticism of commodities, property, or services commits a Class I misdemeanor if he or she solicits, accepts, or agrees to accept any benefit to alter, modify, or change his or her selection, appraisal, or criticism.</para><para>(3) A person commits a Class I misdemeanor if he or she confers or offers or agrees to confer any benefit the acceptance of which would be an offense under subsection (1) or (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 135; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 54. </para></source></law></legaldoc>