<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-917"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-917</statuteno><catchline>Bribery; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits bribery if:</para><para>(a) He offers, confers, or agrees to confer any benefit upon a public servant or peace officer with the intent to influence that public servant or peace officer to violate his public duty, or oath of office, thereby influencing the public servant's or peace officer's vote, opinion, judgment, exercise of discretion, or other action or inaction in his official capacity; or</para><para>(b) While a public servant or peace officer, he solicits, accepts, or agrees to accept any benefit upon an agreement or understanding that he will violate his public duty or oath of office by changing or amending his vote, opinion, judgment, exercise of discretion, or other action or inaction as a public servant or peace officer.</para><para>(2) It is no defense to prosecution under this section that the person sought to be influenced was not qualified to act in the desired way, whether because he had not yet assumed office, lacked jurisdiction, or for any other reason.</para><para>(3) Bribery is a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 202.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not repeal by implication section 49-14,101. This section prohibits anyone from conferring or offering to confer "any benefit" upon a public servant with the intent to influence that public servant's actions in his official capacity. State v. Null, 247 Neb. 192, 526 N.W.2d 220 (1995).</para><para>The crime of felony bribery is not committed unless the acts of the defendant actually influence a public servant's or peace officer's vote, opinion, judgment, exercise of discretion, or other action or inaction in his or her official capacity. State v. Kao, 3 Neb. App. 727, 531 N.W.2d 555 (1995).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>