<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id173">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id175"  statutenumber="28-728">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-728</statuteno><catchline id="id178">Legislative
findings and intent; child abuse and neglect investigation team; child advocacy
center; child abuse and neglect treatment team; powers and duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Legislature finds that child abuse and neglect are
community problems requiring a coordinated response by law enforcement, child
advocacy centers, prosecutors, the Department of Health and Human Services,
and other agencies or entities designed to protect children. It is the intent
of the Legislature to create a child abuse and neglect investigation team
in each county or contiguous group of counties and to create a child abuse
and neglect treatment team in each county or contiguous group of counties.</para>
<para>(2) Each county or contiguous group of counties will be assigned
by the Department of Health and Human Services to a child advocacy center.
The purpose of a child advocacy center is to provide a child-focused location
for conducting forensic interviews and medical evaluations for alleged child
victims of abuse and neglect and for coordinating a multidisciplinary team
response that supports the physical, emotional, and psychological needs of
children who are alleged victims of abuse or neglect. Each child advocacy
center shall meet accreditation criteria set forth by the National Children's
Alliance. Nothing in this section shall prevent a child from receiving treatment
or other services at a child advocacy center which has received or is in the
process of receiving accreditation.</para>
<para>(3) Each county attorney or the county attorney representing
a contiguous group of counties is responsible for convening the child abuse
and neglect investigation team and ensuring that protocols are established
and implemented. A representative of the child advocacy center assigned to
the team shall assist the county attorney in facilitating case review, developing
and updating protocols, and arranging training opportunities for the team.
Each team must have protocols which, at a minimum, shall include procedures
for:</para>
<para>(a) Mandatory reporting of child abuse and neglect as outlined
in section 28-711 to include training to professionals on identification and
reporting of abuse;</para>
<para>(b) Assigning roles and responsibilities between law enforcement
and the Department of Health and Human Services for the initial response;</para>
<para>(c) Outlining how reports will be shared between law enforcement
and the Department of Health and Human Services under sections 28-712.01 and 28-713;</para>
<para>(d) Coordinating the investigative response including, but
not limited to:</para>
<para>(i) Defining cases that require a priority response;</para>
<para>(ii) Contacting the reporting party;</para>
<para>(iii) Arranging for a video-recorded forensic interview at
a child advocacy center for children who are three to eighteen years of age
and are alleged to be victims of sexual abuse or serious physical abuse or
neglect, have witnessed a violent crime, are found in a drug-endangered environment,
or have been recovered from a kidnapping;</para>
<para>(iv) Assessing the need for and arranging, when indicated,
a medical evaluation of the alleged child victim;</para>
<para>(v) Assessing the need for and arranging, when indicated,
appropriate mental health services for the alleged child victim or nonoffender
caregiver;</para>
<para>(vi) Conducting collateral interviews with other persons
with information pertinent to the investigation including other potential
victims;</para>
<para>(vii) Collecting, processing, and preserving physical evidence
including photographing the crime scene as well as any physical injuries as
a result of the alleged child abuse and neglect; and</para>
<para>(viii) Interviewing the alleged perpetrator;</para>
<para>(e) Reducing the risk of harm to alleged child abuse and
neglect victims;</para>
<para>(f) Ensuring that the child is in safe surroundings, including
removing the perpetrator when necessary or arranging for temporary custody
of the child when the child is seriously endangered in his or her surroundings
and immediate removal appears to be necessary for the child's protection as
provided in section 43-248;</para>
<para>(g) Sharing of case information between team members; and</para>
<para>(h) Outlining what cases will be reviewed by the investigation
team including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(i) Cases of sexual abuse, serious physical abuse and neglect,
drug-endangered children, and serious or ongoing domestic violence;</para>
<para>(ii) Cases determined by the Department of Health and Human
Services to be high or very high risk for further maltreatment; and</para>
<para>(iii) Any other case referred by a member of the team when
a system-response issue has been identified.</para>
<para>(4) Each county attorney or the county attorney representing
a contiguous group of counties is responsible for convening the child abuse
and neglect treatment team and ensuring that protocols are established and
implemented. A representative of the child advocacy center appointed to the
team shall assist the county attorney in facilitating case review, developing
and updating protocols, and arranging training opportunities for the team.
Each team must have protocols which, at a minimum, shall include procedures
for:</para>
<para>(a) Case coordination and assistance, including the location
of services available within the area;</para>
<para>(b) Case staffings and the coordination, development, implementation,
and monitoring of treatment or safety plans particularly in those cases in
which ongoing services are provided by the Department of Health and Human
Services or a contracted agency but the juvenile court is not involved;</para>
<para>(c) Reducing the risk of harm to child abuse and neglect
victims;</para>
<para>(d) Assisting those child abuse and neglect victims who are
abused and neglected by perpetrators who do not reside in their homes; and</para>
<para>(e) Working with multiproblem status offenders and delinquent
youth.</para>
<para>(5) For purposes of this section, forensic interview means
a video-recorded interview of an alleged child victim conducted at a child
advocacy center by a professional with specialized training designed to elicit
details about alleged incidents of abuse or neglect, and such interview may
result in intervention in criminal or juvenile court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB993, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>