<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id38">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id40" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-831"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-831</statuteno><catchline id="id43">Human trafficking;
labor trafficking or sex trafficking; labor trafficking of a minor or sex
trafficking of a minor; prohibited acts; penalties.</catchline><para>(1)
No person shall knowingly engage in labor trafficking or sex trafficking.</para>
<para>(2) If an actor knowingly
engages in labor trafficking or sex trafficking by:</para>
<para>(a) Inflicting or threatening to inflict serious personal
injury, as defined
by section 28-318, on another
person, the actor is guilty of a Class III felony;</para>
<para>(b) Physically restraining or threatening to physically restrain
the other person, the actor is guilty of a Class III felony;</para>
<para>(c) Abusing
or threatening to abuse the legal process against another person to cause
arrest or deportation for violation of federal immigration law, the actor
is guilty of a Class IV felony;</para><para>(d) Controlling or threatening to control
another person's access to a controlled substance listed in Schedule I, II
or III of section 28-405, the actor is guilty of a Class IV felony;</para>
<para>(e) Exploiting
another person's substantial functional impairment as defined in section 28-368
or substantial mental impairment as defined in section 28-369, the actor is
guilty of a Class IV felony;</para><para>(f) Knowingly destroying, concealing, removing,
confiscating, or possessing any actual or purported passport or other immigration
document, or any other actual or purported government identification document,
of the other person, the actor is guilty of a Class IV felony; or </para>
<para>(g) Causing or threatening
to cause financial harm to another person, including debt bondage, the
actor is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(3) No person shall engage
in labor trafficking of a minor or sex trafficking of a minor. An actor who
engages in labor trafficking of a minor or sex trafficking of a minor shall
be punished as follows:</para>
<para>(a) In cases in which the actor uses overt force or the threat
of force against the trafficking victim, the actor is guilty of a Class II
felony;</para>
<para>(b) In cases in which the trafficking victim has not attained
the age of fifteen years, the actor is guilty of a Class II felony; or</para>
<para>(c) In cases involving a trafficking victim between the ages
of fifteen and eighteen years, and the actor does not use overt force or threat
of force against the trafficking victim, the actor is guilty of a Class III
felony.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who benefits,
financially or by receiving anything of value, from participation in a venture
which has, as part of the venture, an act that is in violation of this section,
is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1086, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB255, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB998, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>April 10, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>