<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-512"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-512</statuteno><catchline>Theft by deception.</catchline><para>A person commits theft if he obtains property of another by deception. A person deceives if he intentionally:</para><para>(1) Creates or reinforces a false impression, including false impressions as to law, value, intention, or other state of mind; but deception as to a person's intention to perform a promise shall not be inferred from the fact alone that he did not subsequently perform the promise; or</para><para>(2) Prevents another from acquiring information which would affect his judgment of a transaction; or</para><para>(3) Fails to correct a false impression which the deceiver previously created or reinforced, or which the deceiver knows to be influencing another to whom he stands in a fiduciary or confidential relationship; or</para><para>(4) Uses a credit card, charge plate, or any other instrument which purports to evidence an undertaking to pay for property or services delivered or rendered to or upon the order of a designated person or bearer (a) where such instrument has been stolen, forged, revoked, or canceled, or where for any other reason its use by the actor is unauthorized, or (b) where the actor does not have the intention and ability to meet all obligations to the issuer arising out of his use of the instrument.</para><para>The word deceive does not include falsity as to matters having no pecuniary significance, or statements unlikely to deceive ordinary persons in the group addressed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 111. </para></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (1) of this section, the offense of theft by deception may take place over a period of time. State v. Grell, 233 Neb. 314, 444 N.W.2d 911 (1989).</para><para>It is the required element of guilty knowledge, criminal intent, which distinguishes a civil breach of contract from theft by deception&#8212;a person's knowingly creating a false impression in order to obtain another's property. State v. Ladehoff, 228 Neb. 812, 424 N.W.2d 361 (1988).</para><para>Subsection (2) of this section is constitutional. State v. Scott, 225 Neb. 146, 403 N.W.2d 351 (1987).</para><para>Another's property is obtained by deception if an actor, by a statement or conduct, creates or reinforces a false impression in that person with the result that such false impression, alone or with other influences, effectively induces another to part with his or her property. State v. Fleming, 223 Neb. 169, 388 N.W.2d 497 (1986).</para><para>Subsection (1) of this section is not unconstitutionally vague. State v. Sailors, 217 Neb. 693, 352 N.W.2d 860 (1984).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>