<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<sectno id="id16">Sec. 14.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id17" statutenumber="28-604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id19">28-604</statuteno><catchline id="id20">Criminal possession
of a forged instrument; penalty;
aggregation allowed; when.</catchline><para>(1) Whoever,
with knowledge that it is forged and with intent to deceive or harm, possesses
any forged instrument covered by section 28-602 or 28-603 commits criminal
possession of a forged instrument.</para>
<para>(2) Criminal possession of a forged instrument prohibited
by section 28-602 is a Class IV felony.</para>
<para>(3) Criminal possession of a forged instrument prohibited
by section 28-603, the amount or value of which is one thousand dollars or
more, is a Class IV felony.</para>
<para>(4) Criminal possession of a forged instrument prohibited
by section 28-603, the amount or value of which is more than three hundred
dollars but less than one thousand dollars, is a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(5) Criminal possession of a forged instrument prohibited
by section 28-603, the amount or value of which is three hundred dollars or
less, is a Class II misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(6) For the
purpose of determining the class of penalty for criminal possession of a forged
instrument prohibited by section 28-603, the amounts or values of more than
one such forged instrument may be aggregated in the indictment or information
if such forged instruments were part of the same scheme or course of conduct
which took place within a sixty-day period and within one county. Such amounts
or values shall not be aggregated into more than one offense.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 126; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 17, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB155, &#167; 14.</para></source><annotation><para>Where the evidence offered no rational basis for convicting defendant of what he claimed to be the "lesser-included" offense of criminal possession of forged instrument, trial court did not err in refusing requested instruction. State v. Ebert, 212 Neb. 629, 324 N.W.2d 812 (1982).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>