<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id56" statutenumber="28-931"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-931</statuteno><catchline id="id59">Assault on an officer, an emergency responder, certain employees, or a health care professional in the third degree; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the offense of assault on an officer, an emergency responder, a state correctional employee, a Department of Health and Human Services employee, or a health care professional in the third degree if:</para><para>(a) He or she intentionally, knowingly, or recklessly causes bodily injury:</para><para>(i) To a peace officer, a probation officer, a firefighter, an emergency care provider, or an employee of the Department of Correctional Services;</para><para>(ii) To an employee of the Department of Health and Human Services if the person committing the offense is committed as a dangerous sex offender under the Sex Offender Commitment Act; or</para><para>(iii) To a health care professional; and</para><para>(b) The offense is committed while such officer, firefighter, emergency care provider, or employee is engaged in the performance of his or her official duties or while the health care professional is on duty at a hospital or a health clinic.</para><para>(2) Assault on an officer, an emergency responder, a state correctional employee, a Department of Health and Human Services employee, or a health care professional in the third degree shall be a Class IIIA felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 465, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 364, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB771, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB677, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1002, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1201.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The status of the victim under this section is an element of the crime and is not a subsequent offense penalty enhancement. State v. Taylor, 262 Neb. 639, 634 N.W.2d 744 (2001).</para><para>In prosecutions for assaulting a peace officer, obstructing a peace officer, or resisting arrest, a trial court must instruct the jury on the issue of self-defense when there is any evidence adduced which raises a legally cognizable claim that the peace officer used unreasonable force in making the arrest. State v. Yeutter, 252 Neb. 857, 566 N.W.2d 387 (1997).</para><para>For purposes of this section, the State must prove that the victim assaulted was a peace officer engaged in the performance of his or her official duties, but is not required to prove that the defendant was so aware. State v. Cebuhar, 252 Neb. 796, 567 N.W.2d 129 (1997).</para><para>Evidence that defendant hit a police officer with his right forearm and poked the officer in the eye when the officer attempted to prevent defendant from leaving an interviewing room while under arrest was sufficient to sustain the jury's guilty verdicts. Proof that the officer sustained bruises or other visible injuries is not required to prove third degree assault on an officer under this section. State v. Green, 240 Neb. 639, 483 N.W.2d 748 (1992).</para><para>A deputy sheriff is a peace officer. Assault on a peace officer in the third degree is committed when an on-duty deputy sheriff is slapped, and the deputy sheriff suffers physical pain. State v. Melton, 239 Neb. 576, 477 N.W.2d 154 (1991).</para><para>A police officer is a peace officer for purposes of this section. State v. Fly, 236 Neb. 408, 461 N.W.2d 421 (1990).</para><para>Jury properly advised that only reasonably necessary force may be used when making an arrest and that a person attacked so as to cause fear of bodily injury may use reasonable necessary force in defense. State v. Wallace, 223 Neb. 465, 390 N.W.2d 530 (1986).</para><para>An employee of the Douglas County Board of Corrections is considered a jailer and, therefore, a peace officer for the purposes of this section. State v. Parks, 8 Neb. App. 491, 596 N.W.2d 712 (1999).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>