<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-906"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>28-906</statuteno><catchline>Obstructing a peace officer; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) A person commits the offense of obstructing a peace officer, when,
by using or threatening to use violence, force, physical interference, or
obstacle, he or she intentionally obstructs, impairs, or hinders (a) the enforcement
of the penal law or the preservation of the peace by a peace officer or judge
acting under color of his or her official authority or (b) a police animal
assisting a peace officer acting pursuant to the peace officer's official
authority.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section, police animal means a horse or dog
owned or controlled by the State of Nebraska or any county, city, or village for the purpose
of assisting a peace officer acting
pursuant to his or her official authority.</para>
<para>(3) Obstructing a peace officer is a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 191; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 283, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB721, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>In prosecutions for assaulting a peace officer, obstructing a peace officer, or resisting arrest, a trial court must instruct the jury on the issue of self-defense when there is any evidence adduced which raises a legally cognizable claim that the peace officer used unreasonable force in making the arrest. State v. Yeutter, 252 Neb. 857, 566 N.W.2d 387 (1997).</para><para>The mere verbal refusal to provide information to an officer does not constitute an obstacle to the enforcement of the penal laws as contemplated by this section. State v. Yeutter, 252 Neb. 857, 566 N.W.2d 387 (1997).</para><para>"Preservation of the peace," as used in this statute, means maintaining the tranquillity enjoyed by members of a community where good order reigns. In re Interest of Richter, 226 Neb. 874, 415 N.W.2d 476 (1987).</para><para>The act of running away from an officer does obstruct, impair, or hinder the officer's efforts to preserve the peace. In re Interest of Richter, 226 Neb. 874, 415 N.W.2d 476 (1987).</para><para>Words "violence, force, physical interference, or obstacle" are of common usage and understandable by those of ordinary intelligence and, thus, not unconstitutionally vague. State v. Lynch, 223 Neb. 849, 394 N.W.2d 651 (1986).</para><para>The evidence was sufficient to convict the defendant under subsection (1) of this section where the defendant fled in his vehicle because he feared being arrested after he had been questioned by an officer, ordered to exit his vehicle, and approached by two officers and where the defendant disobeyed the officers' orders to get on the ground after the ensuing chase through a residential area. State v. Ellingson, 13 Neb. App. 931, 703 N.W.2d 273 (2005).</para><para>There must be some sort of affirmative physical act, or threat thereof, for a violation of this section to occur. State v. Owen, 7 Neb. App. 153, 580 N.W.2d 566 (1998).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>