<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id141">
<sectno id="id142">Sec. 16.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id143" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="28-611.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>28-611.01</statuteno><catchline>Issuing a no-account check; penalty;
aggregation allowed; when.</catchline><para>(1) Whoever issues or passes a check, draft, assignment
of funds, or similar signed order for the payment of money, knowing that he
or she has no account with the drawee at the time the check, draft, assignment
of funds, or order is issued, commits the offense of issuing a no-account
check. Issuing a no-account check is:</para>
<para>(a) A Class
III felony if the amount of the check, draft, assignment of funds, or order
is one thousand five hundred dollars or more;</para><para>(b) A Class IV felony
if the amount of the check, draft, assignment of funds, or order is five hundred
dollars or more, but less than one thousand five hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(c) A Class
I misdemeanor if the amount of the check, draft, assignment of funds, or order
is two hundred dollars or more, but less than five hundred dollars; and</para>
<para>(d) A Class
II misdemeanor if the amount of the check, draft, assignment of funds, or
order is less than two hundred dollars.</para><para>(2) The aggregate amount of any series
of checks, drafts, assignments, or orders issued or passed within a sixty-day
period in one county may be used in determining the classification of the
offense pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, except that checks, drafts,
assignments, or orders may not be aggregated into more than one offense.</para>
<para>(3) For any
second or subsequent offense under this section, any person so offending shall
be guilty of:</para><para>(a) A Class III felony if the amount of the check, draft, assignment
of funds, or order is five hundred dollars or more; and</para>
<para>(b) A Class
IV felony if the amount of the check, draft, assignment of funds, or order
is less than five hundred dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB155, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>