<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id91" statutenumber="28-718"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>28-718</statuteno><catchline id="id94">Child protection cases; central registry; name-change order; treatment; fee; waiver.</catchline><para>(1) There shall be a central registry of child protection cases maintained in the department containing records of all reports of child abuse or neglect opened for investigation as provided in section 28-713 and classified as either court substantiated or agency substantiated as provided in section 28-720.</para><para>(2) The department shall determine whether a name-change order received from the clerk of a district court pursuant to section 25-21,271 is for a person on the central registry of child protection cases and, if so, shall include the changed name with the former name in the registry and file or cross-reference the information under both names.</para><para>(3) The department may charge a reasonable fee in an amount established by the department in rules and regulations to recover expenses in carrying out central registry records checks. The fee shall not exceed three dollars for each request to check the records of the central registry. The department shall remit the fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the Health and Human Services Cash Fund. The department may waive the fee if the requesting party shows the fee would be an undue financial hardship. The department shall use the fees to defray costs incurred to carry out such records checks. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB122, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB147, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB225, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>