<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-401"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-401</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>As used in the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, unless the
context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Administer means to
directly apply a controlled substance by injection, inhalation, ingestion,
or any other means to the body of a patient or research subject;</para>
<para>(2) Agent means an
authorized person who acts on behalf of or at the direction of another person
but does not include a common
or contract carrier, public warehouse keeper, or employee of a carrier or
warehouse keeper;</para>
<para>(3) Administration means the
Drug Enforcement Administration of the United States Department
of Justice;</para>
<para>(4) Controlled substance means a
drug, biological, substance, or immediate precursor in Schedules I to V of
section 28-405. Controlled substance does not include distilled
spirits, wine, malt beverages, tobacco, or any nonnarcotic substance if such
substance may, under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, 21 U.S.C. 301
et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2014, and the law of this
state, be lawfully sold over the counter without a prescription;</para>
<para>(5) Counterfeit substance means a
controlled substance which, or the container or labeling of which, without
authorization, bears the trademark, trade name, or other identifying mark,
imprint, number, or device, or any likeness thereof, of a manufacturer, distributor,
or dispenser other than the person or persons who in fact manufactured, distributed,
or dispensed such substance and which thereby falsely purports or is represented
to be the product of, or to have been distributed by, such other manufacturer,
distributor, or dispenser;</para>
<para>(6) Department means the
Department of Health and Human Services;</para>
<para>(7) Division of Drug Control means the
personnel of the Nebraska State Patrol who are assigned to enforce the Uniform
Controlled Substances Act;</para>
<para>(8) Dispense means to
deliver a controlled substance to an ultimate user or a research subject pursuant
to a medical order issued by a practitioner authorized to prescribe, including
the packaging, labeling, or compounding necessary to prepare the controlled
substance for such delivery;</para>
<para>(9) Distribute means to
deliver other than by administering or dispensing a controlled substance;</para>
<para>(10) Prescribe means to
issue a medical order;</para>
<para>(11) Drug means (a)
articles recognized in the official United States Pharmacopoeia, official
Homeopathic Pharmacopoeia of the United States, official National Formulary,
or any supplement to any of them, (b) substances intended for use in the diagnosis,
cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of disease in human beings or animals,
and (c) substances intended for use as a component of any article specified
in subdivision (a) or (b) of this subdivision, but does not
include devices or their components, parts, or accessories;</para>
<para>(12) Deliver or delivery means the
actual, constructive, or attempted transfer from one person to another of
a controlled substance, whether or not there is an agency relationship;</para>
<para>(13) Marijuana means all
parts of the plant of the genus cannabis, whether growing or not, the seeds
thereof, and every compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture, or preparation
of such plant or its seeds, but does not include the mature
stalks of such plant, hashish, tetrahydrocannabinols extracted or isolated
from the plant, fiber produced from such stalks, oil or cake made from the
seeds of such plant, any other compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture,
or preparation of such mature stalks, or the sterilized seed of such plant
which is incapable of germination. When the weight of marijuana is referred
to in the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, it means its
weight at or about the time it is seized or otherwise comes into the possession
of law enforcement authorities, whether cured or uncured at that time. When industrial hemp as defined in section
2-5701 is in the possession of a person as authorized under section 2-5701,
it is not considered marijuana for purposes of the Uniform Controlled Substances
Act;</para>
<para>(14) Manufacture means the
production, preparation, propagation, conversion, or processing of a controlled
substance, either directly or indirectly, by extraction from substances of
natural origin, independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination
of extraction and chemical synthesis, and includes any
packaging or repackaging of the substance or labeling or relabeling of its
container. Manufacture does not include the preparation
or compounding of a controlled substance by an individual for his or her own
use, except for the preparation or compounding of components or ingredients
used for or intended to be used for the manufacture of methamphetamine, or
the preparation, compounding, conversion, packaging, or labeling of a controlled
substance: (a) By a practitioner as an incident to his or her prescribing,
administering, or dispensing of a controlled substance in the course of his
or her professional practice; or (b) by a practitioner, or by his or her authorized
agent under his or her supervision, for the purpose of, or as an incident
to, research, teaching, or chemical analysis and not for sale;</para>
<para>(15) Narcotic drug means any
of the following, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from
substances of vegetable origin, independently by means of chemical synthesis,
or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis: (a) Opium, opium
poppy and poppy straw, coca leaves, and opiates; (b) a compound, manufacture,
salt, derivative, or preparation of opium, coca leaves, or opiates; or (c)
a substance and any compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, or preparation
thereof which is chemically equivalent to or identical with any of the substances
referred to in subdivisions (a) and (b) of this subdivision, except that the
words narcotic drug as used in the Uniform Controlled Substances Act does not include decocainized coca leaves or
extracts of coca leaves, which extracts do not contain cocaine or ecgonine,
or isoquinoline alkaloids of opium;</para>
<para>(16) Opiate means any
substance having an addiction-forming or addiction-sustaining liability similar
to morphine or being capable of conversion into a drug having such addiction-forming
or addiction-sustaining liability. Opiate does not include the dextrorotatory
isomer of 3-methoxy-n methylmorphinan and its salts. Opiate includes its
racemic and levorotatory forms;</para>
<para>(17) Opium poppy means the
plant of the species Papaver somniferum L., except the seeds thereof;</para>
<para>(18) Poppy straw means all
parts, except the seeds, of the opium poppy after mowing;</para>
<para>(19) Person means any
corporation, association, partnership, limited liability company, or one or
more persons;</para>
<para>(20) Practitioner means a
physician, a physician assistant, a dentist, a veterinarian, a pharmacist,
a podiatrist, an optometrist, a certified nurse midwife, a certified registered
nurse anesthetist, a nurse practitioner, a scientific investigator, a pharmacy,
a hospital, or any other person licensed, registered, or otherwise permitted
to distribute, dispense, prescribe, conduct research with respect to, or administer
a controlled substance in the course of practice or research in this state,
including an emergency medical service as defined in section 38-1207;</para>
<para>(21) Production includes the
manufacture, planting, cultivation, or harvesting of a controlled substance;</para>
<para>(22) Immediate precursor means a
substance which is the principal compound commonly used or produced primarily
for use and which is an immediate chemical intermediary used or likely to
be used in the manufacture of a controlled substance, the control of which
is necessary to prevent, curtail, or limit such manufacture;</para>
<para>(23) State means the
State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(24) Ultimate user means a
person who lawfully possesses a controlled substance for his or her own use,
for the use of a member of his or her household, or for administration to
an animal owned by him or her or by a member of his or her household;</para>
<para>(25) Hospital has the
same meaning as in section 71-419;</para>
<para>(26) Cooperating individual means any
person, other than a commissioned law enforcement officer, who acts on behalf
of, at the request of, or as agent for a law enforcement agency for the purpose
of gathering or obtaining evidence of offenses punishable under the Uniform
Controlled Substances Act;</para>
<para>(27) Hashish or concentrated cannabis means (a) the separated resin, whether crude
or purified, obtained from a plant of the genus cannabis or (b) any material, preparation, mixture,
compound, or other substance which contains ten percent or more by weight
of tetrahydrocannabinols. When
resins extracted from industrial hemp as defined in section 2-5701 are in
the possession of a person as authorized under section 2-5701, they are not
considered hashish or concentrated cannabis for purposes of the Uniform Controlled
Substances Act;</para>
<para>(28) Exceptionally hazardous drug means (a)
a narcotic drug, (b) thiophene analog of phencyclidine, (c) phencyclidine,
(d) amobarbital, (e) secobarbital, (f) pentobarbital, (g) amphetamine, or
(h) methamphetamine;</para>
<para>(29) Imitation controlled substance means a
substance which is not a controlled substance or controlled substance analogue but which,
by way of express or implied representations and consideration of other relevant
factors including those specified in section 28-445, would lead a reasonable
person to believe the substance is a controlled substance or controlled substance analogue. A placebo
or registered investigational drug manufactured, distributed, possessed, or
delivered in the ordinary course of practice or research by a health care
professional shall not be deemed to be an imitation controlled substance;</para>
<para>(30)(a) Controlled substance analogue means a
substance (i) the chemical structure of which is substantially similar to
the chemical structure of a Schedule I or Schedule II controlled substance
as provided in section 28-405 or (ii) which has a stimulant, depressant, analgesic,
or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system that is substantially
similar to or greater than the stimulant, depressant, analgesic, or hallucinogenic
effect on the central nervous system of a Schedule I or Schedule II controlled
substance as provided in section 28-405. A controlled substance analogue shall,
to the extent intended for human consumption, be treated as a controlled substance
under Schedule I of section 28-405 for purposes of the Uniform Controlled
Substances Act; and</para>
<para>(b) Controlled substance analogue does not
include (i) a controlled substance, (ii) any substance generally recognized
as safe and effective within the meaning of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic
Act, 21 U.S.C. 301 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2014, (iii)
any substance for which there is an approved new drug application, or (iv)
with respect to a particular person, any substance if an exemption is in effect
for investigational use for that person, under section 505 of the Federal
Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, 21 U.S.C. 355, as such section existed on January
1, 2014, to the extent conduct
with respect to such substance is pursuant to such exemption;</para>
<para>(31) Anabolic steroid means any
drug or hormonal substance, chemically and pharmacologically related to testosterone
(other than estrogens, progestins, and corticosteroids), that promotes muscle
growth and includes any controlled substance in Schedule III(d) of section
28-405. Anabolic steroid does not include any anabolic
steroid which is expressly intended for administration through implants to
cattle or other nonhuman species and has been approved by the Secretary of
Health and Human Services for such administration, but if any person prescribes,
dispenses, or distributes such a steroid for human use, such person shall
be considered to have prescribed, dispensed, or distributed an anabolic steroid
within the meaning of this subdivision;</para>
<para>(32) Chart order means an
order for a controlled substance issued by a practitioner for a patient who
is in the hospital where the chart is stored or for a patient receiving detoxification
treatment or maintenance treatment pursuant to section 28-412. Chart order does not include a prescription;</para>
<para>(33) Medical order means a
prescription, a chart order, or an order for pharmaceutical care issued by
a practitioner;</para>
<para>(34) Prescription means an
order for a controlled substance issued by a practitioner. Prescription does not include a chart order;</para>
<para>(35) Registrant means any
person who has a controlled substances registration issued by the state or
the administration;</para>
<para>(36) Reverse distributor means a
person whose primary function is to act as an agent for a pharmacy, wholesaler,
manufacturer, or other entity by receiving, inventorying, and managing the
disposition of outdated, expired, or otherwise nonsaleable controlled substances;</para>
<para>(37) Signature means the
name, word, or mark of a person written in his or her own hand with the intent
to authenticate a writing or other form of communication or a digital signature
which complies with section 86-611 or an electronic signature;</para>
<para>(38) Facsimile means a
copy generated by a system that encodes a document or photograph into electrical
signals, transmits those signals over telecommunications lines, and reconstructs
the signals to create an exact duplicate of the original document at the receiving
end;</para>
<para>(39) Electronic signature has the
definition found in section 86-621;</para>
<para>(40) Electronic transmission means transmission
of information in electronic form. Electronic transmission includes computer-to-computer
transmission or computer-to-facsimile transmission;</para>
<para>(41) Long-term care facility means an
intermediate care facility, an intermediate care facility for persons with
developmental disabilities, a long-term care hospital, a mental health center,
a nursing facility, or a skilled nursing facility, as such terms are defined
in the Health Care Facility Licensure Act;</para>
<para>(42) Compounding
has the same meaning as in section 38-2811; and</para><para>(43) Cannabinoid receptor
agonist shall mean any chemical compound or substance that, according to scientific
or medical research, study, testing, or analysis, demonstrates the presence
of binding activity at one or more of the CB1 or CB2 cell membrane receptors
located within the human body.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 276, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 696, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 323, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 406, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 273, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 537, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 175; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 379, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 428; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 200, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 117, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1119; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1001, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The "personal use exception" in subsection (14) of this section applies to only "preparation" and "compounding" of a controlled substance, but does not apply to the "production" of a controlled substance. State v. Bossow, 274 Neb. 836, 744 N.W.2d 43 (2008).</para><para>Under subsection (22) of this section, the term manufacture includes cultivating marijuana. State v. Havlat, 222 Neb. 554, 385 N.W.2d 436 (1986).</para><para>A jury instruction as to the technical definition of marijuana need not be given where the defendant is charged with delivery of marijuana, when the evidence at trial presents no factual issue as to whether the substance involved was anything but marijuana. State v. Taylor, 221 Neb. 114, 375 N.W.2d 610 (1985).</para><para>The Criminal Code which became effective on January 1, 1979, is not applicable to offenses committed prior to its effective date. State v. Fuller, 203 Neb. 233, 278 N.W.2d 756 (1979).</para><para>Aiding and abetting possession is a lesser-included offense of aiding and abetting distribution. State v. McKimmey, 10 Neb. App. 595, 634 N.W.2d 817 (2001).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
