<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-406</statuteno><catchline>Registration; fees.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall issue registrations and reregistrations to manufacture, distribute, prescribe, or dispense controlled substances within this state on a biennial basis.</para><para>(2) The various fees to be paid by applicants for registrations and reregistrations, as required under the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) Registration or reregistration to manufacture controlled substances, not less than one hundred dollars and not more than three hundred dollars;</para><para>(b) Registration or reregistration to distribute controlled substances, not less than one hundred dollars and not more than three hundred dollars;</para><para>(c) Registration or reregistration to prescribe, administer, or dispense controlled substances, not less than twenty dollars and not more than one hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(d) Registration or reregistration to engage in research on the use and effects of controlled substances, not less than fifty dollars and not more than two hundred dollars;</para><para>(e) Registration or reregistration to engage in laboratory and analytical analysis of controlled substances, not less than fifty dollars and not more than two hundred dollars; and</para><para>(f) Registration or reregistration to provide detoxification treatment or maintenance treatment, not less than twenty dollars and not more than one hundred fifty dollars.</para><para>(3) The department shall remit the fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the Professional and Occupational Credentialing Cash Fund.</para><para>(4) All registrations and reregistrations shall expire on August 31 of each odd-numbered year. Registration shall be automatically denied without a hearing for nonpayment of fees. Any registration or reregistration not renewed by payment of renewal fees by October 1 of odd-numbered years shall be automatically denied and canceled on October 2 of odd-numbered years without a hearing.</para><para>(5) The department is authorized to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to implement this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 323, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 550, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>