<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id35" statutenumber="28-712"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>28-712</statuteno><catchline>Reports of child abuse or neglect; department; determination; alternative response; department; use; advisory committee; recommendations; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receipt of a report pursuant to section 28-711, the department shall determine whether to (a) accept the report for traditional response and an investigation pursuant to section 28-713, (b) accept the report for alternative response pursuant to section 28-712.01, (c) accept the report for screening by the Review, Evaluate, and Decide Team to determine eligibility for alternative response, or (d) classify the report as requiring no further action by the department.</para><para>(2)(a) The Nebraska Children's Commission shall appoint an advisory committee to examine the department's alternative response to reports of child abuse or neglect and to make recommendations to the Legislature, the department, and the commission regarding (i) the receipt and screening of reports of child abuse or neglect by the department, (ii) the ongoing use of alternative response, (iii) the ongoing use of traditional response, and (iv) the provision of services within alternative response and non-court-involved cases to ensure child safety, to reduce the risk of child abuse or neglect, and to engage families. The advisory committee may request, receive, and review data from the department regarding such processes.</para><para>(b) The members of the advisory committee shall include, but not be limited to, a representative of (i) the department, (ii) law enforcement agencies, (iii) county attorneys or other prosecutors, (iv) the state chapter of child advocacy centers as defined in 34 U.S.C. 20302, (v) attorneys for parents, (vi) guardians ad litem, (vii) a child welfare advocacy organization, (viii) families with experience in the child welfare system, (ix) family caregivers, (x) the Foster Care Review Office, and (xi) the office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare. Members of the advisory committee shall be appointed for terms of two years. The Nebraska Children's Commission shall appoint the chairperson of the advisory committee and may fill vacancies on the advisory committee as they occur.</para><para>(3) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section and sections 28-710.01, 28-712.01, and 28-713. Such rules and regulations shall include, but not be limited to, provisions on (a) the transfer of cases from alternative response to traditional response, (b) notice to families subject to a comprehensive assessment and served through alternative response of the alternative response process and their rights, including the opportunity to challenge agency determinations, (c) the provision of services through alternative response, and (d) the collection, sharing, and reporting of data.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB225, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1061, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>