<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments"  statutenumber="28-372"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>28-372</statuteno><catchline>Report of abuse, neglect, or exploitation; required; contents; notification; toll-free number established.</catchline><para>(1) When any physician, psychologist, physician assistant, nurse, nurse aide, other medical, developmental disability, or mental health professional, law enforcement personnel, caregiver or employee of a caregiver, operator or employee of a sheltered workshop, owner, operator, or employee of any facility licensed by the department, or human services professional or paraprofessional not including a member of the clergy has reasonable cause to believe that a vulnerable adult has been subjected to abuse, neglect, or exploitation or observes such adult being subjected to conditions or circumstances which reasonably would result in abuse, neglect, or exploitation, he or she shall report the incident or cause a report to be made to the appropriate law enforcement agency or to the department. Any other person may report abuse, neglect, or exploitation if such person has reasonable cause to believe that a vulnerable adult has been subjected to abuse, neglect, or exploitation or observes such adult being subjected to conditions or circumstances which reasonably would result in abuse, neglect, or exploitation.</para><para>(2) Such report may be made by telephone, with the caller giving his or her name and address, and, if requested by the department, shall be followed by a written report within forty-eight hours. To the extent available the report shall contain: (a) The name, address, and age of the vulnerable adult; (b) the address of the caregiver or caregivers of the vulnerable adult; (c) the nature and extent of the alleged abuse, neglect, or exploitation or the conditions and circumstances which would reasonably be expected to result in such abuse, neglect, or exploitation; (d) any evidence of previous abuse, neglect, or exploitation, including the nature and extent of the abuse, neglect, or exploitation; and (e) any other information which in the opinion of the person making the report may be helpful in establishing the cause of the alleged abuse, neglect, or exploitation and the identity of the perpetrator or perpetrators.</para><para>(3) Any law enforcement agency receiving a report of abuse, neglect, or exploitation shall notify the department no later than the next working day by telephone or mail.</para><para>(4) A report of abuse, neglect, or exploitation made to the department which was not previously made to or by a law enforcement agency shall be communicated to the appropriate law enforcement agency by the department no later than the next working day by telephone or mail.</para><para>(5) The department shall establish a statewide toll-free number to be used by any person any hour of the day or night and any day of the week to make reports of abuse, neglect, or exploitation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 463, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1051, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB417, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>In order for a retaliatory discharge action to lie against an employer for discharging an employee in retaliation for the mandatory filing of a report of patient abuse pursuant to this section, such report must be based upon reasonable cause. Wendeln v. Beatrice Manor, 271 Neb. 373, 712 N.W.2d 226 (2006).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>