<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id106" statutenumber="28-720"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-720</statuteno><catchline id="id109">Cases; central registry; classification; expungement; department; report.</catchline><para>(1) All cases entered into the central registry of child protection cases maintained pursuant to section 28-718 shall be classified as one of the following:</para><para>(a) Court substantiated, if a court of competent jurisdiction has entered a judgment of guilty against the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect upon a criminal complaint, indictment, or information or there has been an adjudication of jurisdiction of a juvenile court over the child under subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247 which relates or pertains to the report of child abuse or neglect;</para><para>(b) Court pending, if a criminal complaint, indictment, or information or a juvenile petition under subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247, which relates or pertains to the subject of the report of abuse or neglect, has been filed and is pending in a court of competent jurisdiction; or</para><para>(c) Agency substantiated, if the department's determination of child abuse or neglect against the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect was supported by a preponderance of the evidence and based upon an investigation pursuant to section 28-712.01 or 28-713.</para><para>(2) If a case described in subdivision (1)(b) of this section is dismissed by the court or a juvenile petition under subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247 is redesignated to indicate there is no fault on the part of the parent, guardian, or custodian, the case shall be immediately expunged from the central registry of child protection cases.</para><para>(3)(a) If the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect is a minor child who is younger than twelve years of age, the case shall not be entered into the central registry of child protection cases.</para><para>(b) If a juvenile petition is filed under subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247 indicating that the juvenile is without proper support through no fault of his or her parent, guardian, or custodian, the case shall not be entered into the central registry of child protection cases.</para><para>(4) If the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect is a minor child who is twelve years of age or older but younger than nineteen years of age, the case shall not be classified as court pending in the central registry of child protection cases.</para><para>(5) The department shall report annually, on or before September 15, to the Governor and electronically to the chairpersons of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature the number of cases entered into the central registry of child protection cases in which the subject is a minor child, the ages of such subjects who are children, and the number of such cases classified as court substantiated or agency substantiated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB122, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB292, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>