<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<sectno id="id18" opdate="January 1, 2010">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id19" statutenumber="28-322.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id21">28-322.05</statuteno><catchline>Unlawful
use of the Internet by a prohibited sex offender; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person required to register under the Sex Offender Registration
Act who is
required to register because of a conviction for one or more of the following
offenses, including any substantially equivalent offense committed in another
state, territory, commonwealth, or other jurisdiction of the United States, and who knowingly and intentionally uses a social
networking web site, instant messaging,
or chat room service that allows a person who is less than eighteen years
of age to access or use its social networking web site, instant messaging,
or chat room service, commits the offense of unlawful use of the Internet
by a prohibited sex offender:</para>
<para>(a) Kidnapping of a minor pursuant to section 28-313;</para>
<para>(b) Sexual assault of a child in the first degree pursuant
to section 28-319.01;</para>
<para>(c) Sexual assault of a child in the second or third degree
pursuant to section 28-320.01;</para>
<para>(d) Incest of a minor pursuant to section 28-703;</para>
<para>(e) Pandering of a minor pursuant to section 28-802;</para>
<para>(f) Visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct of a child
pursuant to section 28-1463.03 or 28-1463.05;</para>
<para>(g) Possessing any visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct
pursuant to section 28-813.01;</para>
<para>(h) Criminal child enticement pursuant to section 28-311;</para>
<para>(i) Child enticement by means of an electronic communication
device pursuant to section 28-320.02;</para>
<para>(j) Enticement by electronic communication device pursuant
to section 28-833; or</para>
<para>(k) An attempt or conspiracy to commit an offense listed in
subdivisions (1)(a) through (1)(j) of this section.</para>
<para>(2) Unlawful use of the Internet by a prohibited sex offender
is a Class I misdemeanor for a first offense. Any second or subsequent conviction
under this section is a Class IIIA felony.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB285, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 29-4001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>