<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-831" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-831</statuteno><catchline>Human trafficking; forced labor or services; prohibited acts; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall knowingly subject or attempt to subject another person to forced labor or services. If an actor knowingly subjects another person to forced labor or services by:</para><para>(a) Inflicting or threatening to inflict serious personal injury as defined by section 28-318, the actor is guilty of a Class III felony;</para><para>(b) Physically restraining or threatening to physically restrain another person, the actor is guilty of a Class III felony;</para><para>(c) Knowingly destroying, concealing, removing, confiscating, or possessing any actual or purported passport or other immigration document, or any other actual or purported government identification document, of such other person, the actor is guilty of a Class IV felony; or </para><para>(d) Causing or threatening to cause financial harm to another person, the actor is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) No person shall knowingly recruit, entice, harbor, transport, provide, or obtain by any means or attempt to recruit, entice, harbor, provide, or obtain by any means a minor for the purpose of having such minor engage in commercial sexual activity, sexually-explicit performance, or the production of pornography, or to cause or attempt to cause a minor to engage in commercial sexual activity, sexually-explicit performance, or the production of pornography. A person who violates this subsection shall be punished as follows:</para><para>(a) In cases in which the actor uses overt force or the threat of force, the actor is guilty of a Class II felony;</para><para>(b) In cases in which the victim has not attained the age of fifteen years and the actor does not use overt force or the threat of force, the actor is guilty of a Class II felony; or</para><para>(c) In cases involving a victim between the ages of fifteen and eighteen years, and the actor does not use overt force or threat of force, the actor is guilty of a Class III felony.</para><para>(3) Any person who knowingly (a) recruits, entices, harbors, transports, provides, or obtains by any means, or attempts to recruit, entice, harbor, transport, provide, or obtain by any means, a person eighteen years of age or older, intending or knowing that the person will be subjected to forced labor or services or (b) benefits, financially or by receiving anything of value, from participation in a venture which has, as part of the venture, an act that is in violation of subsection (1) of this section, is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1086, &#167; 11.</para></source></law></legaldoc>