<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id56" statutenumber="28-405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>28-405</statuteno><catchline id="id59">Controlled substances; schedules; enumerated.</catchline><para>The following are the schedules of controlled substances referred to in the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, unless specifically contained on the list of exempted products of the Drug Enforcement Administration of the United States Department of Justice as the list existed on January 31, 2021:</para><para>Schedule I</para><para>(a) Any of the following opiates, including their isomers, esters, ethers, salts, and salts of isomers, esters, and ethers, unless specifically excepted, whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers, and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) Acetylmethadol;</para><para>(2) Allylprodine;</para><para>(3) Alphacetylmethadol, except levo-alphacetylmethadol which is also known as levo-alpha-acetylmethadol, levomethadyl acetate, and LAAM;</para><para>(4) Alphameprodine;</para><para>(5) Alphamethadol;</para><para>(6) Benzethidine;</para><para>(7) Betacetylmethadol;</para><para>(8) Betameprodine;</para><para>(9) Betamethadol;</para><para>(10) Betaprodine;</para><para>(11) Clonitazene;</para><para>(12) Dextromoramide;</para><para>(13) Difenoxin;</para><para>(14) Diampromide;</para><para>(15) Diethylthiambutene;</para><para>(16) Dimenoxadol;</para><para>(17) Dimepheptanol;</para><para>(18) Dimethylthiambutene;</para><para>(19) Dioxaphetyl butyrate;</para><para>(20) Dipipanone;</para><para>(21) Ethylmethylthiambutene;</para><para>(22) Etonitazene;</para><para>(23) Etoxeridine;</para><para>(24) Furethidine;</para><para>(25) Hydroxypethidine;</para><para>(26) Ketobemidone;</para><para>(27) Levomoramide;</para><para>(28) Levophenacylmorphan;</para><para>(29) Morpheridine;</para><para>(30) Noracymethadol;</para><para>(31) Norlevorphanol;</para><para>(32) Normethadone;</para><para>(33) Norpipanone;</para><para>(34) Phenadoxone;</para><para>(35) Phenampromide;</para><para>(36) Phenomorphan;</para><para>(37) Phenoperidine;</para><para>(38) Piritramide;</para><para>(39) Proheptazine;</para><para>(40) Properidine;</para><para>(41) Propiram;</para><para>(42) Racemoramide;</para><para>(43) Trimeperidine;</para><para>(44) Alpha-methylfentanyl, N-(1-(alpha-methyl-beta-phenyl)ethyl-4-piperidyl) propionanilide, 1-(1-methyl-2-phenylethyl)-4-(N-propanilido) piperidine;</para><para>(45) Tilidine;</para><para>(46) 3-Methylfentanyl, N-(3-methyl-1-(2-phenylethyl)-4-piperidyl)-N-phenylpropanamide, its optical and geometric isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(47) 1-methyl-4-phenyl-4-propionoxypiperidine (MPPP), its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(48) PEPAP, 1-(2-phenethyl)-4-phenyl-4-acetoxypiperidine, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(49) Acetyl-alpha-methylfentanyl, N-(1-(1-methyl-2-phenethyl)-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylacetamide, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(50) Alpha-methylthiofentanyl, N-(1-methyl-2-(2-thienyl)ethyl-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylpropanamide, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(51) Benzylfentanyl, N-(1-benzyl-4-piperidyl)-N-phenylpropanamide, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(52) Beta-hydroxyfentanyl, N-(1-(2-hydroxy-2-phenethyl)-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylpropanamide, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(53) Beta-hydroxy-3-methylfentanyl, (other name: N-(1-(2-hydroxy-2-phenethyl)-3-methyl-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylpropanamide), its optical and geometric isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(54) 3-methylthiofentanyl, N-(3-methyl-1-(2-thienyl)ethyl-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylpropanamide, its optical and geometric isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(55) N-(1-(2-thienyl)methyl-4-piperidyl)-N-phenylpropanamide (thenylfentanyl), its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(56) Thiofentanyl, N-phenyl-N-(1-(2-thienyl)ethyl-4-piperidinyl)-propanamide, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(57) Para-fluorofentanyl, N-(4-fluorophenyl)-N-(1-(2-phenethyl)-4-piperidinyl)propanamide, its optical isomers, salts, and salts of isomers;</para><para>(58) U-47700, 3,4-dichloro-N-[2-(dimethylamino)cyclohexyl]-N-methylbenzamide;</para><para>(59) 4-Fluoroisobutyryl Fentanyl;</para><para>(60) Acetyl Fentanyl;</para><para>(61) Acyrloylfentanyl;</para><para>(62) AH-7921; 3, 4-dichloro-N-[(1-dimethylamino) cyclohexylmethyl] benzamide;</para><para>(63) Butyryl fentanyl;</para><para>(64) Cyclopentyl fentanyl;</para><para>(65) Cyclopropyl fentanyl;</para><para>(66) Furanyl fentanyl;</para><para>(67) Isobutyryl fentanyl;</para><para>(68) Isotonitazene;</para><para>(69) Methoxyacetyl fentanyl;</para><para>(70) MT-45; 1-cycloxhenxyl-4-(1,2-diphenylethyl) piperazine;</para><para>(71) Tetrahydrofuranyl fentanyl;</para><para>(72) 2-fluorofentanyl; N-(2-fluorohenyl)-N-(1-phenethylpiperidin-4-yl) propionamide;</para><para>(73) Ocfentanil;</para><para>(74) Ortho-Fluorofentanyl;</para><para>(75) Para-chloroisobutyryl fentanyl;</para><para>(76) Para-Fluorobutyryl Fentanyl; and</para><para>(77) Valeryl fentanyl.</para><para>(b) Any of the following opium derivatives, their salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, unless specifically excepted, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) Acetorphine;</para><para>(2) Acetyldihydrocodeine;</para><para>(3) Benzylmorphine;</para><para>(4) Codeine methylbromide;</para><para>(5) Codeine-N-Oxide;</para><para>(6) Cyprenorphine;</para><para>(7) Desomorphine;</para><para>(8) Dihydromorphine;</para><para>(9) Drotebanol;</para><para>(10) Etorphine, except hydrochloride salt;</para><para>(11) Heroin;</para><para>(12) Hydromorphinol;</para><para>(13) Methyldesorphine;</para><para>(14) Methyldihydromorphine;</para><para>(15) Morphine methylbromide;</para><para>(16) Morphine methylsulfonate;</para><para>(17) Morphine-N-Oxide;</para><para>(18) Myrophine;</para><para>(19) Nicocodeine;</para><para>(20) Nicomorphine;</para><para>(21) Normorphine;</para><para>(22) Pholcodine; and</para><para>(23) Thebacon.</para><para>(c) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following hallucinogenic substances, their salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, unless specifically excepted, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation, and, for purposes of this subdivision only, isomer shall include the optical, position, and geometric isomers:</para><para>(1) Bufotenine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 3-(beta-Dimethylaminoethyl)-5-hydroxyindole; 3-(2-dimethylaminoethyl)-5-indolol; N,N-dimethylserotonin; 5-hydroxy-N,N-dimethyltryptamine; and mappine;</para><para>(2) 4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxy-alpha-methylphenethylamine; and 4-bromo-2,5-DMA;</para><para>(3) 4-methoxyamphetamine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 4-methoxy-alpha-methylphenethylamine; and paramethoxyamphetamine, PMA;</para><para>(4) 4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxy-alpha-methylphenethylamine; DOM; and STP;</para><para>(5) Ibogaine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 7-Ethyl-6,6beta,7,8,9,10,12,13-octahydro-2-methoxy-6,9-methano-5H-pyrido (1',2':1,2) azepino (5,4-b) indole; and Tabernanthe iboga;</para><para>(6) Lysergic acid diethylamide;</para><para>(7) Marijuana;</para><para>(8) Mescaline;</para><para>(9) Peyote. Peyote shall mean all parts of the plant presently classified botanically as Lophophora williamsii Lemaire, whether growing or not, the seeds thereof, any extract from any part of such plant, and every compound, manufacture, salts, derivative, mixture, or preparation of such plant or its seeds or extracts;</para><para>(10) Psilocybin;</para><para>(11) Psilocyn;</para><para>(12) Tetrahydrocannabinols, including, but not limited to, synthetic equivalents of the substances contained in the plant or in the resinous extractives of cannabis, sp. or synthetic substances, derivatives, and their isomers with similar chemical structure and pharmacological activity such as the following: Delta 1 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol and their optical isomers, excluding dronabinol in a drug product approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration; Delta 6 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol and their optical isomers; and Delta 3,4 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol and its optical isomers. Since nomenclature of these substances is not internationally standardized, compounds of these structures shall be included regardless of the numerical designation of atomic positions covered. Tetrahydrocannabinols does not include cannabidiol contained in a drug product approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</para><para>(13) N-ethyl-3-piperidyl benzilate;</para><para>(14) N-methyl-3-piperidyl benzilate;</para><para>(15) Thiophene analog of phencyclidine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 1-(1-(2-thienyl)-cyclohexyl)-piperidine; 2-thienyl analog of phencyclidine; TPCP; and TCP;</para><para>(16) Hashish or concentrated cannabis;</para><para>(17) Parahexyl. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 3-Hexyl-1-hydroxy-7,8,9,10-tetrahydro-6,6,9-trimethyl-6H-dibenzo(b,d)pyran; and Synhexyl;</para><para>(18) Ethylamine analog of phencyclidine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: N-ethyl-1-phenylcyclohexylamine; (1-phenylcyclohexyl)ethylamine; N-(1-phenylcyclohexyl)ethylamine; cyclohexamine; and PCE;</para><para>(19) Pyrrolidine analog of phencyclidine. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: 1-(1-phenylcyclohexyl)-pyrrolidine; PCPy; and PHP;</para><para>(20) Alpha-ethyltryptamine. Some trade or other names: etryptamine; Monase; alpha-ethyl-1H-indole-3-ethanamine; 3-(2-aminobutyl) indole; alpha-ET; and AET;</para><para>(21) 2,5-dimethoxy-4-ethylamphet-amine; and DOET;</para><para>(22) 1-(1-(2-thienyl)cyclohexyl)pyrrolidine; and TCPy;</para><para>(23) Alpha-methyltryptamine, which is also known as AMT;</para><para>(24) Salvia divinorum or Salvinorin A. Salvia divinorum or Salvinorin A includes all parts of the plant presently classified botanically as Salvia divinorum, whether growing or not, the seeds thereof, any extract from any part of such plant, and every compound, manufacture, derivative, mixture, or preparation of such plant, its seeds, or its extracts, including salts, isomers, and salts of isomers whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation;</para><para>(25) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any quantity of synthetically produced cannabinoids as listed in subdivisions (A) through (L) of this subdivision, including their salts, isomers, salts of isomers, and nitrogen, oxygen, or sulfur-heterocyclic analogs, unless specifically excepted elsewhere in this section. Since nomenclature of these synthetically produced cannabinoids is not internationally standardized and may continually evolve, these structures or compounds of these structures shall be included under this subdivision, regardless of their specific numerical designation of atomic positions covered, so long as it can be determined through a recognized method of scientific testing or analysis that the substance contains properties that fit within one or more of the following categories:</para><para>(A) Tetrahydrocannabinols: Meaning tetrahydrocannabinols naturally contained in a plant of the genus cannabis (cannabis plant), as well as synthetic equivalents of the substances contained in the plant, or in the resinous extractives of cannabis, sp. and/or synthetic substances, derivatives, and their isomers with similar chemical structure and pharmacological activity such as the following: Delta 1 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol, and their optical isomers; Delta 6 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol, and their optical isomers; Delta 3,4 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol, and its optical isomers. This subdivision does not include cannabidiol contained in a drug product approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</para><para>(B) Naphthoylindoles: Any compound containing a 3-(1-naphthoyl)indole structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(C) Naphthylmethylindoles: Any compound containing a 1 H-indol-3-yl-(1-naphthyl)methane structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(D) Naphthoylpyrroles: Any compound containing a 3-(1-naphthoyl)pyrrole structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the pyrrole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(E) Naphthylideneindenes: Any compound containing a naphthylideneindene structure with substitution at the 3-position of the indene ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(F) Phenylacetylindoles: Any compound containing a 3-phenylacetylindole structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(G) Cyclohexylphenols: Any compound containing a 2-(3-hydroxycyclohexyl)phenol structure with substitution at the 5-position of the phenolic ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(H) Benzoylindoles: Any compound containing a 3-(benzoyl)indole structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl group, cyanoalkyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(I) Adamantoylindoles: Any compound containing a 3-adamantoylindole structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, cyanoalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(J) Tetramethylcyclopropanoylindoles: Any compound containing a 3-tetramethylcyclopropanoylindole structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, cyanoalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent;</para><para>(K) Indole carboxamides: Any compound containing a 1-indole-3-carboxamide structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, cyanoalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, substitution at the carboxamide group by an alkyl, methoxy, benzyl, propionaldehyde, adamantyl, 1-naphthyl, phenyl, aminooxoalkyl group, or quinolinyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent or to the adamantyl, 1-mapthyl, phenyl, aminooxoalkyl, benzyl, or propionaldehyde groups to any extent;</para><para>(L) Indole carboxylates: Any compound containing a 1-indole-3-carboxylate structure with substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring by an alkyl, haloalkyl, cyanoalkyl, alkenyl, halobenzyl, benzyl, cycloalkylmethyl, cycloalkylethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-piperidinyl)methyl, 2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl, 1-(N-methyl-2-pyrrolidinyl)methyl, 1-(N-methyl-3-morpholinyl)methyl, or tetrahydropyranylmethyl group, substitution at the carboxylate group by an alkyl, methoxy, benzyl, propionaldehyde, adamantyl, 1-naphthyl, phenyl, aminooxoalkyl group, or quinolinyl group, whether or not further substituted in or on any of the listed ring systems to any extent or to the adamantyl, 1-mapthyl, phenyl, aminooxoalkyl, benzyl, or propionaldehyde groups to any extent; and</para><para>(M) Any nonnaturally occurring substance, chemical compound, mixture, or preparation, not specifically listed elsewhere in these schedules and which is not approved for human consumption by the federal Food and Drug Administration, containing or constituting a cannabinoid receptor agonist as defined in section 28-401;</para><para>(26) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any quantity of a substituted phenethylamine as listed in subdivisions (A) through (C) of this subdivision, unless specifically excepted, listed in another schedule, or specifically named in this schedule, that is structurally derived from phenylethan-2-amine by substitution on the phenyl ring with a fused methylenedioxy ring, fused furan ring, or a fused tetrahydrofuran ring; by substitution with two alkoxy groups; by substitution with one alkoxy and either one fused furan, tetrahydrofuran, or tetrahydropyran ring system; or by substitution with two fused ring systems from any combination of the furan, tetrahydrofuran, or tetrahydropyran ring systems, whether or not the compound is further modified in any of the following ways:</para><para>(A) Substitution of the phenyl ring by any halo, hydroxyl, alkyl, trifluoromethyl, alkoxy, or alkylthio groups; (B) substitution at the 2-position by any alkyl groups; or (C) substitution at the 2-amino nitrogen atom with alkyl, dialkyl, benzyl, hydroxybenzyl or methoxybenzyl groups, and including, but not limited to:</para><para>(i) 2-(4-Chloro-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-C or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-chlorophenethylamine;</para><para>(ii) 2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-methylphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-D or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-methylphenethylamine;</para><para>(iii) 2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-ethylphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-E or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-ethylphenethylamine;</para><para>(iv) 2-(2,5-Dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-H or 2,5-Dimethoxyphenethylamine;</para><para>(v) 2-(4-lodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-I or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-iodophenethylamine;</para><para>(vi) 2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-nitro-phenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-N or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-nitrophenethylamine;</para><para>(vii) 2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-(n)-propylphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-P or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-propylphenethylamine;</para><para>(viii) 2-[4-(Ethylthio)-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl]ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-T-2 or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-ethylthiophenethylamine;</para><para>(ix) 2-[4-(Isopropylthio)-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl]ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-T-4 or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-isopropylthiophenethylamine;</para><para>(x) 2-(4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-B or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-bromophenethylamine;</para><para>(xi) 2-(2,5-dimethoxy-4-(methylthio)phenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-T or 4-methylthio-2,5-dimethoxyphenethylamine;</para><para>(xii) 1-(2,5-dimethoxy-4-iodophenyl)-propan-2-amine, which is also known as DOI or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-iodoamphetamine;</para><para>(xiii) 1-(4-Bromo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-2-aminopropane, which is also known as DOB or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-bromoamphetamine;</para><para>(xiv) 1-(4-chloro-2,5-dimethoxy-phenyl)propan-2-amine, which is also known as DOC or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-chloroamphetamine;</para><para>(xv) 2-(4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-N-[(2-methoxyphenyl)methyl]ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-B-NBOMe; 25B-NBOMe or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-bromo-N-(2-methoxybenzyl)phenethylamine;</para><para>(xvi) 2-(4-iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-N-[(2-methoxyphenyl)methyl]ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-I-NBOMe; 25I-NBOMe or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-iodo-N-(2-methoxybenzyl)phenethylamine;</para><para>(xvii) N-(2-Methoxybenzyl)-2-(3,4,5-trimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine, which is also known as Mescaline-NBOMe or 3,4,5-trimethoxy-N-(2-methoxybenzyl)phenethylamine;</para><para>(xviii) 2-(4-chloro-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)-N-[(2-methoxyphenyl)methyl]ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-C-NBOMe; or 25C-NBOMe or 2,5-Dimethoxy-4-chloro-N-(2-methoxybenzyl)phenethylamine;</para><para>(xix) 2-(7-Bromo-5-methoxy-2,3-dihydro-1-benzofuran-4-yl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2CB-5-hemiFLY;</para><para>(xx) 2-(8-bromo-2,3,6,7-tetrahydrofuro [2,3-f][1]benzofuran-4-yl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-B-FLY;</para><para>(xxi) 2-(10-Bromo-2,3,4,7,8,9-hexahydropyrano[2,3-g]chromen-5-yl)ethanamine, which is also known as 2C-B-butterFLY;</para><para>(xxii) N-(2-Methoxybenzyl)-1-(8-bromo-2,3,6,7- tetrahydrobenzo[1,2-b:4,5-b']difuran-4-yl)-2-aminoethane, which is also known as 2C-B-FLY-NBOMe;</para><para>(xxiii) 1-(4-Bromofuro[2,3-f][1]benzofuran-8-yl)propan-2-amine, which is also known as bromo-benzodifuranylisopropylamine or bromo-dragonFLY;</para><para>(xxiv) N-(2-Hydroxybenzyl)-4-iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenethylamine, which is also known as 2C-INBOH or 25I-NBOH;</para><para>(xxv) 5-(2-Aminopropyl)benzofuran, which is also known as 5-APB;</para><para>(xxvi) 6-(2-Aminopropyl)benzofuran, which is also known as 6-APB;</para><para>(xxvii) 5-(2-Aminopropyl)-2,3-dihydrobenzofuran, which is also known as 5-APDB;</para><para>(xxviii) 6-(2-Aminopropyl)-2,3-dihydrobenzofuran, which is also known as 6-APDB;</para><para>(xxix) 2,5-dimethoxy-amphetamine, which is also known as 2, 5-dimethoxy-a-methylphenethylamine; 2, 5-DMA;</para><para>(xxx) 2,5-dimethoxy-4-ethylamphetamine, which is also known as DOET;</para><para>(xxxi) 2,5-dimethoxy-4-(n)-propylthiophenethylamine, which is also known as 2C-T-7;</para><para>(xxxii) 5-methoxy-3,4-methylenedioxy-amphetamine;</para><para>(xxxiii) 4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxy-amphetamine, which is also known as 4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxy-amethylphenethylamine; DOM and STP;</para><para>(xxxiv) 3,4-methylenedioxy amphetamine, which is also known as MDA;</para><para>(xxxv) 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine, which is also known as MDMA;</para><para>(xxxvi) 3,4-methylenedioxy-N-ethylamphetamine, which is also known as N-ethyl-alpha-methyl-3,4(methylenedioxy)phenethylamine, MDE, MDEA;</para><para>(xxxvii) 3,4,5-trimethoxy amphetamine; and</para><para>(xxxviii) n-hydroxy-3,4-Methlenedioxyamphetamine, which is also known as N-hydroxyMDA;</para><para>(27) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any quantity of a substituted tryptamine unless specifically excepted, listed in another schedule, or specifically named in this schedule, that is structurally derived from 2-(1H-indol-3-yl)ethanamine, which is also known as tryptamine, by mono- or di-substitution of the amine nitrogen with alkyl or alkenyl groups or by inclusion of the amino nitrogen atom in a cyclic structure whether or not the compound is further substituted at the alpha position with an alkyl group or whether or not further substituted on the indole ring to any extent with any alkyl, alkoxy, halo, hydroxyl, or acetoxy groups, and including, but not limited to:</para><para>(A) 5-methoxy-N,N-diallyltryptamine, which is also known as 5-MeO-DALT;</para><para>(B) 4-acetoxy-N,N-dimethyltryptamine, which is also known as 4-AcO-DMT or OAcetylpsilocin;</para><para>(C) 4-hydroxy-N-methyl-N-ethyltryptamine, which is also known as 4-HO-MET;</para><para>(D) 4-hydroxy-N,N-diisopropyltryptamine, which is also known as 4-HO-DIPT;</para><para>(E) 5-methoxy-N-methyl-N-isopropyltryptamine, which is also known as 5-MeOMiPT;</para><para>(F) 5-Methoxy-N,N-Dimethyltryptamine, which is also known as 5-MeO-DMT;</para><para>(G) 5-methoxy-N,N-diisopropyltryptamine, which is also known as 5-MeO-DiPT;</para><para>(H) Diethyltryptamine, which is also known as N,N-Diethyltryptamine, DET; and</para><para>(I) Dimethyltryptamine, which is also known as DMT; and</para><para>(28)(A) Any substance containing any quantity of the following materials, compounds, mixtures, or structures:</para><para>(i) 3,4-methylenedioxymethcathinone, or bk-MDMA, or methylone;</para><para>(ii) 3,4-methylenedioxypyrovalerone, or MDPV;</para><para>(iii) 4-methylmethcathinone, or 4-MMC, or mephedrone;</para><para>(iv) 4-methoxymethcathinone, or bk-PMMA, or PMMC, or methedrone;</para><para>(v) Fluoromethcathinone, or FMC;</para><para>(vi) Naphthylpyrovalerone, or naphyrone; or</para><para>(vii) Beta-keto-N-methylbenzodioxolylpropylamine or bk-MBDB or butylone; or</para><para>(B) Unless listed in another schedule, any substance which contains any quantity of any material, compound, mixture, or structure, other than bupropion, that is structurally derived by any means from 2-aminopropan-1-one by substitution at the 1-position with either phenyl, naphthyl, or thiophene ring systems, whether or not the compound is further modified in any of the following ways:</para><para>(i) Substitution in the ring system to any extent with alkyl, alkoxy, alkylenedioxy, haloalkyl, hydroxyl, or halide substituents, whether or not further substituted in the ring system by one or more other univalent substituents;</para><para>(ii) Substitution at the 3-position with an acyclic alkyl substituent; or</para><para>(iii) Substitution at the 2-amino nitrogen atom with alkyl or dialkyl groups, or by inclusion of the 2-amino nitrogen atom in a cyclic structure.</para><para>(d) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a depressant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) Mecloqualone;</para><para>(2) Methaqualone; and</para><para>(3) Gamma-Hydroxybutyric Acid. Some other names include: GHB; Gamma-hydroxybutyrate; 4-Hydroxybutyrate; 4-Hydroxybutanoic Acid; Sodium Oxybate; and Sodium Oxybutyrate.</para><para>(e) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers:</para><para>(1) Fenethylline;</para><para>(2) N-ethylamphetamine;</para><para>(3) Aminorex; aminoxaphen; 2-amino-5-phenyl-2-oxazoline; or 4,5-dihydro-5-phenyl-2-oxazolamine;</para><para>(4) Cathinone; 2-amino-1-phenyl-1-propanone; alpha-aminopropiophenone; 2-aminopropiophenone; and norephedrone;</para><para>(5) Methcathinone, its salts, optical isomers, and salts of optical isomers. Some other names: 2-(methylamino)-propiophenone; alpha-(methylamino)propiophenone; 2-(methylamino)-1-phenylpropan-1-one; alpha-N-methylaminopropiophenone; methylcathinone; monomethylpropion; ephedrone; N-methylcathinone; AL-464; AL-422; AL-463; UR1432; and 4-MEC;</para><para>(6) (+/-)cis-4-methylaminorex; and (+/-)cis-4,5-dihydro-4-methyl-5-phenyl-2-oxazolamine;</para><para>(7) N,N-dimethylamphetamine; N,N-alpha-trimethyl-benzeneethanamine; and N,N-alpha-trimethylphenethylamine; and</para><para>(8) Benzylpiperazine, 1-benzylpiperazine.</para><para>(f) Any controlled substance analogue to the extent intended for human consumption.</para><para>Schedule II</para><para>(a) Any of the following substances except those narcotic drugs listed in other schedules whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin, independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by combination of extraction and chemical synthesis:</para><para>(1) Opium and opiate, and any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation of opium or opiate, excluding apomorphine, buprenorphine, thebaine-derived butorphanol, dextrorphan, nalbuphine, nalmefene, naloxone, and naltrexone and their salts, but including the following:</para><para>(A) Raw opium;</para><para>(B) Opium extracts;</para><para>(C) Opium fluid;</para><para>(D) Powdered opium;</para><para>(E) Granulated opium;</para><para>(F) Tincture of opium;</para><para>(G) Codeine;</para><para>(H) Ethylmorphine;</para><para>(I) Etorphine hydrochloride;</para><para>(J) Hydrocodone;</para><para>(K) Hydromorphone;</para><para>(L) Metopon;</para><para>(M) Morphine;</para><para>(N) Oxycodone;</para><para>(O) Oxymorphone;</para><para>(P) Oripavine;</para><para>(Q) Thebaine; and</para><para>(R) Dihydroetorphine;</para><para>(2) Any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation thereof which is chemically equivalent to or identical with any of the substances referred to in subdivision (1) of this subdivision, except that these substances shall not include the isoquinoline alkaloids of opium;</para><para>(3) Opium poppy and poppy straw;</para><para>(4) Coca leaves and any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation of coca leaves, and any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation thereof which is chemically equivalent to or identical with any of these substances, including cocaine or ecgonine and its salts, optical isomers, and salts of optical isomers, except that the substances shall not include decocainized coca leaves or extractions which do not contain cocaine or ecgonine; and</para><para>(5) Concentrate of poppy straw, the crude extract of poppy straw in either liquid, solid, or powder form which contains the phenanthrene alkaloids of the opium poppy.</para><para>(b) Unless specifically excepted or unless in another schedule any of the following opiates, including their isomers, esters, ethers, salts, and salts of their isomers, esters, and ethers whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers, and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation, dextrorphan excepted:</para><para>(1) Alphaprodine;</para><para>(2) Anileridine;</para><para>(3) Bezitramide;</para><para>(4) Diphenoxylate;</para><para>(5) Fentanyl;</para><para>(6) Isomethadone;</para><para>(7) Levomethorphan;</para><para>(8) Levorphanol;</para><para>(9) Metazocine;</para><para>(10) Methadone;</para><para>(11) Methadone-intermediate, 4-cyano-2-dimethylamino-4,4-diphenyl butane;</para><para>(12) Moramide-intermediate, 2-methyl-3-morpholino-1,1-diphenylpropane-carboxylic acid;</para><para>(13) Norfentanyl (N-phenyl-N-peperidin-4-yl) propionamide;</para><para>(14) Oliceridine;</para><para>(15) Pethidine or meperidine;</para><para>(16) Pethidine-Intermediate-A, 4-cyano-1-methyl-4-phenylpiperidine;</para><para>(17) Pethidine-Intermediate-B, ethyl-4-phenylpiperidine-4-carboxylate;</para><para>(18) Pethidine-Intermediate-C, 1-methyl-4-phenylpiperidine-4-carboxylic acid;</para><para>(19) Phenazocine;</para><para>(20) Piminodine;</para><para>(21) Racemethorphan;</para><para>(22) Racemorphan;</para><para>(23) Dihydrocodeine;</para><para>(24) Bulk Propoxyphene in nondosage forms;</para><para>(25) Sufentanil;</para><para>(26) Alfentanil;</para><para>(27) Levo-alphacetylmethadol which is also known as levo-alpha-acetylmethadol, levomethadyl acetate, and LAAM;</para><para>(28) Carfentanil;</para><para>(29) Remifentanil;</para><para>(30) Tapentadol; and</para><para>(31) Thiafentanil.</para><para>(c) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a potential for abuse associated with a stimulant effect on the central nervous system:</para><para>(1) Amphetamine, its salts, optical isomers, and salts of its optical isomers;</para><para>(2) Phenmetrazine and its salts;</para><para>(3) Methamphetamine, its salts, isomers, and salts of its isomers;</para><para>(4) Methylphenidate; and</para><para>(5) Lisdexamfetamine, its salts, isomers, and salts of its isomers.</para><para>(d) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a potential for abuse associated with a depressant effect on the central nervous system, including their salts, isomers, and salts of isomers whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designations:</para><para>(1) Amobarbital;</para><para>(2) Secobarbital;</para><para>(3) Pentobarbital;</para><para>(4) Phencyclidine; and</para><para>(5) Glutethimide.</para><para>(e) Hallucinogenic substances known as:</para><para>(1) Nabilone. Another name for nabilone: (+/-)-trans-3-(1,1-dimethylheptyl)- 6,6a,7,8,10,10a-Hexahydro-1-hydroxy-6,6-dimethyl-9H-dibenzo(b,d)pyran-9-one; and</para><para>(2) Dronabinol in an oral solution in a drug product approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration.</para><para>(f) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances:</para><para>(1) Immediate precursor to amphetamine and methamphetamine: Phenylacetone. Trade and other names shall include, but are not limited to: Phenyl-2-propanone; P2P; benzyl methyl ketone; and methyl benzyl ketone;</para><para>(2) Immediate precursors to phencyclidine, PCP:</para><para>(A) 1-phenylcyclohexylamine; or</para><para>(B) 1-piperidinocyclohexanecarbonitrile, PCC; or</para><para>(3) Immediate precursor to fentanyl; 4-anilino-N-phenethylpiperidine (ANPP).</para><para>Schedule III</para><para>(a) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a potential for abuse associated with a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including their salts, isomers, whether optical, position, or geometric, and salts of such isomers whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) Benzphetamine;</para><para>(2) Chlorphentermine;</para><para>(3) Clortermine; and</para><para>(4) Phendimetrazine.</para><para>(b) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a potential for abuse associated with a depressant effect on the central nervous system:</para><para>(1) Any substance which contains any quantity of a derivative of barbituric acid or any salt of a derivative of barbituric acid, except those substances which are specifically listed in other schedules of this section;</para><para>(2) Aprobarbital;</para><para>(3) Butabarbital;</para><para>(4) Butalbital;</para><para>(5) Butethal;</para><para>(6) Butobarbital;</para><para>(7) Chlorhexadol;</para><para>(8) Embutramide;</para><para>(9) Lysergic acid;</para><para>(10) Lysergic acid amide;</para><para>(11) Methyprylon;</para><para>(12) Perampanel;</para><para>(13) Secbutabarbital;</para><para>(14) Sulfondiethylmethane;</para><para>(15) Sulfonethylmethane;</para><para>(16) Sulfonmethane;</para><para>(17) Nalorphine;</para><para>(18) Talbutal;</para><para>(19) Thiamylal;</para><para>(20) Thiopental;</para><para>(21) Vinbarbital;</para><para>(22) Any compound, mixture, or preparation containing amobarbital, secobarbital, pentobarbital, or any salt thereof and one or more other active medicinal ingredients which are not listed in any schedule;</para><para>(23) Any suppository dosage form containing amobarbital, secobarbital, pentobarbital, or any salt of any of these drugs and approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration for marketing only as a suppository;</para><para>(24) Any drug product containing gamma-hydroxybutyric acid, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, for which an application is approved under section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, 21 U.S.C. 355, as such section existed on January 1, 2014;</para><para>(25) Ketamine, its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers. Some other names for ketamine: (+/-)-2-(2-chlorophenyl)-2-(methylamino)-cyclohexanone; and</para><para>(26) Tiletamine and zolazepam or any salt thereof. Trade or other names for a tiletamine-zolazepam combination product shall include, but are not limited to: telazol. Trade or other names for tiletamine shall include, but are not limited to: 2-(ethylamino)-2-(2-thienyl)-cyclohexanone. Trade or other names for zolazepam shall include, but are not limited to: 4-(2-fluorophenyl)-6,8-dihydro-1,3,8-trimethylpyrazolo-(3,4-e) (1,4)-diazepin-7(1H)-one, and flupyrazapon.</para><para>(c) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule:</para><para>(1) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing limited quantities of any of the following narcotic drugs, or any salts calculated as the free anhydrous base or alkaloid, in limited quantities as set forth below:</para><para>(A) Not more than one and eight-tenths grams of codeine per one hundred milliliters or not more than ninety milligrams per dosage unit, with an equal or greater quantity of an isoquinoline alkaloid of opium;</para><para>(B) Not more than one and eight-tenths grams of codeine per one hundred milliliters or not more than ninety milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts;</para><para>(C) Not more than one and eight-tenths grams of dihydrocodeine per one hundred milliliters or not more than ninety milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts;</para><para>(D) Not more than three hundred milligrams of ethylmorphine per one hundred milliliters or not more than fifteen milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts;</para><para>(E) Not more than five hundred milligrams of opium per one hundred milliliters or per one hundred grams, or not more than twenty-five milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts; and</para><para>(F) Not more than fifty milligrams of morphine per one hundred milliliters or per one hundred grams with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts; and</para><para>(2) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any of the following narcotic drug or its salts, as set forth below:</para><para>(A) Buprenorphine.</para><para>(d) Unless contained on the list of exempt anabolic steroids of the Drug Enforcement Administration of the United States Department of Justice as the list existed on January 31, 2021, any anabolic steroid, which shall include any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any quantity of the following substances, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers whenever the existence of such salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) 3-beta,17-dihydroxy-5a-androstane;</para><para>(2) 3-alpha,17-beta-dihydroxy-5a-androstane;</para><para>(3) 5-alpha-androstan-3,17-dione;</para><para>(4) 1-androstenediol (3-beta,17-beta-dihydroxy-5-alpha-androst-1-ene);</para><para>(5) 1-androstenediol (3-alpha,17-beta-dihydroxy-5-alpha-androst-1-ene);</para><para>(6) 4-androstenediol (3-beta,17-beta-dihydroxy-androst-5-ene);</para><para>(7) 5-androstenediol (3-beta,17-beta-dihydroxy-androst-5-ene);</para><para>(8) 1-androstenedione ([5-alpha]-androst-1-en-3,17-dione);</para><para>(9) 4-androstenedione (androst-4-en-3,17-dione);</para><para>(10) 5-androstenedione (androst-5-en-3,17-dione);</para><para>(11) Bolasterone (7-alpha,17-alpha-dimethyl-17-beta-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(12) Boldenone (17-beta-hydroxyandrost-1,4-diene-3-one);</para><para>(13) Boldione (androsta-1,4-diene-3,17-3-one);</para><para>(14) Calusterone (7-beta,17-alpha-dimethyl-17-beta-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(15) Clostebol (4-chloro-17-beta-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(16) Dehydrochloromethyltestosterone (4-chloro-17-beta-hydroxy-17-alpha-methyl-androst-1,4-dien-3-one);</para><para>(17) Desoxymethyltestosterone (17-alpha-methyl-5-alpha-androst-2-en-17-beta-ol) (a.k.a. 'madol');</para><para>(18) Delta-1-Dihydrotestosterone (a.k.a. '1-testosterone')(17-beta-hydroxy-5-alpha-androst-1-en-3-one);</para><para>(19) 4-Dihydrotestosterone (17-beta-hydroxy-androstan-3-one);</para><para>(20) Drostanolone (17-beta-hydroxy-2-alpha-methyl-5-alpha-androstan-3-one);</para><para>(21) Ethylestrenol (17-alpha-ethyl-17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-ene);</para><para>(22) Fluoxymesterone (9-fluoro-17-alpha-methyl-11-beta,17-beta-dihydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(23) Formebulone (formebolone); (2-formyl-17-alpha-methyl-11-alpha,17-beta-dihydroxyandrost-1,4-dien-3-one);</para><para>(24) Furazabol (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxyandrostano[2,3-c]-furazan);</para><para>(25) 13-beta-ethyl-17-beta-hydroxygon-4-en-3-one;</para><para>(26) 4-hydroxytestosterone (4,17-beta-dihydroxy-androst-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(27) 4-hydroxy-19-nortestosterone (4,17-beta-dihydroxy-estr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(28) Mestanolone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxy-5-androstan-3-one);</para><para>(29) Mesterolone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxy-5-androstan-3-one);</para><para>(30) Methandienone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxyandrost-1,4-dien-3-one);</para><para>(31) Methandriol (17-alpha-methyl-3-beta,17-beta-dihydroxyandrost-5-ene);</para><para>(32) Methasterone (2-alpha,17-alpha-dimethyl-5-alpha-androstan-17-beta-ol-3-one);</para><para>(33) Methenolone (1-methyl-17-beta-hydroxy-5-alpha-androst-1-en-3-one);</para><para>(34) 17-alpha-methyl-3-beta,17-beta-dihydroxy-5a-androstane;</para><para>(35) 17-alpha-methyl-3-alpha,17-beta-dihydroxy-5a-androstane;</para><para>(36) 17-alpha-methyl-3-beta,17-beta-dihydroxyandrost-4-ene;</para><para>(37) 17-alpha-methyl-4-hydroxynandrolone (17-alpha-methyl-4-hydroxy-17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(38) Methyldienolone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxyestra-4,9(10)-dien-3-one);</para><para>(39) Methyltrienolone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxyestra-4,9,11-trien-3-one);</para><para>(40) Methyltestosterone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(41) Mibolerone (7-alpha,17-alpha-dimethyl-17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(42) 17-alpha-methyl-delta-1-dihydrotestosterone (17-beta-hydroxy-17-alpha-methyl-5-alpha-androst-1-en-3-one) (a.k.a. '17-alpha-methyl-1-testosterone');</para><para>(43) Nandrolone (17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(44) 19-nor-4-androstenediol (3-beta, 17-beta-dihydroxyestr-4-ene);</para><para>(45) 19-nor-4-androstenediol (3-alpha, 17-beta-dihydroxyestr-4-ene);</para><para>(46) 19-nor-5-androstenediol (3-beta, 17-beta-dihydroxyestr-5-ene);</para><para>(47) 19-nor-5-androstenediol (3-alpha, 17-beta-dihydroxyestr-5-ene);</para><para>(48) 19-nor-4,9(10)-androstadienedione (estra-4,9(10)-diene-3,17-dione);</para><para>(49) 19-nor-4-androstenedione (estr-4-en-3,17-dione);</para><para>(50) 19-nor-5-androstenedione (estr-5-en-3,17-dione);</para><para>(51) Norbolethone (13-beta, 17-alpha-diethyl-17-beta-hydroxygon-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(52) Norclostebol (4-chloro-17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(53) Norethandrolone (17-alpha-ethyl-17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(54) Normethandrolone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(55) Oxandrolone (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxy-2-oxa-[5-alpha]-androstan-3-one);</para><para>(56) Oxymesterone (17-alpha-methyl-4,17-beta-dihydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(57) Oxymetholone (17-alpha-methyl-2-hydroxymethylene-17-beta-hydroxy-[5-alpha]-androstan-3-one);</para><para>(58) Prostanozol (17-beta-hydroxy-5-alpha-androstano[3,2-c]pyrazole);</para><para>(59) Stanozolol (17-alpha-methyl-17-beta-hydroxy-[5-alpha]-androst-2-eno[3,2-c]-pyrazole);</para><para>(60) Stenbolone (17-beta-hydroxy-2-methyl-[5-alpha]-androst-1-en-3-one);</para><para>(61) Testolactone (13-hydroxy-3-oxo-13,17-secoandrosta-1,4-dien-17-oic acid lactone);</para><para>(62) Testosterone (17-beta-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</para><para>(63) Tetrahydrogestrinone (13-beta, 17-alpha-diethyl-17-beta-hydroxygon-4,9,11-trien-3-one);</para><para>(64) Trenbolone (17-beta-hydroxyestr-4,9,11-trien-3-one);</para><para>(65) [3,2-c]-furazan-5 alpha-androstane-17 beta-ol;</para><para>(66) [3,2-c]pyrazole-androst-4-en-17 beta-ol;</para><para>(67) 17 alpha-methyl-androst-ene-3,17 beta-diol;</para><para>(68) 17 alpha-methyl-androsta-1,4-diene-3,17 beta-diol;</para><para>(69) 17 alpha-methyl-androstan-3-hydroxyimine-17 beta-ol;</para><para>(70) 17 beta-hydroxy-androstano[2,3-d]isoxazole;</para><para>(71) 17 beta-hydroxy-androstano[3,2-c]isoxazole;</para><para>(72) 18a-homo-3-hydroxy-estra-2,5(10)-dien-17-one;</para><para>(73) 2 alpha, 3 alpha-epithio-17 alpha-methyl-5 alpha-androstan-17 beta-ol;</para><para>(74) 4-chloro-17 alpha-methyl-17 beta-hydroxy-androst-4-en-3-one;</para><para>(75) 4-chloro-17 alpha-methyl-17 beta-hydroxy-androst-4-en-3,11-dione;</para><para>(76) 4-chloro-17 alpha-methyl-androst-4-ene-3 beta,17 beta-diol;</para><para>(77) 4-chloro-17 alpha-methyl-androsta-1,4,diene-3,17 beta-diol;</para><para>(78) 4-hydroxy-androst-4-ene-3,17-dione;</para><para>(79) 5 alpha-Androstan-3,6,17-trione;</para><para>(80) 6-bromo-androst-1,4-diene-3,17-dione;</para><para>(81) 6-bromo-androstan-3,17-dione;</para><para>(82) 6 alpha-methyl-androst-4-ene-3,17-dione;</para><para>(83) Delta 1-dihydrotestosterone;</para><para>(84) Estra-4,9,11-triene-3,17-dione; and</para><para>(85) Any salt, ester, or ether of a drug or substance described or listed in this subdivision if the salt, ester, or ether promotes muscle growth.</para><para>(e) Hallucinogenic substances known as:</para><para>(1) Dronabinol, synthetic, in sesame oil and encapsulated in a soft gelatin capsule in a drug product approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration. Some other names for dronabinol are (6aR-trans)-6a,7,8,10a-tetrahydro-6,6,9-trimethyl-3-pentyl-6H-dibenzo (b,d)pyran-1-ol or (-)-delta-9-(trans)-tetrahydrocannabinol.</para><para>Schedule IV</para><para>(a) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances, including their salts, isomers, and salts of isomers whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) Barbital;</para><para>(2) Chloral betaine;</para><para>(3) Chloral hydrate;</para><para>(4) Chlordiazepoxide, but not including librax (chlordiazepoxide hydrochloride and clindinium bromide) or menrium (chlordiazepoxide and water soluble esterified estrogens);</para><para>(5) Clonazepam;</para><para>(6) Clorazepate;</para><para>(7) Diazepam;</para><para>(8) Ethchlorvynol;</para><para>(9) Ethinamate;</para><para>(10) Flurazepam;</para><para>(11) Mebutamate;</para><para>(12) Meprobamate;</para><para>(13) Methohexital;</para><para>(14) Methylphenobarbital;</para><para>(15) Oxazepam;</para><para>(16) Paraldehyde;</para><para>(17) Petrichloral;</para><para>(18) Phenobarbital;</para><para>(19) Prazepam;</para><para>(20) Alprazolam;</para><para>(21) Bromazepam;</para><para>(22) Camazepam;</para><para>(23) Clobazam;</para><para>(24) Clotiazepam;</para><para>(25) Cloxazolam;</para><para>(26) Delorazepam;</para><para>(27) Estazolam;</para><para>(28) Ethyl loflazepate;</para><para>(29) Fludiazepam;</para><para>(30) Flunitrazepam;</para><para>(31) Halazepam;</para><para>(32) Haloxazolam;</para><para>(33) Ketazolam;</para><para>(34) Loprazolam;</para><para>(35) Lorazepam;</para><para>(36) Lormetazepam;</para><para>(37) Medazepam;</para><para>(38) Nimetazepam;</para><para>(39) Nitrazepam;</para><para>(40) Nordiazepam;</para><para>(41) Oxazolam;</para><para>(42) Pinazepam;</para><para>(43) Temazepam;</para><para>(44) Tetrazepam;</para><para>(45) Triazolam;</para><para>(46) Midazolam;</para><para>(47) Quazepam;</para><para>(48) Zolpidem;</para><para>(49) Dichloralphenazone;</para><para>(50) Zaleplon;</para><para>(51) Zopiclone;</para><para>(52) Fospropofol;</para><para>(53) Alfaxalone;</para><para>(54) Suvorexant;</para><para>(55) Carisoprodol;</para><para>(56) Brexanolone; 3 alpha-hydroxy-5 alpha-pregnan-20-one;</para><para>(57) Lemborexant;</para><para>(58) Solriamfetol; 2-amino-3-phenylpropyl carbamate; and</para><para>(59) Remimazolam.</para><para>(b) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substance, including its salts, isomers, whether optical, position, or geometric, and salts of such isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible: Fenfluramine.</para><para>(c) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including their salts, isomers, whether optical, position, or geometric, and salts of such isomers whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</para><para>(1) Diethylpropion;</para><para>(2) Phentermine;</para><para>(3) Pemoline, including organometallic complexes and chelates thereof;</para><para>(4) Mazindol;</para><para>(5) Pipradrol;</para><para>(6) SPA, ((-)-1-dimethylamino- 1,2-diphenylethane);</para><para>(7) Cathine. Another name for cathine is ((+)-norpseudoephedrine);</para><para>(8) Fencamfamin;</para><para>(9) Fenproporex;</para><para>(10) Mefenorex;</para><para>(11) Modafinil; and</para><para>(12) Sibutramine.</para><para>(d) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following narcotic drugs, or their salts or isomers calculated as the free anhydrous base or alkaloid, in limited quantities as set forth below:</para><para>(1) Propoxyphene in manufactured dosage forms;</para><para>(2) Not more than one milligram of difenoxin and not less than twenty-five micrograms of atropine sulfate per dosage unit; and</para><para>(3) 2-[(dimethylamino)methyl]-1-(3-methoxyphenyl)cyclohexanol, its salts, optical and geometric isomers, and salts of these isomers to include: Tramadol.</para><para>(e) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substance, including its salts:</para><para>(1) Pentazocine; and</para><para>(2) Butorphanol (including its optical isomers).</para><para>(f) Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances, including its salts, isomers, and salts of such isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible: Lorcaserin.</para><para>(g)(1) Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substance, including its salts, optical isomers, and salts of such optical isomers: Ephedrine.</para><para>(2) The following drug products containing ephedrine, its salts, optical isomers, and salts of such optical isomers, are excepted from subdivision (g)(1) of Schedule IV if they (A) are stored behind a counter, in an area not accessible to customers, or in a locked case so that a customer needs assistance from an employee to access the drug product; (B) are sold by a person, eighteen years of age or older, in the course of his or her employment to a customer eighteen years of age or older with the following restrictions: No customer shall be allowed to purchase, receive, or otherwise acquire more than three and six-tenths grams of ephedrine base during a twenty-four-hour period; no customer shall purchase, receive, or otherwise acquire more than nine grams of ephedrine base during a thirty-day period; and the customer shall display a valid driver's or operator's license, a Nebraska state identification card, a military identification card, an alien registration card, or a passport as proof of identification; (C) are labeled and marketed in a manner consistent with the pertinent OTC Tentative Final or Final Monograph; (D) are manufactured and distributed for legitimate medicinal use in a manner that reduces or eliminates the likelihood of abuse; and (E) are not marketed, advertised, or represented in any manner for the indication of stimulation, mental alertness, euphoria, ecstasy, a buzz or high, heightened sexual performance, or increased muscle mass:</para><para>(i) Primatene Tablets; and</para><para>(ii) Bronkaid Dual Action Caplets.</para><para>Schedule V</para><para>(a) Any compound, mixture, or preparation containing any of the following limited quantities of narcotic drugs or salts calculated as the free anhydrous base or alkaloid, which shall include one or more nonnarcotic active medicinal ingredients in sufficient proportion to confer upon the compound, mixture, or preparation valuable medicinal qualities other than those possessed by the narcotic drug alone:</para><para>(1) Not more than two hundred milligrams of codeine per one hundred milliliters or per one hundred grams;</para><para>(2) Not more than one hundred milligrams of dihydrocodeine per one hundred milliliters or per one hundred grams;</para><para>(3) Not more than one hundred milligrams of ethylmorphine per one hundred milliliters or per one hundred grams;</para><para>(4) Not more than two and five-tenths milligrams of diphenoxylate and not less than twenty-five micrograms of atropine sulfate per dosage unit;</para><para>(5) Not more than one hundred milligrams of opium per one hundred milliliters or per one hundred grams; and</para><para>(6) Not more than five-tenths milligram of difenoxin and not less than twenty-five micrograms of atropine sulfate per dosage unit.</para><para>(b) Unless specifically exempted or excluded or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers: Pyrovalerone.</para><para>(c) Unless specifically exempted or excluded or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a depressant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers:</para><para>(1) Ezogabine (N-(2-amino-4-(4-fluorobenzylamino)-phenyl)-carbamic acid ethyl ester);</para><para>(2) Lacosamide ((R)-2-acetoamido-N-benzyl-3-methoxy-propionamide);</para><para>(3) Pregabalin ((S)-3-(aminomethyl)-5-methylhexanoic acid);</para><para>(4) Brivaracetam ((2S)-2-[(4R)-2-oxo-4-propylpyrrolidin-1-yl] butanamide) (also referred to as BRV; UCB-34714; Briviact), including its salts;</para><para>(5) Cenobamate; and</para><para>(6) Lasmiditan.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 748, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 696, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 323, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 406, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1160, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 571, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1213, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 113, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 500, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 245, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB902, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB123, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB151, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB792, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB19, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB670, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB298, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB390, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB487, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB906, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB236, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>An information containing the descriptive language from this section is not deficient if it contains an incorrect trade name description, since the use of said language is unnecessary to constitute a proper charge and is mere surplusage. State v. Spiegel, 239 Neb. 233, 474 N.W.2d 873 (1991).</para><para>Under subsections (c)(10) and (c)(15) of this section and section 28-404, marijuana is a Schedule I controlled substance, and thus is a "drug." State v. Finnegan, 232 Neb. 75, 439 N.W.2d 496 (1989).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>