<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id86">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id88" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-414.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-414.01</statuteno><catchline>Controlled substance; Schedule
III, IV, or V; prescription; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section
or when administered directly by a practitioner to an ultimate user, a controlled
substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section 28-405 shall not be
dispensed without a written, oral, or electronic medical order. Such medical
order is valid for six months after the date of issuance. Original prescription
information for any controlled substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V
of section 28-405 may be transferred between pharmacies for purposes of refill
dispensing pursuant to section 38-2871.</para>
<para>(2) A prescription
for controlled substances listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section 28-405
must contain the following information prior to being filled by a pharmacist
or dispensing practitioner: (a) Patient's name and address, (b) name of the
drug, device, or biological, (c) strength of the drug or biological, (d) dosage
form of the drug or biological, if applicable, (e) quantity of the drug, device,
or biological prescribed, (f) directions for use, (g) date of issuance, (h)
number of refills, not to exceed five refills within six months after the
date of issuance, (i) prescribing practitioner's name and address, and (j)
Drug Enforcement Administration number of the prescribing practitioner. If
the prescription is a written paper prescription, the paper prescription must
contain the prescribing practitioner's manual signature. If the prescription
is an electronic prescription, the electronic prescription must contain all
of the elements in subdivisions (a) through (j) of this subsection, must be
digitally signed, and must be transmitted to and received by the pharmacy
electronically to meet all of the requirements of 21 C.F.R. 1311, as the regulation
existed on January 1, 2014, pertaining to electronic prescribing of controlled
substances.</para><para>(3) A controlled substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section
28-405 may be dispensed pursuant to a facsimile of a written, signed paper
prescription. The facsimile of a written, signed paper prescription shall
serve as the original written prescription for purposes of this subsection
and shall be maintained in accordance with subsection (2) of section 28-414.03.</para>
<para>(4) A prescription
for a controlled substance listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section 28-405
may be partially filled if (a) each partial filling is recorded in the same
manner as a refilling, (b) the total quantity dispensed in all partial fillings
does not exceed the total quantity prescribed, and (c) each partial filling
is dispensed within six months after the prescription was issued.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>