<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-325"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">28-325</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Abortion; declaration
of purpose.</catchline><para>The Legislature hereby finds and declares:</para>
<para>(1) That the following provisions were motivated by the legislative
intrusion of the United States Supreme Court by virtue of its decision removing
the protection afforded the unborn. Sections 28-325 to 28-345 are in no way
to be construed as legislatively encouraging abortions at any stage of unborn
human development, but are rather an expression of the will of the people
of the State of Nebraska and the members of the Legislature to provide protection
for the life of the unborn child whenever possible;</para>
<para>(2) That the members of the Legislature expressly deplore
the destruction of the unborn human lives which has and will occur in Nebraska
as a consequence of the United States Supreme Court's decision on abortion
of January 22, 1973;</para>
<para>(3) That it is in the interest of the people of the State
of Nebraska that every precaution be taken to insure the protection of every
viable unborn child being aborted, and every precaution be taken to provide
life-supportive procedures to insure the unborn child its continued life after
its abortion;</para>
<para>(4) That currently this state is prevented from providing
adequate legal remedies to protect the life, health, and welfare of pregnant
women and unborn human life;</para>
<para>(5) That it is in the interest of the people of the State
of Nebraska to maintain accurate statistical data to aid in providing proper
maternal health regulations and education;</para>
<para>(6) That the
existing standard of care for preabortion screening and counseling is not
always adequate to protect the health needs of women;</para><para>(7) That clarifying the
minimum standard of care for preabortion screening and counseling in statute
is a practical means of protecting the well-being of women and may better
ensure that abortion doctors are sufficiently aware of each patient's risk
profile so they may give each patient a well-informed medical opinion regarding
her unique case; and</para><para>(8) That providing right to redress against nonphysicians who perform
illegal abortions or encourage self-abortions is an important means of protecting
women's health.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 23, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB594, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>