<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id979"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id00" statutenumber="28-322"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>28-322</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Sexual abuse of an inmate or parolee; terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">For purposes of sections 28-322 to 28-322.03:</para><para id="id00">(1) Inmate or parolee means any individual confined in a facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services or a city or county correctional or jail facility or under parole supervision; and</para><para id="id00">(2) Person means (a) an individual employed by the Department of Correctional Services, including any individual working in central administration of the department, any individual working under contract with the department, and any individual, other than an inmate's spouse, to whom the department has authorized or delegated control over an inmate or an inmate's activities, (b) an individual employed by a city or county correctional or jail facility, including any individual working in central administration of the city or county correctional or jail facility, any individual working under contract with the city or county correctional or jail facility, and any individual, other than an inmate's spouse, to whom the city or county correctional or jail facility has authorized or delegated control over an inmate or an inmate's activities, and (c) an individual employed by the Office of Probation Administration who performs official duties within any facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services or a city or county correctional or jail facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 511, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 155, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 943, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 28. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The control requirement in this section applies only to those nonemployees or noncontractors to whom the Department of Correctional Services has authorized or delegated control over an inmate or an inmate's activities. State v. Loyuk, 289 Neb. 967, 857 N.W.2d 833 (2015).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>