<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id187"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-347"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>28-347</statuteno><catchline>Dismemberment abortion; unlawful; when; medical emergency; Board of Medicine and Surgery; hearing; findings admissible at trial; persons not liable.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to purposely perform or attempt to perform a dismemberment abortion and thereby kill an unborn child unless a dismemberment abortion is necessary due to a medical emergency as defined in subdivision (4) of section 28-3,103.</para><para>(2) A person accused in any proceeding of unlawful conduct under subsection (1) of this section may seek a hearing before the Board of Medicine and Surgery on whether the performance of a dismemberment abortion was necessary due to a medical emergency as defined in subdivision (4) of section 28-3,103. The board's findings are admissible on that issue at any trial in which such unlawful conduct is alleged. Upon a motion of the person accused, the court shall delay the beginning of the trial for not more than thirty days to permit such a hearing to take place.</para><para>(3) No woman upon whom an abortion is performed or attempted to be performed shall be liable for performing or attempting to perform a dismemberment abortion. No nurse, secretary, receptionist, or other employee or agent who is not a physician, but who acts at the direction of a physician, shall be liable for performing or attempting to perform a dismemberment abortion. No pharmacist or other individual who is not a physician, but who fills a prescription or provides instruments or materials used in an abortion at the direction of or to a physician, shall be liable for performing or attempting to perform a dismemberment abortion.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB814, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>