<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id26">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id28" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="28-459"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>28-459</statuteno><catchline>Methamphetamine precursor; seller;
duties; waiver authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2012, each seller shall, before
completing a sale of a methamphetamine precursor, electronically submit required
information to the exchange, if the exchange is available to sellers. Required
information shall include, but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The name,
age, and address of the person purchasing, receiving, or otherwise acquiring
the methamphetamine precursor;</para><para>(b) The name of the product and quantity
of product purchased;</para><para>(c) The date and time of the purchase;</para><para>(d) The name or initials
of the seller who sold the product; and</para><para>(e) The type of identification presented
by the customer, the governmental entity that issued the identification, and
the number on the identification.</para><para>(2) If a seller experiences mechanical or
electronic failure of the electronic logging equipment on the sales end of
the transaction or a failure of the exchange and is unable to comply with
subsection (1) of this section, the seller shall maintain a written log or
an alternative electronic recordkeeping mechanism or may refrain from selling
any methamphetamine precursor until such time as the seller is able to comply
with subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) The Attorney General may grant a waiver
exempting a seller from compliance with subsection (1) of this section upon
a showing of good cause by the seller that he or she is otherwise unable to
submit log information by electronic means, including, but not limited to,
any financial, technological, or other reason which would place an undue burden
on the seller, as established by the Attorney General.</para>
<para>(4) Whenever
the exchange generates a stop-sale alert, the seller shall not complete the
sale unless the seller has a reasonable fear of imminent bodily harm if he
or she does not complete the sale. The exchange shall contain an override
function to the stop-sale alert for the seller to use in a situation in which
a reasonable fear of imminent bodily harm is present.</para><para>(5) This section does
not apply if a lawful prescription for the methamphetamine precursor is presented
to a pharmacist licensed under the Uniform Credentialing Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB20, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>