<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-522"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-522</statuteno><catchline>Criminal trespass; affirmative defenses.</catchline><para>It is an affirmative defense to prosecution under sections 28-520 and 28-521 that:</para><para>(1) A building or occupied structure involved in an offense under section 28-520 was abandoned; or</para><para>(2) The premises were at the time open to members of the public and the actor complied with all lawful conditions imposed on access to or remaining in the premises; or</para><para>(3) The actor reasonably believed that the owner of the premises or other person empowered to license access thereto would have licensed him to enter or remain; or</para><para>(4) The actor was in the process of navigating or attempting to navigate with a nonpowered vessel any stream or river in this state and found it necessary to portage or otherwise transport the vessel around any fence or obstructions in such stream or river.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 121. </para></source><annotation>
<para>A valid license from any owner or other person empowered to license access to a property is sufficient to show that a defendant reasonably believed that he or she was licensed to be on the premises. A defendant need not show that every owner licensed his or her presence. State v. McCave, 282 Neb. 500, 805 N.W.2d 290 (2011).</para>
<para>Criminal trespass is not a lesser-included offense of burglary. State v. Miller, 215 Neb. 145, 337 N.W.2d 424 (1983).</para><para>Whether at the time of taking an automobile, the defendant, had the intent of permanently depriving the owner of its use or whether he intended to return it is a question of fact. State v. King, 204 Neb. 47, 281 N.W.2d 226 (1979).</para><para>An ownership interest is not an affirmative defense to the charge of criminal trespass. State v. Anderson, 14 Neb. App. 253, 706 N.W.2d 564 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>