<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-603"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">28-603</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Forgery, second
degree; penalty; aggregation
allowed; when.</catchline><para>(1) Whoever, with intent
to deceive or harm, falsely makes, completes, endorses, alters, or utters
any written instrument which is or purports to be, or which is calculated
to become or to represent if completed, a written instrument which does or
may evidence, create, transfer, terminate, or otherwise affect a legal right,
interest, obligation, or status, commits forgery in the second degree.</para>
<para>(2) Forgery in the second degree is a Class III felony when
the face value, or purported face value, or the amount of any proceeds wrongfully
procured or intended to be procured by the use of such instrument, is one
thousand dollars or more.</para>
<para>(3) Forgery in the second degree is a Class IV felony when
the face value, or purported
face value, or the amount
of any proceeds wrongfully procured or intended to be
procured by the use of such instrument, exceeds three hundred
dollars but is less than one thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(4) Forgery in the second degree is a Class I misdemeanor
when the face value, or purported
face value, or the amount
of any proceeds wrongfully procured or intended to be
procured by the use of such instrument, is three hundred dollars
or less.</para>
<para>(5) For the
purpose of determining the class of penalty for forgery in the second degree,
the face values, or purported face values, or the amounts of any proceeds
wrongfully procured or intended to be procured by the use of more than one
such instrument, may be aggregated in the indictment or information if such
instruments were part of the same scheme or course of conduct which took place
within a sixty-day period and within one county. Such values or amounts shall
not be aggregated into more than one offense.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 17, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB155, &#167; 13.</para></source><annotation><para>To sustain a conviction for forgery, it is not sufficient for the State to show that a signature is not that of the party whose name is used, but it must also affirmatively be shown that the signing was made without his or her authority. State v. Castor, 262 Neb. 423, 632 N.W.2d 298 (2001).</para><para>The elements of the crime of uttering a forged instrument are (1) the offering of a forged instrument with the representation by words or acts that it is true or genuine, (2) the knowledge that same is false, forged, or counterfeited, and (3) the intent to defraud. State v. Tate, 222 Neb. 586, 385 N.W.2d 456 (1986).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>