<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-328"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-328</statuteno><catchline>Partial-birth abortion; prohibition; violation; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) No partial-birth abortion shall be performed in this state, unless such procedure is necessary to save the life of the mother whose life is endangered by a physical disorder, physical illness, or physical injury, including a life-endangering physical condition caused by or arising from the pregnancy itself.</para><para>(2) The intentional and knowing performance of an unlawful partial-birth abortion in violation of subsection (1) of this section is a Class III felony.</para><para>(3) No woman upon whom an unlawful partial-birth abortion is performed shall be prosecuted under this section or for conspiracy to violate this section.</para><para>(4) The intentional and knowing performance of an unlawful partial-birth abortion shall result in the automatic suspension and revocation of an attending physician's license to practice medicine in Nebraska by the Division of Public Health pursuant to sections 38-177 to 38-1,102.</para><para>(5) Upon the filing of criminal charges under this section by the Attorney General or a county attorney, the Attorney General shall also file a petition to suspend and revoke the attending physician's license to practice medicine pursuant to section 38-186. A hearing on such administrative petition shall be set in accordance with section 38-188. At such hearing, the attending physician shall have the opportunity to present evidence that the physician's conduct was necessary to save the life of a mother whose life was endangered by a physical disorder, physical illness, or physical injury, including a life-endangering physical condition caused by or arising from the pregnancy itself. A defendant against whom criminal charges are brought under this section may bring a motion to delay the beginning of the trial until after the entry of an order by the Director of Public Health pursuant to section 38-196. The findings of the director as to whether the attending physician's conduct was necessary to save the life of a mother whose life was endangered by a physical disorder, physical illness, or physical injury, including a life-endangering physical condition caused by or arising from the pregnancy itself, shall be admissible in the criminal proceedings brought pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 23, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1118.</para></source><annotation><para>Section declared unconstitutional. Stenberg v. Carhart, 530 U.S. 914 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>