<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-904</statuteno><catchline>Resisting arrest; penalty; affirmative defense.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the offense of resisting arrest if, while intentionally preventing or attempting to prevent a peace officer, acting under color of his or her official authority, from effecting an arrest of the actor or another, he or she:</para><para>(a) Uses or threatens to use physical force or violence against the peace officer or another; or</para><para>(b) Uses any other means which creates a substantial risk of causing physical injury to the peace officer or another; or</para><para>(c) Employs means requiring substantial force to overcome resistance to effecting the arrest.</para><para>(2) It is an affirmative defense to prosecution under this section if the peace officer involved was out of uniform and did not identify himself or herself as a peace officer by showing his or her credentials to the person whose arrest is attempted.</para><para>(3) Resisting arrest is (a) a Class I misdemeanor for the first such offense and (b) a Class IIIA felony for any second or subsequent such offense.</para><para>(4) Resisting arrest through the use of a deadly or dangerous weapon is a Class IIIA felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 189; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 465, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 364, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>In prosecutions for assaulting a peace officer, obstructing a peace officer, or resisting arrest, a trial court must instruct the jury on the issue of self-defense when there is any evidence adduced which raises a legally cognizable claim that the peace officer used unreasonable force in making the arrest. State v. Yeutter, 252 Neb. 857, 566 N.W.2d 387 (1997).</para><para>This is a serious offense for which a jury trial is constitutionally required unless knowingly and intelligently waived by the defendant. State v. Bishop, 224 Neb. 522, 399 N.W.2d 271 (1987).</para><para>It is an affirmative defense to prosecution under this section if the peace officer involved was out of uniform and did not identify himself as a peace officer by showing his credentials to the person whose arrest is attempted. State v. Daniels, 220 Neb. 480, 370 N.W.2d 179 (1985).</para><para>Where there was evidence that the arrester communicated his intention to arrest the arrestee, the arrestee understood the intention, and the arrester had the apparent ability to control the arrestee, a jury instruction on resisting arrest was not necessary. State v. White, 209 Neb. 218, 306 N.W.2d 906 (1981).</para><para>Because neither "substantial" nor "substantial force" were defined in either this section or section 28-109, and definitions of such were also absent in the relevant Nebraska case law, the district court's jury instruction, which gave a partial and incomplete dictionary definition, misstated the issue and had a tendency to confuse the jury. The jury reached a guilty verdict 10 minutes after receiving the erroneous supplemental instruction, and thus, the verdict rendered was not surely unattributable to the error and not harmless; the conviction was reversed and the cause remanded for a new trial. State v. Gaudreault, 30 Neb. App. 501, 969 N.W.2d 695 (2022).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>