<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id85" statutenumber="28-638"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-638</statuteno><catchline id="id88">Criminal impersonation; penalty; restitution.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the crime of criminal impersonation if he or she:</para><para>(a) Pretends to be a representative of some person or organization and does an act in his or her fictitious capacity with the intent to gain a pecuniary benefit for himself, herself, or another and to deceive or harm another;</para><para>(b) Carries on any profession, business, or any other occupation without a license, certificate, or other authorization required by law;</para><para>(c) Knowingly provides false personal identifying information or a false personal identification document to a court or a law enforcement officer; or</para><para>(d) Knowingly provides false personal identifying information or a false personal identification document to an employer for the purpose of obtaining employment.</para><para>(2)(a) Criminal impersonation, as described in subdivisions (1)(a) and (1)(b) of this section, is a Class III felony if the credit, money, goods, services, or other thing of value that was gained or was attempted to be gained was five thousand dollars or more. Any second or subsequent conviction under this subdivision is a Class II felony.</para><para>(b) Criminal impersonation, as described in subdivisions (1)(a) and (1)(b) of this section, is a Class IV felony if the credit, money, goods, services, or other thing of value that was gained or was attempted to be gained was one thousand five hundred dollars or more but less than five thousand dollars. Any second or subsequent conviction under this subdivision is a Class III felony.</para><para>(c) Criminal impersonation, as described in subdivisions (1)(a) and (1)(b) of this section, is a Class I misdemeanor if the credit, money, goods, services, or other thing of value that was gained or was attempted to be gained was five hundred dollars or more but less than one thousand five hundred dollars. Any second or subsequent conviction under this subdivision is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(d) Criminal impersonation, as described in subdivisions (1)(a) and (1)(b) of this section, is a Class II misdemeanor if no credit, money, goods, services, or other thing of value was gained or was attempted to be gained, or if the credit, money, goods, services, or other thing of value that was gained or was attempted to be gained was less than five hundred dollars. Any second conviction under this subdivision is a Class I misdemeanor, and any third or subsequent conviction under this subdivision is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(e) Criminal impersonation, as described in subdivision (1)(c) of this section, is a Class IV felony. Any second conviction under this subdivision is a Class III felony, and any third or subsequent conviction under this subdivision is a Class II felony.</para><para>(f) Criminal impersonation, as described in subdivision (1)(d) of this section, is a Class II misdemeanor. Any second or subsequent conviction under this subdivision is a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(g) A person found guilty of violating this section may, in addition to the penalties under this subsection, be ordered to make restitution pursuant to sections 29-2280 to 29-2289.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 276, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 28-608; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB155, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 41. </para></source><annotation><para>"Person" in the context of the term "personal identifying information" for purposes of this section means a real person and not a fictitious person. State v. Covey, 290 Neb. 257, 859 N.W.2d 558 (2015).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>