<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id21">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id23" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-306"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>28-306</statuteno><catchline id="id26">Motor vehicle
homicide; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person who causes the
death of another unintentionally while engaged in the operation of a motor
vehicle in violation of the law of the State of Nebraska or in violation of
any city or village ordinance commits motor vehicle homicide.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section,
motor vehicle homicide is a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(3)(a) If the proximate cause of the death of another is the
operation of a motor vehicle in violation of section 60-6,213 or 60-6,214,
motor vehicle homicide is a Class IIIA felony.</para>
<para>(b) If the proximate cause of the death of another is the
operation of a motor vehicle in violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197.06,
motor vehicle homicide is a Class III felony. The court shall, as part of
the judgment of conviction, order the person not to drive any motor vehicle
for any purpose for a period of at least one year and not more than fifteen
years and shall order that the operator's license of such person be revoked
for the same period.</para>
<para>(c) If the proximate cause of the death of another is the
operation of a motor vehicle in violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197.06,
motor vehicle homicide is a Class II felony if the defendant has a prior conviction
for a violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197.06, under a city or village
ordinance enacted in conformance with section 60-6,196, or under a law of
another state if, at the time of the conviction under the law of such other
state, the offense for which the defendant was convicted would have been a
violation of section 60-6,196. The court shall, as part of the judgment of
conviction, order the person not to drive any motor vehicle for any purpose
for a period of fifteen years and shall order that the operator's license
of such person be revoked for the same period.</para>
<para>(d) An order of the court described in subdivision (b) or
(c) of this subsection shall be administered upon sentencing, upon final judgment
of any appeal or review, or upon the date that any probation is revoked.</para>
<para>(4) The crime
punishable under this section shall be treated as a separate and distinct
offense from any other offense arising out of acts alleged to have been committed
while the person was in violation of this section.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 1, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 291, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 364, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 925, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Operator's license,</emphasis> assessment of points and revocation, see sections 60-496 to 60-497.01, 60-498 to 60-498.04, 60-499, and 60-4,182 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Motor vehicle homicide is not a lesser-included offense of manslaughter under current statutes. State v. Wright, 261 Neb. 277, 622 N.W.2d 676 (2001).</para><para>One who is convicted of manslaughter under section 28-305 for a killing involving the use of a motor vehicle must be sentenced in accordance with that section rather than this section, the motor vehicle homicide statute. State v. Burnett, 254 Neb. 771, 579 N.W.2d 513 (1998).</para><para>In order to convict a defendant of felony motor vehicle homicide under this section, the State must prove the defendant's driving in violation of section 39-669.07 proximately caused the death of another. State v. Batts, 233 Neb. 776, 448 N.W.2d 136 (1989) (pursuant to Laws 1993, LB 370, section 293, language from section 39-669.07 was placed in section 60-6,196).</para><para>In order to convict a defendant under this section, the State must prove that the accused's intoxication was the proximate cause of the accident and resulting death. State v. Ring, 233 Neb. 720, 447 N.W.2d 908 (1989) (pursuant to Laws 1993, LB 370, section 293, language from section 39-669.07 was placed in section 60-6,196).</para><para>Motor vehicle homicide is a lesser-included offense of manslaughter. State v. Roth, 222 Neb. 119, 382 N.W.2d 348 (1986).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
