<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-723"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-723</statuteno><catchline>Subject of report; request to amend, expunge, or remove information; denied; hearing; decision; appeal.</catchline><para>At any time subsequent to the completion of the department's investigation, the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect may request the department to amend, expunge identifying information from, or remove the record of the report from the central register of child protection cases maintained pursuant to section 28-718. If the department refuses to do so or does not act within thirty days, the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect shall have the right to a fair hearing within the department to determine whether the record of the report of child abuse or neglect should be amended, expunged, or removed on the grounds that it is inaccurate or that it is being maintained in a manner inconsistent with the Child Protection Act. Such fair hearing shall be held within a reasonable time after the subject's request and at a reasonable place and hour. In such hearings, the burden of proving the accuracy and consistency of the record shall be on the department. A juvenile court finding of child abuse or child neglect shall be presumptive evidence that the report was not unfounded. The hearing shall be conducted by the head of the department or his or her designated agent, who is hereby authorized and empowered to order the amendment, expunction, or removal of the record to make it accurate or consistent with the requirements of the act. The decision shall be made in writing, at the close of the hearing, or within thirty days thereof, and shall state the reasons upon which it is based. Decisions of the department may be appealed under the provisions of the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 522, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 15.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The Department of Health and Human Services Regulation and Licensure must prove the accuracy and consistency of a central registry report of child abuse or neglect by a preponderance of the evidence in a hearing to expunge, amend, or remove a report under this section. Benitez v. Rasmussen, 261 Neb. 806, 626 N.W.2d 209 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>