<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<sectno id="id41" opdate="October 15, 2010">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id42" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-3,107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-3,107</statuteno><catchline>Report to Department of Health and
Human Services; contents; department; issue public report; failure to file
report; late fee; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any physician who performs or induces
or attempts to perform or induce an abortion shall report to the Department
of Health and Human Services, on a schedule and in accordance with forms and
rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department:</para>
<para>(a) If a determination
of probable postfertilization age was made, the probable postfertilization
age determined and the method and basis of the determination;</para>
<para>(b) If a determination
of probable postfertilization age was not made, the basis of the determination
that a medical emergency existed;</para><para>(c) If the probable postfertilization age
was determined to be twenty or more weeks, the basis of the determination
that the pregnant woman had a condition which so complicated her medical condition
as to necessitate the abortion of her pregnancy to avert her death or to avert
serious risk of substantial and irreversible physical impairment of a major
bodily function, or the basis of the determination that it was necessary to
preserve the life of an unborn child; and</para><para>(d) The method used for the abortion and,
in the case of an abortion performed when the probable postfertilization age
was determined to be twenty or more weeks, whether the method of abortion
used was one that, in reasonable medical judgment, provided the best opportunity
for the unborn child to survive or, if such a method was not used, the basis
of the determination that termination of the pregnancy in that manner would
pose a greater risk either of the death of the pregnant woman or of the substantial
and irreversible physical impairment of a major bodily function of the woman
than would other available methods.</para><para>(2) By June 30 of each year, the department
shall issue a public report providing statistics for the previous calendar
year compiled from all of the reports covering that year submitted in accordance
with this section for each of the items listed in subsection (1) of this section.
Each such report shall also provide the statistics for all previous calendar
years during which this section was in effect, adjusted to reflect any additional
information from late or corrected reports. The department shall take care
to ensure that none of the information included in the public reports could
reasonably lead to the identification of any pregnant woman upon whom an abortion
was performed.</para><para>(3) Any physician who fails to submit a report by the end of thirty
days following the due date shall be subject to a late fee of five hundred
dollars for each additional thirty-day period or portion of a thirty-day period
the report is overdue. Any physician required to report in accordance with
the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act who has not submitted a report,
or has submitted only an incomplete report, more than one year following the
due date, may, in an action brought in the manner in which actions are brought
to enforce the Uniform Credentialing Act pursuant to section 38-1,139, be
directed by a court of competent jurisdiction to submit a complete report
within a time period stated by court order or be subject to civil contempt.
Failure by any physician to conform to any requirement of this section, other
than late filing of a report, constitutes unprofessional conduct pursuant
to section 38-2021. Failure by any physician to submit a complete report in
accordance with a court order constitutes unprofessional conduct pursuant
to section 38-2021. Intentional or reckless falsification of any report required
under this section is a Class V misdemeanor.</para><para>(4) Within ninety days
after October 15, 2010, the department shall adopt and promulgate rules and
regulations to assist in compliance with this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1103, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>