<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-327.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">28-327.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Department of
Health and Human Services; printed materials; duties; availability; Internet web site information.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall cause
to be published the following easily comprehensible printed materials:</para>
<para>(a) Geographically indexed materials designed to inform the
woman of public and private agencies and services available to assist a woman
through pregnancy, upon childbirth, and while the child is dependent, including
adoption agencies and agencies and services for prevention of unintended pregnancies,
which materials shall include a comprehensive list of the agencies available,
a description of the services they offer, and a description of the manner,
including telephone numbers and addresses in which such agencies may be contacted
or printed materials including a toll-free, twenty-four-hour-a-day telephone
number which may be called to orally obtain such a list and description of
agencies in the locality of the caller and of the services they offer;</para>
<para>(b) Materials designed to inform the woman of the probable
anatomical and physiological characteristics of the unborn child at two-week
gestational increments from the time when a woman can be known to be pregnant
to full term, including pictures or drawings representing the development
of unborn children at the two-week gestational increments, and any relevant
information on the possibility of the unborn child's survival. Any such pictures
or drawings shall contain the dimensions of the unborn child and shall be
realistic and appropriate for the stage of pregnancy depicted. The materials
shall be objective, nonjudgmental, and designed to convey only accurate scientific
information about the unborn child at the various gestational ages. The materials
shall also contain objective information describing the methods of abortion
procedures commonly employed, the medical risks commonly associated with each
such procedure, the possible detrimental psychological effects of abortion,
the medical risks commonly associated with abortion, and the medical risks
commonly associated with carrying a child to term; and</para>
<para>(c) A comprehensive list of health care providers, facilities,
and clinics that offer to have ultrasounds performed by a person at least
as qualified as a registered nurse licensed under the Uniform Credentialing
Act, including and specifying those that offer to perform such ultrasounds
free of charge. The list shall be arranged geographically and shall include
the name, address, hours of operation, and telephone number of each entity.</para>
<para>(2) The printed materials
shall be printed in a typeface large enough to be clearly legible.</para>
<para>(3) The printed materials
required under this section shall be available from the department upon the
request by any person, facility, or hospital for an amount equal to the cost
incurred by the department to publish the materials.</para>
<para>(4) The Department
of Health and Human Services shall make available on its Internet web site
a printable publication of geographically indexed materials designed to inform
the woman of public and private agencies with services available to assist
a woman with mental health concerns, following a risk factor evaluation. Such
services shall include, but not be limited to, outpatient and crisis intervention
services and crisis hotlines. The materials shall include a comprehensive
list of the agencies available, a description of the services offered, and
a description of the manner in which such agencies may be contacted, including
addresses and telephone numbers of such agencies, as well as a toll-free,
twenty-four-hour-a-day telephone number to be provided by the department which
may be called to orally obtain the names of the agencies and the services
they provide in the locality of the woman. The department shall update the
publication as necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 110, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB675, &#167;  3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB594, &#167; 12.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>