<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-439"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-439</statuteno><catchline>Drug paraphernalia, defined; enumerated.</catchline><para>As used in sections 28-101, 28-431, and 28-439 to 28-444, unless the context otherwise requires, drug paraphernalia shall mean all equipment, products, and materials of any kind which are used, intended for use, or designed for use, in manufacturing, injecting, ingesting, inhaling, or otherwise introducing into the human body a controlled substance in violation of sections 28-101, 28-431, and 28-439 to 28-444 or the Uniform Controlled Substances Act. It shall include, but not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(1) Diluents and adulterants, such as quinine hydrochloride, mannitol, mannite, dextrose, and lactose, used, intended for use, or designed for use in cutting controlled substances;</para><para>(2) Separation gins and sifters used, intended for use, or designed for use in removing twigs and seeds from, or in otherwise cleaning or refining, marijuana;</para><para>(3) Hypodermic syringes, needles, and other objects used, intended for use, and designed for use in parenterally injecting controlled substances into the human body; and</para><para>(4) Objects used, intended for use, or designed for use in ingesting, inhaling, or otherwise introducing marijuana, cocaine, hashish, or hashish oil into the human body, which shall include but not be limited to the following:</para><para>(a) Metal, wooden, acrylic, glass, stone, plastic, or ceramic pipes with or without screens, permanent screens, hashish heads, or punctured metal bowls;</para><para>(b) Water pipes;</para><para>(c) Carburetion tubes and devices;</para><para>(d) Smoking and carburetion masks;</para><para>(e) Roach clips, meaning objects used to hold burning material, such as a marijuana cigarette, which has become too small or too short to be held in the hand;</para><para>(f) Miniature cocaine spoons, and cocaine vials;</para><para>(g) Chamber pipes;</para><para>(h) Carburetor pipes;</para><para>(i) Electric pipes;</para><para>(j) Air-driven pipes;</para><para>(k) Chillums;</para><para>(l) Bongs; and</para><para>(m) Ice pipes or chillers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 991, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Neither fourth amendment rights nor privacy rights are implicated in "drug paraphernalia" statutes, and thus, strict scrutiny standard of review is inapplicable to constitutional challenge. Casbah, Inc. v. Thone, 651 F.2d 551 (8th Cir. 1981).</para><para>Use of term "designed" does not refer to physical attributes of object but to intent of person charged with violation, and thus does not render statute unconstitutionally vague. List of items exemplary of drug paraphernalia is not vague and overbroad on ground that it includes numerous innocent items, where no item is drug paraphernalia absent requisite intent to use it with controlled substances. Casbah, Inc. v. Thone, 651 F.2d 551 (8th Cir. 1981).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>