<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno opdate="January 1, 2009">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-410</statuteno><catchline>Records of registrants; inventory; violation; penalty; storage.</catchline><para>(1) Each registrant manufacturing, distributing, or dispensing controlled substances in Schedule I, II, III, IV, or V of section 28-405 shall keep and maintain a complete and accurate record of all stocks of such controlled substances on hand. Such records shall be maintained for five years.</para><para>(2) Commencing January 1, 2009, each registrant manufacturing, distributing, storing, or dispensing such controlled substances shall prepare an annual inventory of each controlled substance in his or her possession. Such inventory shall (a) be taken within two years after the previous biennial inventory date but in no event later than December 31, 2009, and each year thereafter be taken within one year after the previous annual inventory date, (b) contain such information as shall be required by the Board of Pharmacy, (c) be copied and such copy forwarded to the department within thirty days after completion, (d) be maintained at the location listed on the registration for a period of five years, (e) contain the name, address, and Drug Enforcement Administration number of the registrant, the date and time of day the inventory was completed, and the signature of the person responsible for taking the inventory, (f) list the exact count or measure of all controlled substances listed in Schedules I, II, III, IV, and V of section 28-405, and (g) be maintained in permanent, read-only format separating the inventory for controlled substances listed in Schedules I and II of section 28-405 from the inventory for controlled substances listed in Schedules III, IV, and V of section 28-405. A registrant whose inventory fails to comply with this subsection shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) This section shall not apply to practitioners who prescribe or administer, as a part of their practice, controlled substances listed in Schedule II, III, IV, or V of section 28-405 unless such practitioner regularly engages in dispensing any such drug or drugs to his or her patients.</para><para>(4) Controlled substances shall be stored in accordance with the following:</para><para>(a) All controlled substances listed in Schedule I of section 28-405 must be stored in a locked cabinet; and</para><para>(b) All controlled substances listed in Schedule II, III, IV, or V of section 28-405 must be stored in a locked cabinet or distributed throughout the inventory of noncontrolled substances in a manner which will obstruct theft or diversion of the controlled substances.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 550, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB902, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
