<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id53">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id55" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-712.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-712.01</statuteno><catchline>Alternative response demonstration
projects; Review, Evaluate, and Decide Team; duties; department; duties; Inspector
General's review.</catchline><para>(1)
This section applies to alternative response demonstration projects designated
under section 28-712.</para>
<para>(2) The Review,
Evaluate, and Decide Team shall convene to review intakes pursuant to the
department's rules, regulations, and policies, to evaluate the information,
and to determine assignment for alternative response or traditional response.
The team shall utilize consistent criteria to review the severity of the allegation
of child abuse or neglect, access to the perpetrator, vulnerability of the
child, family history including previous reports, parental cooperation, parental
or caretaker protective factors, and other information as deemed necessary.
At the conclusion of the review, the intake shall be assigned to either traditional
response or alternative response. Decisions of the team shall be made by consensus.
If the team cannot come to consensus, the intake shall be assigned for a traditional
response.</para><para>(3) In the case of an alternative response, the department shall
complete a comprehensive assessment. The department shall transfer the case
being given alternative response to traditional response if the department
determines that a child is unsafe. Upon completion of the comprehensive assessment,
if it is determined that the child is safe, participation in services offered
to the family receiving an alternative response is voluntary, the case shall
not be transferred to traditional response based upon the family's failure
to enroll or participate in such services, and the subject of the report shall
not be entered into the central registry of child protection cases maintained
pursuant to section 28-718.</para><para>(4) The department shall, by the next working day after receipt
of a report of child abuse and neglect, enter into the tracking system of
child protection cases maintained pursuant to section 28-715 all reports of
child abuse or neglect received under this section that are opened for alternative
response and any action taken.</para><para>(5) The department shall make available
to the appropriate investigating law enforcement agency and the county attorney
a copy of all reports relative to a case of suspected child abuse or neglect.
Aggregate, nonidentifying reports of child abuse or neglect receiving an alternative
response shall be made available quarterly to requesting agencies outside
the department. Such alternative response data shall include, but not be limited
to, the nature of the initial child abuse or neglect report, the age of the
child or children, the nature of services offered, the location of the cases,
the number of cases per month, and the number of alternative response cases
that were transferred to traditional response. No other agency or individual
except the office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare, the Public
Counsel, law enforcement agency personnel, and county attorneys shall be provided
specific, identifying reports of child abuse or neglect being given alternative
response. The office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare shall
have access to all reports relative to cases of suspected child abuse or neglect
subject to traditional response and those subject to alternative response.
The department and the office shall develop procedures allowing for the Inspector
General's review of cases subject to alternative response. The Inspector General
shall include in the report pursuant to section 43-4331 a summary of all cases
reviewed pursuant to this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>