<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id61">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id63" statutenumber="28-713"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-713</statuteno><catchline id="id66">Reports of child
abuse or neglect; law enforcement agency; department; duties.</catchline>
<para>Unless an intake is assigned to alternative
response, upon the receipt of a call reporting child abuse and
neglect as required by section 28-711:</para>
<para>(1) It is the duty of the law enforcement agency to investigate
the report, to take immediate steps to protect the child, and to institute
legal proceedings if appropriate. In situations of alleged out-of-home child
abuse or neglect if the person or persons to be notified have not already
been notified and the person to be notified is not the subject of the report
of child abuse or neglect, the law enforcement agency shall immediately notify
the person or persons having custody of each child who has allegedly been
abused or neglected that such report of alleged child abuse or neglect has
been made and shall provide such person or persons with information of the
nature of the alleged child abuse or neglect. The law enforcement agency may
request assistance from the department during the investigation and shall,
by the next working day, notify either the hotline or the department of receipt
of the report, including whether or not an investigation is being undertaken
by the law enforcement agency. A copy of all reports, whether or not an investigation
is being undertaken, shall be provided to the department;</para>
<para>(2) In situations of alleged out-of-home child abuse or neglect
if the person or persons to be notified have not already been notified and
the person to be notified is not the subject of the report of child abuse
or neglect, the department shall immediately notify the person or persons
having custody of each child who has allegedly been abused or neglected that
such report of alleged child abuse or neglect has been made and shall provide
such person or persons with information of the nature of the alleged child
abuse or neglect and any other information that the department deems necessary.
The department shall investigate for the purpose of assessing each report
of child abuse or neglect to determine the risk of harm to the child involved.
The department shall also provide such social services as are necessary and
appropriate under the circumstances to protect and assist the child and to
preserve the family;</para>
<para>(3) The department may make a request for further assistance
from the appropriate law enforcement agency or take such legal action as may
be appropriate under the circumstances;</para>
<para>(4) The department shall, by the next working day after receiving
a report of child abuse or neglect under subdivision (1) of this section,
make a written report or a summary on forms provided by the department to
the proper law enforcement agency in the county and enter in the tracking
system of child protection cases maintained pursuant to section 28-715 all
reports of child abuse or neglect opened for investigation and any action
taken; and</para>
<para>(5) The department shall, upon request, make available to
the appropriate investigating law enforcement agency and the county attorney
a copy of all reports relative to a case of suspected child abuse or neglect.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 152; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 522, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 463, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 119, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>