
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id637"><amendatorysection statutenumber="28-907.01" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-907.01</statuteno><catchline>Swatting; prohibited; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the offense of swatting if such person:</para><para>(a) Knowingly makes, causes to be made, or directs a false or misleading report of criminal activity or a need for emergency medical services or assistance from firefighters;</para><para>(b) Such report is made to a law enforcement agency, public safety answering point, or any other emergency response organization;</para><para>(c) The person knows or reasonably should know the report is false or misleading; and</para><para>(d) The report results in the dispatch of law enforcement, firefighters, or emergency response personnel.</para><para>(2) An offense under this section may be committed by any means of communication, including, but not limited to, direct communication, electronic communication, communication through a third party, or the use of automated or digital systems.</para><para>(3)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, a violation of this section is a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(b) A violation of this section is a Class II felony if the violation proximately:</para><para>(i) Results in serious bodily injury to any person; or</para><para>(ii) Causes a law enforcement officer to deploy or threaten to deploy deadly force.</para><para>(c) A violation of this section is a Class IB felony if the violation proximately results in the death of any person, including any law enforcement or emergency response personnel.</para><para>(4) Upon conviction for a violation of this section, the court shall, in addition to any other punishment imposed, order the defendant to make restitution, in accordance with sections 29-2280 to 29-2289, for all reasonable costs incurred by any victim of the offense and by any government entity as a result of the violation. Such expenses include, but are not limited to, law enforcement, firefighting, and emergency response personnel costs, tactical or specialized unit deployment, medical treatment, and property damage.</para><para>(5) A violation of this section may be prosecuted in the county:</para><para>(a) In which the defendant made the false report;</para><para>(b) In which the recipient of the false report is located;</para><para>(c) Where the recipient responded to the false report; or</para><para>(d) Where the harm or risk of harm caused by the violation occurred.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Law enforcement agency has the same meaning as in section 81-1401; and</para><para>(b) Public safety answering point has the same meaning as in section 86-1052.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB935, &#167; 24. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>