<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id707"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments " statutenumber="28-713.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>28-713.02</statuteno><catchline>Non-court-involved cases; right of parent; caregiver authority; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) In all non-court-involved cases in which a child lives temporarily with a kin caregiver or a relative caregiver until reunification can be safely achieved:</para><para>(a) A parent shall have the right to have his or her child returned to such parent's home upon demand unless the child is seriously endangered by the child's surroundings and removal is necessary for the child's protection; and</para><para>(b) The kin caregiver or the relative caregiver shall have temporary parental authority to exercise powers regarding the care, custody, and property of the child except (i) the power to consent to marriage and adoption of the child and (ii) for other limitations placed on the delegation of parental authority to the kin caregiver or the relative caregiver by the parent.</para><para>(2) If a child is seriously endangered and removal is necessary, the department shall inform the parent that he or she may be referred for a court-involved case or for a petition to be filed pursuant to subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247.</para><para>(3) The department may reimburse a kin caregiver or a relative caregiver for facilitating services for the child and shall notify such caregiver if such caregiver is eligible for the child-only Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program established in 42 U.S.C. 601 et seq., and any other public benefit for which such caregiver may be eligible, and shall assist such caregiver in applying for such program or benefit.</para><para>(4) In all non-court-involved cases, the department shall provide a written notice of rights to any parent, and, if applicable, to any kin caregiver or relative caregiver, that complies with due process and includes notice (a) of the specific factual basis of the department's involvement, (b) of the possibility that a petition under section 43-247 could be filed in the future if it is determined that the safety of the child is not or cannot be assured, and (c) that the participation of the parent, kin caregiver, or relative caregiver in receiving prevention services could be relevant evidence presented in any future proceedings.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to affect the otherwise existing rights of a child or parent who is involved in a non-court-involved case.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1061, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>