<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-311.08"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>28-311.08</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Unlawful intrusion;
penalty; court; duties; registration
under Sex Offender Registration Act; statute of limitations.</catchline>
<para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly intrude
upon any other person without his or her consent or knowledge in a place of
solitude or seclusion.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Intrude means either the:</para>
<para>(i) Viewing of another
person in a state of undress as it is occurring; or</para><para>(ii) Recording by
video, photographic, digital, or other electronic
means of another person in a state of undress; and</para>
<para>(b) Place of solitude or seclusion means a place where a person
would intend to be in a state of undress and have a reasonable expectation
of privacy, including, but not limited to, any facility, public or private,
used as a restroom, tanning booth, locker room, shower room, fitting room,
or dressing room.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Violation of this section involving an intrusion as defined in subdivision
(2)(a)(i) of this section is a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(b) Violation
of this section involving an intrusion as defined in subdivision (2)(a)(ii)
of this section is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(c) Violation of this section is a Class
III felony if video or an image from the intrusion is distributed to another
person or otherwise made public in any manner which would enable it to be
viewed by another person.</para><para>(4) As part of sentencing following a conviction for a violation
of this section, the court shall make a finding as to the ages of the defendant
and the victim at the time the offense occurred. If the defendant is found
to have been nineteen years of age or older and the victim is found to have
been less than eighteen years of age at such time, then the defendant shall
be required to register under the Sex Offender Registration Act.</para>
<para>(5) No person
shall be prosecuted for unlawful intrusion pursuant to subdivision (3)(b)
or (c) of this section unless the indictment for such offense is found by
a grand jury or a complaint filed before a magistrate within three years after
the later of:</para><para>(a) The commission of the crime;</para><para>(b) Law enforcement's or a victim's receipt
of actual or constructive notice of either the existence of a video or other
electronic recording of the unlawful intrusion or the distribution of images,
video, or other electronic recording of the unlawful intrusion; or</para>
<para>(c) The youngest
victim of the intrusion reaching the age of twenty-one years.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 908, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB61, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 29-4001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
