<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-457"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-457</statuteno><catchline>Methamphetamine; prohibited acts; violation; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Bodily injury has the same meaning as in section 28-109;</para><para>(b) Chemical substance means a substance intended to be used as an immediate precursor or reagent in the manufacture of methamphetamine or any other chemical intended to be used in the manufacture of methamphetamine. Intent for purposes of this subdivision may be demonstrated by the substance's use, quantity, manner of storage, or proximity to other precursors or manufacturing equipment;</para><para>(c) Child means a person under the age of nineteen years;</para><para>(d) Methamphetamine means methamphetamine, its salts, optical isomers, and salts of its isomers;</para><para>(e) Paraphernalia means all equipment, products, and materials of any kind which are used, intended for use, or designed for use in manufacturing, injecting, ingesting, inhaling, or otherwise introducing methamphetamine into the human body;</para><para>(f) Prescription has the same meaning as in section 28-401;</para><para>(g) Serious bodily injury has the same meaning as in section 28-109; and</para><para>(h) Vulnerable adult has the same meaning as in section 28-371.</para><para>(2) Any person who knowingly or intentionally causes or permits a child or vulnerable adult to inhale or have contact with methamphetamine, a chemical substance, or paraphernalia is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. For any second or subsequent conviction under this subsection, any person so offending is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para><para>(3) Any person who knowingly or intentionally causes or permits a child or vulnerable adult to ingest methamphetamine, a chemical substance, or paraphernalia is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. For any second or subsequent conviction under this subsection, any person so offending shall be guilty of a Class IIIA felony.</para><para>(4) Any child or vulnerable adult who resides with a person violating subsection (2) or (3) of this section shall be taken into protective custody as provided in the Adult Protective Services Act or the Nebraska Juvenile Code.</para><para>(5) Any person who violates subsection (2) or (3) of this section and a child or vulnerable adult actually suffers serious bodily injury by ingestion of, inhalation of, or contact with methamphetamine, a chemical substance, or paraphernalia is guilty of a Class IIIA felony unless the ingestion, inhalation, or contact results in the death of the child or vulnerable adult, in which case the person is guilty of a Class IB felony.</para><para>(6) It is an affirmative defense to a violation of this section that the chemical substance was provided by lawful prescription for the child or vulnerable adult and that it was administered to the child or vulnerable adult in accordance with the prescription instructions provided with the chemical substance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 43, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Adult Protective Services Act,</emphasis> see section 28-348.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> see section 43-2,129.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>