<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id5" statutenumber="28-311.08"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-311.08</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Unlawful intrusion; photograph, film, or record image or video of intimate area; distribute or make public; penalty; court; duties; registration under Sex Offender Registration Act; statute of limitations.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly intrude upon any other person without his or her consent in a place of solitude or seclusion. Violation of this subsection is a Class I misdemeanor. A second or subsequent violation of this subsection is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly and intentionally photograph, film, or otherwise record an image or video of the intimate area of any other person without his or her knowledge and consent when his or her intimate area would not be generally visible to the public regardless of whether such other person is located in a public or private place. Violation of this subsection is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(3) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly and intentionally distribute or otherwise make public an image or video of another person recorded in violation of subsection (2) of this section without that person's consent. A first or second violation of this subsection is a Class IIA felony. A third or subsequent violation of this subsection is a Class II felony.</para><para>(4) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly and intentionally distribute or otherwise make public an image or video of another person's intimate area or of another person engaged in sexually explicit conduct (a) if the other person had a reasonable expectation that the image would remain private, (b) knowing the other person did not consent to distributing or making public the image or video, and (c) if distributing or making public the image or video serves no legitimate purpose. Violation of this subsection is a Class I misdemeanor. A second or subsequent violation of this subsection is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(5) It shall be unlawful for any person to threaten to distribute or otherwise make public an image or video of another person's intimate area or of another person engaged in sexually explicit conduct with the intent to intimidate, threaten, or harass any person. Violation of this subsection is a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(6) As part of sentencing following a conviction for a violation of subsection (1), (2), or (3) of this section, the court shall make a finding as to the ages of the defendant and the victim at the time the offense occurred. If the defendant is found to have been nineteen years of age or older and the victim is found to have been less than eighteen years of age at such time, then the defendant shall be required to register under the Sex Offender Registration Act.</para><para>(7) No person shall be prosecuted under this section unless the indictment for such offense is found by a grand jury or a complaint filed before a magistrate within three years after the later of:</para><para>(a) The commission of the crime;</para><para>(b) Law enforcement's or a victim's receipt of actual or constructive notice of either the existence of a video or other electronic recording made in violation of this section or the distribution of images, video, or other electronic recording made in violation of this section; or</para><para>(c) The youngest victim of a violation of this section reaching the age of twenty-one years.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Intimate area means the naked or undergarment-clad genitalia, pubic area, buttocks, or female breast of an individual;</para><para>(b) Intrude means either:</para><para>(i) Viewing another person in a state of undress as it is occurring; or</para><para>(ii) Recording another person in a state of undress by video, photographic, digital, or other electronic means; and</para><para>(c) Place of solitude or seclusion means a place where a person would intend to be in a state of undress and have a reasonable expectation of privacy, including, but not limited to, any facility, public or private, used as a restroom, tanning booth, locker room, shower room, fitting room, or dressing room.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 908, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB61, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB998, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB630, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 29-4001.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>