<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-513"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>28-513</statuteno><catchline>Theft by extortion.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits theft if he or she obtains property, money, or other thing of value of another by threatening to:</para><para>(a) Inflict bodily injury on anyone or commit any other criminal offense;</para><para>(b) Accuse anyone of a criminal offense;</para><para>(c) Expose any secret tending to subject any person to hatred, contempt or ridicule, or to impair his or her credit or business repute;</para><para>(d) Take or withhold action as an official, or cause an official to take or withhold action;</para><para>(e) Bring about or continue a strike, boycott, or other collective unofficial action, if the property, money, or other thing of value is not demanded or received for the benefit of the group in whose interest the actor purports to act;</para><para>(f) Testify or provide information or withhold testimony or information with respect to another's legal claim or defense; or</para><para>(g) Distribute or otherwise make public an image or video of a person's intimate area or of a person engaged in sexually explicit conduct without that person's consent.</para><para>(2) It is an affirmative defense to prosecution based on subdivision (1)(b), (1)(c), or (1)(d) of this section that the property, money, or other thing of value obtained by threat of accusation, exposure, lawsuit, or other invocation of official action was honestly claimed as restitution or indemnification for harm done in the circumstances to which such accusation, exposure, lawsuit, or other official action relates, or as compensation for property or lawful services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB630, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>