<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id547"><amendatorysection statutenumber="28-322.05" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>28-322.05</statuteno><catchline>Sexual abuse of a detainee; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Detainee means an individual who has been:</para><para>(i) Arrested by a person;</para><para>(ii) Detained by a person, regardless of whether the detainee has been arrested or charged; or</para><para>(iii) Placed into the custody of a person, regardless of whether the detainee has been arrested or charged;</para><para>(b) Law enforcement agency means an agency or department of this state or of any political subdivision of this state which is responsible for the prevention and detection of crime; the enforcement of the penal, traffic, or highway laws of this state or any political subdivision of this state; and the enforcement of arrest warrants. Law enforcement agency includes a police department, an office of the town marshal, an office of the county sheriff, the Nebraska State Patrol, and any department to which a deputy state sheriff is assigned as provided in section 84-106; and</para><para>(c) Person means an individual:</para><para>(i) Who is employed by a law enforcement agency, including an individual working under contract with the agency;</para><para>(ii) To whom the law enforcement agency has authorized or delegated authority to make arrests, to place a detainee in detention or custody, or to otherwise exercise control over a detainee or a detainee's activities; and</para><para>(iii) Who is not the spouse of a detainee.</para><para>(2) A person commits the offense of sexual abuse of a detainee if the person engages in sexual penetration or sexual contact with a detainee. It is not a defense to a charge under this section that the detainee consented to such sexual penetration or sexual contact.</para><para>(3) An otherwise lawful pat-down or body cavity search by a person is not a violation of this section.</para><para>(4) Any person who engages in sexual penetration with a detainee is guilty of sexual abuse of a detainee in the first degree. Sexual abuse of a detainee in the first degree is a Class IIA felony.</para><para>(5) Any person who engages in sexual contact with a detainee is guilty of sexual abuse of a detainee in the second degree. Sexual abuse of a detainee in the second degree is a Class IIIA felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB519, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>