<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id00" statutenumber="28-634"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>28-634</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Payment cards; prohibited acts relating to scanning device or encoding machine; violation; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) It is unlawful for a person to intentionally and knowingly:</para><para id="id00">(a) Use a scanning device to access, read, scan, obtain, memorize, or store, temporarily or permanently, information encoded on a payment card without the permission of the authorized user of the payment card, the issuer of the authorized user's payment card, or a merchant;</para><para>(b) Possess a scanning device with the intent to obtain information encoded on a payment card without the permission of the authorized user, the issuer of the authorized user’s payment card, or a merchant or possess a scanning device with knowledge that some other person intends to use the scanning device to obtain information encoded on a payment card without the permission of the authorized user, the issuer of the authorized user’s payment card, or a merchant;</para><para id="id00">(c) Use an encoding machine to place information encoded on a payment card onto a different card without the permission of the authorized user of the card from which the information was obtained, the issuer of the authorized user's payment card, or a merchant; or</para><para>(d) Possess an encoding machine with the intent to place information encoded on a payment card onto a different payment card without the permission of the user, the issuer of the authorized user’s payment card, or a merchant.</para><para id="id00">(2) A violation of this section is a Class IV felony for the first offense and a Class IIIA felony for a second or subsequent offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 276, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB773, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>