<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-728"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-728</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings and intent; child abuse and neglect investigation team; child advocacy center; child abuse and neglect treatment team; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that child abuse and neglect are community problems requiring a cooperative complementary response by law enforcement, child advocacy centers, prosecutors, the Department of Health and Human Services, and other agencies or entities designed to protect children. It is the intent of the Legislature to create a child abuse and neglect investigation team in each county or contiguous group of counties and to create a child abuse and neglect treatment team in each county or contiguous group of counties.</para><para>(2) Each county or contiguous group of counties will be assigned by the Department of Health and Human Services to a child advocacy center. The purpose of a child advocacy center is to provide a child-focused response to support the physical, emotional, and psychological needs of children who are victims of abuse or neglect. Each child advocacy center shall meet accreditation criteria set forth by the National Children's Alliance. Nothing in this section shall prevent a child from receiving treatment or other services at a child advocacy center which has received or is in the process of receiving accreditation.</para><para>(3) Each county attorney or the county attorney representing a contiguous group of counties is responsible for convening the child abuse and neglect investigation team and ensuring that protocols are established and implemented. A representative of the child advocacy center assigned to the team shall assist the county attorney in facilitating case review, developing and updating protocols, and arranging training opportunities for the team. Each team must have protocols which, at a minimum, shall include procedures for:</para><para>(a) Conducting joint investigations of child abuse and other child abuse and neglect matters which the team deems necessary;</para><para>(b) Ensuring that a law enforcement agency will participate in the investigation;</para><para>(c) Conducting joint investigations of other child abuse and neglect matters which the team deems necessary;</para><para>(d) Arranging for a videotaped forensic interview at a child advocacy center for children sixteen years of age or younger who are alleging sexual abuse or serious physical abuse or neglect or who have witnessed a violent crime, been removed from a clandestine drug lab, or been recovered from a kidnapping;</para><para>(e) Reducing the risk of harm to child abuse and neglect victims;</para><para>(f) Ensuring that the child is in safe surroundings, including removing the perpetrator when necessary;</para><para>(g) Sharing of case information; </para><para>(h) How and when the team will meet; and </para><para>(i) Responding to drug-endangered children.</para><para>(4) Each county attorney or the county attorney representing a contiguous group of counties is responsible for convening the child abuse and neglect treatment team and ensuring that protocols are established and implemented. A representative of the child advocacy center appointed to the team shall assist the county attorney in facilitating case review, developing and updating protocols, and arranging training opportunities for the team. Each team must have protocols which, at a minimum, shall include procedures for:</para><para>(a) Case coordination and assistance, including the location of services available within the area;</para><para>(b) Case staffings and the coordination, development, implementation, and monitoring of treatment plans;</para><para>(c) Reducing the risk of harm to child abuse and neglect victims;</para><para>(d) Assisting those child abuse and neglect victims who are abused and neglected by perpetrators who do not reside in their homes; </para><para>(e) How and when the team will meet; and </para><para>(f) Working with multiproblem delinquent youth.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 40.</para></source></law></legaldoc>