<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id55">
<sectno id="id56" opdate="October 15, 2010">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id57" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-3,109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>28-3,109</statuteno><catchline>Action for damages; action for injunctive
relief; attorney's fees.</catchline><para>(1) Any woman upon whom an abortion has been performed in
violation of the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act or the father of
the unborn child who was the subject of such an abortion may maintain an action
against the person who performed the abortion in an intentional or a reckless
violation of the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act for actual damages.
Any woman upon whom an abortion has been attempted in violation of the Pain-Capable
Unborn Child Protection Act may maintain an action against the person who
attempted to perform the abortion in an intentional or a reckless violation
of the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act for actual damages.</para>
<para>(2) A cause
of action for injunctive relief against any person who has intentionally violated
the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act may be maintained by the woman
upon whom an abortion was performed or attempted to be performed in violation
of the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act, by any person who is the
spouse, parent, sibling, or guardian of, or a current or former licensed health
care provider of, the woman upon whom an abortion has been performed or attempted
to be performed in violation of the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act,
by a county attorney with appropriate jurisdiction, or by the Attorney General.
The injunction shall prevent the abortion provider from performing further
abortions in violation of the Pain-Capable Unborn Child Protection Act in
this state.</para><para>(3) If judgment is rendered in favor of the plaintiff in an action
described in this section, the court shall also render judgment for reasonable
attorney's fees in favor of the plaintiff against the defendant.</para>
<para>(4) If judgment
is rendered in favor of the defendant and the court finds that the plaintiff's
suit was frivolous and brought in bad faith, the court shall also render judgment
for reasonable attorney's fees in favor of the defendant against the plaintiff.</para>
<para>(5) No damages
or attorney's fees may be assessed against the woman upon whom an abortion
was performed or attempted to be performed except as provided in subsection
(4) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1103, &#167;  8.</para><operativedate>October 15, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>