<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id5" statutenumber="28-311.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-311.08</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Unlawful intrusion; photograph, film, record, or live broadcast of intimate area; penalty; court; duties; registration under Sex Offender Registration Act; statute of limitations.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly intrude upon any other person without his or her consent or knowledge in a place of solitude or seclusion.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person to knowingly photograph, film, record, or live broadcast an image of the intimate area of any other person without his or her knowledge and consent when his or her intimate area would not be generally visible to the public regardless of whether such other person is located in a public or private place.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Intimate area means the naked or undergarment-clad genitalia, pubic area, buttocks, or female breast of an individual;</para><para>(b) Intrude means either the:</para><para>(i) Viewing of another person in a state of undress as it is occurring; or</para><para>(ii) Recording by video, photographic, digital, or other electronic means of another person in a state of undress; and</para><para>(c) Place of solitude or seclusion means a place where a person would intend to be in a state of undress and have a reasonable expectation of privacy, including, but not limited to, any facility, public or private, used as a restroom, tanning booth, locker room, shower room, fitting room, or dressing room.</para><para>(4)(a) Violation of this section involving an intrusion as defined in subdivision (3)(b)(i) of this section or violation under subsection (2) of this section is a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(b) Subsequent violation of this section involving an intrusion as defined in subdivision (3)(b)(i) of this section, subsequent violation under subsection (2) of this section, or violation of this section involving an intrusion as defined in subdivision (3)(b)(ii) of this section is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(c) Violation of this section is a Class IIA felony if video or an image recorded in violation of this section is distributed to another person or otherwise made public in any manner which would enable it to be viewed by another person.</para><para>(5) As part of sentencing following a conviction for a violation of this section, the court shall make a finding as to the ages of the defendant and the victim at the time the offense occurred. If the defendant is found to have been nineteen years of age or older and the victim is found to have been less than eighteen years of age at such time, then the defendant shall be required to register under the Sex Offender Registration Act.</para><para>(6) No person shall be prosecuted pursuant to subdivision (4)(b) or (c) of this section unless the indictment for such offense is found by a grand jury or a complaint filed before a magistrate within three years after the later of:</para><para>(a) The commission of the crime;</para><para>(b) Law enforcement's or a victim's receipt of actual or constructive notice of either the existence of a video or other electronic recording made in violation of this section or the distribution of images, video, or other electronic recording made in violation of this section; or</para><para>(c) The youngest victim of a violation of this section reaching the age of twenty-one years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 908, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB61, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB998, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 17. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 29-4001.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>