<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-916.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-916.01</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in this section and sections 28-915, 28-915.01, 28-919, and 28-922, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Administrative proceeding shall mean any proceeding, other than a judicial proceeding, the outcome of which is required to be based on a record or documentation prescribed by law, or in which law or regulation is particularized in application to individuals;</para><para>(2) Benefit shall mean gain or advantage, or anything regarded by the beneficiary as gain or advantage, including benefit to any other person or entity in whose welfare he or she is interested, but not an advantage promised generally to a group or class of voters as a consequence of public measures which a candidate engages to support or oppose;</para><para>(3) Government shall include any branch, subdivision, or agency of the government of the state or any locality within it;</para><para>(4) Harm shall mean loss, disadvantage, or injury, or anything so regarded by the person affected, including loss, disadvantage, or injury to any other person or entity in whose welfare he or she is interested;</para><para>(5) Pecuniary benefit shall mean benefit in the form of money, property, commercial interests, or anything else the primary significance of which is economic gain;</para><para>(6) Public servant shall mean any officer or employee of government, including legislators and judges, and any person participating as juror, advisor, consultant, or otherwise, in performing a governmental function, but the term shall not include witnesses;</para><para>(7) Official proceeding shall mean a proceeding heard or which may be heard before any legislative, judicial, administrative, or other governmental agency or official authorized to take evidence under oath, including any referee, hearing examiner, commissioner, notary, or other person taking testimony or deposition in connection with any such proceeding; and</para><para>(8) Statement shall mean any representation, but shall include a representation of opinion, belief, or other state of mind only if the representation clearly relates to state of mind apart from or in addition to any facts which are the subject of the representation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 451, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB496, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>A proceeding is not made official by the formality with which it is conducted; instead, its officiality depends on its purpose and the authority from which it derives. Hence, a false sworn statement made for use in a pending judicial proceeding was considered to have been made in connection with an official proceeding for purposes of subornation of perjury. State v. Meehan, 7 Neb. App. 639, 585 N.W.2d 459 (1998).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>