
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id432"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-374.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-374.02</statuteno><catchline>Adult protective services official; training; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall require each adult protective services official to successfully complete training relating to caring for individuals with Alzheimer's disease and other dementia. Such training shall be no less than one hour in length. An adult protective services official employed by the department on July 18, 2026, shall complete the training within thirty days of such date.</para><para>(2) The training required by subsection (1) of this section shall include, but not be limited to: (a) Psychiatric and behavioral symptoms of Alzheimer's disease and other dementia; (b) methods of communicating respectfully and effectively with individuals with Alzheimer's disease and other dementia; (c) techniques for understanding and approaching behavioral symptoms; (d) information relating to safety including, but not limited to, wandering; (e) alerting law enforcement agencies to potential criminal behavior by a family member, a caretaker, or an institution; (f) alerting law enforcement agencies to neglect or exploitation; (g) the most common types of abuse; (h) methods of identifying incidents of self-neglect; (i) methods of identifying neglect by a caregiver; and (j) protocols for referral of such individuals to local care resources and professionals who are skilled in Alzheimer's disease and other dementia care to encourage cross-referral and for reporting abuse.</para><para>(3) The department may collaborate with a private nonprofit organization with expertise in working with individuals with Alzheimer's disease and other dementia to provide the training required by subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(4) Each adult protective services official shall complete the training once every five years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1055, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Alzheimer's Disease and other Dementia Support Act,</emphasis> see section 71-561.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>