<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-807"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-807</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in sections 28-807 to 28-829, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Adult shall mean any married person or any unmarried person of the age of eighteen years or older;</para><para>(2) Commercial film and photographic print processor shall mean any person who for compensation develops exposed photographic film into negatives, slides, or prints or who for compensation makes prints from negatives or slides. The term shall include, but not be limited to, any employee of such a person but shall not include employees of law enforcement agencies and prosecuting attorneys involved in the investigation and prosecution of criminal offenses or to persons involved in legitimate medical, scientific, or educational activities;</para><para>(3) Distribute shall mean to transfer possession, whether with or without consideration, by any means;</para><para>(4) Disseminate shall mean to manufacture, issue, publish, sell, lend, distribute, transmit, exhibit, or present materials or to offer in person or through an agent or by placing an advertisement for the same, whether with or without consideration, or agree to do the same;</para><para>(5) Knowingly shall mean having general knowledge of, reason to know, or a belief or reasonable ground for belief which warrants further inspection or inquiry of the character and content of any material, taken as a whole, described in this section, which is reasonably susceptible to examination by the defendant;</para><para>(6) Harmful to minors shall mean that quality of any description or representation, in whatever form, of nudity, sexual conduct, sexual excitement, or sadomasochistic abuse, when it (a) predominantly appeals to the prurient, shameful, or morbid interest of minors, (b) is patently offensive to prevailing standards in the adult community as a whole with respect to what is suitable material for minors, and (c) is lacking in serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value for minors;</para><para>(7) Material or work shall mean any book, magazine, newspaper, comic book, pamphlet, or other printed or written material or any picture, drawing, photograph, figure, image, motion picture, whether or not positive or negative exhibited or screened, play, nightclub, live performance, television production, other pictorial representation or electric reproduction, recording transcription, mechanical or otherwise, or other articles, equipment, machines, or materials;</para><para>(8) Minor shall mean any unmarried person under the age of eighteen years;</para><para>(9) Nudity shall mean the showing of the human, post-pubertal male or female genitals, pubic area, or buttocks with less than a full opaque covering, the depiction of covered male genitals in a discernibly turgid state, or the showing of the female breast with less than a full opaque covering of any portion thereof below the top of the nipple;</para><para>(10) Obscene shall mean (a) that an average person applying contemporary community standards would find that the work, material, conduct, or live performance taken as a whole predominantly appeals to the prurient interest or a shameful or morbid interest in nudity, sex, or excretion, (b) the work, material, conduct, or live performance depicts or describes in a patently offensive way sexual conduct specifically set out in sections 28-807 to 28-829, and (c) the work, conduct, material, or live performance taken as a whole lacks serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value;</para><para>(11) Place shall mean any building, structure, or place or any separate part or portion thereof or the ground itself;</para><para>(12) Person shall mean any individual, partnership, limited liability company, firm, association, corporation, trustee, lessee, agent, assignee, or other legal entity;</para><para>(13) Performance, whether with or without consideration, shall mean any play, motion picture, dance, or other exhibition performed before an audience;</para><para>(14) Promote shall mean to manufacture, issue, sell, give, provide, lend, mail, deliver, transfer, transmit, publish, distribute, circulate, disseminate, present, exhibit, or place an order for advertising or to knowingly offer in person or through an agent or agree to do the same;</para><para>(15) Sexual conduct shall mean acts of masturbation, homosexuality, sodomy, sexual intercourse, or prolonged physical contact with a person's clothed or unclothed genitals, pubic area, or buttocks or, if such person is female, breast;</para><para>(16) Sexual excitement shall mean the condition of human male or female genitals when in a state of sexual stimulation or arousal; and</para><para>(17) Sadomasochistic abuse shall mean flagellation or torture by or upon a nude person or a person clad in undergarments, a mask, or a bizarre costume or the condition of being fettered, bound, or otherwise physically restrained when performed to predominantly appeal to the shameful or morbid interest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 163; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 748, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 117, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 178. </para></source><annotation><para>In reviewing a determination of whether certain material is obscene pursuant to the three-part obscenity test, the appellate court should give appropriate deference to the trier of fact on the "prurient interest" and "patently offensive" prongs of the test because these issues depend on the knowledge of "contemporary community standards" which are uniquely within the province of the trier of fact. However, the third prong of the test, whether the material has artistic value, is subject to de novo review because it does not depend on community standards. Tipp-It, Inc. v. Conboy, 257 Neb. 219, 596 N.W.2d 304 (1999).</para><para>The definition of obscenity provided in this section is patterned upon, and coextensive with, the language of Miller v. California, 413 U.S. 15, 93 S.Ct. 2607, 37 L. Ed. 2d 419 (1973). State v. Harrold, 256 Neb. 829, 593 N.W.2d 299 (1999).</para><para>Films which have little plot and which consist of scene after scene of sexual intercourse, lesbianism, homosexuality, cunnilingus, and fellatio are obscene as that term is defined. State v. Embassy Corp., 215 Neb. 631, 340 N.W.2d 160 (1983).</para><para>Subsection (10) of this statute is not unconstitutionally vague. State v. Embassy Corp., 215 Neb. 631, 340 N.W.2d 160 (1983).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>