<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id156">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id158" statutenumber="28-726"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-726</statuteno><catchline id="id161">Information;
access.</catchline><para>Except as provided in this section and
sections 28-722 and 81-3126, no person, official, or agency shall have access
to information in the tracking system of child protection cases maintained
pursuant to section 28-715 or in records in the central registry of
child protection cases maintained pursuant to section 28-718 unless in furtherance
of purposes directly connected with the administration of the Child Protection and Family Safety Act. Such
persons, officials, and agencies having access to such information shall include,
but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(1) A law enforcement agency investigating a report of known
or suspected child abuse or neglect;</para>
<para>(2) A county attorney in preparation of a child abuse or
neglect petition or termination of parental rights petition;</para>
<para>(3) A physician who has before him or her a child whom he
or she reasonably suspects may be abused or neglected;</para>
<para>(4) An agency having the legal responsibility or authorization
to care for, treat, or supervise an abused or neglected child or a parent,
a guardian, or other person responsible for the abused or neglected child's
welfare who is the subject of the report of child abuse or neglect;</para>
<para>(5) Any person engaged in bona fide research or auditing.
No information identifying the subjects of the report of child abuse or neglect
shall be made available to the researcher or auditor;</para>
<para>(6) The Foster Care Review Office and the designated local
foster care review board when the information relates to a child in a foster
care placement as defined in section 43-1301. The information provided to
the office and local board shall not include the name or identity of any person
making a report of suspected child abuse or neglect;</para>
<para>(7) The designated protection and advocacy system authorized
pursuant to the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act
of 2000, 42 U.S.C. 15001, as the act existed on January 1, 2005, and the Protection
and Advocacy for Mentally Ill Individuals Act, 42 U.S.C. 10801, as the act
existed on September 1, 2001, acting upon a complaint received from or on
behalf of a person with developmental disabilities or mental illness;</para>
<para>(8) The person or persons having custody of the abused or
neglected child in situations of alleged out-of-home child abuse or neglect;</para>
<para>(9) For purposes of licensing providers of child care programs,
the Department of Health and Human Services; and</para>
<para>(10) A probation officer administering juvenile intake services
pursuant to section 29-2260.01, conducting court-ordered predispositional
investigations prior to disposition, or supervising a juvenile upon disposition.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 522, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 463, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1222, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 643, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1035, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 119, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 214, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 642, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB782, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB998, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>