<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id698"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-627.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>28-627.03</statuteno><catchline>Financial transaction offense; continuing criminal enterprise; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Financial transaction offense means any violation of sections 28-618 to 28-630 for which the punishment is a felony; and</para><para>(b) Leadership position means a position in which a person acts as a principal administrator, organizer, supervisor, or manager or otherwise leads or directs other persons.</para><para>(2) A person is engaged in a continuing criminal enterprise if such person commits any financial transaction offense and:</para><para>(a) Such offense is part of a continuing series of financial transaction offenses;</para><para>(b) Such series of offenses is undertaken by such person in concert with two or more other persons with respect to whom such person acts in a leadership position; and</para><para>(c) Such person obtains substantial income or resources from such activities.</para><para>(3) A violation of this section shall be punished as a:</para><para>(a) Class II felony if the enterprise, or any other enterprise in which the defendant was in a leadership position:</para><para>(i) Included three or fewer persons; or</para><para>(ii) Had at least two million dollars but less than five million dollars in gross receipts during any twelve-month period of the enterprise's existence;</para><para>(b) Class ID felony if the enterprise, or any other enterprise in which the defendant was in a leadership position:</para><para>(i) Included four or more persons but fewer than ten persons; or</para><para>(ii) Had at least five million dollars but less than ten million dollars in gross receipts during any twelve-month period of the enterprise's existence; and</para><para>(c) Class IC felony if the enterprise, or any other enterprise in which the defendant was in a leadership position:</para><para>(i) Included ten or more persons; or</para><para>(ii) Had at least ten million dollars in gross receipts during any twelve-month period of the enterprise's existence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB559, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>