<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id112">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id114"  statutenumber="28-414.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-414.05</statuteno><catchline>Controlled substance; destruction;
records.</catchline><para>(1)
The owner of any stock of controlled substances may cause such controlled
substances to be destroyed pursuant to this section when the need for such
substances ceases. Complete records of the destruction of controlled substances
pursuant to this section shall be maintained by the registrant for five years
after the date of destruction.</para>
<para>(2) If the owner
is a registrant:</para><para>(a) Controlled substances listed in Schedule II, III, IV, or V
of section 28-405 may be destroyed by a pharmacy inspector, by a reverse distributor,
or by the administration. Upon destruction, any forms required by the administration
to document such destruction shall be completed;</para><para>(b) Liquid controlled substances
in opened containers which originally contained fifty milliliters or less
or compounded liquid controlled substances within the facility where they
were compounded may be destroyed if witnessed by two individuals credentialed
under the Uniform Credentialing Act and designated by the facility and recorded
in accordance with subsection (4) of section 28-411; or</para>
<para>(c) Solid controlled
substances in opened unit-dose containers or which have been adulterated within
a hospital where they were to be administered to patients in such hospital
may be destroyed if witnessed by two individuals credentialed under the Uniform
Credentialing Act and designated by the hospital and recorded in accordance
with subsection (4) of section 28-411.</para><para>(3) If the owner is a resident of a long-term
care facility or hospital, a controlled substance listed in Schedule II, III,
IV, or V of section 28-405 shall be destroyed by two individuals credentialed
under the Uniform Credentialing Act and designated by the facility or hospital.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 11.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>