<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-813" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-813</statuteno><catchline>Obscene literature or material; prepares; distributes; promotes; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for a person knowingly to (a) print, copy, manufacture, prepare, produce, or reproduce obscene material for the purpose of sale or distribution, (b) publish, circulate, sell, rent, lend, transport in interstate commerce, distribute, or exhibit any obscene material, (c) have in his or her possession with intent to sell, rent, lend, transport, or distribute any obscene material, or (d) promote any obscene material or performance.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for a person to place an order for any advertising promoting the sale or distribution of material represented or held out to be obscene, whether or not such material exists in fact or is obscene. In all cases in which a charge for a violation of this section is brought against a person who cannot be found in this state, the executive authority of this state may demand extradition of such person from the executive authority of the state in which such person may be found.</para><para>(3) A person commits an offense of promoting obscene material if knowing its content and character he or she (a) disseminates for monetary consideration any obscene material, (b) produces, presents, or directs obscene performances for monetary consideration, or (c) participates for monetary consideration in that part of a performance which makes it obscene.</para><para>(4) Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 169; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 117, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 27. </para></source><annotation><para>Films which have little plot and which consist of scene after scene of sexual intercourse, lesbianism, homosexuality, cunnilingus, and fellatio are obscene as the term is defined. State v. Embassy Corp., 215 Neb. 631, 340 N.W.2d 160 (1983).</para><para>Subsection (1) of this statute is not unconstitutionally vague. State v. Embassy Corp., 215 Neb. 631, 340 N.W.2d 160 (1983). </para></annotation></law></legaldoc>