<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id198">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id200" statutenumber="28-710"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>28-710</statuteno><catchline id="id203">Act, how cited;
terms, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Sections 28-710 to 28-727
shall be known and may be cited as the Child Protection Act.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of the Child Protection Act:</para>
<para>(a) Child abuse or neglect means knowingly, intentionally,
or negligently causing or permitting a minor child to be:</para>
<para>(i) Placed in a situation that endangers his or her life
or physical or mental health;</para>
<para>(ii) Cruelly confined or cruelly punished;</para>
<para>(iii) Deprived of necessary food, clothing, shelter, or care;</para>
<para>(iv) Left unattended in a motor vehicle if such minor child
is six years of age or younger;</para>
<para>(v) Sexually abused; or</para>
<para>(vi) Sexually exploited by allowing, encouraging, or forcing
such person to solicit for or engage in prostitution, debauchery, public indecency,
or obscene or pornographic photography, films, or depictions;</para>
<para>(b) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para>
<para>(c) Law enforcement agency means the police department or
town marshal in incorporated municipalities, the office of the sheriff in
unincorporated areas, and the Nebraska State Patrol;</para>
<para>(d) Out-of-home child abuse or neglect means child abuse
or neglect occurring in day care homes, foster homes, day care centers, residential child-caring agencies as defined in section
71-1926, and other child care facilities or institutions; and</para>
<para>(e) Subject of the report of child abuse or neglect means
the person or persons identified in the report as responsible for the child
abuse or neglect.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 505, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 522, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 463, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1035, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 119, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 29.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>