<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id40" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-801.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-801.01</statuteno><catchline id="id43">Solicitation of prostitution; penalty; affirmative defense.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who solicits another person not his or her spouse to perform any act of sexual contact or sexual penetration, as those terms are defined in section 28-318, in exchange for money or other thing of value, commits solicitation of prostitution.</para><para>(2) Any person convicted of violating subsection (1) of this section shall be punished as follows:</para><para>(a) If such person has had no prior convictions, such person shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor and pay a fine of not less than two hundred fifty dollars, unless the person solicited is under the age of eighteen years, in which case such person violating this section shall be guilty of a Class IV felony. If the court places such person on probation, such order of probation shall include in its conditions (i) the payment of a fine of not less than two hundred fifty dollars, (ii) that such person shall satisfactorily attend and complete an appropriate mental health and substance abuse assessment conducted by a licensed mental health professional or substance abuse professional authorized to complete such assessment, and (iii) that such person shall satisfactorily attend and complete, at his or her own expense, an educational program designed to educate participants on the effect of prostitution on the participants' health, on the person solicited, and on the community; and</para><para>(b) If such person has had one or more prior convictions, such person shall be guilty of a Class IV felony and pay a fine of not less than five hundred dollars. If the court places such person on probation, such order of probation shall include in its conditions (i) the payment of a fine of not less than five hundred dollars, (ii) that such person shall satisfactorily attend and complete an appropriate mental health and substance abuse assessment conducted by a licensed mental health professional or substance abuse professional authorized to complete such assessment, and (iii) that such person shall satisfactorily attend and complete, at his or her own expense, an educational program designed to educate participants on the effect of prostitution on the participants' health, on the person solicited, and on the community.</para><para>(3) It is an affirmative defense to prosecution under this section that such person was a trafficking victim as defined in section 28-830.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1086, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB255, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB294, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>