<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-412"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-412</statuteno><catchline>Narcotic drugs; administration to narcotic-dependent person; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) It is unlawful to prescribe any narcotic drug listed in section 28-405, except buprenorphine, for the purpose of detoxification treatment or maintenance treatment except as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) A narcotic drug may be administered or dispensed to a narcotic-dependent person for detoxification treatment or maintenance treatment by a practitioner who is registered to provide detoxification treatment or maintenance treatment pursuant to section 28-406.</para><para>(3) A narcotic drug may be administered or dispensed to a narcotic-dependent person when necessary to relieve acute withdrawal symptoms pending the referral of such person for detoxification treatment or maintenance treatment by a physician who is not registered to provide detoxification treatment or maintenance treatment under section 28-406. Not more than one day's supply of narcotic drugs shall be administered or dispensed for such person's use at one time. Such treatment shall not be continued for more than three successive calendar days and may not be renewed or extended.</para><para>(4) A narcotic drug may be administered or dispensed in a hospital to maintain or detoxify a person as an incidental adjunct to medical or surgical treatment conditions other than dependence.</para><para>(5) Any person who violates this section is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Detoxification treatment means the administering or dispensing of a narcotic drug in decreasing doses to a person for a specified period of time to alleviate adverse physiological or psychological effects incident to withdrawal from the continuous or sustained use of a narcotic drug and to bring such person to a narcotic drug-free state within such period of time. Detoxification treatment includes short-term detoxification treatment and long-term detoxification treatment;</para><para>(b) Long-term detoxification treatment means detoxification treatment for a period of more than thirty days but not more than one hundred eighty days;</para><para>(c) Maintenance treatment means the administering or dispensing of a narcotic drug in the treatment of a narcotic-dependent person for a period of more than twenty-one days; and</para><para>(d) Short-term detoxification treatment means detoxification treatment for a period of not more than thirty days.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 379, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>