<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id102" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-414.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>28-414.03</statuteno><catchline>Controlled substances; maintenance of records; label.</catchline><para>(1) Paper prescriptions for all controlled substances listed in Schedule II of section 28-405 shall be kept in a separate file by the dispensing practitioner and shall be maintained for a minimum of five years. The practitioner shall make all such files readily available to the department and law enforcement for inspection without a search warrant.</para><para>(2) Prescriptions for all controlled substances listed in Schedule III, IV, or V of section 28-405 shall be maintained either separately from other prescriptions or in a form in which the information required is readily retrievable from ordinary business records of the dispensing practitioner and shall be maintained for a minimum of five years. The practitioner shall make all such records readily available to the department, the administration, and law enforcement for inspection without a search warrant.</para><para>(3) Before dispensing any controlled substance listed in Schedule II, III, IV, or V of section 28-405, the dispensing practitioner shall affix a label to the container in which the controlled substance is dispensed. Such label shall bear the name and address of the pharmacy or dispensing practitioner, the name of the patient, the date of filling, the serial number of the prescription under which it is recorded in the practitioner's prescription records, the name of the prescribing practitioner, and the directions for use of the controlled substance. Unless the prescribing practitioner writes "do not label" or words of similar import on the original paper prescription or so designates in an electronic prescription or an oral prescription, such label shall also bear the name of the controlled substance.</para><para>(4) For multidrug containers, more than one drug, device, or biological may be dispensed in the same container when (a) such container is prepackaged by the manufacturer, packager, or distributor and shipped directly to the pharmacy in this manner or (b) the container does not accommodate greater than a thirty-one-day supply of compatible dosage units and is labeled to identify each drug or biological in the container in addition to all other information required by law.</para><para>(5) If a pharmacy fills prescriptions for controlled substances on behalf of another pharmacy under contractual agreement or common ownership, the prescription label shall contain the Drug Enforcement Administration number of the pharmacy at which the prescriptions are filled.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB166, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>