<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id35" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-712"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-712</statuteno><catchline>Alternative response implementation
plan; contents; department; use; powers; report; evaluation of alternative
response demonstration projects; department; powers and duties; rules and
regulations.</catchline><para>(1)
The department, in consultation with the Nebraska Children's Commission, shall
develop an alternative response implementation plan in accordance with sections
28-710.01 to 28-712.01. The alternative response implementation plan shall
include the provision of concrete supports and voluntary services, including,
but not limited to: Meeting basic needs, including food and clothing assistance;
housing assistance; transportation assistance; child care assistance; and
mental health and substance abuse services. When the alternative response
implementation plan has been developed, the department may begin using alternative
response in up to five alternative response demonstration project locations
that are designated by the department. The department shall provide a report
of an evaluation on the status of alternative response implementation pursuant
to subsection (2) of this section to the commission and electronically to
the Legislature by November 15, 2015. The commission shall provide feedback
on the report to the department before December 15, 2015. The department may
begin using alternative response in up to five additional alternative response
demonstration project locations on or after January 1, 2016. The department
shall provide a report of another evaluation done pursuant to subsection (2)
of this section to the commission and electronically to the Legislature by
November 15, 2016. The department may continue using alternative response
until July 1, 2017. Continued use of alternative response thereafter shall
require approval of the Legislature. For purposes of this section, demonstration
project location means any geographic region, including, but not limited to,
a city, a township, a village, a county, a group of counties, or a group of
counties and cities, townships, or villages.</para>
<para>(2) The department
shall contract with an independent entity to evaluate the alternative response
demonstration projects. The evaluation shall include, but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The screening
process used to determine which cases shall be assigned to alternative response;</para>
<para>(b) The number
and proportion of repeat child abuse and neglect allegations within a specified
period of time following initial intake;</para><para>(c) The number and proportion of substantiated
child abuse and neglect allegations within a specified period of time following
initial intake;</para><para>(d) The number and proportion of families with any child entering
out-of-home care within a specified period of time following initial intake;</para>
<para>(e) Changes
in child and family well-being in the domains of behavioral and emotional
functioning and physical health and development as measured by a standardized
assessment instrument to be selected by the department;</para>
<para>(f) The number
and proportion of families assigned to the alternative response track who
are reassigned to a traditional response; and</para><para>(g) A cost analysis that
will examine, at a minimum, the costs of the key elements of services received.</para>
<para>(3) The department
shall provide to the Nebraska Children's Commission regular updates on:</para>
<para>(a) The alternative
response implementation plan, including the development of the alternative
response interview protocols of children;</para><para>(b) The status of alternative response implementation;</para>
<para>(c) Inclusion
of child welfare stakeholders, service providers, and other community partners,
including families, for feedback and recommendations on the alternative response
implementation plan;</para><para>(d) Any findings or recommendations made by the independent evaluator,
including costs;</para><para>(e) Any alternative response programmatic modifications; and</para>
<para>(f) The status
of the adoption and promulgation of rules and regulations.</para>
<para>(4) The department
shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out sections 28-710.01
to 28-712.01. Such rules and regulations shall include, but not be limited
to, provisions on the transfer of cases from alternative response to traditional
response; notice to families subject to a comprehensive assessment and served
through alternative response of the alternative response process and their
rights, including the opportunity to challenge agency determinations; the
provision of services through alternative response; the collection, sharing,
and reporting of data; and the alternative response ineligibility criteria.
Whenever the department proposes to change the alternative response ineligibility
criteria, public notice of the changes shall be given. The department shall
provide public notice and time for public comment by publishing the proposed
changes on its web site at least sixty days prior to the public hearing on
such regulation changes. The department shall provide a copy of the proposed
rules and regulations to the Nebraska Children's Commission no later than
October 1, 2014.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>