<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id34" statutenumber="28-1241"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1241</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Fireworks; definitions.</catchline><para>As used in sections 28-1239.01 and 28-1241 to 28-1252, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) 1.3G explosives, also known as display fireworks or Class B fireworks or by United Nations shipping classification number UN0335, means any items classified as 1.3G explosives by the United States Department of Transportation in Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2021;</para><para>(2) 1.4G explosives, also known as consumer fireworks or Class C fireworks or by United Nations shipping classification number UN0336, means any items classified as 1.4G explosives by the United States Department of Transportation in Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2021;</para><para>(3) Distributor means any person engaged in the business of making sales of fireworks at wholesale in this state to any person engaged in the business of making sales of fireworks either as a jobber or as a retailer or both;</para><para>(4) Jobber means any person engaged in the business of making sales of fireworks at wholesale to any other person engaged in the business of making sales at retail;</para><para>(5) Retailer means any person engaged in the business of making sales of fireworks at retail to consumers or to persons other than distributors or jobbers;</para><para>(6) Sale includes barter, exchange, or gift or offer therefor and each such transaction made by any person, whether as principal, proprietor, agent, servant, or employee;</para><para>(7) Fireworks means any composition or device designed for the purpose of producing a visible or audible effect by combustion, deflagration, or detonation and which meets the definition of consumer or special fireworks set forth by the United States Department of Transportation in Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations;</para><para>(8)(a) Consumer fireworks means any device that (i) meets the requirements set forth in 16 C.F.R. parts 1500 and 1507, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2021, and (ii) is tested and approved by a nationally recognized testing facility or by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(b) 1.4G explosives shall be considered consumer fireworks.</para><para>(c) Consumer fireworks does not include:</para><para>(i) Wire sparklers; or</para><para>(ii) Fireworks that have been tested by the State Fire Marshal as a response to complaints and have been deemed to be unsafe; and</para><para>(9) Display fireworks means those materials manufactured exclusively for use in public exhibitions or displays of fireworks designed to produce visible or audible effects by combustion, deflagration, or detonation. Display fireworks includes, but is not limited to, firecrackers containing more than one hundred thirty milligrams of explosive composition, aerial shells containing more than forty grams of explosive composition, and other display pieces which exceed the limits for classification as consumer fireworks. 1.3G explosives shall be considered display fireworks. Display fireworks shall be considered an explosive as defined in section 28-1213 and shall be subject to sections 28-1213 to 28-1239, except that display fireworks may be purchased, received, and discharged by the holder of an approved display permit issued pursuant to section 28-1239.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 273; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 969, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 893, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB880, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB152, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>