<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1105"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1105</statuteno><catchline>Possession of gambling records; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the offense of possession of gambling records if, other than as a player, he or she knowingly possesses any writing, paper, instrument, or article which is:</para><para>(a) Of a kind commonly used in the operation or promotion of a bookmaking scheme or enterprise and such writing, paper, instrument, or article has been used for the purpose of recording, memorializing, or registering any bet, wager, or other gambling information; or</para><para>(b) Of a kind commonly used in the operation, promotion, or playing of a lottery or mutuel scheme or enterprise or other scheme not conducted pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, the State Lottery Act, the Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act, or section 9-701 and such writing, paper, instrument, or article has been used for the purpose of recording, memorializing, or registering any bet, wager, or other gambling information not permitted by such acts or section.</para><para>(2) Possession of gambling records in the first degree is a Class II misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 221; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 152, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 259, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 408, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 193; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 67; </para><para>Initiative Law 2020, No. 430, &#167; 9.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska County and City Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-601.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act,</emphasis> see section 9-1101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>