<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id6" statutenumber="28-1204.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1204.04</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Unlawful possession
of a firearm at a school; penalty; exceptions; confiscation of certain firearms;
disposition.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who possesses a firearm
in a school, on school grounds, in a school-owned vehicle, or at a school-sponsored
activity or athletic event is guilty of the offense of unlawful possession
of a firearm at a school. Unlawful possession of a firearm at a school is
a Class IV felony. This subsection shall not apply to (a) the issuance of
firearms to or possession by members of the armed forces of the United States,
active or reserve, National Guard of this state, or Reserve Officers Training
Corps or peace officers or other duly authorized law enforcement officers
when on duty or training, (b) the possession of firearms by peace officers
or other duly authorized law enforcement officers when contracted by a school
to provide school security or school event control services, (c) firearms
which may lawfully be possessed by the person receiving instruction, for instruction
under the immediate supervision of an adult instructor, (d) firearms which
may lawfully be possessed by a member of a college or university rifle team,
within the scope of such person's duties as a member of the team, (e) firearms
which may lawfully be possessed by a person employed by a college or university
in this state as part of an agriculture or a natural resources program of
such college or university, within the scope of such person's employment,
(f) firearms contained within a private vehicle operated by a nonstudent adult
which are not loaded and (i) are encased or (ii) are in a locked firearm rack
that is on a motor vehicle, (g)
firearms which may lawfully be possessed by a person for the purpose of using
them, with the approval of the school, in a historical reenactment, in a hunter
education program, or as part of an honor guard, or (h) a handgun carried as a concealed handgun
by a valid holder of a permit issued under the Concealed Handgun Permit Act
in a vehicle or on his or her person while riding in or on a vehicle into
or onto any parking area, which is open to the public and used by a school
if, prior to exiting the vehicle, the handgun is locked inside the glove box,
trunk, or other compartment of the vehicle, a storage box securely attached
to the vehicle, or, if the vehicle is a motorcycle, a hardened compartment
securely attached to the motorcycle while the vehicle is in or on such parking
area, except as prohibited by federal law. For purposes of this subsection,
encased means enclosed in a case that is expressly made for the purpose of
containing a firearm and that is completely zipped, snapped, buckled, tied,
or otherwise fastened with no part of the firearm exposed.</para>
<para>(2) Any firearm possessed in violation of subsection (1) of
this section shall be confiscated without warrant by a peace officer or may
be confiscated without warrant by school administrative or teaching personnel.
Any firearm confiscated by school administrative or teaching personnel shall
be delivered to a peace officer as soon as practicable.</para>
<para>(3) Any firearm confiscated by or given to a peace officer
pursuant to subsection (2) of this section shall be declared a common nuisance
and shall be held by the peace officer prior to his or her delivery of the
firearm to the property division of the law enforcement agency which employs
the peace officer. The property division of such law enforcement agency shall
hold such firearm for as long as the firearm is needed as evidence. After
the firearm is no longer needed as evidence, it shall be destroyed in such
manner as the court may direct.</para>
<para>(4) Whenever a firearm is confiscated and held pursuant to
this section or section 28-1204.02, the peace officer who received such firearm
shall cause to be filed within ten days after the confiscation a petition
for destruction of such firearm. The petition shall be filed in the district
court of the county in which the confiscation is made. The petition shall
describe the firearm held, state the name of the owner, if known, allege the
essential elements of the violation which caused the confiscation, and conclude
with a prayer for disposition and destruction in such manner as the court
may direct. At any time after the confiscation of the firearm and prior to
court disposition, the owner of the firearm seized may petition the district
court of the county in which the confiscation was made for possession of the
firearm. The court shall release the firearm to such owner only if the claim
of ownership can reasonably be shown to be true and either (a) the owner of
the firearm can show that the firearm was taken from his or her property or
place of business unlawfully or without the knowledge and consent of the owner
and that such property or place of business is different from that of the
person from whom the firearm was confiscated or (b) the owner of the firearm
is acquitted of the charge of unlawful possession of a handgun in violation
of section 28-1204, unlawful transfer of a firearm to a juvenile, or unlawful
possession of a firearm at a school. No firearm having significant antique
value or historical significance as determined by the Nebraska State Historical
Society shall be destroyed. If a firearm has significant antique value or
historical significance, it shall be sold at auction and the proceeds shall
be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article
VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 82, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB430, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB512, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB390, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Concealed Handgun Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 69-2427.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>