<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id27">
<sectno id="id28">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id29" statutenumber="28-1006"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id31">28-1006</statuteno><catchline id="id32">Investigation;
arrest; seizure of property; reimbursement of expenses.</catchline><para>(1)
It shall be the duty of the sheriff, a police officer, or the Nebraska State
Patrol to make prompt investigation of and arrest for any violation of section
28-1005 or 28-1005.01.</para>
<para>(2) Any animal, equipment, device, or other property or things
involved in any violation of section 28-1005 or 28-1005.01 shall be subject to seizure, and
disposition may be made in accordance with the method of disposition directed
for contraband in sections 29-818 and 29-820.</para>
<para>(3) Any animal involved in any violation of section 28-1005 or 28-1005.01 shall be subject
to seizure. Distribution or disposition shall be made as provided in section 29-818 and in such manner
as the court may direct. The court may give preference to adoption alternatives
through humane societies or comparable institutions and to the protection
of such animal's welfare. For a humane society or comparable institution to
be considered as an adoption alternative under this subsection, it must first
be licensed by the Department of Agriculture as having passed the inspection
requirements in the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act and paid
the fee for inspection under the act. The court may prohibit an adopting or
purchasing party from selling such animal for a period not to exceed one year.</para>
<para>(4) In addition to any other sentence given for a violation
of section 28-1005 or 28-1005.01,
the sentencing court may order the defendant to reimburse a public or private
agency for expenses incurred in conjunction with the care, impoundment, or
disposal, including adoption, of an animal involved in the violation of section 28-1005 or 28-1005.01. Whenever the court believes
that such reimbursement may be a proper sentence or the prosecuting attorney
requests, the court shall order that the presentence investigation report
include documentation regarding the nature and amount of the expenses incurred.
The court may order that reimbursement be made immediately, in specified installments,
or within a specified period of time, not to exceed five years after the date
of judgment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 170, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 551, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 82, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB252, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 11.</para>
</source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act,</emphasis> see section 54-625.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>