<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1408"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1408</statuteno><catchline>Public duty; execution.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, conduct is justifiable when it is required or authorized by:</para><para>(a) The law defining the duties or functions of a public officer or the assistance to be rendered to such officer in the performance of his duties;</para><para>(b) The law governing the execution of legal process;</para><para>(c) The judgment or order of a competent court or tribunal;</para><para>(d) The law governing the armed services or the lawful conduct of war; or</para><para>(e) Any other provision of law imposing a public duty.</para><para>(2) Sections 28-1409 to 28-1416 shall apply to:</para><para>(a) The use of force upon or toward the person of another for any of the purposes dealt with in such sections; and</para><para>(b) The use of deadly force for any purpose, unless the use of such force is otherwise expressly authorized by law or occurs in the lawful conduct of war.</para><para>(3) The justification afforded by subsection (1) of this section shall apply:</para><para>(a) When the actor believes his conduct to be required or authorized by the judgment or direction of a competent court or tribunal or in the lawful execution of legal process, notwithstanding lack of jurisdiction of the court or defect in the legal process; and</para><para>(b) When the actor believes his conduct to be required or authorized to assist a public officer in the performance of his duties, notwithstanding that the officer exceeded his legal authority.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 895, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 28-835, (1975). </para></source></law></legaldoc>