<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id96">
<sectno id="id97" opdate="October 1, 2010">Sec. 9.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id98" statutenumber="28-1250">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id100">28-1250</statuteno><catchline id="id101">Fireworks;
prohibited acts; violations; penalties;
license suspension, cancellation, or revocation; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who violates any of the provisions of sections
28-1244 to 28-1249 commits a Class III misdemeanor. If such person is a licensed
distributor or jobber, the
State Fire Marshal may suspend, cancel, or revoke the license for up to three
years. The suspension, cancellation, or revocation shall become effective
upon the failure to timely appeal the decision under the Administrative Procedure
Act or upon an order of the Nebraska Fire Safety Appeals Board upholding the
decision pursuant to a hearing under the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person, association, partnership,
limited liability company, or corporation to have in his, her, or its possession
any fireworks in violation of any of the provisions of sections 28-1244
to 28-1249. If any person shall have in his, her, or its possession
any fireworks in violation of such sections, a warrant may be issued for the
seizure of such fireworks and when the warrant is executed by the seizure
of such fireworks, such fireworks shall be safely kept by the magistrate to
be used as evidence. Upon conviction of the offender, the fireworks shall
be destroyed, but if the offender is discharged, the fireworks shall be returned
to the person in whose possession they were found. Nothing in such sections
shall apply to the transportation of fireworks by regulated carriers.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 282; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 183; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB880, &#167; 9.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>