<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1202.04" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1202.04</statuteno><catchline>Carrying concealed handgun; contact with peace officer or emergency services personnel; procedures for securing handgun; applicability; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This section applies to a person who is not otherwise prohibited by state law from possessing or carrying a concealed handgun.</para><para>(b) This section does not apply to a qualified law enforcement officer or qualified retired law enforcement officer carrying a concealed handgun pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 926B or 926C, respectively, as such sections existed on January 1, 2023.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (5) of this section, whenever a person who is carrying a concealed handgun is contacted by a peace officer or by emergency services personnel, the person shall immediately inform the peace officer or emergency services personnel that the person is carrying a concealed handgun.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (5) of this section, during contact with a person carrying a concealed handgun, a peace officer or emergency services personnel may secure the handgun or direct that it be secured during the duration of the contact if the peace officer or emergency services personnel determines that it is necessary for the safety of any person present, including the peace officer or emergency services personnel. The person shall submit to the order to secure the handgun.</para><para>(4)(a) When the peace officer has determined that the person is not a threat to the safety of any person present, including the peace officer, and the person has not committed any other violation that would result in his or her arrest, the peace officer shall return the handgun to the person before releasing the person from the scene and breaking contact.</para><para>(b) When emergency services personnel have determined that the person is not a threat to the safety of any person present, including emergency services personnel, and if the person is physically and mentally capable of possessing the handgun, the emergency services personnel shall return the handgun to the person before releasing the person from the scene and breaking contact. If the person is transported for treatment to another location, the handgun shall be turned over to any peace officer. The peace officer shall provide a receipt which includes the make, model, caliber, and serial number of the handgun.</para><para>(5) A person is not required to comply with subsections (2) and (3) of this section if:</para><para>(a) Such person is storing or transporting a handgun in a motor vehicle for any lawful purpose or transporting a handgun directly to or from a motor vehicle to or from any place where such handgun may be lawfully possessed or carried by such person; and</para><para>(b) Such handgun is unloaded, kept separate from ammunition, and enclosed in a case.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Contact with a peace officer means any time a peace officer personally stops, detains, questions, or addresses a person for an official purpose or in the course of his or her official duties, and contact with emergency services personnel means any time emergency services personnel provide treatment to a person in the course of their official duties; and</para><para>(b) Emergency services personnel has the same meaning as in section 28-1202.03.</para><para>(7) A violation of:</para><para>(a) Subsection (2) of this section is a Class III misdemeanor for a first offense, a Class I misdemeanor for a second offense, and a Class IV felony for a third or subsequent offense; and</para><para>(b) Subsection (3) of this section is a Class I misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 454, &#167; 14; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2018), &#167; 69-2440; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB77, &#167; 12. </para><effectivedate>September 2, 2023</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>