<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1229"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1229</statuteno><catchline>Explosives control; Nebraska State Patrol; permits; issuance; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska State Patrol shall have the authority to issue permits for:</para><para>(a) The storage of explosive materials;</para><para>(b) The use of explosive materials; and</para><para>(c) The purchase of explosive materials by business enterprises.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska State Patrol shall not issue a permit to store or use explosive materials to any person who:</para><para>(a) Is under twenty-one years of age;</para><para>(b) Has been convicted in any court of a felony;</para><para>(c) Is charged with a felony;</para><para>(d) Is a fugitive from justice;</para><para>(e) Is an unlawful user of any depressant, stimulant, or narcotic drug;</para><para>(f) Has been admitted as a patient or inmate in a public or private institution for the treatment of a mental or emotional disease or disorder within five years preceding the date of application;</para><para>(g) Has no reasonable educational, industrial, commercial, agricultural, recreational, or other legitimate need for a permit to store or use explosive materials;</para><para>(h) Has been convicted in any court of a misdemeanor crime of domestic violence. This includes any misdemeanor conviction involving the use or attempted use of physical force committed by a current or former spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim or by a person with a similar relationship with the victim;</para><para>(i) Is subject to a court order restraining him or her from harassing, stalking, or threatening an intimate partner or child of such partner; or</para><para>(j) Is an alien illegally in the United States.</para><para>(3) Upon filing of a proper application and payment of the prescribed fee, and subject to the provisions of sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 and other applicable laws, the Nebraska State Patrol shall issue to such applicant a permit to store explosive materials if:</para><para>(a) The applicant, including, in the case of a corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or association, any individual possessing, directly or indirectly, the power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of the corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or association, is not a person to whom the Nebraska State Patrol is prohibited to issue a permit under subsection (2) of this section;</para><para>(b) The applicant has not willfully violated any of the provisions of sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 or of 18 U.S.C. chapter 40; and</para><para>(c) The applicant has a place of storage for explosive materials which meets such standards of public safety, based on the class, type, and quantity of explosive materials to be stored, and security against theft as prescribed in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Nebraska State Patrol pursuant to sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 and by the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States pursuant to 18 U.S.C. chapter 40.</para><para>(4) A permit for the storage of explosive materials shall specify the class, type, and quantity of explosive materials which are authorized to be stored. It shall also specify the type of security required. A permit for the storage of explosive materials shall be valid for a period of two years unless a shorter period is specified in the permit.</para><para>(5) Upon filing of a proper application and payment of the prescribed fee, and subject to the provisions of sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 and other applicable laws, the Nebraska State Patrol shall issue to such applicant a permit to use explosive materials if:</para><para>(a) The applicant is an individual to whom the Nebraska State Patrol is not prohibited to issue a permit under subsection (2) of this section;</para><para>(b) The applicant has not willfully violated any of the provisions of sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 or of 18 U.S.C. chapter 40;</para><para>(c) The applicant has demonstrated and certified in writing that he or she is familiar with all published laws of this state and published local ordinances relating to the use of explosive materials applicable at the place or places he or she intends to use such explosive materials;</para><para>(d) The applicant has demonstrated that he or she has adequate knowledge, training, and experience in the use of explosive materials of the class and type for which he or she seeks a users permit and has passed a qualifying examination, as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol, concerning the use of such explosive materials; and</para><para>(e) The applicant has been fingerprinted and the fingerprints submitted to the Nebraska State Patrol for a criminal history record check. If no disqualifying record is located at the state level, the fingerprints shall be forwarded by the patrol to the Identification Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history record check.</para><para>(6) A permit for the use of explosive materials shall specify the class and type of explosive materials the permitholder is qualified to use. It shall be applicable to the permitholder and to any individual acting under his or her direct personal supervision. A permit may be issued for a single use of explosive materials or, when the applicant is engaged or employed in a business requiring the frequent use of explosive materials, for a period of not more than two years.</para><para>(7) Upon filing of a proper application and payment of the prescribed fees and subject to sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 and other applicable laws, the Nebraska State Patrol shall issue to a business enterprise a permit to purchase explosive materials if:</para><para>(a) The business enterprise has a place of business in this state;</para><para>(b) No individual possessing, directly or indirectly, the power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of the business enterprise is a person to whom the Nebraska State Patrol is prohibited to issue a permit under subsection (2) of this section;</para><para>(c) An authorized officer of the business enterprise certifies that all explosive materials will be used on the date of purchase of such materials unless such business enterprise is in possession of a valid storage permit; and</para><para>(d) The business enterprise employs at least one employee having a valid use permit issued under this section.</para><para>(8) A permit for a business enterprise to purchase explosive materials shall specify the class and type of explosive materials which are authorized to be purchased. The class and type of explosive materials covered by such permit shall be the same as those specified in the use permit or permits issued to an employee or employees of the business enterprise. The permit may be issued for a period of up to two years but shall become void if the business enterprise ceases to employ an individual having a valid use permit issued under this section for the class and type of explosive materials covered by the purchase permit of the business enterprise.</para><para>(9) If the applicant is an individual, an application for a permit issued under this section shall include the applicant's social security number.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 261; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 215, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 163, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 181; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 131, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>