<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1233</statuteno><catchline>Explosive materials; permitholder; records; notice; requirements; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Every holder of any permit required under sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 shall maintain an accurate inventory of all explosives in his or her possession and maintain records of transfers to other persons of explosive materials. Such records shall include a statement of intended use by the transferee and the name, date of birth, place of birth, social security number or taxpayer identification number, and place of residence of any natural person to whom the explosives are transferred. If the explosive materials are transferred to a corporation or other business entity, such records shall include the identity and principal and local places of business and the name, date of birth, place of birth, and place of residence of the natural person acting as the agent of the corporation or other business entity in arranging the transfer. In the case of a federal licensee or permittee who is also a permitholder under the terms of sections 28-1213 to 28-1239, the maintenance of one set of records for the fulfilling of the record-keeping requirements of 18 U.S.C. chapter 40 shall be deemed compliance with the record-keeping requirements of sections 28-1213 to 28-1239.</para><para>(2) Every holder of any storage or business enterprise permit required under sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 shall maintain a log describing the time, place, amount, and type of explosive used in any blasting operations performed by him or her or at his or her direction.</para><para>(3) Every holder of any storage, purchase, or use permit required under sections 28-1213 to 28-1239 shall notify the fire protection district in which any explosive over one pound in weight is to be used or stored twenty-four hours prior to such use or storage, and the holder shall keep a written record in the log describing the time the notice was given, office in the district to which the notice was given, and name of the person in the district notified. The fire protection district may waive the twenty-four-hour notice when the public safety requires such waiver to prevent loss of life or property if such notice is given prior to use or storage. The fire protection district may accept a single notification of ongoing use within a set timeframe not to exceed sixty days. Any holder of a storage, purchase, or use permit who fails to notify the fire protection district pursuant to this subsection is guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 265; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 163, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 284, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>