<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1414"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1414</statuteno><catchline>Mistake of law; reckless or negligent use of force.</catchline><para>(1) The justification afforded by sections 28-1409 to 28-1412 is unavailable when:</para><para>(a) The actor's belief in the unlawfulness of the force or conduct against which he employs protective force or his belief in the lawfulness of an arrest which he endeavors to effect by force is erroneous; and</para><para>(b) His error is the result of ignorance or mistake as to the provisions of sections 28-1406 to 28-1416, any other provision of the criminal law, or the law governing the legality of an arrest or search.</para><para>(2) When the actor believes that the use of force upon or toward the person of another is necessary for any of the purposes for which such belief would establish a justification under sections 28-1408 to 28-1413 but the actor is reckless or negligent in having such belief or in acquiring or failing to acquire any knowledge or belief which is material to the justifiability of his use of force, the justification afforded by those sections is unavailable in a prosecution for an offense for which recklessness or negligence, as the case may be, suffices to establish culpability.</para><para>(3) When the actor is justified under sections 28-1408 to 28-1413 in using force upon or toward the person of another but he recklessly or negligently injures or creates a risk of injury to innocent persons, the justification afforded by those sections is unavailable in a prosecution for such recklessness or negligence towards innocent persons.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 895, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 28-841, (1975). </para></source></law></legaldoc>