<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1101</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in this article, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) A person advances gambling activity if, acting other than as a player, he or she engages in conduct that materially aids any form of gambling activity. Conduct of this nature includes, but shall not be limited to, conduct directed toward (a) the creation or establishment of the particular game, contest, scheme, device, or activity involved, (b) the acquisition or maintenance of premises, paraphernalia, equipment, or apparatus therefor, or (c) engaging in the procurement, sale, or offering for sale within this state of any chance, share, or interest in a lottery of another state or government whether or not such chance, share, or interest is an actual lottery ticket, receipt, contingent promise to pay, order to purchase, or other record of such interest except as provided in the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, the State Lottery Act, or section 9-701;</para><para>(2) Bookmaking shall mean advancing gambling activity by unlawfully accepting bets from members of the public as a business upon the outcome of future contingent events;</para><para>(3) A person profits from gambling activity if, other than as a player, he or she accepts or receives money or other property pursuant to an agreement or understanding with any person whereby he or she participates or is to participate in the proceeds of gambling activity;</para><para>(4) A person engages in gambling if he or she bets something of value upon the outcome of a future event, which outcome is determined by an element of chance, or upon the outcome of a game, contest, or election, or conducts or participates in any bingo, lottery by the sale of pickle cards, lottery, raffle, gift enterprise, or other scheme not authorized or conducted in accordance with the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, the State Lottery Act, or section 9-701, but a person does not engage in gambling by:</para><para>(a) Entering into a lawful business transaction;</para><para>(b) Playing an amusement device or a coin-operated mechanical game which confers as a prize an immediate, unrecorded right of replay not exchangeable for something of value;</para><para>(c) Conducting or participating in a prize contest; or</para><para>(d) Conducting or participating in any bingo, lottery by the sale of pickle cards, lottery, raffle, or gift enterprise conducted in accordance with the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, the State Lottery Act, or section 9-701;</para><para>(5) Gambling device shall mean any device, machine, paraphernalia, writing, paper, instrument, article, or equipment that is used or usable for engaging in gambling, whether that activity consists of gambling between persons or gambling by a person involving the playing of a machine. Gambling device shall also include any mechanical gaming device, computer gaming device, electronic gaming device, or video gaming device which has the capability of awarding something of value, free games redeemable for something of value, instant-win tickets which also provide the possibility of participating in a subsequent drawing or event, or tickets or stubs redeemable for something of value, except as authorized in the furtherance of parimutuel wagering. Supplies, equipment, cards, tickets, stubs, and other items used in any bingo, lottery by the sale of pickle cards, other lottery, raffle, or gift enterprise conducted in accordance with the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, the State Lottery Act, or section 9-701 are not gambling devices within this definition;</para><para>(6) Something of value shall mean any money or property, any token, object, or article exchangeable for money or property, or any form of credit or promise directly or indirectly contemplating transfer of money or property or of any interest therein, or involving extension of a service or entertainment; and</para><para>(7) Prize contest shall mean any competition in which one or more competitors are awarded something of value as a consequence of winning or achieving a certain result in the competition and (a) the value of such awards made to competitors participating in the contest does not depend upon the number of participants in the contest or upon the amount of consideration, if any, paid for the opportunity to participate in the contest or upon chance and (b) the value or identity of such awards to be made to competitors is published before the competition begins.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 217; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 900, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 152, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 259, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 374, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 744, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 949, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 192; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 343, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional provisions,</emphasis> see Article III, section 24, Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para> <para><emphasis>Nebraska County and City Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-601.</para> <para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para> <para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para> <para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para> <para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para> </crossreference><annotation>
<para>The language of this section, strictly construed, simply and plainly 
asserts that an activity is gambling in Nebraska if its outcome is 
predominantly caused by chance. American Amusements Co. v. Nebraska Dept. 
of Rev., 282 Neb. 908, 807 N.W.2d 492 (2011).</para>
<para>A gambling device is one which is used or usable to bet something of value on the outcome of a future event, which outcome is determined by an element of chance, unless the device falls within one of the exceptions contained in subsection (4) of this section. State v. Two IGT Video Poker Games, 237 Neb. 145, 465 N.W.2d 453 (1991).</para><para>Free replay credits are a credit or promise involving extension of a service or entertainment and are thus something of value. State v. Two IGT Video Poker Games, 237 Neb. 145, 465 N.W.2d 453 (1991).</para><para>The definition of "gambling device" contained in subsection (5) of this section, when taken in the context of section 28-1107, is not unconstitutionally overbroad. State v. Two IGT Video Poker Games, 237 Neb. 145, 465 N.W.2d 453 (1991).</para><para>A lottery is a game of chance in which the winner is determined by mere luck, not by skill, and contains the elements of consideration, a prize, and chance. Video Consultants v. Douglas, 219 Neb. 868, 367 N.W.2d 697 (1985).</para><para>The sale of pickle cards constitutes a lottery under this section as it has the requisite elements of consideration, prize, and chance. CONtact, Inc. v. State, 212 Neb. 584, 324 N.W.2d 804 (1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>