<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id13" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-1005.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1005.01</statuteno><catchline>Ownership or possession of animal
fighting paraphernalia; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall knowingly
or intentionally own or possess animal fighting paraphernalia with the intent
to commit a violation of section 28-1005.</para>
<para>(2)(a) For purposes of this section, except as provided in subdivision
(b) of this subsection, animal fighting paraphernalia means equipment, products,
and materials of any kind that are used, intended for use, or designed for
use in the training, preparation, conditioning, or furtherance of the pitting
of an animal against another as defined in section 28-1004. Animal fighting
paraphernalia includes, but is not limited to, the following:</para>
<para>(i) A breaking stick, which means a device designed for insertion behind
the molars of a dog for the purpose of breaking the dog's grip on another
animal or object;</para>
<para>(ii) A cat mill, which means a device that rotates around a central
support with one arm designed to secure a dog and one arm designed to secure
a cat, rabbit, or other small animal beyond the grasp of the dog;</para>
<para>(iii) A treadmill, which means an exercise device consisting of an endless
belt on which the animal walks or runs without changing place;</para>
<para>(iv) A fighting pit, which means a walled area designed to contain an
animal fight;</para>
<para>(v) A springpole, which means a biting surface attached to a stretchable
device, suspended at a height sufficient to prevent a dog from reaching the
biting surface while touching the ground;</para>
<para>(vi) A heel, which means any edged or pointed instrument designed to
be attached to the leg of a fowl;</para>
<para>(vii) A boxing glove or muff, which means a fitted protective covering
for the spurs of a fowl; and</para>
<para>(viii) Any other instrument commonly used in the furtherance of pitting
an animal against another.</para>
<para>(b) Animal fighting paraphernalia does not include equipment, products,
or materials of any kind used by a veterinarian licensed to practice veterinary
medicine and surgery in this state.</para>
<para>(3) Any person violating subsection (1) of this section is guilty of
a Class I misdemeanor and may
also be subject to section 28-1019.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB252, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB329, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>