<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id58">
<sectno id="id59" opdate="October 1, 2010">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id60" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-1243"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1243</statuteno><catchline>Fireworks item deemed unsafe; quarantined;
testing; test results; effect.</catchline><para>(1) If the State Fire Marshal deems any fireworks item to
be unsafe pursuant to subdivision (6)(c)(vi) of section 28-1241, such fireworks
item shall be quarantined from other fireworks. Any licensed distributor,
jobber, or retailer may request, at the distributor's, jobber's, or retailer's
expense, that such fireworks item be tested by an independent, nationally
recognized testing facility to determine if such fireworks item meets the
requirements set forth by the United States Consumer Product Safety Commission
for consumer fireworks, also known as 1.4G explosives, as classified by the
United States Department of Transportation in 49 C.F.R. 172.101, as such regulation
existed on January 1, 2010. A copy of the results of all testing done pursuant
to this section shall be provided to the State Fire Marshal.</para>
<para>(2)
If such fireworks item is in compliance with such requirements and otherwise
permitted under section 28-1241, such fireworks item that was determined to
be unsafe pursuant to subdivision (6)(c)(vi) of section 28-1241 shall be deemed
a consumer firework and be permitted for retail sale or distribution.</para>
<para>(3)
If such fireworks item is in compliance with such requirements but is otherwise
not deemed consumer fireworks, such fireworks item shall not be sold at retail
or distributed to retailers for sale in this state, but a distributor, jobber,
or retailer may sell such fireworks item to another distributor or retailer
in a state that permits the sale of such fireworks item.</para>
<para>(4)
If such fireworks item is not in compliance with such requirements, then the
distributor, jobber, or retailer shall destroy such fireworks item under the
supervision of the State Fire Marshal. If such fireworks item is not destroyed
under the supervision of the State Fire Marshal, notarized documentation shall
be provided to the State Fire Marshal detailing and confirming the fireworks
item's destruction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB880, &#167;  4.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>