<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1203</statuteno><catchline>Transportation or possession of machine guns, short rifles, or short shotguns; penalty; exception.</catchline><para>(1) Any person or persons who shall transport or possess any machine gun, short rifle, or short shotgun commits a Class IV felony.</para><para>(2) The provisions of this section shall not be held to prohibit any act by peace officers, members of the United States armed services, or members of the National Guard of this state, in the lawful discharge of their duties, or persons qualified under the provisions of federal law relating to the short rifle, short shotgun, or machine gun.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 235; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 748, &#167; 17.</para></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (1) of this section, the possessory standard for controlled substances (i.e., a defendant possesses a controlled substance when the defendant knows of the nature or character of the substance and its presence and has dominion or control over the substance) is equally applicable to possession of a firearm. State v. Jasper, 237 Neb. 754, 467 N.W.2d 855 (1991).</para><para>Subsection (1) of this section is not vitiated by the "Right to Bear Arms" amendment of 1988, is a valid exercise of the State's police power in reasonable regulation of certain firearms, and does not contravene Neb. Const. art. I, sec. 1. State v. LaChapelle, 234 Neb. 458, 451 N.W.2d 689 (1990).</para><para>The requirement of "possession" for purposes of subsection (1) of this section may be satisfied by actual or constructive possession of any of the items named in subsection (1). State v. Frieze, 3 Neb. App. 263, 525 N.W.2d 646 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>