<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id149" statutenumber="28-1429.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1429.02</statuteno><catchline id="id152">Vending machines; restrictions on use; violation; penalty; local ordinances; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, it shall be unlawful to dispense cigarettes, other tobacco products, electronic nicotine delivery systems, or alternative nicotine products from a vending machine or similar device. Any person violating this section is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor. In addition, upon conviction for a second offense, the court shall order a six-month suspension of the offender's license to sell tobacco and electronic nicotine delivery systems, if any, and, upon conviction for a third or subsequent offense, the court shall order the permanent revocation of the offender's license to sell tobacco and electronic nicotine delivery systems, if any.</para><para>(2) Cigarettes, other tobacco products, electronic nicotine delivery systems, or alternative nicotine products may be dispensed from a vending machine or similar device when such machine or device is located in an area, office, business, plant, or factory which is not open to the general public or on the licensed premises of any establishment having a license issued under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act for the sale of alcoholic liquor for consumption on the premises when such machine or device is located in the same room in which the alcoholic liquor is dispensed.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section shall be construed to restrict or prohibit a governing body of a city or village from establishing and enforcing ordinances at least as stringent as or more stringent than the provisions of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 130, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB863, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB149, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB397, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>