<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id856"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1903"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1903</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Crush Transnational Repression in Nebraska Act:</para><para>(1) Agent of a foreign principal means an agent directed or controlled by a foreign principal, or the proxies of such agent;</para><para>(2) Foreign adversary means a foreign adversary as determined pursuant to 15 C.F.R. 791.4 as such regulation existed on April 1, 2025;</para><para>(3) Foreign political party means any organization or any other combination of individuals in a country other than the United States, or any unit or branch thereof, having for an aim or purpose, or that is engaged in any activity devoted in whole or in part to:</para><para>(a) The establishment, administration, control, or acquisition of administration or control, of a government of a foreign country or a subdivision thereof; or</para><para>(b) The furtherance or influencing of the political or public interests, policies, or relations of a government of a foreign country or a subdivision thereof;</para><para>(4) Foreign principal means:</para><para>(a) The government of a foreign country or any official or subdivision of such government;</para><para>(b) A foreign political party or any member or subdivision of such party;</para><para>(c) A foreign terrorist organization or any member or subdivision of such organization;</para><para>(d) A partnership, association, corporation, organization, or other combination of persons that is:</para><para>(i) Organized under the laws of, or has its principal place of business in, a foreign adversary, or a subsidiary of such entity; or</para><para>(ii) Owned or controlled wholly or in part by any person or combination of persons of a foreign adversary or foreign terrorist organization; or</para><para>(e) Any entity that is owned or controlled in whole or in part by a person or entity described in subdivision (4)(a), (b), (c), or (d) of this section;</para><para>(5) Foreign terrorist organization means an organization included on the United States Department of State's list of designated foreign terrorist organizations pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1189, as such section existed on April 1, 2025;</para><para>(6)(a) Government of a foreign country means any person or group of persons exercising sovereign de facto or de jure political jurisdiction over any country, other than the United States, or over any part of such country, and includes any subdivision of any such group and any group or agency to which such sovereign de facto or de jure authority or functions are directly or indirectly delegated.</para><para>(b) Government of a foreign country also includes any faction or body of insurgents within a country, other than the United States, assuming to exercise governmental authority whether such faction or body of insurgents has or has not been recognized by the United States; and</para><para>(7) Transnational repression includes actions and behaviors emanating from or attributable to a foreign principal committed by an agent of such foreign principal, acting outside or within the foreign principal's territory, with the intention of harassing, intimidating, censoring, or otherwise extending such principal's ability to influence, control, or impose such principal's preferences on the behavior of individuals outside of the principal's territory or jurisdiction. Such actions and behaviors include direct and indirect methods, including physical contact, threats, electronic targeting, actual or credible threats of collective punishment or harassment of individuals under the principal's effective control, financial coercion, abuse of administrative processes, selective prosecution of laws of general application, or the use or direction of social media and telecommunications entities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB644, &#167; 16. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>