<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id44">
<sectno id="id45">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id46" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-1019"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id48">28-1019</statuteno><catchline id="id49">Conviction; order
prohibiting ownership, possession, or residing with animal; duration; violation;
penalty; seizure of animal.</catchline><para> (1)(a) If a person
is convicted of a Class IV felony under section 28-1005 or 28-1009, the sentencing
court shall order such person not to own, possess, or reside with any animal
for at least five years after the date of conviction, but such time restriction
shall not exceed fifteen years. Any person violating such court order shall
be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(b) If a person is convicted of a Class I misdemeanor under section 28-1005.01 or subdivision
(2)(a) of section 28-1009 or a Class III misdemeanor under section 28-1010,
the sentencing court may order such person not to own, possess, or reside
with any animal after the date of conviction, but such time restriction, if
any, shall not exceed five years. Any person violating such court order shall
be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(c) Any animal involved in a violation of a court order under
subdivision (a) or (b) of this subsection shall be subject to seizure by law
enforcement. Distribution or
disposition shall be made under section 29-818.</para>
<para>(2) This section shall not apply to any person convicted under
section 28-1005, 28-1005.01, or
28-1009 if a licensed physician confirms in writing that ownership or possession
of or residence with an animal is essential to the health of such person.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1055, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB252, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>