<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id848"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1701"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1701</statuteno><catchline>Witness or victim of sexual assault; eligible alcohol or drug offense; immunity from arrest or prosecution; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not be arrested or prosecuted for an eligible alcohol or drug offense if such person witnessed or was the victim of a sexual assault and such person:</para><para>(a) Either:</para><para>(i) In good faith, reported such sexual assault to law enforcement; or</para><para>(ii) Requested emergency medical assistance for the victim of the sexual assault; and</para><para>(b) Evidence supporting the arrest or prosecution of the eligible alcohol or drug offense was obtained or discovered as a result of such person reporting such sexual assault to law enforcement or requesting emergency medical assistance.</para><para>(2) A person shall not be arrested or prosecuted for an eligible alcohol or drug offense if:</para><para>(a) Evidence supporting the arrest or prosecution of the person for the offense was obtained or discovered as a result of the investigation or prosecution of a sexual assault; and</para><para>(b) Such person cooperates with law enforcement in the investigation or prosecution of the sexual assault.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Eligible alcohol or drug offense means:</para><para>(i) A violation of subsection (3) or (13) of section 28-416 or of section 28-441;</para><para>(ii) A violation of section 53-180.02 committed by a person older than eighteen years of age and under the age of twenty-one years, as described in subdivision (4)(a) of section 53-180.05;</para><para>(iii) A violation of a city or village ordinance similar to subdivision (3)(a)(i) or (ii) of this section; or</para><para>(iv) Attempt, conspiracy, solicitation, being an accessory to, aiding and abetting, aiding the consummation of, or compounding a felony with any of the offenses in subdivision (3)(a)(i), (ii), or (iii) of this section as the underlying offense; and</para><para>(b) Sexual assault means:</para><para>(i) A violation of section 28-316.01, 28-319, 28-319.01, 28-320, 28-320.01, 28-320.02, 28-322.01, 28-322.02, 28-322.03, 28-322.04, 28-322.05, 28-703, or 28-1463.03, sex trafficking or sex trafficking of a minor under section 28-831, or subdivision (1)(c) or (g) of section 28-386 or subdivision (1)(d), (e), or (f) of section 28-707; or</para><para>(ii) Attempt, conspiracy, solicitation, being an accessory to, aiding and abetting, aiding the consummation of, or compounding a felony with any of the offenses listed in subdivision (3)(b)(i) of this section as the underlying offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB519, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>