<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1423"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1423</statuteno><catchline>License for sale of tobacco; term; fees; false swearing; penalty.</catchline><para>The term for which such license shall run shall be from the date of filing such application and paying such license fee to and including December 31 of the calendar year in which application for such license is made, and the license fee for any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation selling at retail shall be twenty-five dollars in cities of the metropolitan class, fifteen dollars in cities of the primary and first classes, and ten dollars in cities of all other classes and in towns and villages and in locations outside of the limits of cities, towns and villages. Any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation selling annually in the aggregate more than one hundred fifty thousand cigars, packages of cigarettes, and packages of tobacco in any form, at wholesale, shall pay a license fee of one hundred dollars, and if such combined annual sales amount to less than one hundred fifty thousand cigars, packages of cigarettes and packages of tobacco, the annual license fee shall be fifteen dollars. No wholesaler's license shall be issued in any year on a less basis than one hundred dollars per annum unless the applicant for the same shall file with such application a statement duly sworn to by himself or herself, or if applicant is a partnership, by a member of the firm, or if a limited liability company, by a member or manager of the company, or if a corporation, by an officer or manager thereof, that in the past such wholesaler's combined sales of cigars, packages of cigarettes, and packages of tobacco in every form have not exceeded in the aggregate one hundred fifty thousand annually, and that such sales will not exceed such aggregate amount for the current year for which the license is to issue. Any person swearing falsely in such affidavit shall be guilty of perjury and upon conviction thereof shall be punished as provided by section 28-915 and such wholesaler's license shall be revoked until the full license fee of one hundred dollars is paid. If application for license is made after July 1 of any calendar year, the fee shall be one-half of the fee provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 180, &#167; 4, p. 402; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9852; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 136, &#167; 1, p. 335; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 198, &#167; 1, p. 565; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 28-1026; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 28-1025; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 748, &#167; 20; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 28-1025, (1975); </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 190. </para></source></law></legaldoc>