<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id118">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id120"  statutenumber="28-1418.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1418.01</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections
28-1418 to 28-1429.03:</para>
<para>(1) Alternative
nicotine product means any noncombustible product containing nicotine that
is intended for human consumption, whether chewed, absorbed, dissolved, or
ingested by any other means. Alternative nicotine product does not include
any vapor product, cigarette, cigar, or other tobacco product, or any product
regulated as a drug or device by the United States Food and Drug Administration
under Chapter V of the federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act;</para>
<para>(2) Self-service
display means a retail display that contains a tobacco product, a tobacco-derived
product, a vapor product, or an alternative nicotine product and is located
in an area openly accessible to a retailer's customers and from which such
customers can readily access the product without the assistance of a salesperson.
Self-service display does not include a display case that holds tobacco products,
vapor products, or alternative nicotine products behind locked doors;</para>
<para>(3) Tobacco specialty
store means a retail store that (a) derives at least seventy-five percent
of its revenue from tobacco products, tobacco-derived products, vapor products,
or alternative nicotine products and (b) does not permit minors under the
age of eighteen years to enter the premises unless accompanied by a parent
or legal guardian; and</para><para>(4) Vapor product means any noncombustible product containing nicotine
that employs a heating element, power source, electronic circuit, or other
electronic, chemical, or mechanical means, regardless of shape or size, that
can be used to produce vapor from nicotine in a solution or other form. Vapor
product includes any electronic cigarette, electronic cigar, electronic cigarillo,
electronic pipe, or similar product or device and any vapor cartridge or other
container of nicotine in a solution or other form that is intended to be used
with or in an electronic cigarette, electronic cigar, electronic cigarillo,
electronic pipe, or similar product or device. Vapor product does not include
an alternative nicotine product, cigarette, cigar, or other tobacco product,
or any product regulated as a drug or device by the United States Food and
Drug Administration under Chapter V of the federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic
Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB863, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>