<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1316"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1316</statuteno><catchline>Unlawful use of locks and keys; penalty;
exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) A person commits the offense of unlawful
use of locks and keys if he or
she:</para>
<para>(a) Sells, offers to sell, or gives to any person other than a law enforcement
agency, dealer licensed under the Motor
Vehicle Industry Regulation Act, motor vehicle manufacturer, or
person regularly carrying on the profession of a locksmith any try-out key,
manipulation key, wiggle key, or any other device designed to be used in place
of the normal change key of any motor vehicle; or</para>
<para>(b) Has in his or her possession
any try-out key, wiggle key, manipulation key, or any other device designed
to be used in place of the normal change key of any motor vehicle unless he or she is a locksmith, locksmith
manufacturer, dealer licensed under the Motor
Vehicle Industry Regulation Act, motor vehicle manufacturer, or
law enforcement agency; or</para>
<para>(c) Duplicates a master key for anyone unless written permission has
been granted by the person who has legal control of the master key. All master
keys shall be stamped with the words DO NOT DUPLICATE. All duplications of
master keys shall also be stamped with the words DO NOT DUPLICATE.</para>
<para>(2) Nothing in subsection (1) of this section shall be construed to
make it unlawful if:</para>
<para>(a) The owner of two or more vehicles possesses a change key that can
be used on two or more vehicles that he or
she owns; or</para>
<para>(b) Such owner changes the locks on such vehicle so that they are keyed
alike; or</para>
<para>(c) Any person makes or duplicates the original change keys for such
an owner; or</para>
<para>(d) Anyone stamps any other type of key with the words DO NOT DUPLICATE.</para>
<para>(3) Unlawful use of locks and keys is a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 300; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 60-1401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>