<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id163">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id165" statutenumber="28-1437"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1437</statuteno><catchline id="id168">Legend drugs;
unlawful acts; definition; prescription by facsimile or electronic transmission.</catchline>
<para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person knowingly or intentionally
to possess or to acquire or obtain or to attempt to acquire or obtain by means
of misrepresentation, fraud, forgery, deception, or subterfuge possession
of any drug substance not classified as a controlled substance under the Uniform
Controlled Substances Act, but which can only be lawfully distributed, under
federal statutes in effect on January
1, 2014, upon the written or oral order of a practitioner authorized
to prescribe such substances.</para>
<para>(2) Such substances as referred to in subsection (1) of this
section shall be known as legend drug substances, which shall be defined as
including all drug substances not classified as controlled substances under
the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, but which require a written or oral
prescription from a practitioner authorized to prescribe such substances and
which may only be lawfully dispensed by a duly licensed pharmacist, in accordance
with the provisions of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, 21 U.S.C. 301 to 392, in
effect on January 1, 2014.</para>
<para>(3) A prescription for a legend drug may be transmitted by
the practitioner or the practitioner's agent to a pharmacy by facsimile or
electronic transmission. Except as otherwise provided in sections 28-414 to 28-414.05 for prescriptions
for Schedule II, III, IV, or V controlled substances, the facsimile or electronic
transmission shall serve as the original prescription for purposes of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 485, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 28-476.01, (1975); </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB811, &#167; 25.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>