<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id178">
<sectno id="id179" opdate="May 21, 2009">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id180" statutenumber="28-1463.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id182">28-1463.02</statuteno><catchline id="id183">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>As used in the Child Pornography Prevention Act, unless the
context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Child, in the case of a participant, means any
person under the age of eighteen years and, in the case of a portrayed observer, means any person under the age of sixteen years;</para>
<para>(2) Erotic fondling means touching
a person's clothed or unclothed genitals or pubic area, breasts if the person
is a female, or developing breast area if the person is a female child, for
the purpose of real or simulated overt sexual gratification or sexual stimulation
of one or more persons involved. Erotic fondling shall not be construed to
include physical contact, even if affectionate, which is not for the purpose
of real or simulated overt sexual gratification or sexual stimulation of one
or more of the persons involved;</para>
<para>(3) Erotic nudity means the
display of the human male or female genitals or pubic area, the human female
breasts, or the developing breast area of the human female child, for the
purpose of real or simulated overt sexual gratification or sexual stimulation
of one or more of the persons involved;</para>
<para>(4) Sadomasochistic abuse means flagellation
or torture by or upon a nude person or a person clad in undergarments, a mask,
or bizarre costume, or the condition of being fettered, bound, or otherwise
physically restrained when performed to predominantly appeal to the morbid
interest;</para>
<para>(5) Sexually explicit conduct means: (a)
Real or simulated intercourse, whether genital-genital, oral-genital, anal-genital,
or oral-anal between persons of the same or opposite sex or between a human
and an animal or with an artificial genital; (b) real or simulated masturbation;
(c) real or simulated sadomasochistic abuse; (d) erotic fondling; (e) erotic
nudity; or (f) real or simulated defecation or urination for the purpose of
sexual gratification or sexual stimulation of one or more of the persons involved;
and</para>
<para>(6) Visual depiction means live
performance or photographic representation and
includes any undeveloped film or videotape or data stored on a computer disk
or by other electronic means which is capable of conversion into a visual
image and also includes any photograph, film, video, picture, digital image,
or computer-displayed image, video, or picture, whether made or produced by
electronic, mechanical, computer, digital, or other means.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 668, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 788, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 17.</para></source><annotation><para>Probable cause to search for evidence of crimes involving visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct involving minors may be established by a detailed verbal description of the conduct depicted in the images. State v. Nuss, 279 Neb. 648, 781 N.W.2d 60 (2010).</para><para>While copies of images obtained during a law enforcement investigation may be used to establish probable cause to search for evidence of crimes involving visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct involving minors, they are not absolutely required. State v. Nuss, 279 Neb. 648, 781 N.W.2d 60 (2010).</para><para>Age of child may be proved by stipulation of defendant. State v. Burke, 225 Neb. 625, 408 N.W.2d 239 (1987).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>