<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id587"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1202.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1202.03</statuteno><catchline>Carrying concealed handgun; identification document, required; applicability; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This section applies to a person who is not otherwise prohibited by state law from possessing or carrying a concealed handgun.</para><para>(b) This section does not apply to a qualified law enforcement officer or qualified retired law enforcement officer carrying a concealed handgun pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 926B or 926C, respectively, as such sections existed on January 1, 2023.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, any time a person is carrying a concealed handgun, such person shall also carry such person's identification document. The person shall display the identification document when asked to do so by a peace officer or by emergency services personnel.</para><para>(3) A person is not required to comply with this section if:</para><para>(a) Such person is storing or transporting a handgun in a motor vehicle for any lawful purpose or transporting a handgun directly to or from a motor vehicle to or from any place where such handgun may be lawfully possessed or carried by such person; and</para><para>(b) Such handgun is unloaded, kept separate from ammunition, and enclosed in a case.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Emergency services personnel means a volunteer or paid firefighter or rescue squad member or a person licensed to provide emergency medical services pursuant to the Emergency Medical Services Practice Act or authorized to provide emergency medical services pursuant to the EMS Personnel Licensure Interstate Compact; and</para><para>(b) Identification document means a valid:</para><para>(i) Driver's or operator's license;</para><para>(ii) State identification card;</para><para>(iii) Military identification card;</para><para>(iv) Alien registration card; or</para><para>(v) Passport.</para><para>(5) A violation of this section is a Class III misdemeanor for a first offense and a Class I misdemeanor for any second or subsequent offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB77, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Emergency Medical Services Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1201.</para><para><emphasis>EMS Personnel Licensure Interstate Compact,</emphasis> see section 38-3801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>