<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id239"><amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" statutenumber="28-1429.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1429.05</statuteno><catchline>Electronic nicotine delivery system; delivery sale; prohibited; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not, by delivery sale, sell, give, or furnish to any consumer in this state any electronic nicotine delivery system. A violation of this subsection is a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) Any common carrier that knowingly transports any electronic nicotine delivery system in any form for a person who is in violation of subsection (1) of this section is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) In addition to any other penalty, a violation of this section shall constitute a deceptive trade practice under the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act and shall be subject to any remedies or penalties available for a violation of such act.</para><para>(4) All electronic nicotine delivery systems that are sold, given, or furnished in violation of this section are subject to seizure, forfeiture, and destruction and shall not be purchased or sold in the state. The cost of such seizure, forfeiture, and destruction shall be borne by the person from whom the products are seized.</para><para>(5) This section does not apply to the following:</para><para>(a) The shipment of electronic nicotine delivery systems to a foreign trade zone that is established under 19 U.S.C. 81a et seq. and that is located in this state if the products are from outside of this country, were ordered by a distributor in another state, and are not distributed in this state;</para><para>(b) A government employee who is acting in the course of the employee's official duties; or</para><para>(c) The shipment of electronic nicotine delivery systems to a university that is acquiring the systems to conduct basic and applied research, if the systems are exempt from federal excise tax under 26 U.S.C. 5704(a).</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1204, &#167; 16. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 87-306.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>