<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes and Punishments" id="id152" statutenumber="28-1202.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1202.01</statuteno><catchline id="id155">Carrying concealed handgun; locations; restrictions; posting of prohibition; violation; penalty; affirmative defense; applicability.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section and section 28-1204.04, a person, other than a minor or a prohibited person, may carry a concealed handgun anywhere in Nebraska, with or without a permit under the Concealed Handgun Permit Act.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (10) of this section, a person shall not carry a concealed handgun into or onto any place or premises where the person, persons, entity, or entities in control of the place or premises or employer in control of the place or premises has prohibited the carrying of concealed handguns into or onto the place or premises.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (10) of this section, a person shall not carry a concealed handgun into or onto any: Police, sheriff, or Nebraska State Patrol station or office; detention facility, prison, or jail; courtroom or building which contains a courtroom; polling place during a bona fide election; meeting of the governing body of a county, public school district, municipality, or other political subdivision; meeting of the Legislature or a committee of the Legislature; financial institution; professional or semiprofessional athletic event; building, grounds, vehicle, or sponsored activity or athletic event of any school; place of worship; hospital, emergency room, or trauma center; political rally or fundraiser; establishment having a license issued under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act that derives over one-half of its total income from the sale of alcoholic liquor; place where the possession or carrying of a firearm is prohibited by state or federal law; or any other place or premises where handguns are prohibited by state law.</para><para>(4)(a) A financial institution may authorize its security personnel to carry concealed handguns in the financial institution while on duty so long as each member of the security personnel, as authorized, is not otherwise prohibited by state law from possessing or carrying a concealed handgun and is in compliance with sections 28-1202.02 to 28-1202.04.</para><para>(b) A place of worship may authorize its security personnel to carry concealed handguns on its property if:</para><para>(i) Each member of the security personnel, as authorized, is not otherwise prohibited by state law from possessing or carrying a concealed handgun and is in compliance with sections 28-1202.02 to 28-1202.04;</para><para>(ii) Written notice is given to the congregation; and</para><para>(iii) For leased property, the carrying of concealed handguns on the property does not violate the terms of any real property lease agreement between the place of worship and the lessor.</para><para>(5) If a person, persons, entity, or entities in control of the place or premises or an employer in control of the place or premises prohibits the carrying of concealed handguns into or onto the place or premises and such place or premises are open to the public, a person does not violate this section unless the person, persons, entity, or entities in control of the place or premises or employer in control of the place or premises has posted conspicuous notice that carrying a concealed handgun is prohibited in or on the place or premises or has made a request, directly or through an authorized representative or management personnel, that the person remove the concealed handgun from the place or premises.</para><para>(6) A person carrying a concealed handgun in a vehicle or on his or her person while riding in or on a vehicle into or onto any parking area, which is open to the public, used by any location listed in subsection (2) or (3) of this section, does not violate this section if, prior to exiting the vehicle, the handgun is locked inside the glove box, trunk, or other compartment of the vehicle, a storage box securely attached to the vehicle, or, if the vehicle is a motorcycle, other than an autocycle, a hardened compartment securely attached to the motorcycle. This subsection does not apply to any parking area used by such location when the carrying of a concealed handgun into or onto such parking area is prohibited by federal law.</para><para>(7) An employer may prohibit employees or other persons from carrying concealed handguns in vehicles owned by the employer.</para><para>(8) A violation of this section is a Class III misdemeanor for a first offense and a Class I misdemeanor for any second or subsequent offense.</para><para>(9)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (9)(b) of this section, it is an affirmative defense to a violation of subsection (3) of this section that the defendant was engaged in any lawful business, calling, or employment at the time the defendant was carrying a concealed handgun and the circumstances in which the defendant was placed at the time were such as to justify a prudent person in carrying a concealed handgun for the defense of his or her person, property, or family.</para><para>(b) The affirmative defense provided for in this subsection:</para><para>(i) Does not prevent a prosecution for a violation of section 28-1204.04; and</para><para>(ii) Is not available if the defendant refuses to remove the concealed handgun from the place or premises after a person in control of the place or premises has made a request, directly or through an authorized representative or management personnel, that the defendant remove the concealed handgun from the place or premises.</para><para>(10) Subsections (2) and (3) of this section do not apply to a qualified law enforcement officer or qualified retired law enforcement officer carrying a concealed handgun pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 926B or 926C, respectively, as such sections existed on January 1, 2023.</para><para>(11) Action taken in compliance with section 28-1204.04 shall not be a violation of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 454, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB97, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB430, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 120; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2018), &#167; 69-2441; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB77, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1329, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Concealed Handgun Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 69-2427.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>