<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5" opdate="October 1, 2010">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-1213"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">28-1213</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Explosives, destructive
devices, other terms; defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of
sections 28-1213 to 28-1239, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Person means any individual, corporation, company, association,
firm, partnership, limited liability company, society, or joint-stock company;</para>
<para>(2) Business enterprise means any corporation, partnership,
limited liability company, company, or joint-stock company;</para>
<para>(3) Explosive materials means explosives, blasting agents,
and detonators;</para>
<para>(4) Explosives means any chemical compound, mixture, or device,
the primary or common purpose of which is to function by explosion, including,
but not limited to, dynamite and other high explosives, black powder, pellet
powder, initiating explosives, detonators, safety fuses, squibs, detonating
cord, ignited cord, igniters, display fireworks as defined in section 28-1241,
and firecrackers or devices containing more than one hundred thirty milligrams
of explosive composition, but does not include consumer fireworks
as defined in such section, gasoline, kerosene, naphtha, turpentine, benzine,
acetone, ethyl ether, benzol, fixed ammunition and primers for small arms,
safety fuses, or matches;</para>
<para>(5) Blasting agent means any material or mixture intended for blasting which
meets the requirements of 49 C.F.R. part 173, subpart C, Definitions, Classification and Packaging for Class I, as
such subpart existed on January
1, 2010;</para>
<para>(6) Detonator means any device containing an initiating or
primary explosive that is used for initiating detonation. Excluding ignition
or delay charges, a detonator shall not contain more than ten grams of explosive
material per unit. Detonator includes an electric detonator of instantaneous
or delay type, a detonator for use with safety fuses, a detonating cord delay
connector, and a nonelectric detonator of instantaneous or delay type which
consists of detonating cord, shock tube, or any other replacement for electric
leg wires;</para>
<para>(7)(a) Destructive devices means:</para>
<para>(i) Any explosive, incendiary, chemical or biological poison,
or poison gas (A) bomb, (B) grenade, (C) rocket having a propellant charge
of more than four ounces, (D) missile having an explosive or incendiary charge
of more than one-quarter ounce, (E) mine, (F) booby trap, (G) Molotov cocktail,
(H) bottle bomb, (I) vessel or container intentionally caused to rupture or
mechanically explode by expanding pressure from any gas, acid, dry ice, or
other chemical mixture, or (J) any similar device, the primary or common purpose
of which is to explode and to be used as a weapon against any person or property;
or</para>
<para>(ii) Any combination of parts either designed or intended
for use in converting any device into a destructive device as defined in subdivision
(7)(a)(i) of this section from which a destructive device may be readily assembled.</para>
<para>(b) The term destructive device does not include (i) any device
which is neither designed nor redesigned for use as a weapon to be used against
person or property, (ii) any device, although originally designed for use
as a weapon, which is redesigned for use as a signaling, pyrotechnic, line-throwing,
safety, or similar device, (iii) surplus ordnance sold, loaned, or given by
the Secretary of the Army pursuant to 10 U.S.C. 4684(2), 4685, or 4686, as
such sections existed on March 7, 2006, (iv) any other device which the Nebraska
State Patrol finds is not likely to be used as a weapon or is an antique,
or (v) any other device possessed under circumstances negating an intent that
the device be used as a weapon against any person or property;</para>
<para>(8) Federal permittee means any lawful user of explosive materials
who has obtained a federal user permit under 18 U.S.C. chapter 40, as such
chapter existed on January 1,
2010;</para>
<para>(9) Federal licensee means any importer, manufacturer, or
dealer in explosive materials who has obtained a federal importers', manufacturers',
or dealers' license under 18 U.S.C. chapter 40, as such chapter existed on January 1, 2010; and</para>
<para>(10) Smokeless propellants means solid propellants commonly
called smokeless powders in the trade and used in small arms ammunition.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 245; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 893, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 215, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 180; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 163, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 82, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB880, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Even if a pill bottle filled with the powder from fireworks and then taped and equipped with a fuse is considered one of the enumerated devices in subdivision (7)(a)(i) of this section, such pill bottle is not a destructive device if it was neither designed nor redesigned for use as a weapon to be used against person or property. In re Interest of Anthony P., 13 Neb. App. 659, 698 N.W.2d 457 (2005).</para><para>As structured, this section generally applies the exceptions to the definition of "destructive device" to all of the types of destructive device listed under subdivision (7)(a). In re Interest of Joseph S., 13 Neb. App. 636, 698 N.W.2d 212 (2005).</para><para>To the extent the Legislature categorized a dry ice bomb as an explosive, it obviously considered that term in its ordinary and plain meaning rather than a technical definition based upon the specific chemical process utilized. In re Interest of Joseph S., 13 Neb. App. 636, 698 N.W.2d 212 (2005).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>