<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id34"  statutenumber="28-1241"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id36">28-1241</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Fireworks; definitions.</catchline><para>As used in sections 28-1239.01 and 28-1241 to 28-1252, unless
the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Distributor means any person engaged in the business of
making sales of fireworks at wholesale in this state to any person engaged
in the business of making sales of fireworks either as a jobber or as a retailer
or both;</para>
<para>(2) Jobber means any person engaged in the business of making
sales of fireworks at wholesale to any other person engaged in the business
of making sales at retail;</para>
<para>(3) Retailer means any person engaged in the business of making
sales of fireworks at retail to consumers or to persons other than distributors
or jobbers;</para>
<para>(4) Sale includes barter, exchange, or gift or offer therefor
and each such transaction made by any person, whether as principal, proprietor,
agent, servant, or employee;</para>
<para>(5) Fireworks means any composition or device designed for
the purpose of producing a visible or audible effect by combustion, deflagration,
or detonation and which meets the definition of consumer or
special fireworks set forth by the United States Department of Transportation
in Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations;</para>
<para>(6)(a) Consumer fireworks
means any of the
following devices that (i) meet the requirements set forth in 16 C.F.R. parts
1500 and 1507, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2010, and (ii) are
tested and approved by a nationally recognized testing facility or by the
State Fire Marshal:</para>
<para>(A) Any small
firework device designed to produce visible effects by combustion and which
is required to comply with the construction, chemical composition, and labeling
regulations of the United States Consumer Product Safety Commission set forth
in 16 C.F.R., as such regulations existed on January 1, 2010;</para>
<para>(B) Any small
device designed to produce audible effects such as a whistling device;</para>
<para>(C) Any ground
device or firecracker containing fifty milligrams or less of explosive composition;
or</para><para>(D) Any aerial device containing one hundred thirty milligrams or
less of explosive composition.</para><para>(b) Class C explosives as classified by
the United States Department of Transportation shall be considered consumer
fireworks.</para><para>(c) Consumer fireworks does not include:</para><para>(i) Rockets that are mounted
on a stick or wire and project into the air when ignited, with or without
report;</para><para>(ii) Wire sparklers, except that silver and gold sparklers are deemed
to be consumer fireworks until January 1, 2014;</para><para>(iii) Nighttime parachutes;</para>
<para>(iv) Fireworks
that are shot into the air and after coming to the ground cause automatic
ignition due to sufficient temperature;</para><para>(v) Firecrackers that contain more than
fifty milligrams of explosive composition; and</para><para>(vi) Fireworks that have
been tested by the State Fire Marshal as a response to complaints and have
been deemed to be unsafe; and</para><para>(7) Display fireworks means those materials
manufactured exclusively for use in public exhibitions or displays of fireworks
designed to produce visible or audible effects by combustion, deflagration,
or detonation. Display fireworks includes, but is not limited to, firecrackers
containing more than one hundred thirty milligrams of explosive composition,
aerial shells containing more than forty grams of explosive composition, and
other display pieces which exceed the limits for classification as consumer fireworks. Class B explosives, also known as 1.3G explosives, as classified by the United
States Department of Transportation in
49 C.F.R. 172.101, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2010, shall
be considered display fireworks. Display fireworks shall be considered an
explosive as defined in section 28-1213 and shall be subject to sections 28-1213
to 28-1239, except that display fireworks may be purchased, received, and
discharged by the holder of an approved display permit issued pursuant to
section 28-1239.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 273; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 969, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 893, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB880, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>