<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1420"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1420</statuteno><catchline>License requisite for sale; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>It shall be unlawful for any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation to sell, keep for sale, or give away in course of trade, any cigars, tobacco, electronic nicotine delivery systems, cigarettes, or cigarette material to anyone without first obtaining a license as provided in sections 28-1421 and 28-1422. It shall also be unlawful for any wholesaler to sell or deliver any cigars, tobacco, electronic nicotine delivery systems, cigarettes, or cigarette material to any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation who, at the time of such sale or delivery, is not the recipient of a valid tobacco license for the current year to retail the same as provided in such sections. It shall also be unlawful for any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation to purchase or receive, for purposes of resale, any cigars, tobacco, electronic nicotine delivery systems, cigarettes, or cigarette material if such person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation is not the recipient of a valid tobacco license to retail such tobacco products at the time the same are purchased or received. Whoever shall be found guilty of violating this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor for each offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 180, &#167; 1, p. 401; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9849; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 28-1023; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 242; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 28-1023; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 28-1022; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 105; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 28-1022, (1975); </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 187; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB149, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB397, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>