<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" statutenumber="28-1009"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1009</statuteno><catchline>Abandonment; cruel neglect; harassment of a police animal; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A person who intentionally, knowingly, or recklessly abandons or cruelly neglects an animal is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor unless the abandonment or cruel neglect results in serious injury or illness or death of the animal, in which case it is a Class IV felony.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, a person who cruelly mistreats an animal is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor for the first offense and a Class IIIA felony for any subsequent offense.</para><para>(b) A person who cruelly mistreats an animal is guilty of a Class IIIA felony if such cruel mistreatment involves the knowing and intentional torture, repeated beating, or mutilation of the animal.</para><para>(3) A person commits harassment of a police animal if he or she knowingly and intentionally teases or harasses a police animal in order to distract, agitate, or harm the police animal for the purpose of preventing such animal from performing its legitimate official duties. Harassment of a police animal is a Class IV misdemeanor unless the harassment is the proximate cause of the death of the police animal, in which case it is a Class IIIA felony.</para><para>(4) A person convicted of a Class I misdemeanor under this section may also be subject to section 28-1019. A person convicted of a felony under this section shall also be subject to section 28-1019.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 50, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 283, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 82, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 273, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB227, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB329, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB674, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB829, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Under section 28-1019, if a person is convicted of a Class IV felony under this section, the sentencing court shall order such person not to own, possess, or reside with any animal for at least 5 years and no more than 15 years after the date of conviction. State v. Meduna, 18 Neb. App. 818, 794 N.W.2d 160 (2011).</para><para>Under subsection (1) of this section, a person who intentionally, knowingly, or recklessly abandons or cruelly neglects an animal is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor, unless the abandonment or cruel neglect results in serious injury or illness or death of the animal, in which case it is a Class IV felony. State v. Meduna, 18 Neb. App. 818, 794 N.W.2d 160 (2011). </para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>