<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Crimes And Punishments" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="28-1501"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>28-1501</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Justice Reinvestment Working
Group; created; members; study; issues; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that while serious
crime in the State of Nebraska has not increased in the past five years, the
prison population continues to increase as does the amount spent on correctional
issues. The Legislature further finds that a need exists to closely examine
the criminal justice system of the State of Nebraska in order to increase
public safety while concurrently reducing correctional spending and reinvesting
in strategies that decrease crime and strengthen Nebraska communities.</para>
<para>(2) The State of
Nebraska shall work cooperatively with the Council of State Governments Justice
Center to study and identify innovative solutions and evidence-based practices
to develop a data-driven approach to reduce correctional spending and reinvest
savings in strategies that can decrease recidivism and increase public safety.
The Nebraska Justice Reinvestment Working Group is created under the authority
of the executive, legislative, and judicial branches of Nebraska state government
to work with the Council of State Governments Justice Center in this process.</para>
<para>(3) The Governor, the Executive
Board of the Legislative Council, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court
are authorized to take any necessary actions to engage the Council of State
Governments Justice Center in this process and to ensure that the report required
by subsection (6) of this section is delivered. Upon delivery of the report,
the working group shall be dissolved and discharged of any further duties.</para>
<para>(4) The working group shall
be comprised of four members selected by the Governor, four members selected
by the Speaker of the Legislature, four members selected by the Chief Justice
of the Supreme Court, and four representatives of local governments selected
jointly by the Governor, the Speaker of the Legislature, and the Chief Justice.
The Governor, Speaker of the Legislature, and Chief Justice shall serve as
co-chairpersons of the working group.</para><para>(5) The study undertaken in accordance with
this section shall include a broad range of issues, including:</para>
<para>(a) Courts, specialty
courts, and sentencing trends;</para><para>(b) Development of a process to determine
the impact of pending legislation on the criminal justice system;</para>
<para>(c) Analysis of
the prison population and its growth;</para><para>(d) Reported crimes and arrests;</para>
<para>(e) Alternatives
to incarceration;</para><para>(f) Effectiveness of all available offender programs, including
prison programs and community-based programs;</para><para>(g) Reentry programming and
transition;</para><para>(h) Prison programming;</para><para>(i) Community services;</para>
<para>(j) Probation
and parole services;</para><para>(k) Prison admissions and length of stay; and</para>
<para>(l) Recidivism
rates of offenders released from prison, jail, parole, probation, and other
community-based programs.</para><para>(6) The Council of State Governments Justice Center shall make a
final report that includes a summary of the issues studied as required by
subsection (5) of this section, potential legislative solutions for the problems
associated with prison overcrowding, and an estimate of the cost savings for
all policies recommended by the center. The Council of State Governments Justice
Center shall electronically deliver the report to the Governor, the Clerk
of the Legislature, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court by September
1, 2015.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB907, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>