<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-226"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-226</statuteno><catchline>Trust terms; use restricted; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No individual, firm, corporation, or association doing business directly or indirectly in the State of Nebraska shall use the words trust, trust company, trust association, or trust fund as any part of its title except:</para><para>(a) A trust company as defined in section 8-230;</para><para>(b) A trust company chartered and supervised under the laws of the United States or any other state;</para><para>(c) A bank or savings association chartered and supervised under the laws of the United States or any other state, if such bank or savings association has been further chartered to conduct a trust company business;</para><para>(d) A limited partnership to the extent authorized by subdivision (5) of section 67-234;</para><para>(e) An entity required by any other law to use such words; or</para><para>(f) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (1) of this section:</para><para>(a) An organization described in section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of the code may use the words trust or trust fund;</para><para>(b) A trust created by a testamentary or fiduciary document may use the word trust; and</para><para>(c) An account in a financial institution established by or on behalf of trusts referenced in subdivision (b) of this subsection may use the words trust or trust fund.</para><para>(3) A violation of this section is a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 31, &#167; 13, p. 195; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 752; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVIII, &#167; 20, p. 723; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8082; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-221; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-226; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 44, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>