<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-334"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-334</statuteno><catchline>Liquidation; insolvency; powers and duties of Department of Banking and Finance; writs of assistance.</catchline><para>Whenever it appears to the Department of Banking and Finance that the assets of any association or corporation organized under the laws of this state for the purpose set forth in section 8-302 do not equal the liabilities, that it is conducting its business in an unsafe or unauthorized manner, that it is jeopardizing the interest of its members, or that it is unsafe for such association or corporation to transact business, the department shall take possession of the books, records, and assets of every description of such association or corporation, and the department shall have full authority to retain such possession as against any mesne or final process issued by any court against such association or corporation whose property has been taken possession of by the department, pending the further proceedings specified in sections 8-301 to 8-340.01. If such possession is refused by the secretary, managing officer, or person in charge of such association or corporation, the department shall communicate such fact to the Attorney General together with a copy of such order of possession and it shall become the duty of the Attorney General to apply to the Court of Appeals or to the district court or county court of the county where such association or corporation is located or to a judge of any such court for a writ of assistance in placing the department in immediate possession of such association or corporation. It shall be sufficient to authorize the issuance of the writ and the taking possession of such association or corporation under the writ if it is made to appear that possession was refused.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 17, &#167; 19a, p. 94; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 504; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XIX, &#167; 20, p. 732; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8102; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-319; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-334; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 11.</para></source><annotation><para>A borrowing member upon insolvency is required to repay what he actually received, with interest, and is entitled, after debts are paid, to a pro rata dividend with nonborrowing member for what he has paid. Saunders v. State Savings &amp; Loan Assn., 121 Neb. 473, 237 N.W. 572 (1931).</para><para>Alleged sovereign right of city of Lincoln to priority of payment out of assets of bankrupt trust company is inconsistent with Nebraska legislation and not within the common law of the state. City of Lincoln, Neb. v. Ricketts, 84 F.2d 795 (8th Cir. 1936).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>