<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-179" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>8-179</statuteno><catchline id="id00">National bank; reorganization as state bank; procedure; trust company business; charter.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The resulting state bank under section 8-178 shall file a statement with the department, under the oath of its president or cashier, (a) showing that the procedure prescribed by the laws of the United States and by this state have been followed, (b) setting forth in the statement the matter prescribed by sections 8-1901 to 8-1903, and (c) if the national bank has been further chartered to conduct a trust company business within a trust department of the bank, setting forth the matter prescribed by sections 8-159 to 8-162.01. Upon payment of all applicable fees, the department shall issue to such corporation, a charter to transact the business provided for in its articles of incorporation, and, if applicable, a charter to conduct a trust company business within a trust department of the bank.</para><para id="id00">(2) The department may accept good assets of any such national bank, worth not less than par, in lieu of the payment otherwise provided by law for the stock of such resulting bank. When the parties requesting the conversion, merger, or consolidation are officers or directors of either the national bank or of the state bank, they shall be accepted without investigation as parties of integrity and responsibility. Unless the resulting bank is at a different location than the former national or state bank, the department shall recognize the public necessity, convenience, and advantage of permitting the resulting bank and, if applicable, the trust company business within a trust department of the bank, to engage in business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 11, &#167; 1(2), p. 84; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-165.01; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 79, p. 165; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 384, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 75. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>