<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-1,121"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,121</statuteno><catchline>Fugitive violators; rewards.</catchline><para>If any person against whom has been entered any indictment, complaint, or information charging a violation of the statutes of this state relating to banks and banking, which charged violation is a felony, shall be a fugitive from justice, the county attorney of the county wherein such indictment, complaint, or information was entered, shall promptly inform the Governor of the fact, and the Governor may thereupon make public proclamation that a reward of not more than twenty-five hundred dollars will be paid for information resulting in the apprehension of such fugitive. Such reward shall not be paid unless the fugitive is finally convicted of the violation charged by such indictment, complaint, or information, or of some similar violation growing out of the same transaction or out of his connection with the same bank, nor until such conviction shall become final. Upon the finality of such conviction, the county attorney shall certify the fact to the Governor, designating the person or persons entitled to any such reward. Thereupon the Governor shall order the Director of Administrative Services to draw his warrant for the amount of such reward payable to the person or persons entitled thereto, which warrant shall be drawn upon any money in the General Fund of the state treasury not otherwise appropriated, and the State Treasurer shall pay all such warrants.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 42, &#167; 1, p. 184; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-1,119; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-1,109; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 121, p. 185.</para></source></law></legaldoc>