<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" id="id53" statutenumber="8-157"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-157</statuteno><catchline id="id56">Branch banking;
Director of Banking and Finance; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise
provided in this section and section 8-2103, the general business
of every bank shall be transacted at the place of business specified in its
charter.</para>
<para>(2)(a)(i) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(a)(ii) of this section,
with the approval of the director, any bank located in this state may establish
and maintain in this state an unlimited number of branches at which all banking
transactions allowed by law may be made.</para>
<para>(ii) Any bank that owns or controls more than twenty-two percent of
the total deposits in Nebraska, as described in subdivision (2)(c) of section
8-910 and computed in accordance with subsection (3) of section 8-910, or
any bank that is a subsidiary of a bank holding company that owns or controls
more than twenty-two percent of the total deposits in Nebraska, as described
in subdivision (2)(c) of section 8-910 and computed in accordance with subsection
(3) of section 8-910, shall not establish and maintain an unlimited number
of branches as provided in subdivision (2)(a)(i) of this section. With the
approval of the director, a bank as described in this subdivision may establish
and maintain in the county in which such bank is located an unlimited number
of branches at which all banking transactions allowed by law may be made,
except that if such bank is located in a Class I or Class III county, such
bank may establish and maintain in Class I and Class III counties an unlimited
number of branches at which all banking transactions allowed by law may be
made.</para>
<para>(iii) Any bank which establishes and maintains branches pursuant to
subdivision (2)(a)(i) of this section and which subsequently becomes a bank
as described in subdivision (2)(a)(ii) of this section shall not be subject
to the limitations as to location of branches contained in subdivision (2)(a)(ii)
of this section with regard to any such established branch and shall continue
to be entitled to maintain any such established branch as if such bank had
not become a bank as described in subdivision (2)(a)(ii) of this section.</para>
<para>(b) With the approval of the director, any bank or any branch may establish
and maintain a mobile branch at which all banking transactions allowed by
law may be made. Such mobile branch may consist of one or more vehicles which
may transact business only within the county in which such bank or such branch
is located and within counties in this state which adjoin such county.</para>
<para>(c) For purposes of this subsection:</para>
<para>(i) Class I county means a county in this state with a population of
three hundred thousand or more as determined by the most recent federal decennial
census;</para>
<para>(ii) Class II county means a county in this state with a population
of at least two hundred thousand and less than three hundred thousand as determined
by the most recent federal decennial census;</para>
<para>(iii) Class III county means a county in this state with a population
of at least one hundred thousand and less than two hundred thousand as determined
by the most recent federal decennial census; and</para>
<para>(iv) Class IV county means a county in this state with a population
of less than one hundred thousand as determined by the most recent federal
decennial census.</para>
<para>(3) With the approval of the director, a bank may establish and maintain
branches acquired pursuant to section 8-1506 or 8-1516. All banking transactions
allowed by law may be made at such branches.</para>
<para>(4) With the approval of the director, a bank may acquire the assets
and assume the deposits of a branch of another financial institution in Nebraska
if the acquired branch is converted to a branch of the acquiring bank. All
banking transactions allowed by law may be made at a branch acquired pursuant
to this subsection.</para>
<para>(5) With the approval of the director, a bank may establish a branch
pursuant to subdivision (6) of section 8-115.01. All banking transactions
allowed by law may be made at such branch.</para>
<para>(6) The name given to any branch established and maintained pursuant
to this section shall not be substantially similar to the name of any existing
bank or branch which is unaffiliated with the newly created branch and is
located in the same city, village, or county. The name of such newly created
branch shall be approved by the director.</para>
<para>(7) A bank which has a main chartered office or an approved branch located
in the State of Nebraska may, through any of its executive officers, including
executive officers licensed as such pursuant to section 8-139, or designated
agents, conduct a loan closing at a location other than the place of business
specified in the bank's charter or any branch thereof.</para>
<para>(8) A bank which has a main chartered office or approved branch located
in the State of Nebraska may, upon notification to the department, establish
savings account programs at any elementary or secondary school, whether public
or private, that has students who reside in the same city or village as the
main chartered office or branch of the bank, or, if the main office of the
bank is located in an unincorporated area of a county, at any school that
has students who reside in the same unincorporated area. The savings account
programs shall be limited to the establishment of individual student accounts
and the receipt of deposits for such accounts.</para>
<para>(9) Upon receiving an application for a branch to be established pursuant
to subdivision (2)(a) of this section, to establish a mobile branch pursuant
to subdivision (2)(b) of this section, to acquire a branch of another financial
institution pursuant to subsection (4) of this section, to establish or acquire a branch pursuant to subsection
(1) of section 8-2103, or to move the location of an established
branch other than a move made pursuant to subdivision (6) of section 8-115.01,
the director shall hold a public hearing on the matter if he or she determines,
in his or her discretion, that the condition of the applicant bank warrants
a hearing. If the director determines that the condition of the bank does
not warrant a hearing, the director shall (a) publish a notice of the filing
of the application in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where
the proposed branch or mobile branch would be located, the expense of which
shall be paid by the applicant bank, and (b) give notice of such application
to all financial institutions located within the county where the proposed
branch or mobile branch would be located and to such other interested parties
as the director may determine. The director shall send the notice to financial
institutions by first-class mail, postage prepaid, or electronic mail. Electronic
mail may be used if the financial institution agrees in advance to receive
such notices by electronic mail. A financial institution may designate one
office for receipt of any such notice if it has more than one office located
within the county where such notice is to be sent or a main office in a county
other than the county where such notice is to be sent. If the director receives
any substantive objection to the proposed branch or mobile branch within fifteen
days after publication of such notice, he or she shall hold a hearing on the
application. Notice of a hearing held pursuant to this subsection shall be
published for two consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation
in the county where the proposed branch or mobile branch would be located.
The date for hearing the application shall not be more than ninety days after
the filing of the application and not less than thirty days after the last
publication of notice of hearing. The expense of any publication and mailing
required by this section shall be paid by the applicant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 153; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-1,118; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-1,105; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 141; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-1,105; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 57, p. 158; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 312, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 269, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 77, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 58, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 252, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1026, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 295, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 625, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 983, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 615, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 703, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 272, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 956, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 190, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 782, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 470, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 757, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 456, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 599, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1275, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 56, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 136, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 351, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1089, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1094, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB890, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB963, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>April 7, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Subsection (3) of this section does not indicate that the approval of the director of the Department of Banking and Finance absolves a bank from any obligations it may owe to the minority shareholders, that the director is required to disapprove a merger that is unfair to the minority shareholders, or that the director is empowered to require a bank to pay the fair value of a dissenter's shares. Stoneman v. United Neb. Bank, 254 Neb. 477, 577 N.W.2d 271 (1998).</para><para>Detached facility approximately one block from bank, providing drive-in and walk-in teller stations offering most banking services, is a branch bank. Nebraskans for Independent Banking, Inc. v. Omaha Nat. Bank, 530 F.2d 755 (8th Cir. 1976). (Opinion vacated and cause remanded to district court for further proceedings in light of Supreme Court per curiam opinion, 426 U.S. 310, dated June 7, 1976.)</para><para>Federal district court would not abstain from deciding whether state banking statute was properly adopted by Nebraska Legislature where analysis of the applicable Nebraska case law left no doubt that such statute was invalid. Nebraskans for Independent Banking, Inc. v. Omaha Nat. Bank, 423 F.Supp. 519 (D. Neb. 1976).</para><para>Branch banking is illegal in Nebraska. Farris v. Indian Hills Nat. Bank, 244 F.Supp. 594 (D. Neb. 1964).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>