<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 15, 2010">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" id="id6" statutenumber="8-115.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">8-115.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Banks; new charter;
transfer of charter; procedure.</catchline><para>When an application required
by section 8-120 is made by a corporation, the following procedures shall
be followed:</para>
<para>(1) Except as provided for in subdivision (2) of this section, when
application is made for a new bank charter, a public hearing shall be held
on each application. Notice of the filing of the application shall be published
by the department for three weeks in a legal newspaper published in or of
general circulation in the county where the applicant proposes to operate
the bank. The date for hearing the application shall be not less than thirty
days after the last publication of notice of hearing and not more than ninety
days after the application has been accepted for filing by the director as
substantially complete unless the applicant agrees to a later date. Notice
of the filing of the application shall be sent by the department to all financial
institutions located in the county where the applicant proposes to operate;</para>
<para>(2) When application is made for a new bank charter and the director
determines, in his or her discretion, that the conditions of subdivision (3)
of this section are met, then the public hearing requirement of subdivision
(1) of this section shall only be required if, (a) after publishing a notice
of the proposed application in a newspaper of general circulation in the county
where the main office of the applicant is to be located and (b) after giving
notice to all financial institutions located within such county, the director
receives a substantive objection to the application within fifteen days after
the first day of publication;</para>
<para>(3) The director shall consider the following in each application before
the public hearing requirement of subdivision (1) of this section may be waived:</para>
<para>(a) Whether the experience, character, and general fitness of the applicant
and of the applicant's officers and directors are such
as to warrant belief that the applicant will operate the business honestly,
fairly, and efficiently;</para>
<para>(b) Whether the length of time that the applicant or a majority of the
applicant's officers, directors, and shareholders have been involved in the
business of banking in this state has been for a minimum of five consecutive
years; and</para>
<para>(c) Whether the condition of financial institutions currently owned
by the applicant, the applicant's holding company, if any, or the applicant's
officers, directors, or shareholders is such as to indicate that a hearing
on the current application would not be necessary;</para>
<para>(4) Except as provided in subdivision (6) of this section, when application
is made for transfer of a bank charter and move of the main office of a bank
to any location other than within the corporate limits of the city or village
of its original charter or, if such bank charter is not located in a city
or village, then for transfer outside the county in which it is located, the
director shall hold a hearing on the matter if he or she determines, in his
or her discretion, that the condition of the applicant warrants a hearing.
If the director determines that the condition of the applicant does not warrant
a hearing, the director shall (a) publish a notice of the filing of the application
in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where the proposed main
office and charter of the applicant would be located and (b) give notice of
such application to all financial institutions located within the county where
the proposed main office and charter would be located and to such other interested
parties as the director may determine. If the director receives any substantive
objection to the proposed relocation within fifteen days after the first day
of publication, he or she shall hold a hearing on the application. Notice
of a hearing held pursuant to this subdivision shall be published for two
consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where
the main office would be located. The date for hearing the application shall
be not less than thirty days after the last publication of notice of hearing
and not more than ninety days after the application has been accepted for
filing by the director as substantially complete unless the applicant agrees
to a later date. When the persons making application for transfer of a main
office and charter are officers or directors of the bank, there is a rebuttable
presumption that such persons are parties of integrity and responsibility;</para>
<para>(5) Except as provided in subdivision (6) of this section, when application
is made for a move of any bank's main office within the city, village, or
county, if not chartered within a city or village, of its original charter,
the director shall publish notice of the proposed move in a newspaper of general
circulation in the county where the main office of the applicant is located
and shall give notice of such intended move to all financial institutions
located within the county where such bank is located. If the director receives
a substantive objection to such move within fifteen days after publishing
such notice, he or she shall publish an additional notice and hold a hearing
as provided in subdivision (1) of this section;</para>
<para>(6) With the approval of the director, a bank may move its main office
and charter to the location of a branch of the bank without public notice
or hearing as long as (a) the condition of the bank, in the discretion of
the director, does not warrant a hearing and (b) the branch (i) is located
in Nebraska, (ii) has been in operation for at least one year as a branch
of the bank or was acquired by the bank pursuant to section 8-1506 or 8-1516,
and (iii) is simultaneously relocated to the original main office location;</para>
<para>(7) The director shall send any notice to financial institutions required
by this section by first-class mail, postage prepaid, or electronic mail.
Electronic mail may be used if the financial institution agrees in advance
to receive such notices by electronic mail.
A financial institution may designate one office for receipt of any such notice
if it has more than one office located within the county where such notice
is to be sent or a main office in a county other than the county where such
notice is to be sent;</para>
<para>(8) The expense of any publication and mailing required by this section
shall be paid by the applicant; and</para>
<para>(9) Notwithstanding any provision of this section, the director shall
take immediate action on any charter application or applications concerned
without the benefit of a hearing in the case of an emergency so declared by
the Governor, the Secretary of State, and the director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 25, &#167; 1, p. 191; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 19, &#167; 2, p. 117; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 3;  </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 721, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 220, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB890, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>