<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-138"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-138</statuteno><catchline>Deposits; receiving when insolvent; prohibition; penalty.</catchline><para>No bank shall accept or receive on deposit for any purpose any money, bank bills, United States treasury notes or currency, or other notes, bills, checks, drafts, credits, or currency, when such bank is insolvent; and if any bank shall receive or accept on deposit any such deposits when such bank is insolvent, the officer, agent, or employee knowingly receiving or accepting or being accessory to, or permitting or conniving at the receiving or accepting on deposit therein or thereby, any such deposit shall be guilty of a Class III felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 30, p. 80; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 309; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 30, p. 697; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8010; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-147; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-147; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 38, p. 149; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 44.</para></source><annotation><para>Insolvent bank has no power to receive deposits. Torgeson v. Department of Trade and Commerce, 127 Neb. 38, 254 N.W. 735 (1934).</para><para>In prosecution against banker for receiving deposits knowing bank to be insolvent, intentional fraud, deceit, false reports and wrongful entries on bank books are not elements of the offense as defined by statute. Flannigan v. State, 125 Neb. 519, 250 N.W. 908 (1933).</para><para>Instruction to jury defining insolvency of bank as being when the actual cash value of its assets was insufficient to pay its liabilities to depositors, or when it was unable to meet the demands of its creditors in the usual and ordinary manner, was not prejudicial to defendant. Gutru v. State, 125 Neb. 506, 250 N.W. 913 (1933).</para><para>Conviction under this section sustained upon evidence that deposits were received when real value of assets were less than liabilities of bank, and defendant had knowledge of the deposits and insolvency. Flannigan v. State, 125 Neb. 163, 249 N.W. 609 (1933).</para><para>Banking department has no authority to authorize a bank, its officers or employees, to violate this section. State v. Kastle, 120 Neb. 758, 235 N.W. 458 (1931).</para><para>Constitutionality of this section sustained. Westbrook v. State, 120 Neb. 625, 234 N.W. 579 (1931).</para><para>This section bearing penalty contrasted with section providing no penalty. State ex rel. Davis v. Farmers State Bank of Winside, 112 Neb. 597, 200 N.W. 173 (1924).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>