<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-378"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-378</statuteno><catchline>Mutual association; conversion to capital stock association; authorized; plan of conversion; approval required.</catchline><para>(1) Any state or federal mutual association, if substantial business benefit to the applicant will result, and if otherwise permitted by federal law and regulations, may apply to convert to a state or federal capital stock association, in accordance with the provisions set forth in sections 8-356 to 8-384 and in any rules and regulations that may be adopted or promulgated by the Department of Banking and Finance.</para><para>(2) Any applicant subject to subsection (1) of this section seeking to convert its corporate form pursuant to this section shall first obtain approval of a plan of conversion by resolution adopted by not less than a two-thirds majority vote of the total number of directors authorized.</para><para>(3) Upon approval of a plan of conversion by the board of directors, such plan and the resolution approving it shall be submitted to the department. The department may approve or disapprove the plan of conversion in its discretion, but shall not approve the plan unless a finding is made, after appropriate examination, that substantial business benefit to the applicant will result, that the plan of conversion is fair and equitable, that the interests of the applicant, its members or stockholders, its savings account holders and the public are adequately protected, and that the converting applicant has complied with the requirements of this section. If the department approves the plan of conversion, the approval, which shall be in writing and sent to the home office of the converting applicant, may prescribe terms and conditions to be fulfilled either before or after the conversion to cause the applicant to conform with the requirements of sections 8-356 to 8-384. If the department disapproves the plan of conversion, the objections shall be stated in writing and sent to the home office of the converting applicant, and the applicant afforded an opportunity to amend and resubmit the plan within a reasonable time as prescribed by the department. In the event that the department disapproves the plan after such resubmission, written notice of such final disapproval shall be sent by certified mail to the applicant's home office.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 500, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 13.</para></source></law></legaldoc>