<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-231"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-231</statuteno><catchline>Trust company; substituted in fiduciary capacity for affiliated bank; application; court order; filing.</catchline><para>(1) Any trust company which has been duly authorized to commence the business for which it is organized and which has made the pledge of securities required by sections 8-209 and 8-210 may file an application in the county court of the county in which an affiliated bank is located requesting that it be substituted, except as may be expressly excluded in such application, in every fiduciary capacity for such affiliated bank specified in the application, and such specified affiliated bank shall join in such application. Such application may be made by the trust company seeking substitution and need not list the fiduciary capacities in which substitution is proposed to be made. For purposes of this section, affiliated bank with respect to a trust company shall mean any bank incorporated under the laws of this state and any national banking association having its principal office in this state, more than fifty percent of the voting stock of which is owned directly or indirectly by the same bank holding company as defined in the United States Bank Holding Company Act, as amended, that owns directly or indirectly more than fifty percent of the voting stock of such trust company. The county court may require such notice as it deems necessary.</para><para>(2) When the county court finds that such trust company has been duly authorized to commence the business for which it is organized and that it has made a pledge of securities in accordance with sections 8-209 and 8-210, the county court may enter an order substituting such trust company in every fiduciary capacity for the specified affiliated bank except as may be otherwise specified in the application.</para><para>(3) Upon entry of such order, such trust company shall, without further act, be substituted in every such fiduciary capacity, and such application may be evidenced by filing a copy of the order with the clerk of any county court in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 338, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 50.</para></source></law></legaldoc>