<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id4"><sectno id="id5" opdate=" March 20, 2008">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" id="id6" statutenumber="8-910"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">8-910</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Unlawful acts; authorized ownership or control of banks; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful, except as provided in this section, for:</para><para>(a) Any action to be taken that causes any company to become a bank holding company;</para><para>(b) Any action to be taken that causes a bank to become a subsidiary of a bank holding company;</para><para>(c) Any bank holding company to acquire direct or indirect ownership or control of any voting shares of any bank if, after such acquisition, such company will directly or indirectly own or control more than twenty-five percent of the voting shares of such bank;</para><para>(d) Any bank holding company or subsidiary thereof, other than a bank, to acquire all or substantially all of the assets of a bank; or</para><para>(e) Any bank holding company to merge or consolidate with any other bank holding company.</para><para>(2) The prohibition set forth in subsection (1) of this section shall not apply if:</para><para>(a)(i) The bank holding company is registered with the department as of September 29, 1995, as a bank holding company for any bank or banks; or (ii) the bank holding company registers with the department in accordance with the provisions of section 8-913 as a bank holding company;</para><para>(b) The bank holding company does not have a name deceptively similar to an existing unaffiliated bank or bank holding company located in Nebraska;</para><para>(c) Upon any action referred to in subsection (1) of this section and subject to subsection (3) of this section, the bank or banks so owned or controlled would have deposits in Nebraska in an amount no greater than twenty-two percent of the total deposits of all banks in Nebraska plus the total deposits, savings accounts, passbook accounts, and shares in savings and loan associations and building and loan associations in Nebraska as determined by the director on the basis of the most recent midyear reports, except as provided in subsections (4), (5), and (6) of this section;</para><para>(d) The bank holding company is adequately capitalized and adequately managed;</para><para>(e) The bank holding company complies with sections 8-1501 to 8-1505 if the bank or banks to be acquired are chartered in this state under the Nebraska Banking Act; and</para><para>(f) The bank holding company, if an out-of-state bank holding company, complies with the limitations of section 8-911.</para><para>(3) If any person, association, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation owns or controls twenty-five percent or more of the voting stock of any bank holding company acquiring a bank and any such person, association, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation owns or controls twenty-five percent or more of the voting stock of any other bank or bank holding company in Nebraska, then the total deposits of such other bank or banks and of all banks in Nebraska owned or controlled by such bank holding company shall be included in the computation of the total deposits of a bank holding company acquiring a bank.</para><para>(4) A bank or bank holding company which acquires and holds all or substantially all of the voting stock of one credit card bank under sections 8-1512 and 8-1513 shall not have such acquisition count against the limitations set forth in subdivision (2)(c) of this section.</para><para>(5) A bank holding company which acquired an institution or which formed a bank which acquired an institution under sections 8-1506 to 8-1510 or which acquired any assets and liabilities from the Resolution Trust Corporation or the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation prior to January 1, 1994, shall not have such acquisition or formation count against the limitations set forth in subdivision (2)(c) of this section.</para><para>(6) A bank which accepts deposits from nonresidents of Nebraska and voluntarily segregates the reporting of such deposits in such a manner as to allow the director to determine the amounts of such deposits shall not have such deposits count against the limitations set forth in subdivision (2)(c) of this section. The bank shall report the amount of such deposits, if so segregated, to the director prior to October 1 of each year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 384, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1089, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167;  13.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Banking Act,</emphasis> see section 8-101.01.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>
