<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-219"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-219</statuteno><catchline>Liquidation; reorganization; adjudication of insolvency; grounds; powers and duties of Department of Banking and Finance.</catchline><para>Whenever (1) it appears to the Department of Banking and Finance from any examination or report provided for by the Nebraska Trust Company Act that the capital stock of any trust company transacting business under the act is impaired, or that the trust company is conducting its business in an unsafe or unauthorized manner, or that the trust company is endangering the interest of the beneficiaries for whom it holds property in trust, (2) the officers or employees of the trust company refuse to submit its books, papers, and affairs to the inspection of any examiner, (3) any officer thereof refuses to be examined upon oath touching the affairs of the trust company, or (4) from any examination or report provided for by law, the department has reason to conclude that the trust company is in an unsafe or unsound condition to transact the business for which it is organized or that it is unsafe and inexpedient for it to continue its business, the department shall take charge of the trust company and proceed to reorganize or to liquidate the trust company in the manner provided for the liquidation of insolvent banks. If the trust company neglects or refuses to observe any lawful order of the department, then the department may cause a suit to be brought in the name of the State of Nebraska upon the relation of the Department of Banking and Finance against the trust company in the district court of the county in which the trust company is chartered for the purpose of having the trust company adjudged insolvent and its business wound up.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 35, &#167; 3, p. 163; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 38, &#167; 6, p. 159; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-215; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 81, p. 177; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-215; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-219; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 46.</para></source></law></legaldoc>