<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1,107" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,107</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Insolvent banks; claims; listing and classification; notice to claimant; filing of objection; powers and duties of director.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Upon the expiration of the time fixed for presentation of claims, the director shall thoroughly investigate all claims and file with the clerk of the district court of the county in which the main office of the insolvent bank is located a complete list of all claims against which he or she knows of no defense and which, in his or her judgment, are valid, designating their priority of payment, together with a list of the claims which, in his judgment, are invalid. He or she shall also file an order allowing or rejecting such claims as classified.</para><para id="id00">(2) When the director reclassifies or rejects a claim, which rejection shall be made when he or she doubts the legality of a claim, he or she shall serve written notice of such reclassification or rejection upon the claimant by either registered or certified mail and file, with the clerk of the district court of the county in which the main office of the bank is located, an affidavit of the service of such notice, which affidavit shall be prima facie evidence of such service. Such notice shall state the time and place for the filing by claimant of his or her objections to the classification, reclassification, or rejection of his or her claim.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1923, c. 191, &#167; 22, p. 449; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-199; </para><para>Laws 1930, Spec. Sess., c. 6, &#167; 9, p. 30; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 63, p. 168; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-199; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-193; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 242, &#167; 4, p. 818; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-193; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 107, p. 179; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 104. </para></source><annotation><para>This section does not constitute an unlawful delegation of judicial power to an executive department of government. Department of Banking v. Hedges, 136 Neb. 382, 286 N.W. 277 (1939).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>