<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-705"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>8-705</statuteno><catchline>Examinations, reports of other examiners;
Director of Banking and Finance may accept.</catchline><para>The Director
of Banking and Finance is authorized to accept in his or her discretion, in
lieu of any examination authorized by the laws of this state to be conducted
by his or her department of a banking institution, the examination that may
have been made of such banking institution within a reasonable period by the
Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the Federal Reserve Board, the Comptroller
of the Currency, the Consumer
Financial Protection Bureau, or a foreign state agency if a copy
of the examination is furnished to the director. The director may also in
his or her discretion accept any report relative to the condition of a banking
institution which may have been obtained by the Federal Deposit Insurance
Corporation, the Federal Reserve Board, the Comptroller of the Currency, the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, or
a foreign state agency within a reasonable period in lieu of a report authorized
by the laws of this state to be required of such institution by his or her
department if a copy of such report is furnished to the director.</para>
<para>As used in this section, unless the context otherwise requires, foreign
state agency shall mean any duly constituted regulatory or supervisory agency
which has authority over financial institutions and which is created under
the laws of any other state, any territory of the United States, Puerto Rico,
Guam, American Samoa, the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, or the Virgin
Islands or which is operating under the code of law for the District of Columbia.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 8, &#167; 5, p. 74; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-705; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 375, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB213, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>