<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" id="id25" statutenumber="8-143.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>8-143.01</statuteno><catchline id="id28">Extension of credit; limits; credit report; violation; penalty; powers of director.</catchline><para>(1) No bank shall extend credit to any of its executive officers, directors, or principal shareholders or to any related interest of such persons in an amount that, when aggregated with the amount of all other extensions of credit by the bank to that person and to all related interests of that person, exceeds the higher of twenty-five thousand dollars or five percent of the bank's unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus unless (a) the extension of credit has been approved in advance by a majority vote of the entire board of directors of the bank, a record of which shall be made and kept as a part of the records of such bank, and (b) the interested party has abstained from participating directly or indirectly in such vote.</para><para>(2) No bank shall extend credit to any of its executive officers, directors, or principal shareholders or to any related interest of such persons in an amount that, when aggregated with the amount of all other extensions of credit by the bank to that person and to all related interests of that person, exceeds five hundred thousand dollars except by complying with the requirements of subdivisions (1)(a) and (b) of this section.</para><para>(3) No bank shall extend credit to any of its executive officers, and no such executive officer shall borrow from or otherwise become indebted to his or her bank, except in the amounts and for the purposes set forth in subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(4) A bank shall be authorized to extend credit to any of its executive officers:</para><para>(a) In any amount to finance the education of such executive officer's children;</para><para>(b)(i) In any amount to finance or refinance the purchase, construction, maintenance, or improvement of a residence of such executive officer if the extension of credit is secured by a first lien on the residence and the residence is owned or is expected to be owned after the extension of credit by the executive officer and (ii) in the case of a refinancing, only the amount of the refinancing used to repay the original extension of credit, together with the closing costs of the refinancing, and any additional amount thereof used for any of the purposes enumerated in this subdivision are included within this category of credit;</para><para>(c) In any amount if the extension of credit is (i) secured by a perfected security interest in bonds, notes, certificates of indebtedness, or treasury bills of the United States or in other such obligations fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by the United States, (ii) secured by unconditional takeout commitments or guarantees of any department, agency, bureau, board, commission, or establishment of the United States or any corporation wholly owned directly or indirectly by the United States, or (iii) secured by a perfected security interest in a segregated deposit account in the lending bank; or</para><para>(d) For any other purpose not specified in subdivisions (a), (b), and (c) of this subsection if the aggregate amount of such other extensions of credit to such executive officer does not exceed, at any one time, the greater of two and one-half percent of the bank's unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus or twenty-five thousand dollars, but in no event greater than one hundred thousand dollars or the amount of the bank's lending limit as prescribed in section 8-141, whichever is less.</para><para>(5)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, the board of directors of a bank may obtain a credit report from a recognized credit agency, on an annual basis, for any or all of its executive officers.</para><para>(b) Subdivision (a) of this subsection does not apply to any executive officer if such officer is excluded by a resolution of the board of directors or by the bylaws of the bank from participating in the major policymaking functions of the bank and does not actually participate in the major policymaking functions of the bank.</para><para>(6) No bank shall extend credit to any of its executive officers, directors, or principal shareholders or to any related interest of such persons in an amount that, when aggregated with the amount of all other extensions of credit by the bank to that person and to all related interests of that person, exceeds the lending limit of the bank as prescribed in section 8-141.</para><para>(7)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, no bank shall extend credit to any of its executive officers, directors, or principal shareholders or to any related interest of such persons unless the extension of credit (i) is made on substantially the same terms, including interest rates and collateral, as, and following credit-underwriting procedures that are not less stringent than, those prevailing at the time for comparable transactions by the bank with other persons that are not covered by this section and who are not employed by the bank and (ii) does not involve more than the normal risk of repayment or present other unfavorable features.</para><para>(b) Nothing in subdivision (a) of this subsection shall prohibit any extension of credit made by a bank pursuant to a benefit or compensation program under the provisions of 12 C.F.R. 215.4(a)(2), as such regulation existed on January 1, 2024.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Executive officer means a person who participates or has authority to participate, other than in the capacity of director, in the major policymaking functions of the bank, whether or not the officer has an official title, the title designates such officer as an assistant, or such officer is serving without salary or other compensation. Executive officer includes the chairperson of the board of directors, the president, all vice presidents, the cashier, the corporate secretary, and the treasurer, unless the executive officer is excluded by a resolution of the board of directors or by the bylaws of the bank from participating, other than in the capacity of director, in the major policymaking functions of the bank, and the executive officer does not actually participate in such functions. A manager or assistant manager of a branch of a bank shall not be considered to be an executive officer unless such individual participates or is authorized to participate in the major policymaking functions of the bank; and</para><para>(b) Unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus means the sum of:</para><para>(i) The total equity capital of the bank reported on its most recent consolidated report of condition filed under section 8-166;</para><para>(ii) Any subordinated notes and debentures approved as an addition to the bank's capital structure by the appropriate federal banking agency; and</para><para>(iii) Any valuation reserves created by charges to the bank's income reported on its most recent consolidated report of condition filed under section 8-166.</para><para>(9) Any executive officer, director, or principal shareholder of a bank or any other person who intentionally violates this section or who aids, abets, or assists in a violation of this section is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para><para>(10) The Director of Banking and Finance may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section, including rules and regulations defining or further defining terms used in this section, consistent with the provisions of 12 U.S.C. 84 and implementing Regulation O as such section and regulation existed on January 1, 2024.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 611, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB812, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB258, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB363, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB707, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB279, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 39. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB279, section 1, with LB1074, section 39, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB279 became effective July 19, 2024. Changes made by LB1074 became operative April 18, 2024.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>