<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-205.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-205.01</statuteno><catchline>Fidelity bond; requirements; director; powers and duties.</catchline><para>Each trust company doing business under the Nebraska Trust Company Act shall obtain a fidelity bond, naming the trust company as obligee, in an amount to be fixed by the department. The bond shall be issued by an authorized insurer and shall be conditioned to protect and indemnify the trust company from loss of money or other personal property, including that for which the trust company is responsible, which it may sustain through or by reason of fraud, dishonesty, forgery, theft, embezzlement, wrongful abstraction, misapplication, misappropriation, or other dishonest or criminal act of or by any of its officers or employees. The bond may contain a deductible clause in an amount to be approved by the Director of Banking and Finance. An executed copy of the bond shall be filed with and approved by the director and shall remain a part of the records of the department. If the premium of the bond is not paid, the bond shall not be canceled or subject to cancellation unless at least ten days' advance notice, in writing, is filed with the department. No bond which is current with respect to premium payments shall be canceled or subject to cancellation unless at least forty-five days' advance notice, in writing, is filed with the department. The bond shall always be open to public inspection during the office hours of the department. In the event a bond is canceled, the department may take whatever action it deems appropriate in connection with the continued operation of the trust company involved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 956, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 37.</para></source></law></legaldoc>