
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" id="id43" statutenumber="8-122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-122</statuteno><catchline id="id46">Issuance of charter to transact business.</catchline><para>(1) After the examination and approval by the Director of Banking and Finance of the application required by section 8-120, if the director upon investigation and after any public hearing on the application held pursuant to section 8-115.01 shall be satisfied that the stockholders, directors, and officers of the corporation applying for such charter are parties of integrity and responsibility, that the requirements of section 8-702 have been met, and that the public necessity, convenience, and advantage will be promoted by permitting such corporation to engage in business as a bank, the department shall, upon the payment of the required fees, and, upon the filing with the department of a statement, under oath, of the president, secretary, or treasurer, that the paid-up capital stock and surplus have been paid in, as determined by the Director of Banking and Finance in accordance with section 8-116, issue to such corporation a charter to transact the business of a bank in this state provided for in its articles of incorporation. In the case of a bank organized to merge with an existing bank, there shall be a rebuttable presumption that the public necessity, convenience, and advantage will be met by the merger of the two banks, except that such presumption shall not apply when the new bank that is formed by the merger is at a different location than that of the former existing bank. Any application for merger under this subsection shall be subject to section 8-1516.</para><para>(2) On payment of the required fees and the receipt of the charter, such corporation may begin to conduct a bank.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 16, p. 74; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 8, &#167; 1, p. 79; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 295; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 16, p. 692; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 302, &#167; 2, p. 958; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7997; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-127; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-129; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 12, &#167; 1, p. 77; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 10, &#167; 1, p. 128; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-129; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 22, p. 142; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 19, &#167; 9, p. 120; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 916, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 252, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1275, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1094, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB851, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 22. </para></source><annotation><para>The Department of Banking and Finance is required to hold a public hearing to determine, among other things, the integrity of the parties applying for a bank merger and the fairness of the merger to minority shareholders. Schmid v. Clarke, Inc., 245 Neb. 856, 515 N.W.2d 665 (1994).</para><para>When more than one application is filed for a given license, the Department of Banking and Finance should compare the applications rather than follow a strict first-to-file rule. Southwestern Bank &amp; Trust Co. v. Department of Banking and Finance, 206 Neb. 599, 294 N.W.2d 343 (1980).</para><para>This section involves the granting of a bank charter and not the removal of one. Douglas County Bank v. Department of Banking, 187 Neb. 545, 192 N.W.2d 401 (1971).</para><para>Finding of Department of Banking in the language of this section is adequate to sustain the issuance of a charter. First Nat. Bank &amp; Trust Co. v. Ley, 182 Neb. 164, 153 N.W.2d 743 (1967).</para><para>When an application is made to Department of Banking for a charter to do a banking business, it is its duty to determine, after proper investigation, the integrity and responsibility of the persons making the application. Shumway v. Warrick, 108 Neb. 652, 189 N.W. 301 (1922).</para><para>Where it appears that Department of Banking, in granting a charter, has acted within its jurisdiction, and all the jurisdictional facts essential to uphold its final order are sustained by competent evidence, its action will be upheld on review in error proceedings. In re Commercial State Bank, 105 Neb. 248, 179 N.W.1021 (1920).</para><para>Under this section, prior to its amendment in 1921, where a corporation filed the oath that the capital stock had been paid in, and if parties were of integrity and responsibility and paid the fees required by law, the corporation was entitled to a charter irrespective of the number of banks in the locality. State ex rel. Woolridge v. Morehead, 100 Neb. 864, 161 N.W. 569 (1917), L.R.A. 1917D 310 (1917).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>