<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-167"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-167</statuteno><catchline>Banks; reports to department; contents; publication.</catchline><para>Each report required by section 8-166 shall exhibit in detail and under appropriate headings the resources and liabilities of the bank at the close of business on any past day specified by the call for report and shall be submitted to the department within thirty days, or as may be required by the department, after the receipt of requisition for the report. A summary of such report in the form prescribed by the department shall be published one time in a legal newspaper in the place where such bank is located. If there is no legal newspaper in the place where the bank is located, then such summary shall be published in a legal newspaper published in the same county or, if none is published in the county, in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the county. Such publication shall be at the expense of such bank. Proof of such publication shall be transmitted to the department within thirty days, or as may be required by the department, from the date fixed for such report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 18, p. 75; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 297; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 18, p. 693; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7999; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-130; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 20, p. 145; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 10, &#167; 2, p. 81; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-130; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-132; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 67, p. 161; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 641, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Purpose of Legislature was to require a full statement of the transactions of the officers concerning the business done by them in their official capacities as officers and agents of the bank. Wentz v. State, 108 Neb. 597, 188 N.W. 467 (1922).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>