<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-707"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-707</statuteno><catchline>Insolvent banks; loans from Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; security; sale of assets to corporation; conditions.</catchline><para>With respect to any banking institution which is now or may hereafter be closed on account of inability to meet the demands of its depositors, or by action of the Director of Banking and Finance, or of a court, or by action of its directors, or in the event of its insolvency or suspension, the Director of Banking and Finance, or the receiver or liquidator of such institution with the permission of the Director of Banking and Finance may borrow from the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and furnish any part or all of the assets of said institution to the corporation as security for a loan from the same; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that where the corporation is acting as such receiver or liquidator, the order of a court of record of competent jurisdiction shall be first obtained approving such loan. The Director of Banking and Finance, upon the order of a court of record of competent jurisdiction, and upon a like order and with the permission of the Director of Banking and Finance the receiver or liquidator of any such institution, may sell to the corporation any part or all of the assets of such institution. The provisions of this section shall not be construed to limit the power of any banking institution, the Director of Banking and Finance, or receivers or liquidators, to pledge or sell assets in accordance with any existing law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 8, &#167; 7, p. 75; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-407; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-707. </para></source></law></legaldoc>