<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking"  statutenumber="8-117" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-117</statuteno><catchline>Conditional bank charter; application; contents; hearing; notice; expenses; conversion to full bank charter; extension; written request; notice of expiration.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The director may grant approval for a conditional bank charter which may remain inactive for an initial period of up to eighteen months.</para><para>(b) The purpose for which a conditional bank charter may be granted is limited to the acquisition or potential acquisition of a financial institution which (i) is located in this state or which has a branch in this state and (ii) has been determined to be troubled or failing by its primary state or federal regulator.</para><para>(2) A person or persons organizing for and desiring to obtain a conditional bank charter shall make, under oath, and transmit to the department an application prescribed by the department, to include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) The name of the proposed bank;</para><para>(b) A draft copy of the articles of incorporation of the proposed bank;</para><para>(c) The names, addresses, financial condition, and business history of the proposed stockholders, officers, and directors of the proposed bank;</para><para>(d) The sources and amounts of capital that would be available to the proposed bank; and</para><para>(e) A preliminary business plan describing the operations of the proposed bank.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of a substantially completed application for a conditional bank charter and payment of the fee required by section 8-602, the director may, in his or her discretion, hold a public hearing on the application. If a hearing is to be held, notice of the filing of the application and the date of hearing thereon shall be published by the department for three weeks in a minimum of two newspapers with general circulation in Nebraska. The newspapers shall be selected at the director's discretion, except that the director shall consider the county or counties of residence of the proposed members of the board of directors of the proposed conditional bank charter in making such selection. The date for hearing the application shall be not less than thirty days after the last publication of notice of hearing. Notice shall also be sent by first-class mail to the main office of all financial institutions doing business in the state. Electronic mail may be used if a financial institution agrees in advance to receive such notice by electronic mail.</para><para>(4) If the director determines that a hearing on the application for a conditional bank charter is not necessary, then the department shall publish a notice of the proposed application in a minimum of two newspapers of general circulation in Nebraska. The newspapers shall be selected in accordance with subsection (3) of this section. The department shall send notice of the application by first-class mail to the main office of all financial institutions doing business in the state. Electronic mail may be used if a financial institution agrees in advance to receive such notice by electronic mail. If the director receives a substantive objection to the application within fifteen days after the publication or notice, whichever occurs last, a hearing shall be scheduled on the application.</para><para>(5) The expense of any publication and mailing required by this section shall be paid by the applicant but payment shall not be a condition precedent to approval by the director.</para><para>(6) If the director upon investigation and after any public hearing on the application is satisfied that (a) the stockholders, officers, and directors of the proposed corporation applying for such conditional bank charter are parties of integrity and responsibility, (b) the applicant has sufficient sources and amounts of capital available to the proposed bank, and (c) the applicant has a business plan describing the operations of the proposed bank that indicates the proposed bank has a reasonable probability of usefulness and success, the department shall, upon the payment of any required fees and costs, grant a conditional bank charter effective for a period not to exceed eighteen months from the date of issuance.</para><para>(7) A conditional bank charter may be converted to a full bank charter upon proof satisfactory to the director that:</para><para>(a) The financial institution to be acquired is in a troubled or failing status as required by subsection (1) of this section;</para><para>(b) The requirements of section 8-110 have been met;</para><para>(c) The requirements of section 8-702 have been met;</para><para>(d) Capital stock and surplus in amounts determined pursuant to section 8-116 have been paid in;</para><para>(e) The fees required by section 8-602 have been paid to the department; and</para><para>(f) Any other conditions imposed by the director have been complied with.</para><para>(8) A conditional bank charter may be extended for successive periods of one year if the holder of the charter files a written request for an extension of such charter at least ninety days prior to the expiration date of such charter. Such request shall be accompanied by (a) any information deemed necessary by the director to assure the department that the requirements of subsection (6) of this section continue to be met and (b) the fee required by section 8-602.</para><para>(9) The department shall issue a notice of expiration of a conditional bank charter if eighteen months have passed since the issuance of such charter and the holder of such charter (a) has not converted to a full bank charter pursuant to subsection (7) of this section, (b) has not made a request for an extension pursuant to subsection (8) of this section, or (c) has made a request for an extension pursuant to subsection (8) of this section which was not approved by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB891, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB751, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>