<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-235"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-235</statuteno><catchline>Representative trust offices authorized; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) With the approval of the Director of Banking and Finance, a corporation organized to do business as a trust company under the Nebraska Trust Company Act may establish and maintain representative trust offices within this state and in any other state pursuant to section 8-2304.</para><para>(2) A corporation organized to do business as a trust company under the Nebraska Trust Company Act, in order to establish a representative trust office in Nebraska pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, shall apply to the Director of Banking and Finance on a form prescribed by the director. Within sixty days after receipt of a substantially complete application, the director shall notify the trust company of his or her decision on the application. If the director does not act on the application, the application shall be deemed approved on the sixty-first day after receipt of a substantially complete application.</para><para>(3) The director shall approve the application for a representative trust office if he or she finds that:</para><para>(a) The establishment of the representative trust office would not adversely affect the financial condition of the trust company;</para><para>(b) The activities at the representative trust office will be limited to nonfiduciary trust activities; and</para><para>(c) Establishment of the representative trust office would be in the public interest.</para><para>(4) A state-chartered bank authorized to conduct a trust business pursuant to sections 8-159 to 8-162 may establish and maintain representative trust offices within this state and in any other state pursuant to section 8-2304. The procedure for the establishment of any representative trust offices under this subsection shall be the same as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section. The activities at the representative trust office shall be limited to the activities permitted by the Nebraska Trust Company Act, except that no fiduciary activities may be conducted at the representative trust offices. The general business of banking shall not be conducted at the representative trust offices.</para><para>(5) A representative trust office shall not be closed unless the trust company or state-chartered bank provides sixty days' prior written notice to the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 53.</para></source></law></legaldoc>