<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-206</statuteno><catchline>Specific powers.</catchline><para>A trust company created under the Nebraska Trust Company Act shall have power:</para><para>(1) To receive trust funds for investment or in trust upon such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon and to purchase, hold, and lease fireproof and burglar-proof and other vaults and safes from which revenue may be derived;</para><para>(2) To accept and execute all such trusts as may be committed to it by any corporation, person, or persons, act as assignee, receiver, trustee, and depositor, and accept and execute all such trusts as may be committed or referred to it by order, judgment, or decree of any court of record;</para><para>(3) To take, accept, and hold by the order, judgment, or decree of any such court or by gift, grant, assignment, transfer, devise, or bequest any real or personal property in trust, to care for, manage, and convey the same in accordance with such trusts, and to execute and perform any and all such trusts;</para><para>(4) To act as attorney in fact for any person or corporation, public or private;</para><para>(5) To act either by itself or jointly with any natural person or persons or with any other trust company or state or national bank doing business in this state as administrator of the estate of any deceased person, as personal representative, or as conservator or guardian of the estate of any incapacitated person;</para><para>(6) To act as trustee for any person or of the estate of any deceased person under the appointment of any court of record having jurisdiction of the estate of such person;</para><para>(7) To act as agent or in an agency capacity for any person or entity, public or private;</para><para>(8) To loan money upon real estate and upon collateral security when the collateral would of itself be a legal investment for such corporation;</para><para>(9) To buy, hold, own, and sell securities issued or guaranteed by the United States Government or any authorized agency thereof, including any corporation or enterprise wholly owned directly or indirectly by the United States, or with the authority to borrow directly from the United States treasury, or securities secured by obligations of any of the foregoing, securities of any state or political subdivision thereof which possesses general powers of taxation, stock, warrants, bills of exchange, notes, mortgages, banker's acceptances, certificates of deposit in institutions whose accounts are insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, securities issued pursuant to the Nebraska Business Development Corporation Act, and other investment securities, negotiable and nonnegotiable, except stock or other securities of any corporation organized under the Nebraska Trust Company Act;</para><para>(10) To purchase, own, or rent real estate needed in the conduct of the business and to erect thereon buildings deemed expedient and necessary, the cost of such real estate and buildings not to exceed one hundred percent of the paid-up capital stock, and to purchase, own, and improve such other real estate as it may be required to bid in under foreclosure or in payment of other debts;</para><para>(11) To borrow money, to execute and issue its notes payable at a future date, and to pledge its real estate, mortgages, or other securities therefor. With the approval of the Director of Banking and Finance, any trust company may at any time, through action of its board of directors and without requiring any action of its stockholders, issue and sell its capital notes or debentures. Such capital notes or debentures shall be subordinate and subject to the claims of trustors and beneficiaries of estates and trusts and may be subordinated and subject to the claims of other creditors. The holders of such capital notes or debentures shall not be held individually responsible as such holders for any debts, contracts, or engagements of the trust company and shall not be held liable for assessments to restore impairments in the capital of the trust company as may be from time to time determined by the director; and</para><para>(12) To perform all acts and exercise all powers connected with, belonging to or incident to, or necessary for the full and complete exercise and discharge of the rights, powers, and responsibilities granted in the Nebraska Trust Company Act, and all provisions of the act shall be liberally construed. None of the powers hereby granted shall extend to or be construed to authorize any such corporation to accept deposits or conduct the business of banking as defined in the Nebraska Banking Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 31, &#167; 6, p. 189; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 743; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVIII, &#167; 6, p. 719; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8068; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 35, &#167; 2, p. 160; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-206; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 74, p. 172; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-206; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-206; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 263, &#167; 1, p. 919; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 124; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 909, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1177, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 12.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Banking Act,</emphasis> see section 8-101.01.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Business Development Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-2101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A loan by a trust company to one of its managing officers is prohibited by this section. Burke v. Munger, 138 Neb. 74, 292 N.W. 53 (1940).</para><para>Under this section, trust companies organized under this article were empowered to accept and execute trusts and to discharge the duties imposed thereby. First Trust Company v. Airedale Ranch &amp; Cattle Company, 136 Neb. 521, 286 N.W. 766 (1939).</para><para>In criminal prosecution of officer of trust company for embezzlement of trust funds, court properly instructed jury that trust company had no power to assent to a loan to one of its officers. Buckley v. State, 131 Neb. 752, 269 N.W. 892 (1936).</para><para>Power of petitioner as trustee, upon the death of the insured, to accept and receive the proceeds of the life insurance policy payable to it as trustee, plainly conferred hereunder. Federal Trust Co. v. Damron, 124 Neb. 655, 247 N.W. 589 (1933).</para><para>Under terms of debenture, trust company empowered, under subdivision 7 hereof, to substitute, for farm mortgages originally deposited with it, stocks, bonds, etc., and obligation fulfilled by safely holding same. Myers v. Union Nat. Bank of Fremont, 115 Neb. 49, 211 N.W. 343 (1926).</para><para>Where the next of kin disagree as to who shall be appointed, county court has power to appoint duly authorized trust company as administrator. In re Estate of Anderson, 102 Neb. 170, 166 N.W. 261 (1918).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>