<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-305</statuteno><catchline>Corporate name; requirements; penalty.</catchline><para>The words loan and building association, building association, building and loan association, savings and loan association, or loan and savings association, shall form part of the corporate name of every such corporation. No individual, firm, company, corporation, or association operating in the State of Nebraska, unless (1) organized under authority of the federal government, (2) organized as a building and loan association under the authority of any foreign state and complying with the provisions of the Nebraska statutes, (3) organized and incorporated under and in accordance with the provisions of sections 8-301 to 8-384, or (4) having been in existence and doing business in Nebraska under its present name for a period of ten years prior to January 1, 1949, shall, after August 27, 1949, use in its name the words loan and building association, building and loan association, savings and loan association, loan and savings association, loan and building, building and loan, savings and loan, loan and savings, building and savings, or savings and building, in combination with any other word or words. Any person, firm, company, corporation, or association violating this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor for each offense. Each day such person, firm, or corporation shall use any such prohibited words shall be deemed a separate and distinct offense in violation of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 84; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 485; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XIX, &#167; 2, p. 724; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8084; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-302; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 19, &#167; 1, p. 126; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-302; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-305; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 9, &#167; 1, p. 69; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 15.</para></source></law></legaldoc>