<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" id="id11"  statutenumber="8-162.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>8-162.02</statuteno><catchline id="id14">Bank; fiduciary account controlled by trust department; collateral; public funds exempt.</catchline><para>(1) A bank may deposit or have on deposit funds of a fiduciary account controlled by the bank's trust department unless prohibited by applicable law.</para><para>(2) To the extent that the funds are awaiting investment or distribution and are not insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, a bank shall set aside collateral as security under the control of appropriate fiduciary officers and bank employees. The bank shall place pledged assets of fiduciary accounts in the joint custody or control of not fewer than two of the fiduciary officers or employees of the bank designated for that purpose by the board of directors. The bank may maintain the investments of a fiduciary account off-premises if consistent with applicable law and if the bank maintains adequate safeguards and controls. The market value of the collateral shall at all times equal or exceed the amount of the uninsured or unguaranteed fiduciary funds awaiting investment or distribution.</para><para>(3) A bank may satisfy the collateral requirements of this section with any of the following: (a) Direct obligations of the United States or other obligations fully guaranteed by the United States as to principal and interest; (b) readily marketable securities of the classes in which banks, trust companies, or other corporations exercising fiduciary powers are permitted to invest fiduciary funds under applicable state law; and (c) surety bonds, to the extent the surety bonds provide adequate security, unless prohibited by applicable law.</para><para>(4) A bank, acting in its fiduciary capacity, may deposit funds of a fiduciary account that are awaiting investment or distribution with an affiliated insured depository institution unless prohibited by applicable law. The bank may set aside collateral as security for a deposit by or with an affiliate of fiduciary funds awaiting investment or distribution, as it would if the deposit was made at the bank, unless such action is prohibited by applicable law.</para><para>(5) Public funds deposited in and held by a bank are not subject to this section.</para><para>(6) This section does not apply to a fiduciary account in which, pursuant to the terms of the governing instrument, full investment authority is retained by the grantor or is vested in persons or entities other than the bank and the bank, acting in its fiduciary capacity, does not have the power to exert any influence over investment decisions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB788, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 60. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>