<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-175" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>8-175</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Banks; false entry or statement; other offenses relating to books and records; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">Any person who willfully and knowingly subscribes to, or makes, or causes to be made, any false statement or false entry in the books of any bank, knowingly subscribes to or exhibits false papers with the intent to deceive any person or persons authorized to examine into the affairs of any such bank, makes, states, or publishes any false statement of the amount of the assets or liabilities of any such bank, fails to make true and correct entry in the books and records of such bank of its business and transactions in the manner and form prescribed by the department, mutilates, alters, destroys, secretes, or removes any of the books or records of such bank without the written consent of the director, or makes, states, or publishes any false statement of the amount of the assets or liabilities of any such bank, is guilty of a Class III felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 21, p. 77; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 300; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 21, p. 694; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8002; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-133; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 23, p. 146; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-133; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-135; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 75, p. 163; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 72. </para></source><annotation><para>Crime of making a false statement of condition of a bank with intent to deceive was a felony. State v. Hylton, 175 Neb. 828, 124 N.W.2d 230 (1963).</para><para>Mere making of false report is not sufficient to sustain conviction under this section, but in addition intent to deceive must be charged and proved. Foreman v. State, 127 Neb. 824, 257 N.W. 237 (1934).</para><para>In prosecution hereunder it is not essential to the commission of the offense that the statement be made in the presence of two directors of bank. Flannigan v. State, 124 Neb. 748, 248 N.W. 92 (1933).</para><para>Intent to deceive is an element of the felony described herein. Foreman v. State, 124 Neb. 74, 245 N.W. 422 (1932), 85 A.L.R. 821 (1932).</para><para>This section applies to minutes of meetings of board of directors. Kienke v. Kirsch, 121 Neb. 688, 238 N.W. 33 (1931).</para><para>To be guilty under this section, bank officer must willfully and knowingly make the entry, the entry must be false, and it must have been made with intent to deceive. Spearman v. State, 120 Neb. 799, 235 N.W. 465 (1931).</para><para>Omission by bank officer to include in report to banking department a certificate of deposit caused to be issued by him to pay a personal obligation is making false statement under this section. Wentz v. State, 108 Neb. 597, 188 N.W. 467 (1922).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>