
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1,134" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,134</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Violations; director; powers; fines; notice; hearing; closure; emergency powers; service; procedures.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever the director has reason to believe that a violation of any provision of Chapter 8 or of the Credit Union Act or any rule and regulation or order of the director has occurred, he or she may cause a written complaint to be served upon the alleged violator. The complaint shall specify the statutory provision or rule and regulation or order alleged to have been violated and the facts alleged to constitute a violation thereof and shall order that necessary corrective action be taken within a reasonable time to be prescribed in such order. Any such order shall become final as to any person named in the order unless such person requests, in writing, a hearing before the director no later than ten days after the date such order is served. In lieu of such order, the director may require that the alleged violator appear before the director at a time and place specified in the notice and answer the charge complained of. The notice shall be delivered to the alleged violator or violators in accordance with subsection (4) of this section not less than ten days before the time set for the hearing.</para><para id="id00">(2) The director shall provide an opportunity for a fair hearing to the alleged violator at the time and place specified in the notice or any modification of the notice. On the basis of the evidence produced at the hearing, the director shall make findings of fact and conclusions of law and enter such order as in his or her opinion will best further the purposes of Chapter 8 or the Credit Union Act and the rules and regulations and orders of the director. Written notice of such order shall be given to the alleged violator and to any other person who appeared at the hearing and made written request for notice of the order. If the hearing is held before any person other than the director, such person shall transmit a record of the hearing together with findings of fact and conclusions of law to the director. The director, prior to entering his or her order on the basis of such record, shall provide opportunity to the parties to submit for his or her consideration exceptions to the findings or conclusions and supporting reasons for such exceptions. The order of the director shall become final and binding on all parties unless appealed to the district court of Lancaster County as provided in section 8-1,135. As part of such order, the director may impose a fine, in addition to the costs of the investigation, upon a person found to have violated any provision of Chapter 8, the Credit Union Act, or the rules and regulations or orders of the director. The fine shall not exceed ten thousand dollars per violation for the first offense and twenty-five thousand dollars per violation for a second or subsequent offense involving a violation of the same provision of Chapter 8, the Credit Union Act, the rules and regulations of the director, or the same order of the director. The fines and costs shall be in addition to all other penalties imposed by the laws of this state. The director shall collect the fines and costs and remit them to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit the costs to the Financial Institution Assessment Cash Fund and distribute the fines in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska. If a person fails to pay the fine or costs of the investigation, a lien in the amount of the fine and costs shall be imposed upon all of the assets and property of such person in this state and may be recovered by an action by the director. The lien shall attach to the real property of such person when notice of the lien is filed and indexed against the real property in the office of the register of deeds in the county where the real property is located. The lien shall attach to any other property of such person when notice of the lien is filed against the property in the manner prescribed by law.</para><para id="id00">(3) Whenever the director finds that an emergency exists requiring immediate action to protect the safety and soundness of the financial institutions chartered by the department, the director may, without notice or hearing, issue an order reciting the existence of an emergency and requiring that such action be taken as the director deems necessary to meet the emergency. Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (2) of this section, the order shall be effective immediately. Any person to whom such order is directed shall comply immediately, but on application to the director shall be afforded a hearing as soon as possible and not later than ten days after such application by the affected person. On the basis of the hearing, the director shall continue the order in effect, revoke it, or modify it. This subsection shall not apply to a determination of necessary acquisition made by the department pursuant to sections 8-1506 to 8-1510.</para><para id="id00">(4) Except as otherwise expressly provided, any notice, order, or other instrument issued by or under authority of the director shall be served on any person affected thereby either personally or by certified mail, return receipt requested. Proof of service shall be filed with the office of the director.</para><para id="id00">Every certificate or affidavit of service made and filed as provided in this subsection shall be prima facie evidence of the facts stated in the certificate or affidavit, and a certified copy shall have the same force and effect as the original.</para><para id="id00">(5) Any hearing provided for in this section may be conducted by the director, or by any member of the department acting on behalf of the director, or the director may designate hearing officers who shall have the power and authority to conduct such hearings in the name of the director at any time and place. A verbatim record of the proceedings of such hearings shall be taken and filed with the director, together with findings of fact and conclusions of law made by the director or hearing officer. The director may subpoena witnesses, and any witness who is subpoenaed shall receive the same fees as in civil actions in the district court and mileage as provided in section 81-1176. In case of contumacy or refusal to obey a notice of hearing or subpoena issued under this section, the district court of Lancaster County shall have jurisdiction, upon application of the director, to issue an order requiring such person to appear and testify or produce evidence as the case may require. Failure to obey such order of the court may be punished by such court as contempt.</para><para id="id00">If requested to do so by any party concerned with such hearing, the full stenographic notes, or tapes of an electronic transcribing device, of the testimony presented at such hearing shall be taken and filed. The stenographer shall, upon the payment of the stenographer's fee allowed by the court, furnish a certified transcript of all or any part of the stenographer's notes to any party to the action requiring and requesting such notes.</para><para id="id00">(6) The director may close to the public the hearing, or any portion of the hearing, provided for in this section when he or she finds that the closure is (a) necessary to protect any person against unwarranted injury or (b) in the public interest. The director shall close no more of the public hearing than is necessary to attain the objectives of this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 1039, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 908, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 118; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1053, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 124. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credit Union Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1701.</para><para><emphasis>Financial Institution Assessment Cash Fund,</emphasis> purposes, see sections 8-601 and 8-604.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>