<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-199" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-199</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Financial institutions; department as receiver; powers; no compensation to director.</catchline><para id="id00">Whenever the department has been designated receiver for a financial institution chartered by the department, the department shall have all the powers and privileges provided by the laws of this state with respect to any other receiver and such incidental powers as shall be necessary to carry out an orderly and efficient liquidation or reorganization of any such financial institution for which the department may have become receiver, either by operation of law or by judicial appointment. Acting by and through the director, the department may in its own name as such receiver enforce on behalf of such financial institution or its creditors, shareholders, or owners, by actions at law or in equity, all debts or other obligations of whatever kind or nature due to such financial institution or the creditors or shareholders thereof. In like manner, the department may make, execute, and deliver any and all deeds, assignments, and other instruments necessary and proper to effectuate any sale of real or personal property, or the settlement of any obligations belonging or due to such financial institution for which the department may have become receiver, or its creditors, shareholders, or owners, when such sale or settlement is approved by the district court of the county in which the main office of such financial institution is located. The director shall receive no fees, salary, or other compensation for his or her services in connection with the liquidation or reorganization of such financial institutions other than his or her salary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 9, &#167; 1, p. 79; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 180, &#167; 1, p. 700; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-192; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-185; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 99, p. 174; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 653, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 96. </para></source><annotation><para>In the absence of an allegation of an individual harm upon which a claimant can directly bring suit, claims are derivative and are properly pursued by the receiver under section 8-199 (Reissue 1983). Weimer v. Amen, 235 Neb. 287, 455 N.W.2d 145 (1990).</para><para>Section 8-199 (Reissue 1983) does not unconstitutionally deny access to the courts, violate due process, nor take property for a public purpose without just compensation. Weimer v. Amen, 235 Neb. 287, 455 N.W.2d 145 (1990).</para><para>Section 8-199 (Reissue 1983) granted the receiver broad authority to enforce all debts or other obligations of whatever kind or nature due to the creditors of the failed institution which arose by virtue of the institution's insolvency. Weimer v. Amen, 235 Neb. 287, 455 N.W.2d 145 (1990).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>