<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-148"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-148</statuteno><catchline>Banks; own capital stock; loans on, purchase, or use as collateral by bank prohibited; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) or (3) of this section, a bank shall not make any loan or discount on the security of the shares of its own capital stock or the capital stock of its holding company, if any, be the purchaser or holder of any such shares, or purchase any securities convertible into stock or, except as provided in this section and sections 8-148.01, 8-148.02, 8-148.04, 8-148.06, 8-149, and 21-2109, the shares of any corporation, unless such security or purchase is necessary to prevent loss upon a debt previously contracted in good faith. Such stock so purchased or acquired shall, within six months after the time of its purchase unless written approval of a longer holding period is obtained from the director, be sold or disposed of at public or private sale, or in default thereof, a receiver may be appointed to close up the business of the bank, except that such stock, if shares of another bank or a bank holding company, shall be sold or disposed of as required by the director. In no case shall the amount of stock so held at any one time exceed ten percent of the paid-up capital of such bank.</para><para>(2) Any bank may subscribe to, invest, purchase, and own shares of investment companies registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 when the investment companies' assets consist of and are limited to obligations that are eligible for investment by the bank. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the amounts, terms, and conditions of such subscriptions, investments, purchases, and ownership.</para><para>(3) Any bank may subscribe to, invest, purchase, and own Student Loan Marketing Association stock, Government National Mortgage Association stock, Federal National Mortgage Association stock, Federal Agricultural Mortgage Corporation stock, Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation stock, or stock issued by any authorized agency of the United States Government, including any corporation or enterprise wholly owned directly or indirectly by the United States, or with the authority to borrow directly from the United States treasury, which the department has approved by rule and regulation or order. The department may further adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the amounts, terms, and conditions of such subscriptions, investments, purchases, and ownerships, except that a bank shall not obligate more than five percent of its capital, surplus, undivided profits, and unencumbered reserves for such stock.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 25, p. 78; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 304; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 25, p. 695; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8006; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-137; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-139; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 48, p. 154; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 165, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 532, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 453, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 237, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 996, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 8.</para></source><annotation><para>Except to prevent loss upon a debt previously contracted in good faith, a state bank is without power, directly or through agent, to buy or hold capital stock of another bank. Cooper v. Bane, 110 Neb. 83, 196 N.W. 119 (1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>