<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-116.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-116.01</statuteno><catchline>Banks; capital notes and debentures; issuance; conditions.</catchline><para>With the approval of the director, any bank may at any time, through action of its board of directors and without requiring any action of its stockholders, issue and sell its capital notes or debentures. Such capital notes or debentures shall be subordinate and subject to the claims of depositors and may be subordinated and subjected to the claims of other creditors. The capital stock of any bank as such term capital stock is used respectively in sections 8-116, 8-118, and 8-127, the capital of any corporation transacting a banking business as the term capital is used in section 8-187, and the capital of a bank as the term capital is used in section 8-132, shall be deemed to be unimpaired when the amount of such capital notes and debentures as represented by cash or sound assets exceeds the impairment as found by the department. Before any such capital notes or debentures are retired or paid by the bank, any existing deficiency of its capital, disregarding the notes or debentures to be retired, must be paid in, in cash, to the end that the sound capital assets shall at least equal the capital or capital stock of the bank in the sense such terms capital and capital stock are used in the respective sections named. Such capital notes or debentures shall in no case be subject to any assessment. The holders of such capital notes or debentures shall not be held individually responsible as such holders for any debts, contracts, or engagements of such bank and shall not be held liable for assessments to restore impairments in the capital of such bank.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 8, &#167; 11, p. 76; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-411; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-710; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 14, &#167; 9, p. 109; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-710; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>