
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-147" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-147</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Direct borrowing of bank; loans and investments; limitation on amounts; illegal transfer of assets; violation; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The aggregate amount of direct borrowing of any bank shall at no time exceed the amount of its paid-up capital, surplus, undivided profits, capital reserves, capital notes, and debentures, except with the prior written permission of the director. Direct borrowing does not include:</para><para id="id00">(a) Money borrowed on the bank's bills payable secured by (i) direct or indirect obligations of the United States Government or (ii) obligations guaranteed by agencies of the United States Government;</para><para id="id00">(b) Rediscounts, bills payable, borrowings, or other liabilities with or to the federal reserve system or the federal reserve banks, if the bank is a member of the federal reserve system;</para><para id="id00">(c) Rediscounts, bills payable, borrowings, or other liabilities with or to the Federal Home Loan Bank System or the Federal Home Loan Banks, if the bank is a member of the Federal Home Loan Bank System; or</para><para id="id00">(d) Rediscounts, bills payable, borrowings, or other liabilities with or to the federal intermediate credit banks.</para><para id="id00">(2) The aggregate amount of the loans and investments of any bank shall at no time exceed fifteen times the amount of its paid-up capital, surplus, undivided profits, capital reserves, capital notes, and debentures. For purposes of this section, loans and investments shall not include a bank's (a) cash reserves, (b) real estate and buildings at which the bank is authorized to conduct its business, (c) furniture and fixtures, and (d) obligations set forth in subdivisions (1)(a), (b), and (c) of this section.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any bank becoming a member of the federal reserve system or the Federal Home Loan Bank System shall have the same privileges to the same extent as national banks.</para><para id="id00">(4) With the prior written permission of the director, a bank may rediscount paper in an amount in excess of its paid-up capital stock.</para><para id="id00">(5) Any transfer of assets of a bank in violation of this section is void as against the creditors of the bank.</para><para id="id00">(6) Any officer, director, or employee of a bank who does, or permits to be done, any act in violation of this section and any other person who knowingly assists in the violation of this section is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 24, p. 78; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 303; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 24, p. 695; </para><para>Laws 1922, Spec. Sess., c. 6, &#167; 1, p. 66; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8005; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 190, &#167; 1, p. 435; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-136; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 25, p. 147; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-136; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-138; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 8, &#167; 1, p. 105; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 15, &#167; 11, p. 136; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-138; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 47, p. 153; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 243; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 143, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 779, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 177, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 979, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1053, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 2, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 43. </para></source><annotation><para>Query made by court as to whether borrowing of money upon behalf of bank through execution of individual obligations of directors to third parties was a transaction in violation of this section. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Farmers State Bank of Wood River, 127 Neb. 139, 254 N.W. 728 (1934).</para><para>Bank may rediscount note and mortgage beyond the limits provided in this section by permission of the banking department. Luikart v. Hunt, 124 Neb. 642, 247 N.W. 790 (1933).</para><para>Execution by bank officer of bills payable in behalf of bank in excess of the amount of its capital stock and surplus justified conviction under this section. Hinds v. State, 121 Neb. 508, 237 N.W. 617 (1931).</para><para>Prior to amendment of this section in 1923, in absence of provision for penalty, loan to bank made in violation of this section was not void, and where contract was completely executed by lending of money and execution and delivery of notes therefor, borrowing bank could not refuse payment of notes. State ex rel. Davis v. Farmers State Bank of Winside, 112 Neb. 597, 200 N.W. 173 (1924).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>