
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1,102" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,102</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Insolvent banks; department as receiver and liquidating agent; liens dissolved; assets; transfers to defraud creditors; preferences.</catchline><para id="id00">Upon the declaration of insolvency of a bank by the director, the department shall become the receiver and liquidating agent to wind up the business of that bank, and the department shall be vested with the title to all of the assets of such bank wherever the assets may be situated and whatever kind and character such assets may be, as of the date of the filing of the declaration of insolvency with the clerk of the district court of the county in which the main office of such bank is located. All levies, judgment liens, attachments, or other liens obtained through legal proceedings against such bank or its property acquired within sixty days next preceding the filing of the declaration of insolvency shall be void, and the property affected by the levy, judgment lien, attachment, or other lien obtained through legal proceedings, shall be wholly discharged and released therefrom. If at any time within sixty days prior to the taking over by the director of a bank which is later declared insolvent any transfers of the assets of such bank are made to prevent liquidation and distribution of such assets to the bank's creditors as provided in the Nebraska Banking Act or if any transfers are made so as to create a preference of one creditor over another, such transfers shall be void and the director shall be entitled to recover such assets for the benefit of the trust.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 54, p. 163; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-1,127; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-188; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 102, p. 176; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 99. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>