<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-105</statuteno><catchline>Deputies; examiners and assistants; disqualifications; salaries; bond or insurance.</catchline><para>(1) The director may employ such deputies, examiners, and other assistants as he or she may need to discharge in a proper manner the duties imposed upon him or her by law. Neither the director, nor any deputy or assistant, shall employ any person who at the time of hire is a relative of the director or a relative of any deputy or assistant in the work of the department. The deputies, examiners, and other assistants shall perform such duties as shall be assigned to them. The deputies and financial institution examiners hired after March 4, 2003, shall hold office at the will of the director and shall receive such salary as set by the director and approved by the Governor based upon the level of credentials for the positions. Each employee who is employed as a deputy or a financial institution examiner on March 4, 2003, may elect to become employed at will. The election to become employed at will may be made at any time upon notification to the director in writing, but once made, such election shall be final. Until the election to be employed at will is made, the employee shall be treated as continuing participation in the State Personnel System. The director shall, with the approval of the Governor, fix the compensation of the other examiners and assistants, which shall be paid either monthly or on a biweekly basis.</para><para>(2) The deputies, examiners, and other assistants, before assuming the duties of office, shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 3, p. 135; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 19, &#167; 3, p. 186; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-1,124; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 77; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-103; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 238, &#167; 19, p. 712; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 16, &#167; 3, p. 97; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 311, &#167; 1, p. 1065; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 9, &#167; 1, p. 74; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-103; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 5, p. 135; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1053, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 85, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>