<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>8-141</statuteno><catchline>Loans; limits; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) No bank shall directly or indirectly loan to any single corporation, limited liability company, firm, or individual, including in such loans all loans made to the several members or shareholders of such corporation, limited liability company, or firm, for the use and benefit of such corporation, limited liability company, firm, or individual, more than twenty-five percent of the paid-up capital, surplus, and capital notes and debentures or fifteen percent of the unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus of such bank, whichever is greater. Such limitations shall be subject to the following exceptions:</para><para>(a) Obligations of any person, partnership, limited liability company, association, or corporation in the form of notes or drafts secured by shipping documents or instruments transferring or securing title covering livestock or giving a lien on livestock, when the market value of the livestock securing the obligation is not at any time less than one hundred fifteen percent of the face amount of the notes covered by such documents, shall be subject under this section to a limitation of ten percent of such capital, surplus, and capital notes and debentures or ten percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus, whichever is greater, in addition to such twenty-five percent of such capital and surplus or such fifteen percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus;</para><para>(b) Obligations of any person, partnership, limited liability company, association, or corporation secured by not less than a like amount of bonds or notes of the United States issued since April 24, 1917, or certificates of indebtedness of the United States, treasury bills of the United States, or obligations fully guaranteed both as to principal and interest by the United States shall be subject under this section to a limitation of ten percent of such capital, surplus, and capital notes and debentures or ten percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus, whichever is greater, in addition to such twenty-five percent of such capital and surplus or such fifteen percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus;</para><para>(c) Obligations of any person, partnership, limited liability company, association, or corporation which are secured by negotiable warehouse receipts in an amount not less than one hundred fifteen percent of the face amount of the note or notes secured by such documents shall be subject under this section to a limitation of ten percent of such capital, surplus, and capital notes and debentures or ten percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus, whichever is greater, in addition to such twenty-five percent of such capital and surplus or such fifteen percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus; or</para><para>(d) Obligations of any person, partnership, limited liability company, association, or corporation which are secured by readily marketable collateral having a market value, as determined by reliable and continuously available price quotations, in an amount at least equal to the face amount of the note or notes secured by such collateral, shall be subject under this section to a limitation of ten percent of such capital, surplus, and capital notes and debentures or ten percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus, whichever is greater, in addition to such twenty-five percent of such capital and surplus or such fifteen percent of such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus.</para><para>(2)(a) For purposes of this section, the discounting of bills of exchange, drawn in good faith against actually existing values, and the discounting of commercial paper actually owned by the persons negotiating the bills of exchange or commercial paper shall not be considered as the lending of money.</para><para>(b) Loans or obligations shall not be subject to any limitation under this section, based upon such capital and surplus or such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus, to the extent that such capital and surplus or such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus are secured or covered by guaranties, or by commitments or agreements to take over or to purchase such capital and surplus or such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus, made by any federal reserve bank or by the United States Government or any authorized agency thereof, including any corporation wholly owned directly or indirectly by the United States, or general obligations of any state of the United States or any political subdivision of the state. The phrase general obligation of any state or any political subdivision of the state means an obligation supported by the full faith and credit of an obligor possessing general powers of taxation, including property taxation, but does not include municipal revenue bonds and sanitary and improvement district warrants which are subject to the limitations set forth in this section.</para><para>(c) Any bank may subscribe to, invest in, purchase, and own single-family mortgages secured by the Federal Housing Administration or the United States Department of Veterans Affairs and mortgage-backed certificates of the Government National Mortgage Association which are guaranteed as to payment of principal and interest by the Government National Mortgage Association. Such mortgages and certificates shall not be subject under this section to any limitation based upon such capital and surplus or such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus.</para><para>(d) Obligations representing loans to any national banking association or to any banking institution organized under the laws of any state, when such loans are approved by the director by rule and regulation or otherwise, shall not be subject under this section to any limitation based upon such capital and surplus or such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus.</para><para>(e) Loans or extensions of credit secured by a segregated deposit account in the lending bank shall not be subject under this section to any limitation based on such capital and surplus or such unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus. The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the terms and conditions of such security interest and segregated deposit account.</para><para>(f) For the purpose of determining lending limits, partnerships shall not be treated as separate entities. Each individual shall be charged with his or her personal debt plus the debt of every partnership in which he or she is a partner, except that for purposes of this section (a) an individual shall only be charged with the debt of any limited partnership in which he or she is a partner to the extent that the terms of the limited partnership agreement provide that such individual is to be held liable for the debts or actions of such limited partnership and (b) no individual shall be charged with the debt of any general partnership in which he or she is a partner beyond the extent to which (i) his or her liability for such partnership debt is limited by the terms of a contract or other written agreement between the bank and such individual and (ii) any personal debt of such individual is incurred for the use and benefit of such general partnership.</para><para>(3) A loan made within lending limits at the initial time the loan was made may be renewed, extended, or serviced without regard to changes in the lending limit of a bank following the initial extension of the loan if (a) the renewal, extension, or servicing of the loan does not result in the extension of funds beyond the initial amount of the loan or (b) the accrued interest on the loan is not added to the original amount of the loan in the process of renewal, extension, or servicing.</para><para>(4) Any bank may purchase or take an interest in life insurance contracts for any purpose incidental to the business of banking. A bank's purchase of any life insurance contract, as measured by its cash surrender value, from any one life insurance company shall not at any time exceed twenty-five percent of the paid-up capital, surplus, and capital notes and debentures of such bank or fifteen percent of the unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus of such bank, whichever is greater. A bank's purchase of life insurance contracts, as measured by their cash surrender values, in the aggregate from all life insurance companies shall not at any time exceed thirty-five percent of the paid-up capital, surplus, undivided profits, and capital notes and debentures of such bank. The limitations under this subsection on a bank's purchase of life insurance contracts, in the aggregate from all life insurance companies, shall not apply to any contract purchased prior to April 5, 1994.</para><para>(5) On and after January 21, 2013, the director has the authority to determine the manner and extent to which credit exposure resulting from derivative transactions, repurchase agreements, reverse repurchase agreements, securities lending transactions, and securities borrowing transactions shall be taken into account for purposes of determining compliance with this section. In making such determinations, the director may, but is not required to, act by rule and regulation or order.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Derivative transaction means any transaction that is a contract, agreement, swap, warrant, note, or option that is based, in whole or in part, on the value of, any interest in, or any quantitative measure or the occurrence of any event relating to, one or more commodities, securities, currencies, interest or other rates, indices, or other assets;</para><para>(b) Loan includes:</para><para>(i) All direct and indirect advances of funds to a person made on the basis of any obligation of that person to repay the funds or repayable from specific property pledged by or on behalf of that person;</para><para>(ii) To the extent specified by rule and regulation or order of the director, any liability of a state bank to advance funds to or on behalf of a person pursuant to a contractual commitment; and</para><para>(iii) Any credit exposure to a person arising from a derivative transaction, repurchase agreement, reverse repurchase agreement, securities lending transaction, or securities borrowing transaction between the bank and the person; and</para><para>(c) Unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus means:</para><para>(i) For qualifying banks that have elected to use the community bank leverage ratio framework, as set forth under the Capital Adequacy Standards of the appropriate federal banking agency:</para><para>(A) The bank's tier 1 capital as reported according to the capital guidelines of the appropriate federal banking agency; and</para><para>(B) The bank's allowance for loan and lease losses or allowance for credit losses, as applicable, as reported in the most recent consolidated report of condition filed under 12 U.S.C. 1817(a)(3), as such section existed on January 1, 2021; and</para><para>(ii) For all other banks:</para><para>(A) The bank's tier 1 and tier 2 capital included in the bank's risk-based capital under the capital guidelines of the appropriate federal banking agency, based on the bank's most recent consolidated report of condition filed under 12 U.S.C. 1817(a)(3), as such section existed on January 1, 2021; and</para><para>(B) The balance of the bank's allowance for loan and lease losses not included in the bank's tier 2 capital for purposes of the calculation of risk-based capital by the appropriate federal banking agency, based on the bank's most recent consolidated report of condition filed under 12 U.S.C. 1817(a)(3), as such section existed on January 1, 2021.</para><para>(7) Notwithstanding the provisions of section 8-1,140, the director may, by order, deny or limit the inclusion of goodwill in the calculation of a bank's unimpaired capital and unimpaired surplus or in the calculation of a bank's paid-up capital and surplus.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 33, p. 81; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 312; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 33, p. 698; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 1002; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8013; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 191, &#167; 45, p. 461; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-150; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 33, p. 151; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-150; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 9, &#167; 1(1), p. 67; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-150; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 15, &#167; 14, p. 137; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-150; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 41, p. 151; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 28, &#167; 3, p. 201; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 35, &#167; 1, p. 241; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1151, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 983, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 753, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 788, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 956, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 979, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB963, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB363, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>A violation of this section does not nullify a bank loan which exceeds the statutory limit; status as a loan in excess of a statutory limit is not a defense for a debtor or the debtor's guarantor in an action by a bank to recover the statutorily excessive loan. Schuyler State Bank v. Cech, 228 Neb. 588, 423 N.W.2d 464 (1988).</para><para>Language of this section including partnership within its purview contrasted with section 8-140 before 1931 amendment. State v. Pielsticker, 118 Neb. 419, 225 N.W. 51 (1929).</para><para>Excessive borrower cannot avail himself of this section to defeat collection of his debt. Bank of College View v. Nelson, 106 Neb. 129, 183 N.W. 100 (1921).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>