<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-124"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>8-124</statuteno><catchline>Banks; board of directors; president; meetings; examination; audit.</catchline><para>(1) The affairs and business of any bank shall be managed or controlled by a board of directors of not less than five and not more than twenty-five members, who shall be selected at such time and in such manner as may be provided by the articles of incorporation of the corporation and in conformity with the Nebraska Banking Act. The board of directors shall select a president. No person shall act as president if he or she is not a member of the board of directors.</para><para> (2) The board of directors shall hold at least one regular meeting in each calendar quarter, and at one of such meetings in each year a thorough examination of the books, records, funds, and securities held by the bank shall be made and recorded in detail upon its record book. In lieu of the one annual examination required, the board of directors may accept one annual audit by an accountant or accounting firm approved by the Director of Banking and Finance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 26, p. 78; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 8, &#167; 26, p. 81; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 305; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 26, p. 696; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8007; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-138; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-140; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 15, &#167; 4, p. 112; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-140; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 24, p. 143; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 123; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 721, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 23. </para></source><annotation><para>Terms of office of a bank officer are required to be for one year. Sullivan v. David City Bank, 181 Neb. 395, 148 N.W.2d 844 (1967).</para><para>Person who permits himself to be held out as director of bank is estopped to deny that he was owner of sufficient shares in his own right to qualify as director. Kienke v. Kirsch, 121 Neb. 688, 238 N.W. 33 (1931).</para><para>Buying capital stock of rival bank not an ordinary banking transaction within the powers of a stockholder, the president, a single director, or all combined. Cooper v. Bane, 110 Neb. 83, 196 N.W. 119 (1923).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>