
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1,104" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,104</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Insolvent banks; liquidation; director; collection of debts; sale or compromise of certain debts; procedure; deposit or investment of funds.</catchline><para id="id00">Upon taking possession of the property and business of any bank, the director shall collect all money due to such bank and do such other acts as are necessary to conserve its assets and business and, on declaration of insolvency, he or she shall proceed to liquidate the affairs of the bank under the Nebraska Banking Act. He or she shall collect all debts due to and belonging to the bank. If he or she desires to sell or compromise any or all bad or doubtful debts or any or all of the real and personal property of such bank, he or she shall apply to the district court of the county in which the main office of the bank is located for an order permitting such sale or compromise on such terms and in such manner as the court may direct. All money so collected by the director may be, from time to time, deposited in one or more state banks or national banks. No deposits of such money shall be made unless a pledge of assets, a guaranty bond, or both are given as security for such deposit. All depository banks are authorized to give such security. The director may invest a portion or all of such money in short-time interest-bearing securities of the federal government.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 67, p. 169; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-1,131; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-190; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 104, p. 177; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 101. </para></source><annotation><para>This section does not constitute an unlawful delegation of judicial power to an executive department of government. Department of Banking v. Hedges, 136 Neb. 382, 286 N.W. 277 (1939).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>