<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-706"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>8-706</statuteno><catchline>Examinations, reports of Director of
Banking and Finance; may be furnished to other examiners.</catchline><para>The
Director of Banking and Finance may furnish to the Federal Deposit Insurance
Corporation, the Federal Reserve Board, the Comptroller of the Currency, the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, or
a foreign state agency, or to any official or examiner thereof, a copy or
copies of any or all examinations made of any such banking institution and
of any or all reports made by it and shall give access and disclose to the
Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the Federal Reserve Board, the Comptroller
of the Currency, the Consumer
Financial Protection Bureau, or a foreign state agency, or to
any official or examiner thereof, any and all information possessed by the
office of the director with reference to the conditions or affairs of any
such insured institution. Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit
the duty of any banking institution in this state, deposits in which are to
any extent insured under the provisions of section 8 of the Banking Act of
1933 (section 12B of the Federal Reserve Act, as amended), or of any amendment
of or substitution for the same, to comply with the provisions of such act,
its amendments or substitutions, or the requirements of the Federal Deposit
Insurance Corporation relative to examinations and reports, nor to limit the
powers of the director with reference to examinations and reports under existing
law.</para>
<para>As used in this section, unless the context otherwise requires, foreign
state agency shall mean any duly constituted regulatory or supervisory agency
which has authority over financial institutions and which is created under
the laws of any other state, any territory of the United States, Puerto Rico,
Guam, American Samoa, the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, or the Virgin
Islands or which is operating under the code of law for the District of Columbia.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 8, &#167; 6, p. 74; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-406; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-706; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 375, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB213, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>