<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-218" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>8-218</statuteno><catchline>Examination; powers and duties of Department of Banking and Finance.</catchline><para>The Department of Banking and Finance or any duly appointed examiner authorized by it may make a full examination into all the books, papers, and affairs of any trust company doing business under the Nebraska Trust Company Act as often as deemed necessary. In so doing, the department shall have power to administer oaths and affirmations and to examine on oath or affirmation the officers, agents, and clerks of the trust company, touching the matter which they may be authorized to inquire into and examine, and to summon and by subpoena compel the attendance of any person or persons in this state to testify under oath in relation to the affairs of the trust company. In lieu of any examination authorized by the laws of this state, the Director of Banking and Finance may accept, in his or her discretion, a report of an examination made of a trust company by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the Federal Reserve Bank, or the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency or he or she may examine any such trust company jointly with any such federal agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 31, &#167; 9, p. 193; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 747; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVIII, &#167; 15, p. 722; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8077; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 35, &#167; 3, p. 162; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 38, &#167; 6, p. 158; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-215; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 81, p. 176; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-215; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-218; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB258, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>