<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-702"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>8-702</statuteno><catchline>Banking institutions; maintain insurance
or provide notice; notice requirements; violation; penalty; proof of compliance
filed with Department of Banking and Finance; employment of mortgage loan
originators; requirements; automatic forfeiture of charter.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, any banking institution
organized under the laws of this state shall, before a charter may be issued,
enter into such contracts, incur such obligations, and generally do and perform
any and all such acts and things whatsoever as may be necessary or appropriate
in order to obtain membership in the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation
and provide for insurance of deposits in the banking institution. Any banking
institution may take advantage of any and all memberships, loans, subscriptions,
contracts, grants, rights, or privileges which may at any time be available
or inure to banking institutions or to their depositors, creditors, stockholders,
conservators, receivers, or liquidators by virtue of those provisions of section
8 of the Federal Banking Act of 1933 (section 12B of the Federal Reserve Act,
as amended) which establish the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and
provide for the insurance of deposits or of any other provisions of that or
of any other act or resolution of Congress to aid, regulate, or safeguard
banking institutions and their depositors, including any amendments of the
same or any substitutions therefor. Any banking institution may also subscribe
for and acquire any stock, debentures, bonds, or other types of securities
of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and comply with the lawful regulations
and requirements from time to time issued or made by such corporation.</para>
<para>(2)(a) A banking institution which has not complied with subsection
(1) of this section and which was in operation on September 4, 2005, may continue
to operate if it provides notice to depositors and holders of savings certificates,
certificates of indebtedness, or other similar instruments that such deposits
or instruments are not insured. Such notice shall be given (i) on the date
any such deposit, savings certificate, certificate of indebtedness, or similar
instrument is created for deposits made and instruments created on or after
October 1, 1984, and (ii) annually on October 1 thereafter as follows: AS
PROVIDED BY THE LAWS OF THE STATE OF NEBRASKA YOU ARE HEREBY NOTIFIED THAT
YOUR DEPOSIT, SAVINGS CERTIFICATE, CERTIFICATE OF INDEBTEDNESS, OR OTHER SIMILAR
INSTRUMENT IS NOT INSURED. Any advertising conducted by such banking institution
shall in each case state: THE DEPOSITS, SAVINGS CERTIFICATES, CERTIFICATES
OF INDEBTEDNESS, OR SIMILAR INSTRUMENTS OF THIS INSTITUTION ARE NOT INSURED.
The banking institution shall also display such notice in one or more prominent
places in all facilities in which the institution operates. All such notices
and statements shall be given in large or contrasting type in such a manner
that such notices shall be conspicuous. Each willful failure to give the notice
prescribed in subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall
constitute a Class II misdemeanor. All officers and directors of any such
banking institution shall be jointly and severally responsible for the issuance
of the notices described in subdivision
(2)(a) of this section in the form and manner described. The banking
institution shall annually by November 1 file proof of compliance with subdivision (2)(a) of this section with
the Department of Banking and Finance.</para>
<para>(b) Effective July 31, 2010, or
within sixty days after the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry
is capable of accepting such registrations, whichever occurs later, any
banking institution described in subdivision (a) of this subsection that employs
mortgage loan originators, as defined in section 45-702, shall register such
employees with the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry, as defined
in section 45-702, by furnishing the following information concerning the
employees' identities to the Nationwide
Mortgage Licensing System and Registry:</para>
<para>(i) Fingerprints for submission to the Federal Bureau of Investigation,
and any governmental agency or entity authorized to receive such information,
for a state and national criminal history background check; and</para>
<para>(ii) Personal history and experience, including authorization for the
Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry to obtain information related
to any administrative, civil, or criminal findings by any governmental jurisdiction.</para>
<para>(3) The charter of any banking institution which fails to comply with
the provisions of this section shall be automatically forfeited and such banking
institution shall be liquidated and dissolved, either voluntarily by its board
of directors under the supervision of the department or involuntarily by the
department as in cases of insolvency, except that such charter shall not be
automatically forfeited for failure to comply with subdivision (2)(b) of this
section if the banking institution cures such violation within sixty days
after receipt of notice of such violation from the Department of Banking and
Finance. Any banking institution whose charter is automatically forfeited
under the provisions of this subsection which continues to engage in the business
for which it had been chartered after such forfeiture, as well as the directors
and officers thereof, shall be subject to the penalties provided by law for
illegally engaging in the business of banking.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 8, &#167; 2, p. 73; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-702; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 31, &#167; 2, p. 190; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 252, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 899, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB328, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB892, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>