
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-224.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-224.01</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited acts; violation; penalties; applicability.</catchline><para>(1) No charge shall be allowed against an estate or trust for legal services performed by an attorney who is a salaried employee of the trust company or when a portion of the charge for legal service is retained by the trust company. Any officer or employee of the trust company causing or consenting to such division of fee for legal service shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. No investments of an estate or trust shall be made in the capital stock or securities of the trust company, in the stock or securities of its affiliated companies, or in obligations, either direct or indirect, of any director, officer, or employee of the trust company. The trust company shall not substitute any of the assets of an estate or trust under its control for securities of the trust company. A trust company may administer, in a fiduciary capacity, an estate or trust which contains such capital stock, securities, or obligations as part of its assets if such assets are received in kind from the grantor of the estate or trust and retention of such capital stock, securities, or obligations is properly authorized by the terms of the governing document. Any officer or employee of the trust company making such an investment or consenting to such an investment or causing such substitution or consenting to such substitution shall be guilty of a Class III felony.</para><para>(2) No loan of the assets of the trust company shall be made to any officer or director of such corporation. No trust company shall cause or allow funds of any account entrusted to the trust company to be loaned, directly or indirectly, to any director, officer, or employee of the trust company except when the director, officer, or employee has a specific beneficial interest in the account and such loans are allowed in governing account documents and are not prohibited by other state or federal law. Any director, officer, or employee of the trust company causing, consenting to, or receiving funds from a loan made in violation of this section shall be guilty of a Class III felony.</para><para>(3) This section shall not apply to:</para><para>(a) Investments authorized in section 30-3205; or</para><para>(b) Investments for which the will or trust states that the stock of the trust company or securities of a company or companies affiliated with the trust company may be acquired for the estate or trust.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 423, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>