<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-820" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>8-820</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Personal loans; credit cards; interest; service fee; fee in lieu of interest.</catchline><para id="id00">Subject to the provisions of sections 8-815 to 8-829, any bank may contract for and receive, on any personal loan, charges at a rate not exceeding nineteen percent simple interest per year. In the case of loans initiated by credit card or other type of transaction card, the rate may be any amount agreed to by the parties. Any bank acquired pursuant to sections 8-1512 and 8-1513 may also charge commercially reasonable fees for service and use of a credit card or other type of transaction card on a per transaction and monthly or annual basis. For purposes of this section, section 85 of the National Bank Act, 12 U.S.C. 85, and section 522 of the Depository Institutions Deregulation and Monetary Control Act of 1980, 12 U.S.C. 1831d, all interest, charges, fees, and other amounts permitted under sections 8-815 to 8-829 for loans initiated by credit card or other type of transaction card shall be deemed to be, and may be charged and collected as, interest by the bank, and all other terms and conditions of the agreement between the bank and the borrower that are not prohibited by such sections shall be deemed material to the determination of interest. Notwithstanding the provisions of this section, in the case of loans not initiated by credit card or other type of transaction card, a bank may charge a minimum fee of up to seven dollars and fifty cents in lieu of interest on personal loans and reasonable loan service costs as defined in subdivision (2) of section 45-101.02. Such loan service costs shall not be construed as interest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 31, &#167; 6, p. 214; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 276, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 150, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 454, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1076, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 913, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 423, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 141. </para><operativedate>August 24, 2017</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Notwithstanding interest rate limits under Nebraska statutes, national bank in Nebraska can legally charge, on credit card transactions, same rates allowed by section 45-114 et seq. Fisher v. First Nat. Bank of Omaha, 548 F.2d 255 (8th Cir. 1977).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>