<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-126" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>8-126</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Bank directors; qualifications; approval by department; revocation of approval; procedure.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A majority of the members of the board of directors of any bank shall have their residences in this state or within twenty-five miles of the main office of the bank. Reasonable efforts shall be made to acquire members of such board of directors from the county in which the main office of such bank is located and from counties in which branches of such bank are located.</para><para id="id00">(2) Directors of banks shall be persons of good moral character, known integrity, business experience, and responsibility. No person shall act as a member of the board of directors of any bank until such bank applies for and obtains approval from the department.</para><para id="id00">(3) If the department, upon investigation, determines that any director of a bank is conducting the business of the bank in an unsafe or unauthorized manner or is endangering the interests of the stockholders or depositors, the Director of Banking and Finance has the authority, following notice and opportunity for hearing, to revoke such approval to act as a member of the board of directors.</para><para id="id00"> (4) The Director of Banking and Finance may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations and prescribe forms to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 12, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 291; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 10, p. 689; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 1001; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7991; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-121; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 7, &#167; 1, p. 70; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-121; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-118; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 15, &#167; 2, p. 132; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-118; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 26, p. 144; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1035, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 996, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 322, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 26. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former law a director of commercial state bank must have been the owner of at least four percent of its capital stock in his own name and right, and a person having acted as director was estopped to deny ownership of stock standing in his name. Kienke v. Hudson, 122 Neb. 475, 240 N.W. 562 (1932); Kienke v. Kirsch, 121 Neb. 688, 238 N.W. 33 (1931).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>