<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-302"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-302</statuteno><catchline>Power to require and receive payments from members; limitations.</catchline><para>Any association of not less than five persons, which shall be organized within this state for the purpose of raising money to be loaned among its members, shall be authorized and empowered to levy, assess and collect from its members such sums of money by rates of stated dues, fines, interest and premiums on loans, as the corporation may provide in its articles of incorporation or bylaws, and to exercise such other powers as are hereinafter conferred. Every such corporation may, however, receive payments from its members in any amount, which together with the balance, if any, formerly to the credit of the member thus paying, upon the books of the corporation, shall not exceed the par value of the shares of stock held by him.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 84; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 485; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XIX, &#167; 2, p. 724; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8084; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-302; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 19, &#167; 1, p. 125; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-302; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-302; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 717, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Failure of foreign association to renew its authority to transact business in this state does not invalidate prior contracts. Eastern B. &amp; L. Assn. v. Tonkinson, 76 Neb. 470, 107 N.W. 762 (1906).</para><para>A building and loan association may deduct from a loan made to one of its members the premium bid for the right of precedence in taking a loan, provided such loan was made under a system of open competitive bidding. South Omaha L. &amp; B. Assn. v. Wirrick, 63 Neb. 598, 88 N.W. 694 (1902).</para><para>Section held constitutional. Nebraska L. &amp; B. Assn. v. Perkins, 61 Neb. 254, 85 N.W. 67 (1901); Livingston L. &amp; B. Assn. v. Drummond, 49 Neb. 200, 68 N.W. 375 (1896).</para><para>Stockholder cannot rescind, recover money paid for stock, and repudiate obligations assumed on account of mismanagement of officers. American B. &amp; L. Assn. v. Bear, 48 Neb. 455, 67 N.W. 500 (1896).</para><para>Act cannot affect contracts made before its passage. American B. &amp; L. Assn. v. Rainbolt, 48 Neb. 434, 67 N.W. 493 (1896).</para><para>Subscribers seeking rescission of contract must return stock as condition to right to rescind. Building &amp; L. Assn. of Dakota v. Cameron, 48 Neb. 124, 66 N.W. 1109 (1896).</para><para>Corporations, not building and loan associations, though similar in character, may incorporate under general law. York Park Bldg. Assn. v. Barnes, 39 Neb. 834, 58 N.W. 440 (1894).</para><para>Company will be bound by that construction of the contract which it understood and knew the other party placed upon it, by which the other party was induced to enter into contract. People's B. L. &amp; S. Assn. v. Klauber, 1 Neb. Unof. 676, 95 N.W. 1072 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>