<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1,108" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,108</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Insolvent banks; claims; objections to classification; hearing.</catchline><para id="id00">Any person objecting to the classification of his or her claim and the order based thereon must, within thirty days of the filing of the classification and order with the clerk of the district court, begin an action in that court asking to reclassify his or her claim and to set aside the order of the director. Notice of this action shall be given by the service of a copy of the petition therein upon the director, who shall, within thirty days of such service, file his or her answer or other pleading. The court shall then set the matter for hearing at the earliest convenient date and shall try and determine the issues according to the usual procedure in matters of equity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1923, c. 191, &#167; 23, p. 449; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-1,100; </para><para>Laws 1930, Spec. Sess., c. 6, &#167; 10, p. 31; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 64, p. 168; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-1,100; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-194; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 108, p. 179; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 105. </para></source><annotation><para>When payment of a dividend is deferred by reason of an unsuccessful contest of an alleged setoff, the creditor so delayed should be allowed interest on the dividend to put that creditor on an equality with the other creditors in his class. Colburn v. Ley, 191 Neb. 427, 215 N.W.2d 869 (1974).</para><para>Where any controversy over allowance of claims arises under this section, judicial power is invoked. Department of Banking v. Hedges, 136 Neb. 382, 286 N.W. 277 (1939).</para><para>An order fixing a time for filing of petitions of intervention by claimants under this section is not a final judgment, and may be modified at a subsequent term without compliance with the general statute authorizing modification of final judgments at subsequent terms. State ex rel. Sorensen v. South Omaha State Bank, 135 Neb. 478, 282 N.W. 382 (1938).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>