
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" id="id76" statutenumber="8-602"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-602</statuteno><catchline id="id79">Department of Banking and Finance; services; schedule of fees.</catchline><para>The Director of Banking and Finance shall charge and collect fees for certain services rendered by the Department of Banking and Finance according to the following schedule:</para><para>(1) For filing and examining articles of incorporation, articles of association, and bylaws, except credit unions, one hundred dollars, and for credit unions, fifty dollars;</para><para>(2) For filing and examining an amendment to articles of incorporation, articles of association, and bylaws, except credit unions, fifty dollars, and for credit unions, fifteen dollars;</para><para>(3) For issuing to banks, credit card banks, trust companies, and building and loan associations a charter, authority, or license to do business in this state, a sum which shall be determined on the basis of one dollar and fifty cents for each one thousand dollars of authorized capital, except that the minimum fee in each case shall be two hundred twenty-five dollars;</para><para>(4) For issuing to digital asset depositories under the Nebraska Financial Innovation Act a charter, an authority, or a license to do business in this state, the sum of fifty thousand dollars;</para><para>(5) For issuing an executive officer's or loan officer's license, fifty dollars at the time of the initial license, except credit unions for which the fee shall be twenty-five dollars at the time of the initial license;</para><para>(6) For affixing certificate and seal, five dollars;</para><para>(7) For making substitution of securities held by it and issuing a receipt, fifteen dollars;</para><para>(8) For issuing a certificate of approval to a credit union, ten dollars;</para><para>(9) For investigating the applications required by sections 8-117, 8-120, 8-331, and 8-2402 and the documents required by section 8-201, the cost of such examination, investigation, and inspection, including all legal expenses and the cost of any hearing transcript, with a minimum fee under (a) sections 8-117, 8-120, and 8-2402 of two thousand five hundred dollars, (b) section 8-331 of two thousand dollars, and (c) section 8-201 of one thousand dollars. The department may require the applicant to procure and give a surety bond in such principal amount as the department may determine and conditioned for the payment of the fees provided in this subdivision;</para><para>(10) For the handling of pledged securities as provided in sections 8-210 and 8-2727 at the time of the initial deposit of such securities, one dollar and fifty cents for each thousand dollars of securities deposited and a like amount on or before January 15 each year thereafter. The fees shall be paid by the entity pledging the securities;</para><para>(11) For investigating an application to move its location within the city or village limits of its original license or charter for banks, trust companies, and building and loan associations, two hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(12) For investigating an application under subdivision (6) of section 8-115.01, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(13) For investigating an application for approval to establish or acquire a branch pursuant to section 8-157 or 8-2103 or to establish a mobile branch pursuant to section 8-157, two hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(14) For investigating a notice of acquisition of control under subsection (1) of section 8-1502, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(15) For investigating an application for a cross-industry merger under section 8-1510, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(16) For investigating an application for a merger of two state banks, a merger of a state bank and a national bank in which the state bank is the surviving entity, or an interstate merger application in which the Nebraska state chartered bank is the resulting bank, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(17) For investigating an application or a notice to establish a branch trust office, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(18) For investigating an application or a notice to establish a representative trust office, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(19) For investigating an application to establish a credit union branch under section 21-1725.01, two hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(20) For investigating an applicant under section 8-1513, five thousand dollars;</para><para>(21) For investigating a request to extend a conditional bank charter under section 8-117, one thousand dollars; and</para><para>(22) For investigating an application to establish a branch office, for a merger or an acquisition of control, or for a request to extend a conditional charter for a digital asset depository, five hundred dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 20, &#167; 2, p. 129; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-702; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-602; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 10, &#167; 5, p. 132; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 15, &#167; 8, p. 113; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 23, &#167; 2, p. 127; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 43, &#167; 1, p. 252; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1194, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 164, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 561, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 642, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 470, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 757, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 599, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1089, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1094, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB891, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB74, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB963, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB258, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 44. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Financial Innovation Act,</emphasis> see section 8-3001.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>