<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-177"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-177</statuteno><catchline>Banks; consolidation; approval required; creditors' claims.</catchline><para>Any bank, which is in good faith winding up its business for the purpose of consolidating with some other bank, may transfer its resources and liabilities to the bank with which it is in the process of consolidation, but no consolidation shall be made without the consent of the department, nor shall such consolidation operate to defeat the claim of any creditor or hinder any creditor in the collection of his debt against such banks or either of them.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 41, p. 86; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 320; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 41, p. 701; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8021; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-160; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 36, p. 154; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-160; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-164; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 77, p. 164.</para></source><annotation><para>An indebtedness of a bank incurred in an attempted liquidation in violation of this section is ultra vires and does not furnish the foundation for stockholders' double liability. Luikart v. Jones, 138 Neb. 472, 293 N.W. 346 (1940).</para><para>This section does not, of itself, make a consolidated bank liable for debts of old banks. Wilson v. Continental National Bank, 130 Neb. 614, 266 N.W. 68 (1936).</para><para>Two state banks cannot consolidate without consent of banking department, and sale of entire capital stock to stockholder, president and director of rival bank is not necessarily a consolidation within the meaning of this section. Cooper v. Bane, 110 Neb. 83, 196 N.W. 119 (1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>