
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-205" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-205</statuteno><catchline>Capital stock; amount required; exception; impairment of capital stock; department; powers.</catchline><para>(1) No corporation, except a bank authorized by the Director of Banking and Finance to operate a trust department, shall be authorized to transact business as a trust company under the Nebraska Trust Company Act on or after August 1, 2000, unless it has capital stock of at least five hundred thousand dollars, all of which shall be fully paid up in cash before the corporation is authorized to commence business.</para><para>(2)(a) Corporations, except a bank authorized to operate a trust department, authorized to transact business as a trust company under the act before August 1, 2000, shall, on or after such date, maintain a capital stock of at least two hundred thousand dollars in cities of at least one hundred thousand or more inhabitants, one hundred thousand dollars in cities of at least fifty thousand inhabitants but fewer than one hundred thousand inhabitants, fifty thousand dollars in cities of at least ten thousand inhabitants but fewer than fifty thousand inhabitants, and twenty-five thousand dollars in cities and villages of fewer than ten thousand inhabitants. The population of a city for purposes of this subsection shall be the population as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census.</para><para>(b) A corporation, except a bank authorized to operate a trust department, authorized to transact business as a trust company under the act before August 1, 2000, subject to the capital stock requirement of subdivision (2)(a) of this section, which complies with the capital stock requirement of subsection (1) of this section, shall be subject to the capital stock requirement of subsection (1) of this section and shall maintain a capital stock of at least the minimum amount required by subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(c) A corporation, except a bank authorized to operate a trust department, authorized to transact business as a trust company under the act before August 1, 2000, subject to the capital stock requirement of subdivision (2)(a) of this section, which complies with the capital stock requirement of a corporation located in a larger city pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section, shall be subject to the capital stock requirement of such a corporation located in a larger city pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section and shall maintain a capital stock of at least the minimum amount required for such a corporation located in a larger city pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section.</para><para>(d) A capital stock requirement once attained by a corporation pursuant to either this subsection or subsection (1) of this section shall not be reduced.</para><para>(3) If at any time the department determines that the capital stock of a trust company is impaired, it may require the shareholders of the trust company to make up the capital stock impairment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 31, &#167; 5, p. 188; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 742; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVIII, &#167; 5, p. 719; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8067; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-205; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-205; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 19, &#167; 5, p. 144; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 14, &#167; 8, p. 109; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB67, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>