<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-114" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>8-114</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Banks; corporate status required; unlawful banking; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) It is unlawful for any person to conduct a bank within this state except by means of a corporation duly organized for such purpose under the laws of this state. It is unlawful for any corporation to receive money upon deposit or conduct a bank under the laws of this state until such corporation has complied with all the provisions and requirements of the Nebraska Banking Act.</para><para id="id00">(2) Any violation of this section is a Class V misdemeanor for each day of the continuation of such offense and is cause for the appointment of a receiver as provided in the act to wind up such banking business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 2, p. 66; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 281; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 3, p. 686; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7984; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-115; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-111; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 14, p. 139; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>August 24, 2017</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Where a federal savings and loan association installs a computer in a store to facilitate electronic transfer of funds between the association and its depositors, the store operator, by manning the computer, is not engaging in a banking or savings and loan business. State ex rel. Meyer v. American Community Stores Corp., 193 Neb. 634, 228 N.W.2d 299 (1975).</para><para>It is unlawful to conduct a bank except by means of a corporation. First Nat. Bank &amp; Trust Co. v. Ley, 182 Neb. 164, 153 N.W.2d 743 (1967).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>