<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>8-204</statuteno><catchline>Directors; qualifications; duties;
vacancies.</catchline><para>The control of the business affairs of a trust
company shall be vested in a board of directors of not less than five persons who
shall be selected at such time and in such manner as may be provided by the
articles of incorporation of the trust company and in conformity with the
Nebraska Trust Company Act. Any vacancy on the board shall be
filled within ninety days by appointment by the remaining directors, and any
director so appointed shall serve until the next election of directors, except
that if the vacancy leaves a minimum of five directors, appointment shall
be optional. The board shall select from among its number a president and
secretary and shall appoint trust officers and committees as it deems necessary.
The officers and committee members shall hold their positions at the discretion
of the board of directors. The board of directors shall hold at least one
regular meeting in each calendar quarter and shall prepare and maintain complete
and accurate minutes of the proceedings at such meetings.</para>
<para>The board of directors shall make or cause to be made each year a thorough
examination of the books, records, funds, and securities held for the trust
company and customer accounts. The examination may be conducted by the members
of the board of directors or the board may accept an annual audit by an accountant
or accounting firm approved by the Department of Banking and Finance. Any
such examination or audit must comply in scope with minimum standards established
by the department.</para>
<para>Unless the department otherwise approves, a majority of the members
of the board of directors of any trust company shall be residents of this
state. Reasonable efforts shall be made to acquire members of the board of
directors from the county in which the trust company is located. Directors of trust companies
shall be persons of good moral character and known integrity, business experience,
and responsibility. No person shall act as such member of the board of directors
of any trust company until the corporation applies for and obtains approval
from the Department of Banking and Finance.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 31, &#167; 4, p. 188; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 741; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVIII, &#167; 4, p. 718; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8065; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-204; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB213, &#167; 6.</para></source><annotation><para>Control of business of a trust company is vested under this section in the board of directors. First Trust Company v. Airedale Ranch &amp; Cattle Company, 136 Neb. 521, 286 N.W. 766 (1939).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>