<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-347"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-347</statuteno><catchline>State association; conversion into federal savings and loan association; procedure.</catchline><para>Any building and loan association or other home financing organization by whatever name or style it may be designated, eligible to become a federal savings and loan association, may convert itself into a federal savings and loan association by following the procedure hereinafter outlined:</para><para>(1) At any regular meeting of the shareholders of any such association or at any special meeting of the shareholders of such association, in either case called to consider such action and held in accordance with the laws governing such association, such shareholders by an affirmative record vote of the shareholders owning and voting two-thirds of the total number of shares outstanding, present in person or by proxy, may declare by resolution the determination to convert said association into a federal savings and loan association;</para><para>(2) A copy of the minutes of such meeting of the shareholders verified by the affidavit of the president or vice president and the secretary of the meeting, shall be filed within ten days after said meeting in the office or department of this state having supervision of such association; and such verified copy of the minutes of such meeting when so filed shall be presumptive evidence of the holding and of the action of such meeting;</para><para>(3) Within a reasonable time and without any unnecessary delay after the adjournment of such meeting of shareholders, such association shall take such action as may be necessary to make it a federal savings and loan association, and within ten days after receipt of the federal charter there shall be filed in the office or department of this state having supervision of such association, a copy of the charter issued to such association by the Federal Home Loan Bank Board or a certificate showing the organization of such association as a federal savings and loan association certified by, or on behalf of, the Federal Home Loan Bank Board. Upon the filing of such instrument such association shall cease to be a state association and shall thereafter be a federal savings and loan association.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 15, &#167; 1, p. 86; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-332; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-347. </para></source></law></legaldoc>