<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" id="id4" statutenumber="8-157.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>8-157.01</statuteno><catchline id="id7">Financial institution;
electronic terminals; use; user financial institution.</catchline><para>(1)
Any financial institution which has a main chartered office or approved branch
located in the State of Nebraska may establish and maintain any number of
automatic teller machines at which all banking transactions, defined as receiving
deposits of every kind and nature and crediting such to customer accounts,
cashing checks and cash withdrawals, transfer of funds from checking accounts
to savings accounts, transfer of funds from savings accounts to checking accounts,
transfer of funds from either checking accounts and savings accounts to accounts
of other customers, payment transfers from customer accounts into accounts
maintained by other customers of the financial institution or the financial
institution, including preauthorized draft authority, preauthorized loans,
and credit transactions, receiving payments payable at the financial institution
or otherwise, and account balance inquiry, may be conducted. Any other transaction
incidental to the business of the financial institution or which will provide
a benefit to the financial institution's customers or the general public may
be conducted at an automatic teller machine upon thirty days' prior written
notice to the director if the director does not object to the proposed other
transaction within the thirty-day notice period. Neither such automatic teller
machines nor the transactions conducted thereat shall be construed as the
establishment of a branch or as branch banking. Such automatic teller machines
shall be made available on a nondiscriminating basis for use by customers
of any financial institution which has a main chartered office or approved
branch located in the State of Nebraska which becomes a user financial institution.
It shall not be deemed discrimination if an automatic teller machine does
not offer the same transaction services as other automatic teller machines
or if there are no fees charged between affiliate financial institutions for
the use of automatic teller machines.</para>
<para>(2) Any financial institution may become a user financial institution
by agreeing to pay the establishing financial institution its automatic teller
machine usage fee. Such agreement shall be implied by the use of such automatic
teller machines. Nothing in this subsection shall prohibit a user financial
institution from agreeing to responsibilities and benefits which might be
contained in a standardized agreement. The establishing financial institution
or its designated data processing center shall be responsible for transmitting
transactions originating from its automatic teller machine to a switch, but
nothing contained in this section shall be construed to require routing of
all transactions to a switch. All automatic teller machines must be made available
on a nondiscriminating basis, for use by customers of any financial institution
which has a main chartered office or approved branch located in the State
of Nebraska which becomes a user financial institution, through methods, fees,
and processes that the establishing financial institution has provided for
switching transactions. The director, upon notice and after a hearing, may
terminate or suspend the use of any automatic teller machine if he or she
determines that it is not available on a nondiscriminating basis for use by
customers of any financial institution which has a main chartered office or
approved branch located in the State of Nebraska which becomes a user financial
institution or that transactions originated by customers of user financial
institutions are not being routed to a switch or other data processing centers.
Nothing in this section may be construed to prohibit nonbank employees from
assisting in transactions originated at the automatic teller machines, and
such assistance shall not be deemed to be engaging in the business of banking.
Such nonbank employees may be trained in the use of the automatic teller machines
by financial institution employees.</para>
<para>(3) An establishing financial institution shall not be deemed to make
an automatic teller machine available on a nondiscriminating basis if, through
personnel services offered, advertising on or off the automatic teller machine's
premises, or otherwise, it discriminates in the use of the automatic teller
machine against any user financial institution which has a main chartered
office or approved branch located in the State of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(4) Any consumer initiating
an electronic funds transfer at an automatic teller machine for which an automatic
teller machine surcharge will be imposed shall receive notice in accordance
with the provisions of 15 U.S.C. 1693b(d)(3)(A) and (B), as such section existed
on January 1, 2013. Such notice shall appear on the screen
of the automatic teller machine or appear on a paper notice issued from such
machine after the transaction is initiated and before the consumer is irrevocably
committed to completing the transaction.</para>
<para>(5) A point-of-sale terminal may be established at any point within
this state. A financial institution may contract with a seller of goods and
services or any other third party for the operation of point-of-sale terminals.
A point-of-sale terminal shall be made available on a nondiscriminating basis
for use by customers of any financial institution which has a main chartered
office or approved branch located in the State of Nebraska which becomes a
user financial institution. Nothing in this subsection shall prohibit payment
of fees to a financial institution which issues an access device used to initiate
electronic funds transfer transactions at a point-of-sale terminal.</para>
<para>(6) A seller of goods and services or any other third party on whose
premises one or more point-of-sale terminals are established shall not be,
solely by virtue of such establishment, a financial institution and shall
not be subject to the laws governing, or other requirements imposed on, financial
institutions, except for the requirement that it faithfully perform its obligations
in connection with any transaction originated at any point-of-sale terminal
on its premises. The acquiring financial institution shall be responsible
for compliance with all applicable standards, rules, and regulations governing
point-of-sale transactions.</para>
<para>(7) Any financial institution, upon a request of the director, shall
file with the director a current listing of all point-of-sale terminals established
by the financial institution within this state. For purposes of this subsection,
point-of-sale terminal shall include a group of one or more of such terminals
established at a single business location. Such listing shall contain any
reasonable descriptive information pertaining to the point-of-sale terminal
as required by the director. Neither the establishment of such point-of-sale
terminal nor any transactions conducted thereat shall be construed as the
establishment of a branch or as branch banking. Following establishment of
a point-of-sale terminal, the director, upon notice and after a hearing, may
terminate or suspend the use of such point-of-sale terminal if he or she determines
that it is not made available on a nondiscriminating basis for use by customers
of any financial institution which has a main chartered office or approved
branch located in the State of Nebraska which becomes a user financial institution,
that the necessary information is not on file with the director, or that transactions
originated by customers of user financial institutions are not being routed
to a switch or other data processing center. Nothing in this section shall
be construed to prohibit nonbank employees from assisting in transactions
originated at the point-of-sale terminals, and such assistance shall not be
deemed to be engaging in the business of banking.</para>
<para>(8) Transactions at point-of-sale terminals may include:</para>
<para>(a) Check guarantees;</para>
<para>(b) Account balance inquiries;</para>
<para>(c) Transfers of funds from a customer's account for payment to a seller's
account for goods and services on whose premises the point-of-sale terminal
is located in payment for the goods and services;</para>
<para>(d) Cash withdrawals by a customer from the customer's account or accounts;</para>
<para>(e) Transfers between accounts of the same customers at the same financial
institution; and</para>
<para>(f) Such other transactions as the director, upon application, notice,
and hearing, may approve.</para>
<para>(9)(a) Automatic teller machines may be established and maintained by
a financial institution which has a main chartered office or approved branch
located in the State of Nebraska, by a group of two or more of such financial
institutions, or by a combination of such financial institution or financial
institutions and a third party.</para>
<para>(b) Point-of-sale terminals may be established and maintained by a financial
institution which has a main chartered office or approved branch located in
the State of Nebraska, by a group of two or more of such financial institutions,
or by a combination of such financial institutions and a third party. No one,
through personnel services offered, advertising on or off the point-of-sale
terminal premises, or otherwise, may discriminate in the use of the point-of-sale
terminal against any other user financial institution.</para>
<para>(10) All financial institutions shall be given an equal opportunity
for the use of and access to a switch, and no discrimination shall exist or
preferential treatment be given in either the operation of such switch or
the charges for use thereof. The operation of such switch shall be with the
approval of the director. Approval of such switch shall be given by the director
when he or she determines that its design and operation are such as to provide
access thereto and use thereof by any financial institution without discrimination
as to access or cost of its use. Any switch established in Nebraska and approved
by the director prior to January 1, 1993, shall be deemed to be approved for
purposes of this section.</para>
<para>(11) Use of an automatic teller machine or a point-of-sale terminal
through access to a switch and use of any switch shall be made available on
a nondiscriminating basis to any financial institution. A financial institution
shall only be permitted use of the switch if the financial institution conforms
to reasonable technical operating standards which have been established by
the switch.</para>
<para>(12) To assure maximum safety and security against malfunction, fraud,
theft, and other accidents or abuses and to assure that all such access devices
will have the capability of activating all automatic teller machines and point-of-sale
terminals established in this state, no automatic teller machine or point-of-sale
terminal shall accept an access device which does not conform to such specifications
as are generally accepted. No automatic teller machine or point-of-sale terminal
shall be established or operated which does not accept an access device which
conforms with such specifications.</para>
<para>An automatic teller machine shall bear a logo type or other identification
symbol designed to advise customers that the automatic teller machine may
be activated by any access device which complies with the generally accepted
specifications. A point-of-sale terminal shall either bear or the premises
on which the point-of-sale terminal is established shall contain a visible
logo type or other identification symbol designed to advise customers that
the point-of-sale terminal may be activated by any access device which complies
with the generally accepted specifications. An automatic teller machine or
point-of-sale terminal may also bear, at the option of the establishing or
acquiring financial institution, any of the following:</para>
<para>(a) The names of all individual financial institutions using such automatic
teller machines or point-of-sale terminals in alphabetical order, except that
the establishing or acquiring financial institution may be listed first, and
in a uniform typeface, size, and color; or</para>
<para>(b) The logo type or symbol of any association, corporation, or other
entity or organization formed by one or more of the financial institutions
using such automatic teller machines or point-of-sale terminals.</para>
<para>(13) If the director, upon notice and hearing, determines at any time
that the design or operation of a switch or provision for use thereof does
discriminate against any financial institution in providing access thereto
and use thereof either through access thereto or by virtue of the cost of
its use, he or she may revoke his or her approval of such switch operation
and immediately order the discontinuance of the operation of such switch.</para>
<para>(14) If it is determined by the director, after notice and hearing,
that discrimination against any financial institution has taken place, that
one financial institution has been preferred over another, or that any financial
institution or person has not complied with any of the provisions of this
section, he or she shall immediately issue a cease and desist order or an
order for compliance within ten days after the date of the order, and upon
noncompliance with such order, the offending financial institution shall be
subject to sections 8-1,134 to 8-1,139 and to having the privileges granted
in this section revoked.</para>
<para>(15) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Access means the ability to utilize an automatic teller machine
or a point-of-sale terminal to conduct permitted banking transactions or purchase
goods and services electronically;</para>
<para>(b) Access device means a code, a transaction card, or any other means
of access to a customer's account, or any combination thereof, that may be
used by a customer for the purpose of initiating an electronic funds transfer
at an automatic teller machine or a point-of-sale terminal;</para>
<para>(c) Account means a checking account, a savings account, a share account,
or any other customer asset account held by a financial institution. Such
an account may also include a line of credit which a financial institution
has agreed to extend to its customer;</para>
<para>(d) Acquiring financial institution means any financial institution
establishing a point-of-sale terminal;</para>
<para>(e) Affiliate financial institution means any financial institution
which is a subsidiary of the same bank holding company;</para>
<para>(f) Electronic funds transfer means any transfer of funds, other than
a transaction originated by check, draft, or similar paper instrument, that
is initiated through a point-of-sale terminal, an automatic teller machine,
or a personal terminal for the purpose of ordering, instructing, or authorizing
a financial institution to debit or credit an account;</para>
<para>(g) Establishing financial institution means any financial institution
establishing an automatic teller machine which has a main chartered office
or approved branch located in the State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(h) Financial institution means a state-chartered or federally chartered
bank, savings bank, building and loan association, savings and loan association,
or credit union, or a subsidiary of any such entity;</para>
<para>(i) Foreign financial institution means a financial institution located
outside the United States;</para>
<para>(j) Personal identification number means a combination of numerals or
letters selected for a customer of a financial institution, a merchant, or
any other third party which is used in conjunction with an access device to
initiate an electronic funds transfer transaction;</para>
<para>(k) Personal terminal means a personal computer and telephone, wherever
located, operated by a customer of a financial institution for the purpose
of initiating a transaction affecting an account of the customer; and</para>
<para>(l) User financial institution means any financial institution which
desires to avail itself of and provide its customers with automatic teller
machine or point-of-sale terminal services.</para>
<para>(16) Nothing in this section prohibits ordinary clearinghouse transactions
between financial institutions.</para>
<para>(17) Nothing in this section requires any federally chartered establishing
financial institution to obtain the approval of the director for the establishment
of any automatic teller machine.</para>
<para>(18) Nothing in this section shall prevent any financial institution
which has a main chartered office or an approved branch located in the State
of Nebraska from participating in a national automatic teller machine program
to allow its customers to use automatic teller machines located outside of
the State of Nebraska which are established by out-of-state financial institutions
or foreign financial institutions or to allow customers of out-of-state financial
institutions or
foreign financial institutions to use its automatic teller machines located
in the State of Nebraska. Such participation and any automatic teller machine
usage fees charged or received pursuant to the national automatic teller machine
program or usage
fees charged for the use of its automatic teller machines by customers of
out-of-state financial institutions or foreign financial institutions shall
not be considered for purposes of determining if an automatic teller machine
located in the State of Nebraska has been made available on a nondiscriminating
basis for use by customers of any financial institution which has a main chartered
office or approved branch located in the State of Nebraska which becomes a
user financial institution.</para>
<para>(19) An agreement to operate or share an automatic teller machine may
not prohibit, limit, or restrict the right of the operator or owner of the
automatic teller machine to charge a customer conducting a transaction using
an account from a foreign financial institution an access fee or surcharge
not otherwise prohibited under state or federal law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 615, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 470, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 423, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1089, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB100, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>