
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1,116" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1,116</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Insolvent banks; stockholders; restoration of solvency; conditions.</catchline><para id="id00">After the department has taken possession of any bank under the Nebraska Banking Act, the stockholders of the bank may repair its credit, restore or substitute its reserves, and otherwise place it in safe condition. Such bank shall not be permitted to reopen its business until the director, after careful investigation of its affairs, is of the opinion that its stockholders have complied with the law, that the bank's credit and funds are in all respects repaired, that its reserves are restored or are sufficiently substituted, and that it should be permitted again to reopen for business, at which time the director may issue written permission for resumption of business under its charter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 50, p. 91; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 330; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 51, p. 706; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 297, &#167; 5, p. 951; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8031; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-197; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 20, &#167; 1, p. 92; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 61, p. 166; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 14, &#167; 2, p. 93; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-197; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-1,102; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 116, p. 182; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 112. </para></source><annotation><para>Under this section, power to assess fully paid-up capital stock of a state bank to recoup losses or to restore depleted capital was committed to the directors of the bank upon authority from the stockholders, and fund voluntarily raised by stockholders and used by a holding company in eliminating bad paper and maintaining reserve is not an assessment. State ex rel. Spillman v. Citizens State Bank of Chadron, 115 Neb. 776, 214 N.W. 933 (1927).</para><para>Directors are not empowered to levy assessment where bank not taken over by Department of Banking, and stockholders have not authorized same. McMillan v. Chadron State Bank, 115 Neb. 767, 214 N.W. 931 (1927).</para><para>Directors have power to levy assessment only where stockholders have exercised their option to repair capital, restore reserves, and continue business, rather than to liquidate. Citizens State Bank of Stratton v. Strayer, 114 Neb. 567, 208 N.W. 662 (1926).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>