<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-607" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>8-607</statuteno><catchline>Failure to pay assessment, fee, or cost; Department of Banking and Finance; collection procedures; suspension or revocation of charter, license, or registration.</catchline><para>(1) If a financial institution or entity fails to pay an annual assessment, special assessment, examination fee, examination cost, investigation fee, investigation cost, hearing cost, or travel expense by a date specified by the Department of Banking and Finance, which shall be not less than thirty days from the date of billing, the department may, following notice and opportunity for hearing pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act, impose a fine in accordance with section 8-1,134 for each day the financial institution or entity is in arrears.</para><para>(2) If the financial institution or entity is in arrears for sixty days or more, the department may, in addition to any fine imposed under this section, following notice and opportunity for hearing pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act, suspend or revoke the charter, license, or registration of any financial institution or entity or the license or authority of any person responsible for such failure.</para><para>(3) The Director of Banking and Finance may, in his or her discretion and for good cause shown, permit the payment of any annual assessment, special assessment, examination fee, examination cost, investigation fee, investigation cost, hearing cost, travel expense, or fine, in installments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB836, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act, </emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>