<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-328"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-328</statuteno><catchline>Records; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Complete and adequate records of all accounts and of all minutes of proceedings of the members, directors and executive committee shall be maintained at all times at the office of the association. Records may be kept by hand, mechanical or electronic means.</para><para>(2) Every association shall maintain membership records, which shall show the name and address of the member, whether the member is a share account holder, or a borrower, or a share account holder and borrower, and the date of membership thereof. In the case of account-holding members, the association shall obtain a card containing the signature of the owner of such account or his duly authorized representative and shall preserve such signature card in the records of the association.</para><para>(3) Associations shall not be required to preserve or keep their records or files for a longer period than five years next after the first day of January of the year following the payment in full of a mortgage or other loan or the closing of a savings or investment account or the final closing or completion of any other contract or transaction; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that ledger sheets showing unpaid accounts in favor of members of such savings and loan associations shall not be destroyed.</para><para>(4) No liability shall accrue against any association destroying any such records after the expiration of the time provided in subsection (3) of this section, and in any cause or proceedings in which any such records or files may be called in question or be demanded of the association or any officer or employee thereof, a showing that such records and files have been destroyed in accordance with the terms of subsection (3) of this section shall be a sufficient excuse for the failure to produce them.</para><para>(5) All causes of action against an association based upon a claim or claims inconsistent with an entry or entries in any savings and loan association record or ledger, made in the regular course of business, shall be deemed to have accrued, and shall accrue, one year after the date of such entry or entries; and no action founded upon such a cause may be brought after the expiration of five years from the date of such accrual.</para><para>(6) The provisions of this section, so far as applicable, shall apply to the records of federal savings and loan associations.</para><para>(7) Any association may cause any or all records kept by such association to be copied or reproduced by any photostatic, photographic or microfilming process which correctly and permanently copies, reproduces or forms a medium for copying or reproducing the original record on a film or other durable material and such association may thereafter dispose of the original record. Any such copy or reproduction shall be deemed to be an original record for all purposes and shall be treated as an original record in all courts or administrative agencies for the purpose of its admissibility in evidence. A facsimile, exemplification or certified copy of any such copy or reproduction reproduced from a film record shall, for all purposes, be deemed a facsimile, exemplification or certified copy of the original.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 17, &#167; 12, p. 91; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 497; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XIX, &#167; 13, p. 729; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8095; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-313; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-328; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 195.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
