<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-115</statuteno><catchline>Banks; digital asset depositories; charter or grant of authority required.</catchline><para>No corporation shall conduct a bank or digital asset depository in this state without having first obtained a charter or under a grant of authority in the case of a digital asset depository in the manner provided in the Nebraska Banking Act or the Nebraska Financial Innovation Act, respectively.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 11, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 290; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 9, p. 689; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7990; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-120; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 15, p. 143; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-120; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-117; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 15, p. 140; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 36. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Financial Innovation Act,</emphasis> see section 8-3001.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>When application is made for charter, it is the duty of state officials to investigate and determine integrity and responsibility of applicants for charter. Shumway v. Warrick, 108 Neb. 652, 189 N.W. 301 (1922).</para><para>State Banking Board did not abuse discretion in refusing charter where evidence of unfitness and unfavorable financial ability was presented. In re Commercial State Bank, 105 Neb. 248, 179 N.W. 1021 (1920).</para><para>Refusal to grant charter is not justified where required capital paid in and proposed stockholders show requisite qualifications. State ex rel. Woolridge v. Morehead, 100 Neb. 864, 161 N.W. 569 (1917), L.R.A. 1917D 310 (1917).</para><para>Discretionary power given to state officials to refuse charter to savings bank to be conducted in same room and with same directors as national bank. State ex rel. Chamberlin v. Morehead, 99 Neb. 146, 155 N.W. 879 (1915).</para><para>Even though issued a charter under state law, state bank which becomes a member of Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation thereby becomes an instrumentality of United States, and federal statute forbidding embezzlement of funds of member bank applies to officer of such bank. United States v. Doherty, 18 F.Supp. 793 (D. Neb. 1937), affirmed 94 F.2d 495 (8th Cir. 1938).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>