
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-197" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-197</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Insolvent banks; liquidation by Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or by liquidating trustees.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Pending final judgment on the petition to enjoin under section 8-195, the department shall retain possession of the property and business of the bank. If not enjoined, the director shall proceed to liquidate the affairs of the bank as provided in the Nebraska Banking Act, except that: (a) The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation may, under the laws of this state, accept the appointment as receiver or liquidating agent of any insolvent bank the deposits of which are insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; or (b) when any bank is declared insolvent and ordered to be liquidated and the deposits of such bank are not insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, then depositors and other creditors of such insolvent bank, representing fifty-one percent or more of the deposits and other claims in number and in amount of the total thereof, shall have the right to liquidate such insolvent bank by and through liquidating trustees, who shall have the same power as the department and the director to liquidate such bank if, within thirty days after the filing of the declaration of insolvency, articles of trusteeship executed and acknowledged by fifty-one percent or more of the depositors and other creditors in number, representing fifty-one percent or more of the total of all deposits and claims in such bank, are filed with the director. The articles creating the trusteeship shall be in writing, shall name the trustees, shall state the terms and conditions of such trust, and shall become effective when it is determined by the director that fifty-one percent or more of the depositors and other creditors in number, representing fifty-one percent or more of the total of all deposits and claims in such bank, have signed and acknowledged the same. All nonconsenting depositors and other creditors of the insolvent bank shall be held to be subject to the terms and conditions of such trusteeship to the same extent and with the same effect as if they had joined in the execution thereof, and their respective claims shall be treated in all respects as if they had joined in the execution of such articles of trusteeship. Upon finding that such articles have been executed and acknowledged as provided in this section, the director shall thereupon transfer all of the assets of the insolvent bank to such liquidating trustees and take their receipt therefor, and all duties and responsibilities of the department and the director as otherwise provided by law with respect to such liquidation shall be assumed by such liquidating trustees. The director shall then be relieved from further responsibility in connection therewith, and the director and the person who issued the applicable bond or equivalent commercial insurance policy shall be released from further liability on the director's official bond or equivalent commercial insurance policy in respect to such liquidation. The trustees shall then proceed to liquidate such bank as nearly as may be in the manner provided by law for the liquidation of insolvent banks by the department acting as receiver and liquidating agent.</para><para id="id00">(2) When the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or any party other than the department is appointed receiver and liquidating agent of an insolvent bank or other financial institution chartered by the department, all references to the department or the director as provided in the act for the liquidation of such banks and financial institutions shall mean the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or other appointed receiver and liquidating agent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 53, p. 163; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 90; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-190; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-183; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 97, p. 173; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 994, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 94. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>