<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-135"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>8-135</statuteno><catchline>Deposits; withdrawal methods authorized; lease of safe deposit box; section; how construed.</catchline><para>(1) All persons, regardless of age, may become depositors in any bank and shall be subject to the same duties and liabilities respecting their deposits. Whenever a deposit is accepted by any bank in the name of any person, regardless of age, the deposit may be withdrawn by the depositor by any of the following methods:</para><para>(a) Check or other instrument in writing. The check or other instrument in writing constitutes a receipt or acquittance if the check or other instrument in writing is signed by the depositor and constitutes a valid release and discharge to the bank for all payments so made; or</para><para>(b) Electronic means through:</para><para>(i) Preauthorized direct withdrawal;</para><para>(ii) An automatic teller machine;</para><para>(iii) A debit card;</para><para>(iv) A transfer by telephone;</para><para>(v) A network, including the Internet; or</para><para>(vi) Any electronic terminal, computer, magnetic tape, or other electronic means.</para><para>(2) All persons, individually or with others and regardless of age, may enter into an agreement with a bank for the lease of a safe deposit box and shall be bound by the terms of the agreement.</para><para>(3) This section shall not be construed to affect the rights, liabilities, or responsibilities of participants in an electronic fund transfer under the federal Electronic Fund Transfer Act, 15 U.S.C. 1693 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2019, and shall not affect the legal relationships between a minor and any person other than the bank.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 132; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 35, p. 148; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB213, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB760, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB812, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB258, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>