<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-317"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-317</statuteno><catchline>Certificates of stock; records; payments; matured stock; right to withdraw.</catchline><para>Certificates of stock or other written evidence thereof shall be issued for each account in conformity with sections 8-301 to 8-340.01 and the bylaws. Every stockholder shall receive credit on the books of the association for all amounts paid by the stockholder upon the stockholder's subscription for stock, together with the stockholder's pro rata share of all dividends declared, as hereinafter provided, and when the sum of such payments and dividends, less all fines or other charges, equal the par value of the shares of stock held by the stockholder, the stockholder shall be entitled to receive such par value, with such interest not exceeding the legal rate, as the directors may determine, from the time of maturity until paid. Holders of stock thus matured and members desiring to withdraw before such maturity shall be paid the value of their stock in the order of the maturity of or notice of withdrawal of such stock. At no time shall more than two-thirds of the unloaned funds in the treasury of the association, inclusive of such funds applicable to the demands of withdrawing stockholders, as hereinbefore provided, be applicable to the demands of holders of matured stock without the consent of the board of directors.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 17, &#167; 6, p. 87; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 491; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XIX, &#167; 7, p. 726; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8089; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-307; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-317; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 14, &#167; 1, p. 79; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 481, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 508, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 717, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 9.</para></source><annotation><para>This section only fixes property rights of persons named; strangers to deposit allowed to establish oral trust in the account. Eden v. Eden, 182 Neb. 768, 157 N.W.2d 543 (1968).</para><para>Certificates issued by building and loan association to two or more persons are payable to any one of them. Rose v. Hooper, 175 Neb. 645, 122 N.W.2d 753 (1963).</para><para>Joint tenancy as to building and loan shares of stock is controlled by this section. Kindler v. Kindler, 169 Neb. 153, 98 N.W.2d 881 (1959).</para><para>When building and loan stock certificate is made to the joint account of two or more persons, the survivor or survivors are entitled to the full title thereto. Tobas v. Mutual Building &amp; Loan Assn., 147 Neb. 676, 24 N.W.2d 870 (1946).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
