<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>8-108</statuteno><catchline>Director of Banking and Finance; financial
institution examination; powers; procedure; charge.</catchline><para>(1) The director, his or her
deputy, or any duly appointed examiner shall have power to make a thorough
examination into all the books, papers, and affairs of any bank or other institution
in Nebraska subject to the department's jurisdiction, or its holding company,
if any, and in so doing to administer oaths and affirmations, to examine on
oath or affirmation the officers, agents, and clerks of such institution or
its holding company, if any, touching the matter which they may be authorized
and directed to inquire into and examine, and to subpoena the attendance of
any person or persons in this state to testify under oath or affirmation in
relation to the affairs of such institution or its holding company, if any.
Such powers shall include, but not be limited to, the authority to examine
and monitor by electronic means the books, papers, and affairs of any financial
institution or the holding company of a financial institution. The examination
may be in the presence of at least two members of the board of directors of
the institution or its holding company, if any, undergoing such examination,
and it shall be the duty of the examiner to incorporate in his or her report
the names of the directors in whose presence the examination was made.</para>
<para>(2) The director may accept
any examination or report from the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation,
the Federal Reserve Board, the Comptroller of the Currency, the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, or
a foreign state agency.</para>
<para>(3) The director may provide
any such examination or report to the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation,
the Federal Reserve Board, the Comptroller of the Currency, the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, or
a foreign state agency. The department shall have power to examine the books,
papers, and affairs of any electronic data processing center which has contracted
with a financial institution to conduct the financial institution's electronic
data processing business. The department may charge the electronic data processing
center for the time spent by examiners in such examination at the rate set
forth in section 8-606 for examiners' time spent in examinations of financial
institutions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 8, p. 69; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 287; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 6, p. 687; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7987; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 191, &#167; 8, p. 441; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-118; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 13, p. 142; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-118; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-115; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 8, p. 137; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 653, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 375, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 757, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB213, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>