<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-164" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>8-164</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Dividends declared; conditions.</catchline><para id="id00">The board of directors of any bank may declare dividends on its capital stock but only under the following conditions:</para><para id="id00">(1) All bad debts required to be charged off by either the board of directors or the department shall first have been charged off. All debts due any bank on which interest is past due and unpaid for a period of six months, unless such debts are well secured or in the process of collection, shall be considered bad debts within the meaning of this section; and</para><para id="id00">(2) Twenty percent of the net profits accumulated since the preceding dividend shall first have been carried to the surplus fund unless such surplus fund equals or exceeds the amount of the paid-up capital stock.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 28, p. 79; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 307; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 28, p. 696; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8009; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8142; </para><para>Laws 1930, Spec. Sess., c. 6, &#167; 11, p. 31; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 27, p. 149; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 10, &#167; 1, p. 78; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 122; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-142; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 19, &#167; 4, p. 104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-143; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 10, &#167; 1, p. 82; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 7, &#167; 1, p. 71; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-143; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 64, p. 160; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 653, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 996, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 979, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 62. </para><operativedate>August 24, 2017</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Stockholders ordinarily are entitled to share equally in the distribution of dividends, which should go to the record owners of the stock when such dividends are declared, but this may be varied by agreement between the stockholders, and a purchaser of corporate stock, with notice of such an agreement, takes title to the stock subject thereto. Empson v. Deuel County State Bank, 134 Neb. 597, 279 N.W. 293 (1938).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>