<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-132" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>8-132</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Banks; available funds; deficient reserve; impairment of capital; duty of bank; powers and duties of department; notice to bank.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The available funds of a bank shall consist of cash on hand and balances due from other solvent banks. Cash shall include lawful money of the United States and exchange for any clearinghouse association. Whenever the available funds or any reserve of any bank are deemed deficient by the director, such bank shall not make any new loans or discount otherwise than by discounting or purchasing bills of exchange payable at sight or make any dividends of its profits until it has on hand available funds and reserve deemed sufficient for operation by the director. The department shall notify any bank, in case its available funds or reserves are deemed deficient or its capital is impaired, to make good such available funds, reserves, or capital within such time as the director may direct, and any failure of such bank to make good any deficiency in the amount of its available funds, reserve, or capital within the time directed shall be cause for the department to take possession of such bank, declare it insolvent, and liquidate it as provided in the Nebraska Banking Act.</para><para>(2) The capital of any bank shall be deemed to be unimpaired when the amount of capital notes and debentures as represented by cash or sound assets exceeds an impairment as found by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 10, &#167; 23, p. 77; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 302; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. XVI, &#167; 23, p. 695; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8004; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 8-135; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 18, &#167; 24, p. 147; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 8-135; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 8-137; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 8-137; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 29, &#167; 32, p. 147; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 28, &#167; 1, p. 200; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 2, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 31. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>