<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-228"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-228</statuteno><catchline>State trust company; merger or consolidation with a national bank; effect.</catchline><para>When a state trust company has merged or consolidated with a national bank, the resulting national bank and trust company shall be considered the same business and corporate entity as the former national bank and the former trust company and as a continuation thereof and the ownership and title to all properties, assets, obligations, and liabilities of the merging or consolidating trust company shall automatically pass to and become the properties, assets, obligations, and liabilities of the resulting national bank and trust company and shall be deemed to be transferred to and vested in the resulting national bank and trust company without any deed or other transfer. The resulting national bank and trust company, by virtue of such consolidation or merger and without any order or other action on the part of any court or otherwise, shall hold and enjoy the same and all rights of property, franchises, and interests, including appointments, designations, and nominations and all other rights and interests as trustee, personal representative, administrator, registrar of stocks and bonds, guardian of estates, assignee, receiver, and in every other fiduciary capacity, in the same manner and to the same extent as such rights, franchises, and interests were held or enjoyed by any such merging or consolidating trust company at the time of such merger or consolidation. Upon the merger or consolidation, the state charter of the merging or consolidating state trust company shall automatically terminate and the charter shall be returned to the Department of Banking and Finance. Securities pledged to the department in accordance with section 8-209 shall be transferred to the name of the resulting national bank and trust company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 20, &#167; 2, p. 146; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 909, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 81, &#167; 44.</para></source></law></legaldoc>