<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1731"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1731</statuteno><catchline>Uniform application and interpretation of code; securities regulation and enforcement; governmental cooperation; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) To encourage uniform application and interpretation of the Commodity Code and securities regulation and enforcement in general, the director and the employees of the director may cooperate, including bearing the expense of the cooperation, with the securities agencies or director of another jurisdiction, Canadian province, or territory or such other agencies administering its commodity code, the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, the Securities and Exchange Commission, any self-regulatory organization established under the Commodity Exchange Act or the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, any national or international organization of commodities or securities officials or agencies, and any governmental law enforcement agency.</para><para>(2) The cooperation authorized by subsection (1) of this section may include, but need not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) Making joint examinations or investigations;</para><para>(b) Holding joint administrative hearings;</para><para>(c) Filing and prosecuting joint litigation;</para><para>(d) Sharing and exchanging personnel;</para><para>(e) Sharing and exchanging information and documents;</para><para>(f) Formulating and adopting mutual regulations, statements of policy, guidelines, proposed statutory changes, and releases; and</para><para>(g) Issuing and enforcing subpoenas at the request of the agency administering such code in another jurisdiction, the securities agency of another jurisdiction, the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, or the Securities and Exchange Commission if the information sought would also be subject to lawful subpoena for conduct occurring in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 575, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 29.</para></source></law></legaldoc>