<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1735"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1735</statuteno><catchline>Administrative proceeding; notice of intent; summary order; notice; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall commence an administrative proceeding under the Commodity Code by entering either a notice of intent to do a contemplated act or a summary order. The notice of intent or summary order may be entered without notice, without opportunity for hearing, and need not be supported by findings of fact or conclusions of law, but shall be in writing.</para><para>(2) Upon entry of a notice of intent or summary order, the director shall promptly notify all interested parties that the notice or summary order has been entered and the reasons therefor. If the proceeding is pursuant to a notice of intent, the director shall inform all interested parties of the date, time, and place set for the hearing on the notice. If the proceeding is pursuant to a summary order, the director shall inform all interested parties that they have fifteen business days from the entry of the order to file a written request for a hearing on the matter with the director and that the hearing will be scheduled to commence within thirty business days after the receipt of the written request, unless the parties consent to a later date or the hearing officer sets a later date for good cause.</para><para>(3) If the proceeding is pursuant to a summary order, the director, whether or not a written request for a hearing is received from any interested party, may set the matter down for hearing on the director's own motion.</para><para>(4) If no hearing is requested and none is ordered by the director, the summary order shall automatically become a final order after thirty business days.</para><para>(5) If a hearing is requested or ordered, the director, after notice of and opportunity for hearing to all interested persons, may modify or vacate the order or extend it until final determination.</para><para>(6) No final order or order after hearing may be returned without (a) appropriate notice to all interested persons, (b) opportunity for hearing by all interested persons, and (c) entry of written findings of fact and conclusions of law.</para><para>(7) Every hearing in an administrative proceeding under the Commodity Code shall be public unless the director grants a request joined in by all the respondents that the hearing be conducted privately.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 575, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 24.</para></source></law></legaldoc>