<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1725"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1725</statuteno><catchline>Director; investigation; enforcement; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The director may make investigations, within or without this state, as he or she finds necessary or appropriate to:</para><para>(a) Determine whether any person has violated or is about to violate any provision of the Commodity Code or any rule, regulation, or order of the director; or</para><para>(b) Aid in enforcement of the Commodity Code.</para><para>(2) The director may publish information concerning any violation of the code or any rule, regulation, or order of the director.</para><para>(3) For purposes of any investigation or proceeding under the Commodity Code, the director or any officer or employee designated by rule, regulation, or order may administer oaths and affirmations, subpoena witnesses, compel the attendance of witnesses, take evidence, and require the production of any books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, agreements, or other documents or records which the director finds to be relevant or material to the inquiry.</para><para>(4)(a) In case of contumacy by or refusal to obey a subpoena issued to any person, any court of competent jurisdiction, upon application by the director, may issue to that person an order requiring him or her to appear before the director or the officer designated by the director to produce documentary evidence if so ordered or to give evidence touching the matter under investigation or in question. Any failure to obey the order of the court may be punished by the court as a contempt of court.</para><para>(b) The request for order of compliance may be addressed to either (i) the district court of Lancaster County or the district court in the county where service may be obtained on the person refusing to testify or produce, if the person is within this state, or (ii) the appropriate district court of this state having jurisdiction over the person refusing to testify or produce, if the person is outside this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 575, &#167; 25.</para></source></law></legaldoc>