<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1728"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1728</statuteno><catchline>Violations of commodity code of foreign state; remedies.</catchline><para>(1) Upon a proper showing by the director or securities or commodity agency of a foreign state that a person other than a government or governmental agency or instrumentality has violated or is about to violate any provision of the commodity code of such state or any rule, regulation, or order of the director or securities or commodity agency of the foreign state, the court may grant appropriate legal and equitable remedies.</para><para>(2) Upon a showing of a violation of the securities or commodity act of the foreign state or a rule, regulation, or order of the director or securities or commodity agency of the foreign state, the court, in addition to traditional legal or equitable remedies, including temporary restraining orders, permanent or temporary prohibitory or mandatory injunctions, and writs of prohibition or mandamus, may grant the following special remedies:</para><para>(a) Disgorgement; and</para><para>(b) Appointment of a receiver, conservator, or ancillary receiver or conservator for the defendant or the defendant's assets located in this state.</para><para>(3) Appropriate remedies when the defendant is shown only about to violate the securities or commodity act of the foreign state or a rule, regulation, or order of the director or securities or commodity agency of the foreign state shall be limited to:</para><para>(a) A temporary restraining order;</para><para>(b) A temporary or permanent injunction;</para><para>(c) A writ of prohibition or mandamus; or</para><para>(d) An order appointing a receiver, conservator, or ancillary receiver or conservator for the defendant or the defendant's assets located in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 575, &#167; 28.</para></source></law></legaldoc>