<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id101">
<sectno id="id102" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 11.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" id="id103" statutenumber="8-1001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id105">8-1001</statuteno><catchline id="id106">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Nebraska Sale of Checks and Funds Transmission
Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Person means any individual, partnership, limited liability
company, association, joint-stock association, trust, or corporation, but
does not include the United States Government or the government of the State
of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(2) Licensee means any person duly licensed pursuant to the
act;</para>
<para>(3) Check means any check, draft, money order, personal money
order, or other instrument, order, or instruction for the transmission or
payment of money;</para>
<para>(4) Personal money order means any instrument for the transmission
or payment of money in relation to which the purchaser or remitter appoints
or purports to appoint the seller thereof as his or her agent for the receipt,
transmission, or handling of money, whether such instrument is signed by the
seller, by the purchaser or remitter, or by some other person;</para>
<para>(5) Director means the Director of Banking and Finance;</para>
<para>(6) Financial institution has the same meaning as in section
8-101;</para>
<para>(7) Transmission means a transfer by oral, written, or electronic
means or instruction; and</para>
<para>(8) Control
means the power, directly or indirectly, to direct the management or policies
of a licensee, whether through ownership of securities, by contract, or otherwise.
Any person who (a) has the power to elect a majority of executive officers,
managers, directors, trustees, or other persons exercising managerial authority
of a licensee or any person in control of a licensee, (b) directly or indirectly
has the right to vote ten percent or more of a class of voting security or
has the power to sell or direct the sale of ten percent or more of a class
of voting securities, (c) in the case of a limited liability company, is a
managing member, or (d) in the case of a partnership, has the right to receive,
upon dissolution, or has contributed, ten percent or more of the capital,
is presumed to control that licensee.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 192; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB327, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>