<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1108.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1108.03</statuteno><catchline>Federal covered security; filing fee; notice; open-end management company, face-amount certificate company, or unit investment trust; issue indefinite amount of securities; when.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, there shall be paid to the director a filing fee of one-tenth of one percent of the aggregate offering price of the federal covered securities under section 18(b)(2) of the Securities Act of 1933 which are to be offered in this state, but the filing fee shall in no case be less than one hundred dollars. If an issuer of securities covered by section 8-1108.02 sells securities in this state in excess of the aggregate amount of securities for which a filing fee has been paid, the director may allow the issuer to amend its filing to include the excess securities sold to persons within this state if the issuer pays a filing fee of three-tenths of one percent for the difference between the initial filing fee paid and the filing fee required under this section for the total amount of securities sold. Any such amendment of a filing to cover the excess securities, if granted, shall be effective retroactively to the date of the existing filing.</para><para>Any notice filed pursuant to this section shall be effective for a period of one year from the date received by the director or from such later date as indicated on the notice unless sooner terminated by the issuer. Notice filings must be renewed annually. Notices may be amended by submitting an amended notice filing indicating any material changes and paying any fees, pursuant to this section, that may be required by an increase in the amount of securities covered by the notice.</para><para>(2) An open-end management company or a face-amount certificate company, as those terms are defined in the Investment Company Act of 1940, may choose to issue an indefinite amount of securities, if the following conditions are met:</para><para>(a) The filing made pursuant to subsection (1) of section 8-1108.02 states the company intends to issue an indefinite amount of securities in this state and is accompanied by a filing fee of one thousand dollars;</para><para>(b) Within ninety calendar days after the expiration of the notice, the company files a sales report containing the actual sales that occurred in this state for the one-year notice period just expired. During such ninety-day period, the notice filing shall be considered continuous;</para><para>(c) If the sales report required by subdivision (b) of this subsection shows that the company sold securities in excess of the amount of securities for which the filing fee was paid, the company must pay an additional fee to be calculated as follows: One-tenth of one percent of the aggregate amount of securities sold up to the first ten million dollars; and one-twentieth of one percent of the remainder of the aggregate amount of securities sold. The initial filing fee of one thousand dollars shall be deducted from the fee required to be paid pursuant to such subdivision. If this calculation results in a negative amount, no payment shall be made and no credit or refund shall be allowed or returned for such negative amount;</para><para>(d) A company may continue the effectiveness of its notice to issue an indefinite amount of securities for another notification period if, upon the filing of a sales report required by subdivision (b) of this subsection, the company pays the renewal filing fee of one thousand dollars pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection, plus any additional fee which may be owed pursuant to subdivision (c) of this subsection;</para><para>(e) The notification shall be effective for a period of one year beginning on the date the notice is received by the director unless a later date is indicated on the notice; and</para><para>(f) Failure to file the sales report and pay any additional fees owed shall be cause for the director to issue an order suspending sales of the securities for which the sales report has not been filed and the appropriate fee has not been paid.</para><para>(3) A unit investment trust, as that term is defined in the Investment Company Act of 1940, may choose to issue an indefinite amount of securities for a period of one year or less if the following conditions are met:</para><para>(a) The unit investment trust issuer electing to offer an indefinite amount of securities files a notice pursuant to subsection (1) of section 8-1108.02, stating that it intends to issue an indefinite amount of securities for a period of one year or less in this state, and pays an initial filing fee of one hundred dollars with the notice filing;</para><para>(b) Within ninety calendar days after the occurrence of the earlier of the expiration of the trust's notice filing period, the termination of the offering by the issuer, or the completion of the offering, each trust files a sales report containing the total aggregate offering price of the securities sold in this state for the offering period just expired or terminated;</para><para>(c) If the sales report required by subdivision (b) of this subsection shows that the trust sold securities in excess of the amount of securities for which the filing fee was paid, the trust must pay an additional fee of one-tenth of one percent of the aggregate offering price of the excess securities sold. The initial fee of one hundred dollars shall be deducted from the filing fee paid pursuant to this subdivision. If this calculation results in a negative amount, no payment need be made and no credit or refund shall be allowed or returned for that negative amount; and</para><para>(d) Failure to file the sales report and pay any additional fees owed shall be cause for the director to issue an order suspending sales of the securities for which the sales report has not been filed and the appropriate fee has not been paid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 335, &#167; 10.</para></source></law></legaldoc>