<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1726"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1726</statuteno><catchline>Violations of code; director; powers.</catchline><para>(1) If the director believes, whether or not based upon an investigation conducted under section 8-1725, that any person has engaged or is about to engage in any act or practice constituting a violation of any provision of the Commodity Code or any rule, regulation, or order under the code, the director may:</para><para>(a) Issue a cease and desist order;</para><para>(b) Issue an order imposing (i) a fine in an amount that may not exceed twenty-five thousand dollars for any single violation or one hundred thousand dollars for multiple violations in a single proceeding or a series of related proceedings and (ii) the costs of investigation; or</para><para>(c) Initiate any of the actions specified in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) The director may institute any of the following actions in the appropriate district court of this state or in the appropriate courts of another state in addition to any legal or equitable remedies otherwise available:</para><para>(a) An action for a declaratory judgment;</para><para>(b) An action for a prohibitory or mandatory injunction to enjoin the violation and to ensure compliance with the Commodity Code or any rule, regulation, or order of the director;</para><para>(c) An action for disgorgement or restitution; or</para><para>(d) An action for appointment of a receiver or conservator for the defendant or the defendant's assets.</para><para>(3)(a) The fines and costs shall be in addition to all other penalties imposed by the laws of this state. The director shall collect the fines and costs and remit them to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit the costs to the Securities Act Cash Fund and distribute the fines in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(b) If a person fails to pay the administrative fine or investigation costs referred to in this section, a lien in the amount of such fine and costs may be imposed upon all assets and property of such person in this state and may be recovered by suit by the director. Failure of the person to pay such fine and costs shall constitute a separate violation of the code.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 575, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 283, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB259, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 51. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>