<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-1006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1006</statuteno><catchline>Application; fee; financial statement; surety bond; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Each application for a license shall be accompanied by:</para><para>(a) An application fee of one thousand dollars which shall not be subject to refund but which, if the license be granted, shall constitute the license fee for the first license year or part thereof;</para><para>(b) Financial statements, reasonably satisfactory to the director, showing that the applicant's net worth exceeds fifty thousand dollars; and</para><para>(c) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) of this section, a surety bond issued by a bonding company or insurance company authorized to do business in this state, in the principal sum of one hundred thousand dollars and in an additional principal sum of five thousand dollars for each location, in excess of one, at which the applicant proposes to sell checks in this state, but in no event shall the bond be required to be in excess of two hundred fifty thousand dollars. The bond shall be in form satisfactory to the director and shall run to the state for the benefit of any claimants against the applicant or its agents to secure the faithful performance of the obligations of the applicant and its agents with respect to the receipt, handling, transmission, and payment of money in connection with the sale of checks. The aggregate liability of the surety in no event shall exceed the principal sum of the bond. The bond shall remain in force and effect until the surety is released from liability by the director or until the bond is canceled by the surety, which cancellation may be had only upon thirty days' written notice to the director. Such cancellation shall not affect any liability incurred or accrued prior to the termination of the thirty-day period.</para><para>(2) In lieu of the corporate surety bond or bonds required by subdivision (1)(c) of this section, or of any portion of the principal thereof as required by such subdivision, the applicant may deposit, with the director or with such state banks or trust companies or national banks in this state as such applicant may designate and the director may approve, interest-bearing stocks and bonds, notes, debentures or other obligations of the United States or any agency or instrumentality thereof, or guaranteed by the United States, or of this state, or of a city, county, village, school district, or instrumentality of this state, or guaranteed by this state, to an aggregate amount, based upon principal amount or market value, whichever is lower, of not less than the amount of the required corporate surety bond or portion thereof. The securities shall be deposited and held to secure the same obligations as would the surety bond. The depositor shall have the right, with the approval of the director, to substitute other securities for those deposited and shall be required to do so on written order of the director made for good cause shown. The depositor shall pay the fees prescribed in section 8-602 for pledging and substitution of securities. So long as the licensee so depositing shall continue solvent, and is not in violation of the Nebraska Sale of Checks and Funds Transmission Act, such licensee shall be permitted to receive the interest or dividends on such deposit. The director shall provide for custody of such securities by a qualified trust company or bank located in the State of Nebraska or by any federal reserve bank. The compensation, if any, of the custodian for acting as such under the provisions of this section shall be paid by the depositing licensee. All such securities shall be subject to sale and transfer and to the disposal of the proceeds by the director only on the order of a court of competent jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 26, &#167; 6, p. 194; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 23.</para></source></law></legaldoc>