<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1108.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1108.02</statuteno><catchline>Federal covered security; filing; director; powers; sales; requirements; fees; consent to service of process.</catchline><para>(1) The director, by rule and regulation or order, may require the filing of any or all of the following documents with respect to a federal covered security under section 18(b)(2) of the Securities Act of 1933:</para><para>(a) Prior to the initial offer of such federal covered security in this state, all documents that are part of a federal registration statement filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission under the Securities Act of 1933, together with a consent to service of process signed by the issuer and with a filing fee as prescribed by section 8-1108.03;</para><para>(b) After the initial offer of such federal covered security in this state, all documents which are part of any amendment to the federal registration statement filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission under the Securities Act of 1933; and</para><para>(c) A sales report of the total amount of such federal covered securities offered or sold in this state, together with the filing fee prescribed by section 8-1108.03.</para><para>(2)(a) The director, by rule and regulation or order, may require the filing of any document required to be filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission under the Securities Act of 1933 with respect to a federal covered security under section 18(b)(3) of the Securities Act of 1933 together with a filing fee of two hundred dollars.</para><para>(b) The director, by rule and regulation or order, may require the filing of any document required to be filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission under the Securities Act of 1933 with respect to a federal covered security under section 18(b)(4) of the Securities Act of 1933 together with a filing fee of two hundred dollars. In addition, for federal covered securities under section 18(b)(4)(E) of the Securities Act of 1933, the director may also require the submission of a consent to service of process signed by the issuer and may require that such filing be made no later than fifteen days after the first sale of such federal covered security in this state.</para><para>(c) In connection with filings made pursuant to subdivisions (a) and (b) of this subsection, the director, by rule and regulation or order, may require the filing of all documents which are part of any amendment which the issuer is required to file with the Securities and Exchange Commission.</para><para>(3) The director may issue a stop order suspending the offer and sale of a federal covered security, except a federal covered security under section 18(b)(1) of the Securities Act of 1933, if he or she finds that (a) the order is in the public interest and (b) there is a failure to comply with any condition established under this section or with any other applicable provision of the Securities Act of Nebraska.</para><para>(4) The director, by rule and regulation or order, may waive any or all of the provisions of this section, except that the director does not have the authority to waive the payment of fees as required by this section.</para><para>(5) No person may bring an action pursuant to section 8-1118 based on the failure of an issuer to file any notice or pay any fee required by this section.</para><para>(6) All federal covered securities offered or sold in this state must be sold through a registered agent of a broker-dealer registered under the Securities Act of Nebraska or by persons duly exempted or excluded from such registration, except that this subsection shall not apply to the offer or sale of a federal covered security under section 18(b)(4)(E) of the Securities Act of 1933 if no commission or other remuneration is paid directly or indirectly for soliciting any prospective buyer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 335, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB214, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB252, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB771, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>