<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id41">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" id="id43" statutenumber="8-1402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1402</statuteno><catchline id="id46">Provide records
or information; costs.</catchline><para>(1) Any person, party, agency,
or organization requesting disclosure of records or information pursuant to
section 8-1401 shall pay the costs of providing such records or information,
unless:</para>
<para>(a) The request for disclosure is made pursuant to subdivision
(1)(a) of section 8-1401 and a Nebraska Supreme Court rule provides for the
method of payment;</para>
<para>(b) The request is made pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of
section 8-1401 and the rules for discovery provide for the method of payment;</para>
<para>(c) The request for disclosure is made pursuant to subdivision (1)(d) or (1)(e) of section
8-1401;</para>
<para>(d) Otherwise ordered by a court of competent jurisdiction;
or</para>
<para>(e) The person making the disclosure waives any or all of
the costs.</para>
<para>(2) The requesting person, party, agency, or organization
shall pay five dollars per hour per person for the time actually spent on
the service or, if such person can show that its actual expense in providing
the records or information was greater than five dollars per hour per person,
it shall be paid the actual cost of providing the records or information.</para>
<para>(3) No person authorized to receive payment pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section has an obligation to provide any records or information
pursuant to section 8-1401 until assurances are received that the costs due
under this section will be paid, except for requests made pursuant to subdivisions (1)(d), (1)(e), (1)(f), and (1)(g) of
section 8-1401.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 216, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 384, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 156, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB788, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>