<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-1012.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1012.01</statuteno><catchline>Director; powers; costs; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The director may examine the books, accounts, and records of each licensee.</para><para>(2) The director may contract with other state or federal regulatory agencies to conduct examinations of licensees if the licensee's principal place of business is outside of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) The director may enter into cooperative, coordinating, and information-sharing agreements with any other governmental agency that has similar supervision in this or any other state.</para><para>(4) The director may enter into joint examinations or joint enforcement actions with any other governmental agency that has similar supervision in this or any other state over any licensee.</para><para>(5) The director may, at any time, take such actions independently if he or she deems such actions to be necessary or appropriate to carry out his or her responsibilities under the Nebraska Sale of Checks and Funds Transmission Act or to ensure compliance with Nebraska law.</para><para>(6) The cost of any examination conducted under this section shall be paid by the licensee.</para><para>(7) The director may request information from a licensee regarding the conduct of its business or matters incidental to the business. A licensee receiving such a request for information has twenty-one calendar days from receipt of such request in which to submit a response. The director may assess a penalty up to one thousand dollars per day for each day a licensee fails to respond.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 13.</para></source></law></legaldoc>