<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-1108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1108</statuteno><catchline>Registration of securities; requirements;
fees; effective date; reports; director, powers.</catchline><para>(1) A registration
statement may be filed by the issuer, by any other person on whose behalf
the offering is to be made, or by a registered broker-dealer. Any document
filed under the Securities Act of Nebraska or a predecessor act within five
years preceding the filing of a registration statement may be incorporated
by reference in the registration statement to the extent that the document
is currently accurate. The director may by rule and regulation or order permit
the omission of any item of information or document from any registration
statement.</para>
<para>(2) The director may require as a condition of registration by qualification
(a) that the proceeds from the sale of the registered security be impounded
until the issuer receives a specified amount, (b) that the applicant comply
with the federal Securities Act of 1933 if it appears to the director to be
in the public interest or that the registered security is or will be offered
in such manner as to be subject to such act, (c) such reasonable conditions,
restrictions, or limitations upon the offering as may be in the public interest,
or (d) that any security issued within the past three years, or to be issued,
to a promoter for a consideration substantially different from the public
offering price or to any person for a consideration other than cash, be delivered
in escrow to him or her or to some other depository satisfactory to him or
her under an escrow agreement that the owners of such securities shall not
be entitled to sell or transfer such securities or to withdraw such securities
from escrow until all other stockholders who have paid for their stock in
cash shall have been paid a dividend or dividends aggregating not less than
six percent of the initial offering price shown to the satisfaction of the
director to have been actually earned on the investment in any common stock
so held. The director shall not reject a depository solely because of location
in another state. In case of dissolution or insolvency during the time such
securities are held in escrow, the owners of such securities shall not participate
in the assets until after the owners of all other securities shall have been
paid in full.</para>
<para>(3) For the registration of securities by coordination or qualification, there shall be paid to the
director a registration fee of one-tenth of one percent of the aggregate offering
price of the securities which are to be offered in this state, but the fee
shall in no case be less than one hundred dollars. When a registration statement
is withdrawn before the effective date or a preeffective stop order is entered
under section 8-1109, the director shall retain one hundred dollars of the
fee. Any issuer who sells securities in this state in excess of the aggregate
amount of securities registered may, at the discretion of the director and
while such registration is still effective, apply to register the excess securities
sold to persons within this state by paying a registration fee of three-tenths
of one percent for the difference between the initial fee paid and the fee
required in this subsection. Registration of the excess securities, if granted,
shall be effective retroactively to the date of the existing registration.</para>
<para>(4) When securities are registered by coordination or qualification, they may
be offered and sold by a registered broker-dealer. Every registration shall
remain effective for one year or until sooner revoked by the director or sooner
terminated upon request of the registrant with the consent of the director.
All outstanding securities of the same class as a registered security shall
be considered to be registered for the purpose of any nonissuer transaction.
A registration statement which has become effective may not be withdrawn for
one year from its effective date if any securities of the same class are outstanding.</para>
<para>(5) The director may require the person who filed the registration statement
to file reports, not more often than quarterly, to keep reasonably current
the information contained in the registration statement and to disclose the
progress of the offering with respect to registered securities which are being
offered and sold directly by or for the account of the issuer.</para>
<para>(6) A registration of securities shall be effective for a period of
one year or such shorter period as the director may determine.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 549, &#167; 8, p. 1781; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1157, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 305, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 335, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB214, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>