<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-1502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-1502</statuteno><catchline>Acquisition; notice required; exception;
Director of Banking and Finance; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided
in subsection (2) of this section, no person acting personally or as agent
shall acquire control of any state-chartered bank or trust company without
first giving sixty days' notice to the Department of Banking and Finance on
forms provided by the department of such proposed acquisition.</para>
<para>The Director of Banking and Finance, upon receipt of such notice, shall
act upon it within thirty days, and, unless he or she disapproves the proposed
acquisition within that period of time, it may become effective on the sixty-first
day after receipt without his or her approval, except that the director may
extend the thirty-day period an additional thirty days if in his or her judgment
any material information submitted is substantially inaccurate or the acquiring
party has not furnished all the information required by sections 8-1501 to
8-1505 or by the director.</para>
<para>An acquisition may be made prior to the expiration of the disapproval
period if the director issues written notice of his or her intent not to disapprove
the action.</para>
<para>Within three days after his or her decision to disapprove any proposed
acquisition, the director shall notify the acquiring party in writing of the
disapproval. The notice shall provide a statement of the basis for the disapproval.</para>
<para>(2) The notice requirements of subsection (1) of this section shall
not apply when:</para>
<para>(a) Shares of a state-chartered bank or trust company are acquired by
a person in the regular course of securing or collecting a debt previously
contracted in good faith or through inheritance or a bona fide gift if notice
of such acquisition is given to the department, on forms provided by the department,
within ten days after the acquisition;</para>
<para>(b) Shares of a state-chartered
bank or trust company are transferred from an individual or individuals to
a trust formed by the individual or individuals for estate-planning purposes
if (i) there is no change in the proportion of shares held by the trust for
such individual or individuals compared to the ownership of such individual
or individuals prior to the formation of the trust, (ii) the individual or
individuals control the trust, and (iii) notice of the proposed transfer is
given to the department, on forms provided by the department, at least thirty
days prior to the proposed transfer and the department does not disapprove
the transfer for the reason that the transfer is an attempt to subvert the
requirements of sections 8-1501 to 8-1505; or</para><para>(c) The director, the Governor, and the Secretary
of State jointly determine that an emergency exists which requires expeditious
action or that the department must act immediately to prevent probable failure
of the institution to be acquired.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 240, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 907, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 531, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 599, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB890, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>