<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2742"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2742</statuteno><catchline>Adoption of federal law by reference.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act:</para><para>(1) 31 C.F.R. 1010.100 means 31 C.F.R. 1010.100, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(2) Bank Secrecy Act means the Bank Secrecy Act, 31 U.S.C. 5311 et seq., and the implementing regulations of such act, as such act and regulations existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(3) Bank Service Company Act means the Bank Service Company Act, 12 U.S.C. 1861 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(4) Commodity Exchange Act means the Commodity Exchange Act, 7 U.S.C. 1 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(5) Edge Act means the Edge Act, 12 U.S.C. 611 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(6) Federal Credit Union Act means the Federal Credit Union Act, 12 U.S.C. 1751 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(7) Federal Deposit Insurance Act means the Federal Deposit Insurance Act, 12 U.S.C. 1811 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(8) Federal remittance rule means 12 C.F.R. part 1005, subpart B, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(9) Foreign Account Tax Compliance Act means the Foreign Account Tax Compliance Act, 26 U.S.C. 1471 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(10) International Banking Act of 1978 means the International Banking Act of 1978, 12 U.S.C. 3101 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(11) Securities Exchange Act of 1934 means the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, 15 U.S.C. 78a et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(12) United States Bankruptcy Code means 11 U.S.C. 101 et seq., as such sections existed on January 1, 2025; and</para><para>(13) Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism Act of 2001 means the Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism Act of 2001, Public Law 107-56, as such act existed on January 1, 2025.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB474, &#167; 47. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>