<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2737"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2737</statuteno><catchline>Examination of licensee; notice; director; powers; charge.</catchline><para>(1) The director may conduct an examination of a licensee upon reasonable written notice to the licensee. The director may examine a licensee without prior notice if the director has a reasonable basis to believe that the licensee is in noncompliance with the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act.</para><para>(2) An examination may be conducted in conjunction with examinations to be performed by representatives of agencies of another state or states or departments or agencies of the United States. The director, in lieu of an examination, may accept the examination report of an agency of another state or a department or an agency of the United States or a report prepared by an independent accounting firm. Reports so accepted are considered for all purposes as an official report of the department.</para><para>(3) The director may request financial data from a licensee in addition to that required under section 8-2734.</para><para>(4) The director may conduct an examination of any authorized delegate of a licensee within this state upon reasonable written notice to the licensee and the authorized delegate. The director may conduct an examination of any authorized delegate without prior notice to the authorized delegate or licensee only if the director has a reasonable basis to believe that the licensee or authorized delegate is in noncompliance with the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act.</para><para>(5) The total charge for an examination under this section shall be paid by the licensee or authorized delegate as set forth in sections 8-605 and 8-606.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB355, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>