
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking"  statutenumber="8-2733" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2733</statuteno><catchline>Application; director; duties; powers; onsite investigation; costs; denial of application; reasons; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the filing of a complete application under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act, the director shall investigate the financial condition and responsibility, financial and business experience, character, and general fitness of the applicant. The director may conduct an onsite investigation of the applicant, the reasonable cost of which shall be borne by the applicant. If the director finds that the applicant's business will be conducted honestly, fairly, and in a manner commanding the confidence and trust of the community and that the applicant has fulfilled the requirements imposed by the act and has paid the required application or license fee, the director shall issue a license to the applicant authorizing the applicant to engage in money transmission in this state. If these requirements have not been met, the director shall deny the application in writing, setting forth the reasons for the denial.</para><para>(2) The director shall approve or deny every application for an original license within one hundred twenty days after the date a complete application is submitted, which period may be extended by the written consent of the applicant. The director shall notify the applicant of the date when the application is deemed complete.</para><para>(3) Any applicant aggrieved by a denial issued by the director under the act may, at any time within fifteen business days after the date of the denial, request a hearing before the director. The hearing shall be held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and rules and regulations of the department.</para><para>(4) If an applicant for a license under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act does not complete the license application and fails to respond to a notice or notices from the department to correct the deficiency or deficiencies for a period of one hundred twenty days or more after the date the department sends the initial notice to correct the deficiency or deficiencies, the department may deem the application as abandoned and may issue a notice of abandonment of the application to the applicant in lieu of proceedings to deny the application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB185, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>