
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2107</statuteno><catchline>Director; powers and duties; costs.</catchline>
<para>(1) The director may enter
into cooperative, coordinating, and information-sharing agreements with any
other bank supervisory agencies or any organization affiliated with or representing
one or more bank supervisory agencies with respect to the periodic examination
or other supervision of any branch in Nebraska of an out-of-state state chartered
bank or any branch of a Nebraska state chartered bank in a host state, and
the director may accept such reports of examination and reports of investigation
in lieu of conducting his or her own examinations or investigations.</para>
<para>(2) The director may enter
into contracts with any bank supervisory agencies that have concurrent jurisdiction
over a Nebraska state chartered bank or an out-of-state state chartered bank
operating a branch in this state to engage the services of such agencies'
examiners or to provide the services of department examiners to such agency.</para>
<para>(3) The director may enter
into joint examinations or joint enforcement actions with other bank supervisory
agencies having concurrent jurisdiction over any branch in Nebraska of an
out-of-state state chartered bank or any branch of a Nebraska state chartered
bank in any host state. The director may, at any time, take such actions independently
if he or she deems such actions to be necessary or appropriate to carry out
his or her responsibilities under the Interstate Branching and Merger Act or
to ensure compliance with the laws of this state. In the case of an out-of-state
state chartered bank, the director shall recognize the exclusive authority
of the home state regulator over corporate government matters and the primary
responsibility of the home state regulator with respect to safety and soundness
matters.</para>
<para>(4) The cost of any examination
conducted under this section shall be assessed against such out-of-state state
chartered bank in the manner set forth in sections 8-605 and 8-606 and paid
for by such out-of-state state chartered bank.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 351, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB963, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>