<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="8-2724"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2724</statuteno><catchline>Licensure requirement; applicability.</catchline><para>(1) The requirement
for a license under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act does not apply to:</para>
<para>(a) The United States
or any department, agency, or instrumentality thereof;</para>
<para>(b) Any post office
of the United States Postal Service;</para><para>(c) A state or any political subdivision thereof;</para>
<para>(d)(i) Banks, credit
unions, building and loan associations, savings and loan associations, savings
banks, or mutual banks organized under the laws of any state or the United
States;</para><para>(ii)
Subsidiaries of the institutions listed in subdivision (d)(i) of this subsection;</para>
<para>(iii) Bank holding
companies which have a banking subsidiary located in Nebraska and whose debt
securities have an investment grade rating by a national rating agency; or</para>
<para>(iv) Authorized
delegates of the institutions and entities listed in subdivision (d)(i), (ii),
or (iii) of this subsection, except that authorized delegates that are not
banks, credit unions, building and loan associations, savings and loan associations,
savings banks, mutual banks, subsidiaries of any of the foregoing, or bank
holding companies shall comply with all requirements imposed upon authorized
delegates under the act;</para><para>(e) The provision of electronic transfer of government
benefits for any federal, state, or county governmental agency, as defined
in Consumer Financial Protection Bureau Regulation E, 12 C.F.R. part 1005,
as such regulation existed on January 1, 2013, by a contractor for and on
behalf of the United States or any department, agency, or instrumentality
thereof or any state or any political subdivision thereof; or</para>
<para>(f) An operator
of a payment system only to the extent that the payment system provides processing,
clearing, or settlement services between or among persons who are all exempt
under this section in connection with wire transfers, credit card transactions,
debit card transactions, automated clearinghouse transfers, or similar fund
transfers.</para><para>(2)
An authorized delegate of a licensee or of an exempt entity, acting within
the scope of its authority conferred by a written contract as described in
section 8-2739, is not required to obtain a license under the Nebraska Money
Transmitters Act, except that such an authorized delegate shall comply with
the other provisions of the act which apply to money transmission transactions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 24.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>