<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="8-2727"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2727</statuteno><catchline>License applicant; surety bond; alternate
security; duration.</catchline><para>(1)(a)
Each applicant shall submit, with the application, a surety bond issued by
a bonding company or insurance company authorized to do business in this state
and acceptable to the director in the principal sum of one hundred thousand
dollars and in an additional principal sum of five thousand dollars for each
location, in excess of one, at which the applicant proposes to sell and issue
payment instruments or engage in money transmission in this state, up to a
maximum of two hundred fifty thousand dollars. The director may increase the
amount of the bond to a maximum of two hundred fifty thousand dollars for
good cause. The bond shall be in a form satisfactory to the director and shall
run to the state for the benefit of any claimants against the licensee to
secure the faithful performance of the obligations of the licensee with respect
to the receipt, handling, transmission, and payment of money in connection
with money transmission. In the case of a bond, the aggregate liability of
the surety shall not exceed the principal sum of the bond. Any claimant against
the licensee may bring suit directly on the bond or the director may bring
suit on behalf of any claimant, either in one action or in successive actions.</para>
<para>(b) The director
may at any time require the filing of a new or supplemental bond in the form
as provided in subdivision (a) of this subsection if he or she determines
that the bond filed under this section is exhausted or is inadequate for any
reason, including, but not limited to, the financial condition of a licensee
or an applicant for a license or violations of the Nebraska Money Transmitters
Act, any rule, regulation, or order thereunder, or any state or federal law
applicable to a licensee or an applicant for a license. The new or supplemental
bond shall not exceed five hundred thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) In lieu of the corporate surety
bond or bonds required by subsection (1) of this section or of any portion
of the principal thereof as required by such subsection, the applicant or
licensee may deposit, with the director or with such banks or trust companies
located in this state or with any federal reserve bank as the applicant or
licensee may designate and the director may approve, interest-bearing stocks
and bonds, notes, debentures or other obligations of the United States or
any agency or instrumentality thereof, or guaranteed by the United States,
or of this state, or of a city, county, village, school district, or instrumentality
of this state, or guaranteed by this state, to an aggregate amount, based
upon principal amount or market value, whichever is lower, of not less than
the amount of the required corporate surety bond or portion thereof. The securities
shall be deposited and held to secure the same obligations as would the surety
bond. The licensee shall have the right, with the approval of the director,
to substitute other securities for those deposited and shall be required to
do so on written order of the director made for good cause shown. The licensee
shall pay the fees prescribed in section 8-602 for pledging and substitution
of securities. So long as the licensee so depositing shall continue solvent
and is not in violation of the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act, such licensee
shall be permitted to receive the interest or dividends on such deposit. The
safekeeping of such securities and all other expenses incidental to the pledging
of such securities shall be paid by the licensee. All such securities shall
be subject to sale and transfer and to the disposal of the proceeds by the
director only on the order of a court of competent jurisdiction.</para>
<para>(3) The surety bond
shall remain in effect until cancellation, which may occur only after thirty
days' written notice to the director. Cancellation shall not affect any liability
incurred or accrued during the period the surety bond was in effect.</para>
<para>(4) The surety bond
shall remain in place for at least five years after the licensee ceases money
transmission in this state, except that the director may permit the surety
bond to be reduced or eliminated before that time to the extent that the amount
of the licensee's payment instruments outstanding in this state are reduced.
The director may also permit a licensee to substitute a letter of credit or
such other form of security acceptable to the director for the surety bond
in place at the time the licensee ceases money transmission in the state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 27.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>