<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id302"><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2903"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2903</statuteno><catchline>Financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult; financial institution; authority to delay, refuse, or prevent certain activity; expiration; effect; immunity.</catchline><para>(1) When a financial institution, or an employee of a financial institution, reasonably believes, or has received information from the department or a law enforcement agency demonstrating that it is reasonable to believe, that financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult may have occurred, may have been attempted, is occurring, or is being attempted, the financial institution may, but is not required to:</para><para>(a) Delay or refuse a transaction with or involving the vulnerable adult or senior adult;</para><para>(b) Delay or refuse to permit the withdrawal or disbursement of funds contained in the vulnerable adult's or senior adult's account;</para><para>(c) Prevent a change in ownership of the vulnerable adult's or senior adult's account;</para><para>(d) Prevent a transfer of funds from the vulnerable adult's or senior adult's account to an account owned wholly or partially by another person;</para><para>(e) Refuse to comply with instructions given to the financial institution by an agent or a person acting for or with an agent under a power of attorney signed or purported to have been signed by the vulnerable adult or senior adult; or</para><para>(f) Prevent the designation or change the designation of beneficiaries to receive any property, benefit, or contract rights for a vulnerable adult or senior adult at death.</para><para>(2) A financial institution is not required to act under subsection (1) of this section when provided with information alleging that financial exploitation may have occurred, may have been attempted, is occurring, or is being attempted, but may use the financial institution's discretion to determine whether or not to act under subsection (1) of this section based on the information available to the financial institution at the time.</para><para>(3)(a)(i) A financial institution may notify any third party reasonably associated with a vulnerable adult or senior adult if the financial institution reasonably believes that the financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult may have occurred, may have been attempted, is occurring, or is being attempted.</para><para>(ii) A third party reasonably associated with a vulnerable adult or senior adult includes, but is not limited to, the following: (A) A parent, spouse, adult child, sibling, or other known family member or close associate of a vulnerable adult or senior adult; (B) an authorized contact provided by a vulnerable adult or senior adult to the financial institution; (C) a co-owner, additional authorized signatory, or beneficiary on a vulnerable adult's or a senior adult's account; (D) an attorney in fact, trustee, conservator, guardian, or other fiduciary who has been selected by a vulnerable adult or senior adult, a court, or a third party to manage some or all of the financial affairs of the vulnerable adult or senior adult; and (E) an attorney known to represent or have represented the vulnerable adult or senior adult.</para><para>(b) A financial institution may choose not to notify any third party reasonably associated with a vulnerable adult or senior adult of suspected financial exploitation of the vulnerable adult or senior adult if the financial institution reasonably believes the third party is, may be, or may have been engaged in the financial exploitation of the vulnerable adult or senior adult or if requested to refrain from making a notification by a law enforcement agency, if such notification could interfere with a law enforcement investigation.</para><para>(c) Nothing in this subsection shall prevent a financial institution from notifying the department or a law enforcement agency, if the financial institution reasonably believes that the financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult may have occurred, may have been attempted, is occurring, or is being attempted.</para><para>(4) The authority granted the financial institution under subsection (1) of this section expires upon the sooner of: (a) Thirty business days after the date on which the financial institution first acted under subsection (1) of this section; (b) when the financial institution is satisfied that the transaction or act will not result in financial exploitation of the vulnerable adult or senior adult; or (c) upon termination by an order of a court of competent jurisdiction.</para><para>(5) Unless otherwise directed by order of a court of competent jurisdiction, a financial institution may extend the duration under subsection (4) of this section based on a reasonable belief that the financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult may continue to occur or continue to be attempted.</para><para>(6) A financial institution and its bank holding company, if any, and any employees, agents, officers, and directors of the financial institution and its bank holding company, if any, shall be immune from any civil, criminal, or administrative liability that may otherwise exist (a) for delaying or refusing to execute a transaction, withdrawal, or disbursement, or for not delaying or refusing to execute such transaction, withdrawal, or disbursement under this section and (b) for actions taken in furtherance of determinations made under subsections (1) through (5) of this section.</para><para>(7)(a) Notwithstanding any other law to the contrary, the refusal by a financial institution to engage in a transaction as authorized under subsection (1) of this section shall not constitute the wrongful dishonor of an item under section 4-402, Uniform Commercial Code.</para><para>(b) Notwithstanding any other law to the contrary, a reasonable belief that payment of a check will facilitate the financial exploitation of a vulnerable adult or senior adult shall constitute reasonable grounds to doubt the collectability of the item for purposes of the federal Check Clearing for the 21st Century Act, 12 U.S.C. 5001 et seq., the federal Expedited Funds Availability Act, 12 U.S.C. 4001 et seq., and 12 C.F.R. part 229, as such acts and part existed on January 1, 2020.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 20. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>