<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2721"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2721</statuteno><catchline>Licensee; report to director; when; breach of security of the system; notification.</catchline><para>(1) A licensee shall file a report with the director within one business day after the licensee has reason to know of the occurrence of any of the following events:</para><para>(a) The filing of a petition by or against the licensee under the United States Bankruptcy Code for bankruptcy or reorganization;</para><para>(b) The filing of a petition by or against the licensee for receivership, the commencement of any other judicial or administrative proceeding for its dissolution or reorganization, or the making of a general assignment for the benefit of its creditors; or</para><para>(c) The commencement of a proceeding to revoke or suspend the license of a licensee in a state or country in which the licensee engages in business or is licensed.</para><para>(2) A licensee shall file a report with the director within three business days after the licensee has reason to know of the occurrence of any of the following events:</para><para>(a) A charge or conviction of the licensee or of a key individual or person in control of the licensee for a felony; or</para><para>(b) A charge or conviction of an authorized delegate for a felony.</para><para>(3)(a) Except as provided in subdivisions (b) and (c) of this subsection, a licensee shall notify the director in writing or through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry within three business days after the time that the licensee becomes aware of any breach of security of the system of computerized data owned or licensed by the licensee, which contains personal information about a Nebraska resident, or the unauthorized access to or use of such information about a Nebraska resident as a result of the breach. For purposes of this subsection, the terms breach of the security of the system and personal information have the same meaning as in section 87-802.</para><para>(b) If a licensee would be required under Nebraska law to provide notification to a Nebraska resident regarding such breach, then the licensee shall provide a copy of such notification to the department prior to or simultaneously with the licensee's notification to the Nebraska resident.</para><para>(c) Notice required by this subsection may be delayed if a law enforcement agency determines that the notice will impede a criminal investigation. Notice shall be made in good faith and without unreasonable delay as soon as possible after the law enforcement agency determines that notification will no longer impede the investigation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB474, &#167; 26. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>