<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2104"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2104</statuteno><catchline>Out-of-state bank; powers; interstate
merger transaction; notice; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) An out-of-state
bank may establish and maintain a branch or acquire a branch in this state
upon compliance with any applicable requirements of the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act for
registration or qualification to do business in this state.</para>
<para>(2) An out-of-state bank may engage in an interstate merger transaction
in this state in which it is the resulting bank and establish one or more
branches in this state. The out-of-state bank shall notify the department
of the proposed interstate merger transaction involving a Nebraska state chartered
bank within fifteen days after the date it files an application for an interstate
merger transaction with its primary regulator.</para>
<para>(3) An out-of-state bank may conduct only those activities at its branch
or branches in this state that are permissible under the laws of Nebraska
or of the United States, except that an out-of-state bank with trust powers
may exercise all trust powers in this state as a Nebraska bank with trust
powers subject to the requirements of section 8-209.</para>
<para>(4) All branches of an out-of-state bank shall comply with all applicable
Nebraska laws and regulations in the conduct of their business in this state
to the maximum extent authorized by federal law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 351, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1089, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB963, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 234.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>