<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2730"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2730</statuteno><catchline>Licensee; license and registration through Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry; department; powers; director; reports; powers and duties; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Effective July 1, 2014, the department shall require licensees under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act to be licensed and registered through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. In order to carry out this requirement, the department is authorized to participate in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry. For this purpose, the department may establish, by adopting and promulgating rules and regulations or by order, requirements as necessary. The requirements may include, but are not limited to:</para><para>(a) Background checks of applicants and licensees, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(i) Fingerprints of every executive officer, director, partner, member, sole proprietor, or shareholder submitted to the Federal Bureau of Investigation and any other governmental agency or entity authorized to receive such information for a state, national, and international criminal history record information check, except that the department shall not require the submission of fingerprints by (A) an executive officer or director of an applicant or licensee which is either a publicly traded company or a wholly owned subsidiary of a publicly traded company or (B) an applicant or licensee who has previously submitted the fingerprints of an executive officer, director, partner, member, sole proprietor, or shareholder directly to the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry and the Federal Bureau of Investigation will accept such fingerprints for a criminal background check;</para><para>(ii) Checks of civil or administrative records;</para><para>(iii) Checks of an applicant's or a licensee's credit history; or</para><para>(iv) Any other information as deemed necessary by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry;</para><para>(b) The payment of fees to apply for or renew a license through the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry;</para><para>(c) The setting or resetting, as necessary, of renewal processing or reporting dates;</para><para>(d) Information and reports pertaining to authorized delegates; and</para><para>(e) Amending or surrendering a license or any other such activities as the director deems necessary for participation in the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(2) In order to fulfill the purposes of the act, the department is authorized to establish relationships or contracts with the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry or other entities designated by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry to collect and maintain records and process transaction fees or other fees related to licensees or other persons subject to the act. The department may allow such system to collect licensing fees on behalf of the department and allow such system to collect a processing fee for the services of the system directly from each licensee or applicant for a license.</para><para>(3) The director is required to regularly report enforcement actions and other relevant information to the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry subject to the provisions contained in section 8-2731.</para><para>(4) The director shall establish a process whereby applicants and licensees may challenge information entered into the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry by the director.</para><para>(5) The department shall ensure that the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry adopts a privacy, data security, and breach of security of the system notification policy. The director shall make available upon written request a copy of the contract between the department and the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry pertaining to the breach of security of the system provisions.</para><para>(6) The department shall upon written request provide the most recently available audited financial report of the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry.</para><para>(7) The director may use the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry as a channeling agent for requesting information from and distributing information to the United States Department of Justice or any other governmental agency in order to reduce the points of contact which the Federal Bureau of Investigation may have to maintain for purposes of subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 55. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>