<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2307"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2307</statuteno><catchline>Out-of-state trust company; instate branch trust offices; director; approval.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall act within ninety days after receipt of notice under section 8-2306. The director may extend the ninety-day period if he or she determines that the notice raises issues that require additional information or additional time for analysis.</para><para>(2) The director may deny approval of the proposed branch trust office if he or she finds that the out-of-state trust company lacks sufficient financial resources to establish the branch trust office without adversely affecting its safety or soundness or that the establishment of the proposed branch trust office would not be in the public interest.</para><para>(3) If the out-of-state trust company is not insured by an agency of the federal government, the director may condition his or her approval on the satisfaction by the out-of-state trust company of any requirement applicable to a Nebraska state-chartered trust company pursuant to the Nebraska Trust Company Act.</para><para>(4) If the director does not extend the ninety-day period pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, he or she shall certify his or her approval or denial of the notice to the out-of-state trust company's home state regulator on or before the ninetieth day after receipt of notice. If the director imposes conditions pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, the conditions shall be satisfied prior to the director's certification of approval. A copy of the certification of approval shall be sent to the out-of-state trust company. If the notice is approved, the out-of-state trust company may commence business at the branch trust office upon compliance with sections 8-209 and 8-210.</para><para>(5) If the director does extend the ninety-day period pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, he or she shall act on the notice as soon as reasonably possible. Upon reaching a decision on the notice, the director shall certify his or her approval or denial of the notice to the out-of-state trust company's home state regulator. If the director imposes conditions pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, the conditions shall be satisfied prior to the director's certification of approval. A copy of such certification shall be sent to the out-of-state trust company. If the notice is approved, the out-of-state trust company may commence business at the branch trust office upon compliance with sections 8-209 and 8-210.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 60.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Trust Company Act,</emphasis> see section 8-201.01.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>