<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2726" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2726</statuteno><catchline>License; applicant; qualifications; requirements.</catchline><para>To qualify for a license under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act, an applicant, at the time of filing for a license, and a licensee at all times after a license is issued, shall satisfy the following requirements:</para><para>(1) Each applicant or licensee must have a net worth of not less than fifty thousand dollars, calculated in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles;</para><para>(2) The financial condition and responsibility, financial and business experience, and character and general fitness of the applicant or licensee must reasonably warrant the belief that the applicant's or licensee's business will be conducted honestly, fairly, and in a manner commanding the confidence and trust of the community. In determining whether this requirement is met and for purposes of investigating compliance with the act, the director may review and consider the relevant business records and capital adequacy of the applicant or licensee;</para><para>(3) Each corporate applicant or licensee must be organized under the laws of any state of the United States, the District of Columbia, any territory of the United States, Puerto Rico, Guam, American Samoa, the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, the Virgin Islands, or the Northern Mariana Islands, and must be in good standing in the place of its incorporation;</para><para>(4) Each applicant or licensee must be registered or qualified to do business in the State of Nebraska; and</para><para>(5) Each applicant or licensee must maintain an office in the United States.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB363, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>