<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="8-2737"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2737</statuteno><catchline>Onsite examination of licensee; notice;
examination fee; costs; director; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The director may conduct an annual onsite examination
of a licensee upon reasonable written notice to the licensee. The director
may examine a licensee without prior notice if the director has a reasonable
basis to believe that the licensee is in noncompliance with the Nebraska Money
Transmitters Act. If the director concludes that an onsite examination of
a licensee is necessary, the licensee shall pay an examination fee and the
director shall charge for the actual cost of the examination at an hourly
rate set by the director which is sufficient to cover all reasonable expenses
associated with the examination. The onsite examination may be conducted in
conjunction with examinations to be performed by representatives of agencies
of another state or states. The director, in lieu of an onsite examination,
may accept the examination report of an agency of another state or a report
prepared by an independent accounting firm. Reports so accepted are considered
for all purposes as an official report of the director. The licensee shall
be responsible for the reasonable expenses incurred by the department, the
agencies of another state, or an independent licensed or certified public
accountant in making the examination or report.</para>
<para>(2) The director may
request financial data from a licensee in addition to that required under
section 8-2734 or conduct an onsite examination of any authorized delegate
or location of a licensee within this state without prior notice to the authorized
delegate or licensee only if the director has a reasonable basis to believe
that the licensee or authorized delegate is in noncompliance with the Nebraska
Money Transmitters Act. When the director examines an authorized delegate's
operations, the authorized delegate shall pay all reasonably incurred costs
of such examination. When the director examines a licensee's location, the
licensee shall pay all reasonably incurred costs of such examination.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 37.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>