<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking"  statutenumber="8-2743"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2743</statuteno><catchline>Cease and desist order; notice; hearing;
vacation or modification of order; when; judicial review; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) The department may
order any person to cease and desist whenever the department determines that
the person has violated the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act. Upon entry of
a cease and desist order, the director shall promptly notify the affected
person that such order has been entered, of the reasons for such order, and
that upon receipt, within fifteen business days after the date of the order,
of a written request from the affected person, a hearing will be scheduled
within thirty business days after the date of receipt of the written request,
unless the parties consent to a later date or the hearing officer sets a later
date for good cause. The hearing shall be held in accordance with the Administrative
Procedure Act and rules and regulations of the department. If a hearing is
not requested and none is ordered by the director, the order shall remain
in effect until it is modified or vacated.</para>
<para>(2) The director may
issue an order against a licensee to cease and desist from engaging in money
transmission through an authorized delegate that is the subject of a separate
order pursuant to section 8-2742.</para><para>(3) The director may vacate or modify a cease and
desist order if he or she finds that the conditions which caused its entry
have changed or that it is otherwise in the public interest to do so.</para>
<para>(4) A person aggrieved
by a cease and desist order of the department may obtain judicial review of
the order. The review shall be in the manner prescribed in the Administrative
Procedure Act. The director may obtain an order from the district court of
Lancaster County for enforcement of the cease and desist order.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 43.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>