<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking"  statutenumber="8-2736"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2736</statuteno><catchline>Acquisition of control of licensee;
notice to director; director; duties; powers; disapproval; grounds; notice;
hearing.</catchline><para>(1)
No person acting personally or as an authorized delegate shall acquire control
of any licensee under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act without first giving
thirty days' notice to the director on forms prescribed by the director of
such proposed acquisition.</para>
<para>(2) The director, upon
receipt of such notice, shall act upon the proposed acquisition within thirty
days, and unless he or she disapproves the proposed acquisition within that
period of time, the acquisition shall become effective on the thirty-first
day after receipt without the director's approval, except that the director
may extend the thirty-day period an additional thirty days if, in his or her
judgment, any material information submitted is substantially inaccurate or
the acquiring person has not furnished all the information required by the
director.</para><para>(3)
An acquisition may be made prior to the expiration of the disapproval period
if the director issues written notice of his or her intent not to disapprove
the action.</para><para>(4)(a)
The director may disapprove any proposed acquisition if:</para>
<para>(i) The financial condition
of any acquiring person is such as might jeopardize the financial stability
of the acquired licensee;</para><para>(ii) The business experience, character, and general
fitness of any acquiring person or of any of the proposed management personnel
of the acquiring person indicate that the acquired licensee would not be operated
honestly, carefully, or efficiently; or</para><para>(iii) Any acquiring person neglects, fails, or refuses
to furnish all information required by the director.</para><para>(b) The director may require that
any acquiring person comply with the application requirements of section 8-2729.</para>
<para>(c) The director shall
notify the acquiring person in writing of disapproval of the acquisition.
The notice shall provide a statement of the basis for the disapproval.</para>
<para>(d) Within fifteen
business days after receipt of written notice of disapproval, the acquiring
person may request a hearing on the proposed acquisition. The hearing shall
be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and rules and regulations
of the department. Following such hearing, the director shall, by order, approve
or disapprove the proposed acquisition on the basis of the record made at
the hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 36.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>