<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2734"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2734</statuteno><catchline>License; renewal application; licensing fee; processing fee; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Initial licenses shall remain in full force and effect until the next succeeding December 31. Each licensee shall, annually on or before December 31 of each year, file a license renewal application and pay to the director a license fee of two hundred fifty dollars and any processing fee allowed under subsection (2) of section 8-2730, both of which shall not be subject to refund.</para><para>(2) The renewal application and license fee shall be accompanied by a report, in a form prescribed by the director, which shall include:</para><para>(a) A copy of the licensee's most recent audited consolidated annual financial statement including balance sheet, statement of income or loss, statement of changes in shareholders' equity, and statement of changes in financial position, or, if a licensee is a wholly owned subsidiary of another corporation, the consolidated audited annual financial statement of the parent corporation may be filed in lieu of the licensee's audited annual financial statement;</para><para>(b) The number of payment instruments sold by the licensee in the state, the dollar amount of those instruments, and the dollar amount of payment instruments currently outstanding, for the most recent quarter for which data is available before the date of the filing of the renewal application, but in no event more than one hundred twenty days before the renewal date;</para><para>(c) Any material changes to any of the information submitted by the licensee on its original application which have not previously been reported to the director on any other report required to be filed under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act; and</para><para>(d) A list of the licensee's permissible investments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB778, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB363, &#167; 21. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>