<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2606"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2606</statuteno><catchline>Consumer reporting agency; disclose process of placing and temporarily lifting security freeze; consumer request to lift freeze; when.</catchline><para>(1) When a consumer requests a security freeze under section 8-2603, the consumer reporting agency shall disclose the process of placing and temporarily lifting the security freeze, including the process for allowing access to his or her credit report or any other information derived from his or her file for a specified period of time by temporarily lifting the security freeze.</para><para>(2) If a consumer wishes to allow his or her credit report or any other information derived from his or her file to be accessed for a specified period of time by temporarily lifting the security freeze placed under section 8-2603, the consumer shall contact the consumer reporting agency, request that the freeze be temporarily lifted, and provide the following:</para><para>(a) Sufficient proof of identification of the consumer;</para><para>(b) The unique personal identification number or password provided by the consumer reporting agency under section 8-2605; and</para><para>(c) The proper information regarding the specified time period.</para><para>(3)(a) Until January 1, 2009, a consumer reporting agency that receives a request from a consumer to temporarily lift a security freeze placed under section 8-2603 on his or her file shall comply with the request no later than three business days after receiving the request.</para><para>(b) A consumer reporting agency shall develop procedures involving the use of a telephone, the Internet, or other electronic media to receive and process a request from a consumer to temporarily lift a security freeze placed under section 8-2603 on his or her file in an expedited manner. By January 1, 2009, a consumer reporting agency shall comply with a request to temporarily lift a security freeze within fifteen minutes after receiving such request by telephone or through a secure electronic method.</para><para>(4) A consumer reporting agency is not required to temporarily lift a security freeze within the time provided in subsection (3) of this section if:</para><para>(a) The consumer fails to meet the requirements of subsection (2) of this section; or</para><para>(b) The consumer reporting agency's ability to temporarily lift the security freeze within the time provided in subsection (3) of this section is prevented by:</para><para>(i) An act of God, including fire, earthquake, hurricane, storm, or similar natural disaster or phenomena;</para><para>(ii) An unauthorized or illegal act by a third party, including terrorism, sabotage, riot, vandalism, labor strike or dispute disrupting operations, or similar occurrence;</para><para>(iii) Operational interruption, including electrical failure, unanticipated delay in equipment or replacement part delivery, computer hardware or software failure inhibiting response time, or similar disruption;</para><para>(iv) Governmental action, including an emergency order or regulation, judicial or law enforcement action, or similar directive;</para><para>(v) Regularly scheduled maintenance, during other than normal business hours, of the consumer reporting agency's system or updates to such system;</para><para>(vi) Commercially reasonable maintenance of, or repair to, the consumer reporting agency's system that is unexpected or unscheduled; or</para><para>(vii) Receipt of a removal request outside of normal business hours.</para><para>For purposes of this subsection, normal business hours means Sunday through Saturday, between the hours of 6:00 a.m. and 9:30 p.m., in the applicable time zone in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB674, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB835, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>