
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks And Banking"  statutenumber="8-2741"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2741</statuteno><catchline>License; suspension or revocation;
grounds; director; powers and duties; hearing; surrender; cancellation; expiration.</catchline><para>(1) The director may,
following a hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, suspend
or revoke any license issued pursuant to the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act
if he or she finds:</para>
<para>(a) Any fact or condition
exists that, if it had existed at the time when the licensee applied for its
original or renewal license, would have been grounds for denying such application;</para>
<para>(b) The licensee's net
worth has become inadequate and the licensee, after ten days' written notice
from the director, failed to take such steps as the director deems necessary
to remedy such deficiency;</para><para>(c) The licensee knowingly violated any material provision
of the act or any rule or order validly adopted and promulgated under the
act;</para><para>(d)
The licensee conducted money transmission in an unsafe or unsound manner;</para>
<para>(e) The licensee is insolvent;</para>
<para>(f) The licensee has
suspended payment of its obligations, made an assignment for the benefit of
its creditors, or admitted in writing its inability to pay its debts as they
became due;</para><para>(g)
The licensee filed for liquidation or reorganization under any bankruptcy
law;</para><para>(h)
The licensee refused to permit the director to make any examination authorized
by the act; or</para><para>(i)
The licensee willfully failed to make any report required by the act.</para>
<para>(2) In determining whether
a licensee is engaging in an unsafe or unsound practice, the director may
consider the size and condition of the licensee's money transmission, the
magnitude of the loss, if any, the gravity of the violation of the act, and
the previous conduct of the licensee.</para><para>(3) A licensee may voluntarily surrender a license
by delivering to the director written notice of the surrender, but a surrender
shall not affect civil or criminal liability for acts committed before the
surrender or liability for any fines which may be levied against the licensee
or any of its officers, directors, key shareholders, partners, or members
for acts committed before the surrender.</para><para>(4)(a) If a licensee fails to renew its license as
required by section 8-2734 and does not voluntarily surrender the license
pursuant to this section, the department may issue a notice of expiration
of the license to the licensee in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para>
<para>(b) If a licensee fails
to maintain a surety bond as required by section 8-2727, the department may
issue a notice of cancellation of the license in lieu of revocation proceedings.</para>
<para>(5) Revocation, suspension,
surrender, cancellation, or expiration of a license shall not impair or affect
the obligation of a preexisting lawful contract between the licensee and any
person.</para><para>(6)
Revocation, suspension, cancellation, or expiration of a license shall not
affect civil or criminal liability for acts committed before the revocation,
suspension, cancellation, or expiration or liability for any fines which may
be levied against the licensee or any of its officers, directors, key shareholders,
partners, or members for acts committed before the revocation, suspension,
cancellation, or expiration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 41.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>