<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="8-2734"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2734</statuteno><catchline>License; renewal application; licensing
fee; processing fee; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1)(a) All initial licenses shall remain in full force and
effect until the next succeeding July 1. Beginning July 1, 2014, initial licenses
shall remain in full force and effect until the next succeeding December 31.
Thereafter, each licensee shall, annually on or before December 31 of each
year, file a license renewal application and pay to the director a license
fee of two hundred fifty dollars and any processing fee allowed under subsection
(2) of section 8-2730, both of which shall not be subject to refund.</para>
<para>(b) Licenses which expire
on July 1, 2014, may be renewed until December 31, 2014, upon submission of
a license renewal application and compliance with subsection (2) of this section.
For such renewals, the department shall prorate the license fee provided in
subdivision (1)(a) of this section using a factor of six-twelfths.</para>
<para>(2) The renewal application
and license fee shall be accompanied by a report, in a form prescribed by
the director, which shall include:</para><para>(a) A copy of the licensee's most recent audited consolidated
annual financial statement including balance sheet, statement of income or
loss, statement of changes in shareholders' equity, and statement of changes
in financial position, or, if a licensee is a wholly owned subsidiary of another
corporation, the consolidated audited annual financial statement of the parent
corporation may be filed in lieu of the licensee's audited annual financial
statement;</para><para>(b)
The number of payment instruments sold by the licensee in the state, the dollar
amount of those instruments, and the dollar amount of payment instruments
currently outstanding, for the most recent quarter for which data is available
before the date of the filing of the renewal application, but in no event
more than one hundred twenty days before the renewal date;</para>
<para>(c) Any material changes
to any of the information submitted by the licensee on its original application
which have not previously been reported to the director on any other report
required to be filed under the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act;</para>
<para>(d) A list of the licensee's
permissible investments; and</para><para>(e) A list of the locations, if any, within this state
at which money transmission is being conducted by either the licensee or its
authorized delegates.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 34.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>