<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2740"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2740</statuteno><catchline>Money transmission; unlicensed person; cease and desist order; temporary restraining order.</catchline><para>(1) If the director has reason to believe that a person has violated or is violating section 8-2709, the director may issue an order to cease and desist requiring that the person cease and desist from the violation of section 8-2709.</para><para>(2) In an emergency, the director may petition the district court of Lancaster County for the issuance of a temporary restraining order ex parte pursuant to the rules of civil procedure.</para><para>(3) An order to cease and desist becomes effective when issued by the director.</para><para>(4) An order to cease and desist remains effective and enforceable pending the completion of an administrative proceeding pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(5) A person that is served with an order to cease and desist for violating section 8-2709 may petition the district court of Lancaster County for a judicial order setting aside, limiting, or suspending the enforcement, operation, or effectiveness of the order pending the completion of an administrative proceeding pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(6) Upon entry of an order to cease and desist, the director shall promptly notify the affected person that such order has been entered and provide opportunity for hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB474, &#167; 45. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>