<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2312"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2312</statuteno><catchline>Branch trust office; representative trust office; director; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The director may examine any branch trust office or representative trust office established and maintained in this state by any out-of-state state trust company as he or she deems necessary to determine whether the branch trust office or representative trust office is being operated in compliance with Nebraska law and in accordance with safe and sound practices.</para><para>(2) The director may prescribe requirements for periodic reports by an out-of-state trust company that operates branch trust offices or representative trust offices pursuant to the Interstate Trust Company Office Act. Any such reporting requirements shall be consistent with the reporting requirements applicable to Nebraska trust companies and appropriate for the purpose of enabling the director to carry out his or her responsibilities under the act.</para><para>(3) The director may enter into cooperative, coordinating, and information-sharing agreements with any other trust company supervisory agency that has concurrent jurisdiction over a Nebraska state-chartered trust company or an out-of-state state trust company operating a branch trust office or representative trust office in this state to engage the services of such supervisory agency's examiners or to provide the services of department examiners to such supervisory agency.</para><para>(4) The director may enter into joint examinations or joint enforcement actions with other trust company supervisory agencies having concurrent jurisdiction over any branch trust office or representative trust office of an out-of-state state trust company or any branch trust office or representative trust office of a Nebraska state-chartered trust company in any host state. The director may, at any time, take such actions independently if he or she deems such actions to be necessary or appropriate to carry out his or her responsibilities under the act or to ensure compliance with Nebraska law. In the case of an out-of-state state trust company, the director shall recognize the exclusive jurisdiction of the home state regulator over corporate government matters and the primary responsibility of the home state regulator with respect to safety and soundness matters.</para><para>(5) The cost of any examination conducted under this section shall be assessed against the out-of-state state trust company in the manner set forth in sections 8-605 and 8-606 and paid for by the out-of-state state trust company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 18.</para></source></law></legaldoc>