<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="8-2742"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2742</statuteno><catchline>Authorized delegate; suspension or
revocation of designation; grounds; director; powers and duties; hearing;
final order; application to modify or rescind.</catchline><para>(1) The director may, following a hearing
in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, issue an order suspending
or revoking the designation of an authorized delegate if the director finds
that:</para>
<para>(a) The authorized delegate
violated the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act or a rule or regulation adopted
and promulgated or an order issued under the act;</para><para>(b) The authorized delegate did
not cooperate with an examination or investigation by the director;</para>
<para>(c) The authorized delegate
engaged in fraud, intentional misrepresentation, or gross negligence;</para>
<para>(d) The authorized delegate
is convicted of a violation of a state or federal anti-money laundering statute;</para>
<para>(e) The competence, experience,
character, or general fitness of the authorized delegate or a controlling
person of the authorized delegate indicates that it is not in the public interest
to permit the authorized delegate to engage in money transmission services;
or</para><para>(f)
The authorized delegate is engaged in an unsafe or unsound practice.</para>
<para>(2) In determining whether
an authorized delegate is engaging in an unsafe or unsound practice, the director
may consider the size and condition of the authorized delegate's money transmission,
the magnitude of the loss, if any, the gravity of the violation of the act,
and the previous conduct of the authorized delegate.</para><para>(3) Any authorized delegate to whom
a final order is issued under this section may apply to the director to modify
or rescind the order. The director shall not grant the application unless
the director finds that (a) it is in the public interest to do so and (b)
it is reasonable to believe that the person will comply with the act and any
rule, regulation, or order issued under the act if and when that person is
permitted to resume being an authorized delegate of a licensee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 42.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>