<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2708"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2708</statuteno><catchline>Multistate supervisory process; authority to participate.</catchline><para>(1) The director is authorized to participate in multistate supervisory processes established between states and coordinated through the Conference of State Bank Supervisors and Money Transmitter Regulators Association and any affiliates and successors thereof for all licensees that hold licenses in this state and other states. As a participant in multistate supervision, the director may:</para><para>(a) Cooperate, coordinate, and share information with other state and federal regulators in accordance with section 8-2706;</para><para>(b) Enter into written cooperation, coordination, or information-sharing contracts or agreements with organizations, the membership of which is made up of state or federal governmental agencies; and</para><para>(c) Cooperate, coordinate, and share information with organizations, the membership of which is made up of state or federal governmental agencies, provided that the organizations agree in writing to maintain the confidentiality and security of the shared information in accordance with section 8-2706.</para><para>(2) Nothing in this section constitutes a waiver of the director's authority to conduct an examination or investigation or otherwise take independent action authorized by the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act or a rule or regulation adopted and promulgated or an order issued under the act to enforce compliance with applicable state or federal law.</para><para>(3) A joint examination or investigation, or acceptance of an examination or investigation report, does not waive an examination assessment provided for in the Nebraska Money Transmitters Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB474, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>