<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks And Banking" statutenumber="8-2727"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>8-2727</statuteno><catchline>Refunds.</catchline><para>(1) This section does not apply to:</para><para>(a) Money received for transmission subject to the federal remittance rule; or</para><para>(b) Money received for transmission pursuant to a written agreement between the licensee and payee to process payments for goods or services provided by the payee.</para><para>(2) Every licensee shall refund to the sender within ten days after receipt of the sender's written request for a refund of any and all money received for transmission unless any of the following occurs:</para><para>(a) The money has been forwarded within ten days after the date on which the money was received for transmission;</para><para>(b) Instructions have been given committing an equivalent amount of money to the person designated by the sender within ten days after the date on which the money was received for transmission;</para><para>(c) The agreement between the licensee and the sender instructs the licensee to forward the money at a time that is beyond ten days after the date on which the money was received for transmission. If funds have not yet been forwarded in accordance with the terms of the agreement between the licensee and the sender, the licensee shall issue a refund in accordance with the other provisions of this section;</para><para>(d) The refund is requested for a transaction that the licensee has not completed based on a reasonable belief or a reasonable basis to believe that a crime or violation of law, rule, or regulation has occurred, is occurring, or may occur; or</para><para>(e) The refund request does not enable the licensee to:</para><para>(i) Identify the sender's name and address or telephone number; or</para><para>(ii) Identify the particular transaction to be refunded in the event the sender has multiple transactions outstanding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB616, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB186, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB474, &#167; 32. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>