
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id886"><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-3023"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-3023</statuteno><catchline>Reports; director; powers; examination by department; when; assessments and costs; insurance or bond required.</catchline><para>(1) The director may call for reports verified under oath from a digital asset depository at any time as necessary to inform the director of the condition of the digital asset depository. Such reports shall be available to the public.</para><para>(2) All reports required of a digital asset depository by the director and all materials relating to examinations of a digital asset depository shall be subject to the provisions of sections 8-103 and 8-108.</para><para>(3) Every digital asset depository is subject to examination by the department to determine the condition and resources of a digital asset depository, the mode of managing digital asset depository affairs and conducting business, the actions of officers and directors in the investment and disposition of funds, the safety and prudence of digital asset depository management, compliance with the requirements of the Nebraska Financial Innovation Act, and such other matters as the director may require.</para><para>(4) A digital asset depository shall pay an assessment in a sum to be determined by the director in accordance with section 8-601 and approved by the Governor and the costs of any examination or investigation as provided in sections 8-108 and 8-606.</para><para>(5) A digital asset depository shall maintain appropriate insurance or a bond covering the operational risks of the digital asset depository, which shall include coverage for directors' and officers' liability, errors and omissions liability, and information technology infrastructure and activities liability as determined by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 23. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>