
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id71"><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-3028"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-3028</statuteno><catchline>Voluntary dissolution; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A digital asset depository may voluntarily dissolve in accordance with this section. Voluntary dissolution shall be accomplished by either liquidating the digital asset depository or reorganizing the digital asset depository into an appropriate business entity that does not engage in any activity authorized only for a digital asset depository. Upon complete liquidation or completion of the reorganization, the director shall revoke the charter or authority of the digital asset depository. Thereafter, the corporation or business entity shall not use the words digital asset depository or digital asset bank in its business name or in connection with its ongoing business.</para><para>(2) A digital asset depository institution may dissolve its charter either by liquidation or reorganization. The board of directors shall file an application for dissolution with the director, accompanied by a filing fee established by an order or the rules and regulations of the director. The application shall include a comprehensive plan for dissolution setting forth the proposed disposition of all assets and liabilities in reasonable detail to effect a liquidation or reorganization, and any other plans required by the director. The plan of dissolution shall provide for the discharge or assumption of all of the known and unknown claims and liabilities of the digital asset depository institution. Additionally, the application for dissolution shall include other evidence, certifications, affidavits, documents, or information as the director may require, including demonstration of how assets and liabilities will be disposed, the timetable for effecting disposition of the assets and liabilities, and a proposal of the digital asset depository institution for addressing any claims that are asserted after dissolution has been completed. The director shall examine the application for compliance with this section, the business entity laws applicable to the required type of dissolution, and applicable orders and rules and regulations. The director may conduct a special examination of the digital asset depository institution, consistent with subsection (3) of section 8-3023, for purposes of evaluating the application.</para><para>(3) If the director finds that the application is incomplete, the director shall return it for completion not later than sixty days after it is filed. If the application is found to be complete by the director, the director shall approve or disapprove the application not later than thirty days after it is filed. If the director approves the application, the digital asset depository institution may proceed with the dissolution pursuant to the plan outlined in the application, subject to any further conditions the director may prescribe. If the digital asset depository institution subsequently determines that the plan of dissolution needs to be amended to complete the dissolution, it shall file an amended plan with the director and obtain approval to proceed under the amended plan. If the director does not approve the application or amended plan, the digital asset depository institution may appeal the decision to the director pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(4) Upon completion of all actions required under the plan of dissolution and satisfaction of all conditions prescribed by the director, the digital asset depository institution shall submit a written report of its actions to the director. The report shall contain a certification made under oath that the report is true and correct. Following receipt of the report, the director, no later than sixty days after the filing of the report, shall examine the digital asset depository institution to determine whether the director is satisfied that all required actions have been taken in accordance with the plan of dissolution and any conditions prescribed by the director. If all requirements and conditions have been met, the director shall, within thirty days of the examination, notify the digital asset depository institution in writing that the dissolution has been completed and issue an order of dissolution.</para><para>(5) Upon receiving an order of dissolution, the digital asset depository institution shall surrender its charter to the director. The digital asset depository institution shall then file articles of dissolution and other documents required by sections 21-2,184 to 21-2,201 for a corporation with the Secretary of State. In the case of reorganization, the digital asset depository institution shall file the documents required by the Secretary of State to finalize the reorganization.</para><para>(6) If the director determines that all required actions under the plan for dissolution, or as otherwise required by the director, have not been completed, the director shall notify the digital asset depository institution, not later than thirty days after this determination, in writing, of what additional actions shall be taken in order for the institution to be eligible for a certificate of dissolution. The director shall establish a reasonable deadline of up to thirty days for the submission of evidence that additional actions have been taken and the director may extend any deadline upon good cause. If the digital asset depository institution fails to file a supplemental report showing that the additional actions have been taken before the deadline, or submits a report that is found not to be satisfactory by the director, the director shall notify the digital asset depository institution in writing that its voluntary dissolution is not approved, and the institution may appeal the decision to the director pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 28. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>