<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-3002"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>8-3002</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings and declarations.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds and declares that:</para><para>(1) Economic development initiatives demand buy-in and input from community stakeholders across multiple industries. The Legislature should send a strong message that Nebraska wants to bring high-tech jobs and digital asset operations to our state. Nebraska has an incredible opportunity to be a leader in this emerging technology;</para><para>(2) Nebraska desires to create an entrepreneurial ecosystem where young talent can be paired with private investors in order to create jobs, enhance our quality of life, and prevent the brain drain that is particularly acute in rural Nebraska. If Nebraska does not make intentional and meaningful changes to how it recruits and retains young people, Nebraska will be left behind;</para><para>(3) The rapid innovation of blockchain and digital ledger technology, including the growing use of virtual currency, digital assets, and other controllable electronic records has complicated the development of blockchain services and products in the marketplace;</para><para>(4) Blockchain innovators are able and willing to address banking compliance challenges such as federal customer identification, anti-money laundering, and beneficial ownership requirements to comply with regulators' concerns;</para><para>(5) Compliance with federal and state laws, including, but not limited to, know-your-customer and anti-money-laundering rules and the federal Bank Secrecy Act, is critical to ensuring the future growth and reputation of the blockchain and technology industries as a whole; and</para><para>(6) Authorizing digital asset depositories in Nebraska will provide a necessary and valuable service to blockchain innovators and customers, emphasize Nebraska's partnership with the technology and financial industries, safely grow this state's ever-evolving financial sector, and afford more opportunities for Nebraska residents.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>