<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id640"><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-3007"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>8-3007</statuteno><catchline>Customers; criteria.</catchline><para>(1) No customer shall open or maintain an account with a digital asset depository or otherwise receive any services from the digital asset depository unless the customer meets the criteria of this subsection. A customer shall:</para><para>(a) Make sufficient evidence available to the digital asset depository to enable compliance with anti-money laundering, customer identification, and beneficial ownership requirements, as determined by the federal Bank Secrecy Act guidance and the policies and practices of the institution; and</para><para>(b) If the customer is a legal entity other than a natural person:</para><para>(i) Be in good standing with the jurisdiction in the United States in which it is incorporated or organized; and</para><para>(ii) Be engaged in a business that is lawful and bona fide in Nebraska, in the host state, if applicable, and under federal law consistent with subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) A customer which meets the criteria of subsection (1) of this section may be issued a digital asset depository account and otherwise receive services from the digital asset depository, contingent on the availability of sufficient insurance under subsection (5) of section 8-3023.</para><para>(3) Consistent with subdivisions (1)(a)(iv) and (v) of section 8-3005, and in addition to any requirements specified by federal law, a digital asset depository shall require that any potential customer that is a legal entity other than a natural person provide reasonable evidence that the entity is engaged in a business that is lawful and bona fide in Nebraska, in the host state, and under federal law or is likely to open a lawful, bona fide business within a federal Bank Secrecy Act compliant time frame, as the act existed on January 1, 2021. For purposes of this subsection, reasonable evidence includes business entity filings, articles of incorporation or organization, bylaws, operating agreements, business plans, promotional materials, financing agreements, or other evidence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>