
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id94"><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-3012"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>8-3012</statuteno><catchline>Digital asset depository institution; formation; articles of incorporation; contents; filing; capital requirements; bank holding company; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided by subsection (5) of this section, five or more adult persons, including at least one Nebraska resident, may form a digital asset depository institution. The incorporators shall subscribe the articles of incorporation and transmit them to the director as part of an application for a charter under section 8-3015.</para><para>(2) The articles of incorporation shall include the following information:</para><para>(a) The corporate name;</para><para>(b) The object for which the corporation is organized;</para><para>(c) The term of its existence, which may be perpetual;</para><para>(d) The place in Nebraska where its main office shall be physically located and its operations conducted;</para><para>(e) The amount of capital stock and the number of shares;</para><para>(f) The name and residence of each shareholder subscribing to more than ten percent of the stock and the number of shares owned by that shareholder;</para><para>(g) The number of directors and the names of those who shall manage the affairs of the corporation for the first year; and</para><para>(h) A statement that the articles of incorporation are made to enable the incorporators to avail themselves of the advantages of the laws of the state.</para><para>(3) Copies of all amended articles of incorporation shall be filed in the same manner as the original articles of incorporation.</para><para>(4) The incorporators shall solicit capital prior to filing an application for a charter with the director, consistent with section 8-3013. In the event an application for a charter is not filed or is denied by the director, all capital shall be promptly returned without loss.</para><para>(5) Subject to federal and state law, a bank holding company may apply to hold a digital asset depository.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>