<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id437"><amendatorysection chaptername="Banks and Banking" statutenumber="8-3202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>8-3202</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>In the Uniform Special Deposits Act:</para><para>(1) Account agreement means an agreement that:</para><para>(A) is in a record between a financial institution and one or more depositors;</para><para>(B) may have one or more beneficiaries as additional parties; and</para><para>(C) states the intention of the parties to establish a special deposit governed by the act.</para><para>(2) Financial institution means a bank, savings bank, building and loan association, savings and loan association, or credit union, whether chartered by the United States, the Department of Banking and Finance, or a foreign state agency; any other similar organization which is covered by federal deposit insurance; a trust company; or a digital asset depository that is not a digital asset depository institution.</para><para>(3) Beneficiary means a person that:</para><para>(A) is identified as a beneficiary in an account agreement; or</para><para>(B) if not identified as a beneficiary in an account agreement, may be entitled to payment from a special deposit:</para><para>(i) under the account agreement; or</para><para>(ii) on termination of the special deposit.</para><para>(4) Contingency means an event or circumstance stated in an account agreement that is not certain to occur but must occur before the financial institution is obligated to pay a beneficiary.</para><para>(5) Creditor process means attachment, garnishment, levy, notice of lien, sequestration, or similar process issued by or on behalf of a creditor or other claimant.</para><para>(6) Depositor means a person that establishes or funds a special deposit.</para><para>(7) Good faith means honesty in fact and observance of reasonable commercial standards of fair dealing.</para><para>(8) Knowledge of a fact means:</para><para>(A) with respect to a beneficiary, actual knowledge of the fact; or</para><para>(B) with respect to a financial institution holding a special deposit:</para><para>(i) if the financial institution:</para><para>(I) has established a reasonable routine for communicating material information to an individual to whom the financial institution has assigned responsibility for the special deposit; and</para><para>(II) maintains reasonable compliance with the routine, actual knowledge of the fact by that individual; or</para><para>(ii) if the financial institution has not established and maintained reasonable compliance with a routine described in clause (i) or otherwise exercised due diligence, implied knowledge of the fact that would have come to the attention of an individual to whom the financial institution has assigned responsibility for the special deposit.</para><para>(9) Obligated to pay a beneficiary means a beneficiary is entitled under the account agreement to receive from the financial institution a payment when:</para><para>(A) a contingency has occurred; and</para><para>(B) the financial institution has knowledge the contingency has occurred. Obligation to pay a beneficiary has a corresponding meaning.</para><para>(10) Permissible purpose means a governmental, regulatory, commercial, charitable, or testamentary objective of the parties stated in an account agreement. The term includes an objective to:</para><para>(A) hold funds:</para><para>(i) in escrow, including for a purchase and sale, lease, buyback, or other transaction;</para><para>(ii) as a security deposit of a tenant;</para><para>(iii) that may be distributed to a person as remuneration, retirement or other benefit, or compensation under a judgment, consent decree, court order, or other decision of a tribunal; or</para><para>(iv) for distribution to a defined class of persons after identification of the class members and their interest in the funds;</para><para>(B) provide assurance with respect to an obligation created by contract, such as earnest money to ensure a transaction closes;</para><para>(C) settle an obligation that arises in the operation of a payment system, securities settlement system, or other financial market infrastructure;</para><para>(D) provide assurance with respect to an obligation that arises in the operation of a payment system, securities settlement system, or other financial market infrastructure; or</para><para>(E) hold margin, other cash collateral, or funds that support the orderly functioning of financial market infrastructure or the performance of an obligation with respect to the infrastructure.</para><para>(11) Person means an individual, estate, business or nonprofit entity, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or other legal entity. The term includes a protected series, however denominated, of an entity if the protected series is established under law that limits, or limits if conditions specified under law are satisfied, the ability of a creditor of the entity or of any other protected series of the entity to satisfy a claim from assets of the protected series.</para><para>(12) Record means information:</para><para>(A) inscribed on a tangible medium; or</para><para>(B) stored in an electronic or other medium and retrievable in perceivable form.</para><para>(13) Special deposit means a deposit that satisfies section 8-3205.</para><para>(14) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any other territory or possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States. The term includes an agency or instrumentality of the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB231, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>