<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-102</statuteno><catchline>Portion under joint control of trustees and Department of Health and Human Services.</catchline><para>The trustees shall subdivide, set apart and dedicate that portion of said cemetery located at Lincoln which has heretofore been used for the burial of the dead from the various state institutions and which is legally described as follows, to wit: Beginning at a point 749 feet North and 392 feet East of the S.W. corner of the E 1/2 of the SE 1/4 of Section 19, T. 10, N.R. 7, E. 6th P.M. which is 46 1/2 feet North of the S.W. corner of lot 2911 in burial Section No. 9 in Wyuka Cemetery, thence North 75 feet to the N.W. corner of the Home for the Friendless Plot, according to the original plat of said cemetery, thence on a curve through an arc of 58 degrees 25&#8242; having a radius of 128 feet, the center of which is 183 feet North and 60 feet East of the place of beginning, to a point 77 feet North and 126 feet East of the place of beginning, and thence on a curve through an arc of 81 degrees 06&#8242; having a radius of 100 feet the center of which is 17 feet South and 163 feet East of the place of beginning, to a point at the East end of the Home for the Friendless Plot aforesaid, which is 37 1/2 feet North and 250 feet East of the place of beginning; thence on a curve through an arc of 81 degrees 06&#8242; having a radius of 100 feet the center of which is 88 feet North and 165 feet East of the place of beginning to a point 3 feet South and 125 feet East, of the place of beginning; thence on a curve through an arc of 58 degrees 25&#8242; having a radius of 128 feet the center of which is 107 feet South and 57 feet East of the place of beginning, to the place of beginning, containing 15,835 square feet, or 0.36 acres, situated in Lancaster County, Nebraska. The part so set aside and dedicated shall be under the joint control of the trustees of Wyuka Cemetery and the Department of Health and Human Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 197, &#167; 2, p. 561; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 13-102; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 12-102; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 46.</para></source></law></legaldoc>