<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-530"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-530</statuteno><catchline>Transfer of cemetery to city or village; powers and duties; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The mayor and council of a city or the board of trustees of a village may accept ownership of a cemetery from a cemetery association formed under the provisions of sections 12-501 to 12-529 or 17-944 to 17-947 and may manage and operate the cemetery as a municipal cemetery.</para><para>(2) Upon the transfer of the cemetery from the cemetery association to the city or village, the following shall occur:</para><para>(a) All property and money under the control of the cemetery association shall vest in the city or village, and all money in the control of the cemetery association shall be turned over to the city or village;</para><para>(b) The deeds to all burial lots and other property of the cemetery association shall be transferred to the city or village. If any real estate of the cemetery association was acquired by gift or devise, the city or village shall take title subject to the conditions imposed by the donor. Upon acceptance by the city or village, the conditions shall be binding on such city or village;</para><para>(c) Any funds or any money credited to the cemetery association's perpetual care fund created under section 12-509 shall be transferred by the cemetery association to the city or village and placed in a new or existing fund dedicated to the general care, management, maintenance, improvement, beautification, and welfare of the cemetery; and</para><para>(d) All endowments received by the cemetery association under section 12-301 shall vest absolutely in the city or village to whom the control and management of such cemetery has been transferred. The city or village shall use any such endowment for the exclusive benefits and purposes designated by the endower.</para><para>(3) After the transfer of the cemetery from the cemetery association to the city or village is complete, the cemetery association shall be deemed to be disbanded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 355, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>