<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id24">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cemeteries" id="id26" statutenumber="12-502"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>12-502</statuteno><catchline id="id29">Formation; record
of proceedings; certification; effect; certified transcript as evidence; duty
of county clerk; fees.</catchline><para>The clerk of the cemetery association shall make out a true
record of the proceedings of the meeting provided for by section 12-501 and certify and deliver
the same to the clerk of the county in which such meeting is held,
together with the name by which such association shall be known. The county clerk, immediately upon the receipt of such certified statement, shall record the same in a book provided by the county clerk for that purpose at the
expense of the county and shall be entitled
to the same fees for the services as the county clerk is entitled to demand for other
similar services. After the making
of such record by the county clerk, the trustees and the associated
members and successors shall
be invested with the powers, privileges, and
immunities incident to aggregate corporations. A certified transcript of the record made by the county
clerk shall be
deemed and taken in all courts and places whatsoever within this state as
prima facie evidence of the existence of such cemetery association.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 25, &#167; 46, p. 205; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 680; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 589; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 13-502; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 12-502; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB863, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>This section contains directions as to the details of organization and recording of articles of association. Root v. Morning View Cemetery Assn., 174 Neb. 438, 118 N.W.2d 633 (1962).</para><para>As soon as the county clerk enters of record the true record of the meeting at which the association is organized and the first trustees are elected, the association is a corporation. State ex rel. Craig v. Offutt, 121 Neb. 76, 236 N.W. 174 (1931).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>