<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-506"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-506</statuteno><catchline>Real estate; power to acquire; exemption from taxation and legal process; revenue; disbursement.</catchline><para>Such association shall have the power to purchase or take by gift, devise, or by exercising the power of eminent domain, and to hold lands, not exceeding three hundred and sixty acres, and improvements thereon, exempt from taxation, execution, or from any appropriation of public purchasers, if the same are used exclusively for cemetery purposes and in nowise with a view to profit. After such land is paid for, all the future receipts and income of such association, whether from the sale of lots, from donations, or otherwise, shall be applied exclusively to laying out, protecting, preserving, and embellishing the cemetery and the avenues leading thereto, to the erection of such building or buildings, vault or vaults, chapel, crematory, mausoleum, and other structures as may be deemed necessary for the cemetery purposes, and to paying the necessary expenses of the association. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 25, &#167; 49, p. 206; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 181; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 39, &#167; 1, p. 275; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 176; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 683; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 12, &#167; 1, p. 71; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 592; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 138, &#167; 1, p. 365; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 13-505; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 18, &#167; 1, p. 103; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 13-505; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 12-506; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 33, p. 461.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not prohibit a devise of land to cemetery association in excess of three hundred sixty acres. Root v. Morning View Cemetery Assn., 174 Neb. 438, 118 N.W.2d 633 (1962).</para><para>Receipts from sale of lots are subject to the payment of any debt contracted for the purchase price of the cemetery property, and extends to money borrowed to take up purchase money notes. Townsend v. Beatrice Cemetery Assn., 188 F. 1 (8th Cir. 1911).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>