<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-522"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-522</statuteno><catchline>Grounds; abandonment; sale; notice of petition; contents; form.</catchline><para>Upon the filing of such petition, due notice of the same shall be given all the members of such association, and all other persons interested therein, and in the real estate or other property of such association, by causing a notice of the application to be published in some weekly newspaper printed and published and of general circulation in the county where the action is brought for three successive weeks, which notice shall be substantially in the following form: </para>
<para id="id00">
<table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1" align="center">
<colspec colname="col1" align="center" colwidth="3.0*"/>
<tbody>
<row valign="middle">
<entry align="center">LEGAL NOTICE</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>
<para>The members of the ................... Cemetery Association of ...................., Nebraska, and all other persons interested in the association and in the real estate or other property of the association, are hereby notified that on the ..... day of ........ 20...., the association, filed its petition in the district court of ............... County, Nebraska, the object and prayer of which is (here set forth in at least a general way the object sought and relief prayed for in the petition).</para><para>Any person desiring to oppose the granting of the relief sought by or the prayer of the petition is required to file an objection in writing with the clerk of the district court as required by law on or before Monday, the .... day of ............ 20.... . Dated ........., 20.... . </para>
<para>
<table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="4.00*"/>
<tbody>
<row rowsep="0" valign="middle">
<entry colsep="0" align="right">............ Cemetery Association of</entry></row>
<row rowsep="0" valign="middle">
<entry colsep="0" align="right">..............................., NE.</entry></row>
<row rowsep="0" valign="middle">
<entry colsep="0" align="right">Petitioner.</entry></row>
</tbody></tgroup></table></para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1907, c. 27, &#167; 2, p. 147; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 689; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 598; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 13-511; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 12-522; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 813, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>