<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-923"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-923</statuteno><catchline>Property; acquisition; tax; excess funds.</catchline><para>The board of trustees of each cemetery district organized under sections 12-909 to 12-923 shall annually include in its proposed budget statement the amount of money deemed necessary in order for such district to acquire adequate cemetery land. After the adoption of the district's budget statement, the president and secretary shall certify the amount to be received from taxation for such purpose, according to the adopted budget statement, to the proper county clerk or county clerks and the proper county board or boards which may levy the required tax subject to section 77-3443. The tax so levied for the acquisition of cemetery land in the district shall not exceed the amount so certified in the adopted budget statement nor exceed one and seven-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all taxable property in such district. The tax levied pursuant to this section shall be in addition to the tax levy authorized by section 12-914. Such tax shall be collected as other taxes are collected in the county by the county treasurer. The proceeds of the tax so levied and collected shall constitute a special fund for the acquisition of cemetery land in the district, shall be placed to the credit of the cemetery district so authorizing such levy, and shall be paid to the treasurer of the cemetery district upon warrants drawn upon the fund by the board of trustees of the district. The county treasurer shall keep such fund separate and apart from other county funds. In case the amount of money produced by such tax levies exceeds the amount expended or the amount necessary to insure availability of cemetery land, such excess shall be placed into the county general fund. For purposes of section 77-3443, the county board of each county in which the district is situated shall approve the budget.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 715, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 24.</para></source></law></legaldoc>