<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id14">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cemeteries" id="id16" statutenumber="12-501"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>12-501</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Formation; trustees;
election; notice; clerk; right to establish cemetery limited.</catchline>
<para>(1) For purposes
of sections 12-501 to 12-532, cemetery association means an association formed
under such sections.</para><para>(2) Every cemetery, other than those owned, operated, and maintained by the state, by towns, villages, and cities, by churches, by public charitable corporations, by cemetery districts, and
by fraternal and benevolent societies, shall be owned, conducted, and managed by cemetery
associations organized and incorporated as provided in sections 12-501 to 12-532 except as
specifically provided in sections 12-530 and 12-812.</para>
<para>(3) The establishment of a
cemetery by any agency other than those enumerated in
this section shall constitute a nuisance, and its operation may
be enjoined at the suit of any taxpayer in the state.</para>
<para>(4) It shall be lawful for
any number of persons, not less than five, who are residents of the county
in which they desire to form themselves into an association, to form themselves
into a cemetery association and
to elect any number of their members, not less than three, to serve as trustees,
and one member as clerk, who shall continue in office during the pleasure
of the association. All such elections
shall take place at a meeting of four or more members of such association
by a majority vote of those present.
A notice for such meeting
shall be published in a local newspaper,
or posted in three places within the precinct or township in which the cemetery is or will be located,
at least fifteen days prior to the meeting.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 25, &#167; 45, p. 205; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 274; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 679; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 588; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 13-501; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 121; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 13-501; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 12-501; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB863, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>Under Nebraska's cemetery association laws, it is apparent that there is a public nature to certain of the statutory authority given cemetery associations with regard to cemetery property. Sjuts v. Granville Cemetery Assn., 272 Neb. 103, 719 N.W.2d 236 (2006).</para><para>This section contains the provisions under which cemetery association is established. Root v. Morning View Cemetery Assn., 174 Neb. 438, 118 N.W.2d 633 (1962).</para><para>Presumption of continued existence arises after proper organization. Tetschner v. Cram, 157 Neb. 734, 61 N.W.2d 378 (1953).</para><para>Amendment to bylaws of association organized under this article (sections 12-501 to 12-529), made without any notice whatever to members, is void, where bylaws required notice, but did not prescribe the manner thereof. State ex rel. Craig v. Offutt, 121 Neb. 76, 236 N.W. 174 (1931).</para><para>Property involved belonged to a private corporation organized under this section. Greenwood Cemetery v. City of Wayne, 110 Neb. 300, 193 N.W. 734 (1923).</para><para>Receiver denied for corporation organized under this article. Youngers v. Exeter Cemetery Assn., 85 Neb. 314, 123 N.W. 95 (1909).</para><para>Corporations organized under this article are private corporations. Pokrok Zapadu Publishing Co. v. Zizkovsky, 42 Neb. 64, 60 N.W. 358 (1894).</para><para>This article divests cities of control of cemeteries. State ex rel. Wyuka Cemetery Assn. v. Bartling, 23 Neb. 421, 36 N.W. 811 (1888).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>