<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-104</statuteno><catchline>Soldiers burial grounds; selection; acquisition; use.</catchline><para>A piece or parcel of land not exceeding in extent one acre not otherwise used or appropriated, in such place and in such form as shall be selected and agreed upon between the trustees of Wyuka Cemetery and a committee to be selected by the Grand Army of the Republic of Lincoln, Nebraska, is hereby appropriated and dedicated to the use and for the purpose of a soldiers burial ground. Such ground shall be selected in the manner described in this section, out of the South Half of the East Half of the Southeast Quarter of Section Nineteen, Township Ten, Range Seven East of the Sixth P.M., otherwise known as Wyuka Cemetery, and such plot of ground shall be used for the burial of all discharged or separated soldiers, sailors, marines, and army nurses, as they or their friends shall desire to bury therein, together with such members of their immediate families as the committee from the Grand Army of the Republic shall direct. The trustees of Wyuka Cemetery may appropriate and dedicate for the use and purpose of soldiers burial grounds such other pieces or parcels of ground in Wyuka Cemetery, acquired by the cemetery, as may in the opinion of such trustees be proper and sufficient. Such pieces or parcels of ground so appropriated and dedicated shall be used for the burial of all discharged or separated soldiers, sailors, marines, and army nurses who served in the army or navy of the United States in any war, together with such members of their immediate families as shall be selected by William Lewis Camp of Lincoln, Nebraska, of the United Spanish War Veterans, by Lincoln Post No. 3 of the Department of Nebraska of the American Legion, or by the Lincoln, Nebraska, camp, post, or other local body of any other national organization of war veterans, to be designated by the trustees of Wyuka Cemetery, which admits all discharged or separated soldiers, sailors, marines, and nurses who served in any war of the United States without limitation as to the branch, time, or place of service, or the sex, color, nativity, or religion of the member.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 197, &#167; 4, p. 562; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 13-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 12-104; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 54, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Veterans' cemetery system authorized,</emphasis> see section 12-1301.</para></crossreference> </law></legaldoc>