<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1115</statuteno><catchline>Pre-need sales agent; license required; fee; failure to surrender license; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No agent shall make any pre-need sales on behalf of a pre-need seller in this state without first obtaining a license from the director. The director shall not issue such a license without requiring the proposed agent to fill out an application form stating his or her name, address, and telephone number and the pre-need seller for whom he or she will be making pre-need sales. The pre-need seller for whom the agent will be making pre-need sales shall also sign the agent's application and agree to be responsible for supervising the agent in conjunction with any pre-need sales. The fee for an agent's license shall be twenty dollars which shall accompany the application.</para><para>(2) The agent's license, when issued, shall allow the agent to make pre-need sales only for the pre-need seller whose name appears on the license. If the agency relationship between the pre-need seller and the agent terminates for any reason, the pre-need seller shall immediately notify the department of such termination. Once such notification has been received, the acts of the agent shall no longer be imputed to the pre-need seller and the agent's license shall be considered as void. The agent, upon written request by the department, shall surrender to the department the license within a period of ten days after the receipt of such written notice. Failure on the part of the agent to surrender the license after written notification shall be a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) It shall be the responsibility of the licensed agent to notify the director of any change of the agent's address.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 643, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>