<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1108</statuteno><catchline>Pre-need seller; license required; application; requirements; fee; renewal; records.</catchline><para>(1) No pre-need seller shall make or offer to make a pre-need sale without first obtaining a license from the director. An application for such a license or a renewal of an existing license shall be made in writing, signed by the proposed pre-need seller, duly verified on forms prepared and furnished by the director, and accompanied by an application fee of one hundred dollars. Each application shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) The applicant's full name and his, her, or its home and business address, and if the applicant is a partnership, limited liability company, corporation, or association, the application shall list the names and addresses of all of the officers, directors, members, or trustees thereof;</para><para>(b) The names and addresses of all agents, including employees and independent contractors, authorized to make pre-need sales in the name of the applicant;</para><para>(c) If the applicant is an individual, the applicant's social security number;</para><para>(d) Whether such agents are presently licensed as agents pursuant to section 12-1115 and if not the date upon which application will be made;</para><para>(e) Whether the pre-need seller's license has previously been suspended, revoked, or voluntarily surrendered and the reason therefor; and</para><para>(f) Whether the applicant or any officers, directors, members, or association trustees have been convicted of fraud or a crime involving misappropriation or misuse of funds within the past ten years.</para><para>(2) Upon receipt of the application, the director shall issue a license to the pre-need seller unless the director determines that the applicant (a) is unable to demonstrate its financial ability to meet the requirements of the Burial Pre-Need Sale Act, (b) has made false statements or misrepresentations in the application, (c) is not duly authorized to transact business in the state, (d) has been convicted of fraud or a crime involving misappropriation or misuse of funds within the last ten years, or (e) has failed to comply with any of the terms or conditions of the Burial Pre-Need Sale Act and such is deemed by the director to substantially impede the applicant's ability to abide by such act. If the director determines that an unrestricted license will not be issued or that no license will be issued on the basis of the application, the director may:</para><para>(i) Request additional information from the applicant;</para><para>(ii) Issue a temporary license with restrictions and reporting requirements as the director deems necessary so as to monitor the actions of the applicant for a period not to exceed six months; or</para><para>(iii) Refuse to issue the license.</para><para>The director shall notify the applicant of the action taken, and the notification and any protest shall be made in the same manner as provided in subsection (2) of section 12-1116.</para><para>(3) A license shall expire five years from the date of the issuance and may be renewed for additional five-year periods upon filing with the director a new application for such license.</para><para>(4) The licensee shall maintain accurate accounts, books, and records of all transactions required including copies of all contracts involving pre-need sales and shall make a report as prescribed in section 12-1110.</para><para>(5)(a) The licensee shall make all books and records pertaining to trust funds available to the director for examination. The director, or a qualified person designated by the director, may during ordinary business hours examine the books, records, and accounts of the licensee with respect to the funds received by such licensee and may require the attendance at an examination under oath of all persons whose testimony he or she may deem necessary.</para><para>(b) The reasonable expenses for the examination of the books, records, and accounts of the licensee shall be fixed and determined by the director. The licensee shall be responsible for the payment of the determined expenses to the director within a reasonable time after the receipt of a statement for such expenses. The expenses shall be limited to a reasonable allocation for the salary of each examiner plus actual expenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 643, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 127; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>