<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1105</statuteno><catchline>Pre-need seller; records required.</catchline><para>Upon the making of a pre-need sale by a pre-need seller when some or all of the proceeds from that sale are required to be placed in trust or a letter of credit or surety bond has been approved in lieu thereof, the pre-need seller in addition to retaining a copy of any written agreement entered into shall prepare and maintain a separate record of each such pre-need sale and the record shall contain the following information:</para><para>(1) The name and address of the pre-need purchaser;</para><para>(2) The retail sales price of each item purchased in such pre-need sale, exclusive of any interest that may be charged the pre-need purchaser by the pre-need seller;</para><para>(3) The date and amount of each payment made by the pre-need purchaser to the pre-need seller, designating such payment as principal or interest and the disposition made by the pre-need seller of each such payment as to whether it was retained in whole or in part by the pre-need seller or deposited in trust and, if deposited in trust, the date of such deposit and the name of the trustee with whom the deposit was made; and</para><para>(4) The date of withdrawal and all amounts withdrawn by the pre-need seller pursuant to subsection (2) of section 12-1113 and a designation of the event which permitted such withdrawal.</para><para>The record shall be maintained for inspection purposes by the director for at least one year after the pre-need seller has received all proceeds to which the seller is entitled by reason of the pre-need sale.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 643, &#167; 5.</para></source></law></legaldoc>