<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1116</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; disciplinary actions; grounds;
notice; administrative fine.</catchline><para>(1) The director may deny, revoke,
or suspend any license of any pre-need seller or agent or may levy an administrative
fine in accordance with subsection (3) of this section if the director finds
that:</para>
<para>(a) The licensee has failed to pay the license fee prescribed for such
license;</para>
<para>(b) The licensee, either knowingly or without the exercise of due care
to prevent the same, has violated any of the provisions of the Burial Pre-Need
Sale Act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the director
pursuant to such act;</para>
<para>(c) An act or condition exists which, if it had existed at the time
of the original application of such licensee, would have resulted in the director
refusing to issue such license;
or</para>
<para>(d) The licensee, upon
receipt of a written inquiry from the department, has failed to respond to
such inquiry or has failed to request an additional reasonable amount of time
to respond to such inquiry within fifteen business days after such receipt.</para>
<para>(2) Written notification shall be provided to the licensee upon the
director's making such determination, and the notice shall be mailed by the
director to the last address on file for the licensee by certified or registered
mail, return receipt requested. The notice shall state the specific action
contemplated by the director and the specific grounds for such action. The
notice shall allow the licensee receiving such notice twenty days from the
date of actual receipt to:</para>
<para>(a) Voluntarily surrender his or her license; or</para>
<para>(b) File a written notice of protest of the proposed action of the director.
If a written notice of protest is filed by the licensee, the Administrative
Procedure Act shall govern the hearing process and procedure, including all
appeals. Failure to file a notice of protest within the twenty-day period
shall be equivalent to a voluntary surrender of the licensee's license, and
the licensee shall surrender the license to the director.</para>
<para>(3) In addition to or in lieu of any applicable denial, suspension,
or revocation of a license, any person violating the Burial Pre-Need Sale
Act may, after notice and hearing, be subject to an administrative fine of
not more than one thousand dollars per violation. Such fine may be enforced
in the same manner as civil judgments. Any person charged with a violation
of the act may waive his or her right to a hearing and consent to such discipline
as the director determines is appropriate. The Administrative Procedure Act
shall govern all hearings held pursuant to the Burial Pre-Need Sale Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 643, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 93, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB192, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>