<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id85"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cemeteries" id="id87" statutenumber="12-1401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id89">12-1401</statuteno><catchline id="id90">Statewide Cemetery Registry; established and maintained.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska State Historical Society shall establish and maintain the Statewide Cemetery Registry. The registry shall be located in the office of the Nebraska State Historical Society and shall be made available to the public. The purpose of the registry is to provide a central data bank of accurate and current information regarding the location of cemeteries, burial grounds, mausoleums, and columbaria in the state.</para><para>(2)(a) Each city, village, township, county, church, fraternal and benevolent society, cemetery district, cemetery association, mausoleum association, and any other person owning, operating, or maintaining a cemetery, pioneer cemetery, abandoned or neglected cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium shall register with the Statewide Cemetery Registry.</para><para>(b) Except as provided in subdivision (c) of this subsection, the registration shall include the following:</para><para>(i) The location or address of the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium;</para><para>(ii) A plat of the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium grounds, including any lots, graves, niches, or crypts, if available;</para><para>(iii) The name and address of the person or persons representing the entity owning, operating, or maintaining the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium;</para><para>(iv) The inception date of the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium, if available; and</para><para>(v) If the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium is abandoned, the abandonment date, if available.</para><para>(c) The information required in subdivision (b) of this subsection regarding the operation and maintenance of a cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium prior to January 1, 2006, shall be required only if such information is reasonably available to the registering entity.</para><para>(d) The entity owning, operating, or maintaining the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium may include information regarding the history of the operation of the cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium.</para><para>(3) The entity owning, operating, or maintaining a registered cemetery, mausoleum, or columbarium shall update its entry in the registry every ten years following the initial registration by the entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 211, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB995, &#167;  10.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>