<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1114" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1114</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Pre-need seller; trust funds; retain cost-of-living amount.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) To offset increases in the cost of living as the same may affect the trust accounts, the pre-need seller shall compute each year the total amount of the trust principal of each trust account determined as of December 31 of the immediately preceding year, and then multiply such amount by the percentage increase in the National Consumer Price Index for such year. The amount so determined shall be the amount of the current year's income that is required to be retained in trust by the trustee. Such amount is then considered to be trust principal and shall be retained before any income may be distributed as provided in subsection (1) of section 12-1113.</para><para>(2) If there is insufficient income in any given year to fully fund the amount required to be retained pursuant to subsection (1) of this section:</para><para>(a) As much of the required amount as possible shall be retained;</para><para>(b) The shortage shall be recouped from the income in subsequent years before such income may be distributed as provided in subsection (1) of section 12-1113; and</para><para>(c) The calculation required under subsection (1) of this section for subsequent years shall be computed as though the full amount required to be retained for each year had been retained.</para><para id="id00">(3) If publication of the National Consumer Price Index is discontinued, the director shall select a comparable index for the purposes of determining such percentage increase in the cost of living and notify all licensed pre-need sellers of the index selected.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 643, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB239, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>