<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1205" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1205</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Person discovering remains or goods; duties; violation; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Any person who encounters or discovers human skeletal remains or burial goods associated with an unmarked human burial in or on the ground shall immediately cease any activity which may cause further disturbance of the unmarked human burial and shall within forty-eight hours report the presence and location of such remains or goods to a local law enforcement officer in the county in which the remains or goods are found. Any person who knowingly fails to make such a report shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para><para id="id00">(2) If human skeletal remains or burial goods associated with an unmarked human burial in or on the ground are discovered by any employee, contractor, or agent of the Department of Transportation in conjunction with highway construction, any construction in the area immediately adjacent to such remains or goods shall cease. The department or any of its employees, contractors, or agents shall within forty-eight hours of the discovery of the remains or goods report the presence and location of the remains or goods to a local law enforcement officer in the county in which the remains or goods are found. Any remains or goods may then be removed from the site following an examination by the appropriate agency in accordance with section 39-1363 and any applicable federal requirements. Following removal, the remains or goods shall be disposed of in accordance with the Unmarked Human Burial Sites and Skeletal Remains Protection Act. The construction project may continue once the remains or goods have been removed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 340, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 72. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>