<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cemeteries" statutenumber="12-1208"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>12-1208</statuteno><catchline>Discovery of remains or goods; society;
duties.</catchline><para>(1) Upon notification pursuant to section 12-1206,
the society shall promptly assist in examining the discovered material to
attempt to determine its origin and identity.</para>
<para>(2) If the society finds that the discovered human skeletal remains
or burial goods are of non-American-Indian origin with a known or unknown
identity, it shall notify the county attorney of the finding. Upon receipt
of the finding, the county attorney shall cause the remains and associated
burial goods to be interred in consultation with the county coroner. Reburial
shall be in accordance with the wishes and at the expense of any known persons in the order listed by section 30-2223 or, if no relatives are known, in an
appropriate cemetery at the expense of the county in which the remains were
discovered after a one-year scientific study period if such study period is
considered necessary or desirable by the society. In no case shall any human
skeletal remains that are reasonably identifiable as to familial or tribal
origin be displayed by any entity which receives funding or official recognition
from the state or any of its political subdivisions. In situations in which
human skeletal remains or burial goods that are unidentifiable as to familial
or tribal origin are clearly found to be of extremely important, irreplaceable,
and intrinsic scientific value, the remains or goods may be curated by the
society until the remains or goods may be reinterred as provided in this subsection
without impairing their scientific value.</para>
<para>(3) If the society finds that the discovered human skeletal remains
or burial goods are of American Indian origin, it shall promptly notify in
writing the Commission on Indian Affairs and any known persons in
the order listed in section 30-2223 or, if no relatives
are known, any Indian tribes reasonably identified as tribally linked to such
remains or goods in order to ascertain and follow the wishes of the relative
or Indian tribe, if any, as to reburial or other disposition. Reburial by
any such relative or Indian tribe shall be by and at the expense of such relative
or Indian tribe. In cases in which reasonably identifiable American Indian
human skeletal remains or burial goods are unclaimed by the appropriate relative
or Indian tribe, the society shall notify all other Indian tribes which can
reasonably be determined to have lived in Nebraska in order to ascertain and
follow the wishes of the tribe as to reburial or other disposition. Reburial
by any such tribe shall be by and at the expense of the tribe. If such remains
or goods are unclaimed by the appropriate tribe, the remains or goods shall
be reburied, as determined by the commission, by one of the four federally
recognized Indian tribes in Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 340, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 97, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1113; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB998, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>