<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-815"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-815</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Search warrant; executed and returned; inventory required.</catchline><para>(1) The warrant must be executed and returned within ten days after its date. The officer taking property under the warrant shall give to the person from whom or from whose premises the property was taken a copy of the warrant and a receipt for the property or shall leave the copy and the receipt at the place from which the property was taken. The return shall be made promptly and shall be accompanied by a written inventory of any property taken. The inventory shall be made in the presence of the applicant for the warrant and the person from whose possession or premises the property was taken if they are present, or in the presence of at least one credible witness other than the applicant for the warrant or the person from whose possession or premises the property was taken, and shall be verified by the officer. The judge or magistrate shall deliver a copy of the inventory upon request to the person from whom or from whose premises the property was taken and to the applicant for the warrant.</para><para>(2) The return and inventory required by subsection (1) of this section may be submitted to the magistrate or judge in person or by facsimile or other electronic means.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 161, &#167; 4, p. 572; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB294, &#167; 14. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Fees for service,</emphasis> see section 33-117.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Irrespective of compliance with a rule or statutory time limit within which a search must be executed, a delay in the execution of a warrant may be constitutionally impermissible under the Fourth Amendment. State v. Swift, 251 Neb. 204, 556 N.W.2d 243 (1996).</para><para>The execution of the warrant 6 days after its issuance does not require suppression of evidence obtained based on the warrant. State v. Moore, 2 Neb. App. 206, 508 N.W.2d 305 (1993).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>