<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-751"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-751</statuteno><catchline>Fugitives from this state; requisition; application; contents; filing.</catchline><para>(1) When the return to this state of a person charged with crime in this state is required, the prosecuting attorney shall present to the Governor a written application for a requisition for the return of the person charged in which application shall be stated the name of the person so charged, the crime charged against him or her, the approximate time, place, and circumstances of its commission, the state in which he or she is believed to be, including the location of the accused therein at the time the application is made and certifying that, in the opinion of the said prosecuting attorney the ends of justice require the arrest and return of the accused to this state for trial and that the proceeding is not instituted to enforce a private claim.</para><para>(2) When the return to this state is required of a person who has been convicted of a crime in this state and has escaped from confinement or broken the terms of his or her bail, probation, or parole, the prosecuting attorney of the county in which the offense was committed, the parole board, or, if the escape was from an institution of the Department of Correctional Services, the Director of Correctional Services, or sheriff of the county from which escape was made, shall present to the Governor a written application for a requisition for the return of such person, in which application shall be stated the name of the person, the crime of which he or she was convicted, the circumstances of the escape from confinement or of the breach of the terms of bail, probation, or parole, the state in which he or she is believed to be, including the location of the person therein at the time application is made.</para><para>(3) The application shall be verified by affidavit, shall be executed in duplicate, and shall be accompanied by two certified copies of the indictment returned, or information and affidavit filed, or of the complaint made to the judge or magistrate, stating the offense with which the accused is charged, or of the judgment of conviction or of the sentence. The prosecuting officer, parole board, director, or sheriff may also attach such further affidavits and other documents in duplicate as he or she shall deem proper to be submitted with such application. One copy of the application, with the action of the Governor indicated by endorsement thereon, and one of the certified copies of the indictment, complaint, information, and affidavits, or of the judgment of conviction or of the sentence shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State to remain of record in that office. The other copies of all papers shall be forwarded with the Governor's requisition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 159, &#167; 23, p. 565; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 697, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>