<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-829"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-829</statuteno><catchline>Stop and search of person for dangerous weapon; when authorized; peace officer, defined.</catchline><para>A peace officer may stop any person in a public place whom he reasonably suspects of committing, who has committed, or who is about to commit a crime and may demand of him his name, address and an explanation of his actions. When a peace officer has stopped a person for questioning pursuant to this section and reasonably suspects he is in danger of life or limb, he may search such person for a dangerous weapon. If the peace officer finds such a weapon or any other thing the possession of which may constitute a crime, he may take and keep it until the completion of questioning, at which time he shall either return it, if lawfully possessed, or arrest such person. For purposes of this section, peace officer shall include credentialed conservation officers of the Game and Parks Commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 132, &#167; 1, p. 471.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Detention of person</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Search</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Detention of person</emphasis></para><para>Totality of circumstances provided sufficient justification for investigatory stop where defendant fit "profile" of burglary suspect and engaged in specific activities which aroused the suspicions of the police. State v. Van Ackeren, 242 Neb. 479, 495 N.W.2d 630 (1993).</para><para>For a detention pursuant to this section to be lawful and justifiable, the police officer must be able to point to specific and articulable facts which, taken together with rational inferences from those facts, reasonably warrant that intrusion. State v. Bridge, 234 Neb. 781, 452 N.W.2d 542 (1990).</para><para>A brief stop of a suspicious individual in order to determine his identity or to maintain the status quo momentarily while obtaining more information may be most reasonable in light of the facts known to the officer at the time. State v. DeJesus, 216 Neb. 907, 347 N.W.2d 111 (1984).</para><para>An investigative stop under this provision is justified by objective manifestation that the person is, has been, or is about to be engaged in criminal activity. To determine if the cause is sufficient to authorize a stop, the totality of the circumstances must be considered. State v. Ebberson, 209 Neb. 41, 305 N.W.2d 904 (1981).</para><para>Informal detention for investigation may be lawful although probable cause for formal arrest may not exist. State v. Von Suggs, 196 Neb. 757, 246 N.W.2d 206 (1976).</para><para>A peace officer may stop any person, whom he suspects, in a public place, and demand his name, address, and an explanation of his actions. State v. Brewer, 190 Neb. 667, 212 N.W.2d 90 (1973).</para><para>Peace officer may stop person in public place whom he reasonably suspects of committing, having committed, or is about to commit a crime and may demand his name, address, and an explanation of his actions. State v. McCune, 189 Neb. 165, 201 N.W.2d 852 (1972).</para><para>Detention and search without a warrant based on statements of informer and observations of the officers was proper. State v. Goings, 184 Neb. 81, 165 N.W.2d 366 (1969).</para><para>Peace officer may stop a person for questioning whom he reasonably suspects of having committed or is about to commit a crime. State v. Carpenter, 181 Neb. 639, 150 N.W.2d 129 (1967).</para><para>Informal detention is permissible in spite of lack of probable cause. State v. Hoffman, 181 Neb. 356, 148 N.W.2d 321 (1967).</para><para><emphasis>2. Search</emphasis></para><para>Where four officers were required to subdue defendant who ran from investigatory stop which was justified by reasonable articulable suspicion, it was also reasonable to pat defendant down for a weapon. State v. Van Ackeren, 242 Neb. 479, 495 N.W.2d 630 (1993).</para><para>During an investigatory stop, officers may search a suspect's vehicle in order to secure their safety or the safety of another if they have reasonable belief, based on articulable facts, that they or other persons are in danger. State v. Gross, 225 Neb. 798, 408 N.W.2d 297 (1987).</para><para>The search of the passenger compartment of an automobile, limited to those areas in which a weapon may be placed or hidden, is permissible if the police officer possesses a reasonable belief, based on specific and articulable facts, which reasonably warrants the officer to believe the suspect may gain immediate control of weapons. State v. Pierce and Wells, 215 Neb. 512, 340 N.W.2d 122 (1983).</para><para>Investigative stop and search of auto by police held unconstitutional where officer had no reasonable suspicion the occupants were committing, had committed, or were about to commit a crime. State v. Colgrove, 198 Neb. 319, 253 N.W.2d 20 (1977).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The officers' actions in parking their car behind the appellant's vehicle, approaching the appellant and a companion with guns holstered and identifying themselves as officers, and then inquiring whether either possessed a controlled substance or a large amount of cash were not tantamount to an arrest and did not require probable cause, but instead required a lesser standard, namely, that the officers possess a particularized and objective basis for suspecting the person stopped of criminal activity. State v. Longa, 211 Neb. 356, 318 N.W.2d 733 (1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>