<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-427"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-427</statuteno><catchline>Detention of accused; grounds.</catchline><para>Any peace officer having grounds for making an arrest may take the accused into custody or, already having done so, detain him further when the accused fails to identify himself satisfactorily, or refuses to sign the citation, or when the officer has reasonable grounds to believe that (1) the accused will refuse to respond to the citation, (2) such custody is necessary to protect the accused or others when his continued liberty would constitute a risk of immediate harm, (3) such action is necessary in order to carry out legitimate investigative functions, (4) the accused has no ties to the jurisdiction reasonably sufficient to assure his appearance, or (5) the accused has previously failed to appear in response to a citation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 829, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>An officer may arrest for an infraction if such action is necessary to carry out a legitimate investigative function. State v. Sassen, 240 Neb. 773, 484 N.W.2d 469 (1992).</para><para>Any peace officer having grounds for making an arrest may take the accused into custody or, already having done so, detain him further when the accused fails to identify himself satisfactorily or refuses to sign the citation or when the officer has reasonable grounds to believe that such action is necessary in order to carry out legitimate investigative functions. State v. Petersen, 12 Neb. App. 445, 676 N.W.2d 65 (2004).</para><para>Except as provided in this section, for any offense classified as an infraction, a citation shall be issued in lieu of arrest or continued custody. State v. Petersen, 12 Neb. App. 445, 676 N.W.2d 65 (2004).</para><para>A trooper who did not have grounds to arrest a suspect could not detain the suspect under this section. State v. Scovill, 9 Neb. App. 118, 608 N.W.2d 623 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>