<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-203</statuteno><catchline>District judges and county judges; conservators of the peace; jurisdiction.</catchline><para>The judges of the district courts in their respective districts, and the magistrates mentioned in section 29-201 in their respective counties, shall jointly and severally be conservators of the peace within their respective jurisdictions, and shall have full power to enforce or cause to be enforced all laws that now exist or that shall hereafter be made for the prevention and punishment of offenses, or for the preservation and observance of the peace. Judges of the district courts shall have the same powers to require securities for the keeping of the peace and good behavior, and bail for appearance in courts to answer complaints to keep the peace, and for crimes and offenses committed in their respective districts as any of the magistrates aforesaid have in their respective counties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 262, p. 784; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8916; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9937; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-203.</para></source><annotation><para>District judges have all of the required jurisdiction of magistrates. Otte v. State, 172 Neb. 110, 108 N.W.2d 737 (1961).</para><para>District judge may hold preliminary hearing. Callies v. State, 157 Neb. 640, 61 N.W.2d 370 (1953).</para><para>District judge may sit as examining magistrate. Cohoe v. State, 79 Neb. 811, 113 N.W. 532 (1907); State v. Dennison, 60 Neb. 192, 82 N.W. 628 (1900).</para><para>Preliminary hearing is in no sense a trial. Van Buren v. State, 65 Neb. 223, 91 N.W. 201 (1902).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>