<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-504</statuteno><catchline>Felony; speedy preliminary hearing required.</catchline><para>When the complaint is for a felony, upon the accused being brought before the magistrate, he shall proceed as soon as may be, in the presence of the accused, to inquire into the complaint.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 300, p. 793; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8955; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9979; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 101, &#167; 1, p. 290; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-504; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-504; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 168; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 226, &#167; 16. </para></source><annotation><para>Pursuant to this section, the accused must be brought before a magistrate as soon as is practical under the existing circumstances. State v. Thomas, 236 Neb. 84, 459 N.W.2d 204 (1990).</para><para>A speedy preliminary hearing is a personal right which may be waived. State v. Gau, 182 Neb. 114, 153 N.W.2d 298 (1967); Reinoehl v. State, 62 Neb. 619, 87 N.W. 355 (1901); Latimer v. State, 55 Neb. 609, 76 N.W. 207 (1898).</para><para>A defendant charged with a felony must be given a preliminary hearing as soon as the nature and circumstances of the case will permit. State v. O'Kelly, 175 Neb. 798, 124 N.W.2d 211 (1963).</para><para>Person charged with felony should be given preliminary hearing as soon as possible. Maher v. State, 144 Neb. 463, 13 N.W.2d 641 (1944).</para><para>Complaining witness is not party to action; magistrate is not disqualified by being relative of complaining witness. Ingraham v. State, 82 Neb. 553, 118 N.W. 320 (1908).</para><para>Preliminary examination is necessary, in prosecution by information, before defendant can be put on trial, over objections, unless waived. Jahnke v. State, 68 Neb. 154, 94 N.W. 158 (1903), reversed on rehearing, 68 Neb. 181, 104 N.W. 154 (1905).</para><para>Charging two offenses in same count does not render proceedings invalid. Sothman v. State, 66 Neb. 302, 92 N.W. 303 (1902).</para><para>Plea in abatement is proper method of raising question whether or not preliminary examination was had. Everson v. State, 4 Neb. Unof. 109, 93 N.W. 394 (1903).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>