<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-814.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-814.03</statuteno><catchline>Search warrant; issuance on telephonic statement; procedure.</catchline><para>A search warrant may be issued under section 29-814.05 pursuant to a telephonic statement made to a magistrate or judge in accordance with the procedures set forth in this section. Prior to telephonically contacting a magistrate or judge, the law enforcement officer requesting the warrant shall contact the county attorney or a deputy county attorney of the county in which the warrant is to be issued for purposes of explaining the reasons why a search warrant should be issued pursuant to a telephonic statement. If the county attorney or deputy county attorney is satisfied that a warrant is justified, and that circumstances justify its immediate issuance, the county attorney or deputy county attorney shall contact the magistrate or judge and state that he or she is convinced that a warrant should be issued by telephone. The county attorney or deputy county attorney shall provide the magistrate or judge with a telephone number at which the officer requesting the warrant may be contacted. The magistrate or judge shall call the officer at the number provided and shall place the officer under oath and take his or her statement. The statement shall be taken by means of a voice recording device in the custody of the magistrate or judge. The magistrate or judge shall direct that the recorded statement be transcribed and the magistrate or judge shall certify the accuracy of the transcription. The magistrate or judge shall file with the clerk of the district court of the county in which the property was seized the original of the recording and the transcribed statement. Such filing shall be made at the same time the warrant, copy of the return, inventory, and all other papers connected with the warrant are filed pursuant to section 29-816. For purposes of sections 29-814.01 to 29-814.06, a telephonic statement authorized by this section shall be considered to be an affidavit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 731, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>