<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-404.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-404.03</statuteno><catchline>Arrest without warrant; reasonable cause; conditions.</catchline><para>In determining whether reasonable cause exists to justify an arrest, a law enforcement officer may take into account all facts and circumstances, including those based upon any expert knowledge or experience which the officer in fact possessed, which a prudent officer would judge relevant to the likelihood that a crime has been committed and that the person to be arrested has committed it, and for such purpose the officer may rely on information he receives from any informant whom it is reasonable under the circumstances to credit, whether or not at the time of making the arrest the officer knows the informant's identity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 172, &#167; 3, p. 487. </para></source><annotation><para>Police may consider an anonymous tip, along with other facts and circumstances, in determining whether reasonable cause for an arrest exists. Where anonymous tip identified robber as a black male, 6 feet 1 inch tall, 28 years old, with a red eye, known as "Tony," who could be found at a certain address; eyewitnesses identified robber as black male with a red eye; neighbors of specified address described defendant's car; and defendant was a black male, 6 feet 3 inches tall, 29 years old, found at an address where the described car was parked, and named Tony, reasonable cause for arrest existed. State v. Haynie, 239 Neb. 478, 476 N.W.2d 905 (1991).</para><para>The totality of the circumstances, including a suspect's attempt to flee from a police officer, established reasonable or probable cause that the suspect was driving while his driver's license was still under suspension, which was a misdemeanor; thus, the officer had probable cause to arrest the suspect. Newton v. Huffman, 10 Neb. App. 390, 632 N.W.2d 344 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>