<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-901.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-901.03</statuteno><catchline>Conditions of release; review; procedure.</catchline><para>When a defendant first appears before a judge pursuant to section 29-901, he shall be advised of his right to obtain review of the conditions of release imposed if he is unable to fulfill such conditions and remains in custody for more than twenty-four hours thereafter. Any defendant who shall remain in custody for more than twenty-four hours after a judge other than a district court judge imposes bail or any other condition of release, as a result of his inability to fulfill such condition or conditions, may request a review by the judge who imposed the conditions and, upon such request, the defendant shall be brought before the judge at the first regular court day. If the defendant is indigent and unable to retain legal counsel, the judge shall appoint an attorney to represent the defendant for the purpose of such review. Unless the conditions of release are amended and the defendant is thereupon released, the judge shall set forth in writing the reasons for requiring such condition or conditions. Any defendant who shall be ordered released by a judge other than a district court judge on a condition which requires that he return to custody after specified hours shall, upon application, be entitled to a review by the judge who imposed the condition in the same manner as a defendant who remains in full-time custody. In the event that the judge who imposed the condition or conditions of release is not available, any other judge in the district or of the same court may review such conditions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 828, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 284, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>