<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id6" statutenumber="29-818"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>29-818</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Seized property;
custody; pet animal; additional procedures;
hearing; order to pay expenses; delinquent payments; hearing; notice; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Except for pet animals as provided in subsection (2) of this section, property
seized under a search warrant or validly seized without a warrant shall be
safely kept by the officer seizing the same, unless
otherwise directed by the judge or magistrate, and shall be so kept so long
as necessary for the purpose of being produced as evidence on any trial. Property
seized may not be taken from the officer having it in custody by replevin
or other writ so long as it is or may be required as evidence in any trial,
nor may it be so taken in any event where a complaint has been filed in connection
with which the property was or may be used as evidence, and the court in which
such complaint was filed shall have exclusive jurisdiction for disposition
of the property or funds and to determine rights therein, including questions
respecting the title, possession, control, and disposition thereof.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Any pet animal seized under a search warrant or validly seized without
a warrant may be kept by the officer seizing the same on the property of the
person who owns, keeps, harbors, maintains, or controls such pet animal.</para>
<para>(b) When any pet animal is seized under this
subsection, the court shall provide the person who owns, keeps,
harbors, maintains, or controls such pet animal with notice that a hearing will be
had and specify the date, time, and place of such hearing. Such notice shall
be served by personal or residential service or by certified mail. If such
notice cannot be served by such methods, service may be made by publication
in the county where such pet animal was seized. Such publication shall be made after application
and order of the court. Unless otherwise determined and ordered by the court,
the date of such hearing shall be no later than ten days after the seizure.</para>
<para>(c) At the hearing, the court shall determine the disposition
of the pet animal, and if the court
determines that any pet animal shall not be returned, the court shall order the person
from whom the pet animal was seized to pay all expenses for the support and maintenance
of the pet animal, including expenses
for shelter, food, veterinary care, and board, necessitated by the possession
of the pet animal. At the hearing,
the court shall also consider the person's ability to pay for the expenses
of the pet animal and
the amount of such payments. Payments shall be for a succeeding thirty-day
period with the first payment due on or before the tenth day following the
hearing. Payments for each subsequent succeeding thirty-day period, if any,
shall be due on or before the tenth day of such period.</para>
<para>(d) If a person becomes delinquent in his or her payments
for the expenses of the pet animal, the court shall
hold a hearing to determine the disposition of the seized pet animal. Notice of such hearing shall be given
to the person who owns, keeps, harbors, maintains, or controls such pet animal and to any lienholder
or security interest holder of record as provided in subdivision (b) of this
subsection.</para>
<para>(e) An appeal may be entered within ten days after a hearing
under subdivision (c) or (d) of this subsection. Any person filing an appeal
shall post a bond sufficient to pay all costs of care of the pet animal for thirty days.
Such payment will be required for each succeeding thirty-day period until
the appeal is final.</para>
<para>(f) Should the person be found not guilty, all funds paid
for the expenses of the pet animal shall be returned to the person.</para>
<para>(g) For purposes of this subsection, pet 
animal means any domestic
dog, domestic cat, mini pig, domestic rabbit, domestic ferret, domestic rodent,
bird except a bird raised as an agricultural animal and specifically excluding
any bird possessed under a license issued by the State of Nebraska or the
United States Fish and Wildlife Service, nonlethal aquarium fish, nonlethal
invertebrate, amphibian, turtle, nonvenomous snake that will not grow to more
than eight feet in length at maturity, or such other animal as may be specified
and for which a permit shall be issued by an animal control authority after
inspection and approval, except that any animal forbidden to be sold, owned,
or possessed by federal or state law is not a pet animal.</para>
<para>(h)
This section shall not preempt, and shall not be construed to preempt, any
ordinance of a city of the metropolitan or
primary class.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 161, &#167; 7, p. 573; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB423, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Seizure of vehicle and component parts,</emphasis> see section 60-2608.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Property seized and held as evidence is to be safely kept by the officer seizing it unless otherwise directed by the court, and the officer is to exercise reasonable care and diligence for the safekeeping of the property. The property shall be kept so long as necessary for the purpose of being produced as evidence at trial. State v. Agee, 274 Neb. 445, 741 N.W.2d 161 (2007).</para><para>The court in which a criminal charge was filed has exclusive jurisdiction to determine the rights to seized property and the property's disposition. State v. Agee, 274 Neb. 445, 741 N.W.2d 161 (2007).</para><para>A police officer's failure to "safely" keep a seized vehicle can give rise to liability under the Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act. Section 29-818 requires a police officer to exercise reasonable care and diligence for the safekeeping of property within his custody. Nash v. City of North Platte, 205 Neb. 480, 288 N.W.2d 51 (1980).</para><para>The trial court's decision on the return of seized property is reviewed for an abuse of discretion. State v. Maestas, 11 Neb. App. 262, 647 N.W.2d 122 (2002).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>