<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id176">
<sectno id="id177">Sec. 14.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id178" statutenumber="29-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id180">29-401</statuteno><catchline id="id181">Law violators;
arrest by sheriff or other peace officer; juvenile under eighteen years; requirements.</catchline><para>Every sheriff, deputy sheriff, marshal, deputy marshal, security
guard, police officer, or peace officer as defined in subdivision (15) of
section 49-801 shall arrest and detain any person found violating any law
of this state or any legal ordinance of any city or incorporated village until
a legal warrant can be obtained, except that (1) any such law enforcement
officer taking a juvenile under the age of eighteen years into his or her
custody for any violation herein defined shall proceed as set forth in sections
43-248, 43-248.01, 43-250, 43-251, 43-251.01, and 43-253 and (2) the court
in which the juvenile is to appear shall not accept a plea from the juvenile
until finding that the parents of the juvenile have been notified or that
reasonable efforts to notify such parents have been made as provided in section 43-250.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 283, p. 789; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8937; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9961; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-401; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 175, &#167; 1, p. 490; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1403, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1030, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 451, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB771, &#167; 14.</para></source><annotation><para>The finding required by subsection (2) of this section, that the parents of a child under the age of 18 years have been notified of the child's arrest or that reasonable efforts to notify have been made, is not jurisdictional. State v. Taylor, 234 Neb. 18, 448 N.W.2d 920 (1989).</para><para>An arrest may not be used as a pretext to search for evidence. A pretext arrest is one where the arrest is only a sham, a front being used as an excuse for making a search. The determination of whether an arrest is pretextual is a question of fact for the trial court. This court will not reverse a trial court's finding on this question unless the finding is clearly erroneous. State v. Vann, 230 Neb. 601, 432 N.W.2d 810 (1988).</para><para>Firing of shots at tires of speeding automobile was justified in making arrest. Breese v. Newman, 179 Neb. 878, 140 N.W.2d 805 (1966).</para><para>Arrest of person who fled from police officers was justified under facts. Sperry v. Greiner, 175 Neb. 524, 122 N.W.2d 463 (1963).</para><para>Jury was properly instructed as to the duties of sheriff to arrest and detain under this section. O'Dell v. Goodsell, 152 Neb. 290, 41 N.W.2d 123 (1950).</para><para>Mandamus will lie to compel city officers to use summary powers to prevent violations of law. Moores v. State ex rel. Dunn, 71 Neb. 522, 99 N.W. 249 (1904).</para><para>Arrest and detention without warrant by marshal was legal. Fry v. Kaessner, 48 Neb. 133, 66 N.W. 1126 (1896).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>