<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1401"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1401</statuteno><catchline>Grand jury; when called; death while
being apprehended or in custody; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) The district
courts are hereby vested with power to call grand juries.</para>
<para>(2) A grand jury may be called and summoned in the manner provided by
law on such day of a regular term of the district court in each year in each
county of the state as the district court may direct and at such other times
and upon such notice as the district court may deem necessary.</para>
<para>(3) District courts shall call a grand jury in each case that a petition
meets the requirements of section 32-628, includes a recital as to the reason
for requesting the convening of the grand jury and a specific reference to
the statute or statutes which are alleged to have been violated, and is signed
not more than ninety days prior to the date of filing under section 29-1401.02
by not less than ten percent of the registered voters of the county who cast
votes for the office of Governor in such county at the most recent general
election held for such office.</para>
<para>(4) District courts shall call a grand jury in each case upon certification
by the county coroner or coroner's physician that a person has died while
being apprehended by or while in the custody of a law enforcement officer
or detention personnel. In each case subject to this subsection:</para>
<para>(a) Law enforcement personnel from the jurisdiction in which the death
occurred shall immediately secure the scene, preserve all evidence, and investigate
the matter as in any other homicide;
and</para>
<para>(b) A grand jury shall be impaneled within thirty
days after the certification by the county coroner or coroner's physician,
unless the court extends such time period upon the showing of a compelling
reason.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 171, &#167; 1, p. 591; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9031; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 148, &#167; 1, p. 333; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10055; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1401; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 18, &#167; 19, p. 111; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 29-1401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1401; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 118, &#167; 1, p. 449; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 237, &#167; 1, p. 874; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 676, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 72, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 935, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB842, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The statutory scheme which requires convening a grand jury where a person has died while being apprehended by or while in custody of a law enforcement officer removes the county attorney from the process, and the county attorney has no access to grand jury records. The failure of the grand jury to return an indictment does not prevent the county attorney from proceeding independently. It is not necessary to convene a second grand jury, but, rather, the county attorney may proceed by filing a complaint or information in the district court. In re Grand Jury of Douglas Cty., 263 Neb. 981, 644 N.W.2d 858 (2002).</para><para>District court may order grand jury hereunder. Pinn v. State, 107 Neb. 417, 186 N.W. 544 (1922).</para><para>Under prior law, grand jury was required to be summoned at first term every year unless otherwise directed in writing by court or judge thereof. Krause v. State, 88 Neb. 473, 129 N.W. 1020 (1911).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>