<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-1822"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1822</statuteno><catchline id="id00">See note regarding referendum petition following the source at the end of the section. Mental incompetency of accused after crime commission; effect.</catchline><para>A person who becomes mentally incompetent after the commission of a crime or misdemeanor shall not be tried for the offense during the continuance of the incompetency. If, after the verdict of guilty and before judgment is pronounced, such person becomes mentally incompetent, then no judgment shall be given while such incompetency continues.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 454, p. 823; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9098; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10123; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1821; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1822; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1177, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 13. </para><note>Section 29-1822 was amended by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 13. According to Article III, section 3, of the Constitution of Nebraska, the provisions of LB 268 have been suspended due to the certification by the Secretary of State of sufficient signatures on referendum petitions to suspend the taking effect of such act until the same has been approved by the electors of the state. The question will be submitted to the voters at the November 2016 general election. The prior version of section 29-1822 is found in the 2008 Reissue of Volume 2A of the Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</note></source><annotation><para>District court has discretion to hold hearing voluntarily on mental competency of defendant to undergo sentence. State v. Saxon, 187 Neb. 338, 190 N.W.2d 854 (1971).</para><para>Insanity as a bar to the imposition of sentence presents a factual issue for the determination of the court. State v. Anderson, 186 Neb. 435, 183 N.W.2d 766 (1971).</para><para>Insanity as bar to imposition of sentence cannot be raised by habeas corpus. Sedlacek v. Hann, 156 Neb. 340, 56 N.W.2d 138 (1952).</para><para>This section imposes a duty on but does not go to the jurisdiction of the court. Sedlacek v. Greenholtz, 152 Neb. 386, 41 N.W.2d 154 (1950).</para><para>One who has become insane after the commission of a crime ought not to be tried for the offense during the continuance of the disability. Carlsen v. State, 129 Neb. 84, 261 N.W. 339 (1935).</para><para>Where insanity has not originated after commission of act, there is no requirement of trial of question of insanity. Walker v. State, 46 Neb. 25, 64 N.W. 357 (1895).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>