<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id65">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id67" statutenumber="29-1917"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1917</statuteno><catchline id="id70">Deposition of
witness; when; procedure; use at trial.</catchline><para>(1) Except
as provided in section 29-1926, at any time after the filing of an indictment
or information in a felony prosecution, the prosecuting attorney or the
defendant may request the court to allow the taking of a deposition of any
person other than the defendant who may be a witness in the trial of the offense.
The court may order the taking of the deposition when it finds the testimony
of the witness:</para>
<para>(a) May be material or relevant to the issue to be determined
at the trial of the offense; or</para>
<para>(b) May be of assistance to the parties in the preparation
of their respective cases.</para>
<para>(2) An order granting the taking of a deposition shall include
the time and place for taking such deposition and such other conditions as
the court determines to be just.</para>
<para>(3) The proceedings in taking the deposition of a witness
pursuant to this section and returning it to the court shall be governed in
all respects as the taking of depositions in civil cases.</para>
<para>(4) A deposition taken pursuant to this section may be used
at the trial by any party solely for the purpose of contradicting or impeaching
the testimony of the deponent as a witness.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 235, &#167; 6, p. 870; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 90, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 178, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child victim or child witness,</emphasis> use of videotape deposition, see section 29-1926.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This statute governs the appropriate use of discovery depositions in a criminal case when the deponent is available as a testifying witness. State v. Castor, 257 Neb. 572, 599 N.W.2d 201 (1999).</para><para>A motion for depositions must be filed by a defendant after the information is filed. State v. Murphy, 255 Neb. 797, 587 N.W.2d 384 (1998).</para><para>Subsection (4) of this section governs only the appropriate use of a discovery deposition when the deponent is an available, testifying witness. State v. Allen, 252 Neb. 187, 560 N.W.2d 829 (1997).</para><para>Defendant is not entitled, as a matter of right, to a deposition pursuant to subsection (1) of this section. State v. Tuttle, 238 Neb. 827, 472 N.W.2d 712 (1991).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
