<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1201"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1201</statuteno><catchline>Prisoner held without indictment; discharge or recognizance; when.</catchline><para>Any person held in jail charged with an indictable offense shall be discharged if he or she is not indicted at the term of court at which he or she is held to answer, unless such person is committed to jail on such charge after the rising and final report of the grand jury for that term, in which case the court may discharge such person, or require such person to enter into recognizance with sufficient security for his or her appearance before such court to answer such charge at the next term. However, such person so held in jail without indictment shall not be discharged if it appears to the satisfaction of the court that the witnesses on the part of the state have been enticed or kept away or are detained and prevented from attending court by sickness or some inevitable accident.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 389, p. 812; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9020; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10044; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1201; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1201; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 41. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Prisoners,</emphasis> disposition of untried charges, see section 29-3801 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Nebraska has created a statutory speedy trial right, which generally provides that a person who has been indicted for a criminal offense must be brought to trial within 6 months of his or her indictment. State v. Kula, 254 Neb. 962, 579 N.W.2d 541 (1998).</para><para>The procedure set out in sections 29-3801 et seq., rather than that in sections 29-1201 et seq., applies to instate prisoners. State v. Ebert, 235 Neb. 330, 455 N.W.2d 165 (1990).</para><para>Record did not show delay entitling defendant to discharge hereunder. Shaffer v. State, 123 Neb. 121, 242 N.W. 364 (1932).</para><para>Where jury called for term was excused before felony was committed, information was properly filed at beginning of next regular term. Nichols v. State, 109 Neb. 335, 191 N.W. 333 (1922).</para><para>Where no information or indictment is filed against defendant during the term at which he was held to answer, he is entitled to discharge. Cerny v. State, 62 Neb. 626, 87 N.W. 336 (1901).</para><para>Information filed in time and amended at next term does not entitle accused to discharge. Barker v. State, 54 Neb. 53, 74 N.W. 427 (1898).</para><para>When accused is fugitive from justice, he is not entitled to discharge because of failure to file information. Ex parte Trester, 53 Neb. 148, 73 N.W. 545 (1897).</para><para>Upon failure to indict or file information in term to which recognized, defendant is discharged. State ex rel. Conroy v. Miller, 43 Neb. 860, 62 N.W. 238 (1895).</para><para>When witnesses for state are not prevented from attending and no indictment is brought, accused is entitled to discharge. Ex parte Two Calf, 11 Neb. 221, 9 N.W. 44 (1881).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>