<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1001"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1001</statuteno><catchline>Prisoner; where confined.</catchline><para>Whenever it shall be lawful and necessary to confine any prisoner in custody previous to conviction upon a criminal accusation, or in custody for contempt or alleged contempt of court, or upon an attachment by order of a court or judge, or otherwise in lawful custody, or upon conviction for any offense, the officer or person having him in such custody may convey him to and confine him in the jail of any county in this state, or other secure and convenient place of confinement in this state, to be procured by such officer or person having such prisoner in custody.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 377, p. 810; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9010; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10034; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1001; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1001.</para></source><annotation><para>Counties are obligated to pay costs and expenses of prosecutions, including fees and expenses of attorneys appointed to represent indigent defendants in criminal cases, and there is no requirement that a property tax be levied therefor. Kovarik v. County of Banner, 192 Neb. 816, 224 N.W.2d 761 (1975).</para><para>Transfer of prisoner sentenced to county jail governed by this section. State v. Curry, 184 Neb. 682, 171 N.W.2d 163 (1969).</para><para>Sheriff may hold person in custody for contempt of court in secure and convenient place of confinement. Rhodes v. Sigler, 172 Neb. 439, 109 N.W.2d 731 (1961).</para><para>In confining persons to jail in another county, when there is no secure jail in county, sheriff acts in official capacity, and surety on bond is liable for money received and not accounted for. Martin v. Seeley, 15 Neb. 136, 17 N.W. 346 (1883).</para><para>Where sheriff has custody of prisoners from two different counties for safekeeping, compensation is no greater than if they came from same county. James v. Lincoln County, 5 Neb. 38 (1876).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>