<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1409"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1409</statuteno><catchline>Subpoenas; issuance; advisement of rights; form; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever required by the grand jury, or the prosecuting attorney, the clerk of the court in which such jury is impaneled shall issue subpoenas and other process to bring witnesses to testify before such grand jury.</para><para>(2) At the option of the prosecuting attorney, a grand jury subpoena may contain an advisement of rights. If the prosecuting attorney determines that an advisement is necessary, the grand jury subpoena shall contain the following prominently displayed on the front of the subpoena:</para><para>NOTICE</para><para>(a) You have the right to retain an attorney to represent you and to advise you regarding your grand jury appearance.</para><para>(b) Anything you say to the grand jury may be used against you in a court of law.</para><para>(c) You have the right to refuse to answer questions if you feel the answers would tend to incriminate you or to implicate you in any illegal activity.</para><para>(d) If you cannot afford or obtain an attorney, you may consult with the public defender's office, or request the court to appoint an attorney to represent you.</para><para>(3) Any witness who is not advised of his or her rights pursuant to subsection (2) of this section shall not be prosecuted or subjected to any penalty or forfeiture for or on account of any transaction, matter, or thing concerning which he or she testifies or any evidence he or she produces, nor shall any such testimony or evidence be used as evidence in any criminal proceeding, except for perjury, against him or her in any court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 400, p. 815; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9039; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10063; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1409; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1409; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 524, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>