<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-1903"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1903</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Traffic, criminal, and juvenile cases; witness fees and mileage.</catchline><para>(1) The amount of the witness fee and mileage in traffic, criminal, and juvenile cases is governed by section 33-139.</para><para>(2) A witness in a traffic, criminal, or juvenile case shall be entitled to a witness fee and mileage after appearing in court in response to a subpoena. The clerk of the court shall immediately submit a claim for payment of witness fees and mileage on behalf of all such witnesses to the county clerk in cases involving a violation of state law or to the city clerk in cases involving a violation of a city ordinance. All witness fees and mileage paid by a defendant as part of the court costs ordered by the court to be paid shall be reimbursed to the county or city treasurer as appropriate.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any person accused of crime amounting to a misdemeanor or felony shall have compulsory process to enforce the attendance of witnesses in his or her behalf.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 461, p. 825; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 106, &#167; 1, p. 394; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9101; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10126; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1903; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1903; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB509, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>Defendant may not be arbitrarily deprived of testimony that would have been relevant, material, and vital to the defense. State v. Cain, 223 Neb. 796, 393 N.W.2d 727 (1986).</para><para>Court may require showing of what testimony may be expected of prospective witness before entry of order for compulsory process. O'Rourke v. State, 166 Neb. 866, 90 N.W.2d 820 (1958).</para><para>Where testimony of witness was incompetent, failure to serve compulsory process was not prejudicial. Garcia v. State, 159 Neb. 571, 68 N.W.2d 151 (1955).</para><para>Liability of county arises only by express provisions of statute. Worthen v. Johnson County, 62 Neb. 754, 87 N.W. 909 (1901).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>