<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1904</statuteno><catchline>Depositions; certain witnesses; application by defendant; when granted; interrogatories; notice to county attorney.</catchline><para>Where any issue of fact is joined on any indictment, and any material witness for the defendant resides out of the state, or, residing within the state, is sick or infirm or is about to leave the state, such defendant may apply in writing to the court in term time, or the judge thereof in vacation, for a commission to examine such witness upon interrogatories thereto annexed, and such court or judge may grant the same, and order what and for how long a time notice shall be given the prosecuting attorney before the witness shall be examined.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 462, p. 825; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9102; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10127; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1904; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1904.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Act to Secure the Attendance of Witnesses from Without a State in Criminal Proceedings,</emphasis> see section 29-1911.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This section does not provide for the taking of depositions at county expense in advance of the trial. State v. Kuehn, 273 Neb. 219, 728 N.W.2d 589 (2007).</para><para>It was not necessary to analyze this section to dispose of claim that trial court erred in refusing permission to take deposition of inmates of penal institution. Rains v. State, 173 Neb. 586, 114 N.W.2d 399 (1962).</para><para>Taking of depositions at county expense in advance of trial is not authorized. Vore v. State, 158 Neb. 222, 63 N.W.2d 141 (1954).</para><para>Defendant was entitled to continuance to take deposition out of the state where timely application was made. Dolen v. State, 148 Neb. 317, 27 N.W.2d 264 (1947).</para><para>On admission by state that proposed witness would testify as stated in affidavit, court may refuse continuance. Fanton v. State, 50 Neb. 351, 69 N.W. 953 (1897); Burris v. Court, 48 Neb. 179, 66 N.W. 1131 (1896).</para><para>Correctness of ruling in suppressing deposition, not excepted to, cannot be questioned on error. Clough v. State, 7 Neb. 320 (1878).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>