<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1601</statuteno><catchline>Prosecutions on information; authorized.</catchline><para>The several courts of this state shall possess and may exercise the same power and jurisdiction to hear, try and determine prosecutions upon information, for crimes, misdemeanors and offenses, to issue writs and process, and do all other acts therein, as they possess and may exercise in cases of the like prosecutions upon indictments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 108, &#167; 1, p. 397; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9062; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10086; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1601.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Prosecution on information</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Constitutionality</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Prosecution on information</emphasis></para><para>Prosecution on information is authorized. Duggan v. Olson, 146 Neb. 248, 19 N.W.2d 353 (1945).</para><para>Prosecution upon information verified and filed by acting county attorney is good against attack by habeas corpus. State ex rel. Gossett v. O'Grady, 137 Neb. 824, 291 N.W. 497 (1940).</para><para>District court may try misdemeanor charged in information as proper exercise of its original jurisdiction. Nelson v. State, 115 Neb. 26, 211 N.W. 175 (1926).</para><para>Prosecution for murder may be by information. Hawkins v. State, 60 Neb. 380, 83 N.W. 198 (1900).</para><para><emphasis>2. Constitutionality</emphasis></para><para>Prosecution on information is not a violation of due process of law clause. Jackson v. Olson, 146 Neb. 885, 22 N.W.2d 124 (1946).</para><para>Prosecution of criminal offenses by information does not violate rule of uniformity required by Constitution. Dinsmore v. State, 61 Neb. 418, 85 N.W. 445 (1901).</para><para>This section does not conflict with Fourteenth Amendment. Bolln v. Nebraska, 176 U.S. 83 (1900).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Indictment by a grand jury is not required in the State of Nebraska. State v. Lehman, 203 Neb. 341, 278 N.W.2d 610 (1979).</para><para>Person accused of felony must be charged by information or indictment disclosing nature and cause of accusation. Stowe v. State, 117 Neb. 440, 220 N.W. 826 (1928).</para><para>Pendency of former information, for same offense, is no ground for plea in abatement. Roby v. State, 61 Neb. 218, 85 N.W. 61 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>