<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-1418"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1418</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Indictments; presentation; filing; finding of probable cause; dismissal; motions.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Indictments returned by a grand jury shall be presented by their foreman to the court and shall be filed with the clerk, who shall endorse thereon the day of their filing and shall enter each case upon the register of actions and the date when the parties indicted have been arrested.</para><para id="id00">(2) Any grand jury may indict a person for an offense when the evidence before such grand jury provides probable cause to believe that such person committed such offense.</para><para id="id00">(3) The district court before which the indicted defendant is to be tried shall dismiss any indictment of the grand jury if such district court finds, upon the filing of a motion by the indicted defendant based upon the grand jury record without argument or further evidence, that the grand jury finding of probable cause is not supported by the record.</para><para id="id00">(4) Any other motions testing the validity of the indictment may be heard by the court based only on the record and argument of counsel, unless there is cause shown for the need for additional evidence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 410, p. 816; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9048; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10072; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1418; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1418; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 524, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 53. </para></source><annotation><para>Any error in a ruling on a motion to dismiss under subsection (3) of this section based on the sufficiency of evidence before a grand jury is cured by a subsequent finding at trial of guilt beyond a reasonable doubt which is supported by sufficient evidence. State v. Chauncey, 295 Neb. 453, 890 N.W.2d 453 (2017).</para><para>This section requires the clerk of the trial court to endorse upon an indictment the date of its filing and to enter the case upon the docket. State v. Muse, 15 Neb. App. 13, 721 N.W.2d 661 (2006).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>