<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-1404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1404</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Foreperson; oath or affirmation; form.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, when the foreperson shall be appointed, an oath or affirmation shall be administered to him or her in the following words: Saving yourself and fellow jurors, you, as foreperson of this grand inquest, shall diligently inquire and true presentment make, of all such matters and things as shall be given you in charge or otherwise come to your knowledge, touching the present service. The counsel of the state, your own and your fellows, you shall keep secret, unless called on in a court of justice to make disclosures. You shall present no person through malice, hatred, or ill will, nor shall you leave any person unpresented through fear, favor, or affection, or for any reward or hope thereof; but in all your presentments you shall present the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth, according to the best of your skill and understanding.</para><para>(2) For grand juries impaneled pursuant to subsection (4) of section 29-1401, when the foreperson shall be appointed, an oath or affirmation shall be administered to him or her in the following words: Saving yourself and fellow jurors, you, as foreperson of this grand inquest, shall diligently inquire and true presentment make, of all such matters and things as shall be given you in charge or otherwise come to your knowledge, touching the present service. The counsel of the state, your own and your fellows, you shall keep secret during the course of the impaneled grand jury's investigation and deliberations, unless called on in a court of justice to make disclosures. You shall present no person through malice, hatred, or ill will, nor shall you leave any person unpresented through fear, favor, or affection, or for any reward or hope thereof; but in all your presentments you shall present the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth, according to the best of your skill and understanding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 395, p. 814; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9034; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10058; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1404; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1404; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1000, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>Oath construed. Krause v. State, 88 Neb. 473, 129 N.W. 1020 (1911).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>