<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-1604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1604</statuteno><catchline>Information; procedure; law applicable.</catchline><para>The provisions of the criminal code in relation to indictments, and all other provisions of law, applying to prosecutions upon indictments to writs and process therein, and the issuing and service thereof, to motions, pleadings, trials and punishments or the execution of any sentence, and to all other proceedings in cases of indictments, whether in the court of original or appellate jurisdiction, shall in the same manner and to the same extent, as nearly as may be, apply to informations, and all prosecutions and proceedings thereon.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 108, &#167; 4, p. 398; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9065; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10089; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1604; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1604.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Information</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Information</emphasis></para><para>Filing and service of amended information rendered nonprejudicial defects in service of original information. Svehla v. State, 168 Neb. 553, 96 N.W.2d 649 (1959).</para><para>Provision of criminal code with respect to indictments applies to informations. Shepperd v. State, 168 Neb. 464, 96 N.W.2d 261 (1959).</para><para>Information was sufficient to charge offense of uttering forged check. Benedict v. State, 166 Neb. 295, 89 N.W.2d 82 (1958).</para><para>Statutory provisions relating to indictments applies to informations. Jurgenson v. State, 166 Neb. 111, 88 N.W.2d 129 (1958).</para><para>This section makes the statutory provision for service of an indictment applicable to an information. Hawk v. State, 151 Neb. 717, 39 N.W.2d 561 (1949).</para><para>Information charging assault with intent to commit rape by force was not defective because of allegation of age of complaining witness. Frank v. State, 150 Neb. 745, 35 N.W.2d 816 (1949).</para><para>The provisions of the criminal code in relation to indictments apply to prosecution on information for picketing. Dutiel v. State, 135 Neb. 811, 284 N.W. 321 (1939).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Exact time of commission of alleged prior felony is not essential in charge under Habitual Criminal Act. State v. Harig, 192 Neb. 49, 218 N.W.2d 884 (1974).</para><para>There is no specified length of time that must elapse between filing of information and commencement of trial except requirement of one day must elapse after information has been served before arraignment. Darlington v. State, 153 Neb. 274, 44 N.W.2d 468 (1950).</para><para>This section makes applicable to prosecutions upon information preliminary pleadings provided for attacking indictments, and same waiver of defects for failure to make attack by motion to quash, plea in abatement or demurrer. State ex rel. Gossett v. O'Grady, 137 Neb. 824, 291 N.W. 497 (1940).</para><para>Election is not required between counts charging same offense. Stevens v. State, 84 Neb. 759, 122 N.W. 58 (1909).</para><para>Where offenses are distinct and separate, court should require prosecutor to elect. Miller v. State, 78 Neb. 645, 111 N.W. 637 (1907).</para><para>Several misdemeanors of same kind may be set forth in separate counts; prosecutor is not required to elect. Little v. State, 60 Neb. 749, 84 N.W. 248 (1900).</para><para>The requirement of service of copy of indictment within twenty-four hours after filing applies to information. Hawk v. Olson, 326 U.S. 271 (1945), reversing Hawk v. Olson, 145 Neb. 306, 16 N.W.2d 181 (1944).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>