<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-1406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-1406</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Judge; charge to jury; instruction as to powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The grand jury, after being sworn, shall be charged as to their duty by the judge, who shall call their attention particularly to the obligation of secrecy which their oaths impose, and to such offenses as he or she is by law required to specially charge.</para><para>(2) Upon impanelment of each grand jury, the court shall give to such grand jury adequate and reasonable written notice of and shall assure that the grand jury reasonably understands the nature of:</para><para>(a) Its duty to inquire into offenses against the criminal laws of the State of Nebraska alleged to have been committed or, in the case of a grand jury impaneled pursuant to subsection (4) of section 29-1401, its duty to inquire into offenses against the criminal laws of the State of Nebraska regarding the death of a person who has died while being apprehended or while in the custody of a law enforcement officer or detention personnel;</para><para>(b) Its right to call and interrogate witnesses;</para><para>(c) Its right to request the production of documents or other evidence;</para><para>(d) The subject matter of the investigation and the criminal statutes or other statutes involved, if these are known at the time the grand jury is impaneled;</para><para>(e) The duty of the grand jury by an affirmative vote of twelve or more members of the grand jury to determine, based on the evidence presented before it, whether or not there is probable cause for finding indictments and to determine the violations to be included in any such indictments;</para><para>(f) The requirement that the grand jury may not return an indictment in cases of perjury unless at least two witnesses to the same fact present evidence establishing probable cause to return such an indictment; and</para><para>(g) In the case of a grand jury impaneled pursuant to subsection (4) of section 29-1401, if the grand jury returns a no true bill:</para><para>(i) The grand jury shall create a grand jury report with the assistance of the prosecuting attorney. The grand jury report shall briefly provide an explanation of the grand jury's findings and any recommendations the grand jury determines to be appropriate based upon the grand jury's investigation and deliberations; and</para><para> (ii) The no true bill and the grand jury report shall be filed with the court, where they shall be available for public review, along with the grand jury transcript provided for in subdivision (2)(b) of section 29-1407.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 397, p. 814; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9036; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10060; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-1406; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-1406; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 524, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1000, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Wide discretion is allowed judge in charge, which appellate court will not control. Clair v. State, 40 Neb. 534, 59 N.W. 118 (1894).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>