<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2246"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2246</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Probation Administration Act and sections 43-2,123.01 and 83-1,102 to 83-1,104, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Association means the Nebraska District Court Judges Association;</para><para>(2) Court means a district court, county court, or juvenile court as defined in section 43-245;</para><para>(3) Office means the Office of Probation Administration;</para><para>(4) Probation means a sentence under which a person found guilty of a crime upon verdict or plea or adjudicated delinquent or in need of special supervision is released by a court subject to conditions imposed by the court and subject to supervision. Probation includes post-release supervision;</para><para>(5) Probationer means a person sentenced to probation or post-release supervision;</para><para>(6) Probation officer means an employee of the system who supervises probationers and conducts presentence, predisposition, or other investigations as may be required by law or directed by a court in which he or she is serving or performs such other duties as authorized pursuant to section 29-2258, except unpaid volunteers from the community;</para><para>(7) Juvenile probation officer means any probation officer who supervises probationers of a separate juvenile court;</para><para>(8) Juvenile intake probation officer means an employee of the system who is called upon by a law enforcement officer in accordance with section 43-250 to make a decision regarding the furtherance of a juvenile's detention;</para><para>(9) Chief probation officer means the probation officer in charge of a probation district;</para><para>(10) System means the Nebraska Probation System;</para><para>(11) Administrator means the probation administrator;</para><para>(12) Non-probation-based program or service means a program or service established within the district, county, or juvenile courts and provided to individuals not sentenced to probation who have been charged with or convicted of a crime for the purpose of diverting the individual from incarceration or to provide treatment for issues related to the individual's criminogenic needs. Non-probation-based programs or services include, but are not limited to, problem solving courts established pursuant to section 24-1302 and the treatment of problems relating to substance abuse, mental health, sex offenses, or domestic violence;</para><para>(13) Post-release supervision means the portion of a split sentence following a period of incarceration under which a person found guilty of a crime upon verdict or plea is released by a court subject to conditions imposed by the court and subject to supervision by the office; and</para><para>(14) Rules and regulations means policies and procedures written by the office and approved by the Supreme Court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 680, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1051, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 529, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 451, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB919, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>