<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id263">
<sectno id="id264">Sec. 27.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id265" statutenumber="29-2321"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id267">29-2321</statuteno><catchline id="id268">Appeal of sentence
by prosecuting attorney or
Attorney General; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Appeals under sections 29-2320 to 29-2325 shall
be taken, by either the Attorney
General or the prosecuting attorney, as follows:</para>
<para>(a) If the
appeal is filed by the Attorney General, a notice of appeal shall be filed
in the district court within twenty days after imposition of the sentence.
A copy of the notice of appeal shall be sent to either the defendant or counsel
for the defendant; or</para>
<para>(b)
If the prosecuting attorney wishes to file the appeal, he or she, within ten
days after imposition of the sentence, shall
request approval from the Attorney General to proceed with the appeal. A copy of the request
for approval shall be sent to the defendant or counsel for the defendant.</para>
<para>(2) If the Attorney General approves the request described
in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, the
prosecuting attorney shall file a notice of appeal indicating such approval
in the district court. Such notice of appeal must be filed within twenty days
of the imposition of sentence. A copy of the notice of appeal shall be sent
to the defendant or counsel for the defendant.</para>
<para>(3) If the Attorney General does not approve the request
described in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, an
appeal under sections 29-2320 to 29-2325 shall not be permitted.</para>
<para>(4) In addition to such notice of appeal, the docket fee
required by section 33-103 shall be deposited with the clerk of the district
court.</para>
<para>(5) Upon
compliance with the requirements of this section, the appeal shall proceed
as provided by law for appeals to the Court of Appeals.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 402, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 17, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 27.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>