<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2104</statuteno><catchline>Arrest of judgment; grounds.</catchline><para>A motion in arrest of judgment may be granted by the court for either of the following causes: (1) That the grand jury which found the indictment had no legal authority to inquire into the offense charged, by reason of it not being within the jurisdiction of the court; or (2) that the facts stated in the indictment do not constitute an offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 493, p. 831; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9134; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10159; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2104.</para></source><annotation><para>Challenge to certainty and particularity of information which states an offense in the words of the statute may be made by a motion to quash, but not by a motion in arrest of judgment. State v. Abraham, 189 Neb. 728, 205 N.W.2d 342 (1973).</para><para>A defendant who pleads not guilty without having raised the question of the lack of or a defective verification waives the defect. State v. Gilman, 181 Neb. 390, 148 N.W.2d 847 (1967).</para><para>Striking motion in arrest of judgment from files instead of overruling it was not prejudicial error. Kopp v. State, 124 Neb. 363, 246 N.W. 718 (1933).</para><para>Motion in arrest of judgment should be sustained when information is insufficient to charge offense under statute. Korab v. State, 93 Neb. 66, 139 N.W. 717 (1913).</para><para>Selection of jury from old list prepared during preceding year was not a ground for motion in arrest of judgment, where plea in abatement was filed raising question but ruling thereon was not obtained. Goldsberry v. State, 92 Neb. 211, 137 N.W. 1116 (1912).</para><para>Sufficiency of information which charges no offense may be challenged, though plea of guilty was entered. Smith v. State, 68 Neb. 204, 94 N.W. 106 (1903).</para><para>Motion applies only to jurisdiction of court and sufficiency of indictment. Dodge v. People, 4 Neb. 220 (1876).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>