<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2928"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2928</statuteno><catchline>Treatment in inpatient treatment program; determination; procedure; departments; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If the Department of Health and Human Services determines that treatment in an inpatient treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services is appropriate for a convicted sex offender, that the offender will enter the treatment program voluntarily, and that space is available in the program, the Director of Correctional Services shall transfer the offender to the treatment program designated by the Department of Health and Human Services for treatment. The Department of Correctional Services shall be responsible for physical transfer of the offender to the treatment facility.</para><para>(2) If the Department of Health and Human Services determines that treatment in an inpatient treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services is not appropriate for a convicted sex offender, the offender shall serve the sentence in a facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services and may participate in treatment offered by the Department of Correctional Services if the Department of Correctional Services determines that such treatment is appropriate for the offender. The Department of Correctional Services may make a recommendation concerning treatment as provided in subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(3) If the Department of Health and Human Services determines that treatment in an inpatient treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services is not initially appropriate for a convicted sex offender but may be appropriate at a later time, a treatment decision may be deferred until a designated time, no later than two and one-half years prior to the offender's earliest parole eligibility date, when the offender will be reevaluated.</para><para>(4) If the Department of Correctional Services determines that an offender participating in treatment offered by the Department of Correctional Services will benefit from a treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Correctional Services shall notify the Department of Health and Human Services and recommend admission of the offender to the treatment program. The evaluation process to determine whether such offender is to be admitted into a treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services pursuant to this subsection shall be based upon criteria and procedures established by the Department of Health and Human Services and shall not be subject to appeal or review.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 523, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 46.</para></source></law></legaldoc>