<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2206"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2206</statuteno><catchline>Fine and costs; commitment until paid; installments; deduction from bond; suspension or revocation of motor vehicle operator's license.</catchline><para>(1)(a) In all cases in which courts or magistrates have now or may hereafter have the power to punish offenses, either in whole or in part, by requiring the offender to pay fines or costs, or both, such courts or magistrates may make it a part of the sentence that the party stand committed and be imprisoned in the jail of the proper county until the fines or costs are paid or secured to be paid or the offender is otherwise discharged according to law if the court or magistrate determines that the offender has the financial ability to pay such fines or costs. The court or magistrate may make such determination at the sentencing hearing or at a separate hearing prior to sentencing. A separate hearing shall not be required. In making such determination, the court or magistrate may consider the information or evidence adduced in an earlier proceeding pursuant to section 29-3902, 29-3903, 29-3906, or 29-3916. At any such hearing, the offender shall have the opportunity to present information as to his or her income, assets, debts, or other matters affecting his or her financial ability to pay. Following such hearing and prior to imposing sentence, the court or magistrate shall determine the offender's financial ability to pay the fines or costs, including his or her financial ability to pay in installments under subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(b) If the court or magistrate determines that the offender is financially able to pay the fines or costs and the offender refuses to pay, the court or magistrate may:</para><para>(i) Make it a part of the sentence that the offender stand committed and be imprisoned in the jail of the proper county until the fines or costs are paid or secured to be paid or the offender is otherwise discharged according to law; or</para><para>(ii) Order the offender, in lieu of paying such fines or costs, to complete community service for a specified number of hours pursuant to sections 29-2277 to 29-2279.</para><para>(c) If the court or magistrate determines that the offender is financially unable to pay the fines or costs, the court or magistrate:</para><para>(i) Shall either:</para><para>(A) Impose a sentence without such fines or costs; or</para><para>(B) Enter an order pursuant to subdivision (1)(d) of this section discharging the offender of such fines or costs; and</para><para>(ii) May order, as a term of the offender's sentence or as a condition of probation, that he or she complete community service for a specified number of hours pursuant to sections 29-2277 to 29-2279.</para><para>(d) An order discharging the offender of any fines or costs shall be set forth in or accompanied by a judgment entry. Such order shall operate as a complete release of such fines or costs.</para><para>(2) If the court or magistrate determines, pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, that an offender is financially unable to pay such fines or costs in one lump sum but is financially capable of paying in installments, the court or magistrate shall make arrangements suitable to the court or magistrate and to the offender by which the offender may pay in installments. The court or magistrate shall enter an order specifying the terms of such arrangements and the dates on which payments are to be made. When the judgment of conviction provides for the suspension or revocation of a motor vehicle operator's license and the court authorizes the payment of fines or costs by installments, the revocation or suspension shall be effective as of the date of judgment.</para><para>(3) As an alternative to a lump-sum payment or as an alternative or in conjunction with installment payments, the court or magistrate may deduct fines or costs from a bond posted by the offender to the extent that such bond is not otherwise encumbered by a valid lien, levy, execution, or assignment to counsel of record or the person who posted the bond.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 500, p. 833; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9142; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10167; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2207; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2206; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1010, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 966, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 370, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB722, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB259, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2019</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The court cannot require that a fine be satisfied by applying jail time served without giving the defendant an opportunity to pay the fine. State v. Holloway, 212 Neb. 426, 322 N.W.2d 818 (1982).</para><para>Exemption of certain type or class of offense from the imposition of costs is not an unconstitutional classification. State ex rel. Douglas v. Gradwohl, 194 Neb. 745, 235 N.W.2d 854 (1975).</para><para>This and following section authorize taxation of costs only in cases where a crime has been charged and there has been a conviction. Luther v. State, 85 Neb. 674, 124 N.W. 117 (1909); Speer v. State, 64 Neb. 77, 89 N.W. 624 (1902).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>