<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure"  statutenumber="29-2260.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2260.02</statuteno><catchline>Department of Health and Human
Services; administer Title IV-E state plan; Office of Probation Administration;
powers and duties.</catchline><para>The
Department of Health and Human Services, as the single state agency administering
the Title IV-E state plan, has the authority to enter into the agreement with
the Office of Probation Administration to act as a surrogate of the Department
of Health and Human Services to administer the Title IV-E state plan for children
it has placement and care authority of. The Department of Health and Human
Services as the public agency administering or supervising the administration
of the Title IV-E state plan in accordance with section 472(a)(2)(B)(ii) of
the federal Social Security Act, 42 U.S.C. 672(a)(2)(B)(ii), to obtain federal
reimbursement for allowable maintenance, administrative, and training expenses
in accordance with Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act, Public Law
96-272, Public Law 105-89, and Public Law 110-351, maintains the ultimate
responsibility to supervise the Office of Probation Administration's activities
regarding the Title IV-E requirements for eligible children served under the
agreement.</para>
<para>The Office of Probation Administration
has placement and care responsibility for juveniles in out-of-home placement,
also known as foster care, described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4)
of section 43-247. Placement and care constitutes accountability for the day-to-day
care and protection of juveniles. The responsibility of having placement and
care includes the development of an individual case plan for the juvenile,
including periodic review of the appropriateness and suitability of the plan
and the foster care placement, to ensure that proper care and services are
provided to facilitate return to the juvenile's own home or to make an alternative
placement. The case plan activities include such items as assessing family
strength and needs, identifying and using community resources, and the periodic
review and determination of continued appropriateness of placement. Placement
and care does not include rights retained by the legal custodian, including,
but not limited to, provisions and decisions surrounding education, morality,
religion, discipline, and medical care.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>