<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2202</statuteno><catchline>Verdict of guilty; judgment; when pronounced; suspension of sentence; when; bail.</catchline><para>Except as provided in sections 29-2292 to 29-2294, if the defendant has nothing to say, or if he or she shows no good and sufficient cause why judgment should not be pronounced, the court shall proceed to pronounce judgment as provided by law. The court, in its discretion, may for any cause deemed by it good and sufficient, suspend execution of sentence for a period not to exceed ninety days from the date judgment is pronounced. If the defendant is not at liberty under bail, he or she may be admitted to bail during the period of suspension of sentence as provided in section 29-901.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 496, p. 832; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9137; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10162; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2202; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2202; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 87, &#167; 2, p. 251; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB686, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Bail,</emphasis> conditions, see sections 29-901 to 29-910.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Sentence of defendant</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Suspension of execution of sentence</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Power of court</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Sentence of defendant</emphasis></para><para>Sentence vacated because defendant not present at sentencing even though his absence was by choice. State v. Ernest, 200 Neb. 615, 264 N.W.2d 677 (1978).</para><para>In absence of showing of prejudice, it is not error to sentence defendant before time for filing motion for new trial has expired. Young v. State, 155 Neb. 261, 51 N.W.2d 326 (1952).</para><para>Where conviction is had on each of separate counts charging same offense, single sentence is rendered upon all counts for one entire offense. Yeoman v. State, 81 Neb. 244, 115 N.W. 784 (1908).</para><para>Judgment imposing sentence will not be interfered with as being excessive in absence of clear abuse of discretion. Wright v. State, 45 Neb. 44, 63 N.W. 147 (1895); Morrison v. State, 13 Neb. 527, 14 N.W. 475 (1882).</para><para>Separate sentence should be passed on each count of indictment charging separate misdemeanors of same kind upon which defendant is found guilty. Burrell v. State, 25 Neb. 581, 41 N.W. 399 (1889).</para><para><emphasis>2. Suspension of execution of sentence</emphasis></para><para>Question raised but not decided as to authority of justice of peace to suspend execution of sentence beyond ninety days. Stuckey v. Rohnert, 179 Neb. 727, 140 N.W.2d 9 (1966).</para><para><emphasis>3. Power of court</emphasis></para><para>Ineffectual attempt of district court to pass judgment according to provision of law does not deprive that court of power to pass valid judgment. McCormick v. State, 71 Neb. 505, 99 N.W. 237 (1904).</para><para>Within limits fixed by statute, term of imprisonment rests with trial court. Geiger v. State, 6 Neb. 545 (1877).</para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>A sentence validly imposed takes effect from the time it is pronounced, and a subsequent, different sentence is a nullity. State v. Kinney, 217 Neb. 701, 350 N.W.2d 552 (1984).</para><para>Failure to comply with this section does not affect the jurisdiction of the court, and is not ground for release on habeas corpus. Dunham v. O'Grady, 137 Neb. 649, 290 N.W. 723 (1940).</para><para>In recording judgment, clerk should follow substantially formal language of court. Preuit v. The People, 5 Neb. 377 (1877).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>