<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id65">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id67" statutenumber="29-2521.02">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2521.02</statuteno><catchline id="id70">Criminal homicide
cases; review and analysis by Supreme Court; manner.</catchline><para>The Supreme Court shall
within a reasonable time after July 22, 1978, review and analyze all cases
involving criminal homicide committed on or after April 20, 1973. Such review
and analysis shall examine (1) the facts including mitigating
and aggravating circumstances, (2) the charges filed, (3) the crime for which defendant was convicted,
and (4) the sentence imposed.
Such review shall be updated as new criminal homicide cases occur.</para>

</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 711, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1008, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB390, &#167; 5.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The proportionality review made under the requirements of this section and sections 29-2521.01 and 29-2521.03 is limited to a comparison of the facts and circumstances of the death penalty-imposed case under review with those of all applicable cases in which the death penalty was imposed. State v. Joubert, 224 Neb. 411, 399 N.W.2d 237 (1986).</para><para>Supreme Court's review includes only those cases in which the death penalty was imposed. State v. Palmer, 224 Neb. 282, 399 N.W.2d 706 (1986).</para><para>A literal interpretation of this section would unconstitutionally encroach upon the judicial function. This section will be restricted in application to a review of cases in which the defendant in the district court was convicted of murder in the first degree. State v. Moore, 210 Neb. 457, 316 N.W.2d 33 (1982).</para><para>Sections 29-2521.01 to 29-2521.03 require the Supreme Court to review cases involving criminal homicides committed on or after April 20, 1973, in which the trial court has imposed a sentence of death. State v. Williams, 205 Neb. 56, 287 N.W.2d 18 (1979).</para><para>In adopting sections 29-2521.01 to 29-2522, the Legislature intended to establish a procedure whereby the death penalty would be applied uniformly throughout the state. The procedure does not come into play where the death penalty is not imposed. State v. Welsh, 202 Neb. 249, 275 N.W.2d 54 (1979).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
