<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id94">
<sectno id="id95" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id96" statutenumber="29-2412"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id98">29-2412</statuteno><catchline id="id99">Fine and costs;
nonpayment; commutation upon confinement; credit; amount.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever
it is made satisfactorily to appear to the district court, or to the county
judge of the proper county, after all legal means have been exhausted, that
any person who is subject to being or is confined in jail for any fine or
costs of prosecution for any criminal offense has no estate with which to
pay such fine or costs, it shall be the duty of such court or judge, on his
or her own motion or upon the motion of the person so confined, to discharge
such person from further imprisonment for such fine or costs, which discharge
shall operate as a complete release of such fine or costs.</para>
<para>(2) Nothing in this section
shall authorize any person to be discharged from imprisonment before the expiration
of the time for which he or she may be sentenced to be imprisoned, as part
of his or her punishment, or when such person shall default on a payment due
pursuant to an installment agreement arranged by the court.</para>
<para>(3) Any person held in custody
for nonpayment of a fine or costs or for default on an installment shall be
entitled to a credit on the fine, costs, or installment of ninety dollars
for each day so held. In no case shall a person held in custody for nonpayment
of a fine or costs be held in such custody for more days than the maximum
number to which he or she could have been sentenced if the penalty set by
law includes the possibility of confinement.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 528, p. 838; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9199; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10206; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2412; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2412; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 122, &#167; 2, p. 455; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 111, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 528, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 370, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 17.</para></source><annotation><para>An indigent may not be required to satisfy a fine by imprisonment. The court cannot require that a fine be satisfied by applying jail time served without giving defendant an opportunity to pay the fine or show indigency. State v. Holloway, 212 Neb. 426, 322 N.W.2d 818 (1982).</para><para>Sentence by county court that defendant was "fined sixty days in county jail" was inaccurate and was reversed with directions to resentence. Sinner v. State, 128 Neb. 759, 260 N.W. 275 (1935).</para><para>Issuance of execution to collect fine is not prerequisite to imprisonment until fine is paid. State ex rel. Marasco v. Mundell, 127 Neb. 673, 256 N.W. 519 (1934).</para><para>Prisoner, confined for nonpayment of costs, can be released only after imprisonment of at least one day for each three dollars. In re Newton, 39 Neb. 757, 58 N.W. 436 (1894); In re Dobson, 37 Neb. 449, 55 N.W. 1071 (1893).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>