<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id941"><amendatorysection statutenumber="29-2266.01" chaptername="Criminal Procedure"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2266.01</statuteno><catchline>Probation officer; probationer sentenced for misdemeanor; violations of condition of probation; duties; arrest and detention; county attorney; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever a probation officer has reasonable cause to believe that a probationer sentenced for a misdemeanor has committed or is about to commit a violation of a condition of probation, the probation officer shall either:</para><para>(a) Impose one or more administrative sanctions with the approval of his or her chief probation officer or such chief's designee. The decision to impose an administrative sanction in lieu of formal revocation proceedings rests with the probation officer and his or her chief probation officer or such chief's designee and shall be based upon the probationer's risk level, the severity of the violation, and the probationer's response to the violation. If an administrative sanction is to be imposed, the probationer shall acknowledge in writing the nature of the violation and agree upon the administrative sanction. The probationer has the right to decline to acknowledge the violation; and if he or she declines to acknowledge the violation, the probation officer shall take action pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of this section. The probation officer shall submit a written report to the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed, outlining the nature of the probation violation and the sanction imposed; or</para><para>(b) Submit a written report to the sentencing court, with a copy to the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed, outlining the nature of the probation violation and request that formal revocation proceedings be initiated against the probationer in accordance with sections 29-2267 and 29-2268.</para><para>(2) Whenever a probation officer has reasonable cause to believe that a probationer sentenced for a misdemeanor has violated or is about to violate a condition of his or her probation and that the probationer will attempt to leave the jurisdiction or will place lives or property in danger, the probation officer shall arrest the probationer without a warrant and may call on any peace officer for assistance. Whenever a probationer is arrested, with or without a warrant, he or she shall be detained in a jail or other detention facility.</para><para>(3) Immediately after arrest and detention pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the probation officer shall notify the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed and submit a written report of the reason for such arrest and of any violation of probation. After prompt consideration of such written report, the county attorney shall:</para><para>(a) Notify the probation officer and the jail or detention facility, in writing, that he or she does not intend to file a motion to revoke probation, and authorize the release of the probationer from confinement; or</para><para>(b) File with the sentencing court a motion or information to revoke probation in accordance with sections 29-2267 and 29-2268.</para><para>(4) Whenever a county attorney receives a report from a probation officer that a probationer sentenced for a misdemeanor has violated a condition of probation, the county attorney may file a motion or information to revoke probation in accordance with sections 29-2267 and 29-2268.</para><para>(5) The administrator shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 20. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>