<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2003"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2003</statuteno><catchline>Joint indictment; special venire; when required; how drawn.</catchline><para>When two or more persons have been charged together in the same indictment or information with a crime, and one or more have demanded a separate trial and had the same, and when the court is satisfied by reason of the same evidence being required in the further trial of parties to the same indictment or information, that the petit jurors from the jury panel and bystanders are incompetent, because of having heard the evidence, to sit in further causes in the same indictment or information, then the court may require the jury commissioner to draw in the same manner as described in section 25-1656 such number of names as the court may direct as a separate jury panel from which a jury may be selected, which panel shall be notified and summoned for the day and hour as ordered by the court. The jurors whose names are so drawn shall be summoned to forthwith appear before the court, and, after having been examined, such as are found qualified and have no lawful excuse for not serving as jurors shall constitute a special venire from which the court shall proceed to have a jury impaneled for the trial of the cause. The court may repeat the exercise of this power until all the parties charged in the same indictment or information have been tried.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 213; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9106; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10131; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2003; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2003; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 42. </para></source><annotation><para>If several juries are picked at one time from a single jury panel for a series of trials, examination must be allowed if requested for good reason in subsequent trials in the series to determine if any jurors should be excused for cause. State v. Myers, 190 Neb. 466, 209 N.W.2d 345 (1973).</para><para>Where separate trials are held on joint indictment or information for commission of single offense, jurors who sat in trial of one defendant are disqualified to sit in trial of others. Seaton v. State, 106 Neb. 833, 184 N.W. 890 (1921).</para><para>Section applies only when two or more persons are charged in the same indictment and one has had a separate trial. Koenigstein v. State, 101 Neb. 229, 162 N.W. 879 (1917).</para><para>Provisions of this section are not exclusive. Aabel v. State, 86 Neb. 711, 126 N.W. 316 (1910); Barber v. State, 75 Neb. 543, 106 N.W. 423 (1906); Barney v. State, 49 Neb. 515, 68 N.W. 636 (1896).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>