<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2265"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2265</statuteno><catchline>Probation; transfer or retention of jurisdiction over probationer; determination; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever an offender is placed on probation and will reside in a location outside the jurisdiction of the sentencing court, the sentencing court may:</para><para>(a) Retain jurisdiction over the probationer and the subject matter of the action; or</para><para>(b) Transfer jurisdiction over the probationer and the subject matter of the action to an appropriate court in the judicial district in which the probationer will reside.</para><para>(2) When a court determines to transfer jurisdiction under subdivision (1)(b) of this section, it shall:</para><para>(a) Obtain the concurrence of the court to which transfer is to be made;</para><para>(b) File a certified transcript of the action out of which the probationer's conviction arose with the clerk of the court to which jurisdiction is transferred; and</para><para>(c) Furnish the chief probation officer of the district in which the probationer will reside with a copy of any presentence investigation.</para><para>(3) Upon the filing of the transcript in accordance with subdivision (2)(b) of this section, the court making the transfer shall have no further jurisdiction of the subject matter of the action or over the probationer. The court to which jurisdiction is transferred shall immediately enter an order placing the transferred probationer on probation under such conditions as it may deem appropriate in accordance with the Nebraska Probation Administration Act.</para><para>(4) When a court retains jurisdiction under subdivision (1)(a) of this section and the probationer will reside in a different probation district from that of the sentencing court, the court may notify the chief probation officer in the probation district in which the probationer will reside to supervise such probationer under the terms of the probation order and in accordance with the Nebraska Probation Administration Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 680, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 529, &#167; 42. </para></source></law></legaldoc>