<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-2020"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2020</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Bill of exceptions by defendant; request; procedure; exception in capital cases.</catchline><para>Except as provided in section 29-2525 for cases when the punishment is capital, in all criminal cases when a defendant feels aggrieved by any opinion or decision of the court, he or she may order a bill of exceptions. The ordering, preparing, signing, filing, correcting, and amending of the bill of exceptions shall be governed by the rules established in such matters in civil cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 482, p. 829; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9123; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10148; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2020; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2020; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 120, &#167; 1, p. 452; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 135, &#167; 2, p. 390; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 829, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 17; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The changes made to section 29-2020 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 17, have been omitted because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election. This version of section 29-2020 is found in the 2008 Reissue of Volume 2A of the Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Error proceedings by county attorney,</emphasis> decision on appeal, see section 29-2316.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Preparation of bill of exceptions in criminal case is governed by rules governing a civil case. Benedict v. State, 166 Neb. 295, 89 N.W.2d 82 (1958).</para><para>Sufficient exceptions were taken by convicted defendant to warrant consideration of alleged errors committed at trial. Scott v. State, 121 Neb. 232, 236 N.W. 608 (1931).</para><para>Affidavits for continuance will not be considered by appellate court unless embodied in bill of exceptions. Hans v. State, 50 Neb. 150, 69 N.W. 838 (1897).</para><para>Facts of which there is no evidence or recitation in bill of exceptions, will be disregarded in Supreme Court. McCall v. State, 47 Neb. 660, 66 N.W. 635 (1896).</para><para>In capital case, want of exception will not necessarily deprive prisoner of right to new trial for prejudicial errors of court. Schlencker v. State, 9 Neb. 300, 2 N.W. 710 (1879).</para><para>Arguments of counsel on questions raised during trial and remarks of court in deciding them serve no useful place in bill of exceptions and should be omitted. Clough v. State, 7 Neb. 320 (1878).</para><para>Prisoner tried for felony is entitled to new trial on ground of prejudicial erroneous instruction, even though no objection was taken thereto. Thompson v. People, 4 Neb. 524 (1876).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>