<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2201</statuteno><catchline>Verdict of guilty; accused to be notified before sentence.</catchline><para>Before the sentence is pronounced, the defendant must be informed by the court of the verdict of the jury, and asked whether he has anything to say why judgment should not be passed against him.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 495, p. 832; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9136; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10161; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2201; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2201.</para></source><annotation><para>A sentencing court is not required to use the specific words set out in the statute in conducting an allocution as long as defendant is afforded an opportunity to offer comments as to why judgment should not be passed against him. State v. Dethlefs, 239 Neb. 943, 479 N.W.2d 780 (1992).</para><para>Sentence vacated because defendant not present at sentencing even though his absence was by choice. State v. Ernest, 200 Neb. 615, 264 N.W.2d 677 (1978).</para><para>Error held not prejudicial. State v. Brockman, 184 Neb. 435, 168 N.W.2d 367 (1969).</para><para>Court is not required to delay imposition of sentence until statutory time for filing motion for new trial has expired. Young v. State, 155 Neb. 261, 51 N.W.2d 326 (1952).</para><para>Where record fails to show affirmatively that court, before pronouncing sentence, informed defendant that he had been found guilty, and record shows nothing to contrary, presumption is such information was given. Kopp v. State, 124 Neb. 363, 246 N.W. 718 (1933); Taylor v. State, 86 Neb. 795, 126 N.W. 752 (1910).</para><para>Section is mandatory; if not complied with, cause will be remanded. Evers v. State, 84 Neb. 708, 121 N.W. 1005 (1909); McCormick v. State, 66 Neb. 337, 92 N.W. 606 (1902).</para><para>Confinement of prisoner under sentence of death, from date of sentence to day of execution, is no part of sentence. McGinn v. State, 46 Neb. 427, 65 N.W. 46 (1895).</para><para>Judge is not limited to this one question; cannot coerce answer. Tracey v. State, 46 Neb. 361, 64 N.W. 1069 (1895).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>