<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-2004"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2004</statuteno><catchline id="id00">See note regarding referendum petition following the source at the end of the section. Jury; how drawn and selected; alternate jurors.</catchline><para>(1) All parties may stipulate that the jury may be selected up to thirty-one days prior to the date of trial. The stipulation must be unanimous among all parties and evidenced by a joint stipulation to the county court.</para><para>(2) In all cases, except as may be otherwise expressly provided, the accused shall be tried by a jury drawn, summoned, and impaneled according to provisions of the code of civil procedure, except that whenever in the opinion of the court the trial is likely to be a protracted one, the court may, immediately after the jury is impaneled and sworn, direct the calling of one or two additional jurors, to be known as alternate jurors. Such jurors shall be drawn from the same source and in the same manner, and have the same qualifications as regular jurors, and be subject to examination and challenge as such jurors, except that each party shall be allowed one peremptory challenge to each alternate juror. The alternate jurors shall take the proper oath or affirmation, shall be seated near the regular jurors with equal facilities for seeing and hearing the proceedings in the cause, and shall attend at all times upon the trial of the cause in company with the regular jurors. They shall obey all orders and admonitions of the court, and if the regular jurors are ordered to be kept in the custody of an officer during the trial of the cause, the alternate jurors shall also be kept with the other jurors and shall be discharged upon the final submission of the cause to the jury. If, before the final submission of the cause a regular juror dies or is discharged, the court shall order the alternate juror, if there is but one, to take his or her place in the jury box. If there are two alternate jurors the court shall select one by lot, who shall then take his or her place in the jury box. After an alternate juror is in the jury box he or she shall be subject to the same rules as a regular juror.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 466, p. 825; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9107; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10132; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2004; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 242; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 29-2004; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2004; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1249, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, Third Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 14. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate><note>Section 29-2004 was amended by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 14. According to Article III, section 3, of the Constitution of Nebraska, the provisions of LB 268 have been suspended due to the certification by the Secretary of State of sufficient signatures on referendum petitions to suspend the taking effect of such act until the same has been approved by the electors of the state. The question will be submitted to the voters at the November 2016 general election. The prior version of section 29-2004 is found in the 2008 Reissue of Volume 2A of the Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Change of venue,</emphasis> criminal case pending in county with population of four thousand or less without adequate facilities for jury trials, see section 25-412.01.</para><para><emphasis>For drawing and selecting of jurors,</emphasis> see Chapter 25, article 16.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under this section, a court may discharge a regular juror because of sickness and replace him or her with an alternate juror. State v. Hilding, 278 Neb. 115, 769 N.W.2d 326 (2009).</para><para>In a trial for attempted murder, assault, and other crimes, a juror who was mistakenly seated on the jury despite having been stricken by the State was a "regular juror," within the meaning of this section, and thus, the juror could be replaced by an alternate when the mistake was discovered. State v. Aguilar, 268 Neb. 411, 683 N.W.2d 349 (2004).</para><para>Verdict of jury will be set aside where evidence is clearly insufficient to sustain it. Prichard v. State, 135 Neb. 522, 282 N.W. 529 (1938).</para><para>Accused cannot waive right to trial by jury. Michaelson v. Beemer, 72 Neb. 761, 101 N.W. 1007 (1904).</para><para>Challenge to array or motion to quash panel must be in writing and should point out grounds relied upon. Strong v. State, 63 Neb. 440, 88 N.W. 772 (1902).</para><para>Jurors may be summoned for trial of criminal case when no regular panel is present. Carrall v. State, 53 Neb. 431, 73 N.W. 939 (1898).</para><para>In criminal trials, jurors are not judges of the law. Parrish v. State, 14 Neb. 60, 15 N.W. 357 (1883).</para><para>Under this section, a trial court may replace a juror with an alternate juror after finding that the original juror could not be fair and impartial. State v. Smith, 13 Neb. App. 404, 693 N.W.2d 587 (2005).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>