<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2926"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2926</statuteno><catchline>Determination that treatment is not appropriate; review; procedure; no appeal.</catchline><para>(1) If the Department of Health and Human Services determines that treatment in an inpatient treatment program operated by the department is not appropriate for a convicted sex offender, the offender may request the sentencing judge to review the determination in accordance with subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) Within thirty days of the determination of the Department of Health and Human Services that the treatment in an inpatient treatment program operated by the department is not appropriate for a convicted sex offender, the offender may apply to the sentencing judge for a review of the denial of treatment. The review shall be conducted under the following rules of procedure:</para><para>(a) The court may allow each party to call witnesses on its behalf at such party's expense. Witnesses may be subpoenaed at the expense of the party calling the witness;</para><para>(b) Each party shall be allowed to be represented by counsel at such party's expense;</para><para>(c) Each party may be allowed to cross-examine adverse witnesses;</para><para>(d) The Nebraska Evidence Rules shall not apply unless expressly provided for by law, and the court may consider all evidence which in its discretion is relevant to whether the determination of the department is appropriate;</para><para>(e) The court may affirm the determination of the department, remand the matter for further proceedings, or reverse or modify the determination if such determination is unsupported by competent, material, and substantial evidence in view of the entire record as made on review or if the determination is arbitrary and capricious; and</para><para>(f) The review pursuant to this section shall not be subject to appeal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 523, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 80. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Evidence Rules,</emphasis> see section 27-1103.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>