<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2319"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2319</statuteno><catchline>Exception proceedings by prosecuting attorney; decision of district court; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The judgment of the court in any action taken under the provisions of sections 29-2317 and 29-2318 shall not be reversed nor in any manner affected when the defendant in the trial court has been placed legally in jeopardy, but in such cases the decision of the district court shall determine the law to govern in any similar case which may be pending at the time the decision is rendered, or which may thereafter arise in the district.</para><para>(2) When the decision of the district court establishes that the final order of the trial court was erroneous and that the defendant had not been placed legally in jeopardy prior to the entry of such erroneous order, the trial court may upon application of the prosecuting attorney issue its warrant for the rearrest of the defendant and the cause against the defendant shall thereupon proceed in accordance with the law as determined by the decision of the district court.</para><para>(3) The prosecuting attorney may take exception to any ruling or decision of the district court in the manner provided by sections 29-2315.01 to 29-2316.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 130, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 17, &#167; 14.</para></source><annotation>
<para>The plain language of section 43-2,106.01(2)(d) carves out an exception for delinquency cases in which jeopardy has attached. In such cases, the county attorney is limited to taking exception pursuant to the procedures of this section and sections 29-2317 and 29-2318. In re Interest of Rebecca B., 280 Neb. 137, 783 N.W.2d 783 (2010).</para>
<para>Under section 43-2,106.01(2)(d), when a county attorney files an appeal "in any case determining delinquency issues in which the juvenile has been placed legally in jeopardy," the appeal must be taken by exception 
proceedings to the district court pursuant to this section and sections 29-2317 and 29-2318. In re Interest of Rebecca B., 280 Neb. 137, 783 N.W.2d 783 (2010).</para>
<para>Separate juvenile courts are treated as county courts under this section and sections 29-2317 and 29-2318 for the purpose of exception proceedings under subsection (2)(d) of section 43-2,106.01. In re Interest of Sean H., 271 Neb. 395, 711 N.W.2d 879 (2006).</para><para>There is no statutory authorization for a city attorney representing the State to appeal a decision of a district court which reverses the decision of a county court upon appeal by a criminal defendant. State v. Jones, 264 Neb. 812, 652 N.W.2d 288 (2002).</para><para>The protections afforded by this section are no greater than or different from the double jeopardy protections afforded by the U.S. and Nebraska Constitutions. State v. Neiss, 260 Neb. 691, 619 N.W.2d 222 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>