<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id151"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2208"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2208</statuteno><catchline>Fines or costs; person financially unable to pay; hearing; determination; court or magistrate; powers; order; operate as release.</catchline><para>(1) A person who has been ordered to pay fines or costs and who has not been arrested or brought into custody as described in subdivision (1)(a) of section 29-2412 but who believes himself or herself to be financially unable to pay such fines or costs may request a hearing to determine such person's financial ability to pay such fines or costs. The hearing shall be scheduled on the first regularly scheduled court date following the date of the request. Pending the hearing, the person shall not be arrested or brought into custody for failure to pay such fines or costs or failure to appear before a court or magistrate on the due date of such fines or costs.</para><para>(2) At the hearing, the person shall have the opportunity to present information as to his or her income, assets, debts, or other matters affecting his or her financial ability to pay. Following the hearing, the court or magistrate shall determine the person's financial ability to pay the fines or costs, including his or her financial ability to pay in installments as described in section 29-2206.</para><para>(3) If the court or magistrate determines that the person is financially able to pay the fines or costs and the person refuses to pay, the court or magistrate may:</para><para>(a) Deny the person's request for relief; or</para><para>(b) Enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the person of such fines or costs and order the person to complete community service for a specified number of hours pursuant to sections 29-2277 to 29-2279.</para><para>(4) If the court or magistrate determines that the person is financially unable to pay the fines or costs, the court or magistrate:</para><para>(a) Shall either:</para><para>(i) Enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the person of such fines or costs; or</para><para>(ii) If the person is subject to an order to pay installments pursuant to section 29-2206, the court or magistrate shall either enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the person of such obligation or make any necessary modifications to the order specifying the terms of the installment payments as justice may require and that will enable the person to pay the fines or costs; and</para><para>(b) May order the person to complete community service for a specified number of hours pursuant to sections 29-2277 to 29-2279. </para><para>(5) An order discharging the person of fines or costs shall be set forth in or accompanied by a judgment entry. Such order shall operate as a complete release of such fines or costs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB259, &#167; 12. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>