<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2303</statuteno><catchline>Felony cases; appeal; custody of person convicted; escape; procedures.</catchline><para>Whenever a person shall be convicted of a felony, and the judgment shall be suspended as a result of the notice of appeal, it shall be the duty of the court to order the person so convicted into the custody of the sheriff, to be imprisoned until the appeal is disposed of, or such person is admitted to bail. If a person so convicted shall escape, the jailer or other officer from whose custody the escape was made may return to the clerk of the proper court the writ by virtue of which the convict was held in custody, with information of the escape endorsed thereon, whereupon the clerk shall issue a warrant stating such conviction, and commanding the sheriff of the county to pursue such person into any county in the state; and the sheriff shall take such person and commit him or her to the jail of the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 505, p. 834; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9174; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10181; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2303; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2303; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 722, &#167; 5. </para></source><annotation><para>This section controls the right to bail after conviction and its provisions are purely discretionary. State v. Woodward, 210 Neb. 740, 316 N.W.2d 759 (1982).</para><para>Court may in its discretion admit to bail upon showing of probable error which would call for reversal in all save exceptional cases mentioned in Constitution. Ford v. State, 42 Neb. 418, 60 N.W. 960 (1894).</para><para>Trial court has absolute discretion regarding appeal bonds. State v. Hernandez, 1 Neb. App. 830, 511 N.W.2d 535 (1993).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>