<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2007"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2007</statuteno><catchline>Challenges for cause; how tried.</catchline><para>All challenges for cause shall be tried by the court, on the oath of the person challenged, or on other evidence, and such challenge shall be made before the jury is sworn, and not afterward.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 58, &#167; 469, p. 827; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 9110; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 10135; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 29-2007; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 29-2007.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not bar examination and challenge for cause in subsequent trials in series even after jury is sworn if several juries are picked at one time from a single jury panel for a series of trials. State v. Myers, 190 Neb. 466, 209 N.W.2d 345 (1973).</para><para>All challenges for cause are decided by court. Rakes v. State, 158 Neb. 55, 62 N.W.2d 273 (1954).</para><para>In impaneling a jury, all challenges for cause are tried to the court. Lee v. State, 147 Neb. 333, 23 N.W.2d 316 (1946).</para><para>If cause of challenge is denied by juror on voir dire after accused's peremptory challenges are exhausted, accused has right to have issue tried and witnesses examined. Trobough v. State, 119 Neb. 128, 227 N.W. 443 (1929).</para><para>Decision of trial judge being based on consideration of all facts developed during examination, including appearance and actions of juror, will not be reversed unless clearly wrong. Bemis v. City of Omaha, 81 Neb. 352, 116 N.W. 31 (1908); Ward v. State, 58 Neb. 719, 79 N.W. 725 (1899).</para><para>Evidence relating to challenges to jurors cannot be considered unless settled and allowed by bill of exceptions. West v. State, 63 Neb. 257, 88 N.W. 503 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>