<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id583"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2262.06"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2262.06</statuteno><catchline>Fees; waiver; when; failure to pay; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section, whenever a district court or county court sentences an adult offender to probation, the court shall require the probationer to pay a one-time administrative enrollment fee and thereafter a monthly probation programming fee.</para><para>(2) Participants in non-probation-based programs or services in which probation personnel or probation resources are utilized pursuant to an interlocal agreement authorized by subdivision (16) of section 29-2252 and in which all or a portion of the costs of such probation personnel or such probation resources are covered by funds provided pursuant to section 29-2262.07 shall pay the one-time administrative enrollment fee described in subdivision (3)(a) of this section and the monthly probation programming fee described in subdivision (3)(c) of this section. In addition, the provisions of subsections (4), (7), and (11) of this section applicable to probationers apply to participants in non-probation-based programs or services. Any participant in a non-probation-based program or service who defaults on the payment of any such fees may, at the discretion of the court, be subject to removal from such non-probation-based program or service. This subdivision does not preclude a court or other governmental entity from charging additional local fees for participation in such non-probation-based programs and services or other similar non-probation-based programs and services.</para><para>(3) The court shall establish the administrative enrollment fee and monthly probation programming fees as follows:</para><para>(a) Adult probationers placed on either probation or intensive supervision probation and participants in non-probation-based programs or services shall pay a one-time administrative enrollment fee of thirty dollars. The fee shall be paid in a lump sum upon the beginning of probation supervision or participation in a non-probation-based program or service;</para><para>(b) Adult probationers placed on probation shall pay a monthly probation programming fee of twenty-five dollars, not later than the tenth day of each month, for the duration of probation; and</para><para>(c) Adult probationers placed on intensive supervision probation and participants in non-probation-based programs or services shall pay a monthly probation programming fee of thirty-five dollars, not later than the tenth day of each month, for the duration of probation or participation in a non-probation-based program or service.</para><para>(4) The court shall waive payment of the monthly probation programming fees in whole or in part if after a hearing a determination is made that such payment would constitute an undue hardship on the offender due to limited income, employment or school status, or physical or mental handicap. Such waiver shall be in effect only during the period of time that the probationer or participant in a non-probation-based program or service is unable to pay his or her monthly probation programming fee.</para><para>(5) If a probationer defaults in the payment of monthly probation programming fees or any installment thereof, the court may revoke his or her probation for nonpayment, except that probation shall not be revoked nor shall the offender be imprisoned for such nonpayment if the probationer is financially unable to make the payment, if he or she so states to the court in writing under oath, and if the court so finds after a hearing.</para><para>(6) If the court determines that the default in payment described in subsection (5) of this section was not attributable to a deliberate refusal to obey the order of the court or to failure on the probationer's part to make a good faith effort to obtain the funds required for payment, the court may enter an order allowing the probationer additional time for payment, reducing the amount of each installment, or revoking the fees or the unpaid portion in whole or in part.</para><para>(7) No probationer or participant in a non-probation-based program or service shall be required to pay more than one monthly probation programming fee per month. This subsection does not preclude local fees as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(8) The imposition of monthly probation programming fees in this section shall be considered separate and apart from the fees described in subdivisions (2)(m) and (o) of section 29-2262.</para><para>(9) The court may waive payment of the fees described in subdivisions (2)(m) and (o) of section 29-2262 in whole or in part if the offender has been previously found to be indigent in the case for which he or she is placed on probation or if after a hearing a determination is made that such payment would constitute an undue hardship on the offender due to limited income, employment or school status, or physical or mental handicap. Such waiver shall be in effect only during the period of time that the probationer or participant in a non-probation-based program or service is unable to pay his or her monthly probation programming fee.</para><para>(10) Any adult probationer received for supervision pursuant to section 29-2637 or the Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision shall be assessed both a one-time administrative enrollment fee and monthly probation programming fees during the period of time the probationer is actively supervised by Nebraska probation authorities.</para><para>(11) The probationer or participant in a non-probation-based program or service shall pay the fees described in this section to the clerk of the court. The clerk of the court shall remit all fees so collected to the State Treasurer for credit to the Probation Program Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB530, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision,</emphasis> see section 29-2639.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>When a court sentences a defendant to post-release supervision, it may impose any conditions of post-release supervision authorized by statute. State v. Dill, 300 Neb. 344, 913 N.W.2d 470 (2018).</para><para>Stale financial affidavits and earlier orders allowing a defendant to proceed in forma pauperis were insufficient to show the defendant's financial condition at the time he requested that the court waive payment of probation fees. State v. Jensen, 299 Neb. 791, 910 N.W.2d 155 (2018).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>