<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure"  statutenumber="29-2204.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2204.02</statuteno><catchline>Sentence for Class III, IIIA, or IV felony; court; duties; defendant under eighteen years of age; disposition.</catchline><para>(1) Except when a term of probation is required by law as provided in subsection (2) of this section or except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section, in imposing a sentence upon an offender for a Class III, IIIA, or IV felony, the court shall:</para><para>(a) Impose a determinate sentence of imprisonment within the applicable range in section 28-105; and</para><para>(b) Impose a sentence of post-release supervision, under the jurisdiction of the Office of Probation Administration, within the applicable range in section 28-105.</para><para>(2) If the criminal offense is a Class IV felony, the court shall impose a sentence of probation unless:</para><para>(a) The defendant is concurrently or consecutively sentenced to imprisonment for any felony other than another Class IV felony;</para><para>(b) The defendant has been deemed a habitual criminal pursuant to section 29-2221; or</para><para>(c) There are substantial and compelling reasons why the defendant cannot effectively and safely be supervised in the community, including, but not limited to, the criteria in subsections (2) and (3) of section 29-2260. Unless other reasons are found to be present, that the offender has not previously succeeded on probation is not, standing alone, a substantial and compelling reason.</para><para>(3) If a sentence of probation is not imposed, the court shall state its reasoning on the record, advise the defendant of his or her right to appeal the sentence, and impose a sentence as provided in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(4) For any sentence of imprisonment for a Class III, IIIA, or IV felony for an offense committed on or after August 30, 2015, imposed consecutively or concurrently with (a) a sentence for a Class III, IIIA, or IV felony for an offense committed prior to August 30, 2015, or (b) a sentence of imprisonment for a Class I, IA, IB, IC, ID, II, or IIA felony, the court shall impose an indeterminate sentence within the applicable range in section 28-105 that does not include a period of post-release supervision, in accordance with the process set forth in section 29-2204.</para><para>(5) For any sentence of imprisonment for a misdemeanor imposed consecutively or concurrently with a sentence of imprisonment for a Class III, IIIA, or IV felony for an offense committed on or after August 30, 2015, the court shall impose a determinate sentence within the applicable range in section 28-106 unless the person is also committed to the Department of Correctional Services in accordance with section 29-2204 for (a) a sentence of imprisonment for a Class III, IIIA, or IV felony committed prior to August 30, 2015, or (b) a sentence of imprisonment for a Class I, IA, IB, IC, ID, II, or IIA felony.</para><para>(6) If the defendant was under eighteen years of age at the time he or she committed the crime for which he or she was convicted, the court may, in its discretion, instead of imposing the penalty provided for the crime, make such disposition of the defendant as the court deems proper under the Nebraska Juvenile Code.</para><para>(7)(a) When imposing a determinate sentence upon an offender under this section, the court shall:</para><para>(i) Advise the offender on the record the time the offender will serve on his or her term of imprisonment before his or her term of post-release supervision assuming that no good time for which the offender will be eligible is lost;</para><para>(ii) Advise the offender on the record the time the offender will serve on his or her term of post-release supervision; and</para><para>(iii) When imposing a sentence following revocation of post-release supervision, advise the offender on the record the time the offender will serve on his or her term of imprisonment, including credit for time served, assuming that no good time for which the offender will be eligible is lost.</para><para>(b) If a period of post-release supervision is required but not imposed by the sentencing court, the term of post-release supervision shall be the minimum provided by law.</para><para>(c) If the court imposes more than one sentence upon an offender or imposes a sentence upon an offender who is at that time serving another sentence, the court shall state whether the sentences are to be concurrent or consecutive.</para><para>(d) If the offender has been sentenced to two or more determinate sentences and one or more terms of post-release supervision, the offender shall serve all determinate sentences before being released on post-release supervision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> see section 43-2,129.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>