<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-2934"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2934</statuteno><catchline>Person committed under prior law; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) Each person committed as a mentally disordered sex offender pursuant to sections 29-2911 to 29-2921 as such sections existed prior to July 15, 1992, who is being treated in a regional center or other secure public institution operated by the Department of Health and Human Services and has at least one year remaining on his or her sentence as of such date shall, within one hundred eighty days after such date, be returned to the district court which committed him or her for review and disposition consistent with the terms of this section.</para><para>(2) Each person committed to a regional center or other secure public institution operated by the Department of Health and Human Services as a mentally disordered sex offender by a court pursuant to sections 29-2911 to 29-2921 as such sections existed prior to July 15, 1992, who is in a facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services awaiting treatment as of such date shall be placed in a treatment facility operated by the Department of Health and Human Services for evaluation and treatment as soon as practical after space and staff become available. Within thirty days of such placement, the Department of Health and Human Services shall determine, based on criteria and procedures established by the Department of Health and Human Services, whether the offender will remain in the treatment program or be returned to the Department of Correctional Services to await court review or the end of his or her sentence. Within thirty days after the evaluation-and-treatment period, if the offender has at least one hundred eighty days remaining on his or her sentence, he or she shall be returned to the committing district court for review and disposition consistent with the terms of this section.</para><para>(3) The Department of Health and Human Services shall prepare and present a report and recommendations for each offender to be reviewed by the district court under subsection (1) or (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) Each person identified in subsections (1) and (2) of this section who was committed as a mentally disordered sex offender by a court after having entered a plea of guilty or nolo contendere shall, upon return to the district court, elect whether to be resentenced under the Convicted Sex Offender Act or continue his or her commitment pursuant to sections 29-2911 to 29-2921 as such sections existed prior to July 15, 1992.</para><para>(5) For each person identified in subsections (1) and (2) of this section who was committed as a mentally disordered sex offender by a court after having entered a plea of not guilty and for each person identified in subsection (4) of this section who elected to be resentenced under the act, subsections (6) and (7) of this section shall apply.</para><para>(6) If the court finds that the offender is treatable in an inpatient treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services, the offender shall be returned to or placed in such a treatment program and sections 29-2929 and 29-2930 shall apply.</para><para>(7) If the court finds that the offender is not amenable to treatment, is uncooperative in treatment, or has reached the maximum benefit of treatment in an inpatient treatment program operated by the Department of Health and Human Services but cannot be placed in an aftercare treatment program under conditions set by the court consistent with public safety, the offender shall be placed in a facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services to serve the remainder of his or her original sentence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 523, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 645, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 87. </para></source></law></legaldoc>