<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="CRIMINAL PROCEDURE" statutenumber="29-2543"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>29-2543</statuteno><catchline>Person convicted of crime sentenced to death; Supreme Court; warrant.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any person has been tried and convicted before any district court in this state, has been sentenced to death, and has had his or her sentence of death affirmed by the Supreme Court on mandatory direct review, it shall be the duty of the Supreme Court to issue a warrant, under the seal of the court, reciting therein the conviction and sentence and establishing a date for the enforcement of the sentence directed to the Director of Correctional Services, commanding him or her to proceed at the time named in the warrant. The date of execution shall be set no later than sixty days following the issuance of the warrant.</para><para>(2) Thereafter, if the initial execution date has been stayed and the original execution date has expired, the Supreme Court shall establish a new date for enforcement of the sentence upon receipt of notice from the Attorney General that the stay of execution is no longer in effect and issue its warrant to the director. The date of execution shall be set no later than sixty days following the issuance of the warrant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 268, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 31, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB36, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 35; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The repeal of section 29-2543 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 35, is not effective because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election.</note></source><annotation><para>Nebraska Supreme Court has jurisdiction to set successive execution dates and issue warrants as may be needed. State v. Joubert, 246 Neb. 287, 518 N.W.2d 887 (1994).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>