<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id84" statutenumber="29-3921"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3921</statuteno><catchline id="id87">Commission on Public Advocacy
Operations Cash Fund; created; use; investment; transfers; use.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund is created.
The fund shall be used for the operations of the commission, except that transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature
through June 30, 2011. The Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund
shall consist of money remitted pursuant to section 33-156. It is the intent
of the Legislature that the commission shall be funded solely from the fund.
Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) On July 1, 2011, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible,
the State Treasurer shall transfer one hundred thousand dollars from the Commission
on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund to the Supreme Court Education Fund.
The State Court Administrator shall use these funds to assist the juvenile
justice system in providing prefiling and diversion programming designed to
reduce excessive absenteeism and unnecessary involvement with the juvenile
justice system.</para>
<para>(3) The State Treasurer shall transfer the following amounts from the
Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund to the Court Appointed
Special Advocate Fund:</para>
<para>(a) On July 1, 2011, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible,
one hundred thousand dollars; and</para>
<para>(b) On July 1, 2012, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible,
two hundred thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(4) On July 1, 2012,
or as soon thereafter as administratively possible, the State Treasurer shall
transfer sixty thousand dollars from the Commission on Public Advocacy Operations
Cash Fund to the Nebraska State Patrol Cash Fund.</para><para>The Nebraska State Patrol shall
use such funds to contract with the University of Nebraska to study sex offender
recidivism data before and after the passage of Laws 2009, LB285, which changed
the Nebraska sex offender classification system from an evaluation of risk
assessment system to an offense-based assessment system in the attempt by
the state to comply with federal requirements under the Adam Walsh Child Protection
and Safety Act of 2006.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 646, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 108, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 659, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 760, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB961, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB969, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>