<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id177">
<sectno id="id178">Sec. 16.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id179" statutenumber="29-3921"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id181">29-3921</statuteno><catchline id="id182">Commission
on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund; created; use; investment; study of
juvenile legal defense and guardian ad litem systems.</catchline><para>The
Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund is created. The fund shall
be used for the operations of the commission,
except that transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the
direction of the Legislature through June 30, 2011. The Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund shall
consist of money remitted pursuant to section 33-156. It is the intent of
the Legislature that the commission shall be funded solely from the fund.
Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>The State Treasurer shall transfer two hundred fifty thousand
dollars from the Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund to the
University Cash Fund within fifteen days after May 1, 2008. Such funds shall
be used for a study of the juvenile legal defense and guardian ad litem systems
utilizing the University of Nebraska Public Policy Center to create, administer,
and review a Request for Proposals to select from a national search a research
consultant that is qualified to provide a methodologically sound and objective
assessment of Nebraska's juvenile justice system. The assessment shall include:
(1) Gathering of general data and information about the structure and funding
mechanisms for juvenile legal defense and guardian ad litem representation;
(2) a review of caseloads; (3) examining issues related to the timing of appointment
of counsel and guardians ad litem; (4) supervision of attorneys; (5) charging
and trying juveniles as adults; (6) frequency with which juveniles waive their
right to counsel and under what conditions they do so; (7) allocation of resources;
(8) adequacy of juvenile court facilities; (9) compensation of attorneys;
(10) supervising and training of attorneys; (11) access to investigators,
experts, social workers, and support staff; (12) access to educational officers,
teachers, educational staff, and truancy officers; (13) the relationship between
a guardian ad litem, a juvenile's legal counsel, and the judicial system with
identified educational staff regarding a juvenile's educational status; (14)
examining issues related to truancy and the relationship between the school
districts and the juvenile court system; (15) recidivism; (16) time to permanency
and time in court, especially when a guardian ad litem is appointed; and (17)
coordination of representation for those juveniles that may have been appointed
an attorney in a juvenile delinquency matter and a guardian ad litem because
of abuse or neglect. The assessment shall also highlight promising approaches
and innovative practices within the state and offer recommendations to improve
weak areas.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 646, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 108, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 659, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 760, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB961, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 16.</para><effectivedate>November 21, 2009</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>