<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3804"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3804</statuteno><catchline>Prosecutor; require prisoner's attendance; procedure.</catchline><para>The prosecutor in a city or county in which an untried indictment, information, or complaint is pending shall be entitled to have a prisoner, against whom he or she has lodged a detainer and who is serving a term of imprisonment in any facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services, made available upon presentation of a written request for temporary custody or availability to the director. The court having jurisdiction of such indictment, information, or complaint shall duly approve, record, and transmit the prosecutor's request. Upon receipt of the prosecutor's written request the director shall:</para><para>(1) Furnish the prosecutor with a certificate stating the term of commitment under which the prisoner is being held, the time already served, the time remaining to be served on the sentence, the good time earned, the time of the prisoner's parole eligibility, and any decision of the Board of Parole relating to the prisoner; and</para><para>(2) Offer to deliver temporary custody of the prisoner to the appropriate authority in the city or county where the untried indictment, information, or complaint is pending in order that speedy and efficient prosecution may be had.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 591, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>Subsection (2) of this section does not require a prosecutor to file a detainer against any prisoner, and the filing of a detainer is not required in order for a prisoner to assert his or her right to a speedy trial pursuant to section 29-3803. It is a prosecutor's receipt of the statutorily required certificate from the Director of Correctional Services pursuant to section 29-3803 or this section which triggers the 180-day period for disposition of untried charges prescribed by section 29-3805. State v. Tucker, 259 Neb. 225, 609 N.W.2d 306 (2000).</para><para>A prosecutor must lodge a detainer in order to trigger the expediting provisions of Chapter 29, article 38. Bradley v. Hopkins, 246 Neb. 646, 522 N.W.2d 394 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>