<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id935"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3529"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3529</statuteno><catchline>National Crime Prevention and Privacy Compact; Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety; compact officer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) In order to facilitate the authorized interstate exchange of criminal history record information for noncriminal justice purposes, and to implement the National Crime Prevention and Privacy Compact, 34 U.S.C. 40316, the Legislature approves and ratifies the compact. The Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety shall execute the compact on behalf of the state.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska State Patrol is the repository of criminal history record information for purposes of the compact and shall do all things necessary or incidental to carrying out the compact.</para><para>(3) The Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety or the superintendent's designee is the state's compact officer and shall administer the compact within the state. The Nebraska State Patrol may adopt and promulgates rules and regulations and establish procedures for the cooperative exchange of criminal history record information between the state and federal government for use in noncriminal justice cases.</para><para>(4) The state's ratification of the compact remains in effect until legislation is enacted which specifically renounces the compact.</para><para>(5) This compact does not affect or abridge the obligations and responsibilities of the Nebraska State Patrol under state law, including, but not limited to, the Security, Privacy, and Dissemination of Criminal History Information Act, and does not alter or amend the manner, direct or otherwise, in which the public is afforded access to criminal history record information under state law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB51, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Security, Privacy, and Dissemination of Criminal History Information Act,</emphasis> see section 29-3501.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>