<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3305</statuteno><catchline>Order; contents.</catchline><para>Any order issued under sections 29-3301 to 29-3307 shall specify (1) the character of the alleged criminal offense which is the subject of the application; (2) the specific type or types of identifying physical characteristic evidence which are sought; (3) the identity or description of the individual who may be detained for obtaining such evidence; (4) the name and official status of the peace officer or officers authorized to obtain such evidence and to effectuate any detention which may be necessary to obtain the evidence; (5) the place at which the obtaining of such evidence may be carried out; (6) that the person will be under no legal obligation to submit to any interrogation or to make any statement during the period of his appearance except that required for voice identification; (7) that the individual shall forthwith accompany the officer serving the order for the purpose of carrying out its objectives, or, in the alternative, fixing a time at which the individual shall appear for the purpose of carrying out the objectives of the order; (8) that the person, if he fails to accompany the officer, or to appear at the time fixed, as may be provided, or to otherwise comply with the provisions of the order, shall be guilty of contempt of court and punished accordingly; (9) the period of time during which the named or described individual may be detained for obtaining such evidence, which in no event shall exceed five hours; (10) the period of time, not exceeding fifteen days, during which the order shall continue in force and effect; and (11) any other conditions which the issuing judge or magistrate finds to be necessary to properly protect the rights of the individual who is to supply such evidence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 568, &#167; 5.</para></source><annotation><para>The identifying physical characteristics statutes require a showing of probable cause to believe the person seized has engaged in an articulable criminal offense before the judicial officer can issue an order to produce identifying physical characteristics. State v. Marcus, 265 Neb. 910, 660 N.W.2d 837 (2003).</para><para>When determining whether an order to produce identifying physical characteristics was based on a showing of probable cause, a court considers the totality of the circumstances. State v. Marcus, 265 Neb. 910, 660 N.W.2d 837 (2003).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>