<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3803"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3803</statuteno><catchline>Prisoner; request final disposition; director; duties.</catchline><para>Any person who is imprisoned in a facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services may request in writing to the director final disposition of any untried indictment, information, or complaint pending against him or her in this state. Upon receiving any request from a prisoner for final disposition of any untried indictment, information, or complaint, the director shall:</para><para>(1) Furnish the prosecutor with a certificate stating the term of commitment under which the prisoner is being held, the time already served on the sentence, the time remaining to be served, the good time earned, the time of the prisoner's parole eligibility, and any decision of the Board of Parole relating to the prisoner;</para><para>(2) Send by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested, one copy of the request and the certificate to the court in which the untried indictment, information, or complaint is pending and one copy to the prosecutor charged with the duty of prosecuting it; and</para><para>(3) Offer to deliver temporary custody of the prisoner to the appropriate authority in the city or county where the untried indictment, information, or complaint is pending.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 591, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>It is a prosecutor's receipt of the statutorily required certificate from the Director of Correctional Services pursuant to this section or section 29-3804 which triggers the 180-day period for disposition of untried charges prescribed by section 29-3805. State v. Tucker, 259 Neb. 225, 609 N.W.2d 306 (2000).</para><para>The statutory right of a person in the custody of the Nebraska Department of Correctional Services to a speedy trial on pending criminal charges in Nebraska is governed by sections 29-3801 to 29-3809. The denial of a speedy trial claim governed by these sections is a final, appealable order. State v. Tucker, 259 Neb. 225, 609 N.W.2d 306 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>