<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3101</statuteno><catchline>Arrest of accused person illegally in state; release; violation; warrant; documents filed; notify county attorney.</catchline><para>(a) If a person who has been charged with crime in another state and released from custody prior to final judgment, including the final disposition of any appeal, is alleged to have violated the terms and conditions of his release, and is present in this state, a designated agent of the court, judge, or magistrate which authorized the release may request the issuance of a warrant for the arrest of the person and an order authorizing his return to the demanding court, judge, or magistrate. Before the warrant is issued, the designated agent must file with a judicial officer of this state having authority under the laws of this state to issue warrants for the arrest of persons charged with crime the following documents:</para><para>(1) An affidavit stating the name and whereabouts of the person whose removal is sought, the crime with which the person was charged, the time and place of the crime charged, and the status of the proceedings against him;</para><para>(2) A certified copy of the order or other document specifying the terms and conditions under which the person was released from custody; and</para><para>(3) A certified copy of an order of the demanding court, judge, or magistrate stating the manner in which the terms and the conditions of the release have been violated and designating the affiant its agent for seeking removal of the person.</para><para>(b) Upon initially determining that the affiant is a designated agent of the demanding court, judge, or magistrate, and that there is probable cause for believing that the person whose removal is sought has violated the terms or conditions of his release, the judicial officer shall issue a warrant to a law enforcement officer of this state for the person's arrest.</para><para>(c) The judicial officer shall notify the county attorney of his action and shall direct him to investigate the case to ascertain the validity of the affidavits and documents required by subsection (a) and the identity and authority of the affiant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 228, &#167;1, p. 851. </para></source></law></legaldoc>