<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3901"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3901</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 29-3901 to 29-3908:</para><para>(1) Court shall mean a district court or a county court;</para><para>(2) Felony defendant shall mean a person who is charged by complaint, information, or indictment with or who is under arrest for investigation or on suspicion that he or she may have committed any criminal offense which may be punishable by imprisonment in a Department of Correctional Services adult correctional facility;</para><para>(3) Indigent shall mean the inability to retain legal counsel without prejudicing one's financial ability to provide economic necessities for one's self or one's family. Before a felony defendant's initial court appearance, the determination of his or her indigency shall be made by the public defender, but thereafter it shall be made by the court; and</para><para>(4) Judge shall mean a judge of the district court, a judge of the county court, or a clerk magistrate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1463, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 241, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1989), &#167; 29-1804.04; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 31, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>In determining whether a criminal defendant is indigent as the term is used in this section, a court is to consider the seriousness of the offense; the defendant's income; the availability of resources, including real and personal property, bank accounts, Social Security, and unemployment or other benefits; normal living expenses; outstanding debts; and the number and age of dependents. State v. Eichelberger, 227 Neb. 545, 418 N.W.2d 580 (1988); State v. Masilko, 226 Neb. 45, 409 N.W.2d 322 (1987).</para><para>To determine whether a defendant in a criminal case is indigent, requiring court-appointed counsel, a court must consider factors listed. State v. Richter, 225 Neb. 837, 408 N.W.2d 717 (1987).</para><para>This section defines indigency and along with section 29-1804.05 requires the court to make a reasonable inquiry as to a defendant's financial condition. To determine indigency the court must consider the seriousness of the offense; the defendant's income; the availability of other resources, including real and personal property, bank accounts, Social Security, and unemployment or other benefits; normal living expenses; outstanding debts; and the number and age of dependents. State v. Lafler, 224 Neb. 613, 399 N.W.2d 808 (1987).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>