<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-3929"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3929</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Chief counsel; duties.</catchline><para>The primary duties of the chief counsel shall be to provide direct legal services to indigent defendants, and the chief counsel shall:</para><para>(1) Supervise the operations of the appellate division, the capital litigation division, the DNA testing division, and the major case resource center;</para><para>(2) Prepare a budget and disburse funds for the operations of the commission;</para><para>(3) Present to the commission an annual report on the operations of the commission, including an accounting of all funds received and disbursed, an evaluation of the cost-effectiveness of the commission, and recommendations for improvement;</para><para>(4) Convene or contract for conferences and training seminars related to criminal defense;</para><para>(5) Perform other duties as directed by the commission;</para><para>(6) Establish and administer projects and programs for the operation of the commission;</para><para>(7) Appoint and remove employees of the commission and delegate appropriate powers and duties to them;</para><para>(8) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the management and administration of policies of the commission and the conduct of employees of the commission;</para><para>(9) Transmit monthly to the commission a report of the operations of the commission for the preceding calendar month;</para><para>(10) Execute and carry out all contracts, leases, and agreements authorized by the commission with agencies of federal, state, or local government, corporations, or persons; and</para><para>(11) Exercise all powers and perform all duties necessary and proper in carrying out his or her responsibilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 646, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 659, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 29; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The changes made to section 29-3929 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 29, have been omitted because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>