<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-3523"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3523</statuteno><catchline>Criminal history record information; notation of an arrest; dissemination; limitations; removal; expungement.</catchline><para>(1) That part of criminal history record information consisting of a notation of an arrest, described in subsection (3) of this section, shall not be disseminated to persons other than criminal justice agencies after the expiration of the periods described in subsection (3) of this section except as provided in subsection (2) of this section and except when the subject of the record:</para><para>(a) Is currently the subject of prosecution or correctional control as the result of a separate arrest;</para><para>(b) Is currently an announced candidate for or holder of public office;</para><para>(c) Has made a notarized request for the release of such record to a specific person; or</para><para>(d) Is kept unidentified, and the record is used for purposes of surveying or summarizing individual or collective law enforcement agency activity or practices, or the dissemination is requested consisting only of release of criminal history record information showing (i) dates of arrests, (ii) reasons for arrests, and (iii) the nature of the dispositions including, but not limited to, reasons for not prosecuting the case or cases.</para><para>(2) That part of criminal history record information consisting of a notation of an arrest, described in subsection (3) of this section, may be disseminated to individuals and agencies for the express purpose of research, evaluative, or statistical activities pursuant to an agreement with a criminal justice agency that specifically authorizes access to the information, limits the use of the information to research, evaluative, or statistical activities, and ensures the confidentiality and security of the information.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsections (1) and (2) of this section, the notation of arrest shall be removed from the public record as follows:</para><para>(a) In the case of an arrest for which no charges are filed as a result of the determination of the prosecuting attorney, the arrest shall not be part of the public record after one year from the date of arrest;</para><para>(b) In the case of an arrest for which charges are not filed as a result of a completed diversion, the arrest shall not be part of the public record after two years from the date of arrest; and</para><para>(c) In the case of an arrest for which charges are filed, but dismissed by the court on motion of the prosecuting attorney or as a result of a hearing not the subject of a pending appeal, the arrest shall not be part of the public record after three years from the date of arrest.</para><para>(4) Any person arrested due to the error of a law enforcement agency may file a petition with the district court for an order to expunge the criminal history record information related to such error. The petition shall be filed in the district court of the county in which the petitioner was arrested. The county attorney shall be named as the respondent and shall be served with a copy of the petition. The court may grant the petition and issue an order to expunge such information if the petitioner shows by clear and convincing evidence that the arrest was due to error by the arresting law enforcement agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 713, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 782, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 856, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB470, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 73. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (2)(c) of this section, which requires that the notation of a person's arrest be removed from the record if the charges are later dismissed, the person arrested may file a petition seeking to enforce his or her right to have his or her record expunged. State v. Blair, 17 Neb. App. 611, 767 N.W.2d 143 (2009).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>