<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="29-3920"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>29-3920</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Legislative findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(1) County property owners should be given some relief from the obligation of providing mandated indigent defense services which in most instances are required because of state laws establishing crimes and penalties;</para><para>(2) Property tax relief can be accomplished if the state begins to assist the counties with the obligation of providing indigent defense services required by state laws establishing crimes and penalties;</para><para>(3) Property tax relief in the form of state assistance to the counties of Nebraska in providing for indigent defense services will also increase accountability because the state, which is the governmental entity responsible for passing criminal statutes, will likewise be responsible for paying some of the costs;</para><para>(4) Property tax relief in the form of state assistance to the counties of Nebraska in providing for indigent defense services will also improve inconsistent and inadequate funding of indigent defense services by the counties;</para><para>(5) Property tax relief in the form of state assistance to the counties of Nebraska in providing for indigent defense services will also lessen the impact on county property taxpayers of the cost of a high profile death penalty case which can significantly affect the finances of the counties; and</para><para>(6) To accomplish property tax relief in the form of the state assisting the counties of Nebraska in providing for indigent defense services, the Commission on Public Advocacy Operations Cash Fund should be established to fund the operation of the Commission on Public Advocacy and to fund reimbursement requests as determined by section 29-3933.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 646, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 760, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 26; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The changes made to section 29-3920 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 26, have been omitted because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election. This version of section 29-3920 is found in the 2008 Reissue of Volume 2A of the Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>