<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id655"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4803"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4803</statuteno><catchline>Veteran justice program; created; use of deferred judgments; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The probation administrator shall create a veteran justice program as provided in sections 29-4802 to 29-4804 and subject to the Supreme Court's rules. The program shall be available in every district court and county court. A veteran justice program shall not supersede, alter, or otherwise interfere with the establishment, functioning, participation, or operation of a problem solving court established pursuant to section 24-1302.</para><para>(2) A veteran justice program shall be operated by use of deferred judgments as provided in this section.</para><para>(3) Upon a finding of guilt for which a judgment of conviction may be rendered, a defendant that is eligible to participate in a veteran justice program may request the court defer the entry of judgment of conviction under this section. Upon such request, the court shall provide notice to any victim of the offense of the request and provide an opportunity for the victim to provide a statement for consideration by the court. After giving the prosecutor and defendant the opportunity to be heard, the court may defer the entry of a judgment of conviction and the imposition of a sentence and place the defendant on probation, upon conditions as the court may require under sections 29-2262 and 29-4804. If the court defers the entry of judgment, the court shall provide notice to victims of the offense.</para><para>(4)(a) Whenever a court considers a request to defer judgment under this section, the court shall consider the following:</para><para>(i) The factors set forth in subsections (2) and (3) of section 29-2260 and section 29-4802;</para><para>(ii) The supervision, treatment, and other programming options available in the community; and</para><para>(iii) Any other information the court deems relevant.</para><para>(b) Except as provided in subdivision (4)(c) of this section, there shall be a presumption that a veteran eligible under section 29-4802 shall be allowed to participate in a veteran justice program. The presumption shall only be overcome by a judicial finding, based on an individualized assessment of the veteran and consideration of the factors set forth in subdivisions (4)(a)(i), (ii), and (iii) of this section, that entry of judgment of conviction should not be deferred. The fact that a veteran has previously absconded from or violated pretrial release, probation, parole, supervised release, post-release supervision, or another form of court-ordered supervision, including a violation arising from commission of a new offense or an offense committed while previously participating in a veteran justice program, is not, standing alone, a sufficient basis to overcome the presumption.</para><para>(c) The presumption provided for in subdivision (4)(b) of this section does not apply to a veteran charged with:</para><para>(i) A violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197, or a city or village ordinance enacted in conformance with section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197, following a previous conviction for a violation of any such section or ordinance; or</para><para>(ii) An offense that resulted in serious bodily injury to another person.</para><para>(5) Except as otherwise provided in this section and sections 29-2293 and 29-2294, the supervision of a defendant on probation pursuant to a deferred judgment shall be governed by the Nebraska Probation Administration Act and sections 29-2270 to 29-2273.</para><para>(6) After a hearing providing the prosecutor and defendant an opportunity to be heard and upon a finding that a defendant has violated a condition of his or her probation, the court may enter any order authorized by section 29-2268 or pronounce judgment and impose such new sentence as might have been originally imposed for the offense for which the defendant was convicted.</para><para>(7) Upon satisfactory completion of the conditions of probation and the payment or waiver of all administrative and programming fees assessed under section 29-2293, the defendant or prosecutor may file a motion to withdraw any plea entered by the defendant and to dismiss the action without entry of judgment. The court shall not grant such motion until a victim of the offense has received notice and the opportunity to be heard, as required by subsection (4) of section 29-4804.</para><para>(8) Sections 29-4802 to 29-4804 apply to offenses committed on or after July 1, 2025. For purposes of this subsection, an offense shall be deemed to have been committed prior to July 1, 2025, if any element of the offense occurred prior to such date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB253, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Probation Administration Act,</emphasis> see section 29-2269.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>