<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id24"  statutenumber="29-4004"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id26">29-4004</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Registration;
location; sheriff; duties; Nebraska State Patrol; duties; name-change order; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) Any person subject to the Sex Offender Registration Act
shall register within three working days after becoming subject to the act
at a location designated by the Nebraska State Patrol for purposes of accepting
such registration.</para>
<para>(2) Any person required to register under the act shall inform
the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides, in person, and complete
a form as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose, if he
or she has a new address, temporary domicile, or habitual living location,
within three working days before the change. The sheriff shall submit such
information to the sex offender registration and community notification division
of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner prescribed
by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para>
<para>(3) Any person required to register under the act shall inform
the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides, in person, and complete
a form as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose, if he
or she has a new address, temporary domicile, or habitual living location
 in a different county in this state, within three working days before the
address change. The sheriff shall submit such information to the sex offender
registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol
on the day it is received and in a manner as prescribed by the Nebraska State
Patrol for such purpose. If the change in address, temporary domicile, or
habitual living location is to a location within the State of Nebraska, the
division shall notify the sheriff of each affected county of the new address,
temporary domicile, or habitual living location, within three working days.
The person shall report to the county sheriff of his or her new county of
residence and register with such county sheriff within three working days
after the address change.</para>
<para>(4) Any person required to register under the act shall inform
the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides, in person, and complete
a form as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose, if he
or she moves to a new out-of-state address, within three working days before
the address change. The sheriff shall submit such information to the sex offender
registration and community notification
division of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner
as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose. If the change
in address, temporary domicile, or habitual living location is to a location
outside of the State of Nebraska, the division shall notify the sheriff of
each affected county in Nebraska and the other state's, country's, or territory's
central repository for sex offender registration of the new out-of-state address,
temporary domicile, or habitual living location, within three working days.</para>
<para>(5) Any person required to register under the act who is employed,
carries on a vocation, or attends school shall inform, in person, the sheriff
of the county in which he or she is employed, carries on a vocation, or attends
school and complete a form as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for
such purpose, within three working days after becoming employed, carrying
on a vocation, or attending school. The person shall also notify the sheriff,
in person, of any changes in employment, vocation, or school of attendance,
and complete a form as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose,
within three working days after the change. The sheriff shall submit such
information to the sex offender registration and community notification division
of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner as
prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para>
<para>(6) Any person required to register under the act who is residing,
has a temporary domicile, or is habitually living in another state, and is
employed, carries on a vocation, or attends school in this state, shall report
and register, in person,  with the sheriff of the county in which he or she
is employed, carries on a vocation, or attends school in this state and complete
a form as prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose, within
three working days after becoming employed, carrying on a vocation, or attending
school. The person shall also notify the sheriff of any changes in employment,
vocation, or school of attendance, in person, and complete a form as prescribed
by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose, within three working days after
the change. The sheriff shall submit such information to the sex offender
registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol
on the day it is received and in a manner as prescribed by the Nebraska State
Patrol for such purpose. For purposes of this subsection:</para>
<para>(a) Attends school means enrollment in any educational institution
in this state on a full-time or part-time basis; and</para>
<para>(b) Is employed or carries on a vocation means any full-time
or part-time employment, with or without compensation, which lasts for a duration
of more than fourteen days or for an aggregate period exceeding thirty days
in a calendar year.</para>
<para>(7) Any person incarcerated for a registrable offense under
section 29-4003 in a jail, penal or correctional facility, or other public
or private institution shall be registered by the jail, penal or correctional
facility, or public or private institution prior to his or her discharge,
parole, furlough, work release, or release. The person shall be informed and
information shall be obtained as required in section 29-4006.</para>
<para>(8) Any person required to register or who is registered under
the act, but is incarcerated for more than three working days, shall inform
the sheriff of the county in which he or she is incarcerated, in writing,
within three working days after incarceration, of his or her incarceration
and his or her expected release date, if any such date is available. The sheriff
shall forward the information regarding incarceration to the sex offender
registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol
immediately on the day on which it was received and in a manner prescribed
by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para>
<para>(9) Any person required to register or who is registered under
the act who no longer has a residence, temporary domicile, or habitual living
location shall report such change in person to the sheriff of the county in
which he or she is located, within three working days after such change in
residence, temporary domicile, or habitual living location. Such person shall
update his or her registration, in person, to the sheriff of the county in
which he or she is located, on a form approved by the sex offender registration
and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol at least
once every thirty calendar days during the time he or she remains without
residence, temporary domicile, or habitual living location.</para>
<para>(10) Each registering entity shall forward all written information,
photographs, and fingerprints obtained pursuant to the act to the sex offender
registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol
on the day it is received and in a manner prescribed by the Nebraska State
Patrol for such purpose. The information shall be forwarded on forms furnished
by the division. The division shall maintain a central registry of sex offenders
required to register under the act. Any collected DNA samples shall be forwarded
to the State DNA Data Base.</para>
<para>(11) The sex
offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska
State Patrol shall determine whether a name-change order received from the
clerk of a district court pursuant to section 25-21,271 is for a person in
the central registry of sex offenders and, if so, shall include the changed
name with the former name in the registry, file or cross-reference the information
under both names, and notify the sheriff of the county in which such person
then resides.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 645, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 564, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 713, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB285, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB147, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>