<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4116</statuteno><catchline>Act, how cited.</catchline><para>Sections 29-4116 to 29-4125 shall be known and may be cited as the DNA Testing Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 659, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>In enacting the DNA Testing Act, the Legislature intended to provide (1) an extraordinary remedy&#8212;—vacation of the judgment&#8212;—for the compelling circumstance in which actual innocence is conclusively established by DNA testing and (2) an ordinary remedy—&#8212;a new trial&#8212;—for circumstances in which newly discovered DNA evidence would have, if available at the former trial, probably produced a substantially different result. State v. Parmar, 283 Neb. 247, 808 N.W.2d 623 (2012).</para><para>Postconviction DNA evidence probably would have produced a substantially different result at trial if the evidence (1) tends to create a reasonable doubt about the defendant’'s guilt and (2) does not merely impeach or contradict a key eyewitness'’ testimony, but is probative of a factual situation different from that to which the witness testified. State v. Parmar, 283 Neb. 247, 808 N.W.2d 623 (2012).</para><para>To warrant an order vacating a judgment of conviction under the DNA Testing Act, the movant must present DNA testing results that, when considered with the evidence presented at the trial leading to conviction, show a complete lack of evidence to establish an essential element of the crime charged. But to warrant an order for a new trial under the DNA Testing Act, the movant must present DNA testing results that probably would have produced a substantially different result if the evidence had been offered and admitted at the movant'’s trial. State v. Parmar, 283 Neb. 247, 808 N.W.2d 623 (2012).</para><para>An action under the DNA Testing Act is a collateral attack on a conviction and is therefore similar to a postconviction action and is not part of the criminal proceeding itself. State v. Pratt, 273 Neb. 817, 733 N.W.2d 868 (2007).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>