<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id698"><amendatorysection statutenumber="29-4704" chaptername="Criminal Procedure"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4704</statuteno><catchline>Disclosures required; deadline; redaction of information; prosecutor; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, if a prosecutor intends to use the testimony or statement of a jailhouse informant at a defendant's trial, the prosecutor shall disclose to the defense:</para><para>(a) The known criminal history of the jailhouse informant;</para><para>(b) Any benefit requested by or offered or provided to a jailhouse informant or that may be offered or provided to the jailhouse informant in the future in connection with such testimony;</para><para>(c) The specific statements allegedly made by the defendant against whom the jailhouse informant will testify or provide a statement and the time, place, and manner of the defendant's disclosures;</para><para>(d) The case name and jurisdiction of any criminal case known to the prosecutor in which the jailhouse informant testified or a prosecutor intended to have the jailhouse informant testify about statements made by another suspect or criminal defendant that were disclosed to the jailhouse informant and whether the jailhouse informant requested, was offered, or received any benefit in exchange for or subsequent to such testimony; and</para><para>(e) Any occasion known to the prosecutor in which the jailhouse informant recanted testimony about statements made by another suspect or defendant that were disclosed to the jailhouse informant and any transcript or copy of such recantation.</para><para>(2) The prosecutor shall disclose the information described in subsection (1) of this section to the defense as soon as practicable after discovery, but no later than thirty days before trial. If the prosecutor seeks to introduce the testimony of a jailhouse informant that was not known until after such deadline, or if the information described in subsection (1) of this section could not have been discovered or obtained by the prosecutor with the exercise of due diligence at least thirty days before the trial or other criminal proceeding, the court may permit the prosecutor to disclose the information as soon as is practicable after the thirty-day period.</para><para>(3) If the court finds by clear and convincing evidence that disclosing information listed in subsection (1) of this section will result in the possibility of bodily harm to a jailhouse informant or that a jailhouse informant will be coerced, the court may permit the prosecutor to redact some or all of such information.</para><para>(4) If, at any time subsequent to the deadline in subsection (2) of this section, the prosecutor discovers additional material required to be disclosed under subsection (1) of this section, the prosecutor shall promptly:</para><para>(a) Notify the court of the existence of the additional material; and</para><para>(b) Disclose such material to the defense, except as provided in subsection (3) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB352, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>