<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4108" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4108</statuteno><catchline>DNA samples and DNA records; confidentiality.</catchline><para>(1) All DNA samples and DNA records submitted to the State DNA Sample Bank or the State DNA Data Base are confidential except as otherwise provided in the DNA Identification Information Act. The Nebraska State Patrol shall make DNA records in the State DNA Data Base available:</para><para>(a) To law enforcement agencies and forensic DNA laboratories which serve such agencies and which participate in the Combined DNA Index System; and</para><para>(b) Upon written or electronic request and in furtherance of an official investigation of a criminal offense or offender or suspected offender.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska State Patrol shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the methods of obtaining information from the State DNA Data Base and the Combined DNA Index System and procedures for verification of the identity and authority of the requester.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska State Patrol may, for good cause shown, revoke or suspend the right of a forensic DNA laboratory in this state to have access to or submit records to the State DNA Data Base.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this subsection, person means a law enforcement agency, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, any forensic DNA laboratory, or person. No records or DNA samples shall be provided to any person unless such person enters into a written agreement with the Nebraska State Patrol to comply with the provisions of section 29-4109 relative to expungement, when notified by the Nebraska State Patrol that expungement has been granted. Every person shall comply with the provisions of section 29-4109 within ten calendar days of receipt of such notice and certify in writing to the Nebraska State Patrol that such compliance has been effectuated. The Nebraska State Patrol shall provide notice of such certification to the person who was granted expungement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 278, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 385, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB106, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>