<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id56">
<sectno id="id57" opdate="May 30, 2009">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id58" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="29-4003"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id60">29-4003</statuteno><catchline id="id61">Applicability
of act.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Sex Offender Registration
Act applies to any person who
on or after January 1, 1997:</para>
<para>(i) Has ever pled guilty to, pled nolo contendere to, or been found guilty of any of the following:</para>
<para>(A) Kidnapping of a minor
pursuant to section 28-313, except when the person is the parent of the minor
and was not convicted of any other offense in this section;</para>
<para>(B) False imprisonment of
a minor pursuant to section 28-314 or 28-315;</para>
<para>(C) Sexual assault pursuant
to section 28-319 or 28-320;</para>
<para>(D) Sexual assault of a child
in the second or third degree pursuant to section 28-320.01;</para>
<para>(E) Sexual assault of a child
in the first degree pursuant to section 28-319.01;</para>
<para>(F) Sexual abuse of
a vulnerable adult pursuant to subdivision (1)(c) of section 28-386;</para>
<para>(G) Incest of a minor pursuant
to section 28-703;</para>
<para>(H) Pandering of a minor pursuant
to section 28-802;</para>
<para>(I) Visual depiction of sexually
explicit conduct of a child pursuant to section 28-1463.03 or 28-1463.05;</para>
<para>(J) Knowingly possessing any
visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct which has a child as one of
its participants or portrayed observers pursuant to section 28-813.01;</para>
<para>(K) Criminal child enticement
pursuant to section 28-311;</para>
<para>(L) Child enticement by means
of an electronic communication device pursuant to section 28-320.02;</para>
<para>(M) Debauching a minor pursuant
to section 28-805; or</para>
<para>(N) Attempt, solicitation, aiding or abetting, being an accessory, or
conspiracy to commit an offense listed in subdivisions (1)(a)(i)(A) through (1)(a)(i)(M) of this section;</para>
<para>(ii)
Has ever pled guilty to,
pled nolo contendere to, or been
found guilty of any offense that is substantially equivalent to a registrable
offense under subdivision (1)(a)(i) of this section
by any village, town, city, state,
territory, commonwealth, or other jurisdiction of the United States, by the
United States Government, by
court-martial or other military tribunal, or
by a foreign jurisdiction, notwithstanding a procedure comparable
in effect to that described under section 29-2264 or any other procedure to
nullify a conviction other than by pardon;</para>
<para>(iii) Is incarcerated in a
jail, a penal or correctional facility, or any other public or private institution
or is under probation or parole as a result of pleading guilty to or being
found guilty of a registrable offense under subdivision (1)(a)(i)
or (ii) of this section prior to January 1, 1997; or</para>
<para>(iv) Enters the state and
is required to register as a sex offender under the laws of another village, town, city, state,
territory, commonwealth, or other jurisdiction of the United States.</para>
<para>(b) In addition
to the registrable offenses under subdivision (1)(a) of this section, the
Sex Offender Registration Act applies to any person who on or after January
1, 2010:</para><para>(i)(A) Except as provided in subdivision (1)(b)(i)(B) of this section,
has ever pled guilty to, pled nolo contendere to, or been found guilty of
any of the following:</para><para>(I) Murder in the first degree pursuant to section 28-303;</para>
<para>(II) Murder
in the second degree pursuant to section 28-304;</para><para>(III) Manslaughter pursuant
to section 28-305;</para><para>(IV) Assault in the first degree pursuant to section 28-308;</para>
<para>(V) Assault
in the second degree pursuant to section 28-309;</para><para>(VI) Assault in the third
degree pursuant to section 28-310;</para><para>(VII) Stalking pursuant to section 28-311.03;</para>
<para>(VIII) Unlawful
intrusion on a minor pursuant to section 28-311.08;</para><para>(IX) Kidnapping pursuant
to section 28-313;</para><para>(X) False imprisonment pursuant to section 28-314 or 28-315;</para>
<para>(XI) Sexual
abuse of an inmate or parolee in the first degree pursuant to section 28-322.02;</para>
<para>(XII) Sexual
abuse of an inmate or parolee in the second degree pursuant to section 28-322.03;</para>
<para>(XIII) Sexual
abuse of a protected individual pursuant to section 28-322.04;</para>
<para>(XIV) Incest
pursuant to section 28-703;</para><para>(XV) Child abuse pursuant to subdivision
(1)(d) or (e) of section 28-707;</para><para>(XVI) Enticement by electronic communication
device pursuant to section 28-833; or</para><para>(XVII) Attempt, solicitation, aiding or
abetting, being an accessory, or conspiracy to commit an offense listed in
subdivisions (1)(b)(i)(A)(I) through (1)(b)(i)(A)(XVI) of this section.</para><para>(B) In order for the Sex Offender Registration Act to apply to
the offenses listed in subdivisions (1)(b)(i)(A)(I), (II), (III), (IV), (V),
(VI), (VII), (IX), and (X) of this section, a court shall have found that
evidence of sexual penetration or sexual contact, as those terms are defined
in section 28-318, was present in the record, which shall include consideration
of the factual basis for a plea-based conviction and information contained
in the presentence report;</para><para>(ii) Has ever pled guilty to, pled nolo
contendere to, or been found guilty of any offense that is substantially equivalent
to a registrable offense under subdivision (1)(b)(i) of this section by any
village, town, city, state, territory, commonwealth, or other jurisdiction
of the United States, by the United States Government, by court-martial or
other military tribunal, or by a foreign jurisdiction, notwithstanding a procedure
comparable in effect to that described under section 29-2264 or any other
procedure to nullify a conviction other than by pardon; or</para>
<para>(iii) Enters
the state and is required to register as a sex offender under the laws of
another village, town, city, state, territory, commonwealth, or other jurisdiction
of the United States.</para><para>(2) A person appealing a conviction of a registrable
offense under this section shall be required to comply with the act during
the appeals process.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 645, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 564, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 943, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 713, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB285, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>