<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4304</statuteno><catchline>Confidential communications; waiver; sections, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) A victim does not waive the protections afforded by sections 29-4301 to 29-4304 by testifying in court about the offense, except that:</para><para>(a) If the victim partially discloses the contents of a confidential communication in the course of testifying, then either party may request the court to rule that justice requires the protections afforded by sections 29-4301 to 29-4304 be waived to the extent the protections apply to that portion of the confidential communication; and</para><para>(b) Any waiver shall apply only to the extent necessary to require any witness to respond to counsel's questions concerning a confidential communication that is relevant to the case.</para><para>(2) An advocate cannot waive the protections afforded a victim under sections 29-4301 to 29-4304. However, if a victim brings suit against an advocate or the agency, business, or organization in which the advocate was employed or served as a volunteer at the time of the advocacy relationship, the advocate may testify or produce records regarding confidential communications with the victim and is not in violation of sections 29-4301 to 29-4304.</para><para>(3) Sections 29-4301 to 29-4304 shall not relieve an advocate of any duty to report suspected adult abuse or neglect as required by section 28-372 or suspected child abuse or neglect as required by section 28-711 or any other legal duty to report a criminal or unlawful act.</para><para>(4) Sections 29-4301 to 29-4304 shall not be construed to limit any other testimonial privilege available to any person under the laws of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 613, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>