<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id186"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4315"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4315</statuteno><catchline>Explanation of rights; required, when; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Upon an initial interaction with a victim relating to or arising from a sexual assault of such victim, a health care provider or peace officer, and in the case of a victim under eighteen years of age, the Department of Health and Human Services, shall provide the victim with information that explains the rights of victims under the Sexual Assault Victims' Bill of Rights Act and other relevant law. The information shall be presented in clear language that is comprehensible to a person proficient in English at the fifth grade level, accessible to persons with visual disabilities, and available in all major languages spoken in this state. This information shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) A clear statement that a victim is not required to participate in the criminal justice system or to undergo a medical evidentiary or physical examination in order to retain the rights provided by the act and other relevant law;</para><para>(b) Contact information for appropriate services provided by professionals in the fields of domestic violence and sexual assault, including advocates;</para><para>(c) State and federal relief available to victims of crime;</para><para>(d) Law enforcement protection available to the victim, including domestic violence protection orders, harassment protection orders, and sexual assault protection orders and the process to obtain such protection;</para><para>(e) Instructions for requesting information regarding the victim's sexual assault forensic evidence as provided in section 29-4313; and</para><para>(f) State and federal compensation funds for medical and other costs associated with the sexual assault and information on any municipal, state, or federal right to restitution for a victim in the event of a conviction.</para><para>(2) The information to be provided under subsection (1) of this section shall be developed by the Attorney General and the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice with input from prosecutors, sexual assault victims, and organizations with a statewide presence with expertise on domestic violence, sexual assault, and child sexual assault.</para><para>(3) The information to be provided under subsection (1) of this section shall be made available for viewing and download on the websites of the Department of Health and Human Services and the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice. Other relevant state agencies are also encouraged to make such information available on their websites.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB43, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>