<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id266"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4309"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4309</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For the purposes of the Sexual Assault Victims' Bill of Rights Act:</para><para>(1)(a) Advocate means:</para><para>(i) Any employee or supervised volunteer of a domestic violence and sexual assault victim assistance program or of any other agency, business, or organization that is not affiliated with a law enforcement or prosecutor's office, whose primary purpose is assisting domestic violence and sexual assault victims. This includes employees or supervised volunteers of an Indian tribe or a postsecondary educational institution;</para><para>(ii) A representative from a victim and witness assistance center as established in sections 81-1845 to 81-1847 or a similar entity affiliated with a law enforcement agency or prosecutor's office; or</para><para>(iii) An advocate who is employed by a child advocacy center that meets the requirements of subsection (2) of section 28-728.</para><para>(b) If reasonably possible, an advocate shall speak the victim's preferred language or use the services of a qualified interpreter;</para><para>(2) Health care provider means any individual who is licensed, certified, or registered to perform specified health services consistent with state law;</para><para>(3) Sexual assault means a violation of section 28-319, 28-319.01, 28-320, 28-320.01, 28-320.02, 28-322.01, 28-322.02, 28-322.03, 28-322.04, 28-322.05, 28-703, or 28-1463.03, sex trafficking or sex trafficking of a minor under section 28-831, or subdivision (1)(c) or (g) of section 28-386 or subdivision (1)(d), (e), or (f) of section 28-707;</para><para>(4) Sexual assault forensic evidence means evidence collected by a health care provider contained within any sexual assault forensic evidence collection kit, including a toxicology kit, or any forensic evidence collected by law enforcement through the course of an investigation; and</para><para>(5)(a) Sexual assault victim or victim means any person who is a victim of sexual assault who reports such sexual assault:</para><para>(i) To a health care provider, law enforcement, or an advocate, including anonymous reporting as provided in section 28-902; and</para><para>(ii) In the case of a victim who is under eighteen years of age, to the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(b) Sexual assault victim or victim also includes, if the victim described in subdivision (5)(a) of this section is incompetent, deceased, or a minor who is unable to consent to counseling services, such victim's parent, guardian, or spouse, unless such person is the reported assailant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB43, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>