<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Criminal Procedure" id="id106"  statutenumber="29-4006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4006</statuteno><catchline id="id109">Registration format; contents; verification; name change; duties; information provided to sheriff; violation; warrant.</catchline><para>(1) Registration information required by the Sex Offender Registration Act shall be entered into a database in a format approved by the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol and shall include, but not be limited to, the following information:</para><para>(a) The legal name and all aliases which the person has used or under which the person has been known;</para><para>(b) The person's date of birth and any alias dates of birth;</para><para>(c) The person's social security number;</para><para>(d) The address of each residence at which the person resides, has a temporary domicile, has a habitual living location, or will reside;</para><para>(e) The name and address of any place where the person is an employee or will be an employee, including work locations without a single worksite;</para><para>(f) The name and address of any place where the person is a student or will be a student;</para><para>(g) The license plate number and a description of any vehicle owned or operated by the person and its regular storage location;</para><para>(h) The person's motor vehicle operator's license number, including the person's valid motor vehicle operator's license or state identification card submitted for photocopying;</para><para>(i) The person's original travel and immigration documents submitted for photocopying;</para><para>(j) The person's original professional licenses or certificates submitted for photocopying;</para><para>(k) The person's telephone numbers;</para><para>(l) A physical description of the person;</para><para>(m) A digital link to the text of the provision of law defining the criminal offense or offenses for which the person is registered under the act;</para><para>(n) Access to the criminal history of the person, including the date of all arrests and convictions, the status of parole, probation, or supervised release, registration status, and the existence of any outstanding arrest warrants for the person;</para><para>(o) A current photograph of the person;</para><para>(p) A set of fingerprints and palm prints of the person; and</para><para>(q) A DNA sample of the person.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 29-4005, the registration information shall be verified as provided in subsections (3), (4), and (5) of this section for the duration of the registration period. The person shall appear in person for such verification at the office of the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides, has a temporary domicile, or is habitually living for purposes of accepting verifications and shall have his or her photograph and fingerprints taken upon request of verification personnel.</para><para>(3) A person required to register under the act for fifteen years shall report every twelve months in the month of his or her birth, in person, to the office of the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides for purposes of accepting verifications, regardless of the original registration month. The sheriff shall submit such verification information to the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para><para>(4) A person required to register under the act for twenty-five years shall report, in person, every six months to the office of the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides for purposes of accepting verification. The person shall report, in person, in the month of his or her birth and in the sixth month following the month of his or her birth, regardless of the original registration month. The sheriff shall submit such verification information to the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para><para>(5) A person required to register under the act for life shall report, in person, every three months to the office of the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides for purposes of accepting verification. The person shall report, in person, in the month of his or her birth and every three months following the month of his or her birth, regardless of the original registration month. The sheriff shall submit such verification information to the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para><para>(6) The verification form shall be signed by the person required to register under the act and state whether the address last reported to the division is still correct.</para><para>(7) Upon receipt of registration and confirmation of the registry requirement, the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol shall notify the person by certified mail of his or her registry duration and verification schedule.</para><para>(8) If the person required to register under the act fails to report in person as required in subsection (3), (4), or (5) of this section, the person shall be in violation of this section.</para><para>(9) If the person required to register under the act falsifies the registration or verification information or form or fails to provide or timely update law enforcement of any of the information required to be provided by the Sex Offender Registration Act, the person shall be in violation of this section.</para><para>(10) The verification requirements of a person required to register under the act shall not apply during periods of such person's incarceration or inpatient civil commitment. Verification shall be resumed as soon as such person is placed on any type of supervised release, parole, or probation or outpatient civil commitment or is released from incarceration or civil commitment. Prior to any type of release from incarceration or inpatient civil commitment, the person shall report a change of address, in writing, to the sheriff of the county in which he or she is incarcerated and the sheriff of the county in which he or she resides, has a temporary domicile, or has a habitual living location. The sheriff shall submit the change of address to the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol on the day it is received and in a manner prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para><para>(11) Any person required to register under the act shall, in person, inform the sheriff of any legal change in name within three working days after such change and provide a copy of the legal documentation supporting the change in name. The sheriff shall submit the information to the sex offender registration and community notification division of the Nebraska State Patrol, in writing, immediately after receipt of the information and in a manner prescribed by the Nebraska State Patrol for such purpose.</para><para>(12) At any time that a person required to register under the act violates the registry requirements and cannot be located, the registry information shall reflect that the person has absconded, a warrant shall be sought for the person's arrest, and the United States Marshals Service shall be notified.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 645, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 564, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB285, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB292, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>