<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id673"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4313"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4313</statuteno><catchline>Sexual assault forensic evidence; rights of victim.</catchline><para>(1) A victim has the right to timely analysis of sexual assault forensic evidence.</para><para>(2) Subject to section 28-902, a health care provider shall notify the appropriate law enforcement agency of a victim's reported sexual assault and submit to law enforcement the sexual assault forensic evidence, if evidence has been obtained.</para><para>(3) A law enforcement agency shall collect the sexual assault forensic evidence upon notification by the health care provider and shall retain the sexual assault forensic evidence for the longer of the statute of limitations applicable to the sexual assault or the retention period set forth in subsection (4) of section 28-902.</para><para>(4) A victim has a right to contact the investigating law enforcement agency and be provided with information on the status of the processing and analysis of the victim's sexual assault forensic evidence, if the victim did not report anonymously.</para><para>(5) A victim has the right to have the results of the analysis of the victim's sexual assault forensic evidence uploaded to the appropriate local, state, and federal DNA data bases, as allowed by law.</para><para>(6) A victim has the right to be informed by the investigating law enforcement agency, upon the victim's request, of the results of analysis of the victim's sexual assault forensic evidence, whether the analysis yielded a DNA profile, and whether the analysis yielded a DNA match, either to the named perpetrator or to a suspect already in the Federal Bureau of Investigation's Combined DNA Index System, so long as the provision of such information would not hinder or interfere with investigation or prosecution of the case associated with such information.</para><para>(7) A victim has the right to inspect or request copies of law enforcement reports concerning the sexual assault at the conclusion of the case.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB43, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>