<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id744"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4311"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4311</statuteno><catchline>Medical evidentiary or physical examinations; rights of victim.</catchline><para>(1) A victim has the right to have an advocate of the victim's choosing present during a medical evidentiary or physical examination. The health care provider shall contact the advocate before beginning the medical evidentiary or physical examination, unless declined by the victim. If an advocate cannot appear in a timely manner, the health care provider shall inform the victim of the potential impact of delaying the examination.</para><para>(2) A victim retains such right to have an advocate present at any time during any medical evidentiary or physical examination, regardless of whether the victim has previously waived such right.</para><para>(3) A victim has the right to a free forensic medical examination as provided in section 81-1429.03 without regard to whether a victim participates in the criminal justice system or cooperates with law enforcement.</para><para>(4) A victim has the right to be provided health care in accordance with best practices and established protocols for age-appropriate sexual assault forensic medical examinations as set forth in publications of the Office on Violence Against Women of the United States Department of Justice.</para><para>(5) A victim has the protection of confidential communications as provided in sections 29-4301 to 29-4304.</para><para>(6) A victim has the right to shower at no cost after the medical evidentiary or physical examination, unless showering facilities are not available.</para><para>(7) A victim has the right to anonymous reporting as provided in section 28-902.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB43, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>