<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id705"><amendatorysection chaptername="Criminal Procedure" statutenumber="29-4317"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>29-4317</statuteno><catchline>Health care provider, emergency medical services provider, laboratory, or pharmacy; provision of certain services related to sexual assault, domestic assault, or child abuse; acts prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) A health care provider, an emergency medical services provider, a laboratory, or a pharmacy providing medical services, transportation, medications, or other services related to the examination or treatment of injuries arising out of sexual assault as defined in section 29-4309, domestic assault under section 28-323, or child abuse under section 28-707 shall not:</para><para>(a) Refer a bill for such services to a collection agency or an attorney for collection against the victim or the victim's guardian or family;</para><para>(b) Distribute information regarding such services and status of payment in any way that would affect the credit rating of the victim or the victim's guardian or family; or</para><para>(c) Take any other action adverse to the victim or the victim's guardian or family on account of providing such services.</para><para>(2) This section shall not be construed to prevent an entity described in subsection (1) of this section from otherwise seeking payment for such services from the victim or any other source.</para><para>(3) If a collection agency or an attorney is referred a debt for a bill described in subsection (1) of this section, then upon notice of the applicability of this section, the collection agency or attorney shall return the debt to the referring health care provider, emergency medical services provider, laboratory, or pharmacy.</para><para>(4) No private cause of action shall exist under this section against a debt collector.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB157, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>