<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="1-304">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>1-304</statuteno>
<catchline>Obligation of good faith.</catchline>
<para>Every contract or duty within the Uniform Commercial Code imposes an obligation of good faith in its performance and enforcement.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 23.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Source:</emphasis> Former section 1-203.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes from former law:</emphasis> Except for changing the form of reference to the Uniform Commercial Code, this section is identical to former section 1-203.</para>
<para>1. This section sets forth a basic principle running throughout the Uniform Commercial Code. The principle is that in commercial transactions good faith is required in the performance and enforcement of all agreements or duties. While this duty is explicitly stated in some provisions of the Uniform Commercial Code, the applicability of the duty is broader than merely these situations and applies generally, as stated in this section, to the performance or enforcement of every contract or duty within this code. It is further implemented by section 1-303 on course of dealing, course of performance, and usage of trade. This section does not support an independent cause of action for failure to perform or enforce in good faith. Rather, this section means that a failure to perform or enforce, in good faith, a specific duty or obligation under the contract, constitutes a breach of that contract or makes unavailable, under the particular circumstances, a remedial right or power. This distinction makes it clear that the doctrine of good faith merely directs a court towards interpreting contracts within the commercial context in which they are created, performed, and enforced, and does not create a separate duty of fairness and reasonableness which can be independently breached.</para>
<para>2. "Performance and enforcement" of contracts and duties within the Uniform Commercial Code include the exercise of rights created by the Uniform Commercial Code.</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
