<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2-104">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2-104</statuteno>
<catchline>Definitions; merchant; between merchants; financing agency.</catchline>
<para>(1) "Merchant" means a person who deals in goods of the kind or otherwise by his or her occupation holds himself or herself out as having knowledge or skill peculiar to the practices or goods involved in the transaction or to whom such knowledge or skill may be attributed by his or her employment of an agent or broker or other intermediary who by his or her occupation holds himself or herself out as having such knowledge or skill.</para>
<para>(2) "Financing agency" means a bank, finance company, or other person who in the ordinary course of business makes advances against goods or documents of title or who by arrangement with either the seller or the buyer intervenes in ordinary course to make or collect payment due or claimed under the contract for sale, as by purchasing or paying the seller's draft or making advances against it or by merely taking it for collection whether or not documents of title accompany or are associated with the draft. "Financing agency" includes also a bank or other person who similarly intervenes between persons who are in the position of seller and buyer in respect to the goods (section 2-707).</para>
<para>(3) "Between merchants" means in any transaction with respect to which both parties are chargeable with the knowledge or skill of merchants.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1963, c. 544, Art. II, &#167; 2-104, p. 1708; </para>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 31.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para>Under subsection (1) of this section, one who engages in the business of purchasing and selling corn is a merchant. Laird v. Scribner Coop, 237 Neb. 532, 466 N.W.2d 798 (1991).</para>
<para>Experienced grain farmers who regularly grow and market grain on the open market as the principal means of providing for their livelihood and by reason of such occupation have acquired and possess knowledge or skill peculiar to the practices and operations of grain marketing are merchants within the meaning of section 2-201 and this section. Agrex, Inc. v. Schrant, 221 Neb. 604, 379 N.W.2d 751 (1986).</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
