<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2-102" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>2-102</statuteno><catchline>Scope; certain security and other transactions excluded from this article.</catchline><para>(1) Unless the context otherwise requires, and except as provided in subsection (3), this article applies to transactions in goods and, in the case of a hybrid transaction, it applies to the extent provided in subsection (2).</para><para>(2) In a hybrid transaction:</para><para>(a) If the sale-of-goods aspects do not predominate, only the provisions of this article which relate primarily to the sale-of-goods aspects of the transaction apply, and the provisions that relate primarily to the transaction as a whole do not apply.</para><para>(b) If the sale-of-goods aspects predominate, this article applies to the transaction but does not preclude application in appropriate circumstances of other law to aspects of the transaction which do not relate to the sale of goods.</para><para>(3) This article does not:</para><para>(a) apply to a transaction that, even though in the form of an unconditional contract to sell or present sale, operates only to create a security interest; or</para><para>(b) impair or repeal a statute regulating sales to consumers, farmers, or other specified classes of buyers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 544, Art. II, &#167; 2-102, p. 1706; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB94, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>If a contract involves both the sale of goods and services, and the parties have presented the case to the trial court and the Supreme Court on the theory that the sales article of the U.C.C. applies, this court will dispose of the case on appeal on that theory. Nebraska Builders Prod. Co. v. Industrial Erectors, 239 Neb. 744, 478 N.W.2d 257 (1992).</para><para>Transaction to construct building had predominant purpose of rendering service with goods incidentally involved, and thus fell outside scope of the Uniform Commercial Code. Herman v. Bonanza Bldgs., Inc., 223 Neb. 474, 390 N.W.2d 536 (1986).</para><para>The sales article of the U.C.C. does not apply to a contract for membership in an organization for the purchase of food or other goods. Guaranteed Foods v. Rison, 207 Neb. 400, 299 N.W.2d 507 (1980).</para><para>Valves to be used in nuclear submarines are goods and Uniform Commercial Code—Sales applies to transactions involving them. Crane Co. v. Roberts Supply Co., 196 Neb. 67, 241 N.W.2d 516 (1976).</para><para>The Uniform Commercial Code did not apply to a contract for the sale of an ongoing grain business, including both goods and nongoods, because the principal purpose of the transaction was the sale of nongoods. MBH, Inc. v. John Otte Oil &amp; Propane, 15 Neb. App. 341, 727 N.W.2d 238 (2007).</para><para>Whether the Uniform Commercial Code applies to a contract for the sale of both goods and nongoods is a question of law. MBH, Inc. v. John Otte Oil &amp; Propane, 15 Neb. App. 341, 727 N.W.2d 238 (2007).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>