<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2-606">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2-606</statuteno>
<catchline>What constitutes acceptance of goods.</catchline>
<para>(1) Acceptance of goods occurs when the buyer</para>
<para>(a) after a reasonable opportunity to inspect the goods signifies to the seller that the goods are conforming or that he will take or retain them in spite of their nonconformity; or</para>
<para>(b) fails to make an effective rejection (subsection (1) of section 2-602), but such acceptance does not occur until the buyer has had a reasonable opportunity to inspect them; or</para>
<para>(c) does any act inconsistent with the seller's ownership; but if such act is wrongful as against the seller it is an acceptance only if ratified by him.</para>
<para>(2) Acceptance of a part of any commercial unit is acceptance of that entire unit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1963, c. 544, Art. II, &#167; 2-606, p. 1747.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para>Evidence that someone tried to return a truck that was in their possession for the purpose of a test drive is sufficient to show that the truck was not accepted within the meaning of this section. Woodhouse Ford v. Laflan, 268 Neb. 722, 687 N.W.2d 672 (2004).</para>
<para>The commingling by a buyer of one farmer's grain with that of other farmers is an act inconsistent with the buyer's ownership and may constitute acceptance under this section. Johnson v. Holdrege Coop. Equity Exchange, 206 Neb. 568, 293 N.W.2d 863 (1980).</para>
<para>Acceptance under this section of the Code occurs when the buyer fails to make an effective rejection, if the buyer has had a reasonable opportunity to inspect the goods. Fabricators, Inc. v. Farmers Elevator, Inc., 203 Neb. 150, 277 N.W.2d 676 (1979).</para>
<para>Buyer of defective machine failed to make effective rejection, and by his actions accepted nonconforming goods. Alliance Tractor &amp; Implement Co. v. Lukens Tool &amp; Die Co., 199 Neb. 489, 260 N.W.2d 193 (1977).</para>
<para>City, by accepting sewage processing plant when it denied access to the plant to personnel of the contractor, which was also to operate the plant, became obligated to pay contract rate, less any damages alloted to it. Omaha Pollution Control Corp. v. Carver-Greenfield Corp., 413 F.Supp. 1069 (D. Neb. 1976).</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
