<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2-106" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>2-106</statuteno><catchline>Definitions; contract; agreement; contract for sale; sale; present sale; conforming to contract; termination; cancellation; hybrid transaction.</catchline><para>(1) In this article unless the context otherwise requires "contract" and "agreement" are limited to those relating to the present or future sale of goods. "Contract for sale" includes both a present sale of goods and a contract to sell goods at a future time. A "sale" consists in the passing of title from the seller to the buyer for a price (section 2-401). A "present sale" means a sale which is accomplished by the making of the contract.</para><para>(2) Goods or conduct including any part of a performance are "conforming" or conform to the contract when they are in accordance with the obligations under the contract.</para><para>(3) "Termination" occurs when either party pursuant to a power created by agreement or law puts an end to the contract otherwise than for its breach. On "termination" all obligations which are still executory on both sides are discharged but any right based on prior breach or performance survives.</para><para>(4) "Cancellation" occurs when either party puts an end to the contract for breach by the other and its effect is the same as that of "termination" except that the canceling party also retains any remedy for breach of the whole contract or any unperformed balance.</para><para>(5) "Hybrid transaction" means a single transaction involving a sale of goods and:</para><para>(a) the provision of services;</para><para>(b) a lease of other goods; or</para><para>(c) a sale, lease, or license of property other than goods.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 544, Art. II, &#167; 2-106, p. 1709; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB94, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The initial step in determining whether a buyer may revoke his or her acceptance of goods or conduct is to assess whether there exists a nonconformity in the contract. Richardson v. Mast, 252 Neb. 114, 560 N.W.2d. 488 (1997).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>