<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code"
statutenumber="3-118"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>3-118</statuteno><catchline>Statute
of limitations.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in subsection (e),
an action to enforce the obligation of a party to pay a note payable at a
definite time must be commenced within six years after the due date or dates
stated in the note or, if a due date is accelerated, within six years after
the accelerated due date.</para><para>(b) Except as provided in subsection
(d) or (e), if demand for payment is made to the maker of a note payable on
demand, an action to enforce the obligation of a party to pay the note must
be commenced within six years after the demand. If no demand for payment is
made to the maker, an action to enforce the note is barred if neither principal
nor interest on the note has been paid for a continuous period of ten years.</para><para>(c)
Except as provided in subsection (d), an action to enforce the obligation
of a party to an unaccepted draft to pay the draft must be commenced within
three years after dishonor of the draft or ten years after the date of the
draft, whichever period expires first.</para><para>(d) An action to enforce
the obligation of the acceptor of a certified check or the issuer of a teller's
check, cashier's check, or traveler's check must be commenced within three
years after demand for payment is made to the acceptor or issuer, as the case
may be.</para><para>(e) Subject to the provisions of section 25-227, an action
to enforce the obligation of a party to a certificate of deposit to pay the
instrument must be commenced within six years after demand for payment is
made to the maker, but if the instrument states a due date and the maker is
not required to pay before that date, the six-year period begins when a demand
for payment is in effect and the due date has passed.</para><para>(f) An action
to enforce the obligation of a party to pay an accepted draft, other than
a certified check, must be commenced (i) within six years after the due date
or dates stated in the draft or acceptance if the obligation of the acceptor
is payable at a definite time, or (ii) within six years after the date of
the acceptance if the obligation of the acceptor is payable on demand.</para><para>(g)
Unless governed by other law regarding claims for indemnity or contribution,
an action (i) for conversion of an instrument, for money had and received,
or like action based on conversion, (ii) for breach of warranty, or (iii)
to enforce an obligation, duty, or right arising under this article and not
governed by this section must be commenced within three years after the cause
of action accrues.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 161, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB151, &#167; 2.</para></source>
<annotation><para>Pursuant to subsection (g) of this section, in the absence of fraudulent concealment by the defendant, the discovery rule does not toll the statute of limitations for claims involving negotiable instruments under the Uniform Commercial Code. Mandolfo v. Mandolfo, 281 Neb. 443, 796 N.W.2d 603 (2011).</para></annotation>
 </law></legaldoc>
