<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="7-507">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo>
<statuteno>7-507</statuteno>
<catchline>Warranties on negotiation or delivery of document of title.</catchline>
<para>If a person negotiates or delivers a document of title for value, otherwise than as a mere intermediary under section 7-508, unless otherwise agreed, the transferor, in addition to any warranty made in selling or leasing the goods, warrants to its immediate purchaser only that:</para>
<para>(1) the document is genuine;</para>
<para>(2) the transferor does not have knowledge of any fact that would impair the document's validity or worth; and</para>
<para>(3) the negotiation or delivery is rightful and fully effective with respect to the title to the document and the goods it represents.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 92.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Prior Uniform Statutory Provision:</emphasis> Former section 7-507.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes:</emphasis> Substitution of the word "delivery" for the word "transfer", reference leasing transactions and style.</para>
<para><emphasis>Purposes:</emphasis></para>
<para>1. Delivery of goods by use of a document of title does not limit or displace the ordinary obligations of a seller or lessor as to any warranties regarding the goods that arise under other law. If the transfer of documents attends or follows the making of a contract for the sale or lease of goods, the general obligations on warranties as to the goods (sections 2-312 through 2-318 and 2A-210 through 2A-316) are brought to bear as well as the special warranties under this section.</para>
<para>2. The limited warranties of a delivering or collecting intermediary, including a collecting bank, are stated in section
7-508.</para>
<para><emphasis>Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>Point 1: Sections 2-312 through 2-318 and 2A-310 through 2A-316.</para>
<para>Point 2: Section 7-508.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Delivery". Section 1-201.</para>
<para>"Document of title". Section 1-201.</para>
<para>"Genuine". Section 1-201.</para>
<para>"Goods". Section 7-102.</para>
<para>"Person". Section 1-201.</para>
<para>"Purchaser". Section 1-201.</para>
<para>"Value". Section 1-204.</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
