<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="7-305">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo>
<statuteno>7-305</statuteno>
<catchline>Destination bills.</catchline>
<para>(a) Instead of issuing a bill of lading to the consignor at the place of shipment, a carrier, at the request of the consignor, may procure the bill to be issued at destination or at any other place designated in the request.</para>
<para>(b) Upon request of any person entitled as against a carrier to control the goods while in transit and on surrender of possession or control of any outstanding bill of lading or other receipt covering the goods, the issuer, subject to section 7-105, may procure a substitute bill to be issued at any place designated in the request.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 77.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Prior Uniform Statutory Provision:</emphasis> Former section 7-305.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes:</emphasis> To accommodate electronic bills of lading and for style.</para>
<para><emphasis>Purposes:</emphasis></para>
<para>1. Subsection (a) continues the rules of former section 7-305(1) without substantive change. This proposal is designed to facilitate the use of order bills in connection with fast shipments. Use of order bills on high speed shipments is impeded
by the fact that the goods may arrive at destination before the documents, so that no one is ready to take delivery from the
carrier. This is especially inconvenient for carriers by truck and air, who do not have terminal facilities where shipments can be
held to await the consignee's appearance. Order bills would be useful to take advantage of bank collection. This may be
preferable to C.O.D. shipment in which the carrier, e.g. a truck driver, is the collecting and remitting agent. Financing of
shipments under this plan would be handled as follows: Seller at San Francisco delivers the goods to an airline with instructions
to issue a bill in New York to a named bank. Seller receives a receipt embodying this undertaking to issue a destination bill.
Airline wires its New York freight agent to issue the bill as instructed by the seller. Seller wires the New York bank a draft
on buyer.  New York bank indorses the bill to buyer when the buyer honors the draft. Normally seller would act through its own bank in San Francisco, which would extend credit in reliance on the airline's contract to deliver a bill to the order of its New York
correspondent. This section is entirely permissive; it imposes no duty to issue such bills. Whether a performing carrier will act as issuing agent is left to agreement between carriers.</para>
<para>2. Subsection (b) continues the rule from former section 7-305(2) with accommodation for electronic bills of lading. If the substitute bill changes from an electronic to a tangible medium or vice versa, the issuance of the substitute bill must comply with section 7-105 to give the substitute bill validity and effect.</para>
<para><emphasis>Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>Section 7-105.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Bill of lading". Section 1-201.</para>
<para>"Consignor". Section 7-102.</para>
<para>"Goods". Section 7-102.</para>
<para>"Issuer". Section 7-102.</para>
<para>"Receipt of goods". Section 2-103.</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
