<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="7-105">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>7-105</statuteno>
<catchline>Reissuance in alternative medium.</catchline>
<para>(a) Upon request of a person entitled under an electronic document of title, the issuer of the electronic document may issue a tangible document of title as a substitute for the electronic document if:</para>
<para>(1) the person entitled under the electronic document surrenders control of the document to the issuer; and</para>
<para>(2) the tangible document when issued contains a statement that it is issued in substitution for the electronic document.</para>
<para>(b) Upon issuance of a tangible document of title in substitution for an electronic document of title in accordance with subsection (a):</para>
<para>(1) the electronic document ceases to have any effect or validity; and</para>
<para>(2) the person that procured issuance of the tangible document warrants to all subsequent persons entitled under the tangible document that the warrantor was a person entitled under the electronic document when the warrantor surrendered control of the electronic document to the issuer.</para>
<para>(c) Upon request of a person entitled under a tangible document of title, the issuer of the tangible document may issue an electronic document of title as a substitute for the tangible document if:</para>
<para>(1) the person entitled under the tangible document surrenders possession of the document to the issuer; and</para>
<para>(2) the electronic document when issued contains a statement that it is issued in substitution for the tangible document.</para>
<para>(d) Upon issuance of an electronic document of title in substitution for a tangible document of title in accordance with subsection (c):</para>
<para>(1) the tangible document ceases to have any effect or validity; and</para>
<para>(2) the person that procured issuance of the electronic document warrants to all subsequent persons entitled under the electronic document that the warrantor was a person entitled under the tangible document when the warrantor surrendered possession of the tangible document to the issuer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 61.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Prior Uniform Statutory Provisions:</emphasis> None.</para>
<para><emphasis>Other relevant law:</emphasis> UNCITRAL Draft Instrument on the Carriage of Goods by Sea&#8212;Transport Law.</para>
<para><emphasis>Purpose:</emphasis></para>
<para>1. This section allows for documents of title issued in one medium to be reissued in another medium.  This section applies to both negotiable and nonnegotiable documents. This section sets forth minimum requirements for giving the reissued document effect and validity. The issuer is not required to issue a document in an alternative medium and if the issuer chooses to do so, it may impose additional requirements. Because a document of title imposes obligations on the issuer of the document, it is imperative for the issuer to be the one who issues the substitute document in order for the substitute document to be effective and valid.</para>
<para>2. The request must be made to the issuer by the person entitled to enforce the document of title (section 7-102(a)(9)) and that person must surrender possession or control of the original document to the issuer. The reissued document must have a notation that it has been issued as a substitute for the original document. These minimum requirements must be met in order to give the substitute document effect and validity. If these minimum requirements are not met for issuance of a substitute document of title, the original document of title continues to be effective and valid. Section 7-402. However, if the minimum requirements imposed by this section are met, in addition to any other requirements that the issuer may impose, the substitute document will be the document that is effective and valid.</para>
<para>3. To protect parties who subsequently take the substitute document of title, the person who procured issuance of the
substitute document warrants that it was a person entitled under the original document at the time it surrendered possession or
control of the original document to the issuer. This warranty is modeled after the warranty found in section 4-209.</para>
<para><emphasis>Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>Sections 7-106, 7-402, and 7-601.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Person entitled to enforce". Section 7-102.</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>
