<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="8-307">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>8-307</statuteno>
<catchline>Purchaser's right to requisites for registration of transfer.</catchline>
<para>Unless otherwise agreed, the transferor of a security on due demand shall supply the purchaser with proof of authority to transfer or with any other requisite necessary to obtain registration of the transfer of the security, but if the transfer is not for value, a transferor need not comply unless the purchaser pays the necessary expenses. If the transferor fails within a reasonable time to comply with the demand, the purchaser may reject or rescind the transfer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1995, LB 97, &#167; 37.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para>1. Because registration of the transfer of a security is a matter of vital importance, a purchaser is here provided with the means of obtaining such formal requirements for registration as signature guaranties, proof of authority, transfer tax stamps, and the like. The transferor is the one in a position to supply most conveniently whatever documentation may be requisite for registration of transfer, and the duty to do so upon demand within a reasonable time is here stated affirmatively. If an essential item is peculiarly within the province of the transferor so that the transferor is the only one who can obtain it, the purchaser may specifically enforce the right to obtain it. Compare section 8-304(d). If a transfer is not for value the transferor need not pay expenses.</para>
<para>2. If the transferor's duty is not performed the transferee may reject or rescind the contract to transfer. The transferee is not bound to do so. An action for damages for breach of contract may be preferred.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Purchaser". Sections 1-201(33), 8-116.</para>
<para>"Security". Section 8-102(a)(15).</para>
<para>"Value". Sections 1-201(44), 8-116.</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
