<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="8-111">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>8-111</statuteno>
<catchline>Clearing corporation rules.</catchline>
<para>A rule adopted by a clearing corporation governing rights and obligations among the clearing corporation and its participants in the clearing corporation is effective even if the rule conflicts with the Uniform Commercial Code and affects another party who does not consent to the rule.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1995, LB 97, &#167; 15.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para>1. The experience of the past few decades shows that securities holding and settlement practices may develop rapidly, and in unforeseeable directions. Accordingly, it is desirable that the rules of article 8 be adaptable both to ensure that commercial law can conform to changing practices and to ensure that commercial law does not operate as an obstacle to developments in securities practice. Even if practices were unchanging, it would not be possible in a general statute to specify in detail the rules needed to provide certainty in the operations of the clearance and settlement system.</para>
<para>The provisions of this article and article 1 on the effect of agreements provide considerable flexibility in the specification of the details of the rights and obligations of participants in the securities holding system by agreement. See sections 8-504 through 8-509, and section 1-102(3) and (4). Given the magnitude of the exposures involved in securities transactions, however, it may not be possible for the parties in developing practices to rely solely on private agreements, particularly with respect to matters that might affect others, such as creditors. For example, in order to be fully effective, rules of clearing corporations on the finality or reversibility of securities settlements must not only bind the participants in the clearing corporation but also be effective against their creditors. Section 8-111 provides that clearing corporation rules are effective even if they indirectly affect third parties, such as creditors of a participant. This provision does not, however, permit rules to be adopted that would govern the rights and obligations of third parties other than as a consequence of rules that specify the rights and obligations of the clearing corporation and its participants.</para>
<para>2. The definition of clearing corporation in section 8-102 covers only federal reserve banks, entities registered as clearing agencies under the federal securities laws, and others subject to comparable regulation. The rules of registered clearing agencies are subject to regulatory oversight under the federal securities laws.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross Reference:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Clearing corporation". Section 8-102(a)(5).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
