<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="8-114">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>8-114</statuteno>
<catchline>Evidentiary rules concerning certificated securities.</catchline>
<para>The following rules apply in an action on a certificated security against the issuer:</para>
<para>(1) Unless specifically denied in the pleadings, each signature on a security certificate or in a necessary indorsement is admitted.</para>
<para>(2) If the effectiveness of a signature is put in issue, the burden of establishing effectiveness is on the party claiming under the signature, but the signature is presumed to be genuine or authorized.</para>
<para>(3) If signatures on a security certificate are admitted or established, production of the certificate entitles a holder to recover on it unless the defendant establishes a defense or a defect going to the validity of the security.</para>
<para>(4) If it is shown that a defense or defect exists, the plaintiff has the burden of establishing that the plaintiff or some person under whom the plaintiff claims is a person against whom the defense or defect cannot be asserted.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1995, LB 97, &#167; 18.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para>This section adapts the rules of negotiable instruments law concerning procedure in actions on instruments, see section 3-308, to actions on certificated securities governed by this article. An "action on a security" includes any action or proceeding brought against the issuer to enforce a right or interest that is part of the security, such as an action to collect principal or interest or a dividend, or to establish a right to vote or to receive a new security under an exchange offer or plan of reorganization. This section applies only to certificated securities; actions on uncertificated securities are governed by general evidentiary principles.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Action". Section 1-201(1).</para>
<para>"Burden of establishing". Section 1-201(8).</para>
<para>"Certificated security". Section 8-102(a)(4).</para>
<para>"Indorsement". Section 8-102(a)(11).</para>
<para>"Issuer". Section 8-201.</para>
<para>"Presumed". Section 1-201(31).</para>
<para>"Security". Section 8-102(a)(15).</para>
<para>"Security certificate". Section 8-102(a)(16).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
