<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="8-407">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>8-407</statuteno>
<catchline>Authenticating trustee, transfer agent, and registrar.</catchline>
<para>A person acting as authenticating trustee, transfer agent, registrar, or other agent for an issuer in the registration of a transfer of its securities, in the issue of new security certificates or uncertificated securities, or in the cancellation of surrendered security certificates has the same obligation to the holder or owner of a certificated or uncertificated security with regard to the particular functions performed as the issuer has in regard to those functions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1995, LB 97, &#167; 44.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para>1. Transfer agents, registrars, and the like are here expressly held liable both to the issuer and to the owner for wrongful refusal to register a transfer as well as for wrongful registration of a transfer in any case within the scope of their respective functions where the issuer would itself be liable. Those cases which have regarded these parties solely as agents of the issuer and have therefor refused to recognize their liability to the owner for mere nonfeasance, i.e., refusal to register a transfer, are rejected. Hulse v. Consolidated Quicksilver Mining Corp., 65 Idaho 768, 154 P.2d 149 (1944); Nicholson v. Morgan, 119 Misc. 309, 196 N.Y.Supp. 147 (1922); Lewis v. Hargadine-McKittrick Dry Goods Co., 305 Mo. 396, 274 S.W. 1041 (1924).</para>
<para>2. The practice frequently followed by authenticating trustees of issuing certificates of indebtedness rather than authenticating duplicate certificates where securities have been lost or stolen became obsolete in view of the provisions of section 8-405, which makes express provision for the issue of substitute securities. It is not a breach of trust or lack of due diligence for trustees to authenticate new securities. Cf. Switzerland General Ins. Co. v. N.Y.C. &amp; H.R.R. Co., 152 App.Div. 70, 136 N.Y.S. 726 (1912).</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Certificated security". Section 8-102(a)(4).</para>
<para>"Issuer". Section 8-201.</para>
<para>"Security". Section 8-102(a)(15).</para>
<para>"Security certificate". Section 8-102(a)(16).</para>
<para>"Uncertificated security". Section 8-102(a)(18).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
