<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-507"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-507</statuteno><catchline>Effect of certain events on effectiveness
of financing statement.</catchline><para>(a) A filed financing statement remains
effective with respect to collateral that is sold, exchanged, leased, licensed,
or otherwise disposed of and in which a security interest or agricultural
lien continues, even if the secured party knows of or consents to the disposition.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (c) and section 9-508,
a financing statement is not rendered ineffective if, after the financing
statement is filed, the information provided in the financing statement becomes
seriously misleading under section 9-506.</para>
<para>(c) If the name
that a filed financing statement provides
for a debtor becomes insufficient
as the name of the debtor under section 9-503(a) so that the financing statement
becomes seriously misleading under section 9-506:</para>
<para>(1) the financing statement is effective to perfect a security interest
in collateral acquired by the debtor before, or within four months after,
the filed financing statement becomes seriously
misleading; and</para>
<para>(2) the financing statement is not effective to perfect a security interest
in collateral acquired by the debtor more than four months after the filed financing statement becomes seriously misleading, unless
an amendment to the financing statement which renders the financing statement
not seriously misleading is filed within four months after the
financing statement became seriously misleading.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, § 151; </para>
<para>Laws 2011, LB90, §  16.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2013</operativedate></source><annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Source.</emphasis> Former section 9-402(7).</para>
<para><emphasis>2. Scope of Section.</emphasis> This section deals with situations in which the information in a proper financing statement becomes inaccurate after the financing statement is filed. Compare section 9-338, which deals with situations in which a financing statement contains a particular kind of information concerning the debtor (i.e., the information described in section 9-516(b)(5)) that is incorrect at the time it is filed.</para>
<para><emphasis>3. Post-Filing Disposition of Collateral.</emphasis> Under subsection (a), a financing statement remains effective even if the collateral is sold or otherwise disposed of. This subsection clarifies the third sentence of former section 9-402(7) by providing that a financing statement remains effective following the disposition of collateral only when the security interest or agricultural lien continues in that collateral. This result is consistent with the conclusion of PEB Commentary No. 3. Normally, a security interest does continue after disposition of the collateral. See section 9-315(a)(1). Law other than this article determines whether an agricultural lien survives disposition of the collateral.</para>
<para>As a consequence of the disposition, the collateral may be owned by a person other than the debtor against whom the financing statement was filed. Under subsection (a), the secured party remains perfected even if it does not correct the public record. For this reason, any person seeking to determine whether a debtor owns collateral free of security interests must inquire as to the debtor's source of title and, if circumstances seem to require it, search in the name of a former owner. Subsection (a) addresses only the sufficiency of the information contained in the financing statement. A disposition of collateral may result in loss of perfection for other reasons. See section 9-316.</para>
<para><emphasis>Example:</emphasis> Dee Corp. is an Illinois corporation. It creates a security interest in its equipment in favor of Secured Party. Secured Party files a proper financing statement in Illinois. Dee Corp. sells an item of equipment to Bee Corp., a Pennsylvania corporation, subject to the security interest. The security interest continues, see section 9-315(a)(1), and remains perfected, see section 9-507(a), notwithstanding that the financing statement is filed under "D" (for Dee Corp.) and not under "B". However, because Bee Corp. is located in Pennsylvania and not Illinois, see section 9-307, unless Secured Party perfects under Pennsylvania law within one year after the transfer, its security interest will become unperfected and will be deemed to have been unperfected against purchasers of the collateral. See section 9-316.</para>
<para><emphasis>4. Other Post-Filing Changes.</emphasis> Subsection (b) provides that, as a general matter, post-filing changes that render a financing statement inaccurate and seriously misleading have no effect on a financing statement. The financing statement remains effective. It is subject to two exceptions: Sections 9-508 and 9-507(c). Section 9-508 addresses the effectiveness of a financing statement filed against an original debtor when a new debtor becomes bound by the original debtor's security agreement. It is discussed in the comments to that section. Section 9-507(c) addresses a "pure" change of the debtor's name, i.e., a change that does not implicate a new debtor. It clarifies former section 9-402(7). If a name change renders a filed financing statement seriously misleading, the financing statement is not effective as to collateral acquired more than four months after the change, unless before the expiration of the four months an amendment is filed that specifies the debtor's new correct name (or provides an incorrect name that renders the financing statement not seriously misleading under section 9-506). As under former section 9-402(7), the original financing statement would continue to be effective with respect to collateral acquired before the name change as well as collateral acquired within the four-month period.</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
