<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-620"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>9-620</statuteno><catchline>Acceptance of collateral in full or partial satisfaction of obligation; compulsory disposition of collateral.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (g), a secured party may accept collateral in full or partial satisfaction of the obligation it secures only if:</para><para>(1) the debtor consents to the acceptance under subsection (c);</para><para>(2) the secured party does not receive, within the time set forth in subsection (d), a notification of objection to the proposal signed by:</para><para>(A) a person to which the secured party was required to send a proposal under section 9-621; or</para><para>(B) any other person, other than the debtor, holding an interest in the collateral subordinate to the security interest that is the subject of the proposal;</para><para>(3) if the collateral is consumer goods, the collateral is not in the possession of the debtor when the debtor consents to the acceptance; and</para><para>(4) subsection (e) does not require the secured party to dispose of the collateral or the debtor waives the requirement pursuant to section 9-624.</para><para>(b) A purported or apparent acceptance of collateral under this section is ineffective unless:</para><para>(1) the secured party consents to the acceptance in a signed record or sends a proposal to the debtor; and</para><para>(2) the conditions of subsection (a) are met.</para><para>(c) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(1) a debtor consents to an acceptance of collateral in partial satisfaction of the obligation it secures only if the debtor agrees to the terms of the acceptance in a record signed after default; and</para><para>(2) a debtor consents to an acceptance of collateral in full satisfaction of the obligation it secures only if the debtor agrees to the terms of the acceptance in a record signed after default or the secured party:</para><para>(A) sends to the debtor after default a proposal that is unconditional or subject only to a condition that collateral not in the possession of the secured party be preserved or maintained;</para><para>(B) in the proposal, proposes to accept collateral in full satisfaction of the obligation it secures; and</para><para>(C) does not receive a notification of objection signed by the debtor within twenty days after the proposal is sent.</para><para>(d) To be effective under subdivision (a)(2), a notification of objection must be received by the secured party:</para><para>(1) in the case of a person to which the proposal was sent pursuant to section 9-621, within twenty days after notification was sent to that person; and</para><para>(2) in other cases:</para><para>(A) within twenty days after the last notification was sent pursuant to section 9-621; or</para><para>(B) if a notification was not sent, before the debtor consents to the acceptance under subsection (c).</para><para>(e) A secured party that has taken possession of collateral shall dispose of the collateral pursuant to section 9-610 within the time specified in subsection (f) if:</para><para>(1) sixty percent of the cash price has been paid in the case of a purchase-money security interest in consumer goods; or</para><para>(2) sixty percent of the principal amount of the obligation secured has been paid in the case of a non-purchase-money security interest in consumer goods.</para><para>(f) To comply with subsection (e), the secured party shall dispose of the collateral:</para><para>(1) within ninety days after taking possession; or</para><para>(2) within any longer period to which the debtor and all secondary obligors have agreed in an agreement to that effect entered into and signed after default.</para><para>(g) In a consumer transaction, a secured party may not accept collateral in partial satisfaction of the obligation it secures.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 195; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB94, &#167; 89. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>