<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-702">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-702</statuteno>
<catchline>Savings clause.</catchline>
<para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in this part, this article applies to a transaction or lien within its scope, even if the transaction or lien was entered into or created before July 1, 2001.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (c) and sections 9-703 to 9-709:</para>
<para>(1) transactions and liens that were not governed by article 9, as such article existed immediately before July 1, 2001, were validly entered into or created before July 1, 2001, and would be subject to this article if they had been entered into or created on or after July 1, 2001, and the rights, duties, and interests flowing from those transactions and liens remain valid on and after July 1, 2001; and</para>
<para>(2) the transactions and liens may be terminated, completed, consummated, and enforced as required or permitted by this article or by the law that otherwise would apply if this article had not become law.</para>
<para>(c) This article does not affect an action, case, or proceeding commenced before July 1, 2001. </para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 205; </para>
<para>Laws 2000, LB 929, &#167; 45.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Pre-July 1, 2001, Transactions.</emphasis> Subsection (a) contains the general rule that this article applies to transactions, security interests, and other liens within its scope (see section 9-109), even if the transaction or lien was entered into or created before July 1, 2001. Thus, secured transactions entered into under former article 9 must be terminated, completed, consummated, and enforced under this article. Subsection (b) is an exception to the general rule. It applies to valid, pre-July 1, 2001, transactions and liens that were not governed by former article 9 but would be governed by this article if they had been entered into or created on or after July 1, 2001. Under subsection (b), these valid transactions, such as the creation of agricultural liens and security interests in commercial tort claims, retain their validity under this article and may be terminated, completed, consummated, and enforced under this article. However, these transactions also may be terminated, completed, consummated, and enforced by the law that otherwise would apply had this article not taken effect.</para>
<para><emphasis>2. Judicial Proceedings Commenced Before July 1, 2001.</emphasis> As is usual in transition provisions, subsection (c) provides that this article does not affect litigation pending on the July 1, 2001, date.</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
