<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-518"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-518</statuteno><catchline>Claim concerning inaccurate or wrongfully
filed record.</catchline><para>(a) A person may file in the filing office an information statement with respect to a record
indexed there under the person's name if the person believes that the record
is inaccurate or was wrongfully filed.</para>
<para>(b) An information statement under subsection (a) must:</para>
<para>(1) identify the record to which it relates by the file number assigned
to the initial financing statement to which the record relates;</para>
<para>(2) indicate that it is an information statement;
and</para>
<para>(3) provide the basis for the person's belief that the record is inaccurate
and indicate the manner in which the person believes the record should be
amended to cure any inaccuracy or provide the basis for the person's belief
that the record was wrongfully filed.</para>
<para>(c) A person may file
in the filing office an information statement with respect to a record filed
there if the person is a secured party of record with respect to the financing
statement to which the record relates and believes that the person that filed
the record was not entitled to do so under section 9-509(d).</para>
<para>(d) An information statement
under subsection (c) must:</para><para>(1) identify the record to which it relates by the
file number assigned to the initial financing statement to which the record
relates;</para><para>(2)
indicate that it is an information statement; and</para><para>(3) provide the basis for the person's
belief that the person that filed the record was not entitled to do so under
section 9-509(d).</para><para>(e) The filing of an information statement does not affect the
effectiveness of an initial financing statement or other filed record.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, § 162; </para>
<para>Laws 2011, LB90, §  19.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2013</operativedate></source><annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Source.</emphasis> New.</para>
<para><emphasis>2. Correction Statements.</emphasis> Former article 9 did not afford a nonjudicial means for a debtor to correct a financing statement or other record that was inaccurate or wrongfully filed. Subsection (a) affords the debtor the right to file a correction statement. Among other requirements, the correction statement must provide the basis for the debtor's belief that the public record should be corrected. See subsection (b). These provisions, which resemble the analogous remedy in the Fair Credit Reporting Act, 15 U.S.C. section 1681i, afford an aggrieved person the opportunity to state its position on the public record. They do not permit an aggrieved person to change the legal effect of the public record. Thus, although a filed correction statement becomes part of the "financing statement", as defined in section 9-102, the filing does not affect the effectiveness of the initial financing statement or any other filed record. See subsection (c).</para>
<para>This section does not displace other provisions of this article that impose liability for making unauthorized filings or failing to file or send a termination statement (see section 9-625(e)), nor does it displace any available judicial remedies.</para>
<para><emphasis>3. Resort to Other Law.</emphasis> This article cannot provide a satisfactory or complete solution to problems caused by misuse of the public records. The problem of "bogus" filings is not limited to the UCC filing system but extends to the real property records, as well. A summary judicial procedure for correcting the public record and criminal penalties for those who misuse the filing and recording systems are likely to be more effective and put less strain on the filing system than provisions authorizing or requiring action by filing and recording offices.</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>