<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-502"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-502</statuteno><catchline>Contents of financing statement; record
of mortgage as financing statement; time of filing financing statement.</catchline>
<para>(a) Subject to subsection (b), a financing statement is sufficient only
if it:</para>
<para>(1) provides the name of the debtor;</para>
<para>(2) provides the name of the secured party or a representative of the
secured party; and</para>
<para>(3) indicates the collateral covered by the financing statement.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in section 9-501(b), to be sufficient,
a financing statement that covers as-extracted collateral or timber to be
cut, or which is filed as a fixture filing and covers goods that are or are
to become fixtures, must satisfy subsection (a) and also:</para>
<para>(1) indicate that it covers this type of collateral;</para>
<para>(2) indicate that it is to be filed for record in the real property
records;</para>
<para>(3) provide a description of the real property to which the collateral
is related sufficient to give constructive notice of a mortgage
under the law of this state if the description were contained in a record
of the mortgage of the real property; and</para>
<para>(4) if the debtor does not have an interest of record in the real property,
provide the name of a record owner.</para>
<para>(c) A record of a mortgage is effective, from the date of recording,
as a financing statement filed as a fixture filing or as a financing statement
covering as-extracted collateral or timber to be cut only if:</para>
<para>(1) the record indicates the goods or accounts that it covers;</para>
<para>(2) the goods are or are to become fixtures related to the real property
described in the record or the collateral is related to the real property
described in the record and is as-extracted collateral or timber to be cut;</para>
<para>(3) the record satisfies the requirements for a financing statement
in this section, but:</para>
<para>(A) the record need not indicate that
it is to be filed in the real property records; and</para>
<para>(B) the record sufficiently
provides the name of a debtor who is an individual if it provides the individual
name of the debtor or the surname and first personal name of the debtor, even
if the debtor is an individual to whom section 9-503(a)(4) applies; and</para>
<para>(4) the record is duly recorded.</para>
<para>(d) A financing statement may be filed before a security agreement is
made or a security interest otherwise attaches.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 146; </para>
<para>Laws 2011, LB90, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
