<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-607"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-607</statuteno><catchline>Collection and enforcement by secured
party.</catchline><para>(a) If so agreed, and in any event after default,
a secured party:</para>
<para>(1) may notify an account debtor or other person obligated on collateral
to make payment or otherwise render performance to or for the benefit of the
secured party;</para>
<para>(2) may take any proceeds to which the secured party is entitled under
section 9-315;</para>
<para>(3) may enforce the obligations of an account debtor or other person
obligated on collateral and exercise the rights of the debtor with respect
to the obligation of the account debtor or other person obligated on collateral
to make payment or otherwise render performance to the debtor, and with respect
to any property that secures the obligations of the account debtor or other
person obligated on the collateral;</para>
<para>(4) if it holds a security interest in a deposit account perfected by
control under section 9-104(a)(1), may apply the balance of the deposit account
to the obligation secured by the deposit account; and</para>
<para>(5) if it holds a security interest in a deposit account perfected by
control under section 9-104(a)(2) or (3), may instruct the bank to pay the
balance of the deposit account to or for the benefit of the secured party.</para>
<para>(b) If necessary to enable a secured party to exercise under subdivision
(a)(3) the right of a debtor to enforce a mortgage nonjudicially, the secured
party may record in the office in which a record of the mortgage is recorded:</para>
<para>(1) a copy of the security agreement that creates or provides for a
security interest in the obligation secured by the mortgage; and</para>
<para>(2) the secured party's sworn affidavit in recordable form stating that:</para>
<para>(A) a default has occurred with
respect to the obligation secured by the mortgage; and</para>
<para>(B) the secured party is entitled to enforce the mortgage nonjudicially.</para>
<para>(c) A secured party shall proceed in a commercially reasonable manner
if the secured party:</para>
<para>(1) undertakes to collect from or enforce an obligation of an account
debtor or other person obligated on collateral; and</para>
<para>(2) is entitled to charge back uncollected collateral or otherwise to
full or limited recourse against the debtor or a secondary obligor.</para>
<para>(d) A secured party may deduct from the collections made pursuant to
subsection (c) reasonable expenses of collection and enforcement, including
reasonable attorney's fees and legal expenses incurred by the secured party.</para>
<para>(e) This section does not determine whether an account debtor, bank,
or other person obligated on collateral owes a duty to a secured party.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 182; </para>
    <para>Laws 2011, LB90, &#167; 21.</para></source><annotation><para>Article 9 leaves to the agreement of the parties the circumstances giving rise to a default; default is whatever the security agreement says it is. First State Bank Neb. v. MP Nexlevel, 307 Neb. 198, 948 N.W.2d 708 (2020).</para><para>"Default" is not contingent on an adjudication or agreement and occurs, instead, when determined by the terms of the security agreement. First State Bank Neb. v. MP Nexlevel, 307 Neb. 198, 948 N.W.2d 708 (2020).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>
