<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-523"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-523</statuteno><catchline>Information from filing office; sale
or license of records.</catchline><para>(a) If a person that files a written
record requests an acknowledgment of the filing, the filing office shall send
to the person an image of the record showing the number assigned to the record
pursuant to section 9-519(a)(1) and the date and time of the filing of the
record. However, if the person furnishes a copy of the record to the filing
office, the filing office may instead:</para>
<para>(1) note upon the copy the number assigned to the record pursuant to
section 9-519(a)(1) and the date and time of the filing of the record; and</para>
<para>(2) send the copy to the person.</para>
<para>(b) If a person files a record other than a written record, the filing
office shall communicate to the person an acknowledgment that provides:</para>
<para>(1) the information in the record;</para>
<para>(2) the number assigned to the record pursuant to section 9-519(a)(1);
and</para>
<para>(3) the date and time of the filing of the record.</para>
<para>(c) The filing office shall communicate or otherwise make available
in a record the following information to any person that requests it:</para>
<para>(1) whether there is on file on a date and time specified by the filing
office, but not a date earlier than three business days before the filing
office receives the request, any financing statement that:</para>
<para>(A) designates a particular debtor;</para>
<para>(B) has not lapsed under section 9-515 with respect to all secured parties
of record; and</para>
<para>(C) if the request so states, has lapsed under section 9-515 and a record
of which is maintained by the filing office under section 9-522(a);</para>
<para>(2) the date and time of filing of each financing statement; and</para>
<para>(3) the information provided in each financing statement.</para>
<para>(d) In complying with its duty under subsection (c), the filing office
may communicate information in any medium. However, if requested, the filing
office shall communicate information by issuing its written certificate.</para>
<para>(e) The filing office shall perform the acts required by subsections
(a) through (d) at the time and in the manner prescribed by filing-office
rule, but not later than two business days after the filing office receives
the request.</para>
<para>(f)(1) The Secretary of State shall offer to sell or license to the
public on a nonexclusive basis, in bulk, copies of all records filed in the
office of the Secretary of State under this part, in every medium from time
to time available to the filing office.</para>
<para>(2) Records filed in the office of the Secretary of State under this
part may be made available electronically through the portal established under section 84-1204, Reissue
Revised Statutes of Nebraska. For batch requests, the fee is two dollars per
record accessed through the portal, except
that the fee for a batch request for one thousand or more records is two thousand
dollars. All fees collected pursuant to this subdivision shall be deposited
in the Records Management Cash Fund and shall be distributed as provided in
any agreements between the State Records Board and the Secretary of State.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 167; </para>
<para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
