<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-503"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-503</statuteno><catchline>Name of debtor and secured party.</catchline>
<para>(a) A financing statement sufficiently provides the name of the debtor:</para>
<para>(1) except as otherwise provided in subdivision (3), if the debtor is
a registered organization or the collateral is held in a trust that is a registered
organization, only if the financing statement provides the name that is stated
to be the registered organization's name on the public organic record most
recently filed with or issued or enacted by the registered organization's
jurisdiction of organization which purports to state, amend, or restate the
registered organization's name;</para>
<para>(2) subject to subsection (f), if the collateral is being administered
by the personal representative of a decedent, only if the financing statement
provides, as the name of the debtor, the name of the decedent and, in a separate
part of the financing statement, indicates that the collateral is being administered
by a personal representative;</para>
<para>(3) if the collateral is held in a trust that is not a registered organization,
only if the financing statement:</para>
<para>(A) provides, as the name of the debtor:</para>
<para>(i) if the organic record of the trust specifies a name for the trust,
the name specified; or</para>
<para>(ii) if the organic record of the trust does not specify a name for
the trust, the name of the settlor or testator; and</para>
<para>(B) in a separate part of the financing statement:</para>
<para>(i) if the name is provided in accordance with subdivision (A)(i), indicates
that the collateral is held in a trust; or</para>
<para>(ii) if the name is provided in accordance with subdivision (A)(ii),
provides additional information sufficient to distinguish the trust from other
trusts having one or more of the same settlors or the same testator and indicates
that the collateral is held in a trust, unless the additional information
so indicates;</para>
<para>(4) subject to subsection (g), if the debtor is an individual to whom the Department of Motor Vehicles has issued
a driver's license or state
identification card that has not expired, only if the financing
statement provides the name of the individual which is indicated on the driver's
license or state identification
card;</para>
<para>(5) if the debtor is an individual to whom subdivision (4) does not
apply, only if the financing statement provides the individual name of the
debtor or the surname and first personal name of the debtor; and</para>
<para>(6) in other cases:</para>
<para>(A) if the debtor has a name, only if the financing statement provides
the organizational name of the debtor; and</para>
<para>(B) if the debtor does not have a name, only if it provides the names
of the partners, members, associates, or other persons comprising the debtor,
in a manner that each name provided would be sufficient if the person named
were the debtor.</para>
<para>(b) A financing statement that provides the name of the debtor in accordance
with subsection (a) is not rendered ineffective by the absence of:</para>
<para>(1) a trade name or other name of the debtor; or</para>
<para>(2) unless required under subdivision (a)(6)(B), names of partners,
members, associates, or other persons comprising the debtor.</para>
<para>(c) A financing statement that provides only the debtor's trade name
does not sufficiently provide the name of the debtor.</para>
<para>(d) Failure to indicate the representative capacity of a secured party
or representative of a secured party does not affect the sufficiency of a
financing statement.</para>
<para>(e) A financing statement may provide the name of more than one debtor
and the name of more than one secured party.</para>
<para>(f) The name of the decedent indicated on the order appointing the personal
representative of the decedent issued by the court having jurisdiction over
the collateral is sufficient as the "name of the decedent" under subsection
(a)(2).</para>
<para>(g) If the Department of Motor Vehicles has
issued to an individual more than one driver's license or state identification card of a kind described
in subsection (a)(4), the one that was issued most recently is the one to
which subsection (a)(4) refers.</para>
<para>(h) In this section, the "name of the settlor or testator" means:</para>
<para>(1) if the settlor is a registered organization, the name that is stated
to be the settlor's name on the public organic record most recently filed
with or issued or enacted by the settlor's jurisdiction of organization which
purports to state, amend, or restate the settlor's name; or</para>
<para>(2) in other cases, the name of the settlor or testator indicated in
the trust's organic record.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 147; </para>
<para>Laws 2011, LB90, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1031, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
