<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-525" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>9-525</statuteno><catchline id="id178">Fees.</catchline><para>(a) The fee for filing and indexing a record under this part is:</para><para>(1) Except as provided in subdivision (a)(3) of this section, fourteen dollars if the record is communicated in writing;</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subdivision (a)(3) of this section, eleven dollars if the record is communicated by another medium authorized by filing-office rule; and</para><para>(3) One hundred dollars if the debtor is a transmitting utility and the filing so indicates.</para><para>(b) The number of names required to be indexed does not affect the amount of the fee in subsection (a).</para><para>(c) There is no fee for the filing of a termination statement.</para><para>(d)(1) The fee for responding to a request for information from the filing office, including for communicating whether there is on file any financing statement naming a particular debtor, is five dollars if the request is communicated in writing.</para><para>(2) The fee for responding to a request for information from the filing office, including for communicating whether there is on file any financing statement naming a particular debtor, is four dollars and fifty cents if the request is communicated by another medium authorized by filing-office rule.</para><para>(e) The fees charged by county clerks for inquiries and other services regarding information in the centralized computer system shall be the same as set forth in this section.</para><para>(f) The Secretary of State shall remit the fees received by the Secretary of State pursuant to this section to the State Treasurer for credit to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 169; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1099, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 45. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source><annotation><para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Source.</emphasis> Various sections of former part 4.</para><para><emphasis>2. Fees.</emphasis> This section contains all fee requirements for filing, indexing, and responding to requests for information. Uniformity in the fee structure (but not necessarily in the amount of fees) makes this article easier for secured parties to use and reduces the likelihood that a filed record will be rejected for failure to pay at least the correct amount of the fee. See section 9-516(b)(2).</para><para>The costs of processing electronic records are less than those with respect to written records. Accordingly, this section mandates a lower fee as an incentive to file electronically and imposes the additional charge (if any) for multiple debtors only with respect to written records. When written records are used, this article encourages the use of the uniform forms in section 9-521. The fee for filing these forms should be no greater than the fee for other written records.</para><para>To make the relevant information included in a filed record more accessible once the record is found, this section mandates a higher fee for longer written records than for shorter ones. Finally, recognizing that financing statements naming more than one debtor are most often filed against a husband and wife, any additional charge for multiple debtors applies to records filed with respect to more than two debtors, rather than with respect to more than one.</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>