<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="9-807"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-807</statuteno><catchline>Amendment of pre-operative-date financing
statement.</catchline><para>(a)
In this section, "pre-operative-date financing statement" means a financing
statement filed before July 1, 2013.</para><para>(b) On or after July 1, 2013, a person may add or
delete collateral covered by, continue or terminate the effectiveness of,
or otherwise amend the information provided in, a pre-operative-date financing
statement only in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection
as provided in this article as it existed on July 1, 2013. However, the effectiveness
of a pre-operative-date financing statement also may be terminated in accordance
with the law of the jurisdiction in which the financing statement is filed.</para>
<para>(c) Except as otherwise
provided in subsection (d), if the law of this state governs perfection of
a security interest, the information in a pre-operative-date financing statement
may be amended on or after July 1, 2013, only if:</para><para>(1) the pre-operative-date financing
statement and an amendment are filed in the office specified in section 9-501;</para>
<para>(2) an amendment is filed
in the office specified in section 9-501 concurrently with, or after the filing
in that office of, an initial financing statement that satisfies section 9-806(c);
or</para><para>(3)
an initial financing statement that provides the information as amended and
satisfies section 9-806(c) is filed in the office specified in section 9-501.</para>
<para>(d) If the law of this
state governs perfection of a security interest, the effectiveness of a pre-operative-date
financing statement may be continued only under section 9-805(c) and (e) or
9-806.</para><para>(e)
Whether or not the law of this state governs perfection of a security interest,
the effectiveness of a pre-operative-date financing statement filed in this
state may be terminated on or after July 1, 2013, by filing a termination
statement in the office in which the pre-operative-date financing statement
is filed, unless an initial financing statement that satisfies section 9-806(c)
has been filed in the office specified by the law of the jurisdiction governing
perfection as provided in this article as it existed on July 1, 2013, as the
office in which to file a financing statement.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB90, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
