<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="UCC">
<section id="id27">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" id="id29" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="9-513A"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-513A</statuteno><catchline>Unauthorized financing statement filings;
procedures; remedies.</catchline><para>(a) An individual personally, or as a representative of an organization,
may file in the filing office a notarized affidavit, signed under penalty
of perjury, that identifies a filed financing statement and states that:</para>
<para>(1) the individual
or organization is identified as a debtor in the financing statement;</para>
<para>(2) the financing
statement was not filed by a financial institution or a representative of
a financial institution or by an agricultural input supplier or a representative
of an agricultural input supplier; and</para><para>(3) the financing statement was filed by
a person not entitled to do so under section 9-509, 9-708, or 9-808.</para>
<para>(b) An affidavit filed under
subsection (a) shall include any pertinent information that the office of
the Secretary of State may reasonably require.</para><para>(c) An affidavit may not
be filed under subsection (a) with respect to a financing statement filed
by a financial institution or a representative of a financial institution
or by an agricultural input supplier or a representative of an agricultural
input supplier.</para><para>(d) If an affidavit is filed under subsection (a), the filing office
may file a termination statement with respect to the financing statement identified
in the affidavit. The termination statement must indicate that it was filed
pursuant to this section. Except as provided in subsections (g) and (h), a
termination statement filed under this subsection shall take effect thirty
days after it is filed.</para><para>(e) On the same day that the filing office files a termination statement
under subsection (d), it shall send to each secured party of record identified
in the financing statement a notice advising the secured party of record that
the termination statement has been filed. The notice shall be sent by certified
mail, return receipt requested, to the mailing address provided for the secured
party of record.</para><para>(f) A secured party of record identified in a financing statement
as to which a termination statement has been filed under subsection (d) may
bring an action within twenty business days after the termination statement
is filed against the individual who filed the affidavit under subsection (a)
seeking a determination as to whether the financing statement was filed by
a person entitled to do so under section 9-509, 9-708, or 9-808. An action
under this subsection shall have priority on the court's calendar and shall
proceed by expedited hearing. The action shall be brought in the district
court of the county where the filing office in which the financing statement
was filed is located.</para><para>(g) In an action brought pursuant to subsection (f), a court may,
in appropriate circumstances, order preliminary relief, including, but not
limited to, an order precluding the termination statement from taking effect
or directing a party to take action to prevent the termination statement from
taking effect. If the court issues such an order and the filing office receives
a certified copy of the order before the termination statement takes effect,
the termination statement shall not take effect and the filing office shall
promptly file an amendment to the financing statement that indicates that
an order has prevented the termination statement from taking effect. If such
an order ceases to be effective by reason of a subsequent order or a final
judgment of the court or by an order issued by another court and the filing
office receives a certified copy of the subsequent judgment or order, the
termination statement shall become immediately effective upon receipt of the
certified copy and the filing office shall promptly file an amendment to the
financing statement indicating that the termination statement is effective.</para>
<para>(h) If a court
determines in an action brought pursuant to subsection (f) that the financing
statement was filed by a person entitled to do so under section 9-509, 9-708,
or 9-808 and the filing office receives a certified copy of the court's final
judgment or order before the termination statement takes effect, the termination
statement shall not take effect and the filing office shall remove the termination
statement and any amendments filed under subsection (g) from the files. If
the filing office receives the certified copy after the termination statement
takes effect and within thirty days after the final judgment or order was
entered, the filing office shall promptly file an amendment to the financing
statement that indicates that the financing statement has been reinstated.</para>
<para>(i) Except
as provided in subsection (j), upon the filing of an amendment reinstating
a financing statement under subsection (h) the effectiveness of the financing
statement is retroactively reinstated and the financing statement shall be
considered never to have been ineffective against all persons and for all
purposes.</para><para>(j) A financing statement whose effectiveness was terminated under
subsection (d) and has been reinstated under subsection (h) shall not be effective
as against a person that purchased the collateral in good faith between the
time the termination statement was filed and the time of the filing of the
amendment reinstating the financing statement, to the extent that the person
gave new value in reliance on the termination statement.</para>
<para>(k) The filing
office shall not charge a fee for the filing of an affidavit or a termination
statement under this section. The filing office shall not return any fee paid
for filing the financing statement identified in the affidavit, whether or
not the financing statement is subsequently reinstated.</para>
<para>(l) Neither
the filing office nor any of its employees shall be subject to liability for
the termination or amendment of a financing statement in the lawful performance
of the duties of the filing office under this section.</para>
<para>(m) The Secretary
of State shall adopt and make available a form of affidavit for use under
this section.</para><para>(n) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(1) Agricultural input supplier means a person regularly
in the business of extending credit to agricultural producers; and</para>
<para>(2) Financial institution
means a person that is in the business of extending credit or servicing loans,
including acquiring, purchasing, selling, brokering, or other extensions of
credit and where applicable, holds whatever license, charter, or registration
that is required to engage in such business. The term includes banks, savings
associations, building and loan associations, consumer and commercial finance
companies, industrial banks, industrial loan companies, insurance companies,
investment companies, installment sellers, mortgage servicers, sales finance
companies, and leasing companies.</para></amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 157; </para>
<para>Laws 2000, LB 929, &#167; 40; </para>
<para>Laws 2013, LB210, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source><annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Source.</emphasis> Former section 9-404.</para>
<para><emphasis>2. Duty to File or Send.</emphasis> This section specifies when a secured party must cause the secured party of record to file or send to the debtor a termination statement for a financing statement. Because most financing statements expire in five years unless a continuation statement is filed (section 9-515), no compulsion is placed on the secured party to file a termination statement unless demanded by the debtor, except in the case of consumer goods. Because many consumers will not realize the importance to them of clearing the public record, an affirmative duty is put on the secured party in that case. But many purchase-money security interests in consumer goods will not be filed, except for motor vehicles. See section 9-309(1). Under section 9-311(b), compliance with a certificate of title statute is "equivalent to the filing of a financing statement under this article". Thus, this section applies to a certificate of title unless the section is superseded by a certificate of title statute that contains a specific rule addressing a secured party's duty to cause a notation of a security interest to be removed from a certificate of title. In the context of a certificate of title, however, the secured party could comply with this section by causing the removal itself or providing the debtor with documentation sufficient to enable the debtor to effect the removal.</para>
<para>Subsections (a) and (b) apply to a financing statement covering consumer goods. (Nebraska did not adopt the "consumer goods" language of subsections (a) and (b).) Subsection (c) applies to other financing statements. Subsections (a) and (c) each makes explicit what was implicit under former article 9: If the debtor did not authorize the filing of a financing statement in the first place, the secured party of record should file or send a termination statement. The liability imposed upon a secured party that fails to comply with subsection (a) or (c) is identical to that imposed for the filing of an unauthorized financing statement or amendment. See section 9-625(e).</para>
<para><emphasis>3. "Bogus" Filings.</emphasis> A secured party's duty to send a termination statement arises when the secured party "receives" an authenticated demand from the debtor. In the case of an unauthorized financing statement, the person named as debtor in the financing statement may have no relationship with the named secured party and no reason to know the secured party's address. Inasmuch as the address in the financing statement is "held out by (the person named as secured party in the financing statement) as the place for receipt of such communications (i.e., communications relating to security interests)", the putative secured party is deemed to have "received" a notification delivered to that address. See section 1-202(e). If a termination statement is not forthcoming, the person named as debtor itself may authorize the filing of a termination statement, which will be effective if it indicates that the person authorized it to be filed. See sections 9-509(d)(2) and 9-510(c).</para>
<para><emphasis>4. Buyers of Receivables.</emphasis> Applied literally, former section 9-404(1) would have required many buyers of receivables to file a termination statement immediately upon filing a financing statement because "there is no outstanding secured obligation and no commitment to make advances, incur obligations, or otherwise give value". Subsections (a)(1) and (2) remedy this problem. While the security interest of a buyer of accounts or chattel paper (B-1) is perfected, the debtor is not deemed to retain an interest in the sold receivables and thus could transfer no interest in them to another buyer (B-2) or to a lien creditor (LC). However, for purposes of determining the rights of the debtor's creditors and certain purchasers of accounts or chattel paper from the debtor, while B-1's security interest is unperfected, the debtor-seller is deemed to have rights in the sold receivables, and a competing security interest or judicial lien may attach to those rights. See section 9-109, comment 5, and section 9-318. Suppose that B-1's security interest in certain accounts and chattel paper is perfected by filing, but the effectiveness of the financing statement lapses. Both before and after lapse, B-1 collects some of the receivables. After lapse, LC acquires a lien on the accounts and chattel paper. B-1's unperfected security interest in the accounts and chattel paper is subordinate to LC's rights. See section 9-317(a)(2). But collections on accounts and chattel paper are not "accounts" or "chattel paper". Even if B-1's security interest in the accounts and chattel paper is or becomes unperfected, neither the debtor nor LC acquires rights to the collections that B-1 collects (and owns) before LC acquires a lien.</para>
<para><emphasis>5. Effect of Filing.</emphasis> Subsection (b) states the effect of filing a termination statement: The related financing statement ceases to be effective. If one of several secured parties of record files a termination statement, subsection (b) applies only with respect to the rights of the person who authorized the filing of the termination statement. See section 9-510(b). The financing statement remains effective with respect to the rights of the others. However, even if a financing statement is terminated (and thus no longer is effective) with respect to all secured parties of record, the financing statement, including the termination statement, will remain of record until at least one year after it lapses with respect to all secured parties of record. See section 9-519(g).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>