<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-110">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-110</statuteno>
<catchline>Security interests arising under article 2 or 2A.</catchline>
<para>A security interest arising under section 2-401, 2-505, 2-711(3), or 2A-508(5) is subject to this article. However, until the debtor obtains possession of the goods:</para>
<para>(1) the security interest is enforceable, even if section 9-203(b)(3) has not been satisfied;</para>
<para>(2) filing is not required to perfect the security interest;</para>
<para>(3) the rights of the secured party after default by the debtor are governed by article 2 or 2A; and</para>
<para>(4) the security interest has priority over a conflicting security interest created by the debtor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 83.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Source.</emphasis> Former section 9-113.</para>
<para><emphasis>2. Background.</emphasis> Former section 9-113, from which this section derives, referred generally to security interests "arising solely under the Article on Sales (Article 2) or the Article on Leases (Article 2A)". Views differed as to the precise scope of that section. In contrast, section 9-110 specifies the security interests to which it applies.</para>
<para><emphasis>3. Security Interests Under Articles 2 and 2A.</emphasis> Section 2-505 explains how a seller of goods may reserve a security interest in them. Section 2-401 indicates that a reservation of title by the seller of goods, despite delivery to the buyer, is limited to reservation of a security interest. As did former article 9, this article governs a security interest arising solely under one of those sections; however, until the buyer obtains possession of the goods, the security interest is enforceable even in the absence of a security agreement, filing is not necessary to perfect the security interest, and the seller-secured party's rights on the buyer's default are governed by article 2.</para>
<para>Sections 2-711(3) and 2A-508(5) create a security interest in favor of a buyer or lessee in possession of goods that were rightfully rejected or as to which acceptance was justifiably revoked. As did former article 9, this article governs a security interest arising solely under one of those sections; however, until the seller or lessor obtains possession of the goods, the security interest is enforceable even in the absence of a security agreement, filing is not necessary to perfect the security interest, and the secured party's (buyer's or lessee's) rights on the debtor's (seller's or lessor's) default are governed by article 2 or 2A, as the case may be.</para>
<para><emphasis>4. Priority.</emphasis> This section adds to former section 9-113 a priority rule. Until the debtor obtains possession of the goods, a security interest arising under one of the specified sections of article 2 or 2A has priority over conflicting security interests created by the debtor. Thus, a security interest arising under section 2-401 or 2-505 has priority over a conflicting security interest in the buyer's after-acquired goods, even if the goods in question are inventory. Arguably, the same result would obtain under section 9-322, but even if it would not, a purchase-money-like priority is appropriate. Similarly, a security interest under section 2-711(3) or 2A-508(5) has priority over security interests claimed by the seller's or lessor's secured lender. This result is appropriate, inasmuch as the payments giving rise to the debt secured by the article 2 or 2A security interest are likely to be included among the lender's proceeds.</para>
<para><emphasis>Example:</emphasis> Seller owns equipment subject to a security interest created by Seller in favor of Lender. Buyer pays for the equipment, accepts the goods, and then justifiably revokes acceptance. As long as Seller does not recover possession of the equipment, Buyer's security interest under section 2-711(3) is senior to that of Lender.</para>
<para>In the event that a security interest referred to in this section conflicts with a security interest that is created by a person other than the debtor, section 9-325 applies. Thus, if Lender's security interest in the example was created not by Seller but by the person from whom Seller acquired the goods, section 9-325 would govern.</para>
<para><emphasis>5. Relationship to Other Rights and Remedies Under Articles 2 and 2A.</emphasis> This article does not specifically address the conflict between (i) a security interest created by a buyer or lessee and (ii) the seller's or lessor's right to withhold delivery under section 2-702(1), 2-703(a), or 2A-525, the seller's or lessor's right to stop delivery under section 2-705 or 2A-526, or the seller's right to reclaim under section 2-507(2) or 2-702(2). These conflicts are governed by the first sentence of section 2-403(1), under which the buyer's secured party obtains no greater rights in the goods than the buyer had or had power to convey, or section 2A-307(1), under which creditors of the lessee take subject to the lease contract.</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
