<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-707">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-707</statuteno>
<catchline>Amendment of pre-operative-date financing statement.</catchline>
<para>(a) In this section, "pre-operative-date financing statement" means a financing statement filed before July 1, 2001.</para>
<para>(b) On or after July 1, 2001, a person may add or delete collateral covered by, continue or terminate the effectiveness
of, or otherwise amend the information provided in, a pre-operative-date financing statement only in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection as provided in part 3.  However, the effectiveness of a pre-operative-date financing statement also may be terminated in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction in which the financing statement is filed.</para>
<para>(c) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (d), if the law of this state governs perfection of a security interest, the information in a pre-operative-date financing statement may be amended on or after July 1, 2001, only if:</para>
<para>(1) the pre-operative-date financing statement and an amendment are filed in the office specified in section 9-501;</para>
<para>(2) an amendment is filed in the office specified in section 9-501 concurrently with, or after the filing in that office of, an initial financing statement that satisfies section 9-706(c); or</para>
<para>(3) an initial financing statement that provides the information as amended and satisfies section 9-706(c) is filed in the office specified in section 9-501.</para>
<para>(d) If the law of this state governs perfection of a security interest, the effectiveness of a pre-operative-date financing statement may be continued only under section 9-705(d) and (g) or 9-706.</para>
<para>(e) Whether or not the law of this state governs perfection of a security interest, the effectiveness of a pre-operative-date financing statement filed in this state may be terminated on or after July 1, 2001, by filing a termination statement in the office in which the pre-operative-date financing statement is filed, unless an initial financing statement that satisfies section 9-706(c) has been filed in the office specified by the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection as provided in part 3 as the office in which to file a financing statement.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 2000, LB 929, &#167; 47; </para>
<para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 57.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>1. Scope of This Section.</emphasis> This section addresses post-operative-date amendments to pre-operative-date financing statements.</para>
<para><emphasis>2. Applicable Law.</emphasis> Determining how to amend a pre-operative-date financing statement requires one first to determine the jurisdiction whose law applies. Subsection (b) provides that, as a general matter, post-operative-date amendments to pre-operative-date financing statements are effective only if they are accomplished in accordance with the substantive (or local) law of the jurisdiction governing perfection under part 3 of this article. However, under certain circumstances, the effectiveness of a financing statement may be terminated in accordance with the substantive law of the jurisdiction in which the financing statement is filed. See comment 5, below.</para>
<para><emphasis>Example 1:</emphasis> D is a corporation organized under the law of State Y. It owns equipment located in State X. Under former article 9, SP properly perfected a security interest in the equipment by filing a financing statement in State X. Under this article, the law of State Y governs perfection of the security interest. See sections 9-301 and 9-307. After this article becomes operative, SP wishes to amend the financing statement to reflect a change in D's name. Under subsection (b), the financing statement may be amended in accordance with the law of State Y, i.e., in accordance with subsection (c) as enacted in State Y.</para>
<para><emphasis>Example 2:</emphasis> The facts are as in example 1, except that SP wishes to terminate the effectiveness of the State X filing. The first sentence of subsection (b) provides that the financing statement may be terminated after the operative date of this article in accordance with the law of State Y, i.e., in accordance with subsection (c) as enacted in State Y. However, the second sentence provides that the financing statement also may be terminated in accordance with the law of jurisdiction in which it is filed, i.e., in accordance with subsection (e) as enacted in State X. If the pre-operative-date financing statement is filed in the jurisdiction whose law governs perfection (here, State Y), then both sentences would designate the law of State Y as applicable to the termination of the financing statement. That is, the financing statement could be terminated in accordance with subsection (c) or (e) as enacted in State Y.</para>
<para><emphasis>3. Method of Amending.</emphasis> Subsection (c) provides three methods of effectuating a post-operative-date amendment to a pre-operative-date financing statement. Under subsection (c)(1), if the financing statement is filed in the jurisdiction and office determined by this article, then an effective amendment may be filed in the same office.</para>
<para><emphasis>Example 3:</emphasis> D is a corporation organized under the law of State Z. It owns equipment located in State Z. Before the operative date of this article, SP perfected a security interest in the equipment by filing in two offices in State Z, a local filing office and the office of the Secretary of State. See former section 9-401(1) (third alternative). State Z enacts this article and specifies in section 9-501 that a financing statement covering equipment is to be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. SP wishes to assign its power as secured party of record. Under subsection (b), the substantive law of State Z applies. Because the pre-operative-date financing statement is filed in the office specified in subsection (c)(1) as enacted by State Z, SP may effectuate the assignment by filing an amendment under section 9-514 with the office of the Secretary of State. SP need not amend the local filing, and the priority of the security interest perfected by the filing of the financing statement would not be affected by the failure to amend the local filing.</para>
<para>If a pre-operative-date financing statement is filed in an office other than the one specified by section 9-501 of the relevant jurisdiction, then ordinarily an amendment filed in that office is ineffective. (Subsection (e) provides an exception for termination statements.) Rather, the amendment must be effectuated by a filing in the jurisdiction and office determined by this article. That filing may consist of an initial financing statement followed by an amendment, an initial financing statement together with an amendment, or an initial financing statement that indicates the information provided in the financing statement, as amended. Subsection (c)(2) encompasses the first two options; subsection (c)(3) contemplates the last. In each instance, the initial financing statement must satisfy section 9-706(c).</para>
<para><emphasis>4. Continuation.</emphasis> Subsection (d) refers to the two methods by which a secured party may continue the effectiveness of a pre-operative-date financing statement under this part. The comments to sections 9-705 and 9-706 explain these methods.</para>
<para><emphasis>5. Termination.</emphasis> The effectiveness of a pre-operative-date financing statement may be terminated pursuant to subsection (c). This section also provides an alternative method for accomplishing this result: Filing a termination statement in the office in which the financing statement is filed. The alternative method becomes unavailable once an initial financing statement that relates to the pre-operative-date financing statement and satisfies section 9-706(c) is filed in the jurisdiction and office determined by this article.</para>
<para><emphasis>Example 4:</emphasis> The facts are as in example 1, except that SP wishes to terminate a financing statement filed in State X. As explained in example 1, the financing statement may be amended in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection under this article, i.e., in accordance with the substantive law of State Y. As enacted in State Y, subsection (c)(1) is inapplicable because the financing statement was not filed in the State Y filing office specified in section 9-501. Under subsection (c)(2), the financing statement may be amended by filing in the State Y filing office an initial financing statement followed by a termination statement. The filing of an initial financing statement together with a termination statement also would be legally sufficient under subsection (c)(2), but section 9-512(a)(1) may render this method impractical. The financing statement also may be amended under subsection (c)(3), but the resulting initial financing statement is likely to be very confusing. In each instance, the initial financing statement must satisfy section 9-706(c). Applying the law of State Y, subsection (e) is inapplicable, because the financing statement was not filed in "this state", i.e., State Y.</para>
<para>This section affords another option to SP. Subsection (b) provides that the effectiveness of a financing statement may be terminated either in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection (here, State Y) or in accordance with the substantive law of the jurisdiction in which the financing statement is filed (here, State X). Applying the law of State X, the financing statement is filed in "this state", i.e., State X, and subsection (e) applies. Accordingly, the effectiveness of the financing statement can be terminated by filing a termination statement in the State X office in which the financing statement is filed, unless an initial financing statement that relates to the financing statement and satisfies section 9-706(c) as enacted in State X has been filed in the jurisdiction and office determined by this article (here, the State Y filing office).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
