<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-705">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-705</statuteno>
<catchline>Effectiveness of action taken before July 1, 2001.</catchline>
<para>(a) If action, other than the filing of a financing statement, is taken before July 1, 2001, and the action would
have resulted in priority of a security interest over the rights of a person that becomes a lien creditor had the security interest become enforceable before July 1, 2001, the action is effective to perfect a security interest that attaches under
this article within one year after July 1, 2001. An attached security interest becomes unperfected one year after
July 1, 2001, unless the security interest becomes a perfected security interest under this article before the
expiration of that period.</para>
<para>(b) The filing of a financing statement before July 1, 2001, is effective to perfect a security interest to the extent the filing would satisfy the applicable requirements for perfection under this article.</para>
<para>(c) This article does not render ineffective an effective financing statement that, before July 1, 2001, is filed
and satisfies the applicable requirements for perfection under the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection
as provided in section 9-103, as such section existed immediately before July 1, 2001. However, except as otherwise provided in subsections (d), (e), and (f) and section 9-706, the financing statement ceases to be effective at the earlier of:</para>
<para>(1) the time the financing statement would have ceased to be effective under the law of the jurisdiction in which it is filed; or</para>
<para>(2) June 30, 2006.</para>
<para>(d) The filing of a continuation statement on or after July 1, 2001, does not continue the effectiveness of the financing
statement filed before July 1, 2001.  However, upon the timely filing of a continuation statement on or after July 1, 2001,
and in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection as provided in part 3, the effectiveness of a financing statement filed in the same office in that jurisdiction before July 1, 2001, continues for the period provided by the law of that jurisdiction.</para>
<para>(e) Subdivision (c)(2) applies to a financing statement that, before July 1, 2001, is filed against a transmitting utility and
satisfies the applicable requirements for perfection under the law of the jurisdiction governing perfection as provided in
section 9-103, as such section existed immediately before July 1, 2001, only to the extent that part 3 provides that the law of a
jurisdiction other than the jurisdiction in which the financing statement is filed governs perfection of a security interest in collateral covered by the financing statement.</para>
<para>(f) Subdivision (c)(2) does not apply to a financing statement that was filed in the proper place in the state before July 1, 2001, pursuant to section 9-401, as such section existed immediately before July 1, 2001, and for which the proper place of filing in the state was not changed pursuant to section 9-501, as such section existed on July 1, 2001.</para>
<para>(g) A financing statement that includes a financing statement filed before July 1, 2001, and a continuation statement filed on or after July 1, 2001, is effective only to the extent that it satisfies the requirements of part 5 for an initial financing statement.</para></amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 208; </para>
<para>Laws 2000, LB 929, &#167; 46; </para>
<para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 56.</para>
</source>
</law></legaldoc>
