<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-530">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-530</statuteno>
<catchline>Filing information; Secretary of State; duties.</catchline>
<para>(a) Upon receipt of a financing statement relating to any collateral except collateral described in section 9-501(a)(1), the Secretary of State shall on the day of receipt enter into the centralized computer system the following document information:</para>
<para>(1) Identification of the document and the fact that the original document was filed with the Secretary of State;</para>
<para>(2) Document number;</para>
<para>(3) Name and address of the obligor or obligors;</para>
<para>(4) Name and address of the secured party or secured parties;</para>
<para>(5) Type or types of goods or property covered;</para>
<para>(6) Date and time of filing; and</para>
<para>(7) Social security number or federal tax identification number of the obligor or obligors, if available.</para>
<para>(b)(1) Upon receipt of a notice of lien upon real property or a certificate or a notice affecting the lien presented for filing pursuant to the Uniform Federal Lien Registration Act or a notice of lien upon real property, release, continuation, subordination, or termination presented for filing pursuant to the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act, the Secretary of State shall on the date of receipt enter into the centralized computer system the following document information:</para>
<para>(i) Identification of the document and any county designated as a county in which the real property is situated;</para>
<para>(ii) Document number;</para>
<para>(iii) Type or types of property covered; and</para>
<para>(iv) The information entered pursuant to section 52-1003 or 77-3903, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(2) Upon receipt of a notice of lien upon personal property or a certificate or a notice affecting the lien filed pursuant to the Uniform Federal Lien Registration Act or a notice of lien upon personal property, release, continuation, subordination, or termination filed pursuant to the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act, the Secretary of State shall on the date of receipt enter into the centralized computer system the following document information:</para>
<para>(i) Identification of the document;</para>
<para>(ii) Document number;</para>
<para>(iii) Type or types of property covered; and</para>
<para>(iv) The information entered pursuant to section 52-1003 or 77-3903, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(c) The Secretary of State shall maintain the information received under subsections (a) and (b) of this section so that such information shall be available for the following types of inquiry: In person, written, and telephone and other electronic media, including computers.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 174; </para>
<para>Laws 2001, LB 54, &#167; 30.</para>
</source>
<crossreference>
<para><emphasis>Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act,</emphasis> see section 77-3901.</para>
</crossreference></law></legaldoc>
