<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-328">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-328</statuteno>
<catchline>Priority of security interests in investment property.</catchline>
<para>The following rules govern priority among conflicting security interests in the same investment property:</para>
<para>(1) A security interest held by a secured party having control of investment property under section 9-106 has priority over a security interest held by a secured party that does not have control of the investment property.</para>
<para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in subdivisions (3) and (4), conflicting security interests held by secured parties each of which has control under section 9-106 rank according to priority in time of:</para>
<para>(A) if the collateral is a security, obtaining control;</para>
<para>(B) if the collateral is a security entitlement carried in a securities account and:</para>
<para>(i) if the secured party obtained control under section 8-106(d)(1), the secured party's becoming the person for which the securities account is maintained;</para>
<para>(ii) if the secured party obtained control under section 8-106(d)(2), the securities intermediary's agreement to comply with the secured party's entitlement orders with respect to security entitlements carried or to be carried in the securities account; or</para>
<para>(iii) if the secured party obtained control through another person under section 8-106(d)(3), the time on which priority would be based under this subdivision if the other person were the secured party; or</para>
<para>(C) if the collateral is a commodity contract carried with a commodity intermediary, the satisfaction of the requirement for control specified in section 9-106(b)(2) with respect to commodity contracts carried or to be carried with the commodity intermediary.</para>
<para>(3) A security interest held by a securities intermediary in a security entitlement or a securities account maintained with the securities intermediary has priority over a conflicting security interest held by another secured party.</para>
<para>(4) A security interest held by a commodity intermediary in a commodity contract or a commodity account maintained with the commodity intermediary has priority over a conflicting security interest held by another secured party.</para>
<para>(5) A security interest in a certificated security in registered form which is perfected by taking delivery under section 9-313(a) and not by control under section 9-314 has priority over a conflicting security interest perfected by a method other than control.</para>
<para>(6) Conflicting security interests created by a broker, securities intermediary, or commodity intermediary which are perfected without control under section 9-106 rank equally.</para>
<para>(7) In all other cases, priority among conflicting security interests in investment property is governed by sections 9-322 and 9-323.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 121.</para>
</source>
</law></legaldoc>
