<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-516"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-516</statuteno><catchline>What constitutes filing; effectiveness
of filing.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection
(b), communication of a record to a filing office and tender of the filing
fee or acceptance of the record by the filing office constitutes filing.</para>
<para>(b) Filing does not occur with respect to a record that a filing office
refuses to accept because:</para>
<para>(1) the record is not communicated by a method or medium of communication
authorized by the filing office;</para>
<para>(2) an amount equal to or greater than the applicable filing fee is
not tendered;</para>
<para>(3) the filing office is unable to index the record because:</para>
<para>(A) in the case of an initial financing statement, the record does not
provide a name for the debtor;</para>
<para>(B) in the case of an amendment or information statement, the
record:</para>
<para>(i) does not identify the initial financing statement as required by
section 9-512 or 9-518, as applicable; or</para>
<para>(ii) identifies an initial financing statement whose effectiveness has
lapsed under section 9-515;</para>
<para>(C) in the case of an initial financing statement that provides the
name of a debtor identified as an individual or an amendment that provides
a name of a debtor identified as an individual which was not previously provided
in the financing statement to which the record relates, the record does not
identify the debtor's surname; or</para>
<para>(D) in the case of a record filed or recorded in the filing office described
in section 9-501(a)(1), the record does not provide a sufficient description
of the real property to which it relates;</para>
<para>(4) in the case of an initial financing statement or an amendment that
adds a secured party of record, the record does not provide a name and mailing
address for the secured party of record;</para>
<para>(5) in the case of an initial financing statement or an amendment that
provides a name of a debtor which was not previously provided in the financing
statement to which the amendment relates, the record does not:</para>
<para>(A) provide a mailing address for the debtor; or</para>
<para>(B) indicate whether the name
provided as the name of the debtor is the name of an individual or an organization;</para>
<para>(6) in the case of an assignment reflected in an initial financing statement
under section 9-514(a) or an amendment filed under section 9-514(b), the record
does not provide a name and mailing address for the assignee;</para>
<para>(7) in the case of a continuation statement, the record is not filed
within the six-month period prescribed by section 9-515(d); or</para>
<para>(8) in the case of a financing statement or an amendment to a financing
statement, the same person or entity is listed as both debtor and secured
party.</para>
<para>(c) For purposes of subsection (b):</para>
<para>(1) a record does not provide information if the filing office is unable
to read or decipher the information; and</para>
<para>(2) a record that does not indicate that it is an amendment or identify
an initial financing statement to which it relates, as required by section
9-512, 9-514, or 9-518, is an initial financing statement.</para>
<para>(d) A record that is communicated to the filing office with tender of
the filing fee, but which the filing office refuses to accept for a reason
other than one set forth in subsection (b), is effective as a filed record
except as against a purchaser of the collateral which gives value in reasonable
reliance upon the absence of the record from the files.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 160; </para>
<para>Laws 2003, LB 494, &#167; 1; </para>
<para>Laws 2011, LB90, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
