<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="9-307"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>9-307</statuteno><catchline>Location of debtor.</catchline><para>(a)
In this section, "place of business" means a place where a debtor conducts
its affairs.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in this section, the following rules
determine a debtor's location:</para>
<para>(1) A debtor who is an individual is located at the individual's principal
residence.</para>
<para>(2) A debtor that is an organization and has only one place of business
is located at its place of business.</para>
<para>(3) A debtor that is an organization and has more than one place of
business is located at its chief executive office.</para>
<para>(c) Subsection (b) applies only if a debtor's residence, place of business,
or chief executive office, as applicable, is located in a jurisdiction whose
law generally requires information concerning the existence of a nonpossessory
security interest to be made generally available in a filing, recording, or
registration system as a condition or result of the security interest's obtaining
priority over the rights of a lien creditor with respect to the collateral.
If subsection (b) does not apply, the debtor is located in the District of
Columbia.</para>
<para>(d) A person that ceases to exist, have a residence, or have a place
of business continues to be located in the jurisdiction specified by subsections
(b) and (c).</para>
<para>(e) A registered organization that is organized under the law of a state
is located in that state.</para>
<para>(f) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (i), a registered organization
that is organized under the law of the United States and a branch or agency
of a bank that is not organized under the law of the United States or a state
are located:</para>
<para>(1) in the state that the law of the United States designates, if the
law designates a state of location;</para>
<para>(2) in the state that the registered organization, branch, or agency
designates, if the law of the United States authorizes the registered organization,
branch, or agency to designate its state of location, including by designating its main office, home office,
or other comparable office; or</para>
<para>(3) in the District of Columbia, if neither subdivision (1) nor subdivision
(2) applies.</para>
<para>(g) A registered organization continues to be located in the jurisdiction
specified by subsection (e) or (f) notwithstanding:</para>
<para>(1) the suspension, revocation, forfeiture, or lapse of the registered
organization's status as such in its jurisdiction of organization; or</para>
<para>(2) the dissolution, winding up, or cancellation of the existence of
the registered organization.</para>
<para>(h) The United States is located in the District of Columbia.</para>
<para>(i) A branch or agency of a bank that is not organized under the law
of the United States or a state is located in the state in which the branch
or agency is licensed, if all branches and agencies of the bank are licensed
in only one state.</para>
<para>(j) A foreign air carrier under the Federal Aviation Act of 1958, as
amended, is located at the designated office of the agent upon which service
of process may be made on behalf of the carrier.</para>
<para>(k) This section applies only for purposes of this part.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 100; </para>
<para>Laws 2011, LB90, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
