<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="12-102"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>12-102</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>(a) In this article:</para><para>(1) "Controllable electronic record" means a record stored in an electronic medium that can be subjected to control under section 12-105. The term does not include a controllable account, a controllable payment intangible, a deposit account, an electronic copy of a record evidencing chattel paper, an electronic document of title, electronic money, investment property, or a transferable record.</para><para>(2) "Qualifying purchaser" means a purchaser of a controllable electronic record or an interest in a controllable electronic record that obtains control of the controllable electronic record for value, in good faith, and without notice of a claim of a property right in the controllable electronic record.</para><para>(3) "Transferable record" has the meaning provided for that term in:</para><para>(A) Section 201(a)(1) of the Electronic Signatures in Global and National Commerce Act, 15 U.S.C. section 7021(a)(1); or</para><para>(B) Section 16(a) of the Uniform Electronic Transactions Act.</para><para>(4) "Value" has the meaning provided in section 3-303(a), as if references in that subsection to an "instrument" were references to a controllable account, controllable electronic record, or controllable payment intangible.</para><para>(b) The definitions in article 9 of "account debtor", "controllable account", "controllable payment intangible", "chattel paper", "deposit account", "electronic money", and "investment property" apply to this article.</para><para>(c) Article 1 contains general definitions and principles of construction and interpretation applicable throughout this article.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB649, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB94, &#167; 93. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Electronic Transactions Act,</emphasis> see section 86-612.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>