<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN"
 "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="ucc">
<section><sectno></sectno>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2A-309">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2A-309</statuteno>
<catchline>Lessor's and lessee's rights when goods become fixtures.</catchline>
<para>(1) In this section:</para>
<para>(a) goods are "fixtures" when they become so related to particular real
estate that an interest in them arises under real estate law;</para>
<para>(b) a "fixture filing" is the filing, in the office where a record of
a mortgage on the real estate would be filed or recorded, of a financing statement
covering goods that are or are to become fixtures and conforming to the requirements
of section 9-502(a) and (b);</para>
<para>(c) a lease is a "purchase money lease" unless the lessee has possession
or use of the goods or the right to possession or use of the goods before
the lease agreement is enforceable;</para>
<para>(d) a mortgage is a "construction mortgage" to the extent it secures
an obligation incurred for the construction of an improvement on land including
the acquisition cost of the land, if the recorded writing so indicates; and</para>
<para>(e) "encumbrance" includes real estate mortgages and other liens on
real estate and all other rights in real estate that are not ownership interests.</para>
<para>(2) Under this article a lease may be of goods that are fixtures or
may continue in goods that become fixtures, but no lease exists under this
article of ordinary building materials incorporated into an improvement on
land.</para>
<para>(3) This article does not prevent creation of a lease of fixtures pursuant
to real estate law.</para>
<para>(4) The perfected interest of a lessor of fixtures has priority over
a conflicting interest of an encumbrancer or owner of the real estate if:</para>
<para>(a) the lease is a purchase money lease, the conflicting interest of
the encumbrancer or owner arises before the goods become fixtures, the interest
of the lessor is perfected by a fixture filing before the goods become fixtures
or within ten days thereafter, and the lessee has an interest of record in
the real estate or is in possession of the real estate; or</para>
<para>(b) the interest of the lessor is perfected by a fixture filing before
the interest of the encumbrancer or owner is of record, the lessor's interest
has priority over any conflicting interest of a predecessor in title of the
encumbrancer or owner, and the lessee has an interest of record in the real
estate or is in possession of the real estate.</para>
<para>(5) The interest of a lessor of fixtures, whether or not perfected,
has priority over the conflicting interest of an encumbrancer or owner of
the real estate if:</para>
<para>(a) the fixtures are readily removable factory or office machines, readily
removable equipment that is not primarily used or leased for use in the operation
of the real estate, or readily removable replacements of domestic appliances
that are goods subject to a consumer lease, and before the goods become fixtures
the lease contract is enforceable; or</para>
<para>(b) the conflicting interest is a lien on the real estate obtained by
legal or equitable proceedings after the lease contract is enforceable; or</para>
<para>(c) the encumbrancer or owner has consented in writing to the lease
or has disclaimed an interest in the goods as fixtures; or</para>
<para>(d) the lessee has a right to remove the goods as against the encumbrancer
or owner. If the lessee's right to remove terminates, the priority of the
interest of the lessor continues for a reasonable time.</para>
<para>(6) Notwithstanding subsection (4)(a) but otherwise subject to subsections
(4) and (5), the interest of a lessor of fixtures, including the lessor's
residual interest, is subordinate to the conflicting interest of an encumbrancer
of the real estate under a construction mortgage recorded before the goods
become fixtures if the goods become fixtures before the completion of the
construction. To the extent given to refinance a construction mortgage, the
conflicting interest of an encumbrancer of the real estate under a mortgage
has this priority to the same extent as the encumbrancer of the real estate
under the construction mortgage.</para>
<para>(7) In cases not within the preceding subsections, priority between
the interest of a lessor of fixtures, including the lessor's residual interest,
and the conflicting interest of an encumbrancer or owner of the real estate
who is not the lessee is determined by the priority rules governing conflicting
interests in real estate.</para>
<para>(8) If the interest of a lessor of fixtures, including the lessor's
residual interest, has priority over all conflicting interests of all owners
and encumbrancers of the real estate, the lessor or the lessee may (i) on
default, expiration, termination, or cancellation of the lease agreement but
subject to the lease agreement and this article, or (ii) if necessary to enforce
other rights and remedies of the lessor or lessee under this article, remove
the goods from the real estate, free and clear of all conflicting interests
of all owners and encumbrancers of the real estate, but the lessor or lessee
must reimburse any encumbrancer or owner of the real estate who is not the
lessee and who has not otherwise agreed for the cost of repair of any physical
injury, but not for any diminution in value of the real estate caused by the
absence of the goods removed or by any necessity of replacing them. A person
entitled to reimbursement may refuse permission to remove until the party
seeking removal gives adequate security for the performance of this obligation.</para>
<para>(9) Even though the lease agreement does not create a security interest,
the interest of a lessor of fixtures, including the lessor's residual interest,
is perfected by filing a financing statement as a fixture filing for leased
goods that are or are to become fixtures in accordance with the relevant provisions
of Article 9 - Secured Transactions.</para></amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 159, &#167; 41; </para>
<para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 62.</para></source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Uniform Statutory Source:</emphasis> Sections 9-334 and 9-604.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes:</emphasis> Revised to reflect leasing terminology and to add new material.</para>
<para><emphasis>Purposes:</emphasis></para>
<para>1. While sections 9-334 and 9-604 provided a model for this section,
certain provisions were substantially revised.</para>
<para>2. Section 2A-309(1)(c), which is new, defines purchase money lease
to exclude leases where the lessee had possession or use of the goods or the
right thereof before the lease agreement became enforceable. This term is
used in subsection (4)(a) as one of the conditions that must be satisfied
to obtain priority over the conflicting interest of an encumbrancer or owner
of the real estate.</para>
<para>3. Section 2A-309(4), which states one of several priority rules found
in this section, deletes reference to office machines and the like as well
as certain liens. However, these items are included in subsection (5), another
priority rule that is more permissive than the rule found in subsection (4)
as it applies whether or not the interest of the lessor is perfected. In addition,
subsection (5)(a) expands the scope of the provisions of section 9-334(e)
to include readily removable equipment not primarily used or leased for use
in the operation of real estate; the qualifier is intended to exclude from
the expanded rule equipment integral to the operation of real estate, e.g.,
heating and air conditioning equipment.</para>
<para>4. The rule stated in subsection (7) is more liberal than the rule stated
in section 9-334(c) in that issues of priority not otherwise resolved in this
subsection are left for resolution by the priority rules governing conflicting
interests in real estate, as opposed to the section 9-334(c) automatic subordination
of the security interest in fixtures. Note that, for the purpose of this section,
where the interest of an encumbrancer or owner of the real estate is paramount
to the intent of the lessor, the latter term includes the residual interest
of the lessor.</para>
<para>5. The rule stated in subsection (8) is more liberal than the rule stated
in section 9-604 in that the right of removal is extended to both the lessor
and the lessee and the occasion for removal includes expiration, termination,
or cancellation of the lease agreement, and enforcement of rights and remedies
under this article, as well as default. The new language also provides that
upon removal the goods are free and clear of conflicting interests of owners
and encumbrancers of the real estate.</para>
<para>6. Finally, subsection (9) provides a mechanism for the lessor of fixtures
to perfect its interest by filing a financing statement under the provisions
of the Article on Secured Transactions (Article 9), even though the lease
agreement does not create a security interest. Section 1-201(37). The relevant
provisions of article 9 must be interpreted permissively to give effect to
this mechanism as it implicitly expands the scope of article 9 so that its
filing provisions apply to transactions that create a lease of fixtures, even
though the lease agreement does not create a security interest. This mechanism
is similar to that provided in section 9-109 for the seller of goods on consignment,
even though the consignment is not "intended as security". Section 1-201(37).
Given the lack of litigation with respect to the mechanism created for consignment
sales, this new mechanism should prove effective.</para>
<para><emphasis>Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>Sections 1-201(37), 2A-309(1)(c), and 2A-309(4), and article 9, especially
sections 9-334, 9-408, and 9-604.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Agreement". Section 1-201(3).</para>
<para>"Cancellation". Section 2A-103(1)(b).</para>
<para>"Conforming". Section 2A-103(1)(d).</para>
<para>"Consumer lease". Section 2A-103(1)(e).</para>
<para>"Goods". Section 2A-103(1)(h).</para>
<para>"Lease". Section 2A-103(1)(j).</para>
<para>"Lease agreement". Section 2A-103(1)(k).</para>
<para>"Lease contract". Section 2A-103(1)(l).</para>
<para>"Lessee". Section 2A-103(1)(n).</para>
<para>"Lessor". Section 2A-103(1)(p).</para>
<para>"Lien". Section 2A-103(1)(r).</para>
<para>"Mortgage". Section 9-105(1)(j).</para>
<para>"Party". Section 1-201(29).</para>
<para>"Person". Section 1-201(30).</para>
<para>"Reasonable time". Section 1-204(1) and (2).</para>
<para>"Remedy". Section 1-201(34).</para>
<para>"Rights". Section 1-201(36).</para>
<para>"Security interest". Section 1-201(37).</para>
<para>"Termination". Section 2A-103(1)(z).</para>
<para>"Value". Section 1-201(44).</para>
<para>"Writing". Section 1-201(46).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>