<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN"
 "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="ucc">
<section><sectno></sectno>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2A-519">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2A-519</statuteno>
<catchline>Lessee's damages for nondelivery, repudiation, default,
and breach of warranty in regard to accepted goods.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as otherwise provided with respect to damages liquidated
in the lease agreement (section 2A-504) or otherwise determined pursuant to
agreement of the parties (sections 1-302 and 2A-503), if a lessee elects not
to cover or a lessee elects to cover and the cover is by lease agreement that
for any reason does not qualify for treatment under section 2A-518(2), or
is by purchase or otherwise, the measure of damages for nondelivery or repudiation
by the lessor or for rejection or revocation of acceptance by the lessee is
the present value, as of the date of the default, of the then market rent
minus the present value as of the same date of the original rent, computed
for the remaining lease term of the original lease agreement, together with
incidental and consequential damages, less expenses saved in consequence of
the lessor's default.</para>
<para>(2) Market rent is to be determined as of the place for tender or, in
cases of rejection after arrival or revocation of acceptance, as of the place
of arrival.</para>
<para>(3) Except as otherwise agreed, if the lessee has accepted goods and
given notification (section 2A-516(3)), the measure of damages for nonconforming
tender or delivery or other default by a lessor is the loss resulting in the
ordinary course of events from the lessor's default as determined in any manner
that is reasonable together with incidental and consequential damages, less
expenses saved in consequence of the lessor's default.</para>
<para>(4) Except as otherwise agreed, the measure of damages for breach of
warranty is the present value at the time and place of acceptance of the difference
between the value of the use of the goods accepted and the value if they had
been as warranted for the lease term, unless special circumstances show proximate
damages of a different amount, together with incidental and consequential
damages, less expenses saved in consequence of the lessor's default or breach
of warranty.</para></amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 159, &#167; 69; </para>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 46.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Uniform Statutory Source:</emphasis> Sections 2-713 and 2-714.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes:</emphasis> Substantially revised.</para>
<para><emphasis>Purposes:</emphasis></para>
<para>1. Subsection (1), a revised version of the provisions of section 2-713(1),
states the basic rule governing the measure of lessee's damages for nondelivery
or repudiation by the lessor or for rightful rejection or revocation of acceptance
by the lessee. This measure will apply, absent agreement to the contrary,
if the lessee does not cover or if the cover does not qualify under section
2A-518. There is no sanction for cover that does not qualify.</para>
<para>2. The measure of damage is the present value, as of the date of default,
of the market rent for the remaining term of the lease less the present value
of the original rent for the remaining term of the lease, plus incidental
and consequential damages less expenses saved in consequence of the default.
Note that the reference in section 2A-519(1) is to the date of default not
to the date of an event of default. An event of default under a lease agreement
becomes a default under a lease agreement only after the expiration of any
relevant period of grace and compliance with any notice requirements under
this article and the lease agreement. American Bar Foundation, Commentaries
on Indentures, section 5-1, at 216-217 (1971). Section 2A-501(1). This conclusion
is also a function of whether, as a matter of fact or law, the event of default
has been waived, suspended, or cured. Sections 1-103 and 2A-103(4).</para>
<para>3. Subsection (2), a revised version of the provisions of section 2-713(2),
states the rule with respect to determining market rent.</para>
<para>4. Subsection (3), a revised version of the provisions of section 2-714(1)
and (3), states the measure of damages where goods have been accepted and
acceptance is not revoked. The subsection applies both to defaults which occur
at the inception of the lease and to defaults which occur subsequently, such
as failure to comply with an obligation to maintain the leased goods. The
measure in essence is the loss, in the ordinary course of events, flowing
from the default.</para>
<para>5. Subsection (4), a revised version of the provisions of section 2-714(2),
states the measure of damages for breach of warranty. The measure in essence
is the present value of the difference between the value of the goods accepted
and of the goods if they had been as warranted.</para>
<para>6. Subsections (1), (3), and (4) specifically state that the parties
may by contract vary the damages rules stated in those subsections.</para>
<para><emphasis>Cross Reference:</emphasis></para>
<para>Sections 2-713(1), 2-713(2), 2-714, and 2A-518.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Conforming". Section 2A-103(1)(d).</para>
<para>"Delivery". Section 1-201(b)(15).</para>
<para>"Goods". Section 2A-103(1)(h).</para>
<para>"Lease". Section 2A-103(1)(j).</para>
<para>"Lease agreement". Section 2A-103(1)(k).</para>
<para>"Lessee". Section 2A-103(1)(n).</para>
<para>"Lessor". Section 2A-103(1)(p).</para>
<para>"Notification". Section 1-202.</para>
<para>"Present value". Section 1-201(b)(28).</para>
<para>"Value". Section 1-204.</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>

