<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<legaldoc><law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2A-519">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2A-519</statuteno>
<catchline>Lessee's damages for nondelivery, repudiation, default,
and breach of warranty in regard to accepted goods.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as otherwise provided with respect to damages liquidated
in the lease agreement (section 2A-504) or otherwise determined pursuant to
agreement of the parties (sections 1-302 and 2A-503), if a lessee elects not
to cover or a lessee elects to cover and the cover is by lease agreement that
for any reason does not qualify for treatment under section 2A-518(2), or
is by purchase or otherwise, the measure of damages for nondelivery or repudiation
by the lessor or for rejection or revocation of acceptance by the lessee is
the present value, as of the date of the default, of the then market rent
minus the present value as of the same date of the original rent, computed
for the remaining lease term of the original lease agreement, together with
incidental and consequential damages, less expenses saved in consequence of
the lessor's default.</para>
<para>(2) Market rent is to be determined as of the place for tender or, in
cases of rejection after arrival or revocation of acceptance, as of the place
of arrival.</para>
<para>(3) Except as otherwise agreed, if the lessee has accepted goods and
given notification (section 2A-516(3)), the measure of damages for nonconforming
tender or delivery or other default by a lessor is the loss resulting in the
ordinary course of events from the lessor's default as determined in any manner
that is reasonable together with incidental and consequential damages, less
expenses saved in consequence of the lessor's default.</para>
<para>(4) Except as otherwise agreed, the measure of damages for breach of
warranty is the present value at the time and place of acceptance of the difference
between the value of the use of the goods accepted and the value if they had
been as warranted for the lease term, unless special circumstances show proximate
damages of a different amount, together with incidental and consequential
damages, less expenses saved in consequence of the lessor's default or breach
of warranty.</para></amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 159, &#167; 69; </para>
<para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 46.</para>
</source>
</law></legaldoc>

