<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2A-210">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2A-210</statuteno>
<catchline>Express warranties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Express warranties by the lessor are created as follows:</para>
<para>(a) Any affirmation of fact or promise made by the lessor to the lessee which relates to the goods and becomes part of the basis of the bargain creates an express warranty that the goods will conform to the affirmation or promise.</para>
<para>(b) Any description of the goods which is made part of the basis of the bargain creates an express warranty that the goods will conform to the description.</para>
<para>(c) Any sample or model that is made part of the basis of the bargain creates an express warranty that the whole of the goods will conform to the sample or model.</para>
<para>(2) It is not necessary to the creation of an express warranty that the lessor use formal words, such as "warrant" or "guarantee", or that the lessor have a specific intention to make a warranty, but an affirmation merely of the value of the goods or a statement purporting to be merely the lessor's opinion or commendation of the goods does not create a warranty.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 159, &#167; 21.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Uniform Statutory Source:</emphasis> Section 2-313.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes:</emphasis> Revised to reflect leasing practices and terminology.</para>
<para><emphasis>Purposes:</emphasis></para>
<para>All of the express and implied warranties of the Article on Sales (Article 2) are included in this article, revised to reflect the differences between a sale of goods and a lease of goods. Sections 2A-210 through 2A-216. The lease of goods is sufficiently similar to the sale of goods to justify this decision. Hawkland, The Impact of the Uniform Commercial Code on Equipment Leasing, 1972 Ill. L.F. 446, 459-60. Many state and federal courts have reached the same conclusion.</para>
<para>Value of the goods, as used in subsection (2), includes rental value.</para>
<para><emphasis>Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>Article 2, especially section 2-313, and sections 2A-210 through 2A-216.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Conforming". Section 2A-103(1)(d).</para>
<para>"Goods". Section 2A-103(1)(h).</para>
<para>"Lessee". Section 2A-103(1)(n).</para>
<para>"Lessor". Section 2A-103(1)(p).</para>
<para>"Value". Section 1-201(44).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
