<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="ucc"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="2A-402">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>2A-402</statuteno>
<catchline>Anticipatory repudiation.</catchline>
<para>If either party repudiates a lease contract with respect to a performance not yet due under the lease contract, the loss of which performance will substantially impair the value of the lease contract to the other, the aggrieved party may:</para>
<para>(a) for a commercially reasonable time, await retraction of repudiation and performance by the repudiating party;</para>
<para>(b) make demand pursuant to section 2A-401 and await assurance of future performance adequate under the circumstances of the particular case; or</para>
<para>(c) resort to any right or remedy upon default under the lease contract or this article, even though the aggrieved party has notified the repudiating party that the aggrieved party would await the repudiating party's performance and assurance and has urged retraction. In addition, whether or not the aggrieved party is pursuing one of the foregoing remedies, the aggrieved party may suspend performance or, if the aggrieved party is the lessor, proceed in accordance with the provisions of this article on the lessor's right to identify goods to the lease contract notwithstanding default or to salvage unfinished goods (section 2A-524).</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 159, &#167; 45.</para>
</source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Uniform Statutory Source:</emphasis> Section 2-610.</para>
<para><emphasis>Changes:</emphasis> Revised to reflect leasing practices and terminology.</para>
<para><emphasis>Definitional Cross References:</emphasis></para>
<para>"Aggrieved party". Section 1-201(2).</para>
<para>"Goods". Section 2A-103(1)(h).</para>
<para>"Lease contract". Section 2A-103(1)(l).</para>
<para>"Lessor". Section 2A-103(1)(p).</para>
<para>"Notifies". Section 1-201(26).</para>
<para>"Party". Section 1-201(29).</para>
<para>"Reasonable time". Section 1-204(1) and (2).</para>
<para>"Remedy". Section 1-201(34).</para>
<para>"Rights". Section 1-201(36).</para>
<para>"Value". Section 1-201(44).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
