<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 

<legaldoc><law type="ucc">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="4A-103">
<bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>4A-103</statuteno>
    <catchline>Payment order &#8212; definitions.</catchline>
<para>(a) In this article:</para>
<para>(1) "Payment order" means an instruction of a sender to a receiving
bank, transmitted orally, electronically, or in writing, to pay, or to cause
another bank to pay, a fixed or determinable amount of money to a beneficiary
if:</para>
<para>(i) the instruction does not state a condition to payment to the beneficiary
other than time of payment,</para>
<para>(ii) the receiving bank is to be reimbursed by debiting an account of,
or otherwise receiving payment from, the sender, and</para>
<para>(iii) the instruction is transmitted by the sender directly to the receiving
bank or to an agent, funds-transfer system, or communication system for transmittal
to the receiving bank.</para>
<para>(2) "Beneficiary" means the person to be paid by the beneficiary's bank.</para>
<para>(3) "Beneficiary's bank" means the bank identified in a payment order
in which an account of the beneficiary is to be credited pursuant to the order
or which otherwise is to make payment to the beneficiary if the order does
not provide for payment to an account.</para>
<para>(4) "Receiving bank" means the bank to which the sender's instruction
is addressed.</para>
<para>(5) "Sender" means the person giving the instruction to the receiving
bank.</para>
<para>(b) If an instruction complying with subsection (a)(1) is to make more
than one payment to a beneficiary, the instruction is a separate payment order
with respect to each payment.</para>
<para>(c) A payment order is issued when it is sent to the receiving bank.</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 160, &#167; 4.</para></source>
<annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para>This section is discussed in the comment following section 4A-104.</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc>