<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="UCC">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Uniform Commercial Code" statutenumber="4A-108"><bookinfo>Uniform Commercial Code, Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>4A-108</statuteno><catchline>Relationship to Electronic Fund Transfer Act.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in subsection (b),
this article does not apply to a funds transfer any part of which
is governed by the Electronic Fund Transfer Act, 15 U.S.C. 1693
et seq., as such act
existed on January 1, 2013.</para>
<para>(b) This article applies
to a funds transfer that is a remittance transfer as defined in the Electronic
Fund Transfer Act, 15 U.S.C. 1693o-1, as such section existed on January 1,
2013, unless the remittance transfer is an electronic fund transfer as defined
in the Electronic Fund Transfer Act, 15 U.S.C. 1693a, as such section existed
on January 1, 2013.</para><para>(c)
In a funds transfer to which this article applies, in the event of an inconsistency
between an applicable provision of this article and an applicable provision
of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act, the provision of the Electronic Fund
Transfer Act governs to the extent of the inconsistency.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source>
<para>Laws 1963, c. 544, Art. IV, &#167; 4-108, p. 1815; </para>
<para>Laws 1991, LB 161, &#167; 79; </para>
<para>Laws 2013, LB146, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>February 16, 2013</effectivedate></source><annotation>
<para><emphasis>COMMENT</emphasis></para>
<para>1. Each of the huge volume of checks processed each day must go through a series of accounting procedures that consume time. Many banks have found it necessary to establish a cutoff hour to allow time for these procedures to be completed within the time limits imposed by article 4. Subsection (a) approves a cutoff hour of this type provided it is not earlier than 2 p.m. Subsection (b) provides that if such a cutoff hour is fixed, items received after the cutoff hour may be treated as being received at the opening of the next banking day. If the number of items received either through the mail or over the counter tends to taper off radically as the afternoon hours progress, a 2 p.m. cutoff hour does not involve a large portion of the items received but at the same time permits a bank using such a cutoff hour to leave its doors open later in the afternoon without forcing into the evening the completion of its settling and proving process.</para>
<para>2. The provision in subsection (b) that items or deposits received after the close of the banking day may be treated as received at the opening of the next banking day is important in cases in which a bank closes at twelve or one o'clock, e.g., on a Saturday, but continues to receive some items by mail or over the counter if, for example, it opens Saturday evening for the limited purpose of receiving deposits and cashing checks.</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>