<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id387"><amendatorysection statutenumber="18-814" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>18-814</statuteno><catchline>Retirement plan; report; contents; Auditor of Public Accounts; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning on the first December 31 following the date of the conversion of a transit authority established under the Transit Authority Law into a regional metropolitan transit authority, and each December 31 thereafter, for a retirement plan established pursuant to subdivision (23) of section 18-812 or pursuant to subdivision (24) of section 14-1805 by any regional metropolitan transit authority which is a defined benefit plan, the chairperson of the board or his or her designee shall prepare and electronically file an annual report with the Auditor of Public Accounts and the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature. The report shall be on a form prescribed by the Auditor of Public Accounts and shall include, but not be limited to, the following information:</para><para>(a) The levels of benefits of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a benefit, the total present value of such members' benefits, and the funding sources which will pay for such benefits; and</para><para>(b) A copy of a full actuarial analysis of each such defined benefit plan. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization which offers investment advice or provides investment management services to the retirement plan.</para><para>(2) The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If the authority does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor of Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the authority. All costs of the audit shall be paid by the authority.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB492, &#167; 14. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Transit Authority Law,</emphasis> see section 14-1826.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>