<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-412.08" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>18-412.08</statuteno><catchline>Electric facilities; joint exercise of powers with electric cooperatives or corporations; authority.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds and declares that it is in the public interest of the State of Nebraska that cities and villages of this state be empowered to participate jointly and in cooperation with one or more electric cooperatives or electric membership corporations organized under the laws of this state or any other state in the establishment and operation of facilities for the generation or transmission of electric power and energy in order to achieve economies and efficiencies in meeting the future electric energy needs of the people of the State of Nebraska. In furtherance of such end and in addition to, but not in substitution for, any other powers granted such cities and villages of this state, each city or village which owns or operates electrical facilities shall have and may exercise such power and authority to plan, finance, acquire, construct, own, operate, maintain, improve, and decommission electric generation or transmission facilities located in this state jointly and in cooperation with one or more electric cooperatives or electric membership corporations organized under the laws of this state or any other state, and each city or village shall have and may exercise such power and authority with respect to electric generation or transmission facilities located outside this state jointly or in cooperation with one or more electric cooperatives or electric membership corporations organized under the laws of this state or any other state. The powers granted under this section may be exercised with respect to any electric generation or transmission facility jointly with the powers granted under any other provisions of sections 18-412.07 to 18-412.09 and 70-628.02 to 70-628.04.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 1005, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 658, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 969, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 26. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>