<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id871"><amendatorysection statutenumber="18-810" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>18-810</statuteno><catchline>Board; organization; quorum; meetings; minutes; public records.</catchline><para>(1) Not later than seven days after the qualification of the members, the board shall organize for the transaction of business, shall select a chairperson and vice-chairperson from among its members, and shall adopt bylaws, rules, and regulations to govern its proceedings. The chairperson and vice-chairperson and their successors shall be elected annually by the board and shall serve for a term of one year. Any vacancy in the office of chairperson or vice-chairperson shall be filled by election by the board for the remainder of the term.</para><para>(2) A quorum for the transaction of business shall consist of four members of the board, unless such board is a temporary board under section 18-807, in which case a quorum shall consist of three members of the board.</para><para>(3) Regular meetings of the board shall be held at least once in each calendar month at a time and place to be fixed by the board.</para><para>(4) All actions of the board shall be by resolution except as may otherwise be provided in the Regional Metropolitan Transit Authority Act, and the affirmative vote of a majority of the board members shall be necessary for the adoption of any resolution.</para><para>(5) The board shall keep accurate minutes of all its proceedings. All resolutions and all proceedings of a regional metropolitan transit authority and all official documents and records of such authority shall be public records and open to public inspection, except for such documents which may be withheld from the public pursuant to section 84-712.05.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB492, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>