<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-406" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-406</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Public utility districts; special assessments; when due; equalization; interest.</catchline><para>The special assessment provided in section 18-405 shall be paid in ten installments. The first installment, or one-tenth of the assessment, shall become due and delinquent fifty days after the date of levy, and one-tenth of such assessment shall become due and delinquent each year thereafter, counting from the date of levy, for nine years. The special assessment shall bear interest at a rate not to exceed the rate of interest specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, prior to delinquency, and at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, after delinquency. Prior to the levy of the special assessment as provided in section 18-405, such assessment shall be equalized in the same manner as provided by law for the equalization of special assessments levied in the city or village that levied such special assessment, or in the city of the metropolitan class within the metropolitan utilities district that levied such special assessment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 110, &#167; 5, p. 388; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4479; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 18-1005; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 129; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 18-1005; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-406; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 80, &#167; 1, p. 287; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 933, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 438, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 746, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>