
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-403" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-403</statuteno><catchline>Public utility districts; creation; extension or enlargement of service; notice requirements; protests.</catchline><para>Upon the passage of an ordinance or resolution under section 18-402 creating a water main district, gas main district, sanitary sewer district, storm water disposal district, or other public utility district or ordering the extension or enlargement of a water main, gas main, or other public utility service through such district, it shall be the duty of the city council or village board of trustees which passed the ordinance or of the board of directors of the metropolitan utilities district which passed the resolution to cause a notice to be published in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in such city or village or in the principal city within the metropolitan utilities district, addressed generally to the owners of the real estate within such public utility district, notifying them of the creation of the district and of the ordering of the extension or enlargement of the water main, gas main, or other public utility service within such district and further notifying the owners of the real estate that they have thirty days from and after such publication to file with such city council, village board of trustees, or board of directors their written protest against the creation of the district and of the extension or enlargement of the water main, gas main, or other public utility service so ordered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 110, &#167; 3, p. 386; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4477; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 18-1003; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-403; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 746, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>In absence of notice giving owners of real estate thirty days to file written protest, city cannot levy special assessments for water main extension. Matzke v. City of Seward, 193 Neb. 211, 226 N.W.2d 340 (1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>