<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" id="id5" statutenumber="18-132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-132</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Adoption of standard
codes.</catchline><para>The legislative bodies of all cities and
villages may adopt by ordinance the conditions, provisions, limitations, and
terms of a plumbing code, an electrical code, a fire prevention code, a building
code, and any other standard code which contains rules and regulations printed
as a code in book or pamphlet form, by reference to such code, or portions
thereof, alone, without setting forth in the ordinance the conditions, provisions,
limitations, and terms of such code. When any such code, or portion thereof,
has been incorporated by reference into any ordinance, as provided in this
section, it shall have the same force and effect as though it had been spread
at large in such ordinance without further or additional posting or publication
thereof. Not less than one copy of such standard code, or portion thereof,
shall be filed for use and examination by the public in the office of the
clerk of such city or village prior to the adoption thereof. The adoption
of any such standard code by reference shall be construed to incorporate such
amendments thereto as may be made in such standard code from time to time,
if the copy of such standard code so filed is at all times kept current in
the office of the clerk of such city or village. If there is no ordinance
adopting a plumbing code in effect in a city or village, the 2009 Uniform Plumbing Code accredited by the American
National Standards Institute shall serve as the plumbing code
for all the area within the jurisdiction of the city or village. Nothing in
this section shall be interpreted as creating an obligation for the city or
village to inspect plumbing work done within its jurisdiction to determine
compliance with the plumbing code.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 111, &#167; 1, p. 451; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 18-1501; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-132; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 748, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1304, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB42, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>