
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" id="id5" statutenumber="18-132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-132</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Adoption of standard codes.</catchline><para>(1) The city council of any city or board of trustees of any village may adopt by ordinance the conditions, provisions, limitations, and terms of a plumbing code, an electrical code, a fire prevention code, a building or construction code, and any other standard code which contains rules and regulations printed as a code in book, pamphlet, or electronic form, by reference to such code, or portions thereof, alone, without setting forth in the ordinance the conditions, provisions, limitations, and terms of such code. When any such code, or portion thereof, has been incorporated by reference into such ordinance, as provided in this section, it shall have the same force and effect as though it had been written in its entirety in such ordinance without further or additional publication thereof.</para><para>(2) Not less than one copy of such standard code, or portion thereof, shall be kept for use and examination by the public in the office of the city clerk or village clerk prior to the adoption thereof and as long as such standard code is in effect in such city or village.</para><para>(3) Any building or construction code implemented under this section shall be adopted and enforced as provided in section 71-6406.</para><para>(4) If there is no ordinance adopting a plumbing code in effect in a city or village, the 2018 Uniform Plumbing Code designated by the American National Standards Institute as an American National Standard shall serve as the plumbing code for all the area within the jurisdiction of the city or village. Nothing in this section shall be interpreted as creating an obligation for the city or village to inspect plumbing work done within its jurisdiction to determine compliance with the plumbing code.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 111, &#167; 1, p. 451; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 18-1501; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-132; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 748, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1304, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB42, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB131, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB159, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>