<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-412.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-412.06</statuteno><catchline>Electric service; contracts to purchase authorized; limitation on liability.</catchline><para>(1) Any city or village owning or operating electric generation or transmission facilities may enter into contracts for the purchase of electric energy, power and energy, or capacity, or any combination thereof, upon such terms and conditions and for such periods as the governing body of such city or village may by ordinance authorize. Such terms and conditions may obligate the city or village to make payment under the contracts during such time or times as the facility, if any, to which the contract pertains may be incapable of being operated or may not be in operation for any reason. Any contract authorized by this section may be entered into by the city or village with nonprofit corporations of this or any other state among whose purposes is the financing of electric properties, projects or undertakings for such city or village, other municipalities of this or any other state, public power districts and public power and irrigation districts of this or any other state, other governmental entities or agencies of this or any other state or the federal government, electric cooperatives or electric membership cooperatives of this or any other state, or investor-owned electric utilities organized under the laws of any other state. The obligation and liability of such city or village under the contract shall be limited to the electric revenue of such city or village, unless prior to the execution of the contract by the city or village the contract shall have been approved by a majority of the qualified voters of the city or village voting upon the question.</para><para>(2) Any city or village may enter into contracts for the purchase of electric power to be generated by a project as provided in sections 70-1701 to 70-1705.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 60, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 969, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>