<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" id="id00" statutenumber="18-1753"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1753</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Annexation; additional population; report to Tax Commissioner; calculations.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Any city or village annexing territory which thereby adds additional population to the city or village shall report such annexation to the Tax Commissioner. The annexing city or village shall provide the Tax Commissioner with a copy of the ordinance annexing the territory and specify the effective date of the annexation. The annexing city or village shall provide its calculation of the number of additional residents added to the population of the city or village by reason of the annexation and the new combined total population of the city or village and shall inform the Tax Commissioner of the source and date of the federal census relied upon in the calculations.</para><para id="id00">(2)(a) All calculations of additional population shall be based upon federal census figures from the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census.</para><para id="id00">(b) If the boundaries of the territory annexed and those of federal census enumeration districts are the same, or if federal census enumeration districts are wholly contained within the boundaries of the area annexed, the most recent federal census figures for such enumeration districts shall be added directly to the population of the city or village.</para><para id="id00">(c) If the federal census enumeration districts are partly within and partly without the boundaries of the territory annexed, the federal census figures for such enumeration districts shall be adjusted by reasonable interpretation and supplemented by other evidence to arrive at a figure for the number of people residing in the area annexed as such population existed in that area at the time of the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census. Reasonable interpretation shall include, but not be limited to, the following methods: An actual house count of the annexed territory multiplied by the average number of persons per household as this information existed at the time of the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census; or multiplying the population that existed at the time of the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census in the enumeration district by a ratio of the actual current population of the enumeration district divided in the same manner as the annexation.</para><para id="id00">(d) The population of the city or village following annexation shall be (i) the population of the city or village as reported by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census or (ii) the population of the city or village as reported by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census plus the population of the territory annexed as calculated in subdivisions (b) and (c) of this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 726, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1127, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 21. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>