<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-1901" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1901</statuteno><catchline>Plumbing board; members; appointment; qualifications; terms; quorum; organization; vacancies; how filled; bond; duties.</catchline><para>(1) In cities of the metropolitan class, there shall be a plumbing board of eight members. The plumbing board shall consist of an architect licensed to practice in the State of Nebraska and engaged in business in a city of the metropolitan class, a mechanical engineer licensed to practice in the State of Nebraska and engaged in business in a city of the metropolitan class, two journeymen plumbers, two master plumbers, one member of the general public who is not associated with the plumbing business, and a chief health officer who shall serve as a nonvoting member of the board. Such members shall be appointed by the mayor by and with the consent of the city council. A member shall continue to serve until his or her successor has been appointed and qualified.</para><para>(2) In cities of the primary class, there may be a plumbing board consisting of five members. The plumbing board shall consist of the Director of Building and Safety of the city, a registered professional mechanical engineer licensed to practice in the State of Nebraska and engaged in business in the city, the chief plumbing inspector for the city, one master plumber, and one journeyman plumber. The mechanical engineer, the master plumber, and the journeyman plumber shall be appointed by the mayor by and with the consent of the city council or, in cities having a city manager, by the city manager.</para><para>(3) In all cities of the first class, cities of the second class, and villages, there may be a plumbing board of not less than four members, consisting of at least one member to be known as the chief health officer of the city or village, one member to be known as the plumbing inspector of the city or village, one journeyman plumber, and one master plumber. The journeyman and master plumbers shall be appointed by the mayor by and with the consent of the city council, by the chairperson by and with the consent of the village board of trustees, or, in cities having a city manager, by the city manager.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, in cities where a city-county health department has been established and is maintained as provided in section 71-1628, chief health officer shall mean the health director of such department.</para><para>(5) Except for cities of the metropolitan class and primary class and as provided in subsection (4) of this section, the chief health officer and plumbing inspector shall be appointed by and hold office during the term of office of the mayor, city manager, or chairperson of the village board of trustees, as the case may be. The terms of office of the journeymen and master plumbers shall be for four years. Upon expiration of the term of each appointed member, appointments shall be made for succeeding terms by the same process as the previous appointments.</para><para>(6) The plumbing inspector and journeymen and master plumbers shall be licensed plumbers. The plumbers appointed to the plumbing board in cities of the metropolitan class shall be licensed within such cities. The chief plumbing inspector shall be licensed within such city or village and shall act in a direct advisory capacity to the plumbing board.</para><para>(7) In cities of the metropolitan class, four voting members of the plumbing board shall constitute a quorum, and in all other cities and villages, three members of the plumbing board shall constitute a quorum. The plumbing board shall organize by selecting a chairperson, and in cities of the metropolitan class a recording secretary shall be furnished to the plumbing board. The city or village shall make available to the plumbing board a location for the board to meet and conduct business at a time convenient for the members of the board. All vacancies in the plumbing board may be filled by the mayor and city council, city manager, or chairperson and village board of trustees as provided in this section. Any member of the plumbing board may be removed from office for cause by the district court of the county in which such city or village is situated. The governing body of the city or village may require that each member of the plumbing board give bond in the sum of one thousand dollars, conditioned according to law, the cost of which may be paid by such city or village.</para><para>(8) The plumbing board in a city of the metropolitan class shall maintain a record of all complaints filed in the city regarding violations of the plumbing code and a record of the disposition of each such complaint.</para><para>(9) If two or more municipalities organize a joint plumbing board pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act, appointments shall be made according to the agreements providing for such joint board and the members of such board shall be residents of such cities or villages or live within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of such cities or villages.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 321; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5274; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4497; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-301; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-301; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 57, &#167; 1, p. 210; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 103, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 153, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 53, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1221, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 36, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 666, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB107, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>