<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-1805"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1805</statuteno><catchline>Revenue bonds issued prior to October 23, 1967; sections, how construed.</catchline><para>The provisions of sections 18-1803 to 18-1805 shall not in any way govern, impair, or restrict the issuance of revenue bonds authorized by the municipality prior to October 23, 1967.</para><para>The provisions of sections 18-1803 to 18-1805 shall be independent of and in addition to any other provisions of the laws of the State of Nebraska or provisions of home rule charters, and revenue bonds may be issued under the provisions of sections 18-1803 to 18-1805 for any purpose authorized in such sections even though other provisions of the laws of the State of Nebraska or provisions of home rule charters may provide for the issuance of revenue bonds for the same or similar purposes. The provisions of sections 18-1803 to 18-1805 shall not be considered amendatory of or limited by any other provisions of the laws of the State of Nebraska or provisions of home rule charters, and revenue bonds may be issued under the provisions of sections 18-1803 to 18-1805 without complying with the restrictions or requirements of any other provisions of the laws of the State of Nebraska, except when specifically required by sections 18-1803 to 18-1805, or without complying with the restrictions or requirements of home rule charters. Nothing in sections 18-1803 to 18-1805 shall prohibit or limit the issuance of revenue bonds in accordance with the provisions of other applicable laws of the State of Nebraska or of home rule charters if the governing body shall determine to issue such revenue bonds under such other laws or charter or otherwise limit the provisions of any home rule charter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 80, &#167; 3, p. 256; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 825, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 420, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc>