<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id74">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" id="id76" statutenumber="18-1741"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1741</statuteno><catchline id="id79">Handicapped or
disabled persons; parking permits;
nontransferable; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) This section
applies until the implementation date designated by the Director of Motor
Vehicles under section 60-3,113.01.</para><para>(2)
A handicapped or disabled parking permit shall not be transferable
and shall be used only by the party to whom issued or for the motor vehicle
for which issued and only for the purpose for which the
permit is issued. A
handicapped or disabled parking permit shall be displayed by hanging the permit
from the motor vehicle's rearview mirror so as to be clearly visible through
the front windshield. A handicapped or disabled parking permit shall be displayed
on the dashboard only when there is no rearview mirror. No person
shall alter or reproduce in any manner a handicapped
or disabled parking permit. No person shall knowingly hold more than the allowed number of handicapped or disabled parking permits or
knowingly provide false information on an application for a handicapped or disabled parking permit. No person
who is not the holder of a handicapped or disabled parking permit issued to
him or her as a handicapped or disabled person shall display a handicapped
or disabled parking permit and park in a space or access aisle designated
for the exclusive use of a handicapped or disabled person. No person who is
the holder of a handicapped or disabled parking permit issued for the use
of such person when transporting a handicapped or disabled person shall display
his or her handicapped or disabled parking permit and park in a space or access
aisle designated for the exclusive use of a handicapped or disabled person
unless a handicapped or disabled person will
enter or exit the motor vehicle while it is parked in a designated
space or access aisle. No person who is not the holder of a handicapped or
disabled parking permit issued for use when a vehicle is transporting a handicapped
or disabled person shall display a handicapped or disabled parking permit
and park in a space or access aisle designated for the exclusive use of a
handicapped or disabled person unless a handicapped or disabled person will enter or exit the motor vehicle while
it is parked in a designated space or access aisle. Any violation
of this section shall constitute a handicapped parking infraction as defined in section 18-1741.01 and shall
be subject to the penalties and procedures set forth in sections 18-1741.01
to 18-1741.07.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 13, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 146, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 717, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 593, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1211, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 31, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 809, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
