<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" id="id5" statutenumber="18-1736"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1736</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Handicapped or disabled
persons; designation of parking spaces.</catchline><para>(1) A city or village
may designate parking spaces, including access aisles, for the exclusive use
of (a) handicapped or disabled persons whose motor vehicles display the distinguishing
license plates issued to handicapped or disabled persons pursuant to section
60-3,113, (b) handicapped or disabled persons whose motor vehicles display
a distinguishing license plate issued to a handicapped or disabled person
by another state, (c) such other handicapped or disabled persons or temporarily
handicapped or disabled persons whose motor vehicles display a handicapped
or disabled parking permit, and (d) such other motor vehicles which display
a handicapped or disabled parking permit.</para>
<para>(2) If a city or village so designates a parking space or access aisle,
it shall be indicated by posting aboveground and immediately adjacent to and
visible from each space or access aisle a sign as described in section 18-1737.
In addition to such sign, the space or access aisle may also be indicated
by blue paint on the curb or edge of the paved portion of the street adjacent
to the space or access aisle.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of sections 18-1736 to 18-1741.07:</para>
<para>(a) Access aisle has the same meaning as in section 60-302.01;</para>
<para>(b) Handicapped or disabled parking permit has the same meaning as in
section 60-331.01;</para>
<para>(c) Handicapped or disabled person has the same meaning as in section
60-331.02; and</para>
<para>(d) Temporarily handicapped or disabled person has the same meaning
as in section 60-352.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 13, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 146, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 717, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 482, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 598, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 593, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1211, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 299, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 809, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 225; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB657, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>