<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id54">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" id="id56" statutenumber="18-1739"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1739</statuteno><catchline id="id59">Handicapped or
disabled persons; parking permits;
contents; issuance; duplicate permit.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies until the implementation
date designated by the Director of Motor Vehicles under section 60-3,113.01.</para>
<para>(2) The handicapped or disabled parking permit to be
issued pursuant to section 18-1738 or 18-1738.01 shall be constructed of a
durable plastic designed to resist normal wear or fading for the term of the
permit's issuance and printed so as to minimize the possibility of alteration
following issuance. The permit shall be of a design, size, configuration,
color, and construction and contain such information as specified in the regulations adopted by the United
States Department of Transportation in the Uniform System for Parking for
Persons with Disabilities, 23 C.F.R. part 1235, as such regulations existed
on January 1, 2011.</para>
<para>(3) Until October 1, 2011, in addition
to the requirements of subsection (2) of this section, the handicapped or disabled parking permit
shall show the expiration date and such identifying information with regard
to the handicapped or disabled person or temporarily handicapped or disabled
person to whom it is issued as is necessary to the enforcement of sections
18-1736 to 18-1741.07 as determined by the Department of Motor Vehicles. The
expiration date information shall be distinctively color-coded so as to identify
by color the year in which the permit is due to expire.</para>
<para>(4) No handicapped or disabled parking permit shall
be issued to any person or for any motor vehicle if any permit has been issued to such person
or for such motor vehicle and such permit has been suspended pursuant to section 18-1741.02. At the expiration of such suspension,
a permit may be renewed in the manner provided for renewal in sections 18-1738,
18-1738.01, and 18-1740.</para>
<para>(5) A duplicate handicapped or disabled parking permit
may be provided without cost up
to two times during any single permit period if a permit
is destroyed, lost, or stolen. Such duplicate permit shall be issued as provided in section 18-1738 or 18-1738.01,
whichever is applicable, except that a newly completed medical
form need not be provided if a completed medical form submitted at the time
of the most recent application for a permit or its renewal is on file with
the clerk or designated county official or the Department of Motor Vehicles.
A duplicate permit shall be valid for the remainder of the period for which
the original permit was issued. If
a person has been issued two duplicate permits under this subsection and needs
another permit, such person shall reapply for a new permit under section 18-1738
or 18-1738.01, whichever is applicable.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 13, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 146, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 717, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 482, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 598, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 516, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 928, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 593, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1211, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 31, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 809, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB331, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB212, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>