<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-1750" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1750</statuteno><catchline>Notes for anticipated receipts; issuance; payment; loans from federal government.</catchline><para>(1) Municipalities may issue notes up to seventy percent of the unexpended balance of total anticipated receipts for the current year and the following year. Total anticipated receipts for the current year and the following year shall mean a sum equal to the anticipated receipts from the current existing total levy multiplied by two.</para><para>(2) Municipalities may execute and deliver in evidence of such anticipated receipts their promissory notes, which they may make and negotiate, bearing a rate of interest set by the city council or village board of trustees and maturing not more than two years from the date thereof. Such notes, before they are negotiated, shall be presented to the city treasurer or village treasurer and registered by him or her and shall be payable out of the funds collected by such municipality in the order of their registration after the payment of prior registered warrants, but prior to the payment of any warrant subsequently registered, except that if both warrants and notes are registered, the total of such registered notes and warrants shall not exceed one hundred percent of the unexpended balance of the total anticipated receipts of such municipality for the current year and the following year. For the purpose of making such calculation, such total anticipated receipts shall not include any anticipated receipts against which the municipality has issued notes pursuant to this section in either the current or the immediately preceding year.</para><para>(3) In addition to the provisions of subsections (1) and (2) of this section, municipalities may accept interest-free or low-interest loans from the federal government and may execute and deliver in evidence thereof their promissory notes maturing not more than twenty years from the date of execution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 191; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 112. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>