<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" id="id33" statutenumber="18-1214"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1214</statuteno><catchline id="id36">Motor vehicles; annual
motor vehicle fee; use.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided
in subsection (3) of this section, the governing body of any city or village
shall have power to require any individual whose primary residence or person
who owns a place of business which is within the limits of the city or village
and that owns and operates a motor vehicle within such limits to pay an annual
motor vehicle fee and to require the payment of such fee upon the change of
ownership of such vehicle. All such fees which may be provided for under this
subsection shall be used exclusively for constructing, repairing, maintaining,
or improving streets, roads, alleys, public ways, or parts thereof or for
the amortization of bonded indebtedness when created for such purposes.</para>
<para>(2) No motor vehicle fee shall be required under this section if (a)
a vehicle is used or stored but temporarily in such city or village for a
period of six months or less in a twelve-month period, (b) an individual does
not have a primary residence or a person does not own a place of business
within the limits of the city or village and does not own and operate a motor
vehicle within the limits of the city or village, or (c) an individual is
a full-time student attending a postsecondary institution within the limits
of the city or village and the motor vehicle's situs under the Motor Vehicle
Certificate of Title Act is different from the place at which he or she is
attending such institution.</para>
<para>(3) After December 31, 2012, no motor vehicle fee shall be required
of any individual whose primary residence is or person who owns a place of
business within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of such city or village.</para>
<para>(4) The fee shall be paid to the county treasurer of the county
in which such city or village is located when the registration fees as provided
in the Motor Vehicle Registration Act are paid. Such fees shall be credited by the county treasurer to the road fund
of such city or village.</para>
<para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Limits of the city or village includes the extraterritorial zoning
jurisdiction of such city or village; and</para>
<para>(b) Person includes bodies corporate, societies, communities, the public
generally, individuals, partnerships, limited liability companies, joint-stock
companies, cooperatives, and associations. Person does not include any federal,
state, or local government or any political subdivision thereof.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 348, &#167; 3, p. 1119; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 958, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 57, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 112, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 224; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB49, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB81, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act,</emphasis> see section 60-101.</para><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>