<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-1002"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1002</statuteno><catchline>Site; purchase; payment.</catchline><para>Whenever the Nebraska National Guard and State Guard desire any city or village in this state to acquire at the cost of not to exceed ten thousand dollars to such city or village by condemnation, or otherwise, any lot, piece or parcel of land within the corporate limits of such city or village for a state armory site, the Adjutant General shall notify the municipal clerk of the local governing body thereof in writing to that effect. The clerk shall present the notice to the local governing body at its next regular or special meeting; and, if a majority of the members thereof, the vote thereon to be recorded by yeas and nays in the minutes of the proceedings of such city or village, shall favor the acquisition of said lot, piece or parcel of land, as aforesaid, they shall so order by resolution duly passed and approved and spread at large upon the minutes. The mayor or chairman of the board of trustees, as the case may be, shall thereupon designate a committee from the local governing body to negotiate with the owner or owners of said real estate for the purchase thereof for the purposes and uses aforesaid. If the committee and the owners are able to agree on the price, value and title of the land, the committee shall report in writing its agreement with the owners to the local governing body. If the agreement is ratified, approved, and confirmed in all things by the local governing body by a majority vote of its members, by ordinance upon receipt of a deed properly executed, approved as to form and substance by the city or village attorney in writing, from the owner or owners, as grantors to the city or village, as the case may be, as grantee, said governing body shall direct the issuance through its proper officers of warrants upon the state armory site fund, as authorized by sections 18-1005 and 18-1006. Such warrants so issued shall be drawn payable to the owner or owners of the land.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, Spec. Sess., c. 10, &#167; 1, p. 70; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 130, &#167; 7, p. 492; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 18-1801; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-1002.</para></source></law></legaldoc>