<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-1203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1203</statuteno><catchline>Musical and amusement organizations; tax; amount; petition for higher tax; election.</catchline><para>All incorporated cities and villages within the State of Nebraska are hereby expressly authorized, upon a three-fourths vote of all of the members elected to the city or village board, to levy not to exceed two and one-tenth cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such cities or villages each year to establish and maintain a vocal, instrumental, or amusement organization for the purpose of rendering free public concerts, music festivals, and entertainments within such city or village limits for the people of such city or village and locality. When such vote has been so made and recorded by the city council or village board, a tax of not to exceed two and one-tenth cents on each one hundred dollars of the taxable value of all the taxable property of such city or village shall be levied by such city or village, in addition to all other general and special taxes, for the support, maintenance, and necessary expenses of such vocal, instrumental, or amusement organization. Any incorporated city or village may levy each year a tax of not exceeding three and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such municipality for the maintenance of a municipal band or other vocal, instrumental, or amusement organization for the purpose of rendering free public concerts, music festivals, and entertainments when a petition signed by ten percent of the legal voters of an incorporated city or village, as shown by the last regular municipal election, is filed with the clerk of the city or village and requests the following question to be submitted to the voters of the city or village: Shall a tax of not exceeding .............. cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property of ................, Nebraska, be levied each year for the purpose of providing a fund for the maintenance of a municipal band or other vocal, instrumental, or amusement organization for the purpose of rendering free public concerts, music festivals, and entertainments? When such petition is filed, the board of trustees, council, or city commission shall cause the question to be submitted to the voters of the city or village at the next general municipal election, and if a majority of the votes cast at the election favor such proposition, the board of trustees, council, or city commission shall then levy such tax to maintain such municipal band or other vocal, instrumental, or amusement organization for the purposes enumerated in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 219, &#167;&#167; 1, 2, p. 488; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167;&#167; 4471, 4472; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 40, &#167; 1, p. 172; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 18-901; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-1203; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 287, &#167; 30, p. 948; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 73. </para></source></law></legaldoc>