<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-1501"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1501</statuteno><catchline>Acquisition; buildings; improvements; authorized; charges.</catchline><para>Any city or village, within the State of Nebraska, is hereby authorized to acquire by lease, for a term not to exceed twenty-five years, purchase, condemnation, or otherwise, the necessary land within or without such city or village for the purpose of establishing an aviation field and to erect thereon such buildings and make such improvements, as may be necessary for the purpose of adapting the field to the use of aerial traffic, and may, from time to time, fix and establish a schedule of charges for the use thereof, which charges shall be used in connection with the maintenance and operation of any such field and the activities thereof. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 35, &#167; 1, p. 147; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-801; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 39, &#167; 1(1), p. 182; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-801; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 53, &#167; 1, p. 180; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 66, p. 478. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Acquisition of airports and landing fields by purchase, condemnation, or otherwise,</emphasis> see sections 3-203 and 3-204.</para><para><emphasis>Assistance from the Department of Aeronautics,</emphasis> see Chapter 3, article 1.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>City is liable for negligence in operation of aviation field. Brasier v. Cribbett, 166 Neb. 145, 88 N.W.2d 235 (1958).</para><para>A majority vote is sufficient to authorize issuance of bonds to establish aviation field under home rule charter of the city of Lincoln. State ex rel. City of Lincoln v. Johnson, 117 Neb. 301, 220 N.W. 273 (1928).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>