<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-1722"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1722</statuteno><catchline>Buildings; repair, rehabilitate, or demolish; remove; cost; special assessment; civil action.</catchline><para>If any owner of any building or structure fails, neglects, or refuses to comply with notice by or on behalf of any city or village to repair, rehabilitate, or demolish and remove a building or structure which is an unsafe building or structure and a public nuisance, the city or village may proceed with the work specified in the notice to the property owner. A statement of the cost of such work shall be transmitted to the governing body. The governing body may:</para><para>(1) Levy the cost as a special assessment against the lot or real estate upon which the building or structure is located. Such special assessment shall be a lien on the real estate and shall be collected in the manner provided for special assessments; or</para><para>(2) Collect the cost from the owner of the building or structure and enforce the collection by civil action in any court of competent jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 101, &#167; 1, p. 476; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 964, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Section 19-2422 applies to and authorizes an appeal from a special assessment levied under the authority of subdivision (1) of this section. Main St Properties v. City of Bellevue, 309 Neb. 738, 962 N.W.2d 333 (2021).</para><para>The notice provided an owner was not sufficient to meet due process requirements where the notice did not inform the owner of the specific allegations concerning the building's condition or what was necessary in order to repair or rehabilitate the structure. Blanchard v. City of Ralston, 4 Neb. App. 692, 549 N.W.2d 652 (1996).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>