<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-1502" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>18-1502</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; terms; interest; approval by electors.</catchline><para>For the purpose of acquiring and improving an aviation field as authorized in section 18-1501, any city or village may issue and sell bonds of such city or village to be designated aviation field bonds to provide the necessary funds for such aviation field in an amount not to exceed seven-tenths of one percent of the taxable valuation of all the taxable property in such city or village. Such bonds shall become due in not to exceed twenty years from the date of issuance and shall draw interest payable semiannually or annually. Such bonds may not be sold for less than par and in no case without the proposition of issuing the same having first been submitted to the legal electors of such city or village at a general or special election held in such city or village and a majority of the votes cast upon the question of issuing the bonds being in favor thereof. The authority to sell such bonds shall not be limited by any other provision of law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 35, &#167; 1, p. 148; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 19-801; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 39, &#167; 1(2), p. 182; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 19-802; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 34, &#167; 17, p. 170; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 15, &#167; 12, p. 89; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 53, &#167; 2, p. 181; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 50, &#167; 2, p. 170; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 67, p. 313; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 85. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Revised Airports Act,</emphasis> section included, see section 3-238.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Airport Authority Act did not amend this section as it was an independent act dealing with a different subject. Obitz v. Airport Authority of City of Red Cloud, 181 Neb. 410, 149 N.W.2d 105 (1967).</para><para>This section relates to right of municipality to acquire an airport or other air navigation facility. Brasier v. Cribbett, 166 Neb. 145, 88 N.W.2d 235 (1958).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>