<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2527"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2527</statuteno><catchline>Referendum powers; scope.</catchline><para>The power of referendum allows citizens the right to repeal or amend existing measures, or portions thereof, affecting the governance of each municipal subdivision in the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 807, &#167; 27. </para></source>
<annotation><para>Although the Nebraska Constitution does not prohibit a municipal ballot measure from asking voters to approve distinct and independent propositions in a single vote, a common-law single subject rule does prohibit this type of municipal ballot measure to preserve the integrity of the municipal electoral process. City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para>
<para>A municipal ballot measure with separate provisions does not violate the common-law single subject rule if each of its provisions has a natural and necessary connection with each other and together are part of one general subject. City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para>
<para>A proposed municipal ballot measure is invalid if it would (1) compel voters to vote for or against distinct propositions in a single vote&#8212;when they might not do so if presented separately, (2) confuse voters on the issues they are asked to decide, or (3) create doubt as 
to what action they have authorized after the election. City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para>
<para>Courts liberally construe grants of municipal initiative and referendum powers to permit, rather than restrict, the power and to attain, rather than prevent, its object. City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para>
<para>To determine whether petitioners for a municipal ballot measure are acting under their initiative power or their referendum power, a court should look to the function of their proposed ballot measure&#8212;not its label. City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para>
<para>When petitioners for a municipal ballot measure are not seeking to repeal an ordinance, the correct distinction for determining whether their proposed measure falls under the petitioners' initiative power or their referendum power is whether the proposed measure would enact a new ordinance (initiative power) or would amend an existing ordinance (referendum power). City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc>