<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2115"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2115</statuteno><catchline>Plan; public hearing; notice.</catchline>
<para>(1) The governing body of the city shall hold a public hearing on any
redevelopment plan or substantial modification thereof recommended by the
authority, after reasonable public notice thereof by publication at least
once a week for two consecutive weeks in a legal newspaper of general circulation
in the community, the time of the hearing to be at least ten days from the
last publication. The notice shall describe the time, date, place, and purpose
of the hearing and shall specifically identify the area to be redeveloped
under the plan. All interested parties shall be afforded at such public hearing
a reasonable opportunity to express their views respecting the proposed redevelopment
plan.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, the governing
body of the city or such other division of the city or person as the governing
body shall designate shall, at least ten days prior to the public hearing
required by subsection (1) of this section, provide
notice of the hearing to each registered neighborhood association whose area
of representation is located in whole or in part within a one-mile radius
of the area to be redeveloped in the manner requested by the association and mail
notice of the hearing by first-class United States mail, postage prepaid,
or by certified mail to the president or chairperson of the governing body of each
county, school district, community college, educational service unit, and
natural resources district in which the real property subject to such plan
or major modification is located and whose property tax receipts would be
directly affected. The notice shall set out the time, date, place, and purpose
of the hearing and shall include a map of sufficient size to show the area
to be redeveloped.</para>
<para>(3) If the planning board or planning commission of the city will conduct
a public hearing on the redevelopment plan or substantial modification thereof,
the governing body of the city or such other division of the city or person
as the governing body shall designate shall, at least ten days prior to the
public hearing, provide notice
of the hearing to each registered neighborhood association whose area of representation
is located in whole or in part within a one-mile radius of the area to be
redeveloped in the manner requested by the association and mail
notice of the hearing by first-class United States mail, postage prepaid,
or by certified mail to the president or chairperson of the governing body of each
county, school district, community college, educational service unit, and
natural resources district in which the real property subject to such plan
or major modification is located and whose property tax receipts would be
directly affected. The notice shall set out the time, date, place, and purpose
of the hearing and shall include a map of sufficient size to show the area
to be redeveloped. If the registered neighborhood association has been given
notice of the public hearing to be held by the planning board or planning
commission in conformity with the provisions of this subsection, the governing
body or its designee shall not be required to comply with the notice requirements
of subsection (2) of this section.</para>
<para>(4) Each neighborhood association desiring to receive notice of any
hearing as provided in this section shall register with the city's planning
department or, if there is no planning department, with the city clerk. The
registration shall include a description of the area of representation of
the association, the name of and contact information for the individual designated
by the association to receive the notice on its behalf, and the requested manner of service, whether by email
or regular, certified, or registered mail. Registration of the
neighborhood association for the purposes of this section shall be accomplished
in accordance with such other rules and regulations as may be adopted and
promulgated by the city.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 224, &#167; 6(8), p. 807; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1615; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 52, &#167; 10, p. 258; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 19-2615; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 140, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 875, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB679, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>