<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2711"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2711</statuteno><catchline>Land purchase; creation of loan fund; additional requirements.</catchline><para>(1) If the proposed economic development program involves the purchase of or option to purchase land, the proposed plan shall also specify the manner in which tracts of land will be identified for purchase or option to purchase and whether or not the city proposes to use the proceeds from the future sale of such land for additional land purchases.</para><para>(2) If the proposed economic development program involves the creation of a loan fund, the proposed plan shall also specify:</para><para>(a) The types of financial assistance that will be available, stating the maximum proportion of financial assistance that will be provided to any single qualifying business and specifying the criteria that will be used to determine the appropriate level of assistance;</para><para>(b) The criteria and procedures that will be used to determine the necessity and appropriateness of permitting a qualifying business to participate in the loan fund program;</para><para>(c) The criteria for determining the time within which a qualifying business must meet the goals set for it under its participation agreement;</para><para>(d) What personnel or other assistance beyond regular city employees will be needed to assist in the administration of the loan fund program and the manner in which they will be paid or reimbursed;</para><para>(e) The investment strategies that the city will pursue to promote the growth of the loan fund while assuring its security and liquidity; and</para><para>(f) The methods of auditing and verification that will be used by the city to insure that the assistance given is used in an appropriate manner and that the city is protected against fraud or deceit in the conduct or administration of the economic development program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 840, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 732, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>