<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id47">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" id="id49"  statutenumber="18-2123.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2123.01</statuteno><catchline>Redevelopment project with property
outside corporate limits; formerly used defense site; agreement with county
authorized.</catchline><para>(1)
Notwithstanding any other provisions of the Community Development Law to the
contrary, a city may undertake a redevelopment project that includes real
property located outside the corporate limits of such city if the following
requirements have been met:</para>
<para>(a) The real property
located outside the corporate limits of the city is a formerly used defense
site;</para>
<para>(b) The formerly used
defense site is located within the same county as the city approving such
redevelopment project;</para><para>(c) The formerly used defense site is located within a sanitary
and improvement district;</para><para>(d) The governing body of the city approving such redevelopment
project passes an ordinance stating such city's intent to annex the formerly
used defense site in the future; and</para><para>(e) The redevelopment project has been consented to
by any city exercising extraterritorial jurisdiction over the formerly used
defense site.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, formerly used defense site means
real property that was formerly owned by, leased to, or otherwise possessed
by the United States and under the jurisdiction of the United States Secretary
of Defense. Formerly used defense site does not include missile silos.</para>
<para>(3) The inclusion
of a formerly used defense site in any redevelopment project under this section
shall not result in:</para><para>(a) Any change in the service area of any electric utility or natural
gas utility unless such change has been agreed to by the electric utility
or natural gas utility serving the formerly used defense site at the time
of approval of such redevelopment project; or</para><para>(b) Any change in the service
area of any communications company as defined in section 77-2734.04 unless
(i) such change has been agreed to by the communications company serving the
formerly used defense site at the time of approval of such redevelopment project
or (ii) such change occurs pursuant to sections 86-135 to 86-138.</para>
<para>(4) A city approving
a redevelopment project under this section and the county in which the formerly
used defense site is located may enter into an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal
Cooperation Act in which the county agrees to reimburse such city for any
services the city provides to the formerly used defense site after approval
of the redevelopment project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB66, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>