
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" id="id00" statutenumber="18-2113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2113</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Plan; considerations; cost-benefit analysis.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Prior to recommending a redevelopment plan to the governing body for approval, an authority shall consider whether the proposed land uses and building requirements in the redevelopment project area are designed with the general purpose of accomplishing, in conformance with the general plan, a coordinated, adjusted, and harmonious development of the city and its environs which will, in accordance with present and future needs, promote health, safety, morals, order, convenience, prosperity, and the general welfare, as well as efficiency and economy in the process of development, including, among other things, adequate provision for traffic, vehicular parking, the promotion of safety from fire, panic, and other dangers, adequate provision for light and air, the promotion of the healthful and convenient distribution of population, the provision of adequate transportation, water, sewerage, and other public utilities, schools, parks, recreational and community facilities, and other public requirements, the promotion of sound design and arrangement, the wise and efficient expenditure of public funds, and the prevention of the recurrence of insanitary or unsafe dwelling accommodations or conditions of blight.</para><para id="id00">(2) The authority shall conduct a cost-benefit analysis for each redevelopment project whose redevelopment plan includes the division of taxes as provided in section 18-2147. In conducting the cost-benefit analysis, the authority shall use a cost-benefit model developed for use by local projects. Any cost-benefit model used by the authority shall consider and analyze the following factors:</para><para id="id00">(a) Tax shifts resulting from the division of taxes as provided in section 18-2147;</para><para id="id00">(b) Public infrastructure and community public service needs impacts and local tax impacts arising from the approval of the redevelopment project;</para><para id="id00">(c) Impacts on employers and employees of firms locating or expanding within the boundaries of the area of the redevelopment project;</para><para id="id00">(d) Impacts on other employers and employees within the city or village and the immediate area that are located outside of the boundaries of the area of the redevelopment project;</para><para>(e) Impacts on the student populations of school districts within the city or village; and</para><para id="id00">(f) Any other impacts determined by the authority to be relevant to the consideration of costs and benefits arising from the redevelopment project.</para><para>(3) Copies of each cost-benefit analysis conducted pursuant to subsection (2) of this section shall be posted on the city's public website or made available for public inspection at a location designated by the city.</para><para>(4) This section shall not apply to a redevelopment plan that receives an expedited review under section 18-2155.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 224, &#167; 6(6), p. 806; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1613; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 52, &#167; 9, p. 257; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 19-2613; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 875, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 774, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB874, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1021, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>