<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2451"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2451</statuteno><catchline>Power project agencies; books and records; open to public; annual audit.</catchline><para>The books and records of an agency created pursuant to sections 18-2426 to 18-2434 shall be public records and shall be kept at the principal place of business of such agency. The agency books and records shall be open to public inspection at reasonable times and upon reasonable notice. The agency shall annually cause to be filed with the Auditor of Public Accounts an audit of the books, records, and financial affairs of the agency. Such audit shall be made by a certified public accountant or firm of such accountants selected by the agency and shall be conducted in the manner prescribed in section 84-304.01. When the audit has been completed, written copies of the audit shall be placed and kept on file at the principal place of business of the agency and shall be filed with the Auditor of Public Accounts and the Nebraska Power Review Board within one hundred eighty days after the close of the fiscal year of the agency. If any agency created pursuant to sections 18-2426 to 18-2434 fails to file a copy of an audit within the time prescribed in this section, the books, records, and financial affairs of such agency shall, within one hundred eighty days after the close of the fiscal year of the agency, be audited by a certified public accountant or firm of accountants selected by the Auditor of Public Accounts. The cost of the audit shall be paid by the agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 132, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 310, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 969, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB858, &#167; 12. </para><operativedate>August 07, 2020</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>