<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-2101.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2101.01</statuteno><catchline>Creation of agency; cooperation with federal government; taxes, bonds, and notes; other powers.</catchline><para>Cities of all classes and villages of this state are hereby granted power and authority to create a community development agency by ordinance, which agency may consist of the governing body of the city or village or a new or existing municipal division or department, or combination thereof. When such an agency is created, it shall function in the manner prescribed by ordinance and may exercise all of the power and authority granted to a community redevelopment authority in sections 18-2101 to 18-2144. Cities of all classes and villages of this state are also granted power and authority to do all community development activities, and to do all things necessary to cooperate with the federal government in all matters relating to community development program activities as a grantee, or as an agent or otherwise, under the provisions of the federal Housing and Community Development Act of 1974, as amended through the Housing and Community Development Amendments of 1981. Whenever such a city exercises the power conferred in this section, it may levy taxes for the exercise of such jurisdiction and authority and may issue general obligation bonds, general obligation notes, revenue bonds, and revenue notes including general obligation and revenue refunding bonds and notes for the purposes set forth in such sections and under the power granted to any authority described.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 299, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 445, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 158, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 986, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 71, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>