<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-2107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2107</statuteno><catchline>Authority; powers and duties.</catchline>
<para>An authority shall constitute a public body corporate and politic, exercising
public and essential governmental functions and having all the powers necessary
or convenient to carry out and effectuate the purposes and provisions of the
Community Development Law and sections 18-2147 to 18-2151, including the power:</para>
<para>(1) To sue and to be sued; to have a seal and to alter the same at pleasure;
to have perpetual succession; to make and execute contracts and other instruments
necessary or convenient to the exercise of the powers of the authority; and
to make and from time to time amend and repeal bylaws, rules, and regulations
not inconsistent with the Community Development Law;</para>
<para>(2) To prepare or cause to be prepared and recommend redevelopment plans
to the governing body of the city and to undertake and carry out redevelopment
projects within its area of operation;</para>
<para>(3) To arrange or contract for the furnishing or repair, by any person
or agency, public or private, of services, privileges, works, streets, roads,
public utilities, or other facilities for or in connection with a redevelopment
project; and, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the Community
Development Law or any other provision of law, to agree to any conditions
that it may deem reasonable and appropriate attached to federal financial
assistance and imposed pursuant to federal law relating to the determination
of prevailing salaries or wages or compliance with labor standards, in the
undertaking or carrying out of a redevelopment project, and to include in
any contract let in connection with such a project provisions to fulfill such
federally imposed conditions as it may deem reasonable and appropriate;</para>
<para>(4) Within its area of operation, to purchase, lease, obtain options
upon, or acquire by gift, grant, bequest, devise, eminent domain, or otherwise
any real or personal property or any interest therein, together with any improvements
thereon, necessary or incidental to a redevelopment project; to hold, improve,
clear, or prepare for redevelopment any such property; to sell, lease for
a term not exceeding ninety-nine years, exchange, transfer, assign, subdivide,
retain for its own use, mortgage, pledge, hypothecate, or otherwise encumber
or dispose of any real or personal property or any interest therein; to enter
into contracts with redevelopers of property containing covenants, restrictions,
and conditions regarding the use of such property for residential, commercial,
industrial, or recreational purposes or for public purposes in accordance
with the redevelopment plan and such other covenants, restrictions, and conditions
as the authority may deem necessary to prevent a recurrence of substandard
and blighted areas or to effectuate the purposes of the Community Development
Law; to make any of the covenants, restrictions, or conditions of the foregoing
contracts covenants running with the land and to provide appropriate remedies
for any breach of any such covenants or conditions, including the right in
the authority to terminate such contracts and any interest in the property
created pursuant thereto; to borrow money, issue bonds, and provide security
for loans or bonds; to establish a revolving loan fund; to insure or provide
for the insurance of any real or personal property or the operation of the
authority against any risks or hazards, including the power to pay premiums
on any such insurance; to enter into any contracts necessary to effectuate
the purposes of the Community Development Law; and to provide grants, loans,
or other means of financing to public or private parties in order to accomplish
the rehabilitation or redevelopment in accordance with a redevelopment plan.
No statutory provision with respect to the acquisition, clearance, or disposition
of property by other public bodies shall restrict an authority exercising
powers hereunder, in such functions, unless the Legislature shall specifically
so state;</para>
<para>(5) To invest any funds held in reserves or sinking funds or any funds
not required for immediate disbursement in property or securities in which
savings banks or other banks may legally invest funds subject to their control;
and to redeem its bonds at the redemption price established therein or to
purchase its bonds at less than redemption price, and such bonds redeemed
or purchased shall be canceled;</para>
<para>(6) To borrow money and to apply for and accept advances, loans, grants,
contributions, and any other form of financial assistance from the federal
government, from the state, county, municipality, or other public body, or
from any sources, public or private, including charitable funds, foundations,
corporations, trusts, or bequests, for purposes of the Community Development
Law, to give such security as may be required, and to enter into and carry
out contracts in connection therewith; and notwithstanding any other provision
of law, to include in any contract for financial assistance with the federal
government for a redevelopment project such conditions imposed pursuant to
federal law as the authority may deem reasonable and appropriate and which
are not inconsistent with the purposes of the Community Development Law;</para>
<para>(7) Acting through one or more members of an authority or other persons
designated by the authority, to conduct examinations and investigations and
to hear testimony and take proof under oath at public or private hearings
on any matter material for its information; to administer oaths and to issue
commissions for the examination of witnesses who are outside of the state
or unable to attend before the authority or excused from attendance; and to
make available to appropriate agencies or public officials, including those
charged with the duty of abating or requiring the correction of nuisances
or like conditions, demolishing unsafe or insanitary structures, or eliminating
conditions of blight within its area of operation, its findings and recommendations
with regard to any building or property where conditions exist which are dangerous
to the public health, safety, morals, or welfare;</para>
<para>(8) Within its area of operation, to make or have made all surveys,
appraisals, studies, and plans, but not including the preparation of a general
plan for the community, necessary to the carrying out of the purposes of the
Community Development Law and to contract or cooperate with any and all persons
or agencies, public or private, in the making and carrying out of such surveys,
appraisals, studies, and plans;</para>
<para>(9) To prepare plans and provide reasonable assistance for the relocation
of families, business concerns, and others displaced from a redevelopment
project area to permit the carrying out of the redevelopment project to the
extent essential for acquiring possession of and clearing such area or parts
thereof; and to make relocation payments to or with respect to such persons
for moving expenses and losses of property for which reimbursement or compensation
is not otherwise made, including the making of such payments financed by the
federal government;</para>
<para>(10) To make such expenditures as may be necessary to carry out the
purposes of the Community Development Law; and to make expenditures from funds
obtained from the federal government without regard to any other laws pertaining
to the making and approval of appropriations and expenditures;</para>
<para>(11) To certify on or before September 20 of each year to the governing
body of the city the amount of tax to be levied for the succeeding fiscal
year for community redevelopment purposes, not to exceed two and six-tenths
cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of the taxable property
in such city, which levy is subject to allocation under section 77-3443 on
and after July 1, 1998. The governing body shall levy and collect the taxes
so certified at the same time and in the same manner as other city taxes are
levied and collected, and the proceeds of such taxes, when due and as collected,
shall be set aside and deposited in the special account or accounts in which
other revenue of the authority is deposited. Such proceeds shall be employed
to assist in the defraying of any expenses of redevelopment plans and projects,
including the payment of principal and interest on any bonds issued to pay
the costs of any such plans and projects;</para>
<para>(12) To exercise all or any part or combination of powers granted in
this section;</para>
<para>(13) To plan, undertake, and carry out neighborhood development programs
consisting of redevelopment project undertakings and activities in one or
more community redevelopment areas which are planned and carried out on the
basis of annual increments in accordance with the Community Development Law
and sections 18-2145 and 18-2146 for planning and carrying out redevelopment
projects;</para>
<para>(14) To agree with the governing body of the city for the imposition
of an occupation tax for an enhanced employment area; and</para>
<para>(15) To demolish any
structure determined by the governing body of the city to be unsafe or unfit
for human occupancy in accordance with section 18-1722.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 224, &#167; 5, p. 801; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1607; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 52, &#167; 7, p. 253; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 61, &#167; 6, p. 232; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 19-2607; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 106, &#167; 3, p. 491; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 158, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 986, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 52, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 875, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB562, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB729, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The taking of substandard or blighted areas by a city for redevelopment and resale in accordance with an approved redevelopment plan which is in conformity with a general plan for the municipality as a whole as provided for in these sections, is a proper public use for a municipality. Monarch Chemical Works, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 203 Neb. 33, 277 N.W.2d 423 (1979).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>