<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2710.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2710.01</statuteno><catchline>Economic development program; housing for low-income or moderate-income persons; proposed plan; contents; eligibility criteria.</catchline><para>(1) If the proposed economic development program involves the making of grants or loans for the construction or rehabilitation for sale or lease of housing for persons of low or moderate income, the proposed plan shall specify (a) the income levels which will qualify persons for participation in the housing program and (b) the criteria for determining the adjustments to be made to the income of persons to determine their qualification for participation. For purposes of the Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act, the city shall determine low-income and moderate-income standards for the economic development program by basing such standards upon existing federal government guidelines or standards for qualifying for any federal housing assistance program as such levels may be modified by the consideration of existing local and regional economic conditions and income levels.</para><para>(2) In establishing the criteria to be applied in determining appropriate adjustments to the income of persons seeking consideration for participation in the program pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the city shall consider the following factors:</para><para>(a) The amount of income of the person which is available for housing needs;</para><para>(b) The size of the family to reside in each housing unit;</para><para>(c) The cost and condition of housing available in the city;</para><para>(d) Whether the person or any member of the person's family who will be residing in the housing unit is elderly, infirm, or disabled;</para><para>(e) The ability of the person to compete successfully in the private housing market and to pay the amounts the private enterprise market requires for safe, sanitary, and uncrowded housing; and</para><para>(f) Such other factors as the city determines which are particularly relevant to the conditions facing persons seeking new or rehabilitated housing in the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 207, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>