<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2001"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2001</statuteno><catchline>Street improvements; without petition or creation of district; when.</catchline><para>Any city or village may, without petition or creating a street improvement district, grade, curb, gutter, and pave any portion of a street otherwise paved so as to make one continuous paved street, but the portion to be so improved shall not exceed two blocks, including intersections, or thirteen hundred and twenty-five feet, whichever is the lesser. Such city or village may also grade, curb, gutter, and pave any unpaved street or alley which intersects a paved street for a distance of not to exceed one block on either side of such paved street. The improvements authorized by this section may be performed upon any portion of a street or any unpaved street or alley not previously improved to meet or exceed the minimum standards for pavement set by the city or village for its paved streets.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 76, &#167; 1, p. 280; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 75, &#167; 1, p. 307; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 652, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 738, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>The plain language of this section authorized the city to extend paving on one block of a street and assess the paving costs against abutting property owners where, at one end, the new paving adjoined a paved intersection of two paved streets. Johnson v. City of Fremont, 287 Neb. 960, 845 N.W.2d 279 (2014).</para><para>City improperly used this section to pave a three-block area with two gap paving districts. Iverson v. City of North Platte, 243 Neb. 506, 500 N.W.2d 574 (1993).</para><para>The authorization for special assessment for street improvements in sections 18-2001 to 18-2003 does not extend to a street section already paved. Turner v. City of North Platte, 203 Neb. 706, 279 N.W.2d 868 (1979).</para><para>These statutes are clear, unambiguous, and constitutional. Gaughen v. Sloup, 197 Neb. 762, 250 N.W.2d 915 (1977).</para><para>A street covered with material forming a solid aggregate 3 to 5 inches thick consisting of compacted layers of gravel and an oil-type substance and creating a firm, level surface for vehicular travel is paved within the meaning of Nebraska's "gap and extend" law. Benesch v. City of Schuyler, 5 Neb. App. 59, 555 N.W.2d 63 (1996).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>