<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-2805" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2805</statuteno><catchline>Proposed proprietary budget statement; contents; filing.</catchline><para>(1) At least thirty days prior to the start of the fiscal year of each proprietary function, a proposed proprietary budget statement shall be prepared in writing and filed with the municipal clerk containing the following information:</para><para>(a) For the immediately preceding fiscal year, the revenue from all sources, the unencumbered cash balance at the beginning and end of the year, the amount received by taxation, and the amount of actual expenditure;</para><para>(b) For the current fiscal year, actual and estimated revenue from all sources separately stated as to each such source, the actual unencumbered cash balance available at the beginning of the year, the amount received from taxation, and the amount of actual and estimated expenditure, whichever is applicable;</para><para>(c) For the immediately ensuing fiscal year, an estimate of revenue from all sources separately stated as to each such source, the actual or estimated unencumbered cash balance, whichever is applicable, to be available at the beginning of the year, the amounts proposed to be expended during the fiscal year, and the amount of cash reserve based on actual experience of prior years; and</para><para>(d) A uniform summary of the proposed budget statement which shall include a total of all funds maintained for the proprietary function.</para><para>(2) Such statement shall contain the estimated cash reserve for each fiscal year and shall note whether or not such reserve is encumbered. The cash reserve projections shall be based upon the actual experience of prior years.</para><para>(3) Each proprietary budget statement shall be filed on forms prescribed and furnished by the Auditor of Public Accounts following consultation with representatives of such governing bodies as operate proprietary functions subject to the provisions of the Municipal Proprietary Function Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 86, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1066, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>