<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-2125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2125</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; liability; exempt from taxation; anticipation notes; renewal notes; terms; declaration of intent.</catchline><para>Neither the members of an authority nor any person executing the bonds shall be liable personally on the bonds by reason of the issuance thereof. The bonds and other obligations of the authority, and such bonds and obligations shall so state on their face, shall not be a debt of the city and the city shall not be liable on such bonds, except to the extent authorized by sections 18-2147 to 18-2150, nor in any event shall such bonds or obligations be payable out of any funds or properties other than those of said authority acquired for the purposes of sections 18-2101 to 18-2144, except to the extent authorized by sections 18-2147 to 18-2150. Except to the extent otherwise authorized, the bonds shall not constitute an indebtedness within the meaning of any constitutional or statutory debt limitation or restriction. Bonds of an authority are declared to be issued for an essential public and governmental purpose and to be public instrumentalities and, together with interest thereon and income therefrom, shall be exempt from all taxes. All bonds shall be general obligations of the authority issuing same and shall be payable out of any revenue, income, receipts, proceeds, or other money of the authority, except as may be otherwise provided in the instruments themselves.</para><para>An authority shall have power from time to time to issue bond anticipation notes, referred to as notes herein, and from time to time to issue renewal notes, such notes in any case to mature not later than thirty months from the date of incurring the indebtedness represented thereby in an amount not exceeding in the aggregate at any time outstanding the amount of bonds then or theretofore authorized. Payment of such notes shall be made from any money or revenue which the authority may have available for such purpose or from the proceeds of the sale of bonds of the authority, or such notes may be exchanged for a like amount of such bonds. The authority may pledge such money or revenue of the authority, subject to prior pledges thereof, if any, for the payment of such notes, and may in addition secure the notes in the same manner as herein provided for bonds. All notes shall be issued and sold in the same manner as bonds, and any authority shall have power to make contracts for the future sale from time to time of notes on terms and conditions stated in such contracts, and the authority shall have power to pay such consideration as it shall deem proper for any commitments to purchase notes and bonds in the future. Such notes shall also be collaterally secured by pledges and deposits with a bank or trust company, in trust for the payment of such notes, of bonds in an aggregate amount at least equal to the amount of such notes and, in any event, in an amount deemed by the issuing authority sufficient to provide for the payment of the notes in full at the maturity thereof. The authority may provide in the collateral agreement that the notes may be exchanged for bonds held as collateral security for the notes, or that the trustee may sell the bonds if the notes are not otherwise paid at maturity, and apply the proceeds of such sale to the payment of the notes. Such notes shall bear interest at a rate set by the authority, and shall be sold at such price as shall cause an interest cost thereon not to exceed such rate.</para><para>It is the intention hereof that any pledge of revenue, income, receipts, proceeds, or other money made by an authority for the payment of bonds or notes shall be valid and binding from the time such pledge is made; that the revenue, income, receipts, proceeds, and other money so pledged and thereafter received by the authority shall immediately be subject to the lien of such pledge without the physical delivery thereof or further act, and that the lien of any such pledge shall be valid and binding as against all parties having claims of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise against the authority irrespective of whether such parties have notice thereof. Neither the resolution nor any other instrument by which a pledge is created need be recorded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 224, &#167; 10(2), p. 811; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1625; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 61, &#167; 14, p. 239; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 19-2625; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 70, p. 317; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 158, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>