<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2518"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2518</statuteno><catchline>Petition; filed; signature verification; costs; time limitation.</catchline><para>(1) Each signed petition shall be filed with the city clerk for signature verification. The city clerk shall immediately notify the county clerk or election commissioner of the signed petition. Upon the filing of a petition, a municipality, upon passage of a resolution by the governing body of such municipality, and the county clerk or election commissioner of the county in which such municipality is located may by mutual agreement provide that the county clerk or election commissioner shall ascertain whether the petition is signed by the requisite number of voters. The municipality shall reimburse the county for any costs incurred by the county clerk or election commissioner. When the verifying official has determined that one hundred percent of the necessary signatures required by the Municipal Initiative and Referendum Act have been obtained, he or she shall notify the governing body of the municipality of that fact and shall immediately forward to the governing body a copy of the petition.</para><para>(2) In order for an initiative or referendum proposal to be submitted to the governing body and the voters, the necessary signatures shall be on file with the city clerk within six months from the date the prospective petition was authorized for circulation. If the necessary signatures are not obtained by such date, the petition shall be void.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 807, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 171; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Under section 18-2538, if a municipality does not bring an action for declaratory judgment to determine whether a measure is subject to limited referendum or referendum or whether a measure may be enacted by initiative until after it receives notification pursuant to this section, it shall be required to proceed with the initiative or referendum election. Sydow v. City of Grand Island, 263 Neb. 389, 639 N.W.2d 913 (2002).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>