<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2528" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2528</statuteno><catchline>Referendum; measures excluded; measures subject to limited referendum; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The following measures shall not be subject to referendum or limited referendum:</para><para>(a) Measures necessary to carry out contractual obligations, including, but not limited to, those relating to the issuance of or provided for in bonds, notes, warrants, or other evidences of indebtedness, for projects previously approved by a measure which was, or is, subject to referendum or limited referendum or previously approved by a measure adopted prior to July 17, 1982;</para><para>(b) Measures relating to any industrial development projects, subsequent to measures giving initial approval to such projects;</para><para>(c) Measures adopting proposed budget statements following compliance with procedures set forth in the Nebraska Budget Act;</para><para>(d) Measures relating to the immediate preservation of the public peace, health, or safety which have been designated as urgent measures by unanimous vote of those present and voting of the governing body of the municipality and approved by its chief executive officer;</para><para>(e) Measures relating to projects for which notice has been given as provided for in subsection (4) of this section and for which a sufficient referendum petition was not filed within the time limit stated in such notice or which received voter approval after the filing of such petition;</para><para>(f) Resolutions directing the city clerk to cause measures to be submitted to a vote of the people at a special election as provided in sections 18-2524 and 18-2529;</para><para>(g) Resolutions ordering an earlier effective date for measures enacted by initiative as provided in section 18-2526;</para><para>(h) Measures relating to any facility or system adopted or enacted pursuant to the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act by municipalities and which are necessary to carry out contractual obligations provided for in previously issued bonds, notes, warrants, or other evidence of indebtedness;</para><para>(i) Measures that amend, supplement, change, modify, or repeal a zoning regulation, restriction, or boundary and are subject to protest as provided in section 14-405 or 19-905;</para><para>(j) Measures relating to personnel issues, including, but not limited to, establishment, modification, or elimination of any personnel position, policy, salary, or benefit and any hiring, promotion, demotion, or termination of personnel; and</para><para>(k) Measures relating to matters subject to the provisions of the Municipal Natural Gas System Condemnation Act.</para><para>(2) The following measures shall be subject to limited referendum:</para><para>(a) Measures in furtherance of a policy of the municipality or relating to projects previously approved by a measure which was subject to referendum or which was enacted by initiative or has been approved by the voters at an election, except that such measures shall not be subject to referendum or limited referendum for a period of one year after any such policy or project was approved at a referendum election, enacted by initiative, or approved by the voters at an election;</para><para>(b) Measures relating to the acquisition, construction, installation, improvement, or enlargement, including the financing or refinancing of the costs, of public ways, public property, utility systems, and other capital projects and measures giving initial approval for industrial development projects;</para><para>(c) Measures setting utility system rates and charges, except for measures necessary to carry out contractual obligations provided for in previously issued bonds, notes, warrants, or other evidences of indebtedness, and pay rates and salaries for municipal employees other than the members of the governing body and the chief executive officer; and</para><para>(d) Measures relating to any facility or system adopted or enacted pursuant to the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act by municipalities except for measures necessary to carry out contractual obligations provided for in previously issued bonds, notes, warrants, or other evidence of indebtedness.</para><para>(3) Measures subject to limited referendum shall ordinarily take effect thirty days after their passage by the governing body, including an override of any veto, if necessary. Referendum petitions directed at measures subject to limited referendum shall be filed for signature verification pursuant to section 18-2518 within thirty days after such measure's passage by the governing body, including an override of any veto, if necessary, or after notice is first published pursuant to subdivision (4)(c) of this section. If the necessary number of signatures as provided in section 18-2529 or 18-2530 has been obtained within the time limitation, the effectiveness of the measure shall be suspended unless approved by the voters.</para><para>(4) For any measure relating to the acquisition, construction, installation, improvement, or enlargement of public ways, public property, utility systems, or other capital projects or any measure relating to any facility or system adopted or enacted pursuant to the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, a municipality may exempt all subsequent measures relating to the same project from the referendum and limited referendum procedures provided for in the Municipal Initiative and Referendum Act by the following procedure:</para><para>(a) By holding a public hearing on the project, the time and place of such hearing being published at least once not less than five days prior to the date set for hearing in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation within the municipality;</para><para>(b) By passage of a measure approving the project, including an override of a veto if necessary, at a meeting held on any date subsequent to the date of hearing; and</para><para>(c) After passage of such measure, including an override of a veto if necessary, by giving notice as follows: (i) For those projects for which applicable statutes require an ordinance or resolution of necessity, creating a district or otherwise establishing the project, notice shall be given for such project by including either as part of such ordinance or resolution or as part of any publicized notice concerning such ordinance or resolution a statement that the project as described in the ordinance or resolution is subject to limited referendum for a period of thirty days after the first publication of such notice and that, after such thirty-day period, the project and measures related to it will not be subject to any further right of referendum; and (ii) for projects for which applicable statutes do not require an ordinance or resolution of necessity, notice shall be given by publication of a notice concerning such projects stating in general terms the nature of the project and the engineer's estimate of costs of such project and stating that the project described in the notice is subject to limited referendum for a period of thirty days after the first publication of such notice and that, after such thirty-day period, the project and measures related to it will not be subject to any further right of referendum. The notice required by subdivision (c)(ii) of this subsection shall be published in at least one legal newspaper in or of general circulation within the municipality and shall be published not later than fifteen days after passage by the governing body, including an override of a veto, if necessary, of a measure approving the project.</para><para>The right of a municipality to hold such a hearing prior to passage of the measure by the governing body and give such notice after passage of such measure by the governing body to obtain exemption for any particular project in a manner described in this subsection is optional, and no municipality shall be required to hold such a hearing or give such notice for any particular project.</para><para>(5) Nothing in subsections (2) and (4) of this section shall be construed as subjecting to limited referendum any measure related to matters subject to the provisions of the Municipal Natural Gas System Condemnation Act.</para><para>(6) All measures, except as provided in subsections (1), (2), and (4) of this section, shall be subject to the referendum procedure at any time after such measure has been passed by the governing body, including an override of a veto, if necessary, or enacted by the voters by initiative.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 807, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1010, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 504; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 582, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 384, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB163, &#167; 180. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Municipal Natural Gas System Condemnation Act,</emphasis> see section 19-4624.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Budget Act,</emphasis> see section 13-501.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under subsection (1)(a) of this section, a general tax ordinance cannot be a measure necessary to carry out a contractual obligation if the obligation did not exist when the municipality passed it. Subsection (1)(a) does not shield from the referendum process a revenue measure that funds a city's subsequent contractual obligations for a project that was not previously approved by a measure that was subject to referendum. City of North Platte v. Tilgner, 282 Neb. 328, 803 N.W.2d 469 (2011).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>