<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2442"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2442</statuteno><catchline>Construction and other contracts; cost estimate; sealed bids; when; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) An agency shall cause estimates of the costs to be made by some competent engineer or engineers before the agency enters into any contract for:</para><para>(a) The construction, reconstruction, remodeling, building, alteration, maintenance, repair, extension, or improvement, for the use of the agency, of any:</para><para>(i) Power project, power plant, or system; </para><para>(ii) Irrigation works; or </para><para>(iii) Part or section of a project, plant, system, or works described in subdivision (i) or (ii) of this subdivision; or </para><para>(b) The purchase of any materials, machinery, or apparatus to be used in a project, plant, system, or works described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(2) If the estimated cost exceeds the sum of one hundred thousand dollars, no such contract shall be entered into without advertising for sealed bids. </para><para>(3)(a) The provisions of subsection (2) of this section and sections 18-2443 and 18-2444 relating to sealed bids shall not apply to contracts entered into by an agency in the exercise of its rights and powers relating to (i) radioactive material or the energy therefrom, (ii) any technologically complex or unique equipment, (iii) equipment or supplemental labor procurement from an electric utility or from or through an electric utility alliance, or (iv) any maintenance or repair, if the requirements of subdivisions (b) and (c) of this subsection are met.</para><para>(b) A contract described in subdivision (a) of this subsection need not comply with subsection (2) of this section or sections 18-2443 and 18-2444 if:</para><para>(i) The engineer or engineers certify that, by reason of the nature of the subject matter of the contract, compliance with subsection (2) of this section would be impractical or not in the public interest; </para><para>(ii) The engineer's certification is approved by a two-thirds vote of the board; and </para><para>(iii) The agency advertises notice of its intention to enter into such contract, the general nature of the proposed work, and the name of the person to be contacted for additional information by anyone interested in contracting for such work. </para><para>(c) Any contract for which the board has approved an engineer's certificate described in subdivision (b) of this subsection shall be advertised in three issues, not less than seven days between issues, in one or more newspapers of general circulation in the municipality or county where the principal office or place of business of the agency is located, or if no newspaper is so published then in a newspaper qualified to carry legal notices having general circulation therein, and in such additional newspapers or trade or technical periodicals as may be selected by the board in order to give proper notice of its intention to enter into such contract, and any such contract shall not be entered into prior to twenty days after the last advertisement. </para><para>(4) The provisions of subsection (2) of this section and sections 18-2443 and 18-2444 shall not apply to contracts in excess of one hundred thousand dollars entered into for the purchase of any materials, machinery, or apparatus to be used in projects, plants, systems, or works described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section if, after advertising for sealed bids: </para><para>(a) No responsive bids are received; or </para><para>(b) The board of directors of such agency determines that all bids received are in excess of the fair market value of the subject matter of such bids. </para><para>(5) Notwithstanding any other provision of subsection (2) of this section or sections 18-2443 and 18-2444, an agency may, without advertising or sealed bidding, purchase replacement parts or services relating to such replacement parts for any generating unit, transformer, or other transmission and distribution equipment from the original manufacturer of such equipment upon certification by an engineer or engineers that such manufacturer is the only available source of supply for such replacement parts or services and that such purchase is in compliance with standards established by the board. A written statement containing such certification and a description of the resulting purchase of replacement parts or services from the original manufacturer shall be submitted to the board by the engineer or engineers certifying the purchase for the board's approval. After such certification, but not necessarily before the board's review, notice of any such purchase shall be published once a week for at least three consecutive weeks in one or more newspapers of general circulation in the municipality or county where the principal office or place of business of the agency is located and published in such additional newspapers or trade or technical periodicals as may be selected by the board in order to give proper notice of such purchase.</para><para>(6) Notwithstanding any other provision of subsection (2) of this section or sections 18-2443 and 18-2444, an agency may, without advertising or sealed bidding, purchase used equipment and materials on a negotiated basis upon certification by an engineer that such equipment is or such materials are in compliance with standards established by the board. A written statement containing such certification shall be submitted to the board by the engineer for the board's approval.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 132, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 566, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB636, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB939, &#167;  2.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
