<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2714"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2714</statuteno><catchline>Economic development program; established by ordinance; amendment; repeal; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) After approval by the voters of an economic development program, the governing body of the city shall, within forty-five days after such approval, establish the economic development program by ordinance in conformity with the terms of such program as set out in the original enabling resolution.</para><para>(2) After the adoption of the ordinance establishing the economic development program, such ordinance shall only be amended after the governing body of the city (a) gives notice of and holds at least one public hearing on the proposed changes, (b) approves the proposed changes by a two-thirds vote of the members of such governing body, and (c) except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, submits the proposed changes to a new vote of the registered voters of the city in the manner provided in section 18-2713.</para><para>(3) A new vote of the registered voters of the city is not required for the following types of amendments to an economic development program:</para><para>(a) An amendment adding a type of qualifying business to those that are eligible to participate in the economic development program or removing a type of qualifying business from those that are eligible to participate in such program if such addition or removal is recommended by the citizen advisory review committee established under section 18-2715;</para><para>(b) An amendment making corrective changes to comply with the Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act; or</para><para>(c) An amendment making corrective changes to comply with any other existing or future state or federal law.</para><para>(4) The governing body of a city may, at any time after the adoption of the ordinance establishing the economic development program, by a two-thirds vote of the members of the governing body, repeal the ordinance in its entirety and end the economic development program, subject only to the provisions of any existing contracts relating to such program and the rights of any third parties arising from those contracts. Prior to such vote by the governing body, it shall publish notice of its intent to consider the repeal and hold a public hearing on the issue. Any funds in the custody of the city for such economic development program which are not spent or committed at the time of the repeal and any funds to be received in the future from the prior operation of the economic development program shall be placed into the general fund of the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 840, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB471, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1059, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>