
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2117.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2117.01</statuteno><catchline>Plan; report to Property Tax Administrator; contents; compilation of data.</catchline><para>(1)(a) On or before December 1 each year, each city which has approved one or more redevelopment plans which are financed in whole or in part through the division of taxes as provided in section 18-2147 shall provide a report to the Property Tax Administrator on each such redevelopment plan which includes the following information:</para><para>(i) A copy of the redevelopment plan and any amendments thereto, including the date upon which the redevelopment plan was approved, the effective date for dividing the ad valorem tax as provided to the county assessor pursuant to subsection (5) of section 18-2147, and the location and boundaries of the property in the redevelopment project; and</para><para>(ii) A short narrative description of the type of development undertaken by the city or village with the financing and the type of business or commercial activity locating within the redevelopment project area as a result of the redevelopment project.</para><para>(b) If a city has approved one or more redevelopment plans using an expedited review under section 18-2155, the city may file a single report under this subsection for all such redevelopment plans.</para><para>(2) The report required under subsection (1) of this section must be filed each year, regardless of whether the information in the report has changed, except that a city is not required to refile a copy of the redevelopment plan or an amendment thereto if such copy or amendment has previously been filed.</para><para>(3) The Property Tax Administrator shall compile a report for each active redevelopment project, based upon information provided by the cities pursuant to subsection (1) of this section and information reported by the county assessor or county clerk on the certificate of taxes levied pursuant to section 77-1613.01. Each report shall be electronically transmitted to the Clerk of the Legislature not later than March 1 each year. The report may include any recommendations of the Property Tax Administrator as to what other information should be included in the report from the cities so as to facilitate analysis of the uses, purposes, and effectiveness of tax-increment financing and the process for its implementation or to streamline the reporting process provided for in this section to eliminate unnecessary paperwork.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 875, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 774, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB874, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1021, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>