<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2436"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2436</statuteno><catchline>Directors; number; voting; quorum; meetings.</catchline><para>Each participating municipality shall be entitled to appoint one director, but with the approval of each of the participating municipalities as evidenced by an ordinance or resolution of the governing body thereof, an agency's bylaws may contain a provision entitling any of the participating municipalities to appoint more than one director and specifying the number of directors to be appointed by each of the participating municipalities of the agency. The number of directors may be increased or decreased from time to time by an amendment to the bylaws approved by each of the participating municipalities as evidenced by an ordinance or resolution of the governing body thereof. Each participating municipality shall at all times be entitled to appoint at least one director. Each director shall be entitled to one vote, but with the approval of each of the participating municipalities as evidenced by an ordinance or resolution of the governing body thereof, an agency's bylaws may contain a provision entitling any director or directors to cast more than one vote and specifying the number or numbers of votes such director or directors may cast. Unless the bylaws of the agency shall require a larger number, a quorum of the board shall be constituted for the purpose of conducting the business and exercising the powers of the agency and for all other purposes when directors are present who are entitled to cast a majority of the total votes which may be cast by all of the board's directors. Action may be taken upon a vote of a majority of the votes which the directors present are entitled to cast unless the bylaws of the agency shall require a larger number. The manner of scheduling regular board meetings and the method of calling special board meetings, including the giving or waiving notice thereof, shall be as provided in the bylaws. Such meetings may be held by any means permitted by the Open Meetings Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 132, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB199, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>