<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-2512"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2512</statuteno><catchline>Prospective petition; filing; city clerk; duties; revision; procedure; verification; effect.</catchline><para>Before circulating an initiative or referendum petition, the petitioner shall file with the city clerk a prospective petition. The city clerk shall date the prospective petition immediately upon its receipt. The city clerk shall verify that the prospective petition is in proper form and shall provide a ballot title for the initiative or referendum proposal, pursuant to section 18-2513. If the prospective petition is in proper form, the city clerk shall authorize the circulation of the petition and such authorization shall be given within three working days from the date the prospective petition was filed. If the form of the prospective petition is incorrect, the city clerk shall, within three working days from the date the prospective petition was filed, inform the petitioner of necessary changes and request that those changes be made. When the requested changes have been made and the revised prospective petition has been submitted to the city clerk in proper form, the city clerk shall authorize the circulation of the petition and such authorization shall be given within two working days from the receipt of the properly revised petition. Verification by the city clerk that the prospective petition is in proper form does not constitute an admission by the city clerk, governing body, or municipality that the measure is subject to referendum or limited referendum or that the measure may be enacted by initiative.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 807, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1010, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>