<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id933"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-2115.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2115.01</statuteno><catchline>Notice; manner.</catchline><para>(1) Public notice of any hearing required under section 18-2109 or 18-2115 shall be given by publication at least once a week for two consecutive weeks in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the community. The time of the hearing shall be at least ten days from the last publication.</para><para>(2)(a) Notice of any hearing required under section 18-2109 or 18-2115 shall be given to neighborhood associations that have registered under subsection (5) of this section as follows:</para><para>(i) For a hearing under section 18-2109, notice shall be given to each registered neighborhood association whose area of representation is located in whole or in part within a one-mile radius of the area to be declared substandard and blighted; and</para><para>(ii) For a hearing under section 18-2115, notice shall be given to each registered neighborhood association whose area of representation is located in whole or in part within a one-mile radius of the area to be redeveloped.</para><para>(b) Notice under this subsection shall be given at least ten days prior to the hearing in the manner requested by the neighborhood association. The notice shall be deemed given on the date it is sent.</para><para>(3)(a) Notice of any hearing required under section 18-2109 or 18-2115 shall be given to political subdivisions as follows:</para><para>(i) For a hearing under section 18-2109, notice shall be given to the president or chairperson of the governing body of each county, school district, community college area, educational service unit, and natural resources district in which the real property to be declared substandard and blighted is located; and</para><para>(ii) For a hearing under section 18-2115, notice shall be given to the president or chairperson of the governing body of each county, school district, community college area, educational service unit, and natural resources district in which the real property subject to the redevelopment plan or substantial modification thereof is located.</para><para>(b) Notice under this subsection shall be given at least ten days prior to the hearing by certified mail, return receipt requested. The notice shall be deemed given on the date it is mailed by certified mail.</para><para>(4) All notices given under this section shall describe the time, date, place, and purpose of the hearing.</para><para>(5) Each neighborhood association desiring to receive notice of any hearing required under section 18-2109 or 18-2115 shall register with the city's planning department or, if there is no planning department, with the city clerk. The registration shall include a description of the area of representation of the association, the name of and contact information for the individual designated by the association to receive the notice on its behalf, and the requested manner of service, whether by email, first-class mail, or certified mail. Registration of the neighborhood association for purposes of this section shall be accomplished in accordance with such other rules and regulations as may be adopted and promulgated by the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB874, &#167; 13. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>