<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" id="id5" statutenumber="18-2709"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>18-2709</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Qualifying business, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Qualifying business means any corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or sole proprietorship which derives its principal source of income from any of the following: The manufacture of articles of commerce; the conduct of research and development; the processing, storage, transport, or sale of goods or commodities which are sold or traded in interstate commerce; the sale of services in interstate commerce; headquarters facilities relating to eligible activities as listed in this section; telecommunications activities, including services providing advanced telecommunications capability; tourism-related activities; or the production of films, including feature, independent, and documentary films, commercials, and television programs.</para><para>(2) Qualifying business also means:</para><para>(a) In cities of the first and second class and villages, a business that derives its principal source of income from the construction or rehabilitation of housing;</para><para>(b) A business that derives its principal source of income from retail trade, except that no more than forty percent of the total revenue generated pursuant to the Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act for an economic development program in any twelve-month period and no more than twenty percent of the total revenue generated pursuant to the act for an economic development program in any five-year period, commencing from the date of municipal approval of an economic development program, shall be used by the city for or devoted to the use of retail trade businesses. For purposes of this subdivision, retail trade means a business which is principally engaged in the sale of goods or commodities to ultimate consumers for their own use or consumption and not for resale; and</para><para>(c) In cities with a population of two thousand five hundred inhabitants or less, a business shall be a qualifying business even though it derives its principal source of income from activities other than those set out in this section.</para><para>(3) If a business which would otherwise be a qualifying business employs people and carries on activities in more than one city in Nebraska or will do so at any time during the first year following its application for participation in an economic development program, it shall be a qualifying business only if, in each such city, it maintains employment for the first two years following the date on which such business begins operations in the city as a participant in its economic development program at a level not less than its average employment in such city over the twelve-month period preceding participation.</para><para>(4) A qualifying business need not be located within the territorial boundaries of the city from which it is or will be receiving financial assistance.</para><para>(5) Qualifying business does not include a political subdivision, a state agency, or any other governmental entity, except as allowed for cities of the first and second class and villages for rural infrastructure development as provided for in subsection (4) of section 18-2705.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 840, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 732, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1188, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 207, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 827, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB471, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB863, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB150, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>