<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id213"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-3516"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3516</statuteno><catchline>Election commissioner or county clerk; notification; required; costs of election.</catchline><para>Not later than June first of each year, the election commissioner or county clerk shall determine which community improvement districts in the county are required to hold elections in such year and shall so notify the clerk of each such community improvement district on or before July first of such year. The entire costs of conducting the election shall be borne by the community improvement district holding the election, and such costs shall include all expenses such as procuring a list of the property owners of record in each such community improvement district, printing and mailing notices of the elections to such property owners, printing, preparing, and mailing ballots, paying compensation and mileage for the election boards conducting such elections, and also indirect expenses, such as the pro rata amount of any additional clerical expense or other miscellaneous expenses to be incurred by the election commissioner or county clerk in conducting all of such elections to be held in such calendar year. Within sixty days after the elections have been held, each community improvement district shall be charged and billed for all of the actual expenses incurred by the election commissioner or county clerk attributable to such community improvement district. Payment of the total amount billed to the community improvement district shall be in currency and made by the attorney for the community improvement district to the election commissioner or county clerk within sixty days after receipt of such billing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1114, &#167; 16. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>