<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages Laws Applicable to All" id="id5" statutenumber="18-3417"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3417</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Sale of property for nonpayment of taxes; land bank; power to bid; purchase of tax sale certificate; apply for tax deed or foreclose lien.</catchline><para>(1)(a) At any sale of real property for the nonpayment of taxes conducted pursuant to sections 77-1801 to 77-1863, a land bank may:</para><para>(i) Bid on such real property in an amount equal to the total amount of taxes, interest, and costs due on the real property. If a bid is given pursuant to this subdivision, the bid shall not receive any special treatment by the county treasurer and shall be accepted or rejected in the same manner as any other bid on such real property; or</para><para>(ii) If a land bank is created by a city of the metropolitan class that borders a county in which at least three cities of the first class are located and if approved by a two-thirds vote of the board, give an automatically accepted bid on such real property in an amount equal to the total amount of taxes, interest, and costs due on the real property. If an automatically accepted bid is given, it shall be accepted by the county treasurer regardless of any other bids on such real property. An automatically accepted bid may be given only if the conditions for making such a bid prescribed by the board pursuant to subsection (11) of section 18-3405 have been met.</para><para>(b) If a land bank's bid pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section is accepted by the county treasurer, the land bank shall pay the county treasurer and shall be entitled to a tax sale certificate for such real property.</para><para>(2) If a county holds a tax sale certificate pursuant to section 77-1809, a land bank may purchase such tax sale certificate from the county by paying the county treasurer the amount expressed on the face of the certificate and interest thereon at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, from the date the tax sale certificate was first issued to the county to the date such certificate was purchased by the land bank.</para><para>(3)(a) Subdivision (b) of this subsection applies until January 1, 2015. Subdivision (c) of this subsection applies beginning January 1, 2015.</para><para>(b) Within six months after the expiration of three years from the date of sale of real property for the nonpayment of taxes pursuant to sections 77-1801 to 77-1863, a land bank that has acquired a tax sale certificate for such real property under this section may:</para><para>(i) Apply to the county treasurer for a tax deed for the real property described in the tax sale certificate. A land bank applying for a tax deed shall comply with all the requirements of sections 77-1801 to 77-1863 relating to such tax deed; or</para><para>(ii) Foreclose the lien represented by the tax sale certificate as authorized in section 77-1902.</para><para>(c) Within nine months after the expiration of three years from the date of sale of real property for the nonpayment of taxes pursuant to sections 77-1801 to 77-1863, a land bank that has acquired a tax sale certificate for such real property under this section may:</para><para>(i) Apply to the county treasurer for a tax deed for the real property described in the tax sale certificate. A land bank applying for a tax deed shall comply with all the requirements of sections 77-1801 to 77-1863 relating to such tax deed; or</para><para>(ii) Foreclose the lien represented by the tax sale certificate as authorized in section 77-1902.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB851, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2018, &#167; 19-5217; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB424, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>