<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id223"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-3543"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3543</statuteno><catchline>Appointment of an administrator; petition; hearing; notice.</catchline><para>The court shall fix the time for the hearing of the petition pursuant to section 18-3542 and shall order the clerk of the court to give and publish a notice of the filing of the petition. The notice shall be given by publication the same day of the week each week for three consecutive weeks. Within five days after the first publication of such notice, the petitioner shall cause to be mailed by United States mail a copy of such notice to each holder of outstanding warrants and bonds, to each member of the board of trustees if the board has not petitioned for the appointment, to the city or village in which the community improvement district is located, and to each person whose property ownership is of record on the records of the register of deeds at least thirty days and not more than forty days prior to the mailing of a notice. Notice shall be sent to each bond and warrant holder, trustee, and property owner whose name and post office address are known after diligent investigation and inquiry. The notice shall state the time and place fixed for the hearing of the petition and the prayer of the petition, and that any person with an interest in the community improvement district may, on or before the day fixed for the hearing of the petition, move to join in, dismiss, or answer the petition. The petition may be referred to and described in the notice as the petition of ................. (giving name of petitioner) praying for the referral of the community improvement district to the ........... (name of the city council of the city or board of trustees of the village in which the community improvement district is located) for the appointment of an administrator of the community improvement district and the suspension of the authority of the board of trustees of such community improvement district to exercise the powers granted the board of trustees under the Community Improvement District Act during the period of such administrator's appointment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1114, &#167; 43. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>