<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id548"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-3533"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3533</statuteno><catchline>Improvements; assessment of benefits; exempt property; cost; interest; rate.</catchline><para>(1) The board of trustees or the administrator shall not cause the following property to be assessed for any of the improvements provided for in the Community Improvement District Act: (a) Property by law not assessable, (b) property not included within the area defined in the preliminary resolution, and (c) property not benefited.</para><para>(2) The exemption in subsection (1) of this section does not apply if the exempt property has been specially benefited by the improvements. In such cases, the owner of such property shall pay the community improvement district a sum equivalent to the amount the property has been specially benefited, which amount may be recovered by the community improvement district in an action against the property owner. If the parties do not agree as to the amount of the special benefits, the amount may be determined by the district court in an action brought by the community improvement district for such purpose.</para><para>(3) The board of trustees or the administrator may find that any part or all of such improvements made are of general benefit to the community improvement district, and the board or administrator may levy special assessments on all lots, parcels, or pieces of real estate specially benefited to the extent of the special benefits to such property. The cost of such improvements shall be paid from the assessments levied against all the property in the community improvement district, in the manner provided by section 18-3536, or may be paid from unappropriated money in its general fund. The cost of the improvements shall draw interest at the rate of six percent per annum from the date of acceptance thereof by the board or administrator until warrants are issued for, or payment is otherwise provided, in payment of the contract price.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1114, &#167; 33. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>