<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id300"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-3550"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3550</statuteno><catchline>Administrator; levy; administration tax; use; administrator; fee; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The administrator may levy a separate tax upon the taxable value of the taxable property in the community improvement district which shall be known as the administration tax and which shall be separately accounted for by the treasurer of the community improvement district. Such tax shall be paid annually. Such tax may be used to pay the fees and expenses of the administrator and his or her administration, including the cost of audit services, legal services, and financial advisory services ordered by the administrator.</para><para>(2) The administrator shall receive a minimum fee of five hundred dollars per month during the term of his or her appointment. The administrator shall also be entitled to reimbursement for his or her actual and necessary expenses upon presentation of an accounting of his or her expenses to the city council of the city or board of trustees of the village in which the community improvement district is located. The monthly administrator's fee provided for in this subsection shall be subject to adjustment at any time during the term of the administrator's appointment by the city council or village board of trustees. The factors to be considered by the city council or village board of trustees in its determination to increase the administrator's fee shall include the nature and extent of the administrator's services, the complexity of the problems confronting the community improvement district, and the value of the services of the administrator to the community improvement district. The city council or village board of trustees shall also consider the cost of obtaining comparable services of the administrator in the private sector.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1114, &#167; 50. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>