
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id320"><amendatorysection statutenumber="18-3316" chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3316</statuteno><catchline>Detachment of property from corporate limits; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any person owning real property located within and adjacent to the corporate limits of a city of the first class, city of the second class, or village seeking to have such property detached from the corporate limits of such city or village may file a request with the city council or village board of trustees asking that such property be detached. The request shall contain the legal description of the property sought to be detached. If the city council or village board of trustees determines that the property meets the requirements of this section and that all or a part of such property ought to be detached, the city council or village board of trustees shall adopt an ordinance by a majority vote of its members to order such property detached from the corporate limits of the city or village. The city clerk or village clerk shall file a certified copy of such ordinance in the office of the register of deeds and of the election commissioner or county clerk of the county in which such property is located.</para><para>(2) A city of any class or village may initiate detachment of any real property located within and adjacent to the corporate limits of such city or village by first publishing notice in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city or village of the intention of the city or village to detach such property. Such notice shall include a legal description of the property to be detached and shall provide the date, time, and place of the meeting at which the ordinance ordering such property to be detached will be voted on by the city council or village board of trustees. If, by a majority vote of its members, the city council or village board of trustees adopts the ordinance ordering such property detached from the corporate limits of the city or village, the city clerk or village clerk shall file a certified copy of such ordinance in the office of the register of deeds and of the election commissioner or county clerk of the county in which such property is located.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB131, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>