<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-3001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3001</statuteno><catchline>Planned unit development ordinance; authorized; planned unit development approval; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (5) of this section and notwithstanding any provisions of Chapter 14, article 4, Chapter 15, article 9, Chapter 19, article 9, or of any home rule charter to the contrary, every city or village may include within its zoning ordinance provisions authorizing and regulating planned unit developments within such city or village or within the zoning jurisdiction of such city or village, except such cities or villages shall not have authority to impose such power over other organized cities or villages within the zoning jurisdiction of such cities or villages. As used in this section, planned unit development includes any development of a parcel of land or an aggregation of contiguous parcels of land to be developed as a single project which proposes density transfers, density increases, and mixing of land uses, or any combination thereof, based upon the application of site planning criteria. The purpose of such ordinance shall be to permit flexibility in the regulation of land development, to encourage innovation in land use and variety in design, layout, and type of structures constructed, to achieve economy and efficiency in the use of land, natural resources, and energy and the provision of public services and utilities, to encourage the preservation and provision of useful open space, and to provide improved housing, employment, or shopping opportunities particularly suited to the needs of an area.</para><para>(2) An ordinance authorizing and regulating planned unit developments shall establish criteria relating to the review of proposed planned unit developments to ensure that the land use or activity proposed through a planned unit development shall be compatible with adjacent uses of land and the capacities of public services and utilities affected by such planned unit development and to ensure that the approval of such planned unit development is consistent with the public health, safety, and general welfare of the city or village and is in accordance with the comprehensive plan.</para><para>(3) Within a planned unit development, regulations relating to the use of land, including permitted uses, lot sizes, setbacks, height limits, required facilities, buffers, open spaces, roadway and parking design, and land-use density shall be determined in accordance with the planned unit development regulations specified in the zoning ordinance. The planned unit development regulations need not be uniform with regard to each type of land use.</para><para>(4) The approval of planned unit developments, as authorized under a planned unit development ordinance, shall be generally similar to the procedures established for the approval of zone changes. In approving any planned unit development, a city or village may, either as a condition of the ordinance approving a planned unit development, by covenant, by separate agreement, or otherwise, impose reasonable conditions as deemed necessary to ensure that a planned unit development shall be compatible with adjacent uses of land, will not overburden public services and facilities, and will not be detrimental to the public health, safety, and welfare. Such conditions or agreements may provide for dedications of land for public purposes.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (6) of this section, a city of the second class or village located in a county that has adopted a comprehensive development plan which meets the requirements of section 23-114.02 and is enforcing subdivision regulations shall not finally approve a planned unit development upon property located outside of the corporate boundaries of the city or village until the plans for the planned unit development have been submitted to, reviewed, and approved by the county's planning commission pursuant to subsection (4) of section 17-1002.</para><para>(6) A city of the second class or village located in whole or in part within the boundaries of a county having a population in excess of one hundred thousand inhabitants but less than two hundred fifty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census that has adopted a comprehensive development plan which meets the requirements of section 23-114.02 and is enforcing subdivision regulations shall not finally approve a planned unit development upon property located outside of the corporate boundaries of the city or village until the plans for the planned unit development have been submitted to the county's planning department and public works department for review.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 135, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2007), &#167; 19-4401; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB146, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB875, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB74, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>