<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-3301" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3301</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Contiguous land; annexation; plat; approval; recording; effect.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever the owner or owners or a majority of the owners of any territory lying contiguous to the corporate limits of any city or village, whether the territory be already in fact subdivided into lots or parcels of ten acres or less or remains unsubdivided, except as provided in section 13-1115, shall desire to annex such territory to any city or village, they shall first cause an accurate plat or map of the territory to be made, showing such territory subdivided into blocks and lots, conforming as nearly as may be to the blocks, lots, and streets of the adjacent city or village. It shall also show the descriptions and numberings, as provided in section 18-3304, for platting additions, and conforming thereto as nearly as may be.</para><para id="id00">(2) Such plat or map shall be prepared under the supervision of the city engineer in cases of annexation to adjacent cities, under the supervision of the village engineer in cases of annexation to adjacent villages, and under the supervision of a competent surveyor in any case. A copy of such plat or map, certified by such engineer or surveyor, as the case may be, shall be filed in the office of the city clerk or village clerk, together with a request in writing, signed by a majority of the property owners of the territory described in such plat for the annexation of such territory. The city council or village board of trustees shall, at the next regular meeting after the filing of such plat and request for annexation, vote upon the question of such annexation, and such vote shall be recorded in the minutes of such city council or village board of trustees. If a majority of all the members of the city council or village board of trustees vote for such annexation, an ordinance shall be prepared and passed by the city council or village board of trustees declaring the annexation of such territory to the corporate limits of the city or village.</para><para id="id00">(3) An accurate map or plat of such territory certified by the city engineer, village engineer, or surveyor and acknowledged and proved as provided by law in such cases shall at once be filed and recorded in the office of the county clerk or register of deeds and county assessor of the proper county, together with a certified copy of the ordinance declaring such annexation, under the seal of the city or village. Upon such filing, the annexation of the adjacent territory shall be deemed complete, and the territory included and described in the plat on file in the office of the county clerk or register of deeds shall be deemed and held to be a part of such city or village, and the inhabitants of such territory shall thereafter enjoy the privileges and benefits of such annexation and be subject to the ordinances and regulations of such city or village.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 95, p. 229; </para><para>Laws 1881, c. 23, &#167; 10, p. 188; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5086; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4253; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-407; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-405; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 51, &#167; 11, p. 243; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 64, &#167; 1, p. 281; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 757, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2012), &#167; 17-405; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 312. </para></source><annotation><para>This section refers to voluntary annexation by resolution upon request of owners and inhabitants, but not to annexation by ordinance. Holden v. City of Tecumseh, 188 Neb. 117, 195 N.W.2d 225 (1972).</para><para>Village cannot annex territory not contiguous to it. Village of Niobrara v. Tichy, 158 Neb. 517, 63 N.W.2d 867 (1954).</para><para>Land annexed under section 17-407 is not exempt from taxation for prior city indebtedness because of this section. Gottschalk v. Becher, 32 Neb. 653, 49 N.W. 715 (1891).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>