
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities and Villages Laws Applicable to All" id="id26" statutenumber="18-3404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3404</statuteno><catchline>Creation of land bank; procedure; use of Interlocal Cooperation Act; join by agreement; goal of land bank.</catchline><para>(1) A single municipality may create a land bank if the municipality is a city of the metropolitan class or city of the primary class. Such municipality shall create the land bank by the adoption of an ordinance which specifies the following:</para><para>(a) The name of the land bank;</para><para>(b) The initial individuals to serve as members of the board and the length of terms for which they are to serve; and</para><para>(c) The qualifications and terms of office of members of the board.</para><para>(2) Two or more municipalities may elect to enter into an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act to create a single land bank to act on behalf of such municipalities, which agreement shall contain the information required by subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) A municipality may elect to join an existing land bank by entering into an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act with a city of the metropolitan class or city of the primary class that has created a land bank pursuant to subsection (1) of this section or by joining an existing agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act with the municipalities that formed a land bank pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. Agreements entered into or joined under this subsection shall contain the information required by subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(4) Each land bank created pursuant to the Nebraska Municipal Land Bank Act shall be deemed to be a public corporation acting in a governmental capacity and a political subdivision of the state and shall have permanent and perpetual duration until terminated and dissolved in accordance with section 18-3414.</para><para>(5) The primary goal of any land bank shall be to facilitate the return of vacant, abandoned, and tax-delinquent properties to productive use.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2018, &#167; 19-5204; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB424, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>