<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id805"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-3537"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3537</statuteno><catchline>Change in boundary; petition; notice; hearing; ordinance; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The community improvement district may be enlarged and additional territory annexed to the community improvement district. Initiation of any such enlargement shall be by petition filed with the clerk of the community improvement district, signed by persons owning not less than fifty percent of the area to be annexed. Upon approval by the board of trustees of such community improvement district, the clerk of the community improvement district shall file (a) an application for such annexation with the city or village clerk with a request that the annexation be approved, all in the same manner as approval of the initial articles of association of such community improvement district pursuant to the Community Improvement District Act and (b) notify the county clerk, election commissioner, and register of deeds of each county or counties in which the community improvement district is located of the proposed annexation. The city or village clerk shall process any such application in the same manner as an initial application for approval of the articles of association for such community improvement district and shall schedule a hearing, publish notices, and mail notices to any owner of property in the area proposed to be annexed who did not sign the petition for annexation. The city council or village board of trustees may approve the proposed amendment by ordinance in a similar manner to the initial articles of association as provided in the Community Improvement District Act.</para><para>(2) All property, from and after annexation to the community improvement district as provided in subsection (1) of this section, shall be subject to all taxes and other burdens thereafter levied by the community improvement district, regardless of when the obligation for which the taxes or assessments are levied was incurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1114, &#167; 37. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>