
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id765"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities And Villages; Laws Applicable To All"  statutenumber="18-3104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3104</statuteno><catchline>Appointment of municipality as custodian; findings; hearing; powers; compensation; costs; lien; recording; foreclosure; termination of custodianship; withdrawal or termination of custodianship.</catchline><para>(1) The district court of the county in which a dissolved homeowners association was previously existing shall, in a proceeding brought by a municipality by petition to the district court, appoint the municipality as custodian to manage the affairs of the homeowners association upon a finding that:</para><para>(a) The homeowners association has been administratively dissolved by the Secretary of State pursuant to section 21-19,138;</para><para>(b) The homeowners association has failed in one or more of the following ways:</para><para>(i) To maintain the common area as required by the municipality's conditions of approval for the plat or subdivision of real property;</para><para>(ii) To maintain the common area or private improvements located outside of the common area on the real property in the plat or subdivision in accordance with all terms and conditions of any agreement with the municipality; or</para><para>(iii) To comply with any applicable laws, rules, or regulations pertaining to maintenance of the common area or private improvements located outside of the common area on the real property in the plat or subdivision such that the noncompliance is adverse to the interests of the municipality and may result in expenditures by the municipality not otherwise required;</para><para>(c) The municipality has made a demand on the members to hold a special meeting to remove and elect new directors and to approve a submission of an application to the Secretary of State for reinstatement pursuant to the Municipal Custodianship for Dissolved Homeowners Associations Act or the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act; and</para><para>(d) The members have failed to reinstate the homeowners association within six months after the demand.</para><para>(2) The district court shall hold a hearing, after written notification thereof by the petitioner to all parties to the proceeding and any interested persons designated by the court, before appointing a custodian, and the petitioner shall provide sufficient proof of service to the court. Service by first-class mail shall be deemed sufficient service. The district court appointing the custodian shall have exclusive jurisdiction over the homeowners association and all of its property wherever located.</para><para>(3) The district court shall describe the powers and duties of the custodian in its appointing order, which order may be amended upon motion and notice to the parties from time to time. Among other powers, the appointing order shall provide that the custodian may exercise all of the powers of the homeowners association, through or in place of its board of directors or officers, to the extent necessary to manage the affairs of the association in the best interests of its members. The custodian shall not be liable for the actions or inactions of the homeowners association and shall maintain all immunities granted to municipalities by applicable law.</para><para>(4) Upon application of the custodian, the district court from time to time during the custodianship may order compensation paid and expense disbursements or reimbursements made to the custodian from the assets of the association or proceeds from the sale of the assets. Notice of a hearing to determine compensation and costs shall be provided to all owners and interested parties by the custodian as set forth in subsection (2) of this section, with proof of service provided by the custodian. In the event the district court awards compensation or reimbursement of costs, all such compensation and costs shall be a lien on each and all of the lots in the manner as set forth in subsection (5) of this section. Any court order awarding compensation or reimbursement of costs herein shall identify each lot and the amount of compensation or reimbursement of costs each lot shall be charged as a lien.</para><para>(5)(a) A lien created under subsection (4) of this section shall be effective from the time the district court awards the compensation or reimbursement of costs and a notice containing the dollar amount of the lien is recorded in the office where mortgages or deeds of trust are recorded. The lien may be foreclosed in like manner as a mortgage on real estate but the municipality shall give reasonable notice of its action to all other lienholders whose interest would be affected.</para><para>(b) A lien created under subsection (4) of this section is prior to all other liens and encumbrances on real estate except (i) liens and encumbrances recorded before the recordation of the declaration or agreement, (ii) a first mortgage or deed of trust on real estate recorded before the notice required under subdivision (5)(a) of this section has been recorded, and (iii) liens for real estate taxes.</para><para>(6) In the event the homeowners association is reinstated after appointment of a custodian, any interested party may make a request to the district court for termination of the custodianship.</para><para>(7) A custodian may be allowed to withdraw from or terminate the custodianship upon an order from the district court permitting such withdrawal or termination following a hearing for which notice is provided to all owners and interested parties by the custodian.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB304, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>