
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages Laws Applicable To All" statutenumber="18-3304" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3304</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Additions; plat; contents; duty to file.</catchline><para id="id00">Every original owner of any tract or parcel of land, who shall subdivide such tract or parcel into two or more parts for the purpose of laying out any city or village or an addition to any city or village, or suburban lots, shall cause a plat of such subdivision, with references to known or permanent monuments, to be made, which shall accurately describe all subdivisions of such tract or parcel of land, numbering such tract or parcel by progressive numbers, and giving the dimensions and length and breadth of such tract or parcel, and the breadth and courses of all streets and alleys established therein. Descriptions of lots or parcels of land in such subdivisions, according to the number and designation on such plat, in conveyances or for the purposes of taxation, shall be deemed good and valid for all purposes. The duty to file for record a plat as provided in sections 18-3304 to 18-3315 shall attach as a covenant of warranty in all conveyances made of any part or parcel of such subdivision by the original owners against any and all assessments, costs, and damages paid, lost, or incurred by any grantee in consequence of the omission on the part of the owner filing such plat.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 104, p. 233; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5092; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4265; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-414; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-415; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 75, &#167; 3, p. 243; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2012), &#167; 17-415; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 315. </para></source><annotation><para>When plat of proposed subdivision is prepared, executed, and filed by landowner without any representations by city with regard to disputed easement, it operates as deed of portion of land set apart for public use. Vakoc Constr. Co. v. City of Wayne, 191 Neb. 45, 213 N.W.2d 721 (1974).</para><para>Filing of plat is dedication of streets shown thereon. Village of Maxwell v. Booth, 161 Neb. 300, 73 N.W.2d 177 (1955).</para><para>Where a plat is filed by the owner and surrounding the lands shown on the plat are continuous boundary lines on which appear the words "street", it is equivalent to a deed of the portion so shown as streets in fee simple to the public. City of Schuyler v. Verba, 120 Neb. 729, 235 N.W. 341 (1931).</para><para>Dedication deed of lot for street to public must be signed by owner and lienholder without notice is not estopped to deny that he consented to dedication. Morning v. City of Lincoln, 93 Neb. 364, 140 N.W. 638 (1913).</para><para>Where land is platted pursuant to this section, the fee simple title to streets and alleys vests in the public, and title is held in trust for the use for which such ways were dedicated. Jaynes v. Omaha Street Ry. Co., 53 Neb. 631, 74 N.W. 67 (1898).</para><para>A plat filed with the county clerk and recorded by him becomes an instrument in which the public as well as the proprietor is interested and it should remain in the possession of the county clerk. Lincoln Land Co. v. Ackerman, 24 Neb. 46, 38 N.W. 25 (1888).</para><para>Lines actually run and marked on the ground will control over plat in case of variance. Holst v. Streitz, 16 Neb. 249, 20 N.W. 307 (1884).</para><para>Where land has been platted, occupied, and taxed for more than twenty-five years, courts will not consider evidence to show that plat was not recorded. Bryant v. Estabrook, 16 Neb. 217, 20 N.W. 245 (1884).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>