<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id460"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities and Villages; Laws Applicable to All" statutenumber="18-3525"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>18-3525</statuteno><catchline>Public infrastructure improvements; other costs; resolution of necessity; special assessments; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever the board of trustees or the administrator deems it advisable or necessary to build, reconstruct, purchase, or otherwise acquire public infrastructure improvements or to incur other costs permitted by the Community Improvement District Act, the board of trustees shall declare the advisability and necessity therefor in a proposed resolution.</para><para>(2) Such proposed resolution of necessity shall refer to the plans and specifications for the proposed improvements, proposed agreements or contracts, together with the estimated cost thereof which have been made and filed with the community improvement district clerk before the publication of such resolution. The proposed resolution shall state the amount of such estimated cost.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, the board of trustees or the administrator may assess, to the extent of special benefits, the cost of such improvements upon properties specially benefited thereby. The resolution shall state the outer boundaries of the area within the community improvement district in which it is proposed to make special assessments.</para><para>(4) Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in the Community Improvement District Act, a community improvement district shall not specially assess the cost of public infrastructure for redevelopment unless and until such community improvement district has obtained prior approval by resolution of the city council or village board of trustees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1114, &#167; 25. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>