<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4" opdate="October 1, 2010">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Husband and Wife" id="id5" statutenumber="42-358.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">42-358.02</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Delinquent child
support payments, spousal support
payments, and medical support payments; interest; rate; report;
Title IV-D Division; duties.</catchline><para>(1) All delinquent
child support payments, spousal
support payments, and medical support payments shall draw interest
at the rate specified in section 45-103 in effect on the date of the most
recent order or decree. Such interest shall be computed as simple interest.</para>
<para>(2) All child support payments, spousal support payments, and medical support payments shall
become delinquent the day after they are due and owing, except that no obligor
whose support
payments are automatically withheld from his or her paycheck shall be regarded
or reported as being delinquent or in arrears if (a) any delinquency or arrearage
is solely caused by a disparity between the schedule of the obligor's regular
pay dates and the scheduled date the support payment is due, (b) the total
amount of support payments to be withheld from
the paychecks of the obligor and the amount ordered by the support order are
the same on an annual basis, and (c) the automatic deductions for support payments are continuous and occurring. Interest
shall not accrue until thirty days after such payments are delinquent.</para>
<para>(3) The court shall order the determination of the amount
of interest due, and such interest shall be payable in the same manner as
the support payments upon which the interest accrues subject to subsection
(2) of this section or unless it is waived by agreement of the parties. The
Title IV-D Division of the Department of Health and Human Services shall compute
interest and identify delinquencies pursuant to this section on the payments
received by the State Disbursement Unit pursuant to section 42-369. The Title
IV-D Division shall provide the case information in electronic format, and
upon request in print format, to the judge presiding over domestic relations
cases and to the county attorney or authorized attorney.</para>
<para>(4) Support order payments shall be credited in the following
manner:</para>
<para>(a) First, to the payments due for the current month in the
following order: Child support payments, then spousal support payments, and
lastly medical support payments;</para>
<para>(b) Second, toward any payment arrearage owing, in the following
order: Child support payment arrearage, then spousal support payment arrearage,
and lastly medical support payment arrearage; and</para>
<para>(c) Third, toward the interest on any payment arrearage, in
the following order: Child support payment arrearage interest, then spousal
support payment arrearage interest, and lastly medical support payment arrearage
interest.</para>
<para>(5) Interest which may have accrued prior to September 6,
1991, shall not be affected or altered by changes to this section which take
effect on such date. All delinquent support order payments and all decrees
entered prior to such date shall draw interest at the effective rate as prescribed
by this section commencing as of such date.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 212, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 371, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 845, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 569, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 18, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 972, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 396, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>The district court erred, as a matter of law, in failing to account for the effective date of the amended statute as triggering a change in the applicable interest rate. Prior to September 6, 1991, interest on delinquent child support payments accrues at a rate determined by section 45-104.01, and as of September 6, 1991, interest on delinquent child support payments accrues at a rate determined by section 45-103. Welch v. Welch, 246 Neb. 435, 519 N.W.2d 262 (1994).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>