<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Husband and Wife" statutenumber="42-349"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-349</statuteno><catchline>Dissolution; action; conditions.</catchline><para>No action for dissolution of marriage may be brought unless at least one of the parties has had actual residence in this state with a bona fide intention of making this state his or her permanent home for at least one year prior to the filing of the complaint, or unless the marriage was solemnized in this state and either party has resided in this state from the time of marriage to filing the complaint. Persons serving in the armed forces of the United States who have been continuously stationed at any military base or installation in this state for one year or, if the marriage was solemnized in this state, have resided in this state from the time of marriage to the filing of the complaint shall for the purposes of sections 42-347 to 42-381 be deemed residents of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 820, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 229, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1207, &#167; 18. </para></source><annotation><para>The inference that residency in Nebraska has been with the intent to make it one's permanent home is negated where he or she is a nonimmigrant alien residing in Nebraska on a visitor's visa. Rozsnyai v. Svacek, 272 Neb. 567, 723 N.W.2d 329 (2006).</para><para>One who proves he or she met the durational residency requirement shall be permitted the inference that such residency was with the intention to make Nebraska a permanent home, absent a showing that the residency was a sham and not bona fide. Rector v. Rector, 224 Neb. 800, 401 N.W.2d 167 (1987).</para><para>This section is not unconstitutional. Ashley v. Ashley, 191 Neb. 824, 217 N.W.2d 926 (1974).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>