<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id115"><amendatorysection chaptername="Husband And Wife" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="42-748.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>42-748.04</statuteno><catchline>Initiation by Nebraska Department of Health and Human Services of support proceeding under Convention.</catchline><para>(a) In a support proceeding under sections 42-748.01 to 42-748.13, the Nebraska Department of Health and Human Services shall:</para><para>(1) transmit and receive applications; and</para><para>(2) initiate or facilitate the institution of a proceeding regarding an application in a tribunal of this state.</para><para>(b) The following support proceedings are available to an obligee under the Convention:</para><para>(1) recognition or recognition and enforcement of a foreign support order;</para><para>(2) enforcement of a support order issued or recognized in this state;</para><para>(3) establishment of a support order if there is no existing order, including, if necessary, determination of parentage of a child;</para><para>(4) establishment of a support order if recognition of a foreign support order is refused under subdivision (b)(2), (4), or (9) of section 42-748.08;</para><para>(5) modification of a support order of a tribunal of this state; and</para><para>(6) modification of a support order of a tribunal of another state or a foreign country.</para><para>(c) The following support proceedings are available under the Convention to an obligor against which there is an existing support order:</para><para>(1) recognition of an order suspending or limiting enforcement of an existing support order of a tribunal of this state;</para><para>(2) modification of a support order of a tribunal of this state; and</para><para>(3) modification of a support order of a tribunal of another state or a foreign country.</para><para>(d) A tribunal of this state may not require security, bond, or deposit, however described, to guarantee the payment of costs and expenses in proceedings under the Convention.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB415, &#167; 51. </para><effectivedate>April 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>