<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Husband And Wife" statutenumber="42-364.12"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-364.12</statuteno><catchline>Child support; withholding of earnings; employer; civil contempt; liability for damages; injunction.</catchline><para>Any employer failing to make answer truthfully and completely to the interrogatories propounded pursuant to section 42-364.03 may be punished by the court for civil contempt. The court shall first afford such employer a reasonable opportunity to purge itself of such contempt. Any employer who shall fail or refuse to deliver earnings pursuant to an order to withhold and transmit earnings, when such employer has had in its possession such earnings, shall be personally liable for the amount of such earnings which the employer failed or refused to deliver, together with costs, interest, and reasonable attorney's fees. Any employer who fails to notify in writing the clerk of the court entering an order to withhold and transmit earnings of the termination of the parent-employee and the name and address of the parent-employee's new employer, if known, within thirty days after the termination of employment, may be punished by the court for civil contempt. Any employer who dismisses, demotes, disciplines, or in any way penalizes a parent-employee on account of any proceeding to collect child support, on account of any order or orders entered by the court in such proceeding, or on account of the employer's compliance with such order or orders, shall be liable to the parent-employee for all damages, together with costs, interest thereon, and a reasonable attorney's fee, resulting from the employer's action and may be enjoined by any court of competent jurisdiction from continuing such action. Any proceeding to punish an employer for contempt, to hold the employer liable for earnings not withheld and transmitted, to hold the employer liable for actions taken against the parent-employee, or to enjoin the employer from continuing such actions, must be commenced within ninety days after the employer's act or failure to act upon which such proceeding is based.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 1015, &#167; 17. </para></source></law></legaldoc>