<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Households and Families" statutenumber="42-360"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-360</statuteno><catchline>Reconciliation; transfer of action; when; counseling; costs.</catchline><para>No decree shall be entered under sections 42-347 to 42-381 unless the court finds that every reasonable effort to effect reconciliation has been made. Proceedings filed pursuant to sections 42-347 to 42-381 shall be subject to transfer to a conciliation court pursuant to section 42-822 or 42-823, in counties where such a court has been established. In counties having no conciliation court, the court hearing proceedings under sections 42-347 to 42-381 may refer the parties to qualified marriage counselors or family service agencies, or other persons or agencies determined by the court to be qualified to provide conciliation services, if the court finds that there appears to be some reasonable possibility of a reconciliation being effected. In no case shall the court order marriage counseling upon the request of only one of the parties to the dissolution or his or her attorney. If both parties agree to attend counseling but do not agree on an assignment of the costs of such counseling, the court, after receiving an application for such costs and upon a showing that the parties cannot agree on an assignment of such costs, shall assign such costs in a temporary or permanent order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 820, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 845, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 229, &#167; 16. </para></source><annotation><para>It is only when there exists a reasonable possibility of reconciliation that the statutes require efforts be made to effect it. Condreay v. Condreay, 190 Neb. 513, 209 N.W.2d 357 (1973).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>