<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Households and Families" statutenumber="42-619"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-619</statuteno><catchline>Claims; limitation; affidavit asserting ownership; filing and recording.</catchline><para>The Legislature recognizes that many husbands and wives have failed to keep proper records; that community income and separate funds have been commingled; that property has been acquired by husband or wife on or after September 7, 1947, in many cases with separate funds; that to protect property rights against loss of evidence, it is necessary that claims that property acquired, as defined in section 42-617, was, or is, community property should be filed or recorded. Any claim or defense by either husband or wife or other person, in any action, proceeding, or controversy, that any property acquired, as defined in section 42-617, was or is community property, shall be barred one year from April 20, 1949, unless, within one year from April 20, 1949, an affidavit by either the husband or wife, or other interested person, asserting that the property therein described was or is community property has been filed or recorded as herein provided. In case of real estate, such affidavit shall be recorded in the office of the register of deeds of the county in which the real estate is situated; in case of stocks, the affidavit shall be filed with the corporation issuing the same; in case of bonds, notes, secured or unsecured, securities, or other evidences of indebtedness or other debts, the affidavit shall be delivered to the debtor; in case of life insurance, the affidavit shall be filed with the home office of the insurer; and in case of all other personal property the affidavit shall be filed with the county clerk of the county in which the husband resides or last resided in Nebraska. The filing or recording of an affidavit as provided in sections 42-603 and 42-617 to 42-620, shall not constitute notice to purchasers, mortgagees, pledgees, or assignees for value, that such property is claimed to be community property. This section shall not apply to claims of any person in exclusive possession of property under claim of right, on April 20, 1949.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 129, &#167; 4, p. 338. </para></source></law></legaldoc>