<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Households and Families" statutenumber="42-936"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-936</statuteno><catchline>Registration of order.</catchline><para>(a) Any individual may register a foreign protection order in this state. To register a foreign protection order, an individual shall:</para><para>(1) present a certified copy of the order to the Nebraska State Patrol for the registration of such orders; or</para><para>(2) present a certified copy of the order to another agency designated by the state and request that the order be registered with the Nebraska State Patrol.</para><para>(b) Upon receipt of a foreign protection order, the agency responsible for the registration of such orders shall register the order in accordance with this section. After the order is registered, the responsible agency shall furnish to the individual registering the order a certified copy of the registered order.</para><para>(c) The agency responsible for the registration of foreign protection orders shall register an order upon presentation of a copy of a protection order which has been certified by the issuing state. A registered foreign protection order that is inaccurate or is not currently in effect shall be corrected or removed from the registry in accordance with the law of this state.</para><para>(d) An individual registering a foreign protection order shall file an affidavit by the protected individual stating that, to the best of the protected individual's knowledge, the order is currently in effect.</para><para>(e) A foreign protection order registered under the Uniform Interstate Enforcement of Domestic Violence Protection Orders Act may be entered in any existing state or federal registry of protection orders, in accordance with applicable law.</para><para>(f) A fee shall not be charged for the registration of a foreign protection order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 148, &#167; 94. </para></source></law></legaldoc>