<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id266"><sectno id="id267">Sec. 33.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Households and Families" id="id268" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="42-364.17"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-364.17</statuteno><catchline>Dissolution, legal separation, or order establishing paternity; incorporate financial arrangements.</catchline><para>A decree of dissolution, legal separation, or order establishing paternity shall incorporate financial arrangements for each party's responsibility for reasonable and necessary medical, dental, and eye care, medical reimbursements, day care, extracurricular activity, education, and other extraordinary expenses of the child and calculation of child support obligations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167;  33.</para></source><annotation><para>A party’s responsibility under this section for reasonable and necessary medical, dental, and eye care; medical reimbursements; daycare; extracurricular activity; education; and other extraordinary expenses of the child to be made in the future may be modified if the applicant proves that a material change in circumstances has occurred since entry of the decree or a previous modification. Caniglia v. Caniglia, 285 Neb. 930, 830 N.W.2d 207 (2013).</para><para>An appellate court views this section in the context of the statutory scheme governing child support. Caniglia v. Caniglia, 285 Neb. 930, 830 N.W.2d 207 (2013).</para><para>The expenses stated in this section represent other incidents of support to be addressed in a dissolution decree that are outside of the monthly installment established in Neb. Ct. R. section 4-207. Caniglia v. Caniglia, 285 Neb. 930, 830 N.W.2d 207 (2013).</para><para>The words of this section are plain, direct, and unambiguous. Caniglia v. Caniglia, 285 Neb. 930, 830 N.W.2d 207 (2013).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>








 
