<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Households and Families" id="id68" statutenumber="42-926"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>42-926</statuteno><catchline id="id71">Protection order; copies; distribution; sheriff; duties; dismissal or modification; clerk of court; duties; notice requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the issuance of a temporary ex parte or final protection order under section 42-925, the clerk of the court shall forthwith provide the petitioner, without charge, with two certified copies of such order. The clerk of the court shall also forthwith provide the local police department or local law enforcement agency and the local sheriff's office, without charge, with one copy each of such order and one copy each of the sheriff's return thereon. The clerk of the court shall also forthwith provide a copy of the protection order to the sheriff's office in the county where the respondent may be personally served together with instructions for service. Upon receipt of the order and instructions for service, such sheriff's office shall forthwith serve the protection order upon the respondent and file its return thereon with the clerk of the court which issued the protection order within fourteen days of the issuance of the protection order. If any protection order is dismissed or modified by the court, the clerk of the court shall forthwith provide the local police department or local law enforcement agency and the local sheriff's office, without charge, with one copy each of the order of dismissal or modification. If the respondent has notice as described in subsection (2) of this section, further service under this subsection is unnecessary.</para><para>(2) If the respondent was present at a hearing convened pursuant to section 42-925 and the protection order was not dismissed, the respondent shall be deemed to have notice by the court at such hearing that the protection order will be granted and remain in effect and further service of notice described in subsection (1) of this section is not required for purposes of prosecution under subsection (4) of section 42-924.</para><para>(3) When provided by the petitioner, the court shall make confidential numeric victim identification information, including social security numbers and dates of birth, available to appropriate criminal justice agencies engaged in protection order enforcement efforts. Such agencies shall maintain the confidentiality of this information, except for entry into state and federal databases for protection order enforcement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 623, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 330, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 218, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB310, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB532, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>