<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Households and Families" statutenumber="42-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-101</statuteno><catchline>Marriage a civil contract.</catchline><para>In law, marriage is considered a civil contract, to which the consent of the parties capable of contracting is essential.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 254; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1540; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1489; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 42-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 42-101.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Agreements based on consideration of marriage,</emphasis> must be written, see section 36-202.</para><para><emphasis>Child whose parents marry is legitimate,</emphasis> see section 43-1406.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Nature of contract</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Agreement of parties</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Validity of marriage</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Common-law marriage</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Nature of contract</emphasis></para><para>Although this section denotes marriage as a "civil contract," persons entering into matrimony establish a social status, not a contractual relation. Edmunds v. Edwards, 205 Neb. 255, 287 N.W.2d 420 (1980).</para><para>Where consent is obtained by fraud, marriage may be annulled. Zutavern v. Zutavern, 155 Neb. 395, 52 N.W.2d 254 (1952).</para><para>Marriage is a civil contract which, if procured by fraud, may be set aside. Hudson v. Hudson, 151 Neb. 210, 36 N.W.2d 851 (1949).</para><para>State is always a party. Willits v. Willits, 76 Neb. 228, 107 N.W. 379 (1906).</para><para>Consent of state is necessary. Eaton v. Eaton, 66 Neb. 676, 92 N.W. 995 (1902).</para><para>Marriage is a social status, and only in a limited sense is the relation contractual. University of Michigan v. McGuckin, 64 Neb. 300, 89 N.W. 778 (1902).</para><para><emphasis>2. Agreement of parties</emphasis></para><para>Consent of parties mentally competent is required. Kutch v. Kutch, 88 Neb. 114, 129 N.W. 169 (1910).</para><para>Mental weakness alone does not avoid contract. Aldrich v. Steen, 71 Neb. 33, 98 N.W. 445 (1904).</para><para><emphasis>3. Validity of marriage</emphasis></para><para>It is not a ground for annulment that license was wrongfully obtained where parties are competent and marriage is fully consummated. Baker v. Baker, 112 Neb. 738, 200 N.W. 1003 (1924).</para><para>Marriages valid in Indian tribe under Indian customs, are valid here. Ortley v. Ross, 78 Neb. 339, 110 N.W. 982 (1907).</para><para>Marriage is valid where minds of competent parties meet. University of Michigan v. McGuckin, 62 Neb. 489, 87 N.W. 180 (1901).</para><para>Where marriage is celebrated in good faith, it is binding though parties had agreed it should not be. Hills v. State, 61 Neb. 589, 85 N.W. 836 (1901).</para><para><emphasis>4. Common-law marriage</emphasis></para><para>Since 1923, common-law marriages cannot be made in this state. Collins v. Hoag &amp; Rollins, 122 Neb. 805, 241 N.W. 766 (1932), reversing 121 Neb. 716, 238 N.W. 351 (1931).</para><para><emphasis>5. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Agreements to separate are against public policy. Brun v. Brun, 64 Neb. 782, 90 N.W. 860 (1902).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>