<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id369"><amendatorysection chaptername="Husband And Wife" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="42-748.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>42-748.01</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 42-748.01 to 42-748.13:</para><para>(1) Application means a request under the Convention by an obligee or obligor, or on behalf of a child, made through a central authority for assistance from another central authority.</para><para>(2) Central authority means the entity designated by the United States or a foreign country described in subdivision (5)(D) of section 42-702 to perform the functions specified in the Convention.</para><para>(3) Convention support order means a support order of a tribunal of a foreign country described in subdivision (5)(D) of section 42-702.</para><para>(4) Direct request means a petition filed by an individual in a tribunal of this state in a proceeding involving an obligee, an obligor, or a child residing outside the United States.</para><para>(5) Foreign central authority means the entity designated by a foreign country described in subdivision (5)(D) of section 42-702 to perform the functions specified in the Convention.</para><para>(6) Foreign support agreement:</para><para>(A) means an agreement for support in a record that:</para><para>(i) is enforceable as a support order in the country of origin;</para><para>(ii) has been:</para><para>(I) formally drawn up or registered as an authentic instrument by a foreign tribunal; or</para><para>(II) authenticated by, or concluded, registered, or filed with a foreign tribunal; and</para><para>(iii) may be reviewed and modified by a foreign tribunal; and</para><para>(B) includes a maintenance arrangement or authentic instrument under the Convention.</para><para>(7) United States central authority means the Secretary of the United States Department of Health and Human Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB415, &#167; 48. </para><effectivedate>April 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>