<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Households and Families" statutenumber="42-935"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-935</statuteno><catchline>Nonjudicial enforcement of order.</catchline><para>(a) A law enforcement officer of this state, upon determining that there is probable cause to believe that a valid foreign protection order exists and that the order has been violated, shall enforce the order as if it were the order of a tribunal of this state. Presentation of a protection order that identifies both the protected individual and the respondent and, on its face, is currently in effect constitutes probable cause to believe that a valid foreign protection order exists. For purposes of this section, the protection order may be inscribed on a tangible medium or may have been stored in an electronic or other medium if it is retrievable in perceivable form. Presentation of a certified copy of a protection order is not required for enforcement.</para><para>(b) If a foreign protection order is not presented, a law enforcement officer of this state may consider other information in determining whether there is probable cause to believe that a valid foreign protection order exists.</para><para>(c) If a law enforcement officer of this state determines that an otherwise valid foreign protection order cannot be enforced because the respondent has not been notified or served with the order, the officer shall inform the respondent of the order, make a reasonable effort to serve the order upon the respondent, and allow the respondent a reasonable opportunity to comply with the order before enforcing the order.</para><para>(d) Registration or filing of an order in this state is not required for the enforcement of a valid foreign protection order pursuant to the Uniform Interstate Enforcement of Domestic Violence Protection Orders Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 148, &#167; 93. </para></source></law></legaldoc>