<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Households and Families" id="id00" statutenumber="42-720"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-720</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Duties of support enforcement agency.</catchline><para>(a) In a proceeding under the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act, a support enforcement agency of this state, upon request:</para><para>(1) shall provide services to a petitioner residing in a state;</para><para>(2) shall provide services to a petitioner requesting services through a central authority of a foreign country as described in subdivision (5)(A) or (D) of section 42-702; and</para><para>(3) may provide services to a petitioner who is an individual not residing in a state.</para><para>(b) A support enforcement agency of this state that is providing services to the petitioner shall:</para><para>(1) take all steps necessary to enable an appropriate tribunal of this state, another state, or a foreign country to obtain jurisdiction over the respondent;</para><para>(2) request an appropriate tribunal to set a date, time, and place for a hearing;</para><para>(3) make a reasonable effort to obtain all relevant information, including information as to income and property of the parties;</para><para>(4) within five days, exclusive of nonjudicial days, after receipt of a written notice in a record from an initiating, responding, or registering tribunal, send a copy of the notice to the petitioner;</para><para>(5) within five days, exclusive of nonjudicial days, after receipt of a written communication in a record from the respondent or the respondent's attorney, send a copy of the communication to the petitioner; and</para><para>(6) notify the petitioner if jurisdiction over the respondent cannot be obtained.</para><para>(c) A support enforcement agency of this state that requests registration of a child support order in this state for enforcement or for modification shall make reasonable efforts:</para><para>(1) to ensure that the order to be registered is the controlling order; or</para><para>(2) if two or more child support orders exist and the identity of the controlling order has not been determined, to ensure that a request for such a determination is made in a tribunal having jurisdiction to do so.</para><para>(d) A support enforcement agency of this state that requests registration and enforcement of a support order, arrearages, or judgment stated in a foreign currency shall convert the amounts stated in the foreign currency into the equivalent amounts in dollars under the applicable official or market exchange rate as publicly reported.</para><para>(e) A support enforcement agency of this state shall request a tribunal of this state to issue a child support order and an income withholding order that redirect payment of current support, arrearages, and interest if requested to do so by a support enforcement agency of another state pursuant to section 42-732.</para><para>(f) The act does not create or negate a relationship of attorney and client or other fiduciary relationship between a support enforcement agency or the attorney for the agency and the individual being assisted by the agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 500, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 727, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 148, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 760, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB415, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>