<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id55">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Households and Families" id="id57" statutenumber="42-925"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-925</statuteno><catchline id="id60">Ex parte protection
order; duration; notice requirements; hearing; notice; referral to referee;
notice regarding firearm or ammunition.</catchline><para>(1) An
order issued under subsection (1) of section 42-924 may be issued ex parte
to the respondent if it reasonably appears from the specific facts included
in the affidavit that the petitioner will be in immediate danger of abuse
before the matter can be heard on notice. If an order is issued ex parte, such order is a temporary order and the
court shall forthwith
cause notice of the petition and order to be given to the respondent. The
court shall also cause a form to request a show-cause hearing to be served
upon the respondent. If the respondent wishes to appear and show cause why
the order should not remain in effect, he or she shall affix his or her current
address, telephone number, and signature to the form and return it to the
clerk of the district court within five days after service upon him or her.
Upon receipt of the request for a show-cause hearing, the request of the petitioner,
or upon the court's own motion, the court shall immediately schedule a show-cause
hearing to be held within thirty days after the receipt of the request for
a show-cause hearing and shall notify the petitioner and respondent of the
hearing date. If the respondent appears at the hearing and shows
cause why such order should not remain in effect, the court shall rescind
the temporary order.
If the respondent does not so appear and show cause, the temporary order shall be affirmed and shall be deemed the final protection
order. If the respondent has been properly served with the ex parte order
and fails to appear at the hearing, the temporary order shall be affirmed
and the service of the ex parte order shall be notice of the final protection
order for purposes of prosecution under subsection (4) of section 42-924.</para>
<para>(2) If an order under subsection (1) of section 42-924 is
not issued ex parte, the court shall immediately schedule an evidentiary hearing
to be held within fourteen days after the filing of the petition, and the
court shall cause notice of the hearing to be given to the petitioner and
the respondent. If the respondent does not appear at the hearing and show
cause why such order should not be issued, the court shall issue a final protection order.</para>
<para>(3) The court may by rule or order refer or assign all matters
regarding orders issued under subsection (1) of section 42-924 to a referee
for findings and recommendations.</para>
<para>(4) An order issued under subsection (1) of section 42-924
shall remain in effect for a period of one year from the date of issuance,
unless dismissed or modified by the
court prior to such date. If the order grants temporary custody, such custody
shall not exceed the number of days specified by the court unless the respondent
shows cause why the order should not remain in effect.</para>
<para>(5) The court shall also cause the notice created under section
29-2291 to be served upon the respondent notifying the respondent that it
may be unlawful under federal law for a person who is subject to a protection
order to possess or receive any firearm or ammunition.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 623, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 330, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 218, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB310, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not procedurally limit a litigant's right to call witnesses at a show cause hearing. Zuco v. Tucker, 9 Neb. App. 155, 609 N.W.2d 59 (2000).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>