<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<sectno id="id20" opdate="September 30, 2009">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Households and Families" id="id21" statutenumber="42-369"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id23">42-369</statuteno><catchline id="id24">Support or alimony;
presumption; items includable; payments; disbursement; enforcement; health
insurance.</catchline><para>(1) All orders, decrees, or judgments
for temporary or permanent support payments, including child, spousal, or
medical support, and all orders, decrees, or judgments for alimony or modification
of support payments or alimony shall direct the payment of such sums to be
made commencing on the first day of each month for the use of the persons
for whom the support payments or alimony have been awarded. Such payments
shall be made to the clerk of the district court (a) when the order, decree,
or judgment is for spousal support, alimony, or maintenance support and the
order, decree, or judgment does not also provide for child support, and (b)
when the payment constitutes child care or day care expenses, unless payments
under subdivision (1)(a) or (1)(b) of this section are ordered to be made
directly to the obligee. All other support order payments shall be made to
the State Disbursement Unit. In all cases in which income withholding has
been implemented pursuant to the Income Withholding for Child Support Act
or sections 42-364.01 to 42-364.14, support order payments shall be made to
the State Disbursement Unit. The court may order such payment to be in cash
or guaranteed funds.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If the party against
whom an order, decree, or judgment for child support is entered or the custodial party has health insurance
available to him or her through an employer, organization, or other health insurance entity which
may extend to cover any children affected by the order, decree, or judgment and the health care coverage is accessible
to the children and is available to the responsible party at reasonable cost,
the court shall require health care coverage to be provided. Health care coverage
is accessible if the covered children can obtain services from a plan provider
with reasonable effort by the custodial party. When the administrative agency,
court, or other tribunal determines that the only health care coverage option
available through the noncustodial party is a plan that limits service coverage
to providers within a defined geographic area, the administrative agency,
court, or other tribunal shall determine whether the child lives within the
plan's service area. If the child does not live within the plan's service
area, the administrative agency, court, or other tribunal shall determine
whether the plan has a reciprocal agreement that permits the child to receive
coverage at no greater cost than if the child resided in the plan's service
area. The administrative agency, court, or other tribunal shall also determine
if primary care is available within thirty minutes or thirty miles of the
child's residence. For the purpose of determining the accessibility of health
care coverage, the administrative agency, court, or other tribunal may determine
and include in an order that longer travel times are permissible if residents,
in part or all of the service area, customarily travel distances farther than
thirty minutes or thirty miles. If primary care services are not available
within these constraints, the health care coverage is presumed inaccessible.
If health care coverage is not available or is inaccessible and one or more
of the parties are receiving Title IV-D services, then cash medical support
shall be ordered. Cash medical support or the cost of private health insurance
is considered reasonable in cost if the cost to the party responsible for
providing medical support does not exceed three percent of his or her gross
income. In applying the three-percent standard, the cost is the cost of adding
the children to existing health care coverage or the difference between self-only
and family health care coverage. Cash medical support payments shall not be
ordered if, at the time that the order is issued or modified, the responsible
party's income is or such expense would reduce the responsible party's net
income below the basic subsistence limitation provided in Nebraska Court Rule
section 4-218. If such rule does not describe a basic subsistence limitation,
the responsible party's net income shall not be reduced below nine hundred
three dollars net monthly income for one person or below the poverty guidelines
updated annually in the Federal Register by the United States Department of
Health and Human Services under the authority of 42 U.S.C. 9902(2).</para>
<para>(b) For purposes
of this section:</para><para>(i) Health care coverage has the same meaning as in section 44-3,144;
and</para><para>(ii) Cash medical support means an amount ordered to be paid toward
the cost of health insurance provided by a public entity or by another parent
through employment or otherwise or for other medical costs not covered by
insurance.</para><para>(3) A
support order, decree, or judgment may include the providing of necessary
shelter, food, clothing, care, medical support as defined in section 43-512,
medical attention, expenses of confinement, education expenses, funeral expenses,
and any other expense the court may deem reasonable and necessary.</para>
<para>(4) Orders, decrees, and judgments for temporary or permanent
support or alimony shall be filed with the clerk of the district court and
have the force and effect of judgments when entered. The clerk and the State
Disbursement Unit shall disburse all payments received as directed by the
court and as provided in sections 42-358.02 and 43-512.07. Records shall be
kept of all funds received and disbursed by the clerk and the unit and shall
be open to inspection by the parties and their attorneys.</para>
<para>(5) Unless otherwise specified by the court, an equal and
proportionate share of any child support awarded shall be presumed to be payable
on behalf of each child subject to the order, decree, or judgment for purposes
of an assignment under section 43-512.07.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 820, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 371, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 435, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 972, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Income Withholding for Child Support Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under subsection (4) of this section, alimony judgments are liens, and if the judgments precede a mortgage and are recorded, they will have priority over that mortgage. McCook Nat. Bank v. Myers, 243 Neb. 853, 503 N.W.2d 200 (1993).</para><para>Subsection (4) of this section applied in a situation where the decree is silent with respect to accrued, unpaid temporary child support. Dartmann v. Dartmann, 14 Neb. App. 864, 717 N.W.2d 519 (2006).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, in a divorce case, a judge may not order both parties to provide health insurance for the child or children, but must direct which party shall provide such insurance. Ward v. Ward, 7 Neb. App. 821, 585 N.W.2d 551 (1998).</para><para>Expenses incurred in obtaining medical care for a child, including allowances for mileage and meals, may be included in a support order if the court finds such expenses are reasonable and necessary. The expenses cannot be applied retroactively to the application for modification of the order for support. Hoover v. Hoover, 2 Neb. App. 239, 508 N.W.2d 316 (1993).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>