<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Husband And Wife" statutenumber="42-808"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>42-808</statuteno><catchline>Counselor of conciliation; counties with 250,000 inhabitants or more; personnel; appointment; powers; compensation.</catchline><para>(1) In each county with a population of two hundred fifty thousand inhabitants or more, the county court and district court may appoint one counselor of conciliation and one secretary to assist the conciliation court in disposing of its business and carrying out its functions.</para><para>(2) The counselor of conciliation so appointed shall have the power to:</para><para>(a) Hold conciliation conferences with parties to and hearings in proceedings under the Conciliation Court Law and make recommendations concerning such proceedings to the judge of the conciliation court;</para><para>(b) Provide such supervision in connection with the exercise of his or her jurisdiction as the judge of the conciliation court may direct;</para><para>(c) Cause such reports to be made, such statistics to be compiled, and such records to be kept as the judge of the conciliation court may direct;</para><para>(d) Hold such hearings in all conciliation court cases as may be required by the judge of the conciliation court and make such investigations as may be required by the court to carry out the intent of the Conciliation Court Law;</para><para>(e) Make investigations provided for by sections 42-351 and 42-358 as may be directed by the judge of the conciliation court; and</para><para>(f) Hold informal hearings under section 42-367 and make recommendations to the court for entry of orders thereunder as may be directed by the judge of the conciliation court.</para><para>(3) The judge of the conciliation court may also appoint, with the consent of the board of county commissioners, such associate counselors of conciliation and other office assistants as may be necessary to assist the conciliation court in disposing of its business. Such associate counselors shall carry out their duties under the supervision of the judge of the conciliation court and shall have all the powers of the counselor of conciliation. Office assistants shall work under the supervision and direction of the counselor of conciliation.</para><para>(4) Salaries of persons appointed under this section shall be fixed by the board of county commissioners. All persons appointed under this section may be dismissed for any reason by a majority vote of the judges of the county court and the district court of the county.</para><para>(5) The board of county commissioners shall furnish adequate office space, equipment, and supplies for the use of the personnel of the conciliation court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 228, &#167; 8, p. 655; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 23, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 229, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc>