<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id9"><sectno id="id10" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 36.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Husband and Wife" id="id11" statutenumber="42-925"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id13">42-925</statuteno><catchline id="id14">Ex parte protection order; duration; notice requirements; hearing; notice; referral to referee; notice regarding firearm or ammunition.</catchline><para>(1) An order issued under subsection (1) of section 42-924 may be issued ex parte to the respondent if it reasonably appears from the specific facts included in the affidavit that the petitioner will be in immediate danger of abuse before the matter can be heard on notice. If an order is issued ex parte, the court shall immediately schedule an evidentiary hearing to be held within thirty days after service of such order, and the court shall cause notice of the hearing to be given to the petitioner and the respondent. If the respondent appears at the hearing and shows cause why such order should not remain in effect, the court shall rescind the order. If the respondent does not so appear and show cause, the order shall be affirmed.</para><para>(2) If an order under subsection (1) of section 42-924 is not issued ex parte, the court shall immediately schedule an evidentiary hearing to be held within fourteen days after the filing of the petition, and the court shall cause notice of the hearing to be given to the petitioner and the respondent. If the respondent does not appear at the hearing and show cause why such order should not be issued, the court shall issue such order.</para><para>(3) The court may by rule or order refer or assign all matters regarding orders issued under subsection (1) of section 42-924 to a referee for findings and recommendations.</para><para>(4) An order issued under subsection (1) of section 42-924 shall remain in effect for a period of one year from the date of issuance, unless vacated by the court prior to such date. If the order grants temporary custody, such custody shall not exceed the number of days specified by the court unless the respondent shows cause why the order should not remain in effect.</para><para>(5) The court shall also cause the notice created under section 29-2291 to be served upon the respondent notifying the respondent that it may be unlawful under federal law for a person who is subject to a protection order to possess or receive any firearm or ammunition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 623, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 330, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 218, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 36.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2008</operativedate></source><annotation><para>This section does not procedurally limit a litigant's right to call witnesses at a show cause hearing. Zuco v. Tucker, 9 Neb. App. 155, 609 N.W.2d 59 (2000).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
