<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<sectno id="id16" opdate="May 23, 2009">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id17" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id19">2-113</statuteno><catchline id="id20">Transfer of Nebraska
State Fairgrounds; conditions; Nebraska State Fair relocated to city of Grand
Island; Nebraska State Fair Board; duties.</catchline><para>(1)
Upon completion of the conditions specified in subsection (2) of this section,
the Director of Administrative Services shall, on or before December 31, 2009,
transfer by warranty deed the site and tract of land in Lancaster County known
as the Nebraska State Fairgrounds, to the Board of Regents of the University
of Nebraska. Such transfer shall occur notwithstanding sections 72-811 to
72-818 or any other provision of law.</para>
<para>(2) The transfer described in subsection (1) of this section
shall be contingent upon:</para>
<para>(a) Funds for the purpose of carrying out subsection (4) of
section 2-101 having been provided by or on behalf of the University of Nebraska
in a total amount of no less than twenty-one million five hundred thousand
dollars in cash or legally binding commitments. Such funds may be provided
over time, but they shall in cumulative increments equal at least seven million
five hundred thousand dollars by October 1, 2008, fourteen million five hundred
thousand dollars by February 1, 2009, and twenty-one million five hundred
thousand dollars by July 1, 2009;</para>
<para>(b) The University of Nebraska providing a master plan and
business plan to carry out the master plan for the Innovation Campus to the
Department of Administrative Services and to the Clerk of the Legislature
on or before December 1, 2009, and a commitment to provide on or before December
1 of each year thereafter an annual update of the master plan and business
plan to the Clerk of the Legislature; and</para>
<para>(c) Funds for the purpose of carrying out subsection (4) of
section 2-101 having been provided by or on behalf of the city of Grand Island
in a total amount of no less than eight million five hundred thousand dollars
in cash or legally binding commitments. Up
to one million five hundred thousand dollars in cash or legally binding commitments
provided by or on behalf of the city of Grand Island for the purpose of relocating
and reconstructing recreational facilities displaced by the relocation of
the Nebraska State Fair to Grand Island may be considered part of the eight-million-five-hundred-thousand-dollar
contribution required by this subdivision. Such funds may be provided
over time, but they shall in cumulative increments equal at least three million
dollars by October 1, 2008, six million dollars by February 1, 2009, and eight
million five hundred thousand dollars by July 1, 2009.</para>
<para>(3) The University of Nebraska and the city of Grand Island
shall provide certification to the Department of Administrative Services on
October 1, 2008, February 1, 2009, and July 1, 2009, of all funds provided
to carry out subsection (4) of section 2-101. All amounts as certified in
subdivisions (2)(a) and (c) of this section shall be held and expended as
determined by agreement between the Hall County Livestock Improvement Association
and the Nebraska State Fair Board.</para>
<para>(4)(a) The Nebraska State Fair shall be relocated to the city
of Grand Island pursuant to subsection (4) of section 2-101 contingent upon
completion of the conditions specified in subdivisions
(2)(a) and (c) of this section.</para>
<para>(b) The Nebraska State Fair Board shall be responsible for
any remaining costs associated with site improvements for relocating the Nebraska
State Fair, not to exceed seven million dollars.</para>
<para>(c) On or before December 31, 2009, the Nebraska State Fair
Board shall provide written release or other written instrument acceptable
to the State Building Administrator in consultation with the President of
the University of Nebraska in connection with the transfer of the Nebraska
State Fairgrounds to the Board of Regents.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB224, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>