<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id330"><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-508"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-508</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2024, LB262, ยง52. Operative date January 1, 2025. License fees; delinquent fee; administrative fee; waiver by department; grounds.</catchline><para>(1) License fees under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act are due on or before December 31 and shall be in the amount listed in column A of subsection (2) of this section. The fees due on or before December 31, 2019, and by each December 31 thereafter shall be set by the director on or before July 1 of each year. The director may raise or lower such fees each year to meet the criteria in this subsection, but the fee shall not be greater than the amount in column B of subsection (2) of this section. The same percentage shall be applied to each category for all fee increases or decreases. The director shall use the fees in column A of subsection (2) of this section as a base for future fee increases or decreases. The director shall determine the fees based on estimated annual revenue and fiscal year-end cash fund balances as follows:</para><para>(a) The estimated annual revenue shall not be greater than one hundred seven percent of program cash fund appropriations allocated for the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act; and</para><para>(b) The estimated fiscal year-end cash fund balance shall not be greater than seventeen percent of program cash fund appropriations allocated for the act.</para><para>(2) Fees.</para><para><table frame="none"><tgroup align="center" cols="3"><colspec align="center" colname="col1" colwidth="2.28*"/><colspec align="center" colname="col2" colwidth="1.25*"/><colspec align="center" colname="col3" colwidth="1.25*"/><tbody><row><entry>Fees</entry><entry>A</entry><entry>B</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cultivator, processor-handler, and</entry><entry align="right"/><entry/></row><row><entry align="left">broker license application fee</entry><entry align="right">$100</entry><entry align="right">$150</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Cultivator site registration fee</entry><entry align="right">$400 per site</entry><entry align="right">$600 per site</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Processor-handler site</entry><entry/><entry/></row><row><entry align="left">registration fee</entry><entry align="right">$800 per site</entry><entry align="right">$1,200 per site</entry></row><row><entry align="left">Site modification fee</entry><entry align="right">$50</entry><entry align="right">$75</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para><para>(3) Any fee remaining unpaid for more than one month shall be considered delinquent and the person owing the fee shall pay an additional administrative fee of twenty-five percent of the delinquent amount for each month it remains unpaid, not to exceed one hundred percent of the original amount due. The department may waive the additional administrative fee based upon the existence and extent of any mitigating circumstances that have resulted in the late payment of such fee. The purpose of the additional administrative fee is to cover the administrative costs associated with collecting fees, and all money collected as an additional administrative fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Hemp Program Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>