<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id378"><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-514"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>2-514</statuteno><catchline>Testing; department; powers; list of approved testing facilities; report.</catchline><para>(1) Hemp from each cultivation site registered with the department shall be tested for delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration prior to harvest by an approved testing facility at the licensee's expense. The results of such tests shall be certified directly to the department by the testing facility prior to harvest. The test results shall identify the location ID where the hemp was cultivated.</para><para>(2) The department may, at its discretion, conduct sampling and testing of any hemp from any licensee at any time.</para><para>(3) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the sampling and testing of hemp, including, but not limited to, the number of samples required, the procedure for gathering samples, and certification of the test results to the department.</para><para>(4) Testing of hemp required under this section shall be conducted pursuant to standards adopted by the department using post-decarboxylation or other similarly reliable methods for the testing of delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration.</para><para>(5) Testing of hemp shall be conducted by a testing facility approved by the department.</para><para>(6) The department shall create and maintain a list of approved testing facilities.</para><para>(7) The entire hemp plant is not required to be submitted for testing.</para><para>(8) The test sample shall be obtained from flowering tops when flowering is occurring, shall be approximately eight inches in length, and shall consist of the fan leaf, the stalk, the flower, and, if available, the seed head.</para><para>(9) The requirements of this section shall be sufficient for both dioecious and monoecious cultivars.</para><para>(10) The approved testing facility shall provide a report giving the results of the potency analysis of each sample. For tests directed by the department, the report shall be provided to the licensee and a copy of the report shall be issued to the department. The report shall be provided before the harvest date, if applicable.</para><para>(11) When a test result is adverse, the department may require a licensee to have further tests done and may require harvesting and destruction of any plants in any portions of the site containing noncompliant plants.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>