
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-503</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act:</para><para>(1) Acceptable hemp THC level has the same meaning as in 7 C.F.R. 990.1, as such section existed on January 1, 2020;</para><para>(2) Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 means section 10113 of the federal Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018, Public Law 115-334, and any regulations adopted and promulgated under such section, as such section, act, and regulations existed on January 1, 2020;</para><para>(3) Approved testing facility means a testing facility approved by the department;</para><para>(4) Broker means a person who engages or participates in the marketing of hemp by acting as an intermediary or negotiator between prospective buyers and sellers;</para><para>(5) Commercial sale means the sale of products in the stream of commerce, at retail, wholesale, and online;</para><para>(6) Commission means the Nebraska Hemp Commission;</para><para>(7) Cultivate or cultivating means planting, watering, growing, and harvesting a hemp plant or crop. The presence of plants of the plant Cannabis sativa L. growing as uncultivated, naturalized plants in the environment is not cultivating hemp for purposes of the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act;</para><para>(8) Cultivator means a person who cultivates hemp;</para><para>(9) Department means the Department of Agriculture;</para><para>(10) Director means the Director of Agriculture or his or her designee;</para><para>(11) GPS coordinates means latitude and longitude coordinates derived from a global positioning system;</para><para>(12) Handle or handling means possessing or storing hemp plants or hemp plant parts prior to cultivation, in the process of cultivation, or after being harvested or dried but before processing. Handle or handling also includes possessing or storing such hemp plants or hemp plant parts in a vehicle for any period of time other than during its actual transport from the premises of a person licensed to cultivate or process hemp to the premises of another licensee. Handle or handling does not include possessing, storing, or transporting finished hemp products or hemp seeds;</para><para>(13) Hemp means the plant Cannabis sativa L. and any part of such plant, including the viable seeds of such plant and all derivatives, extracts, cannabinoids, isomers, acids, salts, and salts of isomers, whether growing or not, with a delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration of not more than 0.3 percent on a dry weight basis. Hemp shall be considered an agricultural commodity. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, hemp shall not be considered a controlled substance under the Uniform Controlled Substances Act;</para><para>(14) Licensee means an individual or a business entity possessing a license issued by the department under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act, including authorized employees or agents of such licensee, to cultivate, handle, process, or broker hemp;</para><para>(15) Location ID means the unique identifier established by a licensee for each unique set of GPS coordinates where hemp is cultivated, handled, or processed;</para><para>(16) Lot means a contiguous area in a field, greenhouse, or indoor growing structure containing the same variety or strain of hemp throughout such area;</para><para>(17) Measurement of uncertainty has the same meaning as in 7 C.F.R. 990.1, as such section existed on January 1, 2020;</para><para>(18) Person means an individual, partnership, corporation, limited liability company, association, postsecondary institution, or other legal entity;</para><para>(19) Postsecondary institution means a postsecondary institution as defined in section 85-2403 that also meets the requirements of 20 U.S.C. 1001, as such section existed on January 1, 2019;</para><para>(20) Process or processing means converting hemp plants or plant parts into a marketable form;</para><para>(21) Processor-handler means a person who handles or processes hemp;</para><para>(22) Site means an area defined by the same legal description in a field, greenhouse, or other outdoor area or indoor structure, or for a mobile processor, such processor's primary place of business;</para><para>(23) THC means tetrahydrocannabinol; and</para><para>(24) USDA-licensed hemp producer means a person licensed by the United States Department of Agriculture to produce hemp as provided in 7 C.F.R. part 990, subpart C, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2020.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1152, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>