<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-515"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>2-515</statuteno><catchline>Transportation of hemp; requirements; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, any USDA-licensed hemp producer or state-program-licensed hemp producer transporting hemp shall carry with the hemp being transported a copy of the USDA license or state program license under which it was cultivated and a copy of the test results pertaining to each lot of hemp being transported.</para><para>(2) A USDA-licensed hemp producer or state-program-licensed hemp producer under a USDA-approved tribal program cultivating hemp in this state shall maintain a record of shipments of hemp shipped from or received by such producer. Such record shall, for each shipment of hemp, indicate the date of shipment, identify the point of origin and destination, identify the name of the person sending and receiving the shipment, and include the vehicle identification number of the vehicle transporting the hemp.</para><para>(3) Any USDA-licensed hemp producer or state-program-licensed hemp producer transporting hemp cultivated under such producer's USDA license or state program license shall not be required to carry a copy of the test results relating to such hemp as provided in subsection (1) of this section if such producer carries with the hemp being transported a copy of the applicable USDA license or state program license and is transporting:</para><para>(a) Hemp between two registered sites listed on the producer's USDA or state program license application;</para><para>(b) Samples of hemp for testing to determine the tetrahydrocannabinol level; or</para><para>(c) Live hemp plants to a registered site listed on the producer's USDA or state program license application prior to cultivating such hemp plants.</para><para>(4) Any person who is carrying or transporting hemp who is not a USDA-licensed hemp producer or state-program-licensed hemp producer shall only carry or transport hemp if such hemp meets the following requirements:</para><para>(a) The hemp is carried or transported with a bill of lading stating the owner of the hemp, the point of origin of the hemp, and the destination of the hemp;</para><para>(b) The hemp is carried or transported with a copy of the valid USDA or state program license under which the hemp was cultivated;</para><para>(c) The hemp is carried or transported with a copy of the test results pertaining to each lot of hemp being transported; and</para><para>(d) The hemp is not unloaded or in any way removed from the vehicle transporting such hemp unless authorized by state or federal law enforcement.</para><para>(5) No person shall transport or carry hemp in this state concurrently with any other plant material that is not hemp.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1152, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB262, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>