<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id40"><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-414"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>2-414</statuteno><catchline>Nitrogen reduction incentive program; created; incentive payments; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The nitrogen reduction incentive program is created and shall be administered by the Department of Natural Resources. The department may collaborate with natural resources districts to administer the program.</para><para>(2) The purposes of the program are to:</para><para>(a) Provide incentive payments to farmers; and</para><para>(b) Encourage farmers to (i) reduce the use of commercial fertilizer and (ii) incorporate innovative technology into farming practices, including the proper use of biological nitrogen products.</para><para>(3) The program shall provide an annual per-acre incentive for any farmer who verifies through documentation that commercial fertilizer rates were reduced by the lesser of forty pounds per acre for nitrogen or fifteen percent by incorporating a qualifying product in the farmer's nutrient plans.</para><para>(4) A commercial fertilizer rate reduction from historic baseline use shall be completed to qualify for the program.</para><para>(5) The department shall review the required commercial fertilizer rate of reduction for the program on a biennial basis to determine if higher reduction targets are necessary.</para><para>(6) The department shall:</para><para>(a) Collaborate with natural resources districts to add any new technology to the program as it becomes available. Such technology shall replace nitrogen fertilizer use and maintain farm productivity;</para><para>(b) Identify geographically beneficial target areas while keeping the program open to all farmers in the state;</para><para>(c) Consult with farmers and commercial entities in the agriculture industry to determine a per-acre payment rate tied to the commercial fertilizer rate reduction but not less than ten dollars per acre; and</para><para>(d) Review the per-acre payment rate based on inflation or emerging technology in subsequent years.</para><para>(7)(a) The department shall not award an amount of incentive payments in total per year under the nitrogen reduction incentive program that is greater than the lesser of:</para><para>(i) Five million dollars; or</para><para>(ii) The amount appropriated for such purpose by the Legislature.</para><para>(b) It is the intent of the Legislature that any appropriation from the General Fund to carry out the Nitrogen Reduction Incentive Act be used only for operating expenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1368, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate><terminationdate>December 31, 2029</terminationdate></source></law>
</legaldoc>