<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-953.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-953.01</statuteno><catchline>County weed district board; elections; membership.</catchline><para>The county board may, following an election in which a majority of the votes cast are in favor of such action, function as and exercise the authority and carry out the duties of the county weed district board. To initiate such an election, the county board may, by resolution, require the county clerk of such county to have placed upon the ballot at the election next following such resolution, the question, Shall the county weed district board be dissolved and its duties and authority be exercised by the county board? </para><para>Yes .... No ....</para><para>If a majority of the votes cast on this question are opposed to dissolution of the county weed district board, the county shall remain subject to the direction and authority of the elected county weed district board. If a majority of the votes cast on this question are in favor of the dissolution of the county weed district board, the county board shall function as and exercise the authority and carry out the duties of the county weed district board. If, at any time following the dissolution of the county weed district board, county residents, representing at least ten percent of the votes cast in the preceding general election in such county, submit a petition to the county clerk for reestablishment of the county weed district board as an independent elected body, the clerk shall place the following question on the next general election ballot: Shall the county weed district board be reestablished and elected independent of other county officials? </para><para>Yes .... No ....</para><para>If a majority of the ballots favor reestablishment of the independent board, the county board shall appoint an initial county weed district board and thereafter the county weed district board members shall be elected in conformity with section 32-531.</para><para>When the county board does not function as the county weed district board, such board shall be composed of five members, three of whom shall be from rural areas and two of whom shall be from cities, villages, or townships.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 451.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election of county weed district board members,</emphasis> see section 32-531.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>