<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-222"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-222</statuteno><catchline>County fair; election to establish.</catchline><para>Any county may accept the provisions of and proceed under sections 2-221 to 2-231 by resolution duly adopted by the county board. The resolution shall indicate whether the membership of the county fair board to be established under such sections would be elected or appointed pursuant to section 2-224. If, after the adoption of a resolution for such purpose, fifteen percent of the registered voters of the county file with the county board a petition requesting that the acceptance of the provisions of such sections be submitted to the voters of the county, the county board shall submit the same to a vote of the people in like manner as the question of voting courthouse bonds may be submitted. During the time such question is pending for the vote of the people, no further proceedings shall be had for the establishment of a county fair board. If ten percent of the registered voters of the county file a petition with the county board asking that the question of the acceptance of the provisions of such sections and specifying whether the membership of the county fair board to be established under such sections would be elected or appointed pursuant to section 2-224 be submitted to a vote of the people, the county board shall submit such question to the voters in like manner as the question of voting courthouse bonds may be submitted. If a majority of the votes cast upon the question are in favor of such proposition, the county board shall immediately proceed to establish a county fair board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 168, &#167; 2, p. 377; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 58; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 2-211; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-222; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 437, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Issuance of courthouse bonds,</emphasis> see section 23-120.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under this section, two methods are provided by which a county may accept the provisions of the County Fair Act, and when proceeding under the second method, publication of notice required herein is mandatory. Richardson v. Kildow, 116 Neb. 648, 218 N.W. 429 (1928).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>