<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-229"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-229</statuteno><catchline>County fair; tax levy; amount; collection; budget statement.</catchline><para>(1) During the month of November each year, each appointed county fair board shall prepare and submit to the county board an estimate, itemized as far as possible, of the amount of money which is necessary to be collected by taxation for the support and management of the fair for the ensuing year. The county board may, subject to section 77-3442, levy such amount of taxes as may be necessary but not to exceed the amount actually required for county fair purposes, including capital construction on and renovation, repair, improvement, and maintenance of county fairgrounds. Such tax shall be levied and collected in like manner as general taxes for the county.</para><para>(2) Each elected county fair board shall annually prepare a budget statement setting forth the amount of money necessary for the operation of the county fair board. On or before August 1, the president and the secretary of the board shall certify the amount of tax to be levied upon all the taxable property within the county for the operation of the county fair board for the ensuing year subject to allocation under section 77-3443. The tax shall be assessed, levied, and collected as other county taxes. The proceeds of such tax shall be paid by the county treasurer to the treasurer of the county fair board. The county fair board may act to exceed the allocation provided by the county board under section 77-3444, but if the county fair board acts to exceed the allocation, the total levy shall not exceed three and one-half cents per one hundred dollars of valuation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 168, &#167; 10, p. 379; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 66; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 2-219; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-229; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 398, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 437, &#167; 9.</para></source></law></legaldoc>