<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-953"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-953</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Noxious Weed Control Act:</para><para>(1) Person means any individual, partnership, firm, limited liability company, corporation, company, society, or association, the state or any department, agency, or subdivision thereof, or any other public or private entity;</para><para>(2)(a) Control, with respect to land, means the authority to operate, manage, supervise, or exercise jurisdiction over or any similar power. The state or federal government or a political subdivision shall not be deemed to control land on which it has an easement as long as it does not otherwise operate, manage, supervise, or exercise jurisdiction over the land; and</para><para>(b) Control, with respect to weeds, means the prevention, suppression, or limitation of the growth, spread, propagation, or development or the eradication of weeds;</para><para>(3) County board means the county board of commissioners or supervisors;</para><para>(4) Noxious weeds means and includes any weeds designated and listed as noxious in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director;</para><para>(5) Control authority means the county weed district board or the county board if it is designated as the control authority pursuant to section 2-953.01, which board shall represent all rural areas and cities, villages, and townships within the county boundaries;</para><para>(6) Director means the Director of Agriculture or his or her designated representative; and</para><para>(7) Weed management entity means an entity recognized by the director as being established by and consisting of local stakeholders, including tribal governments, for the purpose of controlling or eradicating harmful, invasive weeds and increasing public knowledge and education concerning the need to control or eradicate harmful, invasive weeds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 7, &#167; 2, p. 78; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 151; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 14, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 1, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 138, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 49, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 453; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 869, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>