<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id194"><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>2-506</statuteno><catchline>Processor-handler or broker; license; application; form; contents; application fee; site registration fee; processor-handler or broker license; expiration; renewal; change in ownership or location; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Except for approved testing facilities, a person shall not process, handle, or broker hemp in this state unless the person meets the requirements of section 2-5701 or is in compliance with this section and licensed as a processor-handler or broker under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act.</para><para>(2) Before a person other than an approved testing facility may be licensed to process, handle, or broker hemp in this state, such person shall submit an application on a form prescribed by the department that includes, but is not limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) If the applicant is an individual, the applicant's full name, birthdate, mailing address, telephone number, and valid email address;</para><para>(b) If the applicant is an entity and not an individual, the name of the applicant, mailing address, telephone number, and valid email address, the full name of each officer and director, partner, member, or owner owning in excess of ten percent of equity or stock in such entity, and the birthdate, title, mailing address, telephone number, and valid email address of each such person;</para><para>(c) The street address, legal description, location ID, and GPS coordinates for the site where hemp will be processed or handled, if applicable; and</para><para>(d) Maps depicting the site where hemp will be processed or handled, if applicable, with appropriate indications for entrances and specific locations corresponding to the GPS coordinates provided under subdivision (c) of this subsection.</para><para>(3) Before a person other than an approved testing facility may be licensed to process, handle, or broker hemp, such person shall submit with the application a nonrefundable application fee as set by the department pursuant to section 2-508.</para><para>(4) Before a person other than an approved testing facility may be licensed to process or handle hemp, such person shall submit with the application a nonrefundable site registration fee as set by the department pursuant to section 2-508. The site registration fee shall be paid for each separate site where hemp is processed or handled. Subsequent modifications to the sites listed in the application shall be submitted on forms prescribed by the department along with the site modification fee and shall only take effect upon written approval of the department. The applicant must certify that all sites where hemp is to be processed or handled are under the control of the applicant and that the department shall have unlimited access to all such sites.</para><para>(5) After the department receives approval by the United States Secretary of Agriculture for the state plan submitted pursuant to section 2-516, an initial processor-handler or broker license application may be submitted at any time. An initial processor-handler or broker license issued by the department expires on December 31 in the calendar year for which it was issued.</para><para>(6) A renewal application for a processor-handler or broker license shall be submitted on forms prescribed by the department. A renewal application is due by December 31 and shall be accompanied by the processor-handler or broker license fee and, if applicable, the site registration fee for all sites listed in the renewal application. The renewal processor-handler or broker license is valid from January 1 or when the license is granted, whichever is later, through December 31 next following.</para><para>(7) A processor-handler or broker license shall lapse automatically upon a change of ownership or location, and a new license must be obtained. The licensee shall promptly provide notice of change in ownership or location to the department.</para><para>(8) A processor-handler licensee who also brokers hemp shall not be required to also obtain a broker license under this section.</para><para>(9) An application and supporting documents submitted to the department under this section are not public records subject to disclosure pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09. Such information may be submitted to the United States Department of Agriculture pursuant to the requirements of section 10113 of the federal Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018, Public Law 115-334, as such section existed on January 1, 2019, or any other federal statute, rule, or regulation, and may be submitted to law enforcement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 6. </para><operativedate>May 31, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>