
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id6" statutenumber="2-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">2-101</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Nebraska State Fair
Board; purpose; meetings; state fair; location; plan to relocate.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Nebraska State Fair Board, formerly known as the State
Board of Agriculture, shall hold an annual meeting for the purpose of deliberating
and consulting as to the wants, prospects, and conditions of the agricultural,
horticultural, industrial, mechanical, and other interests throughout the
state, as well as those interests in the encouragement and perpetuation of
the arts, skilled crafts, and sciences.</para>
<para>(2) The Nebraska State Fair Board may provide in its constitution
and bylaws for the qualification and participation of delegates at the annual
meeting from such associations incorporated under the laws of the state for
purposes of promoting and furthering the interests of participants in agricultural,
horticultural, industrial, mechanical, or other pursuits or for the encouragement
and perpetuation of the arts, skilled crafts, and sciences, and from such
associations as provide for the training, encouragement, and competition of
the youth of Nebraska in such endeavors. The annual meeting shall be held
in every odd-numbered year at the capital of the state and in every even-numbered
year at such location as the board determines. The chairperson of the board
shall also have the power to call meetings of the board whenever he or she
may deem it expedient. All meetings of the board shall be conducted in accordance
with the Open Meetings Act.</para>
<para>(3) The Nebraska State Fair shall be under the direction and
supervision of the Nebraska State Fair Board. The board may, at its discretion,
hold or dispense with the holding of the fair, in any year.</para>
<para>(4)(a) It is the intent of the Legislature that no later than 2010 the Nebraska
State Fair be permanently located within the city of Grand Island upon the
site and tract of land owned by the Hall County Livestock Improvement Association
and known as Fonner Park and,
as available and necessary, upon other parcels of land adjacent to Fonner
Park. The Nebraska State Fair Board shall cooperate and coordinate
with the Hall County Livestock Improvement Association, the city of Grand
Island, and other appropriate entities to provide for and carry out any plan
of improvements to such location, including the
construction of buildings and other capital facilities, the relocation of existing improvements, and
other enhancements, necessary to develop the site as a location suitable for
conducting the Nebraska State Fair. Such cooperation and coordination may
include financial participation in the costs of site development, new construction, and other capital improvements
upon such location and includes
the execution of any agreement for site governance, revenue sharing, and facility
utilization between and among the Nebraska State Fair Board, the Hall County
Livestock Improvement Association, and other appropriate entities.</para>
<para>(b) The Nebraska State Fair Board, the Department of Administrative
Services, and the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska shall cooperate
with each other and with other appropriate entities to provide for and carry
out the plan to relocate the Nebraska State Fair and transfer the Nebraska
State Fairgrounds in Lancaster County to the Board of Regents, including activities
by the Board of Regents to obtain due diligence surveys, reports, and site
assessments at the Nebraska State Fairgrounds in Lancaster County and by the
Nebraska State Fair Board in connection with providing marketable title to
the same in a form acceptable to the Board of Regents.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 1, p. 396; </para><para>Laws 1883, c. 1, &#167; 1, p. 57; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 1, &#167; 1, p. 51; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 2-101; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 1, &#167; 1, p. 51; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 2-101; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 2, &#167; 1, p. 55; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-101; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 544, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 30, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1236, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB224, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The Nebraska State Board of Agriculture is essentially a private corporation possessing no exemption from suit or liability. The Crete Mills v. Nebraska State Board of Agriculture, 132 Neb. 244, 271 N.W. 684 (1937).</para><para>State Board of Agriculture has duty to provide rules and regulations agreeable to which the constitution and bylaws of county agricultural societies must be framed. State ex rel. Otoe County Agricultural Assn. v. Wallen, 117 Neb. 397, 220 N.W. 688 (1928).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>