<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id50"><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-515"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>2-515</statuteno><catchline>Cultivator, processor-handler, or other person transporting hemp; duties; form bill of lading; department; duties; prohibited acts; peace officer; powers; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any cultivator transporting hemp cultivated under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act shall carry with the hemp being transported a copy of the cultivator license under which it was cultivated and a copy of the test results pertaining to such hemp.</para><para>(2) Any processor-handler transporting hemp processed under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act shall carry with the hemp being transported a copy of the processor-handler license under which the hemp is being transported and a copy of the test results pertaining to such hemp.</para><para>(3) Any person other than a cultivator or processor-handler who is transporting hemp shall carry with such hemp being transported (a) a bill of lading indicating the owner of the hemp, the point of origin of the hemp, and the destination of the hemp and (b) either a copy of the test results pertaining to such hemp or other documentation affirming that the hemp was produced in compliance with section 10113 of the federal Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018, Public Law 115-334, as such section existed on January 1, 2019.</para><para>(4)(a) The department may develop a form bill of lading for use by a person transporting hemp pursuant to subsection (3) of this section for hemp originating in this state. Such bill of lading shall, at a minimum, identify the transporting person and indicate the owner, point of origin, and destination of the hemp.</para><para>(b) The department, in consultation with the Nebraska State Patrol, may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations regulating the carrying or transporting of hemp in this state to ensure that marijuana or any other controlled substance is not disguised as hemp and carried or transported into, within, or through this state.</para><para>(c) No person shall carry or transport hemp in this state unless such hemp is:</para><para>(i) Produced in compliance with:</para><para>(A) For hemp originating in this state, the requirements of section 10113 of the federal Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018, Public Law 115-334, as such section existed on January 1, 2019, and the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act and any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated thereunder; or</para><para>(B) For hemp originating outside this state, the requirements of section 10113 of the federal Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018, Public Law 115-334, as such section existed on January 1, 2019; and</para><para>(ii) Carried or transported as provided in subsection (1), (2), or (3) of this section.</para><para>(d) No person shall transport hemp in this state concurrently with any other plant material that is not hemp.</para><para>(5)(a) A peace officer may detain any person carrying or transporting hemp in this state if such person does not provide the documentation required by this section. Unless the peace officer has probable cause to believe the hemp is, or is being carried or transported with, marijuana or any other controlled substance, the peace officer shall immediately release the hemp and the person carrying or transporting such hemp upon production of such documentation.</para><para>(b) The failure of a person detained as described in this subsection to produce documentation required by this section shall constitute probable cause to believe the hemp may be marijuana or any other controlled substance. In such case, a peace officer may collect such hemp for testing to determine the delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration in the hemp, and, if the peace officer has probable cause to believe the person detained is carrying or transporting marijuana or any other controlled substance in violation of state or federal law, the peace officer may seize and impound the hemp or marijuana or other controlled substance and arrest such person.</para><para>(c) This subsection does not limit or restrict in any way the power of a peace officer to enforce violations of the Uniform Controlled Substances Act and federal law regulating marijuana and other controlled substances.</para><para>(6) In addition to any other penalties provided by law, including those imposed under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act, any person who intentionally violates this section shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor and fined not more than one thousand dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 15. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>