<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id38"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id40" statutenumber="2-108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id42">2-108</statuteno><catchline id="id43">Nebraska State Fair Support and Improvement Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska State Fair Support and Improvement Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be maintained in the state accounting system as a cash fund. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund the disbursement of state lottery proceeds designated for the Nebraska State Fair and matching funds from the most populous city within the county in which the state fair is located. The balance of any fund that is administratively created to receive lottery proceeds designated for the Nebraska State Fair and matching fund revenue prior to May 25, 2005, shall be transferred to the Nebraska State Fair Support and Improvement Cash Fund on such date. The Nebraska State Fair Support and Improvement Cash Fund shall be expended by the Nebraska State Fair Board to provide support for operating expenses and capital facility enhancements, including new construction and other capital improvements and other enhancements to and upon any exhibition facility utilized as the location of the Nebraska State Fair. Expenditures from the fund shall not be limited to the amount appropriated. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB435, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc>