<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id14"><sectno id="id15" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id16" statutenumber="2-101.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id18">2-101.01</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Legislative findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that the Nebraska State Fair has been held annually for the exhibition and dissemination of agricultural, horticultural, industrial, mechanical, and other products and innovations and for exhibitions in the arts, skilled crafts, and sciences and is a beneficial cultural and educational event for the state and its citizens. The Legislature declares it to be in the public interest that management of the Nebraska State Fair be based upon a dynamic public-private partnership that includes the active participation of the state and local governments, the private sector, and the citizens of Nebraska. In order to achieve this goal, the Legislature finds that the Nebraska State Fair Board should endeavor to:</para><para>(1) Place a priority on the development of private funding sources, including corporate donations and sponsorships;</para><para>(2) Work with municipal officials to enhance the board's participation in local planning efforts and to create a partnership with local economic development and tourism officials;</para><para>(3) Maintain a policy of openness and accountability that allows for citizen participation in the operation of the Nebraska State Fair; and</para><para>(4) Regularly provide the Governor, the Legislature, and appropriate state agencies with information, including, but not limited to, the development of private funding sources, the use of state appropriations, the fiscal management of the Nebraska State Fair, and the activities and goals established for the Nebraska State Fair.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1236, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
