<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-505"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>2-505</statuteno><catchline>Cultivation of hemp; application; form; contents; application fee; site registration fee; cultivator license; expiration; renewal; change in ownership or location; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Hemp may only be cultivated by a USDA-licensed hemp producer or a person meeting the requirements of section 2-5701 or in compliance with this section.</para><para>(2) Before a person may be licensed to cultivate hemp under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act, such person shall submit an application on a form prescribed by the department that includes, but is not limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) If the applicant is an individual, the applicant's full name, birthdate, mailing address, telephone number, and valid email address;</para><para>(b) If the applicant is an entity and not an individual, (i) the name of the applicant, mailing address, telephone number, and valid email address, (ii) the full name of each officer, director, partner, member, or owner owning in excess of ten percent of equity or stock in such entity, (iii) the full name of each key participant as defined in 7 C.F.R. 990.1, and (iv) the birthdate, title, mailing address, telephone number, and valid email address of each such person or key participant;</para><para>(c) The proposed acreage to be cultivated or the square footage of a greenhouse or other indoor space to be cultivated;</para><para>(d) The street address, legal description, location ID, and GPS coordinates for each field, greenhouse, building, or other site where hemp will be cultivated. The site information may be verified by the department; and</para><para>(e) Maps depicting each site where hemp will be cultivated, with appropriate indications for entrances, field boundaries, and specific locations corresponding to the GPS coordinates provided under subdivision (d) of this subsection.</para><para>(3) Before a person may be licensed to cultivate hemp under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act, such person shall submit with the application a nonrefundable application fee as set by the department pursuant to section 2-508.</para><para>(4) Before a person may be licensed to cultivate hemp under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act, such person shall submit a site registration fee as set by the department pursuant to section 2-508. The site registration fee shall be paid for each separate site where the applicant will cultivate hemp. Subsequent modifications to the sites listed in the application shall be submitted on forms prescribed by the department along with a site modification fee and shall only take effect upon written approval of the department. The applicant must certify that all sites where hemp is to be cultivated are under the control of the applicant and that the department shall have unlimited access to all such sites.</para><para>(5) After the department receives approval by the United States Secretary of Agriculture for the state plan described in section 2-516, an initial cultivator license application may be submitted at any time, except that the department may set a cutoff date for applications ahead of the growing season. An initial cultivator license issued by the department expires on December 31 in the calendar year for which it was issued.</para><para>(6) A renewal application for a license to cultivate hemp shall be submitted on forms prescribed by the department. A renewal application is due by December 31 and shall be accompanied by the cultivator license fee and the site registration fee for all sites listed in the renewal application. The renewal cultivator license is valid from January 1 or when the license is granted, whichever is later, through December 31 next following.</para><para>(7) A cultivator license shall lapse automatically upon a change of ownership or location, and a new license must be obtained. The licensee shall promptly provide notice of change in ownership or location to the department.</para><para>(8) An application and supporting documents submitted to the department under this section are not public records subject to disclosure pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09. Such information may be submitted to the United States Department of Agriculture pursuant to the requirements of the federal Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 or any other federal statute, rule, or regulation, and may be submitted to law enforcement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1152, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>