<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-510"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-510</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2024, LB262, ยง52. Operative date January 1, 2025. Cultivator, processor-handler, or broker; consent to certain actions; acknowledge risk of financial loss under act.</catchline><para>(1) A cultivator, processor-handler, or broker consents to all of the following:</para><para>(a) A background check for any felony controlled substance charge in the ten years prior to the time of application completed by the department or a law enforcement agency at the direction of the department, at any time, for all of the individuals listed on the cultivator's, processor-handler's, or broker's application at the applicant's expense, which shall be in addition to the application and registration fees;</para><para>(b) Entry onto, and inspection of, all registered sites by the department or by persons at the direction of the department, with or without cause, and with reasonable advance notice;</para><para>(c) Reimbursement of the department for expenses relating to sampling and testing of any hemp or hemp material;</para><para>(d) Destruction of any of the following:</para><para>(i) Hemp found to have a measured delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration greater than the acceptable hemp THC level. Only hemp from lots found to have a measured delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol concentration greater than the acceptable hemp THC level shall be subject to destruction;</para><para>(ii) Hemp intended for commercial purposes that is present at a location not included in a cultivator's or processor-handler's application; and</para><para>(iii) Hemp that is cultivated, processed, handled, or brokered in a manner that violates the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated thereunder; and</para><para>(e) Inspections by the department, at least annually, of cultivators and processor-handlers to verify that hemp is not cultivated, processed, or handled in violation of the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act.</para><para>(2) A cultivator, processor-handler, or broker acknowledges that all risk of financial loss under the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act is borne by such person. No compensation shall be paid by the department or the State of Nebraska for destruction of any hemp under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1152, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>