<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1205"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1205</statuteno><catchline>License; terms and conditions; revocation; relocation of racetrack; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) If the commission is satisfied that its rules and regulations and all provisions of sections 2-1201 to 2-1218 have been and will be complied with, it may issue a license for a period of not more than five years. The license shall set forth the name of the licensee, the place where the races or race meetings are to be held, and the time and number of days during which racing may be conducted by such licensee. Any such license issued shall not be transferable or assignable. The commission shall have the power to revoke any license issued at any time for good cause upon reasonable notice and hearing. No license shall be granted to any corporation or association except upon the express condition that it shall not, by any lease, contract, understanding, or arrangement of whatever kind or nature, grant, assign, or turn over to any person, corporation, or association the operation or management of any racing or race meeting licensed under such sections or of the parimutuel system of wagering described in section 2-1207 or in any manner permit any person, corporation, or association other than the licensee to have any share, percentage, or proportion of the money received for admissions to the racing or race meeting or from the operation of the parimutuel system; and any violation of such conditions shall authorize and require the commission immediately to revoke such license.</para><para>(2)(a) Any racetrack for which a licensee is issued a license to conduct a race or race meeting under sections 2-1201 to 2-1218 which is in existence and operational as of April 20, 2022, shall:</para><para>(i) Hold a minimum of five live racing meet days and fifty live horseraces annually beginning January 1, 2026, through December 31, 2030; and</para><para>(ii) Beginning January 1, 2031, hold a minimum of fifteen live racing meet days and one hundred twenty live horseraces annually.</para><para>(b) Any racetrack for which a licensee is issued a license to conduct a race or race meeting under sections 2-1201 to 2-1218 which is not in existence and operational until after April 20, 2022, shall:</para><para>(i) Hold a minimum of one live racing meet day annually for the first three years of operation;</para><para>(ii) Hold a minimum of five live racing meet days and fifty live horseraces annually for the fourth year of operation through the seventh year of operation; and</para><para>(iii) Beginning with the eighth year of operation, hold a minimum of fifteen live racing meet days and one hundred twenty live horseraces annually.</para><para>(c) A racetrack that fails to meet the minimum requirements under this subsection is subject to discipline by the commission, including revocation of the license issued under sections 2-1201 to 2-1218.</para><para>(3) A racetrack for which a licensee is issued a license to conduct a race or race meeting under sections 2-1201 to 2-1218 in existence on November 1, 2020, which is located in the counties of Adams, Dakota, Douglas, Hall, Lancaster, and Platte, may move such racetrack location to another county in Nebraska that does not have a racetrack one time only, subject to approval by the commission as provided in subdivision (27) of section 9-1106, subsequent to the initial issuance of the market analysis and socioeconomic-impact studies conducted pursuant to section 9-1106.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 173, &#167; 5, p. 631; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 2-1505; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-1205; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 599, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1041, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB876, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>April 20, 2022</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Because a relicensure decision would involve a consideration of any rule violations by an equine veterinarian during prior periods of licensure, it is reasonable and consistent with the State Racing Commission's statutory purpose to promptly investigate and resolve alleged rule violations committed during a period of licensure, even if the process of doing so extends into a period when the subject is not licensed. Brunk v. Nebraska State Racing Comm., 270 Neb. 186, 700 N.W.2d 594 (2005).</para><para>Because relicensure of an equine veterinarian involves a consideration of prior rule violations, the State Racing Commission has authority to determine that a person who has violated its rules will not be eligible for relicensure for a specified period. Brunk v. Nebraska State Racing Comm., 270 Neb. 186, 700 N.W.2d 594 (2005).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>