<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id18">
<sectno id="id19">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id20" statutenumber="2-1219"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id22">2-1219</statuteno><catchline id="id23">State Racing Commission;
members; employees; activities prohibited; conflict of interest; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) When any matter comes
before the State Racing Commission that may cause financial benefit or detriment
to a member of the commission, a member of his or her immediate family, or
a business with which the member is associated, which is distinguishable from
the effects of such matter on the public generally or a broad segment of the
public, such member shall take the following actions as soon as he or she
is aware of such potential conflict or should reasonably be aware of such
potential conflict, whichever is sooner:</para><para>(a) Prepare a written statement describing the matter
requiring action or decision and the nature of the potential conflict;</para>
<para>(b) Deliver a copy of
the statement to the secretary of the commission; and</para><para>(c) Recuse himself or herself from
taking any action or making any decision relating to such matter in the discharge
of his or her official duties as a member of the commission.</para>
<para>(2) No horse in which any employee of the State Racing Commission has any interest
shall be raced at any meet under the jurisdiction of the commission.</para>
<para>(3) No employee of the State
Racing Commission shall
have a pecuniary interest or engage in any private employment in a profession
or business which is regulated by or interferes or conflicts with the performance
or proper discharge of the duties of the commission.</para>
<para>(4) No employee of the State
Racing Commission shall
wager or cause a wager to be placed on the outcome of any race at a race meeting
which is under the jurisdiction and supervision of the commission.</para>
<para>(5) No employee of the State
Racing Commission shall
have a pecuniary interest or engage in any private employment in a business
which does business with any racing association licensed by the commission
or in any business issued a concession operator license by the commission.</para>
<para>(6) Any commission employee violating
this section shall forfeit his or her employment.</para>
<para>(7) The commission shall include
in its rules and regulations prohibitions against actual or potential specific
conflicts of interest on the part of racing officials and other individuals
licensed by the commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 10, &#167; 1, p. 125; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 939, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>