<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1589"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1589</statuteno><catchline>Fund; allocations, grants, loans; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the administration of the Nebraska Resources Development Fund. The commission may make an allocation from the fund as a grant to an agency or political subdivision if the commission determines that such an allocation will not be reimbursed from revenue or receipts and when the program or project appears to be of general public benefit, thereby making reimbursement of such money from local tax funds inappropriate or impossible, or when the funds are intended for a state or local contribution to a program or project requiring such contribution to meet the requirements for a matching federal grant.</para><para>(2) The commission may make an allocation from the fund as a loan to an agency or political subdivision for any program or project or any part thereof consistent with the purposes of the fund which will directly generate revenue or receipts, which can be anticipated to culminate in a program or project which will generate revenue or receipts, or which would not generate revenue or receipts but would be of general public benefit to the applicant making repayment from local tax funds appropriate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 975, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1977), &#167; 2-3266; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 34.</para></source><annotation><para>The adoption and implementation of a general benefit project by a natural resources district is an exercise of a power which is legislative in nature, and the requirements of due process that apply to judicial or quasi-judicial proceedings are not applicable. Fisher &amp; Trouble Creek v. Lower Platte No. Nat. Resources Dist., 212 Neb. 196, 322 N.W.2d 403 (1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>