<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<sectno id="id33">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id34" statutenumber="2-1577"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id36">2-1577</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Nebraska Soil
and Water Conservation Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>(1)
There is hereby created the Nebraska Soil and Water Conservation Fund to be
administered by the department. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund
such money as is (a) appropriated to the fund by the Legislature, (b) paid
to the state as fees, deposits, payments, and repayments relating to the fund,
both principal and interest, and (c) donated as gifts, bequests, or other
contributions to such fund from public or private entities. Funds made available
by any agency of the United States may also be credited to such fund if so
directed by such agency.</para>
<para>(2) The money in the fund shall not be subject to any fiscal-year
limitation or lapse provision of unexpended balance at the end of any such
fiscal year or biennium. Transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(3) Any money in the Nebraska Soil and Water Conservation Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 450, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 236, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>