<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-1506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1506</statuteno><catchline>Water Sustainability Fund; goals;
legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The goals of the Water Sustainability Fund are to: (a)
Provide financial assistance to programs, projects, or activities that increase
aquifer recharge, reduce aquifer depletion, and increase streamflow; (b) remediate
or mitigate threats to drinking water; (c) promote the goals and objectives
of approved integrated management plans or ground water management plans;
(d) contribute to multiple water supply management goals including flood control,
reducing threats to property damage, agricultural uses, municipal and industrial
uses, recreational benefits, wildlife habitat, conservation, and preservation
of water resources; (e) assist municipalities with the cost of constructing,
upgrading, developing, and replacing sewer infrastructure facilities as part
of a combined sewer overflow project; (f) provide increased water productivity
and enhance water quality; (g) use the most cost-effective solutions available;
and (h) comply with interstate compacts, decrees, other state contracts and
agreements and federal law.</para>
<para>(2) The Legislature
finds that the goals of the Water Sustainability Fund can be met by equally
considering programs, projects, or activities in the following categories:
(a) Research, data, and modeling; (b) rehabilitation or restoration of water
supply infrastructure, new water supply infrastructure, or water supply infrastructure
maintenance or flood prevention for protection of critical infrastructure;
(c) conjunctive management, storage, and integrated management of ground water
and surface water; and (d) compliance with interstate compacts or agreements
or other formal state contracts or agreements or federal law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB1098, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>