<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1592"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1592</statuteno><catchline>Grant or loan; application; deadline; procedure.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any organization qualified to apply for and receive funds from the
Nebraska Resources Development Fund may file an application with the department
for a grant or loan from such fund. Applications for grants to the department
itself shall be filed by the department. Each application shall be filed in
such manner and form and be accompanied by such information as may be prescribed
by the director and the commission. No
applications may be made to receive funds by grant or loan from the Nebraska
Resources Development Fund after March 30, 2014.</para>
<para>(2) Any such application shall:</para>
<para>(a) Describe the nature and purpose of the proposed program or project;</para>
<para>(b) Set forth or be accompanied by a plan for development of the proposed
program or project, together with engineering, economic, and financial feasibility
data and information, and such estimated costs of construction or implementation
as may be required by the director and the commission;</para>
<para>(c) State whether money other than that for which the application is
made will be used to help in meeting program or project costs and whether
such money is available or has been sought for this purpose;</para>
<para>(d) When appropriate, state that the applicant holds or can acquire
title to all lands or has the necessary easements and rights-of-way for the
project and related lands and has or may acquire all water rights necessary
for the proposed project;</para>
<para>(e) Show that the applicant possesses all necessary authority to undertake
or participate in the proposed program or project; and</para>
<para>(f) Demonstrate the probable environmental and ecological consequences
that may result from such proposed program or project.</para>
<para>(3) Upon receipt of an application, the director shall evaluate and
investigate all aspects of the proposed program or project and the proposed
schedule for development and completion of such program or project, determine
the eligibility of the program or project for funding, and make appropriate
recommendations to the commission pursuant to sections 2-1586 to 2-1595. As
a part of his or her investigation, the director shall consider whether the
plan for development of the program or project is satisfactory. If the director
determines that the plan is unsatisfactory or that the application does not
contain adequate information upon which to make determinations, the director
shall return the application to the applicant and may make such recommendations
to the applicant as are considered necessary to make the plan or the application
satisfactory.</para>
<para>(4) Requests for utilization of the Nebraska Resources Development Fund
for state participation in any water and related land-water resources projects
through acquisition of a state interest therein shall also be filed with the
department for the director's evaluation, investigation, and recommendations.
Such requests shall be filed in the manner and form and be accompanied by
such information as shall be prescribed by the department and the commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 975, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1977), &#167; 2-3269; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1106, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB906, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>