<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id68">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id70" statutenumber="2-1091.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1091.01</statuteno><catchline id="id73">Nursery stock distributor license; application;
contents; fees; licensee
duties; nursery stock; requirements;
license; posting; lapse of license.</catchline><para>(1)
A person shall not operate as a nursery
stock distributor without a valid license issued by the department. Any person validly licensed as a grower, a dealer, or a
broker under the Plant Protection and Plant Pest Act as it existed on the
day before September 6, 2013, shall remain validly licensed until December
31, 2013.</para>
<para>(2) Each
nursery stock distributor shall apply for a license required by
subsection (1) of this section on forms furnished by the department due on January 1 for the current license
year. Such application shall include the full name and mailing
address of the applicant, the names and addresses of any partners, limited
liability company members, or corporate officers, the name and address of
the person authorized by the applicant to receive notices and orders of the
department as provided in the Plant Protection and Plant Pest Act, whether
the applicant is an individual, partnership, limited liability company, corporation,
or other legal entity, the location of the operation, and the signature of
the applicant. A person distributing greenhouse plants grown for indoor use,
annual plants, florist
stock, cut flowers, sod,
turf, onions, or potatoes, or seeds of any such plant, shall not be required
to obtain a license but may do so pursuant to section 2-10,105.</para>
<para>(3) A nursery
stock distributor license shall expire on December 31 of each year unless
previously lapsed or revoked.</para><para>(4) All applications shall be accompanied
by a license fee for the first acre on which nursery stock is located. If
the nursery stock distributor does not have physical possession of nursery
stock, the nursery stock distributor shall pay a license fee based on one
acre. Additionally the applicant shall pay an acreage fee for each additional
acre on which nursery stock is located. The license fees are set forth in
section 2-1091.02. If the applicant has distributed nursery stock prior to
applying for a license, the applicant shall pay an additional administrative
fee as set forth in section 2-1091.02.</para><para>(5) All nursery stock distributed by a nursery
stock distributor shall be only sound, healthy nursery stock that is reasonably
capable of growth, labeled correctly, free from injurious plant pests, and
stored or displayed under conditions which maintain its vigor as provided
in the rules and regulations. Any fee charged to the department for diagnostic
services or shipping costs shall be paid by the nursery stock distributor.</para>
<para>(6) A valid
copy of the nursery stock distributor's license shall be posted in a conspicuous
place at the distribution location.</para><para>(7) A nursery stock distributor shall obtain
a license for each distribution location.</para><para>(8) Each applicant for a nursery stock distributor license shall furnish
a signed written statement that such person will acquire and distribute only
nursery stock which has been distributed by a person who is duly licensed
pursuant to the act or approved by an authorizing agency within the state
of origin recognized by the department.</para>
<para>(9) Every nursery
stock distributor shall continually maintain a complete and accurate
list with the department of all sources from which nursery stock is received.</para>
<para>(10) Each nursery
stock distributor shall keep and make available for examination
by the department for a period of three years an accurate record of all transactions
conducted in the ordinary course of business. Records pertaining to such business
shall at a minimum include the names of the persons from which nursery stock
was received, the receiving date, the amount received, and the variety and
place of origin of the nursery stock received and all documents accompanying each shipment indicating
compliance with state or federal requirements and quarantines.</para>
<para>(11) A nursery stock distributor license shall lapse
automatically upon a change of ownership, and the subsequent owner must obtain
a new license. The nursery
stock distributor license shall lapse automatically upon
a change of location, and such licensee must obtain a new license. A licensee
shall notify the department in writing at least thirty days prior to any change
in ownership, name, or address. A nursery stock distributor shall
notify the department in writing before there is a change of the name or address
of the person authorized to receive notices and orders of the department.
When a nursery stock distributor permanently
ceases operating, he or she shall return the license to the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 406, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB68, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>