<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1227</statuteno><catchline>Simulcast; license; agreement between tracks; sections applicable; wagering; how conducted.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may authorize and approve one or more applications by any racetrack issued a license under sections 2-1201 to 2-1223 for a license to provide the simulcast of horseraces for wagering purposes from a track operated by the applicant which is conducting a race to a receiving track which is also licensed pursuant to sections 2-1201 to 2-1223 and has applied for a simulcast facility license. No application shall be approved by the commission without a written agreement between the receiving track and the sending track relating to the simulcast. The written agreement between the receiving track and the sending track shall have the consent of the organization representing a majority of the licensed owners and trainers at both the sending and the receiving track.</para><para>(2) Every licensee authorized to accept wagers on simulcast racing events pursuant to sections 2-1224 to 2-1227 shall be deemed to be conducting a licensed horserace meeting and shall be subject to all appropriate provisions of sections 2-1201 to 2-1223 relating to the conduct of horserace meetings.</para><para>(3) The sums retained by any receiving track from the total deposits in pools wagered on simulcast racing events conducted pursuant to sections 2-1201 to 2-1227 shall be equal to the retained percentages applicable to the sending track. Of the sums retained by the receiving track from simulcast pools, the parimutuel tax shall be levied in accordance with sections 2-1201 to 2-1223. Of the sums retained by the receiving track, an amount as determined by agreement between the sending track and receiving track shall be distributed to the sending track.</para><para>(4) Any simulcast between a sending track located in the state and receiving track located in the state as provided in this section shall result in the combination of all wagers placed at the receiving track located in the state with the wagers placed at the sending track located in the state so as to produce common parimutuel betting pools for the calculation of odds and the determination of payouts from such pools, which payout shall be the same for all winning tickets, irrespective of whether the wager is placed at a sending track located in the state or receiving track located in the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 708, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 591, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 471, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>