<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1806"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1806</statuteno><catchline>Potato shipper; license; application; issuance; display; records; cancellation and annulment of license; grounds; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>Every person desiring to engage in business as a potato shipper shall file with the Department of Agriculture an application for a license in such form and detail as the department may prescribe. If it is found that there has been compliance with the provisions of sections 2-1801 to 2-1811 and the rules and regulations of the department issued in conformance therewith, a license shall forthwith be issued to the applicant. Every person who engages in business as a potato shipper without having a license shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor. Each licensed potato shipper shall display conspicuously in his place of business the license granted to him. Should the licensed potato shipper change his place of business he shall immediately notify the department. Each licensed potato shipper shall keep such records with respect to shipments of potatoes by him as the department may by regulation require. Such records shall be preserved for a period of not less than two years and be, at all times during business hours, subject to inspection by authorized agents of the department. In the event that a licensed potato shipper shall violate any of the provisions of sections 2-1801 to 2-1811 or the regulations of the department issued in conformance therewith, the department may, upon due notice and after full hearing, cancel and annul his license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 4, &#167; 6, p. 71; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 4, &#167; 2, p. 60; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 9, &#167; 1, p. 79; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 16.</para></source></law></legaldoc>