<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id5"  statutenumber="2-1201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">2-1201</statuteno><catchline id="id8">State Racing Commission;
creation; members; terms; qualifications; bond or insurance.</catchline><para>(1) There
hereby is created a State Racing Commission.</para>
<para>(2) Until July 15, 2010, the commission
shall consist of
three members who shall be appointed by the Governor and subject to confirmation
by a majority of the members elected to the Legislature and may be for cause
removed by the Governor. One member shall be appointed each year for a term
of three years. The members shall serve until their successors are appointed
and qualified.</para>
<para>(3) On and after July 15, 2010, the commission
shall consist of five members who shall be appointed by the Governor and subject
to confirmation by a majority of the members elected to the Legislature and
may be for cause removed by the Governor. One member of the commission shall
be appointed from each congressional district, as such districts existed on
January 1, 2010, and two members of the commission shall be appointed at large
for terms as follows:</para>
<para>(a) The member representing the second
congressional district who is appointed on or after April 1, 2010, shall serve
until March 31, 2014, and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified.
Thereafter the term of the member representing such district shall be four
years and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified;</para>
<para>(b) The member representing the third
congressional district who is appointed on or after April 1, 2011, shall serve
until March 31, 2015, and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified.
Thereafter the term of the member representing such district shall be four
years and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified;</para>
<para>(c) The member representing the first
congressional district who is appointed on or after April 1, 2012, shall serve
until March 31, 2016, and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified.
Thereafter the term of the member representing such district shall be four
years and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified;</para>
<para>(d) Not later than sixty days after July
15, 2010, the Governor shall appoint one at-large member who shall serve until
March 31, 2013, and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified.
Thereafter the term of such member shall be four years and until his or her
successor is appointed and qualified; and</para>
<para>(e) Not later than sixty days after July
15, 2010, the Governor shall appoint one at-large member who shall serve until
March 31, 2014, and until his or her successor is appointed and qualified.
Thereafter the term of such member shall be four years and until his or her
successor is appointed and qualified.</para>
<para>(4) Not more than three members of the commission shall belong
to the same political party.
No more than two of the members shall reside, when appointed, in the same
congressional district. No
more than two of the members shall reside in any one county. Any vacancy
shall be filled by appointment by the Governor for the unexpired term. The
members shall serve without compensation but
shall be reimbursed for their actual expenses incurred in the performance
of their duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The members of the commission shall be bonded
or insured as required by section 11-201.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 173, &#167; 1, p. 629; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 2-1501; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-1201; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>