
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-10,103.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-10,103.01</statuteno><catchline>Nursery
stock distributor; disciplinary actions; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) A nursery stock distributor may
be placed on probation requiring such person to comply with the conditions
set out in an order of probation issued by the director or be ordered to cease
and desist from failing to comply or be ordered to pay an administrative fine
pursuant to section 2-10,103.02 after:</para>
<para>(a) The director determines the nursery stock distributor has
not complied with section 2-10,103;</para>
<para>(b) The nursery stock distributor is
given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing
to show cause why the specified order should not be issued; and</para>
<para>(c) The director finds that issuing the specified order is appropriate
based on the hearing record or the available information if the hearing is
waived by the nursery stock distributor.</para>
<para>(2) A nursery stock distributor may
be suspended after:</para>
<para>(a) The director determines the nursery stock distributor has
not complied with section 2-10,103;</para>
<para>(b) The nursery stock distributor is
given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing
to show cause why the license should not be suspended; and</para>
<para>(c) The director finds that issuing an order suspending the license
is appropriate based on the hearing record or the available information if
the hearing is waived by the nursery stock distributor.</para>
<para>(3) A license may be immediately suspended and the director may order
the nursery stock distributor's operation
to cease prior to hearing when:</para>
<para>(a) The director determines an immediate danger to the public health,
safety, or welfare exists; and</para>
<para>(b) The nursery stock distributor receives
written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show
cause why the suspension should not be sustained. Within fifteen days after
the suspension, the nursery stock distributor may
request in writing a date for a hearing and the director shall consider the
interests of the nursery stock distributor when
the director establishes the date and time of the hearing, except that no
hearing shall be held sooner than is reasonable under the circumstances. When
a nursery stock distributor does
not request a hearing date within such fifteen-day period, the director shall
establish a hearing date and notify the nursery stock distributor of
the date and time of such hearing.</para>
<para>(4) A license may be revoked after:</para>
<para>(a) The director determines the nursery stock distributor has
committed serious, repeated, or multiple violations of any of the requirements
of section 2-10,103;</para>
<para>(b) The nursery stock distributor is
given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing
to show cause why the license should not be revoked; and</para>
<para>(c) The director finds that issuing an order revoking the license is
appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if
the hearing is waived by the nursery stock distributor.</para>
<para>(5) Any nursery stock distributor whose
license has been suspended shall cease operations until the license is reinstated.
Any nursery stock distributor whose
license is revoked shall cease operating until a new license is issued.</para>
<para>(6) The director may terminate a proceeding to suspend or revoke a license
or subject a nursery stock distributor to
an order of the director described in subsection (1) of this section at any
time if the reasons for such proceeding no longer exist. A license which has
been suspended may be reinstated, a person with a revoked license may be issued
a new license, or a nursery stock distributor may
no longer be subject to the director's order if the director determines that
the conditions which prompted the suspension, revocation, or order of the
director no longer exist.</para>
<para>(7) Proceedings to suspend or revoke a license or subject a nursery stock distributor to an order of the
director described in subsection (1) of this section shall not preclude the
department from pursuing other civil or criminal actions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 406, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB68, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>