<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id23">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id25" statutenumber="2-1504">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1504</statuteno><catchline id="id28">Nebraska Natural
Resources Commission; creation; functions; membership; selection; terms; vacancy.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Nebraska Natural Resources Commission is established.
The commission shall advise the department as requested by the director and
shall perform such other functions as are specifically conferred on the commission
by law. The commission shall have no jurisdiction over matters pertaining
to water rights.</para>
<para>(2) The voting
members of the commission, all
of whom shall have attained the age of majority, shall be:</para>
<para>(a) One resident of each of the following river basins, with
delineations being those on the Nebraska river basin map officially adopted
by the commission and on file with the department: (i) The Niobrara River,
White River, and Hat Creek basin, (ii) the North Platte River basin, (iii)
the South Platte River basin, (iv) the middle Platte River basin, (v) the
lower Platte River basin, (vi) the Loup River basin, (vii) the Elkhorn River
basin, (viii) the Missouri tributaries basin, (ix) the Republican River basin,
(x) the Little Blue River basin, (xi) the Big Blue River basin, and (xii)
the Nemaha River basin;</para>
<para>(b) One additional resident of each river basin which encompasses
one or more cities of the metropolitan class;
and</para>
<para>(c) Fourteen members appointed by the Governor,
subject to confirmation by the Legislature. Of the members appointed by the Governor, one shall
represent each
of the following categories: Agribusiness interests; agricultural interests;
ground water irrigators; irrigation districts; manufacturing interests; metropolitan
utilities districts; municipal users of water from a city of the primary class;
municipal users of water from a city of the first or second class or a village;
outdoor recreation users; public power districts; public power and irrigation
districts; range livestock owners; surface water irrigators; and wildlife
conservation interests.</para>
<para>(3) Members of
the commission described
in subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall be selected for four-year
terms at individual caucuses of the natural resources district directors residing
in the river basin from which the member is selected. Such caucuses shall
be held for each basin within ten days following the first Thursday after
the first Tuesday of the year the term of office of the member from that basin
expires. The dates and locations for such caucuses shall be established by
the commission, and the commission
shall provide notice to the public by issuing press releases for publication
in a newspaper of general circulation in each county that comprises the river
basin for which a caucus election will be held. Terms of office of such members shall follow
the sequence originally determined by the river basin representatives to the
commission at their first meeting on the third Thursday after the first Tuesday
in January 1975. All river basin members shall take office on the third Thursday
after the first Tuesday in January following their selection and any vacancy
shall be filled for the unexpired term by a caucus held within thirty days
following the date such vacancy is created. Each member of the commission
representing a river basin shall qualify by filing with the other members
of the commission an acceptance in writing of his or her selection.</para>
<para>(4) Members
of the commission described in subdivision (2)(b) of this section shall be
residents of natural resources districts which encompass one or more cities
of the metropolitan class and shall be selected in the same manner, at the
same time, and for a four-year term having the same term sequence as provided
for the other members from such basin under subsection (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(5) For members
of the commission described in subdivision (2)(c) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) The Governor
shall appoint the eleven additional members added by Laws 2014, LB1098, within
thirty days after April 17, 2014. The eleven additional appointments shall
be for staggered four-year terms, as determined by the Governor. The Governor
shall also set the terms of the current members of the commission appointed
under such subdivision and serving on April 17, 2014, to staggered four-year
terms. Future appointments shall be for four-year terms. Members whose terms
have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have been appointed.
In the case of a vacancy, the Governor shall appoint a successor for the unexpired
term. Members may be removed for cause. Initial appointees shall begin serving
immediately following notice of appointment, except that the member appointed
representing municipal users of water from the class of city or a village
that is being represented by the current member representing municipal users
of water and the members representing surface water irrigators and ground
water irrigators shall not begin serving until the term of the current member
representative of the category expires or such member resigns or is otherwise
removed; and</para><para>(b) In appointing such members, the Governor shall:</para>
<para>(i) Create
a broad-based commission which has knowledge of, has experience with, and
is representative of Nebraska's water use and economy;</para>
<para>(ii) Give recognition
to the importance of both water quantity and water quality; and</para>
<para>(iii) Appoint
members who represent diverse geographic regions of the state, including urban
and rural areas, and represent, to the extent possible, the racial and ethnic
diversity of the state.</para><para>(6) After the members have been appointed as required under this
section, the commission shall revise or adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
as necessary to administer the Water Sustainability Fund pursuant to sections
2-1506 to 2-1513.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 8, &#167; 4, p. 94; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 2-1904; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-1504; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 7, &#167; 2, p. 74; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 3, &#167; 2, p. 82; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 6, &#167; 3, p. 76; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 4, &#167; 2, p. 66; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 9, &#167; 2, p. 78; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 7, &#167; 1, p. 78; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 5, &#167; 1, p. 73; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 67, p. 140; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 542, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 337, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 510, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 423, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 36, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 37, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1106, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1098, &#167; 2.</para><operativedate>April 17, 2014</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Department of Natural Resources,</emphasis> powers, see Chapter 61, article 2.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Designation by Legislature of University of Nebraska officers as members of Natural Resources Commission was a legislative appointment in violation of Constitution; but designation of Director of Water Resources was valid as simply adding to the duties of a state officer. Neeman v. Nebraska Nat. Resources Commission, 191 Neb. 672, 217 N.W.2d 166 (1974).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>