
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1203</statuteno><catchline>Commission; powers; fines; board of stewards; powers; appeal; fine.</catchline><para>The commission shall have power to prescribe and enforce rules and regulations governing horseraces and race meetings licensed as provided in sections 2-1201 to 2-1229 and games of chance as provided in the Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act. Such rules and regulations shall contain criteria to be used by the commission for decisions on approving and revoking track licenses and setting racing dates.</para><para>The commission may revoke or suspend licenses issued to racing industry participants and may, in lieu of or in addition to such suspension or revocation, impose a fine in an amount not to exceed twenty-five thousand dollars upon a finding that a rule or regulation has been violated by a licensed racing industry participant. The exact amount of the fine shall be proportional to the seriousness of the violation and the extent to which the licensee derived financial gain as a result of the violation.</para><para>The commission may delegate to a board of stewards such of the commission's powers and duties as may be necessary to carry out and effectuate the purposes of sections 2-1201 to 2-1229.</para><para>Any decision or action of such board of stewards may be appealed to the commission or may be reviewed by the commission on its own initiative. The board of stewards may impose a fine not to exceed five thousand dollars upon a finding that a rule or regulation has been violated.</para><para>The commission shall remit administrative fines collected under this section to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 173, &#167; 3, p. 630; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 2-1503; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-1203; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 582, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 939, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 200, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 718, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1153, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 295, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 243, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 573, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB656, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB561, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB876, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>April 20, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act,</emphasis> see section 9-1101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>