<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-10,103.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-10,103.04</statuteno><catchline>Notice or order; service; notice;
contents; hearings; procedure; new hearing.</catchline><para>(1) Any notice
or order provided for in the Plant Protection and Plant Pest Act shall be
personally served on the person holding the nursery stock distributor
license, the person named in the notice, or the person authorized by the person
holding the nursery stock distributor license to receive notices
and orders of the department or shall be sent by certified mail, return receipt
requested, to the last-known address of the person holding the nursery stock distributor
license, the person named in the notice, or the person authorized
to receive such notices and orders. A copy of the notice and the order shall
be filed in the records of the department.</para>
<para>(2) Any notice to comply provided for in the act shall set forth the
acts or omissions with which the person holding the nursery stock distributor
license or the person named in the notice is charged.</para>
<para>(3) A notice of the right of the person holding the nursery stock
distributor license or the person named in the notice to a hearing
provided for in the act shall set forth the time and place of the hearing
except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of section 2-10,103.01. A notice
of the right of the person holding the nursery stock
distributor license or the person named in the notice to such
hearing shall include notice that the right of the person holding the nursery stock
distributor license or the person named in the notice to a hearing
may be waived pursuant to subsection (5) of this section. A
notice of such right to a hearing shall include notice of the potential actions
that may be taken against the person holding the nursery stock distributor
license or the person named in the notice.</para>
<para>(4) The hearings provided for in the act shall be conducted by the director
at a time and place he or she designates. The director shall make a final
finding based upon the complete hearing record and issue an order. If the
director has suspended a license pursuant to subsection (3) of section 2-10,103.01,
the director shall sustain, modify, or rescind the order. All hearings shall
be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
<para>(5) The person holding the nursery stock distributor
license or the person named in the notice shall be deemed to waive
the right to a hearing if such person does not come to the
hearing at the time and place set forth in the notice described in subsection
(3) of this section without requesting the director at least two days before
the designated time to change the time and place for the hearing, except that
before an order of the director becomes final, the director may designate
a different time and place for the hearing if the person shows
the director that the person had a justifiable reason
for not coming to the hearing and not timely requesting a change in the time
and place for such hearing. If the person holding the nursery stock distributor
license or the person named in the notice waives the right to
a hearing, the director shall make a final finding based upon the available
information and issue an order. If the director has suspended a license pursuant
to subsection (3) of section 2-10,103.01, the director shall sustain, modify,
or rescind the order.</para>
<para>(6) Any person aggrieved by the finding of the director shall have ten
days from the entry of the director's order to request a new hearing if such
person can show that a mistake of fact has been made which affected the director's
determination. Any order of the director shall become final upon the expiration
of ten days after its entry if no request for a new hearing is made.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 406, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB68, &#167; 16.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>