<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1230"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1230</statuteno><catchline>Telephonic and electronic wagering; legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(a) The horseracing, horse breeding, and parimutuel wagering industries are important sectors of the agricultural economy of the state, provide substantial revenue for state and local governments, and employ many residents of the state;</para><para>(b) The ability to provide licensed and regulated teleracing facilities through which parimutuel wagering is permitted holds the potential to strengthen the horseracing industry and further its economic contributions to the state and its citizens and it is in the best interests of the state to encourage experimentation with parimutuel wagering through licensed teleracing facilities;</para><para>(c) The offering of controlled telephonic wagering also holds the potential to strengthen the horseracing industry and further its economic contributions to the state and its citizens and it is in the best interests of the state to encourage experimentation with telephonic wagering;</para><para>(d) The purpose of such experimentation is to determine whether teleracing facilities and telephonic wagering will promote the overall growth of the horseracing industry, resulting in additional revenue for the support of racing organizations, purses, breeders, and labor; and</para><para>(e) Parimutuel wagering through teleracing facilities or telephonic wagering should be authorized and regulated in a manner which would not unreasonably jeopardize horseracing or employment opportunities or infringe on current operations or markets of licensed racetracks.</para><para>(2) The Legislature hereby authorizes experimentation with parimutuel wagering through teleracing facilities and telephonic wagering on horseraces conducted within the state and on simulcasting and interstate simulcasting received by licensed racetracks within the state under the regulation of the State Racing Commission in the manner and subject to the conditions provided in sections 2-1207 and 2-1230 to 2-1242.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 718, &#167; 8.</para></source><annotation><para>Sections 2-1230 through 2-1242 are unconstitutional because they purport to authorize telephonic wagering which does not occur within a licensed racetrack enclosure. State ex rel. Stenberg v. Omaha Expo. &amp; Racing, 263 Neb. 991, 644 N.W.2d 563 (2002).</para><para>Article III, section 24, of the Constitution of Nebraska, plainly requires that parimutuel wagering on horses must be conducted by an entity licensed to do so and must be conducted by licensees at a racetrack enclosure which is licensed to operate horse races. Wagering that occurs in a detached facility, one that is by definition outside a licensed racetrack enclosure, cannot logically occur within a licensed racetrack enclosure as required by the constitution. State ex rel. Stenberg v. Douglas Racing Corp., 246 Neb. 901, 524 N.W.2d 61 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>