<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1203.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1203.02</statuteno><catchline>Licensees, administrators, and managers; application; fingerprinting and criminal history record check; costs.</catchline><para>(1) Any person between sixteen and seventy-five years of age applying for or holding a license to participate in or be employed at a horserace meeting licensed by the commission shall be subject to fingerprinting and a check of his or her criminal history record information maintained by the Identification Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for the purpose of determining whether the commission has a basis to deny the license application or to suspend, cancel, or revoke the person's license, except that the commission shall not require a person to be fingerprinted if such person has been previously fingerprinted in connection with a license application in this state within the last five years prior to the application for such license. Any person between sixteen and seventy-five years of age involved in the administration or management of a racetrack, including the governing body, shall be subject to fingerprinting and a check of his or her criminal history record information maintained by the Identification Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation. The applicant, licensee, or person involved in the administration or management of a racetrack shall pay the actual cost of any fingerprinting or check of his or her criminal history record information. The requirements of this subsection shall not apply to employees of concessions who do not work in restricted-access areas, admissions employees whose duties involve only admissions ticket sales and verification or parking receipts sales and verification, and medical or emergency services personnel authorized to provide such services at the racetrack.</para><para>(2) If the applicant is an individual who is applying for a license to participate in or be employed at a horserace meeting, the application shall include the applicant's social security number.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 200, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1153, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB561, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB876, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>