
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id50">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id52"  statutenumber="2-15,122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id54">2-15,122</statuteno><catchline id="id55">Natural Resources
Water Quality Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>There
is hereby created the Natural Resources Water Quality Fund. The State Treasurer
shall credit to the fund for the uses and purposes of section 2-15,123 such
money as is specifically appropriated, such funds, fees, donations, gifts,
services, or devises or bequests of real or personal property received by
the department from any source, federal, state, public, or private, to be
used by the department for the purpose of funding programs listed in subsection
(2) of section 2-15,123, and such money credited under sections 2-2634, 2-2638,
and 2-2641. The department shall allocate money from the fund pursuant to
section 2-15,123. The fund shall be exempt from provisions relating to lapsing
of appropriations, and the unexpended and unencumbered balance existing in
the fund on June 30 each year shall be reappropriated, except that transfers may be made from the fund to the
General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in
the Natural Resources Water Quality Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 961, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 874, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>