<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-10,103.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>2-10,103.02</statuteno><catchline>Administrative fine; collection;
use.</catchline><para>(1) The director
may issue an order imposing an administrative fine on any
person who has violated any provision, requirement, condition, limitation,
or duty imposed by the Plant Protection and Plant Pest Act or rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act in an amount which
shall not exceed one thousand
dollars for each violation. A violation means each action which violates any
separate or distinct provision, requirement, condition, limitation, or duty
imposed by the act or such rules and regulations. In determining
whether to impose an administrative fine and, if a fine is imposed, the amount
of the fine, the director shall take into consideration (a) the seriousness
of the violation, (b) the extent to which the person derived
financial gain as a result of his or her failure to comply, (c) the extent
of intent, willfulness, or negligence by the person in
the violation, (d) the likelihood of the violation reoccurring, (e) the history
of the person's failure to comply,
(f) the person's attempts to prevent
or limit his or her failure to comply, (g) the person's willingness
to correct violations, (h) the nature of the person's disclosure
of violations, (i) the person's cooperation with
investigations of his or her failure to comply, and (j) any factors which
may be established by the rules and regulations.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall remit administrative
fines collected under the act to the State Treasurer on a monthly basis for
distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution
of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(3) Any administrative fine imposed under the Plant Protection and Plant
Pest Act and unpaid shall constitute a debt to the State of Nebraska which
may be collected by lien foreclosure or sued for and recovered in any proper
form of action in the name of the State of Nebraska in the district court
of the county in which the violator resides or owns property. The lien shall
attach to the real estate of the violator when notice of such lien is filed
and indexed against the real estate in the office of the register of deeds
or county clerk in the county where the real estate is located.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 406, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB68, &#167; 15.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>