<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1207.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1207.01</statuteno><catchline>Deduction from wagers; distribution; costs.</catchline><para>(1) The amount deducted from wagers pursuant to subsection (2) of section 2-1207 may be used to promote agriculture and horsebreeding in Nebraska and shall be distributed as described in this section as purse supplements and breeder and stallion awards for Nebraska-bred horses, as defined and registered pursuant to section 2-1213, at the racetrack where the funds were generated. The official registrar for each breed, as established in section 2-1213, shall distribute purse supplements and breeder and stallion awards and shall annually spend a minimum of eighty percent of all amounts deducted pursuant to subsection (2) of section 2-1207 on such purse supplements and breeder and stallion awards.</para><para>(2)(a) If a racetrack does not continue to conduct live race meets, amounts deducted may be distributed as purse supplements and breeder and stallion awards at racetracks that conduct live race meets of the same breed of horse that has primarily run in live race meets at such track.</para><para>(b) Amounts deducted pursuant to a contract with the organization representing the majority of the licensed owners and trainers at the racetrack's most recent live thoroughbred race meet shall be used by that organization to promote live thoroughbred horseracing in the state or as purse supplements at racetracks that conduct live thoroughbred race meets in the state.</para><para>(c) Amounts deducted pursuant to a contract between the organization representing the majority of licensed owners and trainers at the racetrack's most recent live quarterhorse race meet shall be used by such organization to promote live quarterhorse race meets in the state.</para><para>(3) Any costs incurred by the commission pursuant to this section and subsection (2) of section 2-1207 shall be separately accounted for and be deducted from such funds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 365, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1354, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1255, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB561, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB1001, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>