<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id51">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" id="id53"  statutenumber="2-1510"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1510</statuteno><catchline>Program, project, or activity; funding
request; director; powers; findings; conflict of interest.</catchline><para>(1) Each program,
project, or activity for which funding is requested, whether such request
has as its origin an application or the action of the department itself, shall
be reviewed as provided in sections 2-1506 to 2-1513 by the director prior
to the approval of any allocation for such program, project, or activity by
the commission.</para>
<para>(2) The director
may recommend approval of and the commission may approve grants or loans,
including the appropriate repayment period and the rate of interest, for program,
project, or activity costs or acquisition of interests in programs, projects,
or activities if after investigation and evaluation the director finds that:</para>
<para>(a) The plan
does not conflict with any existing Nebraska state land plan;</para>
<para>(b) The proposed
program, project, or activity is economically and financially feasible based
upon standards adopted by the commission pursuant to sections 2-1506 to 2-1513;</para>
<para>(c) The plan
for development of the proposed program, project, or activity is satisfactory;</para>
<para>(d) The plan
of development minimizes any adverse impacts on the natural environment;</para>
<para>(e) The applicant
is qualified, responsible, and legally capable of carrying out the program,
project, or activity;</para><para>(f) In the case of a loan, the borrower has demonstrated the ability
to repay the loan and there is assurance of adequate operation, maintenance,
and replacement during the repayment life of the program, project, or activity;</para>
<para>(g) The plan
considers other plans and programs of the state and resources development
plans of the political subdivisions of the state; and</para><para>(h) The money required
from the Water Sustainability Fund is available.</para><para>(3) The director and staff
of the department shall carry out their powers and duties under sections 2-1506
to 2-1513 independently of and without prejudice to their powers and duties
under other provisions of law.</para><para>(4) No member of the commission shall be
eligible to participate in the action of the commission concerning an application
for funding to any entity in which such commission member has any interest.
The director may be delegated additional responsibilities consistent with
the purposes of sections 2-1506 to 2-1513. It shall be the sole responsibility
of the commission to determine the priority in which funds are allocated for
eligible programs, projects, or activities under section 2-1508.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB1098, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>