<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1208.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1208.04</statuteno><catchline>Exotic wagering; withholding; Track Distribution Fund; created; distributed; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Racetracks shall separately account for their gross exotic daily receipts. For all meets commencing after July 16, 1994, any racetrack that had for its previous race meet a total parimutuel handle of less than fifty million dollars shall withhold an amount equal to one-half of one percent of such receipts and any racetrack that had for its previous race meet a total parimutuel handle of fifty million dollars or more shall withhold an amount equal to one percent of such receipts, except that for all meets commencing on or after January 1, 1995, each racetrack shall withhold an amount equal to one-fourth of one percent of such receipts, which amount shall be deducted from purses at the withholding track. Such amount withheld shall be paid to the State Racing Commission on the last day of each month during each race meeting for deposit in the Track Distribution Fund, which fund is hereby created.</para><para>(2) The fund shall be distributed monthly to recipient racetracks which conduct wagering by the parimutuel method on thoroughbred horseracing. Such racetracks shall receive the percentage which the total number of days of horseraces run at such racetrack in the year of distribution bears to the total number of days of horseraces run at all such racetracks in the year of distribution. Before January 1, 1995, one-half of the amount received under this subsection by a racetrack shall be used to supplement purses at the track, and on and after January 1, 1995, the entire amount received by a racetrack shall be used to supplement purses at the track.</para><para>(3) Any money in the Track Distribution Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Any money in the fund which is not distributed at the end of the calendar year shall be available for expenditure by the commission to defray its expenses pursuant to section 2-1209.</para><para>(4) The assessment required by this section shall be in addition to the assessments, taxes, and fees required by Chapter 2, article 12.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1041, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 467, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1354, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>