<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id66">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" id="id68"  statutenumber="2-1511"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1511</statuteno><catchline>Director; recommendations; agreement;
contents; loan; repayment period; successor; contract; lien; filing.</catchline>
<para>(1) The director
shall make recommendations based upon his or her review of the criteria set
forth in section 2-1510 of whether an application should be considered further
or rejected and the form of allocation he or she deems appropriate. The commission
shall act in accordance with such recommendations according to the application
procedures adopted and promulgated in rules and regulations. </para>
<para>(2) If, after
review of the recommendation by the director, the commission determines that
an application for a grant, loan, acquisition of an interest, or combination
thereof pursuant to sections 2-1506 to 2-1513 is satisfactory and qualified
to be approved, before the final approval of such application may be given
and the funds allocated, the department shall enter into an agreement in the
name of the state with the applicant agency or organization and with any other
organizations it deems to be involved in the program, project, or activity
to which funds shall be applied. The department shall also enter into such
agreements as are appropriate before allocation of any funds for the acquisition
of an interest in any qualified program, project, or activity when such acquisition
is initiated by the department itself pursuant to section 2-1512. All agreements
entered into pursuant to this section shall include, but not be limited to,
a specification of the amount of funds involved, whether the funds are considered
as a grant or loan or for the acquisition of an interest in the name of the
state, and, if a combination of these is involved, the amount of funds allocated
to each category, the specific purpose for which the allocation is made, the
terms of administration of the allocated funds, and any penalties to be imposed
upon the applicant organization should it fail to apply or repay the funds
in accordance with the agreement.</para><para>(3) If the allocation to be approved is
a loan, the department and the applicant or applicants shall include in the
agreement provisions for repayment to the Water Sustainability Fund of money
loaned together with any interest at reasonable rates as established by the
commission. The agreement shall further provide that repayment of the loan
together with any interest thereon shall commence no later than one full year
after construction of the project or implementation of the program or activity
is completed and that repayment shall be completed within the time period
specified by the commission. The repayment period shall not exceed fifty years,
except that the commission may extend the time for making repayment in the
event of extreme emergency or hardship. Such agreement shall also provide
for such assurances of and security for repayment of the loan as shall be
considered necessary by the department.</para>
<para>(4) With the
express approval of the commission, an applicant may convey its interest in
a program, project, or activity to a successor. The department shall contract
with the qualified successor in interest of the original obligor for repayment
of the loan together with any interest thereon and for succession to its rights
and obligations in any contract with the department.</para>
<para>(5) The state
shall have a lien upon a program, project, or activity constructed, improved,
or renovated with money from the Water Sustainability Fund for the amount
of the loan together with any interest thereon. This lien shall attach to
all program, project, or activity facilities, equipment, easements, real property,
and property of any kind or nature in which the loan recipient has an interest
and which is associated with the program, project, or activity. The department
shall file a statement of the lien, its amount, terms, and a description of
the program, project, or activity with the register of deeds of each county
in which the program, project, or activity or any part thereof is located.
The register of deeds shall record the lien, and it shall be indexed as other
liens are required by law to be indexed. The lien shall be valid until paid
in full or otherwise discharged. The lien shall be foreclosed in accordance
with applicable state law governing foreclosure of mortgages and liens. Any
lien provided for by this section may be subordinate to that which secures
federal assistance or other secured assistance received on the same program,
project, or activity.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB1098, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>