<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-10,106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>2-10,106</statuteno><catchline>Importation and distribution; labeling
requirements; exception; department; powers.</catchline><para>(1) It shall
be unlawful for any person, including any carrier transporting nursery stock,
to bring into or cause to be brought into Nebraska any nursery stock unless
such shipment is plainly and legibly marked with a label showing the name
and address of the consignor and consignee, the nature and quantity of the
contents, the place of origin, and the license or its equivalent issued by
the recognized authorizing agency stating that the nursery from which the
nursery stock originates has been inspected.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person to distribute in Nebraska nursery
stock for the purpose of resale in Nebraska without meeting the labeling criteria
stated in this section.</para>
<para>(3) The requirements of this section shall not apply to nursery stock
distributed to the final consumer at a distribution location where a valid nursery stock distributor's license
has been conspicuously posted.</para>
<para>(4) The department may cause to be held for inspection any plants, regardless
of proper labeling according to the Plant Protection and Plant Pest Act, if
there is reason to believe they are infested or infected with plant pests.
Such plants shall be held only for a period of time reasonable for proper
inspection and any treatment deemed necessary by the department. The department
shall not be held responsible for costs incurred by treatment or delay.</para>
<para>(5) In carrying out this section, the department may intercept or detain
any person or property including vehicles or vessels reasonably believed to
be carrying any plants or any other articles capable of carrying plant pests.
The department may hold for treatment, destroy, or otherwise dispose of any
plants, if found infested or infected with plant pests, at the owner's cost.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 874, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB68, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>