<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-1229"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1229</statuteno><catchline>Interstate simulcast facility license; issuance; agreement between tracks.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may authorize and approve an application for an interstate simulcast facility license by any receiving track within the state to receive the interstate simulcast of horseraces for parimutuel wagering purposes from any track located outside of the state. In determining whether such application should be approved, the commission shall consider whether such interstate simulcast would have a significant effect upon either live racing or the simulcasting of live racing of the same type and at the same time conducted in this state and whether it would expand the access to or availability of simulcasting to areas of the state or markets which are not at the time of the application fully served.</para><para>(2)(a) Prior to approving any such application from a track running primarily thoroughbred horseraces, the commission shall confer with and receive any recommendations of the organization which represents the majority of the thoroughbred breeders in Nebraska as to what effect an interstate simulcast would have upon thoroughbred horse breeding and horseracing in this state. Prior to approving any such application from a track running primarily quarterhorse horseraces, the commission shall confer with and receive recommendation of the organization which represents the majority of quarterhorse breeders in Nebraska as to what effect an interstate simulcast would have upon quarterhorse breeding and horseracing in this state.</para><para>(b) No application submitted under section 2-1228 shall be approved by the commission without:</para><para>(i) The prior written approval of any other racetrack issued a license under sections 2-1201 to 2-1223 and conducting live racing of the same type on the same day at the same time as the proposed interstate simulcast race or races and of the organization which represented a majority of the licensed owners and trainers at the racetrack's immediately preceding live thoroughbred or quarterhorse race meeting;</para><para>(ii) The prior written approval of any other racetrack issued a license under sections 2-1224 to 2-1227 which is simulcasting the racing program of any licensee conducting live racing in this state of the same type on the same day at the same time as the proposed interstate simulcast race or races; and</para><para>(iii) A written agreement between the receiving track and the sending track located outside of the state in any other state, territory, or possession of the United States, the District of Columbia, or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico setting forth the division of all proceeds between the sending and receiving tracks and all other conditions under which such interstate simulcast will be conducted. Such written agreement shall have the consent of the group representing the majority of horsepersons racing at the sending track and of the organization which represented a majority of the licensed owners and trainers at the receiving track's immediately preceding live race meeting.</para><para>(3) Every licensee authorized to accept wagers on interstate simulcast events pursuant to this section shall be deemed to be conducting a licensed horserace meeting and shall also be subject to all appropriate provisions of sections 2-1201 to 2-1223 relating to the conduct of horserace meetings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 591, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 471, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB1001, &#167; 9. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>