
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id43" statutenumber="2-1587"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-1587</statuteno><catchline id="id46">Nebraska Resources Development Fund; created; reserve fund; administration; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Nebraska Resources Development Fund to be administered by the department. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund, to carry out sections 2-1586 to 2-1595, such money as is (a) appropriated to or transferred into the fund by the Legislature, (b) paid to the state as fees, deposits, payments, and repayments relating to the fund, both principal and interest, and (c) donated as gifts, bequests, or other contributions to such fund from public or private entities. Funds made available by any department or agency of the United States may also be credited to this fund if so directed by such department or agency. The money in the fund shall not be subject to any fiscal year or biennium limitation requiring reappropriation of the unexpended balance at the end of the fiscal year or biennium. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) To aid in the funding of projects and to prevent excessive fluctuations in appropriation requirements for the Nebraska Resources Development Fund, the department shall create a reserve fund to be used only for projects requiring total expenditures from the Nebraska Resources Development Fund in excess of five million dollars. Unless disapproved by the Governor, the department may credit to such reserve fund that portion of any appropriation to the Nebraska Resources Development Fund which exceeds five million dollars. The department may also credit to the reserve fund such other funds as it determines are available.</para><para>(3) Any money in the Nebraska Resources Development Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 975, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1977), &#167; 2-3264; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 985, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB661, &#167; 23. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>