<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id42">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id44" statutenumber="2-1208.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id46">2-1208.01</statuteno><catchline id="id47">Parimutuel
wagering; tax; rates; return.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby imposed a tax on the gross
sum wagered by the parimutuel method at each race enclosure during a calendar
year as follows:</para>
<para>(a) The first ten million dollars
shall not be taxed;</para>
<para>(b) Any amount over ten million dollars but less than or equal
to seventy-three million dollars shall be taxed at the rate of two and one-half
percent; and</para>
<para>(c) Any amount in excess of seventy-three million dollars
shall be taxed at the rate of four percent.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except as provided in subdivision
(2)(b) of this section, an amount equal to two percent of the
first taxable seventy million dollars at each race meeting shall be retained
by the licensee for capital improvements and for maintenance of the premises
within the licensed racetrack enclosure and shall be a credit against the
tax levied in subsection (1)
of this section. This
subdivision includes each race meeting held after January 1, 2010, within
the licensed racetrack enclosure located in Lancaster County where the Nebraska
State Fair was held prior to 2010.</para>
<para>(b) For race meetings
conducted at the location where the Nebraska State Fair is held, an amount
equal to two and one-half percent of the first taxable seventy million dollars
at each race meeting shall be retained by the licensee for the purpose of
maintenance of the premises within the licensed racetrack enclosure and maintenance
of other buildings, streets, utilities, and existing improvements at the location
where the Nebraska State Fair is held. Such amount shall be a credit against
the tax levied in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) A
return as required by the Tax Commissioner shall be filed for a racetrack
enclosure for each month during which wagers are accepted at the enclosure.
The return shall be filed with and the net tax due pursuant to this section
shall be paid to the Department of Revenue on the tenth day of the following
month.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 5, &#167; 3, p. 73; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 6, &#167; 2, p. 67; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 9, &#167; 2, p. 124; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 76, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 631, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 830, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 154, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1041, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 467, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 591, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1055, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 365, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1236, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB224, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>