<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2649.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2649.02</statuteno><catchline>Notice; requirements; hearings; procedure; request for new hearing.</catchline><para>Under the Pesticide Act:</para><para>(1) Any notice or order shall be personally served on the license holder, the person named in the notice, or a person authorized by the license holder to receive notices and orders of the department or shall be sent by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested, to the last-known address of the license holder, the person named in the notice, or the person authorized to receive such notices and orders. A copy of the notice and the order shall be filed in the records of the department;</para><para>(2) A notice to comply under the act shall set forth the acts or omissions with which the license holder or person named in the notice is charged;</para><para>(3) A notice of the right of the license holder or person named in the notice to a hearing shall set forth the time and place of the hearing except as provided in subsection (3) of section 2-2643.03. A notice of such right to a hearing shall include notice that the right to a hearing may be waived pursuant to subsection (5) of this section. A notice of the right to a hearing shall include notice of the potential actions that may be taken against the license holder or person named in the notice;</para><para>(4) The hearings shall be conducted by the director at the time and place he or she designates. The director shall make a final finding based upon the complete hearing record and issue an order. If the director has suspended a license pursuant to subsection (3) of section 2-2643.03, the director shall sustain, modify, or rescind the order. All hearings shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act;</para><para>(5) A license holder or person named in the notice shall be deemed to waive the right to a hearing if such license holder or person does not come to the hearing at the time and place set forth in the notice described in subsection (3) of this section without requesting the director at least two days before the designated time to change the time and place for the hearing, except that before an order of the director becomes final, the director may designate a different time and place for the hearing if the license holder or person named in the notice shows the director that he or she had a justifiable reason for not coming to the hearing and not timely requesting a change in the time and place for such hearing. If the license holder or person named in the notice waives the right to a hearing, the director shall make a final finding based upon the available information and issue an order. If the director has suspended a license pursuant to subsection (3) of section 2-2643.03, the director shall sustain, modify, or rescind the order; and</para><para>(6) Any person aggrieved by the finding of the director has ten days after the entry of the director's order to request a new hearing if such person can show that a mistake of fact has been made which affected the director's determination. An order of the director becomes final upon the expiration of ten days after the entry of the order if no request for a new hearing is made.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 22.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis>                see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>