<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="May 1, 2010">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-2655"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2655</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska aerial pesticide business
license; when required; liability; exempt operations.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not apply pesticides
by use of an aircraft or cause or arrange aerial pesticide spraying operations
to occur on the property of another unless such person holds a Nebraska aerial
pesticide business license for the principal departure location of the aircraft
to be used. Any person applying pesticides without a principal departure location
licensed in this state and who applies pesticides by use of an aircraft within
this state may obtain a Nebraska aerial pesticide business license for the
principal out-of-state departure location. An individual licensed as a commercial
applicator shall apply pesticides by use of an aircraft only under the direct
supervision of a person holding a Nebraska aerial pesticide business license.
Such supervising license holder is jointly liable with the commercial applicator
for any damages caused by the commercial applicator. An individual who is
licensed as a commercial applicator with an aerial pest control category may
perform aerial operations without the supervision by a person holding a Nebraska
aerial pesticide business license if the commercial aerial applicator acquires
a Nebraska aerial pesticide business license. For purposes of sections 2-2655
to 2-2659, unless utilizing a licensed aerial pesticide business to perform
the application of pesticides by use of an aircraft, a person causing or arranging
aerial pesticide spraying operations shall include a person performing billing
and collection of payment for aerial spraying services performed, employing
or contracting with pilots to perform aerial applications, assigning aerial
spraying work orders to pilots, or paying compensation to pilots for aerial
spraying services performed whether or not such person is licensed as a commercial
applicator.</para>
<para>(2) Sections 2-2655 to
2-2659 shall not apply to aerial spraying operations conducted by federal,
state, or local government with public aircraft.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB254, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>