<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-2636"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2636</statuteno><catchline>Pesticide applicators; restrictions;
department; duties; reciprocity.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall
license pesticide applicators involved in the categories established in 40
C.F.R. 171, as the regulation existed on January 1, 2013, and
any other categories established pursuant to rules and regulations necessary
to meet the requirements of the state. The department may issue a reciprocal
license to a pesticide applicator licensed or certified in another state or
by a federal agency. Residents of the State of Nebraska are not eligible for
reciprocal certification. The department may waive part or all of any license
certification examination requirements for a reciprocal license if the other
state or federal agency that licensed or certified the pesticide applicator
has substantially the same certification examination standards and procedural
requirements as required under the Pesticide Act.</para>
<para>(2) A person shall not use a restricted-use pesticide unless the person
is:</para>
<para>(a) Licensed as a commercial or noncommercial applicator and authorized
by the license to use the restricted-use pesticide in the category covering
the proposed pesticide use;</para>
<para>(b) Licensed as a private applicator; or</para>
<para>(c) At least sixteen years of age and working under the direct supervision
of a licensed certified applicator pursuant to subsection (5) of section 2-2642.</para>
<para>(3) A person shall not use lawn care or structural pest control pesticides
on the property of another person for hire or compensation unless the person
is:</para>
<para>(a) Licensed as a commercial applicator; or</para>
<para>(b) At least sixteen years of age and working under the direct supervision
of a licensed certified applicator pursuant to subsection (5) of section 2-2642.</para>
<para>(4) An employee or other person acting on behalf of any political subdivision
of the state shall not use pesticides for outdoor vector control unless the
applicator is:</para>
<para>(a) Licensed as a commercial applicator or a noncommercial applicator;
or</para>
<para>(b) At least sixteen years of age and working under the direct supervision
of a licensed certified applicator pursuant to subsection (5) of section 2-2642.</para>
<para>(5) In order to receive a commercial, noncommercial, or private applicator
license, a person shall be at least sixteen years of age.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 588, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 874, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB100, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB69, &#167; 6.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>