<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2643.03" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2643.03</statuteno><catchline>License holder; disciplinary actions; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A license holder may be put on probation requiring such person to comply with the conditions set out in an order of probation issued by the director or be ordered to cease and desist from failing to comply or be ordered to pay an administrative fine pursuant to subdivision (9) of section 2-2626 after: (a) The director determines the license holder has not complied with section 2-2643.02; (b) the license holder is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why an order should not be issued; and (c) the director finds that issuing an order is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the license holder.</para><para>(2) A license issued under the Pesticide Act may be modified or suspended until the license holder complies with the conditions set out in an order issued by the director or for a specific period of time after: (a) The director determines the license holder has not complied with section 2-2643.02; (b) the license holder is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the license should not be modified or suspended; and (c) the director finds that issuing an order modifying or suspending the license is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the license holder.</para><para>(3) A license may be immediately suspended prior to hearing if: (a) The director determines an immediate danger to the public health, safety, or welfare exists; and (b) the license holder receives the written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the suspension should not be sustained. If a license is suspended under this subsection, the license holder may request a date and time for hearing. The director shall accommodate the requested date and time, if possible. In any event, if the license holder requests that the hearing be held within two business days, the director shall set the date and time for the hearing within two business days of the request. If a license holder does not request a hearing date within fifteen days after the suspension, the director shall establish a hearing date and shall notify the license holder of the date and time of such hearing.</para><para>(4) A license may be revoked after: (a) The director determines the license holder has committed serious, repeated, or multiple violations of any of the requirements of section 2-2643.02; (b) the license holder is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the license should not be revoked; and (c) the director finds that issuing an order revoking the license is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the license holder.</para><para>(5) Any license holder who has a license which has been suspended shall cease operating as a license holder until the license is reinstated. Any license holder who has a license which has been revoked shall cease operating as a license holder until a new license is issued.</para><para>(6) The director may terminate any proceedings to suspend or revoke a license or to subject a license holder to an order of the director at any time if the reasons for such proceedings no longer exist. A license which has been suspended may be reinstated, a person with a revoked license may be issued a new license, or a license holder may no longer be subject to an order of the director if the director determines the conditions which prompted the suspension, revocation, or probation no longer exist.</para><para>(7) Proceedings for license modification, suspension, revocation, or probation shall not preclude the department from pursuing other administrative, civil, or criminal actions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 874, &#167; 11.</para></source></law></legaldoc>