<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-2626"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2626</statuteno><catchline>Department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>The department shall have the following powers, functions, and duties:</para>
<para>(1) To administer, implement, and enforce the Pesticide Act and serve
as the lead state agency for the regulation of pesticides. The department
shall involve the natural resources districts and other state agencies, including
the Department of Environmental Quality, the Department of Natural Resources,
or the Department of Health and Human Services, in matters relating to water
quality. Nothing in the act shall be interpreted in any way to affect the
powers of any other state agency or of any natural resources district to regulate
for ground water quality or surface water quality as otherwise provided by
law;</para>
<para>(2) To be responsible for the development and implementation of a state
management plan and pesticide management plans. The Department of Environmental
Quality shall be responsible for the adoption of standards for pesticides
in surface water and ground water, and the Department of Health and Human
Services shall be responsible for the adoption of standards for pesticides
in drinking water. These standards shall be established as action levels in
the state management plan and pesticide management plans at which prevention
and mitigation measures are implemented. Such action levels may be set at
or below the maximum contaminant level set for any product as set by the federal
agency under the federal Safe Drinking Water Act, 42 U.S.C. 300f et seq.,
as the act existed on January 1, 2013. The Department of Agriculture
shall cooperate with and use existing expertise in other state agencies when
developing the state management plan and pesticide management plans and shall
not hire a hydrologist within the department for such purpose;</para>
<para>(3) After notice and public hearing, to adopt and promulgate rules and
regulations providing lists of state-limited-use pesticides for the entire
state or for a designated area within the state, subject to the following:</para>
<para>(a) A pesticide shall be included on a list of state-limited-use pesticides
if:</para>
<para>(i) The Department of Agriculture determines that the pesticide, when
used in accordance with its directions for use, warnings, and cautions and
for uses for which it is registered, may without additional regulatory restrictions
cause unreasonable adverse effects on humans or the environment, including
injury to the applicator or other persons because of acute dermal or inhalation
toxicity of the pesticides;</para>
<para>(ii) The water quality standards set by the Department of Environmental
Quality or the Department of Health and Human Services pursuant to this section
are exceeded; or</para>
<para>(iii) The Department of Agriculture determines that the pesticide requires
additional restrictions to meet the requirements of the Pesticide Act, the
federal act, or any plan adopted under the Pesticide Act or the federal act;</para>
<para>(b) The Department of Agriculture may regulate the time and conditions
of use of a state-limited-use pesticide and may require that it be purchased
or possessed only:</para>
<para>(i) With permission of the department;</para>
<para>(ii) Under direct supervision of the department or its designee in certain
areas and under certain conditions;</para>
<para>(iii) In specified quantities and concentrations or at specified times;
or</para>
<para>(iv) According to such other restrictions as the department may set
by regulation;</para>
<para>(c) The Department of Agriculture may require a person authorized to
distribute or use a state-limited-use pesticide to maintain records of the
person's distribution or use and may require that the records be kept separate
from other business records;</para>
<para>(d) The state management plan and pesticide management plans shall be
coordinated with the Department of Agriculture and other state agency plans
and with other state agencies and with natural resources districts;</para>
<para>(e) The state management plan and pesticide management plans may impose
progressively more rigorous pesticide management practices as pesticides are
detected in ground water or surface water at increasing fractions of the standards
adopted by the Department of Environmental Quality or the Department of Health
and Human Services; and</para>
<para>(f) A pesticide management plan may impose progressively more rigorous
pesticide management practices to address any unreasonable adverse effect
of pesticides on humans or the environment. When appropriate, a pesticide
management plan may establish action levels for imposition of such progressively
more rigorous management practices based upon measurable indicators of the
adverse effect on humans or the environment;</para>
<para>(4) To adopt and promulgate such rules and regulations as are necessary
for the enforcement and administration of the Pesticide Act. The regulations
shall include, but not be limited to, regulations providing for:</para>
<para>(a) The collection of samples, examination of records, and reporting
of information by persons subject to the act;</para>
<para>(b) The safe handling, transportation, storage, display, distribution,
use, and disposal of pesticides and their containers;</para>
<para>(c) Labeling requirements of all pesticides required to be registered
under provisions of the act, except that such regulations shall not impose
any requirements for federally registered labels contrary to those required
pursuant to the federal act;</para>
<para>(d) Classes of devices which shall be subject to the Pesticide Act;</para>
<para>(e) Reporting and record-keeping requirements for persons distributing
or using pesticide products made available under 7
U.S.C. 136i-1 of the federal act and for persons required to keep
records under the Pesticide Act;</para>
<para>(f) Methods to be used in the application of pesticides when the Department
of Agriculture finds that such regulations are necessary to carry out the
purpose and intent of the Pesticide Act. Such regulations may include methods
to be used in the application of a restricted-use pesticide, may relate to
the time, place, manner, methods, materials, amounts, and concentrations in
connection with the use of the pesticide, may restrict or prohibit use of
the pesticides in designated areas during specified periods of time, and may
provide specific examples and technical interpretations of subdivision (4)
of section 2-2646. The regulations shall encompass all reasonable factors
which the department deems necessary to prevent damage or injury by drift
or misapplication to (i) plants, including forage plants, or adjacent or nearby
property, (ii) wildlife in the adjoining or nearby areas, (iii) fish and other
aquatic life in waters in reasonable proximity to the area to be treated,
(iv) surface water or ground water, and (v) humans, animals, or beneficial
insects. In adopting and promulgating such regulations, the department shall
give consideration to pertinent research findings and recommendations of other
agencies of the state, the federal government, or other reliable sources.
The department may, by regulation, require that notice of a proposed use of
a pesticide be given to landowners whose property is adjacent to the property
to be treated or in the immediate vicinity thereof if the department finds
that such notice is necessary to carry out the purpose of the act;</para>
<para>(g) State-limited-use pesticides for the state or for designated areas
in the state;</para>
<para>(h) Establishment of the amount of any fee or fine as directed by the
act;</para>
<para>(i) Establishment of the components of any state management plan or
pesticide management plan;</para>
<para>(j) Establishment of categories for licensed pesticide applicators in
addition to those established in 40 C.F.R. 171, as the regulation existed
on January 1, 2013; and</para>
<para>(k) Establishment of a process for the issuance of permits for emergency-use
pesticides made available under 7 U.S.C. 136p of the federal
act;</para>
<para>(5) To enter any public or private premises at any reasonable time to:</para>
<para>(a) Inspect and sample any equipment authorized or required to be inspected
under the Pesticide Act or to inspect the premises on which the equipment
is kept or stored;</para>
<para>(b) Inspect or sample any area exposed or reported to be exposed to
a pesticide or where a pesticide use has occurred;</para>
<para>(c) Inspect and sample any area where a pesticide is disposed of or
stored;</para>
<para>(d) Observe the use and application of and sample any pesticide;</para>
<para>(e) Inspect and copy any records relating to the distribution or use
of any pesticide or the issuance of any license, permit, or registration under
the act; or</para>
<para>(f) Inspect, examine, or take samples from any application equipment,
building, or place owned, controlled, or operated by any person engaging in
an activity regulated by the act if, from probable cause, it appears that
the application equipment, building, or place contains a pesticide;</para>
<para>(6) To sample, inspect, make analysis of, and test any pesticide found
within this state;</para>
<para>(7) To issue and enforce a written or printed order to stop the sale,
removal, or use of a pesticide if the Department of Agriculture has reason
to believe that the pesticide is in violation of any provision of the act.
The department shall present the order to the owner or custodian of the pesticide.
The person who receives the order shall not distribute, remove, or use the
pesticide until the department determines that the pesticide is in compliance
with the act. This subdivision shall not limit the right of the department
to proceed as authorized by any other provision of the act;</para>
<para>(8)(a) To sue in the name of the director to enjoin any violation of
the act. Venue for such action shall be in the county in which the alleged
violation occurred, is occurring, or is threatening to occur; and</para>
<para>(b) To request the county attorney or the Attorney General to bring
suit to enjoin a violation or threatened violation of the act;</para>
<para>(9) To impose or levy an administrative fine of not more than five thousand
dollars for each violation on
any person who has violated any provision, requirement, condition,
limitation, or duty imposed by the act or rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act. A violation means each action
which violates any separate or distinct provision, requirement, condition,
limitation, or duty imposed by the act or rules and regulations adopted and
promulgated pursuant to the act;</para>
<para>(10) To cause a violation warning letter to be served upon the alleged
violator or violators pursuant to the act;</para>
<para>(11) To take reasonable measures to assess and collect all
fees and fines prescribed by the act and the
rules or regulations adopted under the act;</para>
<para>(12) To access, inspect, and copy all books, papers, records, bills
of lading, invoices, and other information relating to the use, manufacture,
repackaging, and distribution of pesticides necessary for the enforcement
of the act;</para>
<para>(13) To seize, for use as evidence, without formal warrant if probable
cause exists, any pesticide which is in violation of the act or is not approved
by the Department of Agriculture or which is found to be used or distributed
in the violation of the act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated
under it;</para>
<para>(14) To declare as a pest any form of plant or animal life, other than
humans and other than bacteria, viruses, and other microorganisms on or in
living humans or other living animals, which is injurious to health or the
environment;</para>
<para>(15) To adopt classifications of restricted-use pesticides as determined
by the federal agency under the federal act. In addition to the restricted-use
pesticides classified by the administrator, the Department of Agriculture
may also determine state-limited-use pesticides for the state or for designated
areas within the state as provided in subdivision (3) of this section;</para>
<para>(16) To receive grants-in-aid from any federal entity, and to enter
into cooperative agreements with any federal entity, any agency of this state,
any subdivision of this state, any agency of another state, any Indian tribe,
or any private person for the purpose of obtaining consistency with or assistance
in the implementation of the Pesticide Act. The Department of Agriculture
may reimburse any such entity from the Pesticide Administrative Cash Fund
for the work performed under the cooperative agreement. The department may
delegate its administrative responsibilities under the act to cities of the
metropolitan and primary classes if it reasonably believes that such cities
can perform the responsibilities in a manner consistent with the act and the
rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under it;</para>
<para>(17) To prepare and adopt such plans as are necessary to implement any
requirements of the federal agency under the federal act;</para>
<para>(18) To request the assistance of the Attorney General or the county
attorney in the county in which a violation of the Pesticide Act has occurred
with the prosecution or enforcement of any violation of the act;</para>
<para>(19) To enter into a settlement agreement with any person regarding
the disposition of any license, permit, registration, or administrative fine;</para>
<para>(20) To issue a cease and desist order pursuant to section 2-2649;</para>
<para>(21) To deny an application or cancel, suspend, or modify the registration
of a pesticide pursuant to section 2-2632;</para>
<para>(22) To issue, cancel, suspend, modify, or place on probation any license
or permit issued pursuant to the act; and</para>
<para>(23) To make such reports to the federal agency as are required under
the federal act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 588, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 93, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 874, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB254, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB69, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>