<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-2641"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2641</statuteno><catchline>Private applicator; qualifications;
application for license; requirements; fee.</catchline><para>(1) A person
shall be deemed to be a private applicator if the person uses a restricted-use
pesticide in the State of Nebraska for the purpose of producing an agricultural
commodity:</para>
<para>(a) On property owned or rented by the person or person's employer or
under the person's general control; or</para>
<para>(b) On the property of another person if applied without compensation
other than the trading of personal services between producers of agricultural
commodities.</para>
<para>(2) An employee shall qualify as a private applicator under subdivision
(1)(a) of this section only if he or she provides labor for the pesticide
use but does not provide the necessary equipment or pesticides.</para>
<para>(3) Every person applying for a license as a private applicator shall
meet the certification requirement of (a) undertaking a training session approved
by the department or (b) passing an examination showing that the person is
properly qualified to perform functions associated with pesticide use to a
degree directly related to the nature of the activity and the associated responsibility.
The examination shall be approved by the department and monitored by the department
or its authorized agent. If the applicant is an individual, the application
shall include the applicant's date of birth.</para>
<para>(4) Application for an original or renewal private applicator license
shall be made to the department and accompanied by a license fee of twenty-five
dollars. All fees collected shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Natural Resources Water Quality Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 588, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 874, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB100, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB69, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>