<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2701.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2701.02</statuteno><catchline>Sales permit; information required; notice to purchaser; liability for damages.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who applies for a permit to sell a tractor model in the state shall provide to the department at the time of application information on the availability and accessibility of service and replacement parts for such tractor model. Such information shall include the names and addresses of any regional service, parts, or supply dealers, instructions on how to order parts and supplies, and any limitations as to the availability and accessibility of service and replacement parts. Any person who fails to provide the information required in this section shall not be issued a sales permit for the tractor model. The information received by the department pursuant to this section shall be public information.</para><para>(2) Any person who initially sells to the ultimate consumer a current tractor model for which a sales permit has been issued after April 17, 1986, shall provide to the purchaser written notice that the information required in subsection (1) of this section has been filed with and is available at the department. Any remedy for failure to comply with this subsection shall be as provided in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3) Any person who provides to the department information required in subsection (1) of this section which is inaccurate at the time of application shall be liable for damages to any injured purchaser of the tractor for which a sales permit has been issued, and any person who fails to provide the notice required in subsection (2) of this section shall be liable for damages to the person who purchased such tractor from such person. For purposes of this section, damages may include, but shall not be limited to, loss of profits, the additional cost of shipment of parts, and the additional cost of obtaining parts or services from another provider. In any action brought under this section, the court may award reasonable attorney's fees to the prevailing party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 768, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>