<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-2638"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2638</statuteno><catchline>Commercial applicator license; when
required; application; denial, when; fee; resident agent for service of process.</catchline><para>(1) An individual who uses restricted-use pesticides on the property
of another person in the State of Nebraska for hire or compensation shall
meet all certification requirements of the Pesticide Act and shall be a commercial
applicator license holder of a license issued for the categories and subcategories
in which the pesticide use is to be made.</para>
<para>(2) Any person who uses lawn care or structural pest control pesticides
on the property of another person in the State of Nebraska for hire or compensation
shall be a commercial applicator license holder, regardless of whether such
person uses any restricted-use pesticide.</para>
<para>(3) Application for an original or renewal commercial applicator license
shall be made to the department on forms prescribed by the department. The
application shall include information as required by the director and be accompanied
by a license fee of ninety dollars. If the applicant is an individual, the
application shall include the applicant's date of birth. The fee may be increased by
the director by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to
the act. The fee shall not exceed one hundred fifty dollars per license. All
fees collected shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the
Natural Resources Water Quality Fund.</para>
<para>(4) The department may deny a commercial applicator license if it has
determined that:</para>
<para>(a) The applicant has had a license as a licensed certified applicator
issued by this state or another state revoked within the last two years;</para>
<para>(b) The applicant has been unable to satisfactorily fulfill certification
or licensing requirements;</para>
<para>(c) The applicant for any other reason cannot be expected to be able
to fulfill the provisions of the Pesticide Act applicable to the category
for which application is made; or</para>
<para>(d) An applicant for an original commercial applicator license has not
passed an examination under sections 2-2637 and 2-2640.</para>
<para>(5) An individual to whom a commercial applicator license is issued
shall be a licensed certified applicator authorized to use restricted-use
pesticides in the categories and subcategories in which the individual is
licensed.</para>
<para>(6) As a condition to issuance of a commercial applicator license, an
applicant located outside this state shall file with the department a written
designation of a resident agent for service of process in actions taken in
the administration and enforcement of the act. In lieu of designating a resident
agent, the applicant may designate in writing the Secretary of State as the
recipient of service of process for the applicant in this state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 588, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 874, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB100, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB69, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>