<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id19" statutenumber="2-2303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2303</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Nebraska Wheat Resources Act, unless the
context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Board means the
Nebraska Wheat Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board;</para>
<para>(2) Commercial
channels means the sale of wheat for any use when sold to any commercial buyer,
dealer, processor, cooperative, or any person, public or private, who resells
any wheat or product produced from wheat;</para><para>(3) First purchaser means any person, public
or private corporation, association, partnership, or limited liability company
buying, accepting for shipment, or otherwise acquiring the property in or
to wheat from a grower and includes a mortgagee, pledgee, lienor, or other
person, public or private, having a claim against the grower when the actual
or constructive possession of such wheat is taken as part payment or in satisfaction
of such mortgage, pledge, lien, or claim;</para><para>(4) Grower means any
landowner personally engaged in growing wheat, a tenant of the landowner personally
engaged in growing wheat, and both the owner and the tenant jointly and includes a person, partnership, limited liability
company, association, corporation, cooperative, trust, sharecropper, and other
business units, devices, and arrangements;</para>
<para>(5) Net market
price means the sales price, or other value, per volumetric unit received
by a producer for wheat after adjustment for any premium or discount;</para>
<para>(6) Net market
value means the value found by multiplying the net market price by the appropriate
quantity of the volumetric units or the minimum value in a production contract
received by a producer for wheat after adjustments for any premium or discount.
For wheat pledged as collateral for a loan issued under any Commodity Credit
Corporation price support loan program, net market value means the principal
amount of the loan; and</para><para>(7) Sale includes any pledge or mortgage
of wheat after harvest to any person, public or private.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 5, &#167; 3, p. 59; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 11, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 1, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB905, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>