<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2635"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2635</statuteno><catchline>Pesticide dealer license; when required;
application; fee; expiration; display; department; powers; disciplinary actions;
restricted-use pesticides; records required; registered agent for service
of process.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this
section, a person shall not distribute at wholesale or retail or possess pesticides
with an intent to distribute them without a pesticide dealer license for each
distribution location. Any manufacturer, registrant, or distributor who has
no pesticide dealer outlet licensed within this state and who distributes
such pesticides directly into this state shall obtain a pesticide dealer license
for his, her, or its principal out-of-state location or outlet.</para>
<para>(2) The requirements of subsection (1) of this section shall not apply
to:</para>
<para>(a) A commercial applicator or noncommercial applicator licensed under
sections 2-2636 to 2-2642 who uses restricted-use pesticides only as an integral
part of a pesticide application service and does not distribute any unapplied
pesticide;</para>
<para>(b) A federal, state, county, or municipal agency using restricted-use
pesticides only for its own program; or</para>
<para>(c) Persons who sell only pesticide products in containers holding fifty
pounds or less by weight or one gallon or less by volume and do not sell any
restricted-use pesticides or bulk pesticides.</para>
<para>(3) A pesticide
dealer may distribute restricted-use pesticides only to:</para>
<para>(a) A licensed pesticide dealer;</para>
<para>(b) A licensed certified applicator issued a license with the appropriate
category for using the restricted-use pesticide being distributed;</para>
<para>(c) An applicator issued a license by another state with the appropriate
category for using the restricted-use pesticide being distributed;</para>
<para>(d) A noncertified applicator authorized by the Pesticide Act to apply
restricted-use pesticides if the licensed certified applicator supervising
the noncertified applicator is issued a license with the appropriate category
for using the restricted-use pesticide being distributed; or</para>
<para>(e) Any other person if the pesticide dealer maintains records set out
in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act requiring
the person to verify in writing that:</para>
<para>(i) The restricted-use pesticide will be delivered to an applicator
described in subdivision (3)(b), (c), or (d) of this section; and</para>
<para>(ii) The applicator receiving the restricted-use pesticide acknowledges
and agrees to the distribution.</para>
<para>(4) A pesticide dealer license shall expire on December 31 of each year,
unless it is suspended or revoked before that date. Such license shall not
be transferable to another person or location and shall be prominently displayed
to the public in the pesticide dealer's place of business.</para>
<para>(5) If the pesticide dealer has had a license suspended or revoked,
or has otherwise had a history of violations of the Pesticide Act, the department
may require an additional demonstration of dealer qualifications prior to
issuance or renewal of a license to such person.</para>
<para>(6) Application for an initial pesticide dealer license shall be submitted
to the department prior to commencing business as a pesticide dealer. Application
for renewal of a pesticide dealer license shall be submitted to the department
by January 1 of each year. All applications shall be accompanied by an annual
license fee of twenty-five dollars. The fee may be increased by the director
by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act. The
fee shall not exceed one hundred dollars per license. Application shall be
on a form prescribed by the department and shall include the full name of
the person applying for such license. If such applicant is a partnership, limited
liability company, association, corporation, or organized group of persons,
the full name of each member of the firm, partnership, or limited liability
company or of the principal officers of the association or corporation shall
be given on the application. Such application shall further state the address
of each outlet to be licensed, the principal business address of the applicant,
the name of the person domiciled in this state authorized to receive and accept
service of summons of legal notices of all kinds for the applicant, and any
other necessary information prescribed by the department.</para>
<para>An applicant located outside this state shall file with the department
a written designation of a resident agent for service of process in actions
taken in the administration and enforcement of the act. In lieu of designating
a resident agent, the applicant may designate the Secretary of State as the
recipient of service of process for the applicant in this state.</para>
<para>If an application for renewal of a pesticide dealer license is not filed
before January 1 of the year for which the license is to be issued, an additional
fee equal to twenty-five percent of the fee due and owing per month, not to
exceed one hundred percent, shall be paid by the applicant before the license
may be issued. The purpose
of the additional fee is to cover the administrative costs associated with
collecting fees.</para>
<para>An application for a duplicate pesticide dealer's license shall be accompanied
by a nonrefundable application fee of ten dollars.</para>
<para>All fees collected pursuant
to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for
credit to the Pesticide Administrative Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(7) Each licensed pesticide dealer shall be responsible for the acts
of each person employed by him or her in the solicitation and distribution
of pesticides and all claims and recommendations for use of pesticides. The
dealer's license shall be subject to denial, suspension, modification, or
revocation after a hearing for any violation of the act, whether committed
by the dealer or by the dealer's officer, agent, or employee.</para>
<para>(8) The department shall require each pesticide dealer to maintain records
of the dealer's purchases and distribution of all restricted-use pesticides
and may require such records to be kept separate from other business records.
The department may prescribe by rules and regulations the information to be
included in the records. The dealer shall keep such records for a period of
three years and shall provide the department access to examine such records
and a copy of any record on request.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 267, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 588, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB69, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>