
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2645"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2645</statuteno><catchline>Violation of act; claim of damages; inspection; failure to file report or cooperate with department; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A person claiming damages from a pesticide use may file with the department a written report claiming that the person has been damaged. The report shall be filed as soon as possible following the day of the alleged occurrence.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in the Pesticide Act, upon receipt of a report if the department has reasonable cause to believe that a violation of the act has occurred, it shall investigate such report to determine if any violation has occurred and if any enforcement action shall be taken under the act. The department is not required to investigate any complaint that the department determines is made more than ninety days after the person complaining knew of the incident or damages, is outside the scope of the Pesticide Act, or is determined by the department to involve a matter which is frivolous, minor, or insignificant under the intent of the act. If a complaint is investigated, the department shall notify the licensee, owner, or lessee of the property on which the alleged act occurred and any other person who may be charged with responsibility for the damages claimed. The department shall furnish copies of the report to such licensee, owner, lessee, or other person upon receiving a written request. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require the department to take enforcement action in any matter.</para><para>(3) The department shall inspect damages whenever possible and shall report its findings to the person claiming damage and to the person alleged to have caused the damage. The claimant shall permit the department and the licensee to inspect, within reasonable hours, the property alleged to have been damaged. If the claimant refuses to permit the department to inspect the property alleged to have been damaged, or fails to provide additional information regarding the allegation when requested by the department, the department may decline to investigate the claim.</para><para>(4) Failure to file a report shall not bar maintenance of a civil or criminal action. If a person fails to file a report or cooperate with the department and is the only person claiming injury from the particular use of a pesticide, the department may, if in the public interest, refuse to take action or hold a hearing for the denial, suspension, or revocation of a license issued under the act to the person alleged to have caused the damage.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 588, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 436, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB100, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB320, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>