<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2304</statuteno><catchline>Board; membership; qualifications; appointment; districts; enumerated.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall be composed of seven members who shall (a) be citizens of Nebraska, (b) be at least twenty-one years of age, (c) have been actually engaged in growing wheat in this state for a period of at least five years, and (d) derive a substantial portion of their income from growing wheat. The Director of Agriculture and the vice chancellor of the University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources shall serve as nonvoting members of the board. With the exception of the nonvoting members, the Governor shall appoint the members to the board.</para><para>(2) The seven appointed members shall be appointed from the following districts:</para><para>(a) District 1: The counties of Sioux, Scotts Bluff, Dawes, Box Butte, Morrill, Sheridan, and Garden;</para><para>(b) District 2: The counties of Kimball, Banner, and Cheyenne;</para><para>(c) District 3: The counties of Perkins, Deuel, Keith, Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Grant, Hooker, Thomas, and Cherry;</para><para>(d) District 4: The counties of Lincoln, Chase, Dundy, Hayes, Hitchcock, and Frontier;</para><para>(e) District 5: The counties of Buffalo, Dawson, Phelps, Custer, Gosper, Kearney, Red Willow, Furnas, Harlan, and Franklin;</para><para>(f) District 6: The counties of Adams, Webster, Nuckolls, Thayer, Jefferson, Gage, Johnson, Nemaha, Pawnee, Richardson, Otoe, Cass, Lancaster, Seward, York, Hamilton, Hall, Sherman, Howard, Merrick, Nance, Polk, Butler, Saunders, Sarpy, Douglas, Washington, Dodge, Colfax, Platte, Burt, Cuming, Stanton, Madison, Boone, Valley, Greeley, Antelope, Pierce, Wayne, Thurston, Dakota, Dixon, Cedar, Knox, Wheeler, Garfield, Loup, Blaine, Brown, Rock, Holt, Boyd, Keya Paha, Clay, Fillmore, and Saline; and</para><para>(g) District 7: The at-large district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 5, &#167; 4, p. 60; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 193; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 11, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 685, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 474, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>