<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-2705"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-2705</statuteno><catchline>Tractor model tests; fees; University of Nebraska Tractor Test Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>Application to the board for the testing of a tractor model by the University of Nebraska shall be accompanied by the fee prescribed in section 2-2705.01 and such fee as is prescribed by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska as a partial reimbursement for making the application.</para><para>Fees collected for the testing of tractors by the Nebraska Tractor Testing Laboratory shall be credited to the University of Nebraska Tractor Test Cash Fund, which fund is hereby created. The fund shall be used by the Nebraska Tractor Testing Laboratory to defray the expenses of testing tractors. Any accrued interest shall also be credited to the fund, except that the cash carryover of such fund from one biennium to the next biennium shall not exceed, by more than fifteen percent, the total cash fund expenditures for the average of the five preceding years. Any amount in excess of such fifteen percent shall be forwarded to the University of Nebraska. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>The Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska may establish and change from time to time as it determines advisable a schedule of fees for such tractor tests, except that such fee schedule shall not include the application fee prescribed in section 2-2705.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. III, &#167; 40, p. 1396; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 75-340; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 480, &#167; 5, p. 1488; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 692, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 768, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 13.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis>                see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis>                see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>