<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id28">
<sectno id="id29">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" id="id30" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-3234.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3234.05</statuteno><catchline>Trails; establishment; district;
powers; findings.</catchline><para>If
the district decides to establish the trail after following the procedure
under section 2-3234.04, the district may acquire private real property, or
an interest therein, to develop and maintain the trail by:</para>
<para>(1) Seeking to
secure the written consent of the private real property owners affected by
the trail to enter into negotiations and proceeding in good faith to reach
negotiated agreements with such owners for the private real property, or an
interest therein needed; or</para><para>(2) If all reasonable efforts to secure written consent and negotiated
agreements to acquire private real property, or an interest therein, have
failed, the district board may, by resolution adopted by a supermajority of
the district board at a public meeting, elect to conduct a proceeding to determine
whether to use the power of eminent domain to acquire such property. Such
proceeding shall be a public hearing with general notice to the public and
specific notice by registered mail to all private real property owners whose
property would be subject to condemnation by eminent domain. The public hearing
shall be held no sooner than forty-five days after the date the resolution
is adopted. At the public hearing, the district board shall receive evidence
on the question of whether to acquire private real property by eminent domain
for the purpose of constructing the trail. The district board may, by vote
of a supermajority of its members, elect to proceed with eminent domain to
acquire such property if the district board finds, by clear and convincing
evidence received at the public hearing, that all of the following criteria
are met:</para><para>(a) Whether the trail has been publicized at a public hearing held
in accordance with section 2-3234.04 in the area where the trail is planned
and reasonable notice of the hearing was provided to affected private real
property owners;</para><para>(b) Whether good faith attempts to negotiate agreements meeting
the requirements of subdivision (1) of this section with the affected private
real property owners have been made and have failed for some or all of the
private real property that is determined by the district board to be necessary
for the trail to be developed;</para><para>(c) Whether all other trail route alternatives
have been considered, with an evaluation of the extent to which private real
property may be involved and which may require the exercise of eminent domain
for each alternate route;</para><para>(d) Whether in locating the proposed trail consideration was given
to the directness of the route; potential benefit to communities and public
facilities adjacent to the trail route; trail design and costs; safety to
trail users, vehicle operators, and adjacent persons; and adverse impacts
and intrusions upon private real property owners or persons using such property;</para>
<para>(e) Whether
good faith attempts have been made to address the concerns of affected private
real property owners regarding trail design, privacy, land protection, management,
and maintenance; and</para><para>(f) Whether any development and management of the trail is designed
to harmonize with and complement any established forest or agricultural plan
for the affected private real property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1010, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>