<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3005" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3005</statuteno><catchline>State Veterinarian; rules and regulations; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The State Veterinarian, subject to the approval of the Director of Agriculture, shall adopt and promulgate such rules and regulations to carry out the purposes and intent of the Nebraska Poultry Disease Control Act. As far as practical, the disease provisions of the rules and regulations officially promulgated by the United States Department of Agriculture, commonly known and cited as the National Poultry Improvement Plan and Auxiliary Provisions, shall be adopted (a) to establish and maintain breeding poultry flocks and hatcheries as pullorum and typhoid clean, (b) to establish requirements for poultry being exhibited, (c) to assure that only breeding poultry flocks and hatching eggs which are pullorum and typhoid clean are moved into and within Nebraska, (d) to establish testing requirements to monitor the presence of pullorum and typhoid in Nebraska, and (e) to establish testing requirements to monitor the presence of H5/H7 subtypes of low pathogenic avian influenza Type A in breeding poultry flocks and commercial poultry flocks.</para><para>(2) The State Veterinarian shall have authority to monitor for the presence of various subtypes of avian influenza in noncommercial poultry and any other dangerous, infectious, contagious, or otherwise transmissible disease of poultry. For fiscal year 2006-07, the State Veterinarian shall carry out a program of surveillance of noncommercial poultry flocks for the presence of various subtypes of avian influenza and may cooperate with the University of Nebraska to develop and carry out such program of surveillance. The State Veterinarian may continue such program of surveillance beyond fiscal year 2006-07 as deemed necessary subject to the availability of funds for such purpose. Any activities carried out by or on behalf of the State Veterinarian pursuant to this section shall be conducted with the voluntary cooperation of noncommercial poultry flock owners or the property owner where such poultry are located to the extent that this section does not conflict with the State Veterinarian's disease surveillance authorities pursuant to section 54-701.02.</para><para>(3) The State Veterinarian shall have quarantine power and may require reports and records from persons subject to the act as established in the rules and regulations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 6, &#167; 5, p. 92; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 871, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 38, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>