<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3813"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3813</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 2-3813 and 2-3814, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Grain shall mean wheat, corn, soybeans, and sorghum grains;</para><para>(2) Quality factors shall mean:</para><para>(a) Heat-damaged kernels which include kernels that have been discolored or damaged by high heat from respiring grain;</para><para>(b) Total-damaged kernels which represent the percentage, by weight, of kernels damaged by weather, disease, insects, molds, and moisture and includes heat damage;</para><para>(c) Foreign material which is all matter other than the grain being examined which remains in a sample after removal of dockage and shrunken and broken kernels;</para><para>(d) Shrunken and broken kernels which are kernels, kernel pieces, and other matter that pass through a sixty-four thousandths by three-eighths inch oblong-hole sieve;</para><para>(e) Total defects which are the sum of heat-damaged kernels, shrunken and broken kernels, and foreign material;</para><para>(f) Wheat of other classes which is any class that is mixed with the predominant class;</para><para>(g) Dockage, though not a grading factor, which appears on the certificate if it exceeds forty-nine hundredths of one percent. Dockage shall be rounded down to the nearest one-half percent. Dockage shall include chaff, dust, and items removed from a sample by an initial screening with a dockage tester; and</para><para>(h) Grade which is determined by analyzing the physical and biological factors present in the sample. Limits for the grading factors shall be established for each numerical grade. Numerical grades shall range from number 1, highest, to sample grade, lowest. Factors that exceed the established limits shall lower the numerical grade. Higher test weights shall be acceptable; and</para><para>(3) Department shall mean the Department of Agriculture.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1007, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>