<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id15" statutenumber="2-3228"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3228</statuteno><catchline id="id18">Districts; powers; Nebraska Association of Resources Districts; retirement plan reports; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Each district shall have the power and authority to:</para><para>(a) Receive and accept donations, gifts, grants, bequests, appropriations, or other contributions in money, services, materials, or otherwise from the United States or any of its agencies, from the state or any of its agencies or political subdivisions, or from any person as defined in section 49-801 and use or expend all such contributions in carrying on its operations;</para><para>(b) Establish advisory groups by appointing persons within the district, pay necessary and proper expenses of such groups as the board shall determine, and dissolve such groups;</para><para>(c) Employ such persons as are necessary to carry out its authorized purposes and, in addition to other compensation provided, establish and fund a pension plan designed and intended for the benefit of all permanent full-time employees of the district. Any recognized method of funding a pension plan may be employed. Employee contributions shall be required to fund at least fifty percent of the benefits, and past service benefits may be included. The district shall pay all costs of any such past service benefits, which may be retroactive to July 1, 1972, and the plan may be integrated with old age and survivors' insurance, generally known as social security. A uniform pension plan, including the method for jointly funding such plan, shall be established for all districts in the state. A district may elect not to participate in such a plan but shall not establish an independent plan;</para><para>(d) Purchase liability, property damage, workers' compensation, and other types of insurance as in the judgment of the board are necessary to protect the assets of the district;</para><para>(e) Borrow money to carry out its authorized purposes;</para><para>(f) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out its authorized purposes; and</para><para>(g) Invite the local governing body of any municipality or county to designate a representative to advise and counsel with the board on programs and policies that may affect the property, water supply, or other interests of such municipality or county.</para><para>(2) Beginning December 31, 1998, through December 31, 2017:</para><para>(a) The Nebraska Association of Resources Districts as organized under the Interlocal Cooperation Act shall file with the Public Employees Retirement Board an annual report on each retirement plan established pursuant to this section and section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code and shall submit copies of such report to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The annual report shall be in a form prescribed by the Public Employees Retirement Board and shall contain the following information for each such retirement plan:</para><para>(i) The number of persons participating in the retirement plan;</para><para>(ii) The contribution rates of participants in the plan;</para><para>(iii) Plan assets and liabilities;</para><para>(iv) The names and positions of persons administering the plan;</para><para>(v) The names and positions of persons investing plan assets;</para><para>(vi) The form and nature of investments;</para><para>(vii) For each defined contribution plan, a full description of investment policies and options available to plan participants; and</para><para>(viii) For each defined benefit plan, the levels of benefits of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a benefit, and the total present value of such members' benefits, as well as the funding sources which will pay for such benefits.</para><para>If a plan contains no current active participants, the association may file in place of such report a statement with the Public Employees Retirement Board indicating the number of retirees still drawing benefits, and the sources and amount of funding for such benefits; and</para><para>(b) If such retirement plan is a defined benefit plan which was open to new members on January 1, 2004, in addition to the reports required by section 13-2402, the association shall cause to be prepared an annual report and shall file the same with the Public Employees Retirement Board and the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and submit to the Auditor of Public Accounts a copy of such report. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If the association does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor of Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the association. All costs of the audit shall be paid by the association. The report shall consist of a full actuarial analysis of each such retirement plan established pursuant to this section. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization offering investment advice or which provides investment management services to the retirement plan. The report to the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee shall be submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 28, p. 118; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 404, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 36, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 387, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 15, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 480, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 436, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 891, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB759, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>