<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3814"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3814</statuteno><catchline>Department; grain inspections; special certificate; fee; powers; Nebraska Origin and Premium Quality Grain Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) In order to assist Nebraska grain producers and the state's grain industry in competing for a larger share of the international grain trade against the more stringent grain standards of other exporting nations, the department shall, upon request, provide inspection of grain shipments assembled by farmers and grain dealers who are arranging or attempting to arrange grain sales with foreign buyers. As a means of expediting such sales and to insure the quality of grain shipments for export originating in Nebraska, the department shall provide grain inspections. Such inspections shall include a certificate stating the quality factors present in the grain shipments destined for export points. A special certificate shall be designed by the department for shipments that substantially exceed grade and quality factors required under current United States grain standards. Such special certificate shall be designated as Nebraska Origin and Premium Quality Grain and shall be issued only on grain shipments containing levels of grade and quality factors totaling not more than fifty percent of the maximum allowable limits of total defects and other quality factors as required by current United States Grade Number One.</para><para>(2) The department shall assess and collect a fee for the inspections made. The fee shall be in an amount equal to the costs of the inspections.</para><para>(3) The department may:</para><para>(a) Contract for services which are necessary to carry out its duties under sections 2-3813 and 2-3814;</para><para>(b) Accept funds or fees from any source, including, but not limited to, federal, state, public, and private, to be used in carrying out such sections;</para><para>(c) Expend funds for purposes of carrying out such sections; and</para><para>(d) Enter upon public or private land for the purpose of inspecting such grain.</para><para>(4) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to aid in implementing such sections. The rules and regulations may include, but shall not be limited to, provisions governing: (a) Assignment of responsibilities; (b) the charges and fees to be assessed; (c) setting the grades; and (d) methods for determining quality factors.</para><para>(5) There is hereby created the Nebraska Origin and Premium Quality Grain Cash Fund. The fund shall consist of money appropriated by the Legislature which is received as gifts or grants or collected as fees from any source, including, but not limited to, federal, state, public, and private. The fund shall be utilized for the purpose of carrying out sections 2-3813 and 2-3814. Any money in such fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1007, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 22.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis>                see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis>                see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>