<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-3993"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3993</statuteno><catchline>Report on dairy production and processing;
Department of Agriculture; duties; Agriculture Committee of Legislature; hearing.</catchline>
<para>(1) On or before
November 15, 2014, the Director of Agriculture shall provide a report to the
Legislature, in electronic format, that contains:</para>
<para>(a) A quantitative
and qualitative description of dairy production in Nebraska, including an
overview on the numbers, sizes, and ownership characteristics of dairy operations
in the state, current quantity and value of milk production, trends i<?Pub Caret?>n
milk production, and measures of productivity of dairy production in Nebraska;</para>
<para>(b) A comparison
of volume and value of milk production and trends in milk production in Nebraska
to that of neighboring states and nationally;</para><para>(c) A listing and description
of milk processing facilities in Nebraska and a description of marketing affiliations
and final consumer markets and destinations, including self-processing and
direct marketing, for milk produced in Nebraska;</para><para>(d) An evaluation of the potential
for expanded milk production in Nebraska with respect to (i) the ability of
agricultural, institutional, and commercial assets within the state to support
expanded production, (ii) the capacity of instate processors to utilize increased
instate milk production, (iii) the potential for expansion of self-processing
and direct marketing of Nebraska milk and dairy products, (iv) serving new
or expanding markets outside of Nebraska, and (v) the potential for investment
in new or expanded dairy processing facilities;</para><para>(e) A discussion of constraints
to the establishment of new milk production facilities, expansion of milk
production, and relocation of dairy operations into Nebraska;</para>
<para>(f) A review of
public and private programs and initiatives to stimulate expanded milk production
in Nebraska and to recruit milk production to relocate to Nebraska; and</para>
<para>(g) A compilation
and overview of state incentives and outreach and marketing programs for the
recruitment or relocation of dairy production and processing or the stimulation
of investment in new or expanded dairy production and processing for states
surrounding Nebraska.</para><para>(2) In the report, the Director of Agriculture may include any recommendations
to the Legislature regarding actions state government may take to aid and
encourage expansion of milk production and markets for milk production in
Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the Agriculture Committee
of the Legislature shall hold a public hearing to receive the report and to
take public comment on the report and any recommendations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB941, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>