<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3520"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3520</statuteno><catchline>Annual license fee; inspection fee, amount; how determined; license renewal; applicability of section.</catchline><para>There shall be paid to the department an annual license fee of two dollars and fifty cents and an inspection fee based on volume, as follows:</para><para>(1) Retailers:</para><para>(a) Not more than ten thirty-dozen cases annual average per week, the sum of five dollars;</para><para>(b) More than ten thirty-dozen cases but not more than twenty-five such cases annual average per week, the sum of seven dollars and fifty cents; and</para><para>(c) More than twenty-five thirty-dozen cases annual average per week, the sum of ten dollars; and</para><para>(2) Egg handlers:</para><para>(a) Not more than ten thirty-dozen cases annual average per week, the sum of five dollars;</para><para>(b) More than ten thirty-dozen cases but not more than two hundred such cases annual average per week, the sum of twenty-five dollars;</para><para>(c) More than two hundred thirty-dozen cases but not more than five hundred such cases annual average per week, the sum of fifty dollars;</para><para>(d) More than five hundred thirty-dozen cases but not more than one thousand such cases annual average per week, the sum of seventy-five dollars;</para><para>(e) More than one thousand thirty-dozen cases but not more than fifteen hundred such cases annual average per week, the sum of one hundred dollars;</para><para>(f) More than fifteen hundred thirty-dozen cases but not more than two thousand such cases annual average per week, the sum of one hundred twenty-five dollars;</para><para>(g) More than two thousand thirty-dozen cases but not more than twenty-five hundred such cases annual average per week, the sum of one hundred fifty dollars; and</para><para>(h) More than twenty-five hundred thirty-dozen cases annual average per week, the sum of two hundred dollars.</para><para>Application for a license shall be made to the department on forms prescribed and furnished by the department. Licenses shall expire on July 31 of the year following issuance and shall be renewed on or before August 1 of each year. The license fee and the inspection fee shall be paid at the time of the initial application for a license and at the time of each succeeding application for renewal.</para><para>The inspection fee shall be based upon the annual average per week volume during the preceding twelve-month period ending June 30. If no annual average per week volume is available from the preceding twelve-month period, the inspection fee shall be based upon the estimated per week volume for the upcoming year.</para><para>This section does not apply to a producer with production from a flock of three thousand hens or less or to an egg handler required to have a license under the Nebraska Graded Egg Act but whose primary food-related business activity is not egg handling.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 268, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 487, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 871, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 250, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>