<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id144">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id146" statutenumber="2-3989"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3989</statuteno><catchline id="id149">Water supply
requirements; testing.</catchline><para>The water supply at a facility
producing milk for manufacturing purposes shall be safe, clean, and ample
for the cleaning of dairy utensils and equipment. The water supply shall meet
the bacteriological standards established by the Department of Health and
Human Services at all times. Water samples shall be taken, analyzed, and found
to be in compliance with the requirements of the Nebraska Milk Act prior to
the issuance of a permit to the producer and whenever any major change to
the well or water source occurs. Wells or water sources which do not meet
the construction standards of the Department of Health and Human Services
shall be tested annually, and wells or water sources which do meet the construction
standards of the Department of Health and Human Services shall be tested every
three years. Whenever major alterations or repairs occur or a well or water
source repeatedly recontaminates, the water supply shall be unacceptable until
such time as the construction standards are met and an acceptable supply is
demonstrated. All new
producers issued permits under the Nebraska Milk Act shall be required to
meet the construction standards established by the Department of Health and
Human Services for private water supplies.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 5, &#167; 15, p. 76; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 81-263.101; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 632, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 900, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 38, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 268, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 40; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1997), &#167; 2-3925; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB111, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB67, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>