<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3203</statuteno><catchline>Natural resources districts; establishment.</catchline><para>In furtherance of the policy set forth in section 2-3201, the entire area of the State of Nebraska shall be divided into natural resources districts. The Nebraska Natural Resources Commission is hereby authorized and directed to determine and establish the exact number, and the boundaries of such districts. Boundaries of natural resources districts shall be established on or before October 1, 1971. When establishing such boundaries the commission shall employ the following guidelines and criteria:</para><para>(1) The primary objective shall be to establish boundaries which provide effective coordination, planning, development and general management of areas which have related resources problems. Such areas shall be determined according to the hydrologic patterns. The recognized river basins of the state shall be utilized in determining and establishing the boundaries for districts and where necessary for more efficient development and general management two or more districts shall be created within a basin;</para><para>(2) Boundaries of districts shall follow approximate hydrologic patterns except where doing so would divide a section, a city or village, or produce similar incongruities which might hinder the effective operation of the districts;</para><para>(3) Existing boundaries of political subdivisions or voting precincts may be followed wherever feasible. Districts shall be of sufficient size to provide adequate finances and administration for plans of improvement; and</para><para>(4) The number of districts shall be not less than sixteen nor more than twenty-eight.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 3, p. 101; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 538, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>