<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3951.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3951.02</statuteno><catchline>Board members; nomination and appointment.</catchline><para>(1) Members of the board shall
be nominated and appointed as follows:</para>
<para>(a) Each first purchaser of
milk which purchases milk from at least twenty-one milk producers may submit
to the Governor the names of up to two nominees for each forty milk production
units, or major portion thereof, from which the first purchaser purchases
milk. The Governor shall appoint one member for each forty production units,
or major portion thereof, from nominees submitted pursuant to this subdivision, except that if milk production units
certified by the Department of Agriculture have decreased so that each board
member appointed pursuant to this subdivision represents less than a major
portion of forty production units, the Governor shall maintain representation
of one member for each forty production units, or major portion thereof, by
not filling a vacancy caused by a member's term expiring; and</para>
<para>(b) All other first purchasers
of milk and individual producer-processors who are not included among milk
production units claimed by a first purchaser of milk entitled to submit nominees
under subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall
be combined as a group for the purpose of submitting nominees, and each first
purchaser and individual producer-processor of the group may nominate up to
two nominees. The Governor shall appoint two members from
nominees submitted pursuant to this subdivision.</para>
<para>(2) Whenever the number
of members of the board as determined by subsection (1) of this section results
in less than seven members, the Governor shall appoint a member or members
from the state at large to maintain membership of the board at seven members.
Whenever such appointment is required, the board shall call for and submit
a list of two or more nominees for each additional member needed to the Governor,
and the Governor shall appoint a member or members from the nominees submitted
pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(3) Nominations in the case of term expiration or
new or at-large membership and for all other vacancies shall be provided according
to the process prescribed in section 2-3951.04. The Governor may choose the
members of the board from the nominees submitted or may reject all nominees.
If the Governor rejects all nominees, names of nominees shall again be provided
to the Governor until the appointment is filled.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 836, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB70, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>