<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id39"><sectno id="id40">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id41" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-3226.07"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3226.07</statuteno><catchline>Water Contingency Cash Fund; created; investment; natural resources district; financial assistance; request to department; compensation to water rights holders.</catchline><para>(1) The Water Contingency Cash Fund is created. The department shall administer the fund. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) No later than five days after April 2, 2008, a natural resources district with jurisdiction that includes a river subject to an interstate compact among three or more states and that also includes one or more irrigation districts within the compact river basin, and such natural resources district, using authority granted under Laws 2007, LB 701, enters or has entered into agreements, shall submit a request in writing to the department certifying the amount of financial assistance necessary to meet its obligations under section 2-3226.04 by or through obligations of joint entities or joint public agencies formed for the purposes described in section 2-3226.01. Within fifteen days after April 2, 2008, if such a request has been received by the department, the department shall expend from the Water Contingency Cash Fund the amount requested to provide financial assistance to the submitting natural resources district. The natural resources district shall use the financial assistance provided by the state from the Water Contingency Cash Fund to compensate water rights holders who agree or have agreed to lease and forgo the use of water. Any financial assistance provided under this section not used for such purpose by the natural resources district within sixty days after it is received by such district shall be returned to the department for credit to the Water Contingency Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1094, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>
