<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3211.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3211.01</statuteno><catchline>Districts; change of boundaries, division, or merger; assets, liabilities, obligations, and tax receipts; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) Each new natural resources district established by merging two or more natural resources districts in their entirety shall assume all assets, liabilities, and obligations of such merged districts on the effective date of the merger.</para><para>(2) Whenever a change of boundaries, division of one district into two or more new districts, or division and merger of one district into two or more existing districts takes place, the commission shall determine the apportionment of any assets, liabilities, and obligations. Such apportionment shall be based on all relevant factors, including, but not limited to, the proportionate land areas involved in the change, division, or merger and the extent to which particular assets, liabilities, or obligations are related to specific land areas. Interests in real estate and improvements to real estate shall be assumed by the district in which they are located on the effective date of the change, division, or merger. The value of such interests in real estate and improvements shall be considered in the apportionment, and any such assets may be encumbered or otherwise liquidated by the assuming district to effect the proper apportionment.</para><para>(3) All taxes levied pursuant to section 2-3225 and all assessments levied pursuant to sections 2-3254 to 2-3254.06 prior to the change of boundaries, division, or merger shall be apportioned by the commission on the basis of the relationship between the intended uses of such taxes or assessments and the land areas involved in the change, division, or merger. Taxes or assessments levied pursuant to sections 2-3254 to 2-3254.06 which are in the possession of or payable to a district at the time of the change, division, or merger and taxes or assessments in the possession of or payable to any other special-purpose district merged into a natural resources district shall be put into a special fund by the district receiving such assets and shall be expended as nearly as practicable for the purposes for which they were levied or assessed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1045, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 108, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 16.</para></source></law></legaldoc>