<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<sectno id="id13">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id14" statutenumber="2-3226.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id16">2-3226.05</statuteno><catchline id="id17">River-flow
enhancement bonds; repayment of financial assistance; costs and expenses of qualified projects; occupation
tax authorized; collection; accounting; lien; foreclosure.</catchline><para>(1) A district with an integrated management
plan as described in subsection (1) of section 2-3226.01 may levy
an occupation tax upon the activity of irrigation of agricultural lands within
such district on an annual basis, not to exceed ten dollars per irrigated
acre, the proceeds of which may be used for (a) repaying
principal and interest on any bonds or refunding bonds issued pursuant to
section 2-3226.01 for one or more projects under section 2-3226.04, (b)  the repayment of financial assistance
received by the district pursuant to section 2-3226.07, or (c) payment of all or any part of the costs and expenses
of one or more qualified projects described in section 2-3226.04. If such
district has more than one river basin as described in section 2-1504 within
its jurisdiction, such district shall confine such occupation tax authorized
in this section to the geographic area affected by an integrated management
plan adopted in accordance with section 46-715.</para>
<para>(2) Acres classified by the county assessor as irrigated shall
be subject to such district's occupation tax unless, on or before July 1,
2007, and on or before March 1 in each subsequent year, the record owner certifies
to the district the nonirrigation status of such acres.</para>
<para>(3) Any such occupation tax shall remain in effect so long
as the natural resources district
has bonds outstanding which have been issued stating such occupation tax as
an available source for payment and
for the purpose of paying all or any part of the costs and expenses of one
or more projects authorized pursuant to section 2-3226.04.</para>
<para>(4) Such occupation taxes shall be certified to, collected
by, and accounted for by the county treasurer at the same time and in the
same manner as general real estate taxes, and such occupation taxes shall
be and remain a perpetual lien against such real estate until paid. Such occupation
taxes shall become delinquent at the same time and in the same manner as general
real property taxes. The county treasurer shall publish and post a list of
delinquent occupation taxes with the list of real property subject to sale
for delinquent property taxes provided for in section 77-1804. In addition,
the list shall be provided to natural resources districts which levied the
delinquent occupation taxes. The list shall include the record owner's name,
the parcel identification number, and the amount of delinquent occupation
tax. For services rendered in the collection of the occupation tax, the county
treasurer shall receive the fee provided for collection of general natural
resources district money under section 33-114.</para>
<para>(5) Such lien shall be inferior only to general taxes levied
by political subdivisions of the state. When such occupation taxes have become
delinquent and the real property on which the irrigation took place has not
been offered at any tax sale, the district may proceed in district court in
the county in which the real estate is situated to foreclose in its own name
the lien in the same manner and with like effect as a foreclosure of a real
estate mortgage, except that sections 77-1903 to 77-1917 shall govern when
applicable.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1094, &#167;  3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB862, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>