<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3206</statuteno><catchline>Districts; assumption of assets and liabilities; apportionment; taxes; special fund.</catchline><para>(1) Each district established pursuant to section 2-3203 shall assume, on July 1, 1972, all assets, liabilities, and obligations of any soil and water conservation district, watershed conservancy district, watershed district, advisory watershed improvement board, and watershed planning board, whose territory is included within the boundaries of such natural resources district. When the jurisdiction of any soil and water conservation district, watershed conservancy district, watershed district, advisory watershed improvement board, or watershed planning board, is included within two or more natural resources districts, the commission shall determine the apportionment of any assets, liabilities, and obligations. Such apportionment shall be based on the proportionate land area included in each district. Physical assets attached to the land shall be assumed by the district in which they are located. The value of attached physical assets shall be considered in the apportionment of the assets, liabilities and obligations, and any such assets may be encumbered or otherwise liquidated by the assuming district to effect the proper apportionment. When any other special-purpose district is merged with a natural resources district as contemplated by section 2-3201 and in the manner provided in sections 2-3207 to 2-3212, the assets, liabilities, and obligations of such special-purpose district shall similarly be assumed by the natural resources district.</para><para>(2) All taxes levied in 1971 by the counties of this state pursuant to sections 2-1560 and 31-827 for watershed districts and watershed conservancy districts shall be treated as assets of such watershed districts and watershed conservancy districts and when funds are not available or paid to such districts on account of such levies until after July 1, 1972, such funds shall be paid to the order of the natural resources district or districts within the boundaries of which such watershed district or watershed conservancy district lies, and in the proportionate amounts as other assets are to be divided. Tax funds in possession of or payable to each watershed district and watershed conservancy district at the time of merger shall be put in a special fund of the natural resources district or districts receiving the assets of such watershed district or watershed conservancy district and such funds shall be expended within the boundaries of such watershed district or watershed conservancy district and for projects begun or planned by such districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 6, p. 104; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 544, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 543, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>