<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3951.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3951.04</statuteno><catchline>Board members; nominations; notification;
procedure.</catchline><para>(1) When nominations for board members are required,
written notification shall be given to each producer represented or to be
represented by such member,
including an at-large member. The first purchaser or purchasers
of milk shall notify each producer from whom the first purchaser buys milk
that each producer may submit written nominations. If the group represented
is a combination of first purchasers of milk and individual producer-processors or if the member is an at-large member,
the individual producer-processors shall receive notification from the Department
of Agriculture.</para>
<para>(2) Nominations shall be in writing and shall contain an acknowledgment
and consent by the producer being nominated. The nomination shall be returned
by the producer to the first purchaser of milk or to the department from whom
the producer received notification within fifteen days after the receipt of
the notification. For nominations to replace a member whose term is to expire
or for a new member, the producers shall receive notification between August
1 and August 15 preceding the expiration of the term of the member or the
beginning of the term of a new member. For all other vacancies, the producers
shall receive notification within thirty days after the member vacates his
or her position on the board or
within thirty days after the board calls for an at-large member or members
as provided in section 2-3951.02.</para>
<para>(3) The first purchasers of milk, the department, or the board shall submit
nominations to the Governor by September 30, in the case of term expiration
or new or at-large member,
or forty-five days after the member vacates his or her position for all other
vacancies. The Governor shall make the appointments within thirty days after
receipt of the nominations.</para>
<para>(4) All nominees shall meet the qualifications provided in section 2-3951.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 836, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB70, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>