
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id7">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" id="id9"  statutenumber="2-3226.11"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3226.11</statuteno><catchline>Flood protection and water quality
enhancement bonds; use of proceeds; certain projects; county board; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) The proceeds
of bonds issued pursuant to section 2-3226.10 shall be used to pay costs of
design, rights-of-way acquisition, and construction of multipurpose projects
and practices for storm water management within the natural resources district
issuing such bonds, including flood control and water quality. For purposes
of this section, flood control and water quality projects and practices include,
but are not limited to, low-impact development best management measures, flood
plain buyout, dams, reservoir basins, and levees. The proceeds of bonds issued
pursuant to section 2-3226.10 shall not be used to fund combined sewer separation
projects in a city of the metropolitan class. No project for which bonds are
issued under section 2-3226.10 shall include a reservoir or water quality
basin having a permanent pool greater than four hundred surface acres. Any
project having a permanent pool greater than twenty surface acres shall provide
for public access. </para>
<para>(2) A district
shall only convey real property that is acquired for a project described in
subsection (1) of this section by eminent domain proceedings pursuant to sections
76-704 to 76-724 to a political subdivision or an agency of state or federal
government.</para><para>(3)(a)
Prior to the issuing of bonds pursuant to section 2-3226.10 or expending funds
of a natural resources district encompassing a city of the metropolitan class
to pay costs of a reservoir or water quality basin project or projects greater
than twenty surface acres, a county board of the affected county may pass
a resolution stating that it does not approve of the construction of such
reservoir or water quality basin project or projects within its exclusive
zoning jurisdiction. The county board shall hold a public hearing and shall
vote on the resolution within ninety days after notice from the board of directors
of the natural resources district of its intent to issue bonds. </para>
<para>(b) No proceeds from bonds
issued pursuant to section 2-3226.10 or funds of a natural resources district
encompassing a city of the metropolitan class may be used to pay costs of
a reservoir or water quality basin project or projects greater than twenty
surface acres if the county board of the affected county passes such a resolution.</para>
<para>(c) Sections 2-3226.10
to 2-3226.14 do not (i) limit the authority of a natural resources district
with regard to reservoirs, water quality basin projects, or other projects
of less than twenty surface acres or (ii) prohibit use of funds of a natural
resources district for preliminary studies or reports necessary, in the discretion
of the board of directors of the natural resources district, to determine
whether a reservoir or water quality basin project should be presented to
a county board pursuant to this section.</para><para>(4) Proceeds of bonds issued pursuant to section 2-3226.10
shall not be used to fund any project in any city or county (a) located within
a watershed in which is located a city of the metropolitan class and (b) which
is party to an agreement under the Interlocal Cooperation Act, unless such
city or county has adopted a storm water management plan approved by the board
of directors of the natural resources district encompassing a city of the
metropolitan class.</para><para>(5)
A natural resources district encompassing a city of the metropolitan class
shall only issue bonds for projects in cities and counties that have adopted
zoning regulations or ordinances that comply with state and federal flood
plain management rules and regulations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB160, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>