<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="2-3225"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3225</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Districts; tax;
levies; limitation; use; collection.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Each
district shall have the power and authority to levy a tax of not to exceed
four and one-half cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable valuation annually
on all of the taxable property within such district unless a higher levy is
authorized pursuant to section 77-3444. </para>
<para>(b) Each district shall also have the power and authority
to levy a tax equal to the dollar amount by which its restricted funds budgeted
to administer and implement ground water management activities and integrated
management activities under the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection
Act exceed its restricted funds budgeted to administer and implement ground
water management activities and integrated management activities for FY2003-04,
not to exceed one cent on each one hundred dollars of taxable valuation annually
on all of the taxable property within the district.</para>
<para>(c) In addition to the power and authority granted in subdivisions
(1)(a) and (b) of this section, each district located in a river basin, subbasin,
or reach that has been determined to be fully appropriated pursuant to section
46-714 or designated overappropriated pursuant to section 46-713 by the Department
of Natural Resources shall also have the power and authority to levy a tax
equal to the dollar amount by which its restricted funds budgeted to administer
and implement ground water management activities and integrated management
activities under the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act exceed
its restricted funds budgeted to administer and implement ground water management
activities and integrated management activities for FY2005-06, not to exceed
three cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable valuation on all of the
taxable property within the district for fiscal year 2006-07 and each fiscal
year thereafter through fiscal year 2017-18.</para>
<para>(d) In addition to the power and authority granted in subdivisions
(a) through (c) of this subsection, a district with jurisdiction that includes
a river subject to an interstate compact among three or more states and that
also includes one or more irrigation districts within the compact river basin
may annually levy a tax not to exceed ten cents per one hundred dollars of
taxable valuation of all taxable property in the district. The proceeds of
such tax may be used for the payment of principal and interest on bonds and
refunding bonds issued pursuant to section 2-3226.01 or for the repayment
of financial assistance received by the district pursuant to section 2-3226.07.
Such levy is not includable in the computation of other limitations upon the
district's tax levy.</para>
<para>(2) The proceeds of the tax levies authorized in subdivisions
(1)(a) through (c) of this section shall be used, together with any other
funds which the district may receive from any source, for the operation of
the district. When adopted by the board, the tax levies authorized in subdivisions
(1)(a) through (d) of this section shall be certified by the secretary to
the county clerk of each county which in whole or in part is included within
the district. Such levy shall be handled by the counties in the same manner
as other levies, and proceeds shall be remitted to the district treasurer.
Such levy shall not be considered a part of the general county levy and shall
not be considered in connection with any limitation on levies of such counties.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 25, p. 115; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 540, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 577, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 110, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 148, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1226, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1094, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB400, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 46-701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Section (1)(d) of this section violates the prohibition against levying a property tax for state purposes found in Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 1A, and such provision is therefore unconstitutional. Garey v. Nebraska Dept. of Nat. Resources, 277 Neb. 149, 759 N.W.2d 919 (2009).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>