<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3328"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3328</statuteno><catchline>Private nonprofit corporation; transfer of program; conditions; Director of Agriculture; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If a private nonprofit corporation as described in section 2-3326 (a) is formed, (b) submits to the Director of Agriculture on or before August 1, 1995, copies of its articles of incorporation and bylaws which the director determines comply with subsection (1) of section 2-3327, (c) provides to the director written documentation showing that the corporation has been certified by the United Soybean Board as a qualified state soybean board, and (d) provides to the Director of Administrative Services a contractual guarantee that the corporation accepts and agrees to pay out of any funds available to it all existing and future liabilities of the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board which have not been extinguished prior to October 1, 1995, including unpaid bills and claims for goods and services, claims for refunds of fees and assessments, accrued salaries and benefits, unemployment compensation claims, and claims relating to wrongful action, and upon compliance with sections 2-3326 to 2-3328, the transfer of Nebraska's soybean industry development program from the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board to the private nonprofit corporation shall be arranged.</para><para>(2) The Director of Agriculture shall complete the review of the articles and bylaws not later than September 1, 1995. Upon determining that the articles and bylaws contain the items required by section 2-3327, the director shall so notify the corporation in writing and shall send a copy of the articles and bylaws to the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 434, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 692, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>