<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3408"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3408</statuteno><catchline>Commercially sold eggs and turkeys; fee; how computed and assessed.</catchline><para>(1) There shall be paid to the director a fee of not to exceed five cents per case upon all commercial eggs sold through commercial channels to carry out the intent and purposes of sections 2-3401 to 2-3416. The fee for commercial eggs produced in this state shall be paid by the egg producer who owns the eggs and shall be collected and remitted to the director by the first purchaser. The fee for commercial eggs produced outside of this state and sold in this state to retailers, wholesalers, distributors, or food purveyors shall be paid to the director by the person importing such eggs into the state. Under the provisions of sections 2-3401 to 2-3416, no eggs shall be subject to the fee more than once.</para><para>(2) There shall be paid to the director a fee of not to exceed three cents per turkey grown in the State of Nebraska and sold through commercial channels. The fee shall be paid by the turkey producer and shall be collected by the first purchaser. Under the provisions of sections 2-3401 to 2-3416, no turkeys shall be subject to the fee more than once.</para><para>(3) The director may, subject to the approval of a majority of the members of the advisory committee, whenever he or she determines that the fees provided by this section are yielding more than is required to carry out the intent and purposes of sections 2-3401 to 2-3416, reduce such fees for such period as the director shall deem justified. In the event that the director, after reducing such fees, finds that sufficient revenue is not being produced by such reduced fees, he or she may restore in full or in part such fees to such rates as will in his or her judgment produce sufficient revenue to carry out the intent and purposes of sections 2-3401 to 2-3416.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 514, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 991, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>