<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id27">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id29"  statutenumber="2-3290.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id31">2-3290.01</statuteno><catchline id="id32">Water project;
public use; public access; district; duties; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) A district shall permit public use of those portions of a water
project located on lands owned by the district and on land over which the
district has a lease or an easement permitting use thereof for public recreational
purposes. All recreational users of such portions of a water project shall
abide by the applicable rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the
board.</para>
<para>(2) The district shall provide public access for recreational
use at designated access points at any water project. Recreational users,
whether public or private, shall abide by all applicable rules and regulations
for use of the water project adopted and promulgated by the district or the
political subdivision in which the water project is located. Public recreational
users may only access the water project through such designated access points.
Nothing in this subsection shall require public access when the portion of
the project cost paid by the natural resources district with public funds
does not exceed twenty percent of the total cost of the project.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section, water project means a project with cooperators
or others, as authorized in section 2-3235, that results in construction of
a reservoir or other body of water having a permanent pool suitable for recreational
purposes greater than one hundred fifty surface acres, the construction of
which commenced after July 14, 2006. Water project shall not mean soil conservation
projects, wetlands projects, projects
described in section 2-3226.11, or other district projects with
cooperators or others that do not have a recreational purpose.</para>
<para>(4) For projects
funded under section 2-3226.11 that result in a reservoir or other body of
water having a permanent pool suitable for recreational purposes greater than
twenty surface acres, the district shall provide public access for recreational
use at designated access points and shall include access to the land area
a minimum distance of one hundred feet from the permanent pool. Recreational
users, whether public or private, shall abide by all applicable rules, regulations,
ordinances, or resolutions for use of the project adopted by the district
or the political subdivision in which the project is located. Public recreational
users may only access the project through such designated access points.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB160, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>