<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id101">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id103" statutenumber="2-3981"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3981</statuteno><catchline id="id106">Dairy plants,
milk for manufacturing purposes, and pickup tankers; quality tests; standards.</catchline><para>(1) All dairy plants using milk for manufacturing purposes
shall run the quality tests set out in this section in a state-certified laboratory
and report the results to the department upon request. The test methods shall
be those stated in laboratory procedures.</para>
<para>(2) Milk for manufacturing purposes shall be classified for
bacterial content by the standard plate count or plate loop count. Bacterial
count limits of individual producer milk shall not exceed five hundred thousand
per milliliter.</para>
<para>(3) Bacterial counts for milk for manufacturing purposes
shall be run at least four times in six consecutive months at irregular intervals
at times designated by the director on representative samples of each producer's
milk. Whenever any two out of four consecutive bacterial counts exceed five
hundred thousand per milliliter, the producer shall be sent a written notice
by the department. Such notice shall be in effect so long as two of the last
four consecutive samples exceed the limit of the standard set out in subsection (2) of this section.
A producer sample shall be taken between three and twenty-one days after the
second excessive count. If that sample indicates an excessive bacterial count,
the producer's milk shall be rejected until subsequent testing indicates a
bacterial count of five hundred thousand per milliliter or less.</para>
<para>(4) All standards and procedures of the Grade A Pasteurized
Milk Ordinance relating
to somatic cells shall apply to milk for manufacturing purposes.</para>
<para>(5) The industry shall test all producer's milk and bulk
milk pickup tankers for drug residues in accordance with Appendix N, Drug
Residue Testing and Farm Surveillance, of the Grade A Pasteurized Milk Ordinance.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 632, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 900, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 871, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 268, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 201, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 198, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 2-3917; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB111, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB67, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>