<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3327"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3327</statuteno><catchline>Transition to private nonprofit corporation; Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The private nonprofit corporation described in section 2-3326 seeking designation as a qualified state soybean board pursuant to the federal Soybean Promotion, Research, and Consumer Information Act of 1990, 7 U.S.C. 6301 et seq., shall have initial articles of incorporation and bylaws which include provisions providing that:</para><para>(a) The members of the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board serving immediately prior to October 1, 1995, become the initial directors of the corporation and shall serve until their terms would have expired pursuant to the Nebraska Soybean Resources Act;</para><para>(b) Except for the election of an at-large member who shall be elected by the board, elections of subsequent members of the board of directors of the corporation shall be by districts to provide adequate representation of producers and such elections will be conducted by the Cooperative Extension Service of the University of Nebraska pursuant to a contract with the corporation, which contract provides for use of absentee ballots in the election;</para><para>(c) Any employee of the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board immediately prior to October 1, 1995, becomes, at the option of the employee, an employee of the corporation on October 1, 1995;</para><para>(d) The financial records of the corporation are audited annually by a certified public accountant in accordance with any requirements of the federal Soybean Promotion, Research, and Consumer Information Act of 1990, 7 U.S.C. 6301 et seq., and any regulations under such act;</para><para>(e) The duties of the corporation are the duties provided for a qualified state soybean board under the federal Soybean Promotion, Research, and Consumer Information Act of 1990, 7 U.S.C. 6301 et seq., or any substantially similar successor federal act which provides for an assessment on the marketing of soybeans for purposes similar to the purposes provided in the federal Soybean Promotion, Research, and Consumer Information Act of 1990;</para><para>(f) The corporation assumes all existing and future liabilities of the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board;</para><para>(g) The expenditure of any funds paid or transferred to the corporation will be used in a manner consistent with the original purposes of the Nebraska Soybean Resources Act;</para><para>(h) The corporation submits quarterly reports to the Auditor of Public Accounts detailing the expenditures of funds received or transferred to it from the state until all the funds are expended; and</para><para>(i) Any amendment to the articles and bylaws of the corporation shall not become effective until approved by a two-thirds vote of the directors of the private nonprofit corporation.</para><para>(2) The Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Board shall:</para><para>(a) Utilize the existing appropriation to the Soybean Development, Utilization, and Marketing Fund to carry out its duties under the Nebraska Soybean Resources Act through September 30, 1995, and may contract with the private nonprofit corporation for transitional programs and services in addition to the contracts authorized under section 2-3311;</para><para>(b) Contract for the transfer of furniture, equipment, and other property from the board to the corporation; and</para><para>(c) Transfer all books, files, and records from the board to the corporation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 434, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>