
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id5" statutenumber="2-3965"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3965</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Act, how cited; provisions adopted by reference; copies.</catchline><para>(1) Sections 2-3965 to 2-3992 and the publications adopted by reference in subsections (2) and (3) of this section shall be known and may be cited as the Nebraska Milk Act.</para><para>(2) The Legislature adopts by reference the following official documents of the National Conference on Interstate Milk Shipments as published by the United States Department of Health and Human Services, United States Public Health Service/Food and Drug Administration:</para><para>(a) Grade A Pasteurized Milk Ordinance, 2017 Revision, as delineated in subsection (3) of this section;</para><para>(b) Methods of Making Sanitation Ratings of Milk Shippers, 2017 Revision;</para><para>(c) Procedures Governing the Cooperative State-Public Health Service/Food and Drug Administration Program of the National Conference on Interstate Milk Shipments, 2017 Revision; and</para><para>(d) Evaluation of Milk Laboratories, 2017 Revision.</para><para>(3) All provisions of the Grade A Pasteurized Milk Ordinance, 2017 Revision, including footnotes relating to requirements for cottage cheese, and the appendixes with which the ordinance requires mandatory compliance are adopted with the following exceptions:</para><para>(a) Section 9 of the ordinance is replaced by section 2-3969;</para><para>(b) Section 15 of the ordinance is replaced by section 2-3970;</para><para>(c) Section 16 of the ordinance is replaced by section 2-3974;</para><para>(d) Section 17 of the ordinance is not adopted;</para><para>(e) Section 3 of the ordinance, Administrative Procedures, Issuance of Permits, is adopted with the following modifications:</para><para>(i) The department may suspend a permit for a definite period of time or place the holder of a permit on probation upon evidence of violation by the holder of any of the provisions of the Nebraska Milk Act; and</para><para>(ii) Decisions of the department may be appealed and such appeals shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act; and</para><para>(f) Section 1 of the ordinance, Definitions, is adopted except for paragraph DD.</para><para>(4) Copies of the Ordinance, the Appendixes, and the publications, adopted by reference, shall be filed in the offices of the Secretary of State, Clerk of the Legislature, and Department of Agriculture. The copies filed with the Clerk of the Legislature shall be filed electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 632, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 900, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 856, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 366, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 201, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 198, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 2-3901; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB67, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB333, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>