<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3235"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3235</statuteno><catchline>Districts; cooperation; agreements; authorized; contributions; materials and services to landowners; terms.</catchline><para>(1) Each district shall have the power and authority to cooperate with or to enter into agreements with and, within the limits of appropriations available, to furnish financial or other aid to any cooperator, any agency, governmental or otherwise, or any owner or occupier of lands within the district for the carrying out of projects for benefit of the district as authorized by law, subject to such conditions as the board may deem necessary.</para><para>(2) As a condition to the extending of any benefits to or the performance of work upon any lands not owned or controlled by this state or any of its agencies, the directors may require contributions in money, services, materials, or otherwise to any operations conferring such benefits and may require landowners to enter into and perform such agreements or covenants as to the permanent use of such lands as will tend to prevent or control erosion thereon.</para><para>(3) Each district may make available, on such terms as it shall prescribe, to landowners within the district specialized equipment, materials, and services which are not readily available from other sources and which will assist such landowners to carry on operations upon their lands for the conservation of soil and water resources and for the prevention and control of soil erosion. Whenever reasonably possible, purchases or contracts for such equipment shall be made from retail establishments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 35, p. 123; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 15, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 480, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 436, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 891, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>This section gives a natural resources district express authority to cooperate, enter agreements, and furnish aid to private developers and landowners to carry out projects that benefit the district. Japp v. Papio-Missouri River NRD, 273 Neb. 779, 733 N.W.2d 551 (2007).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>