<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id112">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id114" statutenumber="2-3982"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3982</statuteno><catchline id="id117">Classification
for sediment content; sediment standards; determination; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Milk for manufacturing purposes shall be classified for
sediment content, regardless of the results of the appearance and odor examination
described in section 2-3980, according to sediment standards as follows:</para>
<para>(a) No. 1: Acceptable, not to exceed fifty-hundredths milligrams
or its equivalent;</para>
<para>(b) No. 2: Acceptable, not to exceed one and fifty-hundredths
milligrams or its equivalent;</para>
<para>(c) No. 3: Probational, not over ten days, not to exceed
two and fifty-hundredths milligrams or its equivalent; and</para>
<para>(d) No. 4: Reject, over two and fifty-hundredths milligrams
or its equivalent.</para>
<para>(2) Methods for determining the sediment content of the milk
of individual producers shall be the methods described in 7 C.F.R. 58.134,
as such section existed on July 1, 2011.</para>
<para>(3) Sediment testing shall be performed at least four times
every six months at irregular intervals as designated by the director.</para>
<para>(4) If the sediment disc is classified as No. 1, No. 2, or
No. 3, the producer's milk may be accepted. If the sediment disc is classified
as No. 4, the milk shall be rejected. A producer's milk that is classified
as No. 3 may be accepted for a period not to exceed ten calendar days. If
at the end of ten days the producer's milk does not meet acceptable sediment
classification No. 1 or No. 2, it shall be rejected from the market. If the
sediment disc is classified as No. 4, the milk shall be rejected and no further
shipments accepted unless the milk meets the requirements of No. 3 or better.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 900, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 268, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 198, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 2-3917.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB111, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB67, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>