<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3215"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3215</statuteno><catchline>Board; vacancy; how filled.</catchline>
<para>(1) In addition
to the events listed in section 32-560, a vacancy on the board shall exist
in the event of the removal from the district or subdistrict of any director.
After notice and hearing, a vacancy shall also exist in the event of the absence
of any director from more than two consecutive regular meetings of the board
unless such absences are excused by a majority of the remaining board members.</para>
<para>(2) In the event of a vacancy
from any of such causes or otherwise, the board of directors shall give notice
of the date the vacancy occurred, the office vacated, and the length of the
unexpired term (a) in writing to the Secretary of State and (b) to the public
by a notice published in a newspaper of general circulation within the district
or by posting in three public places in the district. The vacancy
shall be filled by the board of directors. The person so appointed shall have
the same qualifications as the person whom he or she succeeds. Such appointments
shall be in writing and until a successor is elected
and qualified. The written appointment shall be filed with the Secretary of
State.</para>
<para>(3)(a) If the vacancy
occurs during the first year of the unexpired term or prior to August 1 of
the second year of the unexpired term, the appointee shall serve until the
first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January next succeeding the next
regular general election and at such regular general election a director shall
be elected to succeed the appointee and serve the remainder of the unexpired
term.</para><para>(b)
If the vacancy occurs on or after August 1 of the second year of the unexpired
term or during the third or fourth year of the unexpired term, the appointee
shall serve until the term expires.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 15, p. 112; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 543, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 569, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1045, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 460; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB154, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>