<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3502</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in the Nebraska Graded Egg Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Consumer shall mean any person who buys shell eggs for his or her own consumption and not for resale;</para><para>(2) Department shall mean the Department of Agriculture;</para><para>(3) Director shall mean the Director of Agriculture;</para><para>(4) Egg handler shall mean any person who engages in any business in commerce which involves buying or selling any shell eggs or processing any shell egg products. Egg handler shall include, but not be limited to, persons who assemble, collect, break, process, grade, package, or wholesale shell eggs;</para><para>(5) Exterior condition of a shell egg shall mean the cleanliness and shape of the shell of the egg and whether the shell is whole or is broken or cracked;</para><para>(6) Food purveyors shall mean all restaurants, cafeterias, institutions, hotels, and other establishments where shell eggs are offered for sale to consumers for immediate consumption, either in the shell or in processed form;</para><para>(7) Graded eggs shall mean shell eggs which have been graded as to quality and classified as to weight according to the Nebraska Graded Egg Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under such act;</para><para>(8) Interior condition of a shell egg shall mean the condition of the yolk, the white, and the air cell of the shell egg;</para><para>(9) Producer shall mean any person engaged in the production of shell eggs in the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(10) Retailer shall mean any person who sells shell eggs to the consumer;</para><para>(11) Sell shall include offer, expose, or have in possession for sale, exchange, barter, or trade;</para><para>(12) Shell eggs shall mean eggs of the domesticated chicken; and</para><para>(13) Shell egg packer shall mean any person engaged in the sorting of eggs from sources other than or in addition to his or her own production, into their various qualities, either mechanically or by other means.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 268, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 871, &#167; 7.</para></source></law></legaldoc>