<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3254.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3254.03</statuteno><catchline>Improvement project; financed with bonds; requirements; warrants issued; when.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to awarding contracts for work in connection with any project the board proposes to finance in whole or in part by improvement project area bonds issued pursuant to section 2-3254.02, there shall be placed on file with the board an engineer's estimate of the total cost of such project. After any award of a contract for any such project, there shall be placed on file with the board a revised engineer's estimate of the total cost of that part of such project for which an award has been made. Such revised estimate shall be based upon the prices provided for in such contract. The revised estimate shall specifically state the estimated total cost of that part of the project for which awards have been made and which relates to that portion of the project which will result in special benefits to an area.</para><para>(2) For the purpose of making partial payments as the work progresses, warrants may be issued by the district. Such warrants shall not be issued in an amount which exceeds the engineer's revised estimate for that part of the project for which awards have been made and which relates to that portion of the project which will result in special benefits to an area. Such warrants shall become due and payable not later than five years from the date of their issuance and shall draw interest at a rate fixed by the board and stated in such warrants from the date of presentation for registration and payment. The warrants shall be redeemed and paid from the proceeds of special assessments, from the sale of bonds issued and sold as provided for in section 2-3254.02, or from other available funds of the district, including proceeds from the tax levied pursuant to section 2-3225. The district may agree to pay annual or semiannual interest on all warrants issued by the district, and may issue warrants to pay such interest or issue warrants in return for cash to pay such interest. If determined appropriate by the board, the district may pay fees to fiscal agents in connection with the placement of warrants or bonds issued by the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 388, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>