<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3214"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3214</statuteno><catchline>Board of directors; nomination; election; subdistricts; oath.</catchline><para>(1) District directors shall be elected as provided in section 32-513. Elections shall be conducted as provided in the Election Act. Registered voters residing within the district shall be eligible for nomination as candidates for any at-large position or, in those districts that have established subdistricts, as candidates from the subdistrict within which they reside.</para><para>(2) The board of directors may choose to: (a) Nominate candidates from subdistricts and from the district at large who shall be elected by the registered voters of the entire district; (b) nominate and elect each candidate from the district at large; or (c) nominate and elect candidates from subdistricts of substantially equal population except that any at-large candidate would be nominated and elected by the registered voters of the entire district. Unless the board of directors determines that the nomination and election of all directors will be at large, the board shall strive to divide the district into subdistricts of substantially equal population, except that no subdistrict shall have a population greater than three times the population of any other subdistrict within the district. Such subdistricts shall be consecutively numbered and shall be established with due regard to all factors including, but not limited to, the location of works of improvement and the distribution of population and taxable values within the district. The boundaries and numbering of such subdistricts shall be designated at least six months prior to the primary election. Unless the district has been divided into subdistricts with substantially equal population, all directors shall be elected by the registered voters of the entire district and all registered voters shall vote on the candidates representing each subdistrict and any at-large candidates. If a district has been divided into subdistricts with substantially equal population, the board of directors may determine that directors shall be elected only by the registered voters of the subdistrict except that an at-large director may be elected by registered voters of the entire district.</para><para>(3) Except in districts which have chosen to have a single director serve from each subdistrict, the number of subdistricts for a district shall equal a number which is one less than a majority of directors for the district. In districts which have chosen to have a single director serve from each subdistrict, the number of subdistricts shall equal a number which is equal to the total number of directors of the district or which is one less than the total number of directors for the district if there is an at-large candidate. If the number of directors to be elected exceeds the number of subdistricts or if the term of the at-large director expires in districts which have chosen to have a single director serve from each subdistrict, candidates may file as a candidate from the district at large. Registered voters may each cast a number of votes not larger than the total number of directors to be elected.</para><para>(4) Elected directors shall take their oath of office in the same manner provided for county officials.</para><para>(5) At least six months prior to the primary election, the board of directors may choose to have a single director serve from each subdistrict.</para><para>(6) The board of directors shall certify to the Secretary of State and the election commissioners or county clerks the number of directors to be elected at each election and the length of their terms as provided in section 32-404.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 9, &#167; 14, p. 110; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 543, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 641, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 302, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 148, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 459; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 480, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB285, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB287, &#167; 2. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>