<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id6" statutenumber="2-32,101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">2-32,101</statuteno><catchline id="id9">District; recreation
area; enforcement; procedures;
expenditure of funds for services or contracts, authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any
law enforcement officer, including, but not limited to, any Game and Parks
Commission conservation officer, local police officer, member of the Nebraska
State Patrol, or sheriff or deputy sheriff, is authorized to enforce sections
2-3292 to 2-32,100 and any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant
to such sections. A district shall not employ law enforcement personnel and
shall be prohibited from expending any funds for such purpose except as provided in subsection (2) of this section.
Each district shall provide a copy of its rules and regulations to the appropriate
law enforcement officer. Any law enforcement officer may arrest and detain
any person committing a violation of the rules and regulations in a recreation
area or committing any misdemeanor or felony as provided by the laws of this
state.</para>
<para>(2) A district
may expend funds to enter into agreements pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation
Act for the services of certified law enforcement personnel or to contract
for the services of private security services to patrol and protect district-owned
or district-managed recreation areas and to assist law enforcement officers
in enforcing sections 2-3292 to 2-32,100 and any rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated pursuant to such sections.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 861, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 391; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB817, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>