
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id5" statutenumber="2-3226.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3226.01</statuteno><catchline id="id8">River-flow enhancement
bonds; authorized; natural resources districts; powers and duties; acquisition
of water rights by purchase or lease; agreements; contents.</catchline><para>(1)
In order to implement its duties and obligations under the Nebraska Ground
Water Management and Protection Act and in addition to other powers authorized
by law, the board of a district with jurisdiction that is part of a river
basin for which the district has, in accordance with section 46-715, adopted
an integrated management plan which references section 2-3226.04 and explicitly
states its intent in the plan to utilize qualified projects described in section
2-3226.04 may issue negotiable bonds and refunding bonds of the district and
entitled river-flow enhancement bonds, with terms determined appropriate by
the board, payable by (a) funds granted to such district by the state or federal
government for one or more qualified projects, (b) the occupation tax authorized
by section 2-3226.05, or (c) the levy authorized by section 2-3225. The district
may issue the bonds or refunding bonds directly, or such bonds may be issued
by any joint entity as defined in section 13-803 whose member public agencies
consist only of qualified natural resources districts or by any joint public
agency as defined in section 13-2503 whose participating public agencies consist
only of qualified natural resources districts, in connection with any joint
project which is to be owned, operated, or financed by the joint entity or
joint public agency for the benefit of its member natural resources districts.
For the payment of such bonds or refunding bonds, the district may pledge
one or more permitted payment sources.</para>
<para>(2) Within forty-five days after receipt of a written request by the
Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature, the qualified natural resources
districts shall submit an electronic report to the
committee containing an explanation of existing or planned activities for
river-flow enhancement, the revenue source for implementing such activities,
and a description of the estimated benefit or benefits to the district or
districts.</para>
<para>(3) If a
district uses the proceeds of a bond issued pursuant to this section for the
purposes described in subdivision (1) of section 2-3226.04 or the state uses
funds for those same purposes, the agreement to acquire water rights by purchase
or lease pursuant to such subdivision shall identify (a) the method of payment,
(b) the distribution of funds by the party or parties receiving payments,
(c) the water use or rights subject to the agreement, and (d) the water use
or rights allowed by the agreement. If any irrigation district is party to
the agreement, the irrigation district shall allocate funds received under
such agreement among its users or members in a reasonable manner, giving consideration
to the benefits received and the value of the rights surrendered for the specified
contract period.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1094, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB862, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 46-701.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>