<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3519"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3519</statuteno><catchline>Shell eggs; sampling; procedures; seizure; ordered off sale; when; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to prescribe methods of selecting samples of lots or containers of shell eggs which shall be reasonably calculated to produce by such sampling fair representations of the entire lots or containers sampled. Any sample so taken shall be prima facie evidence, in any court in this state, of the true condition of the entire lot in the examination of which such sample was taken. Insofar as practicable, the methods of sampling prescribed in the rules and regulations shall be the same as those prescribed by the United States Department of Agriculture under the Egg Products Inspection Act.</para><para>(2) The department, through its agents, may enter any premises within the state where shell eggs are held, during ordinary business hours, and may inspect representative samples of such eggs and containers for the purpose of determining whether or not any provision of the Nebraska Graded Egg Act has been violated.</para><para>(3) Any agent of the department may, while enforcing the Nebraska Graded Egg Act, seize and hold for evidence any shell eggs held to be in violation of any provisions of the act.</para><para>(4) Any shell eggs found by agents of the department to be in violation of the Nebraska Graded Egg Act may be ordered off sale by the department. Further disposition of such eggs shall only be in accordance with the written or oral permission of the department, except that the department shall release all shell eggs ordered off sale which have been brought into conformity with the act.</para><para>(5) Any person affected by action taken by the department under subsection (3) or (4) of this section shall be advised that such person may request in writing, within ten days of such action, a hearing before the director or his or her designated representative on such action. The department shall proceed to hearing within seventy-two hours after receiving the written request. If no written request for hearing is filed within the ten days, the department's action shall be sustained.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 268, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 871, &#167; 13.</para></source></law></legaldoc>