<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-3987"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-3987</statuteno><catchline>Milkhouse or milkroom; sanitation requirements.</catchline><para>A milkhouse or milkroom at a facility producing milk for manufacturing purposes shall be conveniently located and properly constructed, lighted, and ventilated for handling and cooling milk in farm bulk tanks. The milkhouse or milkroom shall meet the following requirements:</para><para>(1) Adequate natural or artificial lighting shall be provided for conducting milkhouse or milkroom operations. Light fixtures shall not be installed directly above farm bulk milk tanks in areas where milk is drained or in areas where equipment is washed or stored. A minimum of thirty footcandles of light intensity shall be provided where the equipment is washed. All artificial lighting shall be from permanent fixtures;</para><para>(2) Adequate ventilation shall be provided to prevent odors and condensation on walls and ceilings;</para><para>(3) The milkhouse or milkroom shall be used for no other purpose;</para><para>(4) Adequate facilities for washing and storing milking equipment shall be provided in the milkhouse or milkroom. Only C-I-P equipment shall be stored in the milking area or milking parlor. Hot and cold running water under pressure shall be provided in the milkhouse or milkroom;</para><para>(5) If the milkhouse or milkroom is part of the milking facility or other building, it shall be partitioned and sealed to prevent the entrance of dust, flies, or other contamination. Walls, floors, and ceilings shall be kept clean and in good repair;</para><para>(6) Feed concentrates, if stored in the building, shall be kept in a tightly covered box or bin;</para><para>(7) The floor of the building shall be of concrete or other impervious material and graded to provide drainage;</para><para>(8) All doors in the milkhouse or milkroom shall be self-closing. Outer screen doors shall open outward and be maintained in good repair;</para><para>(9) No animals shall be allowed in the milkhouse or milkroom;</para><para>(10) A farm bulk tank shall be properly located in the milkhouse or milkroom for access to all areas for cleaning and servicing. It shall not be located over a floor drain or under a ventilator or a light fixture;</para><para>(11) A suitable hoseport opening shall be provided in the milkhouse or milkroom for hose connections and the hoseport shall be fitted with a tight-fitting door which shall be kept closed except when the port is in use. An easily cleanable surface shall be constructed under the hoseport adjacent to the outside wall large enough to protect the milkhose from contamination;</para><para>(12) The truck approach to the milkhouse or milkroom shall be properly graded and surfaced to prevent mud or pooling of water at the point of loading. It shall not pass through any livestock holding area;</para><para>(13) All windows, if designed to be opened, shall be adequately screened;</para><para>(14) Surroundings shall be neat, clean, and free of harborage and pooled water; and</para><para>(15) Handwashing facilities shall be provided which shall include soap, single-service towels, running water under pressure, a sink, and a covered refuse container.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 5, &#167; 13, p. 75; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 81-263.99; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 632, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 333, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 900, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 38, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 268, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1997), &#167; 2-3923; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB111, &#167; 23.</para></source></law></legaldoc>