<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4326" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4326</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Director; department; enforcement; orders; seizure of material; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) When the director has reasonable cause to believe agricultural liming materials are being sold in violation of the Agricultural Liming Materials Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act, he or she may issue and enforce a written or printed stop-sale, stop-use, or removal order to the owner or custodian of any lot of agricultural liming material. The department may order the owner or custodian to hold such material at a designated place when the department finds such material is being offered or exposed for sale by the owner or custodian in violation of the act or the rules and regulations. Such material shall be released when the act or the rules and regulations have been complied with, such violations have otherwise been legally disposed of in writing, and all costs and expense incurred in connection with such material's holding have been paid. This section shall not apply if the owner or custodian is the ultimate consumer of the agricultural liming material and he or she has title to such materials.</para><para>(2) Any agricultural liming materials not in compliance with the act or the rules and regulations shall be subject to seizure on complaint of the director to a court of competent jurisdiction in the area in which the agricultural liming materials are located. If the court finds the agricultural liming materials to be in violation of the act or the rules and regulations and orders the condemnation of the agricultural liming materials, such agricultural liming materials shall be disposed of in any manner consistent with the quality of the agricultural liming materials and the laws of the State of Nebraska. The court shall not order disposition without first giving the claimant an opportunity to apply to the court for release of the agricultural liming materials or for permission to process or relabel such product to bring it into compliance with the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 396, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 539, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 871, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB92, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>