<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id5" statutenumber="2-4901"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">2-4901</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Climate Assessment
Response Committee; created; members; expenses; meetings.</catchline><para>(1) The Climate Assessment Response Committee is hereby created.
The office of the Governor shall be the lead agency and shall oversee the
committee and its activities. The committee shall be composed of representatives
appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature
from livestock producers, crop producers, the
Nebraska Emergency Management Agency, and
the Conservation and Survey Division and Cooperative Extension
Service of the University of Nebraska. The
Director of Agriculture or his or her designee, the chief executive officer
of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee, and
the Director of Natural Resources or his or her designee shall be ex officio
members of the committee. Representatives from the federal Consolidated Farm Service
Agency and Federal Crop Insurance Corporation may also serve on the committee
at the invitation of the Governor. The chairperson of the Committee on Agriculture of
the Legislature and the chairperson of the Committee on Natural Resources
of the Legislature shall be nonvoting, ex officio members
of the committee. The Governor may appoint a member of the Governor's Policy
Research Office and any other state agency representatives or
invite any other federal agencies to name representatives as he or she deems
necessary. The Governor shall appoint one of the Climate Assessment Response
Committee members to serve as the chairperson of the committee. Committee
members shall be reimbursed for actual and necessary expenses as provided
in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
<para>(2) The committee shall meet at least twice each year and
shall meet more frequently (a) at the call of the chairperson, (b) upon request
of a majority of the committee members, and (c) during periods of drought
or other severe climate situations.</para>
<para>(3) The chairperson may establish subcommittees and may invite
representatives of agencies other than those with members on the committee
to serve on such subcommittees.</para>
<para>(4) Any funds for the activities of the committee and for
other climate-related expenditures may be appropriated directly to the office
of the Governor for contracting with other agencies or persons for tasks approved
by the committee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 274, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 403, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB389, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>