
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4403"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4403</statuteno><catchline>Farm; farm operation; public grain warehouse; public grain warehouse operation; not a nuisance; when; suit; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) A farm or farm operation or a public grain warehouse or public grain warehouse operation shall not be found to be a public or private nuisance if the farm or farm operation or public grain warehouse or public grain warehouse operation existed before a change in the land use or occupancy of land in and about the locality of such farm or farm operation or public grain warehouse or public grain warehouse operation and before such change in land use or occupancy of land the farm or farm operation or public grain warehouse or public grain warehouse operation would not have been a nuisance.</para><para>(2) No suit shall be maintained against a farm or farm operation or public grain warehouse or public grain warehouse operation for public or private nuisance more than two years after the condition which is the subject matter of the suit reaches a level of offense sufficient to sustain a claim of nuisance.</para><para>(3) The limitation provided for in this section shall not apply to any action brought to determine compliance with or to enforce a previous order of a court related to the same claim of nuisance or to any claims for additional damages or equitable relief available when a farm or farm operation or public grain warehouse or public grain warehouse operation fails to remediate a nuisance pursuant to such court order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 668, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1193, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB227, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>This section, as amended by 1998 Neb. Laws, LB1193, contains no language evidencing an intent that it should be applied retrospectively and thus operates prospectively only. Soukop v. ConAgra, Inc., 264 Neb. 1015, 653 N.W.2d 655 (2002).</para><para>The Nebraska Right to Farm Act applies only where there has been a change in land use or occupancy of land in and about the locality of such farm or farm operation, not where the change has taken place on the farm itself. Flansburgh v. Coffey, 220 Neb. 381, 370 N.W.2d 127 (1985).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>