<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4006</statuteno><catchline>Board; membership districts; meeting; appoint member; elect officers.</catchline><para>(1) One member shall be appointed from each of the following districts:</para><para>(a) District 1: The counties of Gage, Johnson, Nemaha, Pawnee, and Richardson;</para><para>(b) District 2: The counties of Lancaster, Cass, and Otoe;</para><para>(c) District 3: The counties of Nuckolls, Thayer, Jefferson, and Saline;</para><para>(d) District 4: The counties of Clay, Fillmore, Hamilton, York, and Seward;</para><para>(e) District 5: The counties of Buffalo, Hall, Merrick, Polk, Butler, Saunders, Sarpy, Douglas, Platte, Colfax, Dodge, Washington, Burt, Cuming, Stanton, Madison, Boone, Nance, Howard, Greeley, Sherman, Valley, Custer, Blaine, Loup, Garfield, Wheeler, Antelope, Pierce, Wayne, Thurston, Dakota, Dixon, Cedar, Knox, Holt, Boyd, Rock, Brown, and Keya Paha; and</para><para>(f) District 6: The counties of Dawson, Dundy, Hitchcock, Red Willow, Furnas, Harlan, Franklin, Webster, Adams, Kearney, Phelps, Gosper, Frontier, Hayes, Chase, Perkins, Keith, Lincoln, Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Grant, Hooker, Thomas, Cherry, Kimball, Cheyenne, Deuel, Scotts Bluff, Banner, Morrill, Garden, Sioux, Box Butte, Sheridan, and Dawes.</para><para>(2) Within thirty days after the appointment of the initial board, such board shall conduct its first regular meeting. At this meeting, the board shall appoint the seventh member to the board. Such appointment shall be made at large and the appointee shall meet the same qualifications as the other members on the board.</para><para>(3) The board shall elect from its members a chairperson, treasurer, and such other officers as may be necessary. The term of office for members of the board shall be for three years, except that the term of the members of the board first taking office shall be for one, two, or three years as determined by lot.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 11, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>