<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4608"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4608</statuteno><catchline>Excessive soil erosion; complaint; inspection; remedial action; failure to comply.</catchline><para>(1) Except to the extent jurisdiction has been assumed by a municipality or county in accordance with section 2-4606, the district may inspect or cause to be inspected any land within the district upon receipt of a written and signed complaint which alleges that soil erosion is occurring in excess of the applicable soil-loss limit. Complaints shall be filed on a form provided by the director. Complaints may be filed by any owner or operator of land being damaged by sediment, by any state agency or political subdivision whose roads or other public facilities are being damaged by sediment, by any state agency or political subdivision with responsibility for water quality maintenance if it is alleged that the soil erosion complained of is adversely affecting water quality, or by a staff member or other agent of the district authorized by the board of directors to file such complaints. Inspections following receipt of a written and signed complaint may be made only after notice to the owner and, if appropriate, the operator of the land involved, and such person shall be given an opportunity to accompany the inspector.</para><para>(2) The owner, the operator if appropriate, and the district may agree to a plan and schedule for eliminating excessive erosion on and sedimentation from the land involved. Any such agreement may be enforced in district court in the same manner as an administrative order issued pursuant to the Erosion and Sediment Control Act. If no agreement is reached, the findings of the inspection shall be presented to the district board of directors and the owner and, if appropriate, the operator of the land shall be given a reasonable opportunity to be heard at a meeting of the board or, if requested, at a public hearing. If the district finds that the alleged sediment damage is occurring and that excess soil erosion is occurring on the land inspected, it shall issue an administrative order to the owner of record and, if appropriate, to the operator describing the land and stating as nearly as possible the extent to which the soil erosion exceeds the applicable soil-loss limit. When the complained-of erosion is the result of agricultural, horticultural, or silvicultural activities, the district shall direct the owner and, if appropriate, the operator to bring the land into conformance with the applicable soil-loss limit. When the complained-of erosion is the result of a nonagricultural land-disturbing activity, the district may authorize the owner and, if appropriate, the operator to either bring such land into conformance with the soil-loss limit or to prevent sediment resulting from excessive erosion from leaving such land.</para><para>(3) The district may specify, as applicable, alternative soil and water conservation practices or erosion or sediment control practices which the owner and, if appropriate, the operator may use to comply with the administrative order. A copy of the administrative order shall be delivered by either personal service or certified or registered mail to each person to whom it is directed and shall:</para><para>(a) In the case of erosion occurring on the site of any nonagricultural land-disturbing activity, state a reasonable time after service or mailing of the order when the work necessary to establish or maintain erosion or sediment control practices shall be commenced and the time, not more than forty-five days after service or mailing of the order, when the work shall be satisfactorily completed;</para><para>(b) In all other cases, state the time, not more than six months after service or mailing of the order, the work needed to establish or maintain the necessary soil and water conservation practices or permanent erosion control practices shall be commenced and the time, not more than one year after the service or mailing of the order, the work shall be satisfactorily completed, unless the requirements of the order are superseded by section 2-4610; and</para><para>(c) State any reasonable requirements regarding the operation, utilization, and maintenance of the practices to be installed, constructed, or applied.</para><para>(4) Upon failure to comply with the order, the owner or, if appropriate, the operator shall be deemed in violation of the Erosion and Sediment Control Act and subject to further actions as provided by such act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 474, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 594, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 480, &#167; 23.</para></source><annotation><para>A landowner, who was required to implement conservation measures on his land, did not have standing to sue a city in an inverse condemnation action where the city filed a complaint under this section but the natural resources district was responsible for prosecuting the complaint. Strom v. City of Oakland, 255 Neb. 210, 583 N.W.2d 311 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>