<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id00" statutenumber="2-4323"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4323</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Retailer licensee; tonnage report; inspection fee; additional administrative fee; department; powers; director; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Every retailer licensee shall file, not later than the last day of January and July of each year, a semiannual tonnage report on forms provided by the department, setting forth the number of net tons of each agricultural liming material sold in Nebraska during the preceding six-month period, which report shall cover the periods from July 1 to December 31 and January 1 to June 30, and such other information as the director shall deem necessary. All persons required to be licensed pursuant to the Agricultural Liming Materials Act shall file such report regardless of whether any inspection fee is due. Upon filing the report, such person shall pay the inspection fee at the rate prescribed pursuant to this section. The inspection fee shall be at the rate fixed by the director but not exceeding ten cents per ton. The fee shall be set at an amount to cover the expenses of the inspection provided in section 2-4325 and the costs of administering this section. The minimum inspection fee required pursuant to this section shall be five dollars, and no inspection fee shall be paid more than once for any one product. In the case of agricultural lime slurry, the fee shall be paid on the base lime material only.</para><para>(2) If a person fails to report and pay the fee required by subsection (1) of this section by January 31 and July 31, the fee shall be considered delinquent and the person owing the fee shall pay an additional administrative fee of twenty-five percent of the delinquent amount for each month it remains unpaid, not to exceed one hundred percent of the original amount due. The department may waive the additional administrative fee based upon the existence and extent of any mitigating circumstances that have resulted in the late payment of such fee. The purpose of the additional administrative fee is to cover the administrative costs associated with collecting fees, and all money collected as an additional administrative fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Fertilizers and Soil Conditioners Administrative Fund. Failure to make an accurate statement of tonnage or to pay the inspection fee or comply as provided in this subsection shall constitute sufficient cause for the cancellation of all product registrations or licenses on file for such person.</para><para>(3) The director shall annually make information available in such form as he or she may deem proper concerning the tons of agricultural liming material sold in this state. Such report shall in no way divulge the operation of any registrant or licensee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 396, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 539, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB92, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>February 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>