<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4004"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4004</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; membership districts; officers; terms; vacancy;
how filled.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall be composed of grower members who (a) are citizens of Nebraska,
(b) are at least twenty-one years of age, and (c) derive
a portion
of their income from growing grain sorghum. The Director of Agriculture and
the vice chancellor of the University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture
and Natural Resources shall be ex officio members of the board but shall have
no vote in board matters.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided
in section 2-4006 or 2-4007, the members shall be appointed as follows:</para>
<para>(a) One member shall
be appointed by the Governor from each of the following districts:</para>
<para>(i) District 1: The counties
of Cedar, Dixon, Dakota, Wayne, Thurston, Stanton, Cuming, Burt, Colfax, Dodge,
Washington, Douglas, Butler, Saunders, Sarpy, Seward, Saline, Lancaster, Cass,
Otoe, Jefferson, Gage, Johnson, Nemaha, Pawnee, and Richardson;</para>
<para>(ii) District 2: The
counties of Knox, Antelope, Pierce, Madison, Boone, Platte, Nance, Merrick,
Polk, Hamilton, York, Adams, Clay, Fillmore, Webster, Nuckolls, and Thayer;</para>
<para>(iii) District 3: The
counties of Keya Paha, Boyd, Brown, Rock, Holt, Blaine, Loup, Garfield, Wheeler,
Custer, Valley, Greeley, Sherman, Howard, Dawson, Buffalo, Hall, Gosper, Phelps,
Kearney, Furnas, Harlan, and Franklin; and</para><para>(iv) District 4: The counties of Sioux, Dawes, Box
Butte, Sheridan, Cherry, Scotts Bluff, Banner, Kimball, Morrill, Cheyenne,
Garden, Deuel, Grant, Hooker, Thomas, Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Keith, Perkins,
Lincoln, Chase, Hayes, Frontier, Dundy, Hitchcock, and Red Willow; and</para>
<para>(b) Three members shall
be appointed from the state at large, two of whom shall be appointed by the
Governor and one appointed by the board. When making at-large appointments,
the Governor and the board shall, to the extent practicable, seek to achieve
an equitable representation of grain sorghum producers in terms of the geographic
distribution of grain sorghum production in the state. No more than two at-large
members may reside in a single district as defined by subdivision (a) of this
subsection.</para><para>(3)
The board shall elect from its members a chairperson, treasurer, and such
other officers as may be necessary. Except as provided in section 2-4006,
the term of office for members of the board shall be three years and until
their successors are appointed and qualified.</para><para>(4) Whenever a vacancy occurs on the board for
any reason, the remaining board members shall appoint an individual to fill
such vacancy from the district in which the vacancy exists. If the vacant
position is that of an at-large member, the appointment
to fill such vacancy shall be made at large subject
to subdivision (2)(b) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 11, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB107, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
