
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4327" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4327</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Violations; penalty; written warning; Attorney General or county attorney; duties; enforcement; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Any person violating the Agricultural Liming Materials Act shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor upon the first conviction thereof, and a Class II misdemeanor for each subsequent conviction thereof.</para><para>(2) Nothing in the act shall be construed to require the director or his or her duly authorized agent to report a violation in order to prosecute or to institute seizure proceedings as a result of minor violations of the act when he or she believes that the public interest will best be served by a suitable written warning to the violator.</para><para>(3) The Attorney General or the county attorney of the county in which any violation occurs or is about to occur, when notified by the department of such violation or threatened violation, shall pursue appropriate proceedings pursuant to section 2-4326 or this section or both without delay.</para><para>(4) In order to insure compliance with the act, the department may apply for a restraining order, a temporary or permanent injunction, or a mandatory injunction against any person violating or threatening to violate the act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act. The district court of the county where the violation is occurring or is about to occur shall have jurisdiction to grant such relief upon good cause shown. Relief may be granted notwithstanding the existence of any other remedy at law and shall be granted without bond.</para><para>(5) Any person adversely affected by an action, order, or ruling made by the department pursuant to the act may appeal the action, order, or ruling, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 396, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB92, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>