<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4202"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4202</statuteno><catchline>Legislative policy.</catchline><para>It is hereby declared to be the policy of the Legislature to provide for the conservation and protection of the natural resources of this state through control and prevention of soil erosion, reduction of sediment damage, control of flood waters, enhancement of domestic water supply, improvement of water quality, and collection and containment of water. Within this state, the landowners involved in farm and ranch operations and the political subdivisions must be provided with financial assistance to encourage conservation of the state's water and related land resources. Without such conservation incentives, the control, containment, and utilization of our water resources and the productivity of our soil will be greatly threatened.</para><para>Assistance provided to landowners under the Conservation Corporation Act will enhance farm and ranch operations, one of the chief industries of this state, by protecting or enhancing agricultural productivity and will protect, preserve, and promote the source of food supplies to the citizens of this state. Assistance provided to political subdivisions under the Conservation Corporation Act will promote the general welfare of the citizens of such political subdivisions and further promote the productivity of business enterprises and the general health, welfare, and safety. The necessity for the Conservation Corporation Act to protect the health, safety, and general welfare of all people of this state is hereby declared as a matter of legislative determination.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 385, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 20, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 387, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>