<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4320"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4320</statuteno><catchline>Sale; label, statement, or delivery slip; information requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Agricultural liming materials sold, offered, or exposed for sale in this state by any manufacturer, distributor, or retailer shall have affixed to each package in a conspicuous manner on the outside of such package a plainly printed, stamped, or otherwise marked label, tag, or statement or, in the case of bulk sales, a delivery slip, setting forth the following information:</para><para>(a) The name and principal office address of the manufacturer or distributor;</para><para>(b) The brand or trade name of the material;</para><para>(c) The identification of the product as to the type of the agricultural liming material;</para><para>(d) The net weight of the agricultural liming material;</para><para>(e) The minimum effective calcium carbonate equivalent, which is a percentage of weight function of calcium carbonate equivalent and fineness as prescribed by the rules and regulations of the director; and</para><para>(f) The pounds of effective calcium carbonate per ton.</para><para>Additional information may also be listed on the package including the minimum percentage by weight of calcium carbonate and magnesium carbonate.</para><para>(2) No information or statement shall appear on any package, label, delivery slip, or advertising matter which is false or misleading to the purchaser as to the quality, analysis type, or composition of the agricultural liming material.</para><para>(3) In the case of any material which has been changed in any way as to render inaccurate or misleading any of the information required by subsection (1) of this section subsequent to its packaging, labeling, or loading and before its delivery to the consumer, a plainly marked notice of the change shall be affixed by the manufacturer, distributor, or retailer to the package or delivery slip to identify the kind and degree of such change in such package.</para><para>(4) At every site from which agricultural liming materials are delivered in bulk and at every place where consumer orders for bulk deliveries are placed, there shall be conspicuously posted a copy of the statements required by subsections (1) and (3) of this section for each brand of material.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 396, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 539, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>