<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-4610"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-4610</statuteno><catchline>Conformance with farm unit conservation plan or soil-loss limit; effect; lack of cost-sharing assistance; effect; cost-sharing assistance; availability.</catchline><para>(1) Any person owning or operating private agricultural, horticultural, or silvicultural lands who has a farm unit conservation plan approved by the district and is implementing and maintaining the plan in strict compliance with a conservation agreement or any person whose normal agricultural, horticultural, and silvicultural practices are in conformance with the applicable soil-loss limit shall, for purposes of such land, be deemed to be in compliance with the requirements of the Erosion and Sediment Control Act and any approved erosion and sediment control program.</para><para>(2) If there is not available to any owner or operator at least ninety percent cost-sharing assistance for the installation of permanent soil and water conservation practices which are required in an approved farm unit conservation plan or are required to conform agricultural, horticultural, and silvicultural practices to the applicable soil-loss limit, any such owner or operator shall not be required to install such practices pursuant to the Erosion and Sediment Control Act until such cost-sharing assistance is made available, except that such owner or operator may agree to a cost-share rate of less than ninety percent. To be enforceable, any agreement providing for cost-sharing assistance at a rate of less than ninety percent shall include notice that the owner or operator may choose not to sign such agreement and that such choice will preserve the right to not less than ninety percent cost-sharing assistance before any permanent soil and water conservation practices can be required by the district. The owner or operator may be required to utilize temporary soil and water conservation practices in the interim to minimize soil erosion and sediment damage.</para><para>(3) To prevent excessive erosion and sediment from leaving the land due to any nonagricultural land-disturbing activity, cost-sharing assistance may be available from any district. Such assistance may be used for any erosion or sediment control practice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 474, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 594, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 480, &#167; 24.</para></source></law></legaldoc>