<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-5504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-5504</statuteno><catchline>Railroad land; lease renewal; conditions; controversy; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except when an owner of railroad land has received a bona fide third-party offer to lease the property that the owner desires to accept, at the expiration of an existing lease, the agricultural tenant shall be given the opportunity to renew the lease at fair market lease rate. If a bona fide third-party offer has been made to lease the property that the owner desires to accept, then the agricultural tenant shall be given first opportunity for a period of thirty days after receipt of written notice of such third-party offer to renew the lease at a rate that is substantially equal in value to the third-party offer.</para><para>(2) All controversies regarding application and reasonableness of lease terms and conditions or fair market lease rate arising between a railroad or its successor in interest and an agricultural tenant who is the owner, lessee, or licensee of a substantial improvement situated on railroad land owned or controlled by the railroad or its successor in interest shall be resolved by negotiation or by Department of Agriculture action.</para><para>(3) The parties shall first negotiate in good faith to resolve any controversy. If any such controversy is not resolved within sixty days after notification is given to an agricultural tenant by a railroad or its successor in interest that it wishes to (a) renew a lease upon new terms, (b) terminate a lease, (c) not renew a lease upon the expiration of a current lease, or (d) change the terms of an existing lease, then either party may file a complaint with the department setting forth facts upon which such complaint is based.</para><para>(4) The department, after reasonable notice to the parties, shall hear and determine all matters in controversy and make such order as the facts of the controversy warrant. In conducting its hearing, the department shall have those powers granted to it under the Administrative Procedure Act. Any person shall have the right to appeal from such order in accordance with the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 435, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>