
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id114">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id116" statutenumber="2-5106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id118">2-5106</statuteno><catchline id="id119">Buffer Strip
Incentive Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The
Buffer Strip Incentive Fund is created. Proceeds raised from fees imposed
for the registration of pesticides and earmarked for the fund pursuant to
section 2-2634, proceeds raised from federal grants earmarked for the fund,
and any proceeds raised from public or private donations made to the fund
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. The fund
shall be administered by the department to maintain the buffer strip program
and for expenses directly related to the program, including necessary expenses
of the department in carrying out its duties and responsibilities under the
Buffer Strip Act, except that transfers may be made from the fund to
the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The annual
cost of administering the buffer strip program shall not exceed ten percent
of the total annual proceeds credited to the Buffer Strip Incentive Fund.
Such administrative costs shall include funds allocated by the department
to the districts for their administrative costs. Any money in the fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1126, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB98, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>