<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id4"><sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Agriculture" id="id6" statutenumber="2-5420"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">2-5420</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Application process; priority; restriction on use of grant funds.</catchline><para>(1) To be eligible for a grant under the Agricultural Opportunities and Value-Added Partnerships Act, an applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Document a matching amount in money or in-kind contributions or a combination of both equal to twenty-five percent of the grant funds requested, except that if the grant funds will be used to acquire or lease a building or equipment to be used in a farming or ranching operation or in a private enterprise, an applicant shall provide a matching amount in money and in-kind contribution of no less than fifty percent of the grant funds requested of which the matching amount in money shall be no less than twenty-five percent of the grant funds requested;</para><para>(b) Specify measurable goals and expected outcomes for the project for which the grant funds are requested; and</para><para>(c) Specify an evaluation and impact assessment process or procedure for the project for which the grant funds are requested.</para><para>(2) Priority for the awarding of grants may be given to applicants that provide a matching amount in money.</para><para>(3) Whenever grant funds are used to acquire or lease a building or equipment to be used in a farming or ranching operation or in a private enterprise, any removal from the state or resale of the building or equipment within three years after the date of award of the grant funds without the prior approval of the Department of Economic Development shall be deemed a utilization or diversion of grant funds to a purpose or expenditure not specified or contemplated in the application or terms of the award of the grant for purposes of section 2-5421.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 90, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB789, &#167; 1.</para><terminationdate>January 1, 2015</terminationdate></source>  </law></legaldoc>
