<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Agriculture" statutenumber="2-5002"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>2-5002</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 2-5002 to 2-5006:</para><para>(1) Aquaculture shall have the definition found in section 2-3804.01;</para><para>(2) Aquaculture facility shall mean any facility, structure, lake, pond, tank, or tanker truck used for the purpose of propagating, selling, brokering, trading, or transporting live fish or viable gametes;</para><para>(3) Aquaculturist shall mean any individual, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation, other than an employee of a state or federal hatchery, involved in producing, transporting, or marketing cultured aquatic stock or products thereof;</para><para>(4) Aquatic disease shall mean any departure from a normal state of health of aquatic organisms caused by disease agents;</para><para>(5) Aquatic organism shall mean an individual member of any species of fish, mollusk, crustacean, aquatic reptile, aquatic amphibian, aquatic insect, or other aquatic invertebrate. Aquatic organism shall include the viable gametes, eggs or sperm, of an aquatic organism;</para><para>(6) Board shall mean the Nebraska Aquaculture Board;</para><para>(7) Commercial aquaculturist shall mean an aquaculturist engaged in the business of growing, selling, brokering, or processing live or viable aquatic organisms for commercial purposes;</para><para>(8) Commission shall mean the Game and Parks Commission;</para><para>(9) Cultured aquatic stock shall mean aquatic organisms raised from privately owned stocks and aquatic organisms lawfully acquired and held in private ownership until they become intermingled with wild aquatic organisms;</para><para>(10) Department shall mean the Department of Agriculture; and</para><para>(11) Director shall mean the Director of Agriculture.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 830, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1165, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>