<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-664"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-664</statuteno><catchline>Benefits; false statements by employer; penalty; failure or refusal to make combined tax payment.</catchline><para>Any employer, whether or not subject to the Employment Security Law, or any officer or agent of such an employer or any other person who makes a false statement or representation knowing it to be false, or who knowingly fails to disclose a material fact, to prevent or reduce the payment of benefits to any individual entitled thereto, to obtain benefits for an individual not entitled thereto, to avoid becoming or remaining subject to such law, or to avoid or reduce any contribution or other payment required from an employer under sections 48-648 and 48-649 to 48-649.04, or who willfully fails or refuses to make any such contributions or other payment or to furnish any reports required under the Employment Security Law or to produce or permit the inspection or copying of records as required under such law, shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor. Each such false statement or representation or failure to disclose a material fact and each day of such failure or refusal shall constitute a separate offense. An individual employer, partner, corporate officer, or member of a limited liability company or limited liability partnership who willfully fails or refuses to make any combined tax payment shall be jointly and severally liable for the payment of such combined tax and any penalties and interest owed thereon. When an unemployment benefit overpayment occurs, in whole or in part, as the result of a violation of this section by an employer, the amount of the overpayment recovered shall not be credited back to such employer's experience account.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 16, p. 400; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-715; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-664; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 167, &#167; 13, p. 539; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 295; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 484, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB265, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 79. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>