<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-660.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-660.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Benefits; nonprofit organizations; combined tax; payments in lieu of contributions; election; notice; appeal; lien; liability.</catchline><para>(1) Benefits paid to employees of nonprofit organizations shall be financed in accordance with this section. For the purpose of this section, a nonprofit organization is an organization, or group of organizations, described in subdivision (9) of section 48-603.</para><para>(2)(a) Any nonprofit organization which is, or becomes, subject to the Employment Security Law shall pay combined tax under sections 48-648 to 48-661 unless it elects, in accordance with this subsection, to pay to the commissioner for the unemployment fund an amount, equal to the amount of regular benefits and of one-half of the extended benefits paid, that is attributable to service in the employ of such nonprofit organization, to individuals for weeks of unemployment which begin during the effective period of such election.</para><para>(b) Any nonprofit organization which is, or becomes, subject to the Employment Security Law may elect to become liable for payments in lieu of contributions for a period of not less than twelve months beginning with the date on which such subjectivity begins by filing a written notice of its election with the commissioner not later than thirty days immediately following the date of the determination of such subjectivity.</para><para>(c) Any nonprofit organization which makes an election in accordance with subdivision (b) of this subsection shall continue to be liable for payments in lieu of contributions until it files with the commissioner a written notice terminating its election not later than thirty days prior to the beginning of the taxable year for which such termination shall first be effective.</para><para>(d) Any nonprofit organization which has been paying combined tax under the Employment Security Law may change to a reimbursable basis by filing with the commissioner not later than thirty days prior to the beginning of any taxable year a written notice of election to become liable for payments in lieu of contributions. Such election shall not be terminable by the organization for that and the next year.</para><para>(e) The commissioner may for good cause extend the period within which a notice of election, or a notice of termination, must be filed and may permit an election to be retroactive but not any earlier than with respect to benefits paid after December 31, 1969.</para><para>(f) The commissioner, in accordance with such rules and regulations as he or she may adopt and promulgate, shall notify each nonprofit organization of any determination which he or she may make of its status as an employer and of the effective date of any election which it makes and of any termination of such election. Such determinations shall be subject to redetermination and appeal, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(3) Payments in lieu of contributions shall be made in accordance with this subsection as follows:</para><para>(a) At the end of each calendar quarter, or at the end of any other period as determined by the commissioner, the commissioner shall bill each nonprofit organization, or group of such organizations, which has elected to make payment in lieu of contributions for an amount equal to the full amount of regular benefits plus one-half of the amount of extended benefits paid during such quarter or other prescribed period that is attributable to service in the employ of such organization;</para><para>(b) Payment of any bill rendered under subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be made not later than thirty days after such bill was mailed to the last-known address of the nonprofit organization or was otherwise delivered to it unless there has been an application for review and redetermination in accordance with subdivision (d) of this subsection;</para><para>(c) Payments made by any nonprofit organization under this subsection shall not be deducted or deductible, in whole or in part, from the remuneration of individuals in the employ of the organization;</para><para>(d) The amount due specified in any bill from the commissioner shall be conclusive on the organization unless, not later than thirty days after the bill was mailed to its last-known address or otherwise delivered to it, the organization files an application for redetermination by the commissioner setting forth the grounds for such application. The commissioner shall promptly review and reconsider the amount due specified in the bill and shall thereafter issue a redetermination in any case in which such application for redetermination has been filed. Any such redetermination shall be conclusive on the organization unless the organization appeals the redetermination, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act; and</para><para>(e) Past-due payments of amounts in lieu of contributions shall be subject to the same interest that, pursuant to section 48-655, applies to past-due contributions, and the commissioner may file a lien against such nonprofit organization in accordance with the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act. Such liens shall set forth the amount of payments in lieu of contributions and interest in default and shall be enforced as provided in the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act.</para><para>(4) If any nonprofit organization is delinquent in making payments in lieu of contributions as required under subsection (3) of this section, the commissioner may terminate such organization's election to make payments in lieu of contributions as of the beginning of the next taxable year, and such termination shall be effective for that and the next taxable year.</para><para>(5) Each employer that is liable for payments in lieu of contributions shall pay to the commissioner for the fund the amount of regular benefits plus the amount of one-half of extended benefits paid that are attributable to service in the employ of such employer. If benefits paid to an individual are based on wages paid by more than one employer and one or more of such employers are liable for payments in lieu of contributions, the amount payable to the fund by each employer that is liable for such payments shall be determined in accordance with section 48-652.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 651, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 165, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB271, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 75. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act,</emphasis> see section 77-3901.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under the Nebraska Employment Security Law, the contribution type of financing as provided by section 48-649, R.R.S.1943, and reimbursement financing under section 48-660.01, R.R.S.1943, are separate and distinct systems, and a nonprofit organization must elect to use one or the other. West Nebraska General Hospital v. Hanlon, 208 Neb. 173, 302 N.W.2d 694 (1981).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>