  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-819.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-819.01</statuteno><catchline>Commission; power to make findings and enter orders; when.</catchline><para>Whenever it is alleged that a party to an industrial dispute has engaged in an act which is in violation of any of the provisions of the Industrial Relations Act, or which interferes with, restrains, or coerces employees in the exercise of the rights provided in such act, the commission shall have the power and authority to make such findings and to enter such temporary or permanent orders as the commission may find necessary to provide adequate remedies to the injured party or parties, to effectuate the public policy enunciated in section 48-802, and to resolve the dispute.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 444, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 809, &#167; 7. </para></source><annotation><para>The Commission on Industrial Relations' issuance of cease and desist orders is the equivalent of the commission ordering a party to cease and desist violating provisions of the Industrial Relations Act. Such orders are appropriate and adequate remedies under this section and subsection (2) of section 48-825. Crete Ed. Assn. v. Saline Cty. Sch. Dist. No. 76-0002, 265 Neb. 8, 654 N.W.2d 166 (2002).</para><para>Under the facts presented in this case, the order of the Commission on Industrial Relations to post notices regarding the employer's violation of the Industrial Relations Act was not an appropriate and adequate remedy under this section and subsection (2) of section 48-825. Crete Ed. Assn. v. Saline Cty. Sch. Dist. No. 76-0002, 265 Neb. 8, 654 N.W.2d 166 (2002).</para><para>The Commission of Industrial Relations has the authority to allow interest on an award. IAFF Local 831 v. City of No. Platte, 215 Neb. 89, 337 N.W.2d 716 (1983).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 