<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="48-101.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>48-101.01</statuteno><catchline>Mental injuries and mental illness;
first responder; compensation; when.</catchline><para>(1) Personal injury
includes mental injuries and mental illness unaccompanied by physical injury
for an employee who is a first responder if such first responder:</para>
<para>(a) Establishes, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the employee's
employment conditions causing the mental injury or mental illness were extraordinary
and unusual in comparison to the normal conditions of the particular employment;
and</para>
<para>(b) Establishes, by a preponderance of the evidence, the medical causation
between the mental injury or mental illness and the employment conditions
by medical evidence.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section, mental injuries and mental illness
arising out of and in the course of employment unaccompanied by physical injury
are not considered compensable if they result from any event or series of
events which are incidental to normal employer and employee relations, including,
but not limited to, personnel actions by the employer such as disciplinary
actions, work evaluations, transfers, promotions, demotions, salary reviews,
or terminations.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section, first responder means a sheriff, a
deputy sheriff, a police officer, an officer of the Nebraska State Patrol,
a volunteer or paid firefighter, or a volunteer or paid individual licensed
under a licensure classification in subdivision (1) of section 38-1217 who
provides medical
care in order to prevent loss of life or aggravation of physiological or psychological
illness or injury.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB780, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB646, &#167; 2.</para><note>For applicability of this section, see section 48-1,111.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>