  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-233</statuteno><catchline>Anabolic steroids; employees; prohibited acts; sanction.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to the penalties provided in the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, any employee of a state agency, political subdivision, or institution who possesses, dispenses, delivers, administers, uses, or knowingly allows a subordinate employee or a student attending such employee's employing institution to possess, dispense, deliver, administer, or use an anabolic steroid unless such substance is needed for a valid medical purpose:</para><para>(a) For the first conviction, shall be dismissed from employment and shall not be an employee of the dismissing entity or any other state agency, political subdivision, or institution for a period of one year after his or her dismissal; and</para><para>(b) For a second or any subsequent conviction, shall be dismissed from employment and shall not thereafter be an employee of the dismissing entity or any other state agency, political subdivision, or institution.</para><para>(2) Any sanction imposed pursuant to this section shall be subject to the Administrative Procedure Act except for those employees governed by sections 79-824 to 79-842.</para><para>(3) The use of an anabolic steroid for the purpose of hormonal manipulation that is intended to increase muscle mass, strength, or weight without a medical necessity to do so or for the intended purpose of improving physical appearance or performance in any form of exercise, sport, or game shall not be a valid medical purpose or in the course of professional practice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 571, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1053. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 