<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-825"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-825</statuteno><catchline>Labor negotiations; prohibited practices; complaints; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A proceeding against a party alleging a violation of section 48-824 is commenced by filing a complaint with the commission within one hundred eighty days after the alleged violation thereby causing a copy of the complaint to be served upon the accused party. The accused party has ten days within which to file a written answer to the complaint. If the commission determines that the complaint has no basis in fact, the commission may dismiss the complaint. If the complaint has a basis in fact, the commission shall set a time for hearing. The parties may be represented by counsel, summon witnesses, and request the commission to subpoena witnesses on the requester's behalf.</para><para>(2) The commission shall file its findings of fact and conclusions of law. If the commission finds that the party accused has committed a prohibited practice, the commission, within thirty days after its decision, shall order an appropriate remedy. Any party may petition the district court for injunctive relief pursuant to the rules of civil procedure.</para><para>(3) Any party aggrieved by any decision or order of the commission may, within thirty days after the date such decision or order is filed, appeal to the Court of Appeals.</para><para>(4) Any order or decision of the commission may be modified, reversed, or set aside by the appellate court on one or more of the following grounds and no other:</para><para>(a) If the commission acts without or in excess of its powers;</para><para>(b) If the order was procured by fraud or is contrary to law;</para><para>(c) If the facts found by the commission do not support the order; and</para><para>(d) If the order is not supported by a preponderance of the competent evidence on the record considered as a whole.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 382, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>In an appellate court's review of orders and decisions of the Commission of Industrial Relations involving an industrial dispute over wages and conditions of employment, the appellate court's standard of review is as follows: Any order or decision of the commission may be modified, reversed, or set aside by the appellate court on one or more of the following grounds and no other: (1) If the commission acts without or in excess of its powers, (2) if the order was procured by fraud or is contrary to law, (3) if the facts found by the commission do not support the order, and (4) if the order is not supported by a preponderance of the competent evidence on the record considered as a whole. Hyannis Ed. Assn. v. Grant Cty. Sch. Dist. No. 38-0011, 269 Neb. 956, 698 N.W.2d 45 (2005).</para><para>If the Commission of Industrial Relations finds that an accused party has committed a prohibited practice under subsection (2) of this section, it has the authority to order an appropriate remedy, and such authority is to be liberally construed to effectuate the public policy enunciated in section 48-802. Operating Engrs. Local 571 v. City of Plattsmouth, 265 Neb. 817, 660 N.W.2d 480 (2003).</para><para>The Commission on Industrial Relations' issuance of cease and desist orders is the equivalent of the commission ordering a party to cease and desist violating provisions of the Industrial Relations Act. Such orders are appropriate and adequate remedies under subsection (2) of this section and section 48-819.01. Crete Ed. Assn. v. Saline Cty. Sch. Dist. No. 76-0002, 265 Neb. 8, 654 N.W.2d 166 (2002).</para><para>Under the facts presented in this case, the order of the Commission on Industrial Relations to post notices regarding the employer's violation of the Industrial Relations Act was not an appropriate and adequate remedy under subsection (2) of this section and section 48-819.01. Crete Ed. Assn. v. Saline Cty. Sch. Dist. No. 76-0002, 265 Neb. 8, 654 N.W.2d 166 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 