<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id26">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id28" statutenumber="48-153"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>48-153</statuteno><catchline id="id31">Judges; number;
term; qualifications; continuance in office; prohibition on holding other
office or pursuing other occupation.</catchline><para>The Nebraska
Workers' Compensation Court shall consist of seven judges. Judges holding
office on August 30, 1981, shall continue in office until expiration of their
respective terms of office and thereafter for an additional term which shall
expire on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January immediately
following the first general election at which they are retained in office
after August 30, 1981. Judge of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court shall
include any person appointed to the office of judge of the Nebraska Workmen's
Compensation Court prior to July 17, 1986, pursuant to Article V, section
21, of the Nebraska Constitution. Any person serving as a judge of the Nebraska
Workmen's Compensation Court immediately prior to July 17, 1986, shall be
a judge of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court. The right of judges of
the compensation court to continue in office shall be determined in the manner
provided in sections 24-813 to 24-818, and the terms of office thereafter
shall be for six years beginning on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday
in January immediately following their retention at such election. In case
of a vacancy occurring in the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, the same
shall be filled in accordance with the provisions of Article V, section 21,
of the Nebraska Constitution and the right of any judge so appointed to continue
in office shall be determined in the manner provided in sections 24-813 to
24-818. All such judges shall hold office until their successors are appointed
and qualified, or until death, voluntary resignation, or removal for cause.
No judge of the compensation court shall, during his or her tenure in office
as judge, hold any other office or position of profit, pursue any other business
or avocation inconsistent or which interferes with his or her duties as such
judge, or serve on or under any committee of any political party.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 57, &#167; 2, p. 188; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-163; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-153; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 113, &#167; 1, p. 363; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 288, &#167; 1, p. 865; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 280, &#167; 2, p. 806; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 292, &#167; 2, p. 798; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 187, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 649, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 237, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 111, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 18, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 868, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB151, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
