<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id67" statutenumber="48-621"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>48-621</statuteno><catchline id="id70">Employment Security Administration Fund; Employment Security Special Contingent Fund; created; use; investment; federal funds; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) The administrative fund shall consist of the Employment Security Administration Fund and the Employment Security Special Contingent Fund. Each fund shall be maintained as a separate and distinct account in all respects, as follows:</para><para>(a) There is hereby created in the state treasury a special fund to be known as the Employment Security Administration Fund. All money credited to this fund is hereby appropriated and made available to the Commissioner of Labor. All money in this fund shall be expended solely for the purposes and in the amounts found necessary as defined by the specific federal programs, state statutes, and contract obligations for the proper and efficient administration of all programs of the Department of Labor. The fund shall consist of all money appropriated by this state and all money received from the United States of America or any agency thereof, including the Department of Labor and the Railroad Retirement Board, or from any other source for such purpose. Money received from any agency of the United States or any other state as compensation for services or facilities supplied to such agency, any amounts received pursuant to any surety bond or insurance policy for losses sustained by the Employment Security Administration Fund or by reason of damage to equipment or supplies purchased from money in such fund, and any proceeds realized from the sale or disposition of any equipment or supplies which may no longer be necessary for the proper administration of such programs shall also be credited to this fund. All money in the Employment Security Administration Fund shall be deposited, administered, and disbursed in the same manner and under the same conditions and requirements as provided by law for other special funds in the state treasury. Any balances in this fund, except balances of money therein appropriated from the General Fund of this state, shall not lapse at any time. Fund balances shall be continuously available to the commissioner for expenditure consistent with the Employment Security Law. Any money in the Employment Security Administration Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act; and</para><para>(b) There is hereby created in the state treasury a special fund to be known as the Employment Security Special Contingent Fund. Any money in the Employment Security Special Contingent Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. All money collected under section 48-655 as interest on delinquent contributions, less refunds, shall be credited to this fund from the clearing account of the Unemployment Compensation Fund at the end of each calendar quarter. Such money shall not be expended or available for expenditure in any manner to permit substitution for, or a corresponding reduction in, federal funds which, in the absence of such money, would be available to finance expenditures for the administration of the unemployment insurance law. However, nothing in this section shall prevent the money in the Employment Security Special Contingent Fund from being used as a revolving fund to cover necessary and proper expenditures under the law for which federal funds have been duly requested but not yet received. Upon receipt of duly requested federal funds, covered expenditures shall be charged against such federal funds. Money in the Employment Security Special Contingent Fund may only be used by the Commissioner of Labor as follows:</para><para>(i) To replace within a reasonable time any money received by this state pursuant to section 302 of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, and required to be paid under section 48-622;</para><para>(ii) To meet special extraordinary and contingent expenses which are deemed essential for good administration but which are not provided in grants from the Secretary of Labor of the United States. No expenditures shall be made from this fund for this purpose except on written authorization by the Governor at the request of the Commissioner of Labor; and</para><para>(iii) To be transferred to the Job Training Cash Fund.</para><para>(2)(a) Money credited to the account of this state in the Unemployment Trust Fund by the United States Secretary of the Treasury pursuant to section 903 of the Social Security Act may not be requisitioned from this state's account or used except:</para><para>(i) For the payment of benefits pursuant to section 48-619; and</para><para>(ii) For the payment of expenses incurred for the administration of the Employment Security Law and public employment offices. Money requisitioned or used for this purpose must be pursuant to a specific appropriation by the Legislature. Any such appropriation law shall specify the amount and purposes for which the money is appropriated and must be enacted before expenses may be incurred and money may be requisitioned. Such appropriation is subject to the following conditions:</para><para>(A) Money may be obligated for a limited period ending not more than two years after the effective date of the appropriation law; and</para><para>(B) An obligated amount shall not exceed the aggregate amounts transferred to the account of this state pursuant to section 903 of the Social Security Act less the aggregate of amounts used by this state pursuant to the Employment Security Law and amounts charged against the amounts transferred to the account of this state.</para><para>(b) For purposes of subdivision (2)(a)(ii)(B) of this section, amounts appropriated for administrative purposes shall be charged against transferred amounts when the obligation is entered into.</para><para>(c) The appropriation, obligation, and expenditure or other disposition of money appropriated under this subsection shall be accounted for in accordance with standards established by the United States Secretary of Labor.</para><para>(d) Money appropriated as provided in this subsection for the payment of administration expenses shall be requisitioned as needed for the payment of obligations incurred under such appropriation. Upon requisition, administration expenses shall be credited to the Employment Security Administration Fund from which such payments shall be made. Money so credited shall, until expended, remain a part of the Employment Security Administration Fund. If not immediately expended, credited money shall be returned promptly to the account of this state in the Unemployment Trust Fund.</para><para>(e) Notwithstanding subdivision (2)(a) of this section, money credited with respect to federal fiscal years 1999, 2000, and 2001 shall be used solely for the administration of the unemployment compensation program and are not subject to appropriation by the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 13, p. 397; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 10, p. 248; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 10, p. 398; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-712; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-621; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 175, &#167; 6, p. 574; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 163, &#167; 5, p. 421; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 208, &#167; 3, p. 729; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 50, p. 2375; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 305, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 1, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1072, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 608, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 953, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 197, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 20. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>