<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-224"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-224</statuteno><catchline>Withholding of wages; when authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Any employee of the State of Nebraska, any municipal corporation, or any public body or agency created by the laws of this state, who desires to participate voluntarily in any employee organization, credit union, or any community charity or public welfare plan approved by the Governor and the Director of Administrative Services, in the case of employees of the State of Nebraska, or by the duly elected governing body of such municipal corporation or other public body or agency, may execute an order authorizing the withholding from any wages or salary paid to such employee of a sum each month or pay period and the same to be paid to the designated recipient thereof. For purposes of this section, community charity includes any not-for-profit federation of health and human services agencies and associations.</para><para>(2) If a not-for-profit federation of health and human services agencies and associations is authorized pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, approval to similar not-for-profit federations shall also be granted on a similar equitable basis. For purposes of this subsection, a similar not-for-profit federation shall meet the following requirements:</para><para>(a) The federation has had an established office in the state for at least the last five years;</para><para>(b) The federation represents at least ten Nebraska-based health and human services agencies and associations in addition to the federation;</para><para>(c) The federation is a Nebraska corporation in good standing which holds a valid 501(c)(3) designation by the Internal Revenue Code;</para><para>(d) The federation and its agencies have an active, voluntary board which exercises administrative control over the federation and holds regular meetings; and</para><para>(e) The federation has a program focus and service delivery which is organized on either a statewide or regional basis.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 571, &#167; 1, p. 1878; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 76. </para></source><annotation><para>A political subdivision is not compelled to check off dues for a union because it has certified the union and agreed to bargain with it. State ex rel. Council #32 v. City of Hastings, 214 Neb. 20, 332 N.W.2d 661 (1983).</para><para>Cited as indicating public policy allowing public employees to join labor union. American Federation of State, Co., &amp; Mun. Emp. v. Woodward, 406 F.2d 137 (8th Cir. 1969).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>