
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-663.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-663.01</statuteno><catchline>Benefits; false statements by employee; forfeit; appeal; failure to repay overpayment of benefits; penalty; levy authorized; procedure; failure or refusal to honor levy; liability.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, or of section 48-627 or 48-663, an individual who willfully fails to disclose amounts earned during any week with respect to which benefits are claimed by him or her or who willfully fails to disclose or has falsified as to any fact which would have disqualified him or her or rendered him or her ineligible for benefits during such week, shall forfeit all or part of his or her benefit rights, as determined by an adjudicator, with respect to uncharged wage credits accrued prior to the date of such failure or to the date of such falsifications.</para><para>(b) In addition to any benefits which he or she may be required to repay pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section, if an overpayment is established pursuant to this section, an individual shall be required to pay to the department a penalty equal to fifteen percent of the amount of benefits received as a result of such willful failure to disclose or falsification. All amounts collected pursuant to this subdivision shall be remitted for credit to the Unemployment Compensation Fund.</para><para>(c) An appeal may be taken from any determination made pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section in the manner provided in section 48-634.</para><para>(2)(a) If any person liable to repay an overpayment of unemployment benefits resulting from a determination under subdivision (1)(a) of this section and pay the penalty required under subdivision (1)(b) of this section fails or refuses to repay such overpayment and pay any penalty assessed within twelve months after the date the overpayment determination becomes final, the commissioner may issue a levy on salary, wages, or other regular payments due to or received by such person and such levy shall be continuous from the date the levy is served until the amount of the levy is satisfied. Notice of the levy shall be mailed to the person whose salary, wages, or other regular payment is levied upon at his or her last-known address not later than the date that the levy is served. Exemptions or limitations on the amount of salary, wages, or other regular payment that can be garnished or levied upon by a judgment creditor shall apply to levies made pursuant to this section. Appeal of a levy may be made in the manner provided in section 48-634, but such appeal shall not act as a stay of the levy.</para><para>(b) Any person upon whom a levy is served who fails or refuses to honor the levy without cause may be held liable for the amount of the levy up to the value of the assets of the person liable to repay the overpayment that are under the control of the person upon whom the levy is served at the time of service and thereafter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 163, &#167; 16(2), p. 432; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB265, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1058, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB271, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 78. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>