<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-609"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-609</statuteno><catchline>Personnel; powers of commissioner; bond or insurance; retirement system.</catchline><para>Subject to other provisions of the Employment Security Law, the Commissioner of Labor is authorized to appoint, fix the compensation of, and prescribe the duties and powers of such officers, accountants, attorneys, experts, and other persons as may be necessary in the performance of his or her duties under such law. The commissioner may delegate to any such person such power and authority as he or she deems reasonable and proper for the effective administration of such law. Employees handling money or signing warrants under such law shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201. The commissioner may pay the share of the premium from the Employment Security Administration Fund. The commissioner shall classify positions under such law and shall establish salary schedules and minimum personnel standards for the positions so classified. He or she shall provide for the holding of examinations to determine the qualifications of applicants for the positions so classified, and except for temporary appointments of not to exceed six months in duration, such personnel shall be appointed on the basis of efficiency and fitness as determined in such examinations. The commissioner shall adopt, promulgate, and enforce fair and reasonable rules and regulations for appointments, promotions, and demotions based upon ratings of efficiency and fitness and for terminations for cause.</para><para>The commissioner may provide for a contributory retirement system for the employees of the department employed prior to July 1, 1984, and paid from funds provided pursuant to Title III of the Social Security Act or funds from other federal sources, or let a contract for such purpose with an insurance company licensed in Nebraska, and pay the employer's share of such system or contract from the Employment Security Administration Fund as long as this fund is wholly financed from Title III of the Social Security Act or from other federal sources. The employee's contribution to any such plan shall be deducted from his or her salary. Any person employed by the department after June 30, 1984, and paid from funds provided pursuant to Title III of the Social Security Act or funds from other federal sources shall be enrolled in the State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska when he or she becomes eligible.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 11, p. 391; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 8, p. 246; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-711; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-609; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 240, &#167; 1, p. 715; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 747, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 272, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 29, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 21. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1331.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 