<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id174">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" id="id176" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="48-818.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>48-818.03</statuteno><catchline>School district, educational service
unit, or community college; wage rates; commission; duties; orders authorized.</catchline>
<para>When establishing
wage rates pursuant to subsection (1) of section 48-818 for a school district,
educational service unit, or community college with their certificated and
instructional employees, the commission shall determine whether the total
compensation of the members of the bargaining unit or classification falls
within a ninety-eight percent to one hundred two percent range of the array's
midpoint. If the total compensation falls within the ninety-eight percent
to one hundred two percent range, the commission shall order no change in
wage rates. If the total compensation is less than ninety-eight percent of
the midpoint, the commission shall enter an order increasing wage rates to
ninety-eight percent of the midpoint. If the total compensation is more than
one hundred two percent of the midpoint, the commission shall enter an order
decreasing wage rates to one hundred two percent of the midpoint. If the total
compensation is more than one hundred seven percent of the midpoint, the commission
shall enter an order reducing wage rates to one hundred two percent of the
midpoint in three equal annual reductions. If the total compensation is less
than ninety-three percent of the midpoint, the commission shall enter an order
increasing wage rates to ninety-eight percent of the midpoint in three equal
annual increases. If the commission finds that the year in dispute occurred
during a time of recession, the applicable range will be ninety-five percent
to one hundred two percent. For purposes of this section, recession occurrence
means the two nearest quarters in time, excluding the immediately preceding
quarter, to the effective date of the contract term in which the sum of the
net state sales and use tax, individual income tax, and corporate income tax
receipts are less than the same quarters for the prior year. Each of these
receipts shall be rate and base adjusted for state law changes. The Department
of Revenue shall report and publish such receipts on a quarterly basis.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB397, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>