<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-118.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-118.02</statuteno><catchline>Third-party claims; expenses and attorney's fees; apportionment.</catchline><para>If either party after receiving notice under section 48-118.01 fails, by and through his or her attorney, to join in the third-party claim or suit, such party waives any and all claims or causes of action for improper prosecution of the third-party suit or inadequacy of a settlement made in accordance with section 48-118.04. The party bringing the claim or prosecuting the suit is entitled to deduct from any amount recovered the reasonable expenses of making such recovery, including a reasonable sum for attorney's fees. Such expenses and attorney's fees shall be prorated (1) to the amounts payable to the employer or his or her workers' compensation insurer under the right of subrogation established in section 48-118 and (2) to the amount in excess of such amount payable to the employer or his or her workers' compensation insurer under the right of subrogation. Such expenses and attorney's fees shall be apportioned by the court between the parties as their interests appear at the time of such recovery.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 13, &#167; 24. </para></source><annotation><para>This section and sections 48-118 through 48-118.04 should be read as a whole. In re Estate of Evertson, 295 Neb. 301, 889 N.W.2d 73 (2016).</para><para>When an employer has a subrogation interest in the recovery in a worker's third-party claim, the party bringing the claim or prosecuting the suit is entitled to deduct from any amount recovered the reasonable expenses of making such recovery, including a reasonable sum for attorney fees. Sterner v. American Fam. Ins. Co., 19 Neb. App. 339, 805 N.W.2d 696 (2011).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>