<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id64">
<sectno id="id65" opdate="July 1, 2011">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id66" statutenumber="48-627"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id68">48-627</statuteno><catchline id="id69">Benefits; eligibility
conditions; availability for work; requirements.</catchline><para>An
unemployed individual shall be eligible to receive benefits with respect to
any week, only if the Commissioner of Labor finds:</para>
<para>(1) He or she has registered for work at, and thereafter continued
to report at, an employment office in accordance with such rules and regulations
as the commissioner may prescribe, except that the commissioner may, by rule
and regulation, waive or alter either or both of the requirements of this
subdivision as to individuals attached to regular jobs and as to such other
types of cases or situations, with respect to which he or she finds that compliance
with such requirements, would be oppressive, or would be inconsistent with
the purposes of the Employment Security Law, except that no such rule or regulation
shall conflict with section 48-623;</para>
<para>(2) He or she has made a claim for benefits, in accordance
with section 48-629;</para>
<para>(3) He or she is able to work and is available for work. No
individual, who is otherwise eligible, shall be deemed ineligible, or unavailable
for work, because he or she is on vacation without pay during such week, if
such vacation is not the result of his or her own action as distinguished
from any collective action by a collective-bargaining agent or other action
beyond his or her individual control, and regardless of whether he or she
has not been notified of the vacation at the time of his or her hiring. An individual who is otherwise eligible
shall not be deemed unavailable for work or failing to engage in an active
work search solely because such individual is seeking part-time work if the
majority of the weeks of work in an individual's base period include part-time
work. For purposes of this subdivision, seeking only part-time work shall
mean seeking less than full-time work having comparable hours to the individual's
part-time work in the base period, except that the individual must be available
for work at least twenty hours per week. Receipt of a non-service-connected
total disability pension by a veteran at the age of sixty-five or more shall
not of itself bar the veteran from benefits as not able to work. An otherwise
eligible individual while engaged in a training course approved for him or
her by the commissioner shall be considered available for work for the purposes
of this section. An inmate in a penal or custodial institution shall be considered
unavailable for work for purposes of this section;</para>
<para>(4) He or she has been unemployed for a waiting period of
one week. No week shall be counted as a week of unemployment for the purpose
of this subdivision (a) unless it occurs within the benefit year, which includes
the week with respect to which he or she claims payment of benefits, (b) if
benefits have been paid with respect thereto, or (c) unless the individual
was eligible for benefits with respect thereto, as provided in sections 48-627
and 48-628, except for the requirements of this subdivision and of subdivision
(6) of section 48-628;</para>
<para>(5)(a) For any benefit year
beginning on or after January 1, 2006, he or she has, within his or her base
period, been paid a total sum of wages for employment by employers equal to
not less than two thousand five hundred dollars, of which sum at least eight
hundred dollars has been paid in each of two quarters in his or her base period,
and subsequent to filing the claim which establishes the previous benefit
year, the individual has earned wages in insured work of at least six times
his or her weekly benefit amount for the previous benefit year.</para>
<para>(b) For any benefit year beginning on
or after July 1, 2011, he or she has (i) within his or her base period, been
paid a total sum of wages for employment by employers equal to not less than
three thousand seven hundred seventy dollars, of which sum at least one thousand
eight hundred fifty dollars has been paid in one quarter in his or her base
period and eight hundred dollars has been paid in a second quarter of his
or her base period, and (ii) subsequent to filing the claim which establishes
the previous benefit year, earned wages in insured work of at least six times
his or her weekly benefit amount for the previous benefit year. Commencing
January 1, 2012, and each January 1 thereafter,
the amount which an individual is required to earn within his or her base
period shall be adjusted annually. The adjusted amount shall be equal to the
then current amount adjusted by the cumulative percentage change in the Consumer
Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Federal Bureau of Labor
Statistics for the one-year period ending on the previous September 30.</para>
<para>(c) For the purposes of this
subdivision (5), (i) for the determination of monetary
eligibility, wages paid within a base period shall not include wages from
any calendar quarter previously used to establish a valid claim for benefits,
(ii)  wages
shall be counted as wages for insured work for benefit purposes with respect
to any benefit year only if such benefit year begins subsequent to the date
on which the employer, by whom such wages were paid, has satisfied the conditions
of section 48-603 or subsection (3) of section 48-661, with respect to becoming
an employer, and (iii) with respect to weeks
of unemployment beginning on or after January 1, 1978, wages for insured work
for benefit purposes with respect to any benefit year shall include wages
paid for services as defined by subdivision (4)(a), (b), (c), or (d) of section
48-604 to the extent that such services were not services in employment under
subdivision (4)(a) of section 48-604 or section 48-661 immediately prior to
September 2, 1977, even though the employer by whom such wages were paid had
not satisfied the conditions of subdivision (8), (9), (10), or (11) of section
48-603 with respect to becoming an employer at the time such wages were paid
except to the extent that assistance under Title II of the federal Emergency
Jobs and Unemployment Assistance Act of 1974 was paid on the basis of such
services; and</para>
<para>(6) He or she is participating in reemployment services at
no cost to such individual as directed by the commissioner, such as job search
assistance services, if the individual has been determined to be likely to
exhaust regular benefits and to need reemployment services pursuant to a profiling
system established by rule and regulation of the commissioner which is in
compliance with section 303(j)(1) of the federal Social Security Act, unless
the commissioner determines that: (a) The individual has completed such services;
or (b) there is justifiable cause for the claimant's failure to participate
in such services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 4, p. 376; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 3, p. 235; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 3, p. 383; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-704; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-627; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 115, &#167; 3, p. 382; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 163, &#167; 10, p. 425; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 167, &#167; 6, p. 531; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 190, &#167; 6, p. 543; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 209, &#167; 2, p. 739; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 230, &#167; 1, p. 804; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 241, &#167; 1, p. 717; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 291, &#167; 3, p. 872; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 292, &#167; 1, p. 875; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 651, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 372, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 509, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 470, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 446, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 469, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1033, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 1, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 240, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 225, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 484, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 739, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1020, &#167; 3.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Availability is required for eligibility to receive unemployment compensation benefits. Robinson v. Commissioner of Labor, 267 Neb. 579, 675 N.W.2d 683 (2004).</para><para>Without an order from the sentencing court granting the privilege to leave the jail for work, an inmate was not "available" for work under this section. Robinson v. Commissioner of Labor, 267 Neb. 579, 675 N.W.2d 683 (2004).</para><para>This section describes weekly requirements for continuing eligibility and does not address the reasons why a person became unemployed or threshold questions of eligibility. Ponderosa Villa v. Hughes, 224 Neb. 627, 399 N.W.2d 813 (1987).</para><para>A lump-sum severance allowance paid to a claimant is not to be prorated to the calendar quarters immediately following the date of payment in order to determine whether the monetary eligibility requirements of subdivision (e) of this section have been met. Sorensen v. Meyer, 220 Neb. 457, 370 N.W.2d 173 (1985).</para><para>The provision that a claimant earn a certain amount of wages during any benefit year and during each of two quarters thereof is intended to prevent a claimant from electing to simply collect unemployment benefits rather than work. Sorensen v. Meyer, 220 Neb. 457, 370 N.W.2d 173 (1985).</para><para>A professional symphony musician employed under a seasonal contract rather than an annual contract was entitled to unemployment benefits for the time he was unemployed during the symphony's "off season". Hanlon v. Boden, 209 Neb. 169, 306 N.W.2d 858 (1981).</para><para>Registration for work alone is not sufficient to show prima facie a right to benefits. Hunter v. Miller, 148 Neb. 402, 27 N.W.2d 638 (1947).</para><para>For purposes of section 48-628(7), a student is not "registered for full attendance" and therefore disqualified from receiving unemployment benefits if the student's educational program allows him or her to remain "available for work" pursuant to subdivision (3) of this section. Lecuona v. Cramer, 14 Neb. App. 770, 714 N.W.2d 786 (2006).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>