<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id245" statutenumber="48-1,116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1,116</statuteno><catchline id="id248">Compensation Court Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Compensation Court Cash Fund is hereby created. The fund shall be used to aid in providing for the expense of administering the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act and the payment of the salaries and expenses of the personnel of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court.</para><para>All fees received pursuant to sections 48-120, 48-120.02, 48-138, 48-139, 48-145.04, and 48-165 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Compensation Court Cash Fund. The fund shall also consist of amounts credited to the fund pursuant to sections 48-1,113, 48-1,114, and 77-912. The State Treasurer may receive and credit to the fund any money which may at any time be contributed to the state or the fund by the federal government or any agency thereof to which the state may be or become entitled under any act of Congress or otherwise by reason of any payment made from the fund.</para><para>Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature until June 30, 2026. Any money in the Compensation Court Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 757, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 13, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB293, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 133. </para><operativedate>May 22, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>