<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id13" statutenumber="48-225"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>48-225</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Veterans preference;
terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes
of sections 48-225 to 48-231:</para>
<para>(1) Veteran means:</para>
<para>(a) A person who served full-time duty with military
pay and allowances in the armed forces of the United States, except for training
or for determining physical fitness, and was discharged or otherwise separated
with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions); or</para>
<para>(b) The spouse
of a veteran who has a one hundred percent permanent disability as determined
by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs;</para><para>(2) Full-time duty means duty during time of war or during a period
recognized by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs as qualifying
for veterans benefits administered by the department and that such duty from
January 31, 1955, to February 28, 1961, exceeded one hundred eighty days unless
lesser duty was the result of a service-connected or service-aggravated disability;</para>
<para>(3) Disabled veteran means an individual who has served on
active duty in the armed forces of the United States, has been discharged
or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under
honorable conditions) therefrom, and has established the present existence
of a service-connected disability or is receiving compensation, disability
retirement benefits, or pension because of a public statute administered by
the United States Department of Veterans Affairs or a military department;
and</para>
<para>(4) Preference eligible means any veteran as defined in this
section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 751, &#167; 1, p. 2826; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 2, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 368, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 54, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB588, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>