<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-616"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-616</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Commissioner of Labor; cooperation with Secretary of Labor of the United States; duties.</catchline><para id="id00">In the administration of the Employment Security Law, the Commissioner of Labor shall cooperate, to the fullest extent consistent with such law, with the Secretary of Labor of the United States. The commissioner is authorized and directed to adopt appropriate rules and regulations, administrative methods, and standards, as may be necessary to secure to this state and its citizens all advantages available under the Social Security Act, under sections 3303 and 3304 of the Federal Unemployment Tax Act, and under the Act of Congress entitled An act to provide for the establishment of a national employment system and for cooperation with states in the promotion of such system, and for other purposes, approved June 6, 1933, as amended. The commissioner shall comply with the regulations of the Secretary of Labor relating to the receipt or expenditure by this state of money granted under any of such acts. The commissioner shall make such reports, in such form and containing such information as the Secretary of Labor may from time to time require, and shall comply with such provisions as the Secretary of Labor may from time to time find necessary to assure the correctness and verification of such reports. Upon request, the commissioner shall furnish to any agency of the United States charged with the administration of public works or assistance through public employment the name, address, ordinary occupation, and employment status of each recipient of benefits and such recipient's rights to further benefits under the Employment Security Law. The commissioner may afford reasonable cooperation with every agency of the United States charged with the administration of any unemployment insurance law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 11, p. 394; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 8, p. 247; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 16, p. 401; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-711; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-616; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 238, &#167; 3, p. 709; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>