<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-622.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>48-622.01</statuteno><catchline>State Unemployment Insurance Trust
Fund; created; use; investment; commissioner; powers and duties; cessation
of state unemployment insurance tax; effect.</catchline><para>(1) There is
hereby created in the state treasury a special fund to be known as the State
Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund. All state unemployment insurance tax collected
under sections 48-648 to 48-661, less refunds, shall be paid into the fund.
Such money shall be held in trust for payment of unemployment insurance benefits.
Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, except that interest earned on money
in the fund shall be credited to the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund through June 30, 2015, and thereafter
to the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund at the end of each
calendar quarter.</para>
<para>(2) The commissioner shall have authority to determine when and in what
amounts withdrawals from the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund for payment
of benefits are necessary. Amounts withdrawn for payment of benefits shall
be immediately forwarded to the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States
of America to the credit of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust
Fund, provisions of law in this state relating to the deposit, administration,
release, or disbursement of money in the possession or custody of this state
to the contrary notwithstanding.</para>
<para>(3) If and when the state unemployment insurance tax ceases to exist
as determined by the Governor, all money then in the State Unemployment Insurance
Trust Fund less accrued interest shall be immediately transferred to the credit
of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund, provisions of law in
this state relating to the deposit, administration, release, or disbursement
of money in the possession or custody of this state to the contrary notwithstanding.
The determination to eliminate the state unemployment insurance tax shall
be based on the solvency of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust
Fund and the need for training of Nebraska workers. Accrued interest in the
State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund shall be credited to the Nebraska
Training and Support Trust Fund through
June 30, 2015, and thereafter to the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(4) Upon certification from the commissioner that disallowed costs by
the United States Department of Labor for FY2007-08, FY2008-09, and FY2009-10,
or any one of them, have been reduced to an amount certain by way of settlement
or final judgment, the State Treasurer shall transfer the amount of such settlement
or final judgment from the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund to the
Employment Security Special Contingent Fund. The total amount of such transfers
shall not exceed $2,816,345. The amount of the reappropriation of Federal
Funds appropriated in FY2004-05 under section 903(d) of the federal Social
Security Act shall be reduced by the amount transferred.</para>
<para>(5) Upon certification
from the commissioner that the amount needed to settle pending class action
litigation and terminate the contributory retirement system established pursuant
to section 48-609 has been reduced to an amount certain, the State Treasurer
shall transfer the amount certified by the commissioner as needed to effectuate
the settlement from the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund to the Employment
Security Special Contingent Fund. The amount transferred pursuant to this
subsection shall not exceed two million seven hundred seventy-three thousand
dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB631, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB906, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB997, &#167; 1.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB906, section 16, with LB997, section 1, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB906 became effective March 30, 2014. Changes made by LB997 became effective July 18, 2014.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>