<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id100" statutenumber="48-675"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>48-675</statuteno><catchline>Short-time compensation program; commissioner; decision; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) The commissioner shall approve or disapprove a short-time compensation plan in writing within thirty days after its receipt and promptly communicate the decision to the employer. A decision disapproving the plan shall clearly identify the reasons for the disapproval. The disapproval shall be final, but the employer shall be allowed to submit another short-time compensation plan for approval not earlier than forty-five days after the date of the disapproval, except that the commissioner may, for good cause shown, approve a plan for an employer within such forty-five-day period.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, a short-time compensation plan will only be approved for a contributory employer that (a) is eligible for experience rating under section 48-649.03, (b) has a positive balance in the employer's experience account, (c) has filed all quarterly reports and other reports required under the Employment Security Law, and (d) has paid all obligation assessments, contributions, interest, and penalties due through the date of the employer's application.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, a short-time compensation plan will only be approved for an employer liable for making payments in lieu of contributions that has filed all quarterly reports and other reports required under the Employment Security Law and has paid all obligation assessments, payments in lieu of contributions, interest, and penalties due through the date of the employer's application.</para><para>(4) The commissioner may, for good cause shown, waive any requirement in subsection (2) or (3) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB961, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB780, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>