<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-629.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-629.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Claims; advisement to claimant; amounts deducted; how treated.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) An individual filing a new claim for unemployment compensation shall, at the time of the filing of such claim, be advised that:</para><para id="id00">(a) Unemployment compensation is subject to federal and state income tax;</para><para id="id00">(b) Requirements exist pertaining to estimated tax payments;</para><para id="id00">(c) The individual may elect to have federal income tax withheld from the individual's payment of unemployment compensation at the amount specified in the Internal Revenue Code;</para><para>(d) The individual may elect to have state income tax withheld from the individual's payment of unemployment compensation at the rate of five percent; and</para><para id="id00">(e) The individual shall be permitted to change a previously elected withholding status.</para><para id="id00">(2) Amounts deducted and withheld from unemployment compensation for federal income tax purposes shall remain in the Unemployment Compensation Fund until transferred to the federal Internal Revenue Service as a payment of income tax. Amounts deducted and withheld from unemployment compensation for state income tax purposes shall remain in the Unemployment Compensation Fund until transferred to the Department of Revenue as a payment of income tax.</para><para id="id00">(3) The commissioner shall follow all procedures specified by the United States Department of Labor and the federal Internal Revenue Service pertaining to the deducting and withholding of income tax.</para><para id="id00">(4) Amounts shall be deducted and withheld under this section only after amounts are deducted and withheld for any overpayments of unemployment compensation, child support obligations, or any other amounts required to be withheld under the Employment Security Law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1072, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 49. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>