<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-622.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>48-622.01</statuteno><catchline>State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund; created; use; investment; commissioner; powers and duties; cessation of state unemployment insurance tax; effect.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created in the state treasury a special fund to be known as the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund. All state unemployment insurance tax collected under sections 48-648 to 48-661, less refunds, shall be paid into the fund. Such money shall be held in trust for payment of unemployment insurance benefits. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, except that interest earned on money in the fund shall be credited to the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund at the end of each calendar quarter.</para><para>(2) The commissioner shall have the authority to determine when and in what amounts withdrawals from the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund for payment of benefits are necessary. Amounts withdrawn for payment of benefits shall be immediately forwarded to the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States of America to the credit of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund, any provision of law in this state relating to the deposit, administration, release, or disbursement of money in the possession or custody of this state to the contrary notwithstanding.</para><para>(3) If and when the state unemployment insurance tax ceases to exist as determined by the Governor, all money then in the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund less accrued interest shall be immediately transferred to the credit of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund, any provision of law in this state relating to the deposit, administration, release, or disbursement of money in the possession or custody of this state to the contrary notwithstanding. The determination to eliminate the state unemployment insurance tax shall be based on the solvency of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund and the need for training of Nebraska workers. Accrued interest in the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund shall be credited to the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB631, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB906, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB997, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 21. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2018</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>