<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-516"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-516</statuteno><catchline>Foreign labor agent; reports required; contents.</catchline><para>Any labor agent hiring, enticing or soliciting common or agricultural workers in this state for employment beyond this state, shall make monthly reports to the commissioner on the first day of each month covering the preceding month correctly showing the name and address of every representative, subagent, contractor, recruiter or solicitor engaged in any part of the work of that agency connected with the hiring, enticing or soliciting of common or agricultural workers in this state to be employed beyond the limits of this state, and correctly showing:</para><para>(1) The name, age, sex and address of each person solicited to be employed beyond the limits of this state;</para><para>(2) The name and address of the employer of every such person;</para><para>(3) The place where every such person is to be employed;</para><para>(4) The kind of work every such person is employed to do;</para><para>(5) The term of employment of every such person;</para><para>(6) The wages to be paid to every such person for his work; and</para><para>(7) Whether or not transportation is to be furnished, arranged for, or paid for any such common laborer or agricultural worker either leaving or returning to this state.</para><para>The commissioner shall cancel the license of every agent or private employment agency who or which fails to make and file such reports on or before the tenth day of each month for the preceding month in accordance with the cancellation provisions provided in section 48-505.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 285, &#167; 5, p. 817; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 162, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 