<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-634"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>48-634</statuteno><catchline>Administrative appeal; notice; time
allowed; hearing; parties.</catchline><para>(1) The
claimant or any other party entitled to notice of a determination as provided
in section 48-632, may file an appeal from such determination with the department. Notice of
appeal must be in writing or in accordance with rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated by the commissioner and must be delivered and received within
twenty days after the date of mailing of the notice of determination to his
or her last-known address or, if such notice is not mailed, after the date
of delivery of such notice of determination,
except that for good cause shown an appeal filed outside the prescribed time
period may be heard. In accordance with section 303 of the federal Social
Security Act, 42 U.S.C. 503, the commissioner shall provide the opportunity
for a fair hearing before an impartial appeal tribunal on each appeal.</para>
<para>(2) Unless the appeal is withdrawn,
the appeal tribunal, after affording the parties reasonable opportunities
for a fair hearing, shall make findings and conclusions and on the basis thereof
affirm, modify, or reverse such determination. If an appeal involves a question
as to whether services were performed by the claimant in employment or for
an employer, the tribunal shall give special notice of such issue and of the
pendency of the appeal to the employer and to the commissioner, both of whom
shall be parties to the proceeding and be afforded a reasonable opportunity
to adduce evidence bearing on such question. The parties shall be promptly
notified of the tribunal's decision and shall be furnished with a copy of
the decision and the findings and conclusions in support of the decision.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 4, p. 386; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-634; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 328, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 239, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 192, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1058, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>Before appeal tribunal of Labor Department may take jurisdiction over appeal filed beyond limitation date for newly discovered evidence, appellant must demonstrate new evidence would make a valid claim or defense. Nicholson v. City of Bellevue, 215 Neb. 540, 339 N.W.2d 758 (1983).</para><para>A notice of appeal filed pursuant to this section, which is properly addressed and to which sufficient postage has been affixed, shall be valid if it is deposited in the United States mail within ten days after the mailing of the notice of the deputy's determination. Parson v. Chizek, 201 Neb. 754, 272 N.W.2d 48 (1978).</para><para>Administrative appeal within division is provided. A. Borchman Sons v. Carpenter, 166 Neb. 322, 89 N.W.2d 123 (1958).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>