<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-503</statuteno><catchline>Employment agency; license; qualifications; fee; offices; location.</catchline><para>No person, firm, or corporation in this state shall open, operate, or maintain a private employment agency for hire or for help without first obtaining a license for the same from the Commissioner of Labor, and the license fee shall be one hundred fifty dollars per annum payable in advance on May 1 of each year, and each license shall expire on April 30 of each year. When application is made by a firm or corporation, it must be verified by each member who will benefit from such license. The Commissioner of Labor may require evidence of the moral character of all applicants and make such investigation of the applicants as he or she deems necessary. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. No license shall be issued to any person or persons except those of good moral character. No license shall be issued to any person or persons if anyone financially interested in or who has managerial control of the proposed private employment agency has been convicted of a felony. Such licenses shall permit the private employment agency to maintain one office under such license and to conduct business only at that location. Every license shall contain a designation of the city, street, and number of the building in which the licensed parties conduct such private employment agency. In case of removal to another location during the period covered by such license, the commissioner shall be notified thirty days prior to the change of location and the license corrected accordingly. No such license shall be transferable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 189, &#167; 2, p. 702; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7728; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 48-502; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-503; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 285, &#167; 2, p. 815; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1460, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 162, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 127. </para></source><annotation><para>License to operate employment agency is required. State ex rel. Weasmer v. Manpower of Omaha, Inc., 161 Neb. 387, 73 N.W.2d 692 (1955).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 