<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id465"><amendatorysection statutenumber="48-649.04" chaptername="Labor"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>48-649.04</statuteno><catchline>State or political subdivision; combined tax; election to make payments in lieu of contributions.</catchline><para>(1) The state or any of its political subdivisions and any instrumentality of one or more of the foregoing or any other governmental entity for which services in employment as provided in subdivision (4)(a) of section 48-604 are performed shall be required to pay combined tax on wages paid for services rendered in its or their employment on the same basis as any other employer who is liable for the payment of combined tax under the Employment Security Law, unless the state or any political subdivision thereof and any instrumentality of one or more of the foregoing or any other governmental entity for which such services are performed files with the commissioner its written election not later than thirty days after such employer becomes subject to this section to become liable to make payments in lieu of contributions in an amount equal to the full amount of regular benefits plus the full amount of extended benefits paid during each calendar quarter that is attributable to service in employment of such electing employer.</para><para>(2) Eligible employers electing to make payments in lieu of contributions shall not be liable for combined tax payments.</para><para>(3) The commissioner, after the end of each calendar quarter, shall notify any such employer that has elected to make payments in lieu of contributions of the amount of benefits for which it is liable to pay pursuant to its election that have been paid that are attributable to service in its employment and the employer so notified shall reimburse the fund within thirty days after receipt of such notice.</para><para>(4) Any employer which makes an election in accordance with this section to become liable for payments in lieu of contributions shall continue to be liable for payments in lieu of contributions for all benefits paid based upon wages paid for service in employment of such employer while such election is effective. Any such election shall continue until such employer files with the commissioner, not later than December 1 of any calendar year, a written notice terminating its election as of December 31 of that year. Upon termination of the election, such employer shall again be liable for the payment of contributions and for the reimbursement of such benefits as may be paid based upon wages paid for services in employment of such employer while such election was effective.</para><para>(5) The commissioner may require any employer subject to this section whose annual payroll for either of the two preceding calendar years has equaled or exceeded one hundred thousand dollars to pay the amount owed pursuant to this section by an electronic method approved by the commissioner, except when the employer establishes to the satisfaction of the commissioner that payment by an electronic method would create a hardship for the employer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 67. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>