
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id208"><amendatorysection statutenumber="48-628.06" chaptername="Labor"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-628.06</statuteno><catchline>Benefits; disqualification; educational institution.</catchline><para>An individual shall be disqualified for benefits for any week of unemployment if claimed benefits are based on services performed:</para><para>(1) In an instructional, research, or principal administrative capacity for an educational institution, if:</para><para>(a) Such week commences during the period between two successive academic years or terms, or when an agreement provides instead for a similar period between two regular, but not successive, terms during such period;</para><para>(b) Such individual performs such services in the first of such academic years or terms; and</para><para>(c) There is a contract or reasonable assurance that such individual will perform services in any such capacity for any educational institution in the second of such academic years or terms;</para><para>(2) In any other capacity for an educational institution, if such week commences during a period between two successive academic years or terms, such individual performs such services in the first of such academic years or terms, and there is a reasonable assurance that such individual will perform such services in the second of such academic years or terms. If benefits are denied to any individual for any week under this subdivision and such individual was not offered an opportunity to perform such services for the educational institution for the second of such academic years or terms, such individual shall be entitled to a retroactive payment of the benefits for each week for which the individual filed a timely claim for benefits and for which benefits were denied solely by reason of this subdivision;</para><para>(3) In any capacity described in subdivision (1) or (2) of this section in an educational institution while in the employ of an educational service agency, and such individual shall be disqualified as specified in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section. As used in this subdivision, educational service agency means a governmental agency or governmental entity which is established and operated exclusively for the purpose of providing services to one or more educational institutions;</para><para>(4) In any capacity described in subdivision (1) or (2) of this section in an educational institution if such services are provided to or on behalf of the educational institution while in the employ of an organization or entity described in section 3306(c)(7) or 3306(c)(8) of the Federal Unemployment Tax Act, 26 U.S.C. 3306(c)(7) or (8), and such individual shall be disqualified as specified in subdivisions (1), (2), and (3) of this section; and</para><para>(5) In any capacity described in subdivision (1) or (2) of this section if such week commences during an established and customary vacation period or holiday recess if such individual performs such services in the period immediately before such vacation period or holiday recess, and there is a reasonable assurance that such individual will perform such services in the period immediately following such vacation period or holiday recess.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 36. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>