<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id124" statutenumber="48-652"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>48-652</statuteno><catchline id="id127">Employer's experience
account; reimbursement account; contributions by employer; liability; termination;
reinstatement.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A separate experience account shall
be established for each employer who is liable for payment of contributions.
Whenever and wherever in the Employment Security Law the terms reserve account
or experience account are used, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise,
such terms shall be deemed interchangeable and synonymous and reference to
either of such accounts shall refer to and also include the other.</para>
<para>(b) A separate reimbursement account shall be established for each employer
who is liable for payments in lieu of contributions. All benefits paid with
respect to service in employment for such employer shall be charged to his
or her reimbursement account and such employer shall be billed for and shall
be liable for the payment of the amount charged when billed by the commissioner.
Payments in lieu of contributions received by the commissioner on behalf of
each such employer shall be credited to such employer's reimbursement account,
and two or more employers who are liable for payments in lieu of contributions
may jointly apply to the commissioner for establishment of a group account
for the purpose of sharing the cost of benefits paid that are attributable
to service in the employ of such employers. The commissioner shall prescribe
such rules and regulations as he or she deems necessary with respect to applications
for establishment, maintenance, and termination of group accounts authorized
by this subdivision.</para>
<para>(2) All contributions paid by an employer shall be credited to the experience
account of such employer. State unemployment insurance tax payments shall
not be credited to the experience account of each employer. Partial payments
of combined tax shall be credited so that at least eighty percent of the combined
tax payment excluding interest and penalty is credited first to contributions
due. In addition to contributions credited to the experience account, each
employer's account shall be credited as of June 30 of each calendar year with
interest at a rate determined by the commissioner based on the average annual
interest rate paid by the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States of
America upon the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund for the preceding
calendar year multiplied by the balance in his or her experience account at
the beginning of such calendar year. If the total credits as of such date
to all employers' experience accounts are equal to or greater than ninety
percent of the total amount in the Unemployment Compensation Fund, no interest
shall be credited for that year to any employer's account. Contributions with
respect to prior years which are received on or before January 31 of any year
shall be considered as having been paid at the beginning of the calendar year.
All voluntary contributions which are received on or before January 10 of
any year shall be considered as having been paid at the beginning of the calendar
year.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Each experience account shall be charged only for benefits based
upon wages paid by such employer. No benefits shall be charged to the experience
account of any employer if (i) such benefits were paid on the basis of a period
of employment from which the claimant (A) left work voluntarily without good
cause, (B) left work voluntarily due to a nonwork-connected illness or injury,
(C) left work voluntarily with good cause to escape abuse as defined in section
42-903 between household members as provided in subdivision (1) of section
48-628.01, (D) left work from which he or she was discharged for misconduct
connected with his or her work, (E) left work voluntarily and is entitled
to unemployment benefits without disqualification in accordance with subdivision
(3) or (5) of section 48-628.01, or (F) was involuntarily separated from employment
and such benefits were paid pursuant to section 48-628.05, and (ii) the employer
has filed timely notice of the facts on which such exemption is claimed in
accordance with rules and regulations prescribed by the commissioner. No benefits
shall be charged to the experience account of any employer if such benefits
were paid on the basis of wages paid in the base period that are wages for
insured work solely by reason of subdivision (5)(c)(iii) of section 48-627.
No benefits shall be charged to the experience account of any employer if
such benefits were paid during a week when the individual was participating
in training approved under section 236(a)(1) of the federal Trade Act of 1974,
19 U.S.C. 2296(a)(1).</para>
<para>(b) Each reimbursement account shall be charged only for benefits paid
that were based upon wages paid by such employer in the base period that were
wages for insured work solely by reason of subdivision (5) of section 48-627.</para>
<para>(c) Benefits paid to an eligible individual shall be charged against
the account of his or her most recent employers within his or her base period
against whose accounts the maximum charges hereunder have not previously been
made in the inverse chronological order in which the employment of such individual
occurred. The maximum amount so charged against the account of any employer,
other than an employer for which services in employment as provided in subdivision
(4)(a) of section 48-604 are performed, shall not exceed the total benefit
amount to which such individual was entitled as set out in section 48-626
with respect to base period wages of such individual paid by such employer
plus one-half the amount of extended benefits paid to such eligible individual
with respect to base period wages of such individual paid by such employer.
The commissioner shall by rules and regulations prescribe the manner in which
benefits shall be charged against the account of several employers for whom
an individual performed employment during the same quarter or during the same
base period. Any benefit check duly issued and delivered or mailed to a claimant
and not presented for payment within one year from the date of its issue may
be invalidated and the amount thereof credited to the Unemployment Compensation
Fund, except that a substitute check may be issued and charged to the fund
on proper showing at any time within the year next following. Any charge made
to an employer's account for any such invalidated check shall stand as originally
made.</para>
<para>(4)(a) An employer's experience account shall be deemed to be terminated
one calendar year after such employer has ceased to be subject to the Employment
Security Law, except that if the commissioner finds that an employer's business
is closed solely because of the entrance of one or more of the owners, officers,
partners, or limited liability company members or the majority stockholder
into the armed forces of the United States, or of any of its allies, after
July 1, 1950, such employer's account shall not be terminated and, if the
business is resumed within two years after the discharge or release from active
duty in the armed forces of such person or persons, the employer's experience
account shall be deemed to have been continuous throughout such period.</para>
<para>(b) An experience account terminated pursuant to this subsection shall
be reinstated if (i) the employer becomes subject again to the Employment
Security Law within one calendar year after termination of such experience
account and the employer makes a written application for reinstatement of
such experience account to the commissioner within two calendar years after
termination of such experience account and (ii) the commissioner finds that
the employer is operating substantially the same business as prior to the
termination of such experience account.</para>
<para>(5) All money in the Unemployment Compensation Fund shall be kept mingled
and undivided. The payment of benefits to an individual shall in no case be
denied or withheld because the experience account of any employer does not
have a total of contributions paid in excess of benefits charged to such experience
account.</para>
<para>(6) A contributory or reimbursable employer shall be relieved of charges
if the employer was previously charged for wages and the same wages are being
used a second time to establish a new claim as a result of the October 1,
1988, change in the base period.</para>
<para>(7) If an individual's base period wage credits represent part-time
employment for a contributory employer and the contributory employer continues
to employ the individual to the same extent as during the base period, then
the contributory employer's experience account shall not be charged if the
contributory employer has filed timely notice of the facts on which such exemption
is claimed in accordance with rules and regulations prescribed by the commissioner.</para>
<para>(8) If a contributory
employer responds to the department's request for information within the time
period set forth in subsection (1) of section 48-632 and provides accurate
information as known to the employer at the time of the response, the employer's
experience account shall not be charged if the individual's separation from
employment is voluntary and without good cause as determined under subdivision
(1) of section 48-628.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 7, p. 383; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 5, p. 240; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 5, p. 392; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-707; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-652; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 175, &#167; 11, p. 579; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 163, &#167; 13, p. 428; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 167, &#167; 9, p. 534; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 208, &#167; 5, p. 732; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 651, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 509, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 800, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 995, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 901, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 275, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1033, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 292; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 1, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 240, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 953, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 418, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 739, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB265, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB500, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB631, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1020, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1058, &#167; 7.</para></source><annotation><para>Where employees have left work voluntarily without good cause or have been discharged for misconduct, an employer is not charged with benefits paid to its employees. Fauss v. Messerly, 200 Neb. 326, 263 N.W.2d 668 (1978).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>