<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id5" statutenumber="48-622.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>48-622.02</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund; created; investment; use; Administrative Costs Reserve Account; created; use; Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund; created; use; investment; Administrative Costs Reserve Account; created; use.</catchline><para>(1) Until July 1, 2015:</para><para>(a) There is in the state treasury a special fund to be known as the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. All money deposited or paid into the fund is hereby appropriated and made available to the commissioner. No expenditures shall be made from the fund without the written authorization of the Governor upon the recommendation of the commissioner. Any interest earned on money in the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund shall be credited to the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund;</para><para>(b) Money in the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund shall be used for (i) administrative costs of establishing, assessing, collecting, and maintaining state unemployment insurance tax liability and payments, (ii) administrative costs of creating, operating, maintaining, and dissolving the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund and the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund, (iii) support of public and private job training programs designed to train, retrain, or upgrade work skills of existing Nebraska workers of for-profit and not-for-profit businesses, (iv) recruitment of workers to Nebraska, (v) training new employees of expanding Nebraska businesses, (vi) the costs of creating a common web portal for the attraction of businesses and workers to Nebraska, and (vii) payment of unemployment insurance benefits if solvency of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund and of the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund so require; and</para><para>(c) There is within the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund a separate account to be known as the Administrative Costs Reserve Account. Money shall be allocated from the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund to the Administrative Costs Reserve Account in amounts sufficient to pay the anticipated administrative costs identified in subdivision (1)(b) of this section.</para><para>(2) On and after July 1, 2015:</para><para>(a) The Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund is created. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. On July 1, 2015, the State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund to the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund. No expenditures shall be made from the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund without the written authorization of the Governor upon the recommendation of the commissioner. Any interest earned on money in the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund shall be credited to the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund;</para><para>(b) Money in the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund shall be used for (i) administrative costs of establishing, assessing, collecting, and maintaining state unemployment insurance tax liability and payments, (ii) administrative costs of creating, operating, maintaining, and dissolving the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund and the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund, (iii) support of public and private job training programs designed to train, retrain, or upgrade work skills of existing Nebraska workers of for-profit and not-for-profit businesses, (iv) recruitment of workers to Nebraska, (v) training new employees of expanding Nebraska businesses, (vi) the costs of creating a common web portal for the attraction of businesses and workers to Nebraska, (vii) developing and conducting labor availability and skills gap studies pursuant to the Sector Partnership Program Act, for which money may be transferred to the Sector Partnership Program Fund as directed by the Legislature, and (viii) payment of unemployment insurance benefits if solvency of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund and of the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund so require;</para><para>(c) The Administrative Costs Reserve Account is created within the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund. Money shall be allocated from the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund to the Administrative Costs Reserve Account in amounts sufficient to pay the anticipated administrative costs identified in subdivision (2)(b) of this section; and</para><para>(d) The State Treasurer shall transfer two hundred fifty thousand dollars from the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund to the Sector Partnership Program Fund no later than July 15, 2016.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB631, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB911, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB997, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1110, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Sector Partnership Program Act,</emphasis> see section 48-3401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>