<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-603"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>48-603</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Employer, defined.</catchline><para>As used in the Employment Security Law, unless the context clearly requires otherwise, employer shall mean:</para><para>(1) Any individual or type of organization, including any partnership, limited liability company, association, trust, estate, joint-stock company, insurance company or corporation, whether domestic or foreign, or the receiver, trustee in bankruptcy, trustee or successor thereof, or the legal representative of a deceased person, which for some portion of a day but not necessarily simultaneously in each of twenty different calendar weeks, whether or not such weeks are or were consecutive, within either the current or preceding calendar year, and for the purpose of this definition, if any week includes both December 31 and January 1, the days up to January 1 shall be deemed one calendar week and the days beginning January 1 another such week, has or had in employment one or more individuals, irrespective of whether the same individuals are or were employed in each such day; all individuals performing services for any employer of any person in this state, who maintains two or more separate establishments within this state, shall be deemed to be employed by a single employer; any artifice or device, including any contract or subcontract, by an employer for the performance of work, which is a part of such employer's usual trade, occupation, profession, or business, entered into for the purpose or with the intent of evading the application of this section to such employer, is hereby prohibited and declared to be unlawful;</para><para>(2) Any employer of any person in this state who in any calendar quarter in either the current or preceding calendar year has paid wages for employment in the total sum of fifteen hundred dollars or more;</para><para>(3) Any individual or employer of any person in this state which acquired the organization, trade, or business, or substantially all the assets thereof, of another employer which, at the time of such acquisition, was an employer subject to the Employment Security Law;</para><para>(4) Any employer of any person in this state, which acquired the organization, trade, or business, or substantially all the assets thereof, of another employer of any person in this state, not an employer subject to such law, and which, if subsequent to such acquisition it were treated as a single unit with such other employer, would be an employer under subdivision (1) or (2) of this section;</para><para>(5) Any employer of any person in this state which, having become an employer under any provision of the Employment Security Law and which has not, under section 48-661, ceased to be an employer subject to such law;</para><para>(6) For the effective period of its election pursuant to section 48-661, any other employer of any person in this state who has elected to become fully subject to the Employment Security Law;</para><para>(7) Any employer of any person in this state not an employer by reason of any other subdivision of this section (a) for which services in employment are or were performed with respect to which such employer is liable for any federal tax against which credit may be taken for contributions required to be paid into a state unemployment compensation fund; or (b) which, as a condition for approval of the Employment Security Law for full tax credit against the tax imposed by the Federal Unemployment Tax Act, is required, pursuant to such act, to be an employer under the Employment Security Law;</para><para>(8) The state or any political subdivision thereof and any instrumentality of any one or more of the foregoing;</para><para>(9) Any organization for which service in employment as defined in subdivision (4)(b) of section 48-604 is performed;</para><para>(10) Any individual or employing unit for which service in employment as defined in subdivision (4)(c) of section 48-604 is performed;</para><para>(11) Any individual or employing unit for which service in employment as defined in subdivision (4)(d) of section 48-604 is performed; and</para><para>(12)(a) In determining whether or not an employing unit for which service other than domestic service is also performed is an employer under subdivision (1) or (10) of this section, the wages earned or the employment of an employee performing domestic service shall not be taken into account; and</para><para>(b) In determining whether or not an employing unit for which agricultural labor is also performed is an employer under subdivision (11) of this section, the wages earned or the employment of an employee performing services in agricultural labor shall not be taken into account. If an employing unit is determined an employer of agricultural labor, such employing unit shall be determined an employer for the purposes of subdivision (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 2, p. 371; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 1, p. 229; </para><para>Laws 1940, Spec. Sess., c. 2, &#167; 1, p. 54; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 1, p. 374; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-702; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-603; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 114, &#167; 1, p. 369; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 190, &#167; 1, p. 538; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 651, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 509, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 290; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB271, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>