<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id470"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="48-238"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>48-238</statuteno><catchline>Veterans preference in private employment; policy; notice to Commissioner of Labor; registry.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Private employer means a sole proprietorship, a corporation, a partnership, an association, a limited liability company, or any other entity with one or more employees;</para><para>(b) Veteran means (i) a person who served full-time duty with military pay and allowances in the armed forces of the United States, except for training or for determining physical fitness, and was discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions), or (ii) the spouse of a veteran who (A) has a one hundred percent permanent disability as determined by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs or (B) was killed in hostile action; and</para><para>(c) Voluntary veterans preference employment policy means a private employer's voluntary preference for hiring and promoting a veteran over another equally qualified applicant or employee.</para><para>(2) A private employer may adopt a voluntary veterans preference employment policy. Such policy shall be in writing and applied uniformly to decisions regarding hiring and promotion.</para><para>(3) If a private employer offers a voluntary veterans preference employment policy, a veteran desiring to use such policy shall provide the private employer with a copy of the veteran's Department of Defense Form 214, also known as the DD Form 214, or its successor form. A spouse of a veteran desiring to use such preference shall provide the private employer with a copy of the veteran's Department of Defense Form 214 or its successor form, proof of marriage to the veteran, and either (a) a copy of the veteran's disability verification from the United States Department of Veterans Affairs demonstrating a one hundred percent permanent disability rating or (b) a copy of the veteran's Department of Defense Form 1300 or its successor form documenting that the veteran was killed in hostile action.</para><para>(4) If a private employer implements a voluntary veterans preference employment policy, it shall notify the Commissioner of Labor of such policy. The commissioner shall use the information to maintain a registry of the private employers that have a voluntary veterans preference employment policy in Nebraska.</para><para>(5) A voluntary veterans preference employment policy shall not be considered a violation of any state or local equal employment opportunity law including the Nebraska Fair Employment Practice Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB272, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Fair Employment Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1125.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>