<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id42">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id44" statutenumber="48-804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>48-804</statuteno><catchline id="id47">Commissioners,
appointment, term; vacancy; removal; presiding officer; selection; duties;
quorum; applicability of law.</catchline><para>(1) The Commission
of Industrial Relations shall be composed of five commissioners appointed
by the Governor, with the advice and consent of the Legislature. The commissioners
shall be representative of the public. Each commissioner shall be appointed
and hold office for a term of six years and until a successor has qualified.
In case of a vacancy, the Governor shall appoint a successor to fill the vacancy
for the unexpired term.</para>
<para>(2) Any commissioner may be removed by the Governor for the
same causes as a judge of the district court may be removed.</para>
<para>(3) The commissioners shall, on July 1 of every odd-numbered
year by a majority vote, select one of their number as presiding officer for
the next two years, who shall preside at all hearings by the commission en
banc, and shall assign the work of the commission to the several commissioners
and perform such other supervisory duties as the needs of the commission may
require. A majority of the commissioners shall constitute a quorum to transact
business. The act or decision of any three of the commissioners shall in all
cases be deemed the act or decision of the commission. Three commissioners shall preside over and decide all industrial
disputes where the matter at issue is the comparability of wages, benefits,
and terms and conditions of employment.</para>
<para>(4) The commission shall not be subject to the Administrative
Procedure Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 178, &#167; 4, p. 588; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 407, &#167; 2, p. 1407; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 819, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 444, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB472, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB397, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
