<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-622.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>48-622.03</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Worker Training Board;
created; members; chairperson; annual program plan; report.</catchline><para>(1)
There is hereby created as of January 1, 1996, the Nebraska Worker Training
Board consisting of seven members appointed and serving for terms determined
by the Governor as follows:</para>
<para>(a) A representative of employers in Nebraska;</para>
<para>(b) A representative of employees in Nebraska;</para>
<para>(c) A representative of the public;</para>
<para>(d) The Commissioner of Labor or a designee;</para>
<para>(e) The Director of Economic Development or a designee;</para>
<para>(f) The Commissioner of Education or a designee; and</para>
<para>(g) The chairperson of the governing board of the Nebraska Community
College Association or a designee.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning July 1, 1996, and annually thereafter, the Governor shall
appoint a chairperson for the board. The chairperson shall be either the representative
of the employers, the representative of the employees, or the representative
of the public.</para>
<para>(3) Beginning July 1, 1996, through
June 30, 2015, the board shall prepare an annual program plan
for the upcoming fiscal year containing guidelines for the program financed
by the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund. Beginning July 1, 2015, and annually thereafter, the board
shall prepare an annual program plan for the upcoming fiscal year containing
guidelines for the program financed by the Nebraska Training and Support Cash
Fund. The guidelines shall include, but not be limited to, guidelines
for certifying training providers, criteria for evaluating requests for the
use of money under section 48-622.02, and guidelines for requiring employers
to provide matching funds. The guidelines shall give priority to training
that contributes to the expansion of the Nebraska workforce and increasing
the pool of highly skilled workers in Nebraska.</para>
<para>(4) Beginning September 1, 1997, through
June 30, 2015, the board shall provide a report to the Governor
covering the activities of the program financed by the Nebraska Training and
Support Trust Fund for the previous fiscal year. Beginning July 1, 2015, and annually thereafter, the board
shall provide a report to the Governor covering the activities of the program
financed by the Nebraska Training and Support Cash Fund for the previous fiscal
year. The report shall contain an assessment of the effectiveness
of the program and its administration.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB631, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB997, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>