<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-122.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-122.01</statuteno><catchline>Compensation; schedule.</catchline><para>Compensation under section 48-122 shall be payable in the amount and to the following persons subject to the maximum limits specified in sections 48-122 and 48-122.03:</para><para>(1) If there is a widow or widower and no children of the deceased, as defined in section 48-124, to such widow or widower, sixty-six and two-thirds percent of the average weekly wage of the deceased, during widowhood or widowerhood;</para><para>(2) To the widow or widower, if there is a child or children living with the widow or widower, sixty percent of the average weekly wage of the deceased, or fifty-five percent, if such child is not or such children are not living with a widow or widower, and, in addition thereto, fifteen percent for each child. When there are two or more such children, the indemnity benefits payable on account of such children shall be divided among such children, share and share alike;</para><para>(3) Two years' indemnity benefits in one lump sum shall be payable to a widow or widower upon remarriage;</para><para>(4) To the children, if there is no widow or widower, sixty-six and two-thirds percent of such wage for one child, and fifteen percent for each additional child, divided among such children, share and share alike;</para><para>(5) The income benefits payable on account of any child under this section shall cease when he or she dies, marries, or reaches the age of nineteen, or when a child over such age ceases to be physically or mentally incapable of self-support, or if actually dependent ceases to be actually dependent, or, if enrolled as a full-time student in any accredited educational institution, ceases to be so enrolled or reaches the age of twenty-five. A child who originally qualified as a dependent by virtue of being less than nineteen years of age may, upon reaching age nineteen, continue to qualify if he or she satisfies the tests of being physically or mentally incapable of self-support, actual dependency, or enrollment in an educational institution;</para><para>(6) To each parent, if actually dependent, twenty-five percent;</para><para>(7) To the brothers, sisters, grandparents, and grandchildren, if actually dependent, twenty-five percent to each such dependent. If there should be more than one of such dependents, the total income benefits payable on account of such dependents shall be divided share and share alike;</para><para>(8) The income benefits of each beneficiary under subdivisions (6) and (7) of this section shall be paid until he or she, if a parent or grandparent, dies, marries, or ceases to be actually dependent, or, if a brother, sister, or grandchild, dies, marries, or reaches the age of nineteen or if over that age ceases to be physically or mentally incapable of self-support, or ceases to be actually dependent; and</para><para>(9) A person ceases to be actually dependent when his or her income from all sources exclusive of workers' compensation income benefits is such that, if it had existed at the time as of which the original determination of actual dependency was made, it would not have supported a finding of dependency. In any event, if the present annual income of an actual dependent person including workers' compensation income benefits at any time exceeds the total annual support received by the person from the deceased employee, the workers' compensation benefits shall be reduced so that the total annual income is no greater than such amount of annual support received from the deceased employee. In all cases, a person found to be actually dependent shall be presumed to be no longer actually dependent three years after each time as of which the person was found to be actually dependent. This presumption may be overcome by proof of continued actual dependency as defined in this subdivision and section 48-124.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 193, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1221, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>