<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-125.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-125.02</statuteno><catchline>State employee claim; Prompt Payment Act applicable; other claims; processing of claim; requirements; failure to pay; effect; presumption of payment.</catchline><para>(1) Regarding payment of a claim for medical, surgical, or hospital services for a state employee under the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act, the Prompt Payment Act applies.</para><para>(2) For claims other than claims under subsection (1) of this section regarding payment of a claim for medical, surgical, or hospital services for an employee under the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act:</para><para>(a) The workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer shall notify the provider within fifteen business days after receiving a claim as to what information is necessary to process the claim. Failure to notify the provider assumes the workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer has all information necessary to pay the claim. The workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer shall pay providers in accordance with sections 48-120 and 48-120.04 within thirty business days after receipt of all information necessary to process the claim. Failure to pay the provider within the thirty days will cause the workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer to reimburse the provider's billed charges instead of the scheduled or contracted fees;</para><para>(b) If a claim is submitted electronically, the claim is presumed to have been received on the date of the electronic verification of receipt by the workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer or its clearinghouse. If a claim is submitted by mail, the claim is presumed to have been received five business days after the claim has been placed in the United States mail with first-class postage prepaid. The presumption may be rebutted by sufficient evidence that the claim was received on another day or not received at all; and</para><para>(c) Payment of a claim by the workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer means the receipt of funds by the provider. If payment is submitted electronically, the payment is presumed to have been received on the date of the electronic verification of receipt by the provider or the provider's clearinghouse. If payment is submitted by mail, the payment is presumed to have been received five business days after the payment has been placed in the United States mail with first-class postage prepaid. The presumption may be rebutted by sufficient evidence that the payment was received on another day or not received at all.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB588, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Prompt Payment Act,</emphasis> see section 81-2401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>