
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id121"><amendatorysection statutenumber="48-628.12" chaptername="Labor"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-628.12</statuteno><catchline>Benefits; disqualification; leave work voluntarily without good cause.</catchline><para>An individual shall be disqualified for benefits:</para><para>(1) For any benefit year beginning before October 1, 2018:</para><para>(a) For the week in which he or she has left work voluntarily without good cause, if so found by the commissioner, and for the thirteen weeks immediately thereafter. For purposes of this subdivision, a temporary employee of a temporary help firm has left work voluntarily without good cause if the temporary employee does not contact the temporary help firm for reassignment upon completion of an assignment and the temporary employee has been advised by the temporary help firm of his or her obligation to contact the temporary help firm upon completion of assignments and has been advised by the temporary help firm that the temporary employee may be denied benefits for failure to do so; or</para><para>(b) For the week in which he or she has left work voluntarily for the sole purpose of accepting previously secured, permanent, full-time, insured work, if so found by the commissioner, and for the two weeks immediately thereafter. For this subdivision to apply, such work shall:</para><para>(i) Be accepted by the individual;</para><para>(ii) Offer a reasonable expectation of betterment of wages or working conditions, or both; and</para><para>(iii) Enable the individual to earn wages payable to him or her; or</para><para>(2) For any benefit year beginning on or after October 1, 2018, for the week in which he or she has left work voluntarily without good cause, if so found by the commissioner, and for all subsequent weeks until the individual has earned wages in insured work in an amount of at least four times his or her weekly benefit amount and has separated from the most recent subsequent employment under nondisqualifying conditions. For purposes of this subdivision, a temporary employee of a temporary help firm has left work voluntarily without good cause if the temporary employee does not contact the temporary help firm for reassignment upon completion of an assignment and the temporary employee has been advised by the temporary help firm of his or her obligation to contact the temporary help firm upon completion of assignments and has been advised by the temporary help firm that the temporary employee may be denied benefits for failure to do so.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 42. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>