<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-121.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-121.01</statuteno><catchline>Maximum and minimum weekly income benefit; amounts; Governor; power to suspend.</catchline><para>(1)(a)(i) Commencing July 1, 1991, the maximum weekly income benefit under sections 48-121 and 48-122 shall be two hundred sixty-five dollars.</para><para>(ii) Commencing June 1, 1994, the maximum weekly income benefit under sections 48-121 and 48-122 shall be three hundred ten dollars.</para><para>(iii) Commencing January 1, 1995, the maximum weekly income benefit under sections 48-121 and 48-122 shall be three hundred fifty dollars.</para><para>(b) Commencing January 1, 1996, and each January 1 thereafter, the maximum weekly income benefit under sections 48-121 and 48-122 shall be one hundred percent, computed to the next higher whole dollar, of the state average weekly wage determined pursuant to section 48-121.02, except that for the purposes of calendar years commencing after 1996, the Governor may not later than November 15, 1996, and not later than each November 15 thereafter, conduct a public hearing after not less than thirty days' notice to consider whether he or she should issue an order to suspend the effectiveness of the change in the maximum weekly income benefit otherwise required by this subdivision for the ensuing calendar year. In order to make his or her decision, the Governor shall consider such factors as recent trends in economic conditions in the state, general wage levels, workers' compensation benefit levels, and workers' compensation premium levels. After such hearing but not later than November 30 immediately thereafter, the Governor may issue an order to suspend the effectiveness of the change in the maximum weekly income benefit otherwise required by this subdivision for the ensuing calendar year.</para><para>(2) The minimum weekly income benefit under sections 48-121 and 48-122 shall be forty-nine dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 608, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 292, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 313, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 757, &#167; 5. </para></source><annotation><para>Section 48-121 does not prohibit a worker from concurrently receiving statutory benefits for separate injuries arising out of separate accidents, so long as the combined payments do not exceed the maximum weekly rate allowed by this section. Vega v. Iowa Beef Processors, 264 Neb. 282, 646 N.W.2d 643 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 