<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-637"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-637</statuteno><catchline>Administrative appeals; decisions; effect in subsequent proceedings; certification of questions.</catchline><para>The final decisions of an appeal tribunal, and the principles of law declared by it in arriving at such decisions, unless expressly or impliedly overruled by a later decision of the tribunal or by a court of competent jurisdiction, shall be binding upon the commissioner and any deputy in subsequent proceedings which involve similar questions of law; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that if in connection with any subsequent proceeding the commissioner or a deputy has serious doubt as to the correctness of any principle so declared he may certify his findings of fact in such case, together with the question of law involved to the appeal tribunal, which, after giving notice and reasonable opportunity for hearing upon the law to all parties to such proceedings, shall thereupon certify to the commissioner, such deputy and such parties its answer to the question submitted. If the question thus certified to the appeal tribunal arises in connection with a claim for benefits, the tribunal in its discretion may remove to itself the entire proceedings on such claim, and, after proceeding in accordance with the requirements of sections 48-633 to 48-643 with respect to proceedings before an appeal tribunal, shall render its decision upon the entire claim.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 4, p. 387; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-637.</para></source><annotation><para>Provision is made for appeal to district court from determination of appeal tribunal. Beecham v. Falstaff Brewing Corporation, 150 Neb. 792, 36 N.W.2d 233 (1949).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 