<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id43" statutenumber="48-647"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-647</statuteno><catchline id="id46">Benefits; assignments void; exemption from legal process; exception; child support obligations; Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program benefits overissuance; disclosure required; collection.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any assignment, pledge, or encumbrance of any right to benefits which are or may become due or payable under sections 48-623 to 48-626 shall be void except as set forth in this section. Such rights to benefits shall be exempt from levy, execution, attachment, or any other remedy provided for the collection of debt. Benefits received by any individual, so long as they are not mingled with other funds of the recipient, shall be exempt from any remedy for the collection of all debts, except debts incurred for necessaries furnished to such individual or his or her spouse or dependents during the time when such individual was unemployed.</para><para>(b) Any assignment, pledge, or encumbrance of any right or claim to contributions or to any money credited to any employer's reserve account in the Unemployment Compensation Fund shall be void. Such right or claim to contributions or money shall be exempt from levy, execution, attachment, or any other remedy provided for the collection of debt.</para><para>(c) Any waiver of any exemption provided for in this section shall be void.</para><para>(2)(a) An individual filing a new claim for unemployment compensation shall, at the time of filing such claim, disclose whether or not he or she owes child support obligations as defined under subdivision (h) of this subsection. If such individual discloses that he or she owes child support obligations and is determined to be eligible for unemployment compensation, the commissioner shall notify the Department of Health and Human Services that the individual has been determined to be eligible for unemployment compensation.</para><para>(b) The commissioner shall deduct and withhold from any unemployment compensation otherwise payable to an individual disclosing child support obligations:</para><para>(i) The amount specified by the individual to the commissioner to be deducted under this subsection, if neither subdivision (ii) nor (iii) of this subdivision is applicable;</para><para>(ii) The amount, if any, determined pursuant to an agreement between the Department of Health and Human Services and such individual owing the child support obligations to have a specified amount withheld if such agreement is submitted to the commissioner, unless subdivision (iii) of this subdivision is applicable; or</para><para>(iii) The amount otherwise required to be deducted and withheld from such unemployment compensation pursuant to legal process, as that term is defined in subdivision (2)(i) of this section, properly served upon the commissioner.</para><para>(c) Any amount deducted and withheld under subdivision (b) of this subsection shall be paid by the commissioner to the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(d) Any amount deducted and withheld under subdivision (b) or (g) of this subsection shall for all purposes be treated as if it were paid to the individual as unemployment compensation and paid by such individual to the Department of Health and Human Services in satisfaction of his or her child support obligations.</para><para>(e) For purposes of subdivisions (a) through (d) and (g) of this subsection, the term unemployment compensation shall mean any compensation payable under the Employment Security Law, including amounts payable by the commissioner pursuant to an agreement under any federal law providing for compensation, assistance, or allowances with respect to unemployment.</para><para>(f) This subsection shall apply only if appropriate arrangements have been made for reimbursement by the Department of Health and Human Services for the administrative costs incurred by the commissioner under this section which are attributable to child support obligations being enforced by the department.</para><para>(g) The Department of Health and Human Services and the commissioner shall develop and implement a collection system to carry out the intent of this subdivision. The collection system shall, at a minimum, provide that:</para><para>(i) The commissioner shall periodically notify the Department of Health and Human Services of the information listed in section 43-1719 with respect to individuals determined to be eligible for unemployment compensation during such period;</para><para>(ii) Unless the county attorney, the authorized attorney, or the Department of Health and Human Services has sent a notice on the same support order under section 43-1720, upon the notification required by subdivision (2)(g)(i) of this section, the Department of Health and Human Services shall send notice to any such individual who owes child support obligations and who is subject to income withholding pursuant to subdivision (2)(a), (2)(b)(ii), or (2)(b)(iii) of section 43-1718.01. The notice shall be sent by certified mail to the last-known address of the individual and shall state the same information as required under section 43-1720;</para><para>(iii)(A) If the support obligation is not based on a foreign support order entered pursuant to section 43-1729 and the individual requests a hearing, the Department of Health and Human Services shall hold a hearing within fifteen days of the date of receipt of the request. The hearing shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. The assignment shall be held in abeyance pending the outcome of the hearing. The department shall notify the individual and the commissioner of its decision within fifteen days of the hearing; and</para><para>(B) If the support obligation is based on a foreign support order entered pursuant to section 43-1729 and the individual requests a hearing, the county attorney or authorized attorney shall apply the procedures described in sections 43-1732 to 43-1742;</para><para>(iv)(A) If no hearing is requested by the individual under this subsection or pursuant to a notice sent under section 43-1720, (B) if after a hearing under this subsection or section 43-1721 the Department of Health and Human Services determines that the assignment should go into effect, (C) in cases in which the court has ordered income withholding for child support pursuant to subsection (1) of section 43-1718.01, or (D) in cases in which the court has ordered income withholding for child support pursuant to section 43-1718.02 and the case subsequently becomes one in which child support collection services are being provided under Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, the Department of Health and Human Services shall certify to the commissioner the amount to be withheld for child support obligations from the individual's unemployment compensation. Such amount shall not exceed the maximum amount permitted to be withheld under section 303(b) of the federal Consumer Credit Protection Act, 15 U.S.C. 1673(b)(2)(A) and (B), and the amount withheld to satisfy a debt of child support when added to the amount withheld to pay current support shall not exceed such maximum amount;</para><para>(v) The collection system shall comply with the requirements of Title III and Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, as amended;</para><para>(vi) The collection system shall be in addition to and not in substitution for or derogation of any other available remedy; and</para><para>(vii) The Department of Health and Human Services and the commissioner shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out subdivision (2)(g) of this section.</para><para>(h) For purposes of this subsection, the term child support obligations shall include only obligations which are being enforced pursuant to a plan described in section 454 of the federal Social Security Act which has been approved by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under Part D of Title IV of the federal Social Security Act.</para><para>(i) For purposes of this subsection, the term legal process shall mean any writ, order, summons, or other similar process in the nature of garnishment, which:</para><para>(i) Is issued by a court of competent jurisdiction of any state, territory, or possession of the United States or an authorized official pursuant to order of such a court of competent jurisdiction or pursuant to state law. For purposes of this subdivision, the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services shall be deemed an authorized official pursuant to order of a court of competent jurisdiction or pursuant to state law; and</para><para>(ii) Is directed to, and the purpose of which is to compel, the commissioner to make a payment for unemployment compensation otherwise payable to an individual in order to satisfy a legal obligation of such individual to provide child support.</para><para>(j) Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize withholding from unemployment compensation of any support obligation other than child support obligations.</para><para>(3)(a) An individual filing a new claim for unemployment compensation shall, at the time of filing such claim, disclose whether or not he or she owes an uncollected overissuance, as defined in 7 U.S.C. 2022(c)(1) as such section existed on January 1, 2017, of Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program benefits, if not otherwise known or disclosed to the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency. The commissioner shall notify the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency enforcing such obligation of any individual disclosing that he or she owes an uncollected overissuance whom the commissioner determines is eligible for unemployment compensation.</para><para>(b) The commissioner shall deduct and withhold from any unemployment compensation payable to an individual who owes an uncollected overissuance:</para><para>(i) The amount specified by the individual to the commissioner to be deducted and withheld under this subsection;</para><para>(ii) The amount, if any, determined pursuant to an agreement submitted to the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency under 7 U.S.C. 2022(c)(3)(A), as such section existed on January 1, 2017; or</para><para>(iii) Any amount otherwise required to be deducted and withheld from unemployment compensation pursuant to 7 U.S.C. 2022(c)(3)(B), as such section existed on January 1, 2017.</para><para>(c) Any amount deducted and withheld under this subsection shall be paid by the commissioner to the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency.</para><para>(d) Any amount deducted and withheld under subdivision (b) of this subsection shall be treated as if it were paid to the individual as unemployment compensation and paid by such individual to the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency as repayment of the individual's uncollected overissuance.</para><para>(e) For purposes of this subsection, unemployment compensation means any compensation payable under the Employment Security Law, including amounts payable by the commissioner pursuant to an agreement under any federal law providing for compensation, assistance, or allowances with respect to unemployment.</para><para>(f) This subsection applies only if arrangements have been made for reimbursement by the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency for the administrative costs incurred by the commissioner under this subsection which are attributable to the repayment of uncollected overissuances to the state Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 15, p. 400; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-714; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-647; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 801, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 974, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 523, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1224, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 240, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 275; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 106; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 864, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 217; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 60. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>