<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id35" statutenumber="48-155"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>48-155</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Presiding judge;
how chosen; term; powers and duties; acting presiding judge; selection; powers.</catchline>
<para>The judges of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court shall,
on July 1 of every odd-numbered year by a majority vote, select one of their
number as presiding judge for the next two years, subject to approval of the
Supreme Court. The presiding judge may designate one of the other judges to
act as presiding judge in his or her stead whenever necessary during the disqualification,
disability, or absence of the presiding judge. The presiding judge shall rule
on all matters submitted to the compensation court except those arising in
the course of hearings
or as otherwise provided by law, assign or direct the assignment of the work
of the compensation court to the several judges, clerk, and employees who
support the judicial proceedings of the compensation court, preside at such
meetings of the judges of the compensation court as may be necessary, and
perform such other supervisory duties as the needs of the compensation court
may require. During the disqualification, disability, or absence of the presiding
judge, the acting presiding judge shall exercise all of the powers of the
presiding judge.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 57, &#167; 4, p. 189; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-165; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-155; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 113, &#167; 2, p. 364; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 225, &#167; 1, p. 791; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 396, &#167; 1, p. 1386; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 360, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1221, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 13, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB151, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
