<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-631"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>48-631</statuteno><catchline>Claims; redetermination; time; notice;
appeal.</catchline><para>The deputy may reconsider a determination whenever
he or she finds
that an error in computation or identity has occurred in connection therewith,
or that wages of the claimant pertinent to such determination, but not considered
in connection therewith, have been newly discovered, or that benefits have
been allowed or denied or the amount of benefits fixed on the basis of misrepresentations
of fact, but no such redetermination shall be made after two years from the
date of the original determination. Notice of any such redetermination shall
be promptly given to the parties entitled to notice of the original determination,
in the manner prescribed in section 48-630 with respect to notice of an original
determination. If the amount of benefits is increased or decreased upon such
redetermination, an appeal therefrom solely with respect to the matters involved
in such increase or decrease may be filed in the manner and subject to the
limitations provided in section 48-634. Subject to the same
limitations and for the same reasons, the Commissioner of Labor may reconsider
the determination, in any case in which the final decision has been rendered
by an appeal tribunal or a court, and may apply to the tribunal or court which
rendered such final decision to issue a revised decision. In the event that
an appeal involving an original determination is pending as of the date a
redetermination thereof is issued, such appeal, unless withdrawn, shall be
treated as an appeal from such redetermination.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 4, p. 385; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-631; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 238, &#167; 5, p. 711; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB11, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
