<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-310"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-310</statuteno><catchline>Children under sixteen; working hours; limit; posting of notice; fee; special permit; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) No person under sixteen years of age shall be employed or permitted to work in any employment as defined in section 48-301 more than forty-eight hours in any one week, nor more than eight hours in any one day, nor before the hour of 6 in the morning, nor after the hour of 8 in the evening if the child is under the age of fourteen, nor after the hour of 10 in the evening if such child is between the ages of fourteen and sixteen. The person issuing the work certificate may limit or extend the stated hour in individual cases by endorsement on the certificate, except a child shall only be permitted to work after the hour of 10 p.m. if there is no school scheduled for the following day and, if he or she is between fourteen and sixteen years of age, he or she has consented to such extension by signing his or her name on the endorsement extension, and his or her employer has obtained a special permit from the Department of Labor. The Department of Labor may issue a special permit to allow employment of such child beyond 10 p.m. upon being satisfied, after inspection of the working conditions, of the safety, healthfulness, and general welfare to the child of the business premises. The special permit may be issued for periods not to exceed ninety days and may be renewed only after reinspection. The fee for each permit or renewal shall be established by rule and regulation of the Commissioner of Labor, and all money so collected by the commissioner shall be remitted to the State Treasurer who shall credit the funds to the General Fund. Every employer shall post in a conspicuous place in every room where such children are employed a printed notice stating the hours required of them each day, the hours of commencing and stopping work, and the time allowed for meals. The printed form of such notice shall be furnished by the Department of Labor.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsections (3) and (4) of this section, no person under sixteen years of age shall be employed or permitted to work as a door-to-door solicitor.</para><para>(3) A person under sixteen years of age engaged in the delivery or distribution of newspapers or shopping news may be employed or permitted to work as a door-to-door solicitor of existing customers of such newspapers or shopping news.</para><para>(4) A person under sixteen years of age is permitted to work as a door-to-door solicitor if he or she is working on behalf of his or her own individual entrepreneurial endeavor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1907, c. 66, &#167; 10, p. 266; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3584; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. IV, art. III, &#167; 10, p. 556; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7678; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 48-310; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-310; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 290, &#167; 3, p. 869; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 296, &#167; 6, p. 808; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 399, &#167; 1, p. 1389; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 330, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 484, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>