<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-622.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>48-622.02</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Training and Support Trust
Fund; created; investment; use; Administrative Costs Reserve Account; created;
use.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created in the state treasury a
special fund to be known as the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund.
Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. All money deposited or paid into the
fund is hereby appropriated and made available to the commissioner. No expenditures
shall be made from the fund without the written authorization of the Governor
upon the recommendation of the commissioner. Any interest earned on money
in the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund shall be credited to the Nebraska
Training and Support Trust Fund.</para>
<para>(2) Money in the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund shall be used
for (a) administrative costs of establishing, assessing, collecting, and maintaining
state unemployment insurance tax liability and payments, (b) administrative
costs of creating, maintaining, and dissolving the State Unemployment Insurance
Trust Fund and the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund, (c) support of
public and private job training programs designed to train, retrain, or upgrade
work skills of existing Nebraska workers of
for-profit and not-for-profit businesses, (d) recruitment of workers
to Nebraska, (e) training new employees of expanding Nebraska businesses,
(f) the costs of creating a common web portal for the attraction of businesses
and workers to Nebraska, and (g) payment of unemployment insurance benefits
if solvency of the state's account in the Unemployment Trust Fund and of the
State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund so require.</para>
<para>(3) There is hereby created within the Nebraska Training and Support
Trust Fund a separate account to be known as the Administrative Costs Reserve
Account. Money shall be allocated from the Nebraska Training and Support Trust
Fund to the Administrative Costs Reserve Account in amounts sufficient to
pay the anticipated administrative costs identified in subdivisions (2)(a)
through (g) of this section. The administrative costs determined to be applicable
to creation and operation of the State Unemployment Insurance Trust Fund and
the Nebraska Training and Support Trust Fund shall be paid out of the Administrative
Costs Reserve Account.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1337, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB631, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB911, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>