<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id26" statutenumber="48-227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-227</statuteno><catchline id="id29">Veterans preference; examination or numerical scoring; notice and application; statement; veteran; duty; notice; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Veterans who obtain passing scores on all parts or phases of an examination or numerical scoring shall have five percent added to their passing score if a claim for such preference is made on the application. An additional five percent shall be added to the passing score or numerical scoring of any disabled veteran.</para><para>(2) When no examination or numerical scoring is used, the preference shall be given to the qualifying veteran if two or more equally qualified candidates are being considered for the position.</para><para>(3) All notices of positions of employment available for veterans preference and all applications for such positions by the state or its governmental subdivisions shall state that the position is subject to a veterans preference.</para><para>(4) A veteran desiring to use a veterans preference shall provide the hiring authority with a copy of the veteran's Department of Defense Form 214, also known as the DD Form 214, or its successor form or record. A spouse of a veteran desiring to use a veterans preference shall provide the hiring authority with a copy of the veteran's Department of Defense Form 214 or its successor form or record, a copy of the veteran's disability verification from the United States Department of Veterans Affairs demonstrating a one hundred percent permanent disability rating, and proof of marriage to the veteran. Any marriage claimed for veterans preference must be valid under Nebraska law.</para><para>(5) Within thirty days after filling a position, veterans who have applied and are not hired shall be notified by regular mail, electronic mail, telephone call, or personal service that they have not been hired. Such notice also shall advise the veteran of any administrative appeal available.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 751, &#167; 3, p. 2827; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 5, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 54, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB588, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB497, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>