<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-661"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-661</statuteno><catchline>Employer; election to become subject to Employment Security Law; written election to become or cease to be an employer; termination of coverage.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, any employer not otherwise subject to the Employment Security Law, who is or becomes an employer subject to such law within any calendar year, shall be subject to such law during the whole of such calendar year.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this section, an employer, other than an employer subject by reason of subdivision (4)(a) of section 48-604, shall cease to be an employer subject to the Employment Security Law only as of January 1 of any calendar year, if he or she files with the commissioner, on or before January 31 of such year, a written application for termination of coverage, and the commissioner finds: (a) That there were no twenty different days, each day being in a different calendar week, within the preceding calendar year within which such employer employed one or more individuals in employment subject to such law and there was no calendar quarter within the preceding calendar year in which such employer paid wages for employment in the total sum of fifteen hundred dollars or more; (b) if the employer is subject by reason of subdivision (9) of section 48-603 there were no twenty different days, each being in a different calendar week, within the preceding calendar year within which such employer employed four or more individuals in employment subject to that section; (c) if the employer is subject by reason of subdivision (10) of section 48-603 there were no twenty different days, each being in a different calendar week, within the preceding calendar year within which such employer employed ten or more individuals in employment subject to that section and there was no calendar quarter within the preceding calendar year in which such employer paid remuneration in cash for employment subject to that section in the total sum of twenty thousand dollars or more; or (d) if the employer is subject by reason of subdivision (11) of section 48-603 there was no calendar quarter within the preceding calendar year in which such employer paid cash remuneration in the total sum of one thousand dollars or more for services in employment subject to that section. The commissioner may on his or her motion terminate the coverage of any employer who has not made such written request, but is otherwise eligible to terminate. Any employer whose entire experience account has been transferred to another employer under section 48-654 may request termination as of the date of such transfer if such request is made within thirty days after the determination is made allowing the transfer.</para><para>(3) An employer not otherwise subject to the Employment Security Law, who files with the commissioner his or her written election to become an employer subject thereto for not less than two calendar years, shall, with the written approval of such election by the commissioner, become an employer subject thereto to the same extent as all other employers, as of the date stated in such approval, and shall cease to be subject thereto as of January 1 of any calendar year subsequent to such two calendar years, only if on or before January 31 of such year, he or she has filed with the commissioner a written notice to that effect. Any employer of any person in this state for whom services that do not constitute employment as defined in section 48-604 are performed, may file with the commissioner a written election that all such services performed by individuals in his or her employ in one or more distinct establishments or places of business shall be deemed to constitute employment for all the purposes of the Employment Security Law for not less than two calendar years. Upon the written approval of such election by the commissioner, such services shall be deemed to constitute employment subject to such law from and after the date stated in such approval. Such services shall cease to be deemed employment subject hereto as of January 1 of any calendar year subsequent to such two calendar years, only if on or before January 31 of such year such employer has filed with the commissioner a written notice to that effect.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 8, p. 386; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 6, p. 243; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 6, p. 394; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-708; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-661; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 167, &#167; 11, p. 537; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 190, &#167; 10, p. 549; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 293, &#167; 1, p. 878; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 302, &#167; 1, p. 821; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 651, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 35, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 509, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 339, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 1, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 