<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-631"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-631</statuteno><catchline>Claims; redetermination; time; notice; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) The adjudicator may reconsider a determination if he or she finds that:</para><para>(a) An error in computation or identity has occurred in connection with the determination;</para><para>(b) Wages of the claimant pertinent to such determination, but not considered in connection therewith, have been newly discovered; or</para><para>(c) Benefits have been allowed or denied or the amount of benefits has been set based on misrepresentations of fact.</para><para>(2) No such redetermination shall be made after two years from the date of the original determination.</para><para>(3) Notice of any redetermination shall be promptly given to the parties entitled to notice of the original determination, in the manner prescribed in section 48-630 with respect to notice of an original determination.</para><para>(4) If the amount of benefits is increased or decreased by a redetermination, an appeal therefrom may be filed solely with respect to the matters involved in such increase or decrease in the manner and subject to the limitations provided in section 48-634. Subject to the same limitations and for the same reasons, the Commissioner of Labor may reconsider the determination, in any case in which the final decision has been rendered by a hearing officer or a court, and may apply to the hearing officer or court which rendered such final decision to issue a revised decision. In the event that an appeal involving an original determination is pending as of the date a redetermination is issued, such appeal, unless withdrawn, shall be treated as an appeal of the redetermination.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 4, p. 385; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-631; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 238, &#167; 5, p. 711; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB11, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 51. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>