<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-625"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>48-625</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Benefits; weekly payment; how computed.</catchline><para>(1) Each eligible individual who is unemployed in any week shall be paid with respect to such week a benefit in an amount equal to his or her full weekly benefit amount if he or she has wages payable to him or her with respect to such week equal to one-fourth of such benefit amount or less. In the event he or she has wages payable to him or her with respect to such week greater than one-fourth of such benefit amount, he or she shall be paid with respect to that week an amount equal to the individual's weekly benefit amount less that part of wages payable to the individual with respect to that week in excess of one-fourth of the individual's weekly benefit amount. In the event there is any deduction from such individual's weekly benefit amount because of earned wages pursuant to this subsection or as a result of the application of subdivision (5) of section 48-628, the resulting benefit payment, if not an exact dollar amount, shall be computed to the next lower dollar amount.</para><para>Any amount of unemployment compensation payable to any individual for any week, if not an even dollar amount, shall be rounded to the next lower full dollar amount.</para><para>No deduction shall be made for any supplemental payments received by a claimant under the provisions of subsection (b) of section 408 of Title IV of the Veterans Readjustment Assistance Act of 1952.</para><para>The percentage of benefits and the percentage of extended benefits which are federally funded may be adjusted in accordance with the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, Public Law 99-177.</para><para>(2) Vacation leave pay including that received in a lump sum or upon separation from employment shall be prorated in an amount reasonably attributable to each week claimed and considered payable with respect to such week.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 108, &#167; 3, p. 375; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 56, &#167; 2, p. 234; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 94, &#167; 2, p. 382; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 48-703; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-625; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 163, &#167; 8, p. 424; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 167, &#167; 5, p. 531; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 800, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 801, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 248, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 950, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 461, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 1, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 608, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 739, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB271, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>