<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-603.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-603.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Indian tribes; applicability of Employment Security Law.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of the Employment Security Law, unless the context otherwise requires, the term employer shall include any Indian tribe for which services in employment as provided in subdivision (4)(a) of section 48-604 are performed.</para><para>(2) The term employment shall include service performed in the employ of an Indian tribe, as defined in 26 U.S.C. 3306(u), as such section existed on January 1, 2015, if such service is excluded from employment as defined in the Federal Unemployment Tax Act solely by reason of 26 U.S.C. 3306(c)(7), as such section existed on January 1, 2015, and is not otherwise excluded from employment under the Employment Security Law. For purposes of this section, the exclusions from employment in subdivisions (6)(f) and (6)(g) of section 48-604 shall be applicable to services performed in the employment of an Indian tribe.</para><para>(3) Benefits based on service in employment defined in this section shall be payable in the same amount, on the same terms, and subject to the same conditions as benefits payable on the basis of other covered employment under the Employment Security Law. Section 48-628.06 shall apply to services performed in an educational institution or educational service agency owned or operated by an Indian tribe.</para><para>(4)(a) Indian tribes or tribal units, subdivisions, subsidiaries, or business enterprises wholly owned by such Indian tribes, subject to the Employment Security Law, shall pay combined tax under the same terms and conditions as all other subject employers, unless they elect to make payments in lieu of contributions equal to the amount of benefits attributable to service in the employ of the Indian tribe.</para><para>(b) Indian tribes electing to make payments in lieu of contributions shall make such election in the same manner and under the same conditions as provided in section 48-649.04 pertaining to state and local governments subject to the Employment Security Law. Indian tribes shall determine if reimbursement for benefits paid will be elected by the tribe as a whole, by individual tribal units, or by combinations of individual tribal units.</para><para>(c) Except as provided in subsection (7) of this section, Indian tribes or tribal units shall be billed for the full amount of benefits attributable to service in the employ of the Indian tribe or tribal unit on the same schedule as other employing units that have elected to make payments in lieu of contributions.</para><para>(d) At the discretion of the commissioner, any Indian tribe or tribal unit that elects to become liable for payments in lieu of contributions shall be required within thirty days after the effective date of its election to:</para><para>(i) Execute and file with the commissioner a surety bond approved by the commissioner; or</para><para>(ii) Deposit with the commissioner money or securities on the same basis as other employers with the same election option.</para><para>(5)(a)(i) Failure of the Indian tribe or tribal unit to make required payments, including assessments of interest and penalty, within ninety days of receipt of the bill will cause the Indian tribe to lose the option to make payments in lieu of contributions, as described in subsection (4) of this section, for the following tax year unless payment in full is received before combined tax rates for the next tax year are computed.</para><para>(ii) Any Indian tribe that loses the option to make payments in lieu of contributions due to late payment or nonpayment, as described in subdivision (5)(a)(i) of this section, shall have such option reinstated if, after a period of one year, all combined taxes have been paid timely and no combined tax, payments in lieu of contributions for benefits paid, penalties, or interest remain outstanding.</para><para>(b)(i) Failure of the Indian tribe or any tribal unit thereof to make required payments, including assessments of interest and penalty, after all collection activities deemed necessary by the commissioner have been exhausted will cause services performed for such tribe to not be treated as employment for purposes of subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(ii) The commissioner may determine that any Indian tribe that loses coverage under subdivision (5)(b)(i) of this section may have services performed for such tribe again included as employment for purposes of subsection (2) of this section if all contributions, payments in lieu of contributions, penalties, and interest have been paid.</para><para>(6) Notices of payment and reporting delinquency to Indian tribes or their tribal units shall include information that failure to make full payment within the prescribed timeframe:</para><para>(a) Will cause the Indian tribe to be liable for taxes under the Federal Unemployment Tax Act, as the act existed on January 1, 2015;</para><para>(b) Will cause the Indian tribe to lose the option to make payments in lieu of contributions; and</para><para>(c) Could cause the Indian tribe to be excepted from the definition of employer, as provided in subsection (1) of this section, and services in the employ of the Indian tribe, as provided in subsection (2) of this section, to be excepted from employment.</para><para>(7) Extended benefits paid that are attributable to service in the employ of an Indian tribe and not reimbursed by the federal government shall be financed in their entirety by such Indian tribe.</para><para>(8) If an Indian tribe fails to make payments required under this section, including assessments of interest and penalty, within ninety days after a final notice of delinquency, the commissioner shall immediately notify the United States Internal Revenue Service and the United States Department of Labor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 192, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 199, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 739, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB271, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB172, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>