<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1625"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1625</statuteno><catchline>State board; state plan; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The state board shall submit to the Governor recommendations for
changes in the state plan submitted to the Secretary of Labor outlining the
five-year strategy for the statewide workforce investment system for the State
of Nebraska in accordance with section 112 of the federal Workforce Investment
Act of 1998, 29
U.S.C. 2822.</para>
<para>(2) The state board shall submit to the chairperson and members of the
Business and Labor Committee of the Legislature, the chairperson of each of
the standing committees of the Legislature, the Speaker of the Legislature,
the Clerk of the Legislature, the Department of Health and Human Services,
the Department of Economic Development, the State Department of Education,
and the Department of Labor a copy of any recommendations for modification
of the state plan and the annual report of the state board. The recommendations and report submitted to the committees,
the Speaker of the Legislature, and the Clerk of the Legislature shall be
submitted electronically. The annual report of the state board
shall include information on the number of individuals served, the state's
average cost per individual receiving training or placement services, short-term
and long-term performance measures of job placements, and training and skill
levels of training participants. In order to promote better accountability,
such reports shall contain measures of accomplishment of the performance measures
set forth at 20 C.F.R. 666.100, as the regulation existed on March 2, 2001,
and shall use consistent units of measure in order to provide comparability
both within a single annual report and between different annual reports.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 64.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>