<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1617"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1617</statuteno><catchline>Purpose of act.</catchline><para>(1) The purpose of the Nebraska Workforce Investment Act is to provide workforce investment activities through statewide and local workforce investment systems that will improve the quality of the workforce and enhance the productivity and competitiveness of Nebraska through its workforce.</para><para>(2) The Legislature recognizes the following principles:</para><para>(a) Nebraskans must upgrade their skills to succeed in today's workplace;</para><para>(b) In business, workforce skills are the key competitive advantage;</para><para>(c) Workforce skills will be Nebraska's primary job-creating incentive for business;</para><para>(d) Efficiency and accountability mandate the consolidation of program services and the elimination of unwarranted duplication;</para><para>(e) Streamlined state and local partnerships must focus on outcomes, not process;</para><para>(f) Locally designed, customer-focused, market-driven service delivery which offers a single point of entry for all services is vital; and</para><para>(g) Job training services must be developed in concert with the input and needs of existing employers and businesses, and must consider anticipated demand for targeted job opportunities.</para><para>In recognition of these principles, the Nebraska Workforce Investment Act will coordinate state and local activities to increase employment, retention, occupational skills, and earnings in the workforce. The act will enhance the productivity and competitiveness of state business and industry and encourage continuous improvement in worker preparation beginning with youth in middle school through adulthood.</para><para>(3) Nebraska's workforce development plan must implicate a comprehensive, consumer-driven, employment and career development system that meets the needs of all members of the workforce, including those entering the workforce for the first time, those in employment transition, and those currently employed but seeking to enhance their skills for continued career advancement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 