<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1623"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1623</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Workforce Investment Board;
members.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Workforce Investment Board is established
to assist in the development of a state plan to carry out the functions described
in the federal Workforce Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) The state board shall include:</para>
<para>(a) The Governor;</para>
<para>(b) Two members of the Legislature selected by and serving at the pleasure
of the Speaker of the Legislature; and</para>
<para>(c) Members appointed by the Governor who serve at the pleasure of the
Governor who are:</para>
<para>(i) Representatives of business in the state who:</para>
<para>(A) Are owners of businesses, chief executives or operating officers
of businesses, and other business executives or employers with optimum policymaking
or hiring authority, including members of local boards described in subdivision
(2)(a)(i) of section 48-1620;</para>
<para>(B) Represent businesses with employment opportunities that reflect
the employment opportunities of the state; and</para>
<para>(C) Are appointed from among individuals nominated by state business
organizations and business trade associations;</para>
<para>(ii) A representative
of health care employers of the state who conducts statewide health workforce
planning and training;</para><para>(iii) Chief
elected officials representing both cities and counties;</para>
<para>(iv) Representatives of labor
organizations who have been nominated by state labor federations;</para>
<para>(v) Representatives of individuals
and organizations that have experience with respect to youth programs authorized
under section 129 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2854;</para>
<para>(vi) Representatives of individuals
and organizations that have experience and expertise in the delivery of workforce
investment activities, including chief executive officers of community colleges
and community-based organizations within the state;</para>
<para>(vii)(A) The officials from
each of the lead state agencies with responsibility for the programs and activities
that are described in section 48-1619 and carried out by one-stop partners;
and</para>
<para>(B) In any case in which no lead state agency official has responsibility
for such a program, service, or activity, a representative in the state with
expertise relating to such program, service, or activity; and</para>
<para>(viii) Such other representatives
and state agency officials as the Governor may designate.</para>
<para>(3) The two members of the Legislature serving on the state board shall
be nonvoting, ex officio members. All other members shall be voting members.
The Governor may designate a representative to participate on his or her behalf
in state board committee and general meetings. Such representative shall be
entitled to vote on matters brought before the board and shall be considered
a member of the board for purposes of determining if a quorum is present.</para>
<para>(4) Members of the board that represent organizations, agencies, or
other entities shall be individuals with optimum policymaking authority within
the organizations, agencies, or entities. The members of the board shall represent
diverse regions of the state, including urban, rural, and suburban areas.</para>
<para>(5) A majority of the voting members of the state board shall be private
sector representatives described in subdivision (2)(c)(i) of this section.
The Governor shall select a chairperson and a vice-chairperson for the state
board from among the representatives described in such subdivision.</para>
<para>(6) To transact business at all meetings of the state board, a quorum
of voting members must be present. A majority of the voting members shall
constitute a quorum of the Nebraska Workforce Investment Board.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 194, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB210, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB502, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
