<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1618</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Workforce Investment Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Chief elected official means the chief elected executive officer of a unit of general local government in a local area, and in a case in which a local area includes more than one unit of general local government, the individuals designated under the local area plan or the agreement described in section 117(c)(1)(B) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2832(c)(1)(B);</para><para>(2) Commissioner means the Commissioner of Labor;</para><para>(3) Core services means services described in section 134(d)(2) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2864(d)(2), available to individuals who are adults or dislocated workers through the one-stop delivery system;</para><para>(4) Federal Workforce Investment Act means the Workforce Investment Act of 1998, 29 U.S.C. 2801 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(5) Intensive services means services described in section 134(d)(3) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2864(d)(3), available to adults and dislocated workers respectively through the one-stop delivery system who are unemployed and are unable to obtain employment through core services and who have been determined by a one-stop operator to be in need of more intensive services in order to obtain employment or who are employed but who are determined by a one-stop operator to be in need of such intensive services in order to obtain or retain employment that allows for self-sufficiency;</para><para>(6) Local area means a local area designated by the Governor and described in the state plan pursuant to section 116 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2831;</para><para>(7) Local board means a local workforce investment board established pursuant to section 48-1620;</para><para>(8) One-stop career center means a physical location that provides access to all one-stop services and partners, is certified by the local area, and includes an onsite resource area that meets the minimum criteria as established by the local area plan;</para><para>(9) One-stop partner means an entity described in section 121(b)(1) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2841(b)(1), that is participating with the approval of the local board and chief elected official, in the operation of a one-stop delivery system;</para><para>(10) State board means the Nebraska Workforce Investment Board established pursuant to section 48-1623; and</para><para>(11) Youth council means a council established under section 117(h) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2832(h).</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 