<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id42"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1305</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Apprenticeship Council; established; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Apprenticeship Council is established as an advisory council within the department pursuant to 29 C.F.R. 29.13(a)(2), as such regulation existed on January 1, 2026.</para><para>(2) Members of the council shall be appointed by the Governor for terms of three years.</para><para>(3)(a) The council shall include at least five voting members appointed by the Governor. The members must be primarily based in Nebraska and familiar with apprenticeable occupations. Familiarity with apprenticeable occupations shall be determined by actual experience with a Nebraska apprenticeship program.</para><para>(b) The council shall have an equal number of representatives of employer organizations and employee organizations and include public members who shall not number in excess of the number named to represent either employer organizations or employee organizations. The council shall be comprised of representatives with experience in both large apprenticeship programs and small apprenticeship programs in Nebraska.</para><para>(c) The Governor shall appoint a chairperson of the council from among the voting members.</para><para>(d) The commissioner, or the commissioner's designee, shall serve as an ex officio, nonvoting member.</para><para>(4) The council shall do all of the following:</para><para>(a) Advise the Nebraska Office of Registered Apprenticeship regarding the duties set forth in the Nebraska Registered Apprenticeship Act; and</para><para>(b) Provide community outreach and education regarding the benefits of apprenticeship.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB847, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>