<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id747"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1101.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1101.01</statuteno><catchline>Purpose.</catchline><para>(1) It is the policy of this state to foster the employment of all employable persons in the state on the basis of merit regardless of their race, color, religion, sex, disability, national origin, or military or veteran status and to safeguard their right to obtain and hold employment without discrimination because of their race, color, religion, sex, disability, national origin, or military or veteran status. Denying equal opportunity for employment because of race, color, religion, sex, disability, national origin, or military or veteran status is contrary to the principles of freedom and is a burden on the objectives of the public policy of this state.</para><para>(2) Except for the veterans preference provided for in sections 48-225 to 48-231, the policy of this state does not require any person to employ an applicant for employment because of his or her race, color, religion, sex, disability, national origin, or military or veteran status, and the policy of this state does not require any employer, employment agency, labor organization, or joint labor-management committee to grant preferential treatment to any individual or to any group because of race, color, religion, sex, disability, national origin, or military or veteran status.</para><para>(3) It is the public policy of this state that all people in Nebraska, both with and without disabilities, shall have the right and opportunity to enjoy the benefits of living, working, and recreating within this state. It is the intent of the Legislature that state and local governments, Nebraska businesses, Nebraska labor organizations, and Nebraskans with disabilities understand their rights and responsibilities under the law regarding employment discrimination and the prevention of discrimination on the basis of disability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para> R.S.1943, (2021), &#167; 48-1101; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 78. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>