<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id5" statutenumber="48-1230"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">48-1230</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Employer; regular
paydays; altered; notice; deduct, withhold, or divert portion of wages; when; itemized statement; duty of employer to
furnish; unpaid wages; when due.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as otherwise provided in this section, each employer shall pay all
wages due its employees on regular days designated by the employer or agreed
upon by the employer and employee. Thirty days' written notice shall be given
to an employee before regular paydays are altered by an employer. An employer
may deduct, withhold, or divert a portion of an employee's wages only when
the employer is required to or may do so by state or federal law or by order
of a court of competent jurisdiction or the employer has written agreement
with the employee to deduct, withhold, or divert.</para>
<para>(2) Within
ten working days after a written request is made by an employee, an employer
shall furnish such employee with an itemized statement listing the wages earned
and the deductions made from the employee's wages under subsection (1) of
this section for each pay period that earnings and deductions were made. The
statement may be in print or electronic format.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in section
48-1230.01:</para>
<para>(a) Whenever an employer, other than a political subdivision,
separates an employee from the payroll, the unpaid wages shall become due
on the next regular payday or within two weeks of the date of termination,
whichever is sooner; and</para>
<para>(b) Whenever a political subdivision separates an employee
from the payroll, the unpaid wages shall become due within two weeks of the
next regularly scheduled meeting of the governing body of the political subdivision
if such employee is separated from the payroll at least one week prior to
such meeting, or if an employee of a political subdivision is separated from
the payroll less than one week prior to the next regularly scheduled meeting
of the governing body of the political subdivision, the unpaid wages shall
be due within two weeks of the following regularly scheduled meeting of the
governing body of the political subdivision.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 220A, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1130, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB255, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB884, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The Nebraska Wage Payment and Collection Act does not represent a very clear mandate of public policy which would warrant recognition of an exception to the employment-at-will doctrine. Malone v. American Bus. Info., 262 Neb. 733, 634 N.W.2d 788 (2001).</para><para>Application of the Wage Payment and Collection Act does not affect the need to satisfy the requisites of pursuing a claim against a city of the metropolitan class. Thompson v. City of Omaha, 235 Neb. 346, 455 N.W.2d 538 (1990).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>