<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1222"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1222</statuteno><catchline>Equal Opportunity Commission; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall have the power and the duty to carry out the provisions of sections 48-1219 to 48-1227.</para><para>(2) For this purpose, the commission shall have the power to enter the place of employment of any employer to inspect and copy payrolls and other employment records, to compare character of work and operations on which persons employed by him are engaged, to question such person, and to obtain such other information as is reasonably necessary to the administration and enforcement of the provisions of sections 48-1219 to 48-1227.</para><para>(3) The commission shall have power to examine witnesses under oath, and to require by subpoena the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of any documentary evidence relating to the subject matter of any investigation undertaken pursuant to this section. Witnesses summoned by the commission shall be paid the same fees as are allowed witnesses attending the district court. In the event of the failure of a person to attend, testify or produce documents under or in response to a subpoena, the district court for the county in which the appearance is requested on application of the commission may issue an order requiring such person to appear before the commission, or to produce documentary evidence, and any failure to obey such order of the court may be punished by the court as a contempt thereof.</para><para>(4) The commission is authorized to endeavor to eliminate pay practices unlawful under the provisions of sections 48-1219 to 48-1227, by informal methods of conference, conciliation and persuasion, and to supervise the payment of wages owing to any employee under the provisions of sections 48-1219 to 48-1227.</para><para>(5) The commission shall have power to issue such regulations, not inconsistent with the purpose of sections 48-1219 to 48-1227, as it deems necessary or appropriate to carry out its provisions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 389, &#167; 4, p. 1367. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For witness fees in district court,</emphasis> see section 33-139.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 