<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id64">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id66" statutenumber="48-1401"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1401</statuteno><catchline id="id69">Political subdivisions;
exception; deferred compensation plan; provisions; investment; payment for civil damages; conditions.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any county, municipality, or other political subdivision,
instrumentality, or agency of the State of Nebraska, except any agency subject
to sections 84-1504 to 84-1506 or section 85-106, 85-320, or 85-606.01, may
enter into an agreement to defer a portion of any individual's compensation
derived from such county, municipality, or other political subdivision, instrumentality,
or agency to a future period in time pursuant to section 457 of the Internal
Revenue Code. Such deferred compensation plan shall be voluntary and shall
be available to all regular employees and elected officials.</para>
<para>(2) The compensation to be deferred may never exceed the total
compensation to be received by the individual from the employer or exceed
the limits established by the Internal Revenue Code for such a plan.</para>
<para>(3) All compensation deferred under the plan, all property
and rights purchased with the deferred compensation, and all investment income
attributable to the deferred compensation, property, or rights shall be held
in trust for the exclusive benefit of participants and their beneficiaries
by the county, municipality, or other political subdivision, instrumentality,
or agency until such time as payments are made under the terms of the deferred
compensation plan.</para>
<para>(4) The county, municipality, or other political subdivision,
instrumentality, or agency shall designate its treasurer or an equivalent
official, including the State Treasurer, to be the custodian of the funds
and securities of the deferred compensation plan.</para>
<para>(5) The county, municipality, or other political subdivision,
instrumentality, or agency may invest the compensation to be deferred under
an agreement in or with: (a) Annuities; (b) mutual funds; (c) banks; (d) savings
and loan associations; (e) trust companies qualified to act as fiduciaries
in this state; (f) an organization established for the purpose of administering
public employee deferred compensation retirement plans and authorized to do
business in the State of Nebraska; or (g) investment advisers as defined in
the federal Investment Advisers Act of 1940.</para>
<para>(6) The deferred compensation program shall exist and serve
in addition to, and shall not be a part of, any existing retirement or pension
system provided for state, county, municipal, or other political subdivision,
instrumentality, or agency employees, or any other benefit program.</para>
<para>(7) Any compensation deferred under such a deferred compensation
plan shall continue to be included as regular compensation for the purpose
of computing the retirement, pension, or social security contributions made
or benefits earned by any employee.</para>
<para>(8) Any sum so deferred shall not be included in the computation
of any federal or state taxes withheld on behalf of any such individual.</para>
<para>(9) The state, county, municipality, or other political subdivision,
instrumentality, or agency shall not be responsible for any investment results
entered into by the individual in the deferred compensation agreement.</para>
<para>(10)(a) Except as provided in subdivision
(b) of this subsection, all compensation deferred under the plan,
all property and rights purchased with the deferred compensation, and all
investment income attributable to the deferred compensation, property, or
rights shall not be subject to garnishment, attachment, levy, the operation
of bankruptcy or insolvency laws, or any other process of law whatsoever and
shall not be assignable.</para>
<para>(b) If a participant
in the deferred compensation plan is convicted of or pleads no contest to
a felony that is defined as assault, sexual assault, kidnapping, child abuse,
false imprisonment, or theft by embezzlement and is found liable for civil
damages as a result of such felony, following distribution of the participant's
compensation deferred under the plan, property and rights purchased with the
deferred compensation, or investment income attributable to the deferred compensation,
property, or rights from the plan, the court may order the payment of such
compensation, property and rights, or investment income for such civil damages,
except that the compensation, property and rights, or investment income to
the extent reasonably necessary for the support of the participant or any
of his or her beneficiaries shall be exempt from such payment. Any order for
payment of compensation, property and rights, or investment income shall not
be stayed on the filing of any appeal of the conviction. If the conviction
is reversed on final judgment, all compensation, property and rights, or investment
income paid as civil damages shall be forfeited and returned to the participant.
The changes made to this section by Laws 2012, LB916, shall apply to persons
convicted of or who have pled no contest to such a felony and who have been
found liable for civil damages as a result of such felony prior to, on, or
after April 7, 2012.</para><para>(11) Nothing contained
in this section shall in any way limit, restrict, alter, amend, invalidate,
or nullify any deferred compensation plan previously instituted by any county,
municipality, or other political subdivision, instrumentality, or agency of
the State of Nebraska, and any such plan is hereby authorized and approved.</para>
<para>(12) If a county has not established a deferred compensation
plan pursuant to this section, each individual may require that the county
enter into an agreement with the individual to defer a portion of such individual's
compensation and place it under the management and supervision of the state
deferred compensation plan created pursuant to sections 84-1504 to 84-1506.
If such an agreement is made, the county shall designate the State Treasurer
as custodian of such deferred compensation funds and such deferred compensation
funds shall become a part of the trust administered by the Public Employees
Retirement Board pursuant to sections 84-1504 to 84-1506.</para>
<para>(13) For purposes of this section, individual means (a) any
person designated by the county, municipality, or other political subdivision,
instrumentality, or agency of the State of Nebraska, except any agency subject
to sections 84-1504 to 84-1506 or section 85-106, 85-320, or 85-606.01, as
a permanent part-time or full-time employee of the county, municipality, or
other political subdivision, instrumentality, or agency and (b) a person under
contract providing services to the county, municipality, or other political
subdivision, instrumentality, or agency of the State of Nebraska, except any
agency subject to sections 84-1504 to 84-1506 or section 85-106, 85-320, or
85-606.01, and who has entered into a contract with such county, municipality,
political subdivision, instrumentality, or agency to have compensation deferred
prior to August 28, 1999.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 328, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>