<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id666"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1715"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1715</statuteno><catchline>Seed corn producer; forms; required; Director of Agriculture; reports; directory of certified exempt contractors; powers and duties; confidentiality.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2025, any seed corn producer in this state that intends to utilize one or more farm labor contractors for the roguing or detasseling of seed corn shall:</para><para>(a) Complete and submit a form to the Director of Agriculture that the seed corn producer intends to utilize one or more farm labor contractors for detasseling or roguing of seed corn during the current or upcoming growing season; and</para><para>(b) Complete and submit a signed and notarized form prescribed by the Department of Agriculture, under penalty of perjury, to the Director of Agriculture on or after August 1 but not later than September 1 of each year. Such form shall contain the following information for the crop year for which such form is filed:</para><para>(i) The total number of acres of seed corn the producer planted in this state;</para><para>(ii) The name of each certified exempt contractor, if any, with whom the producer contracted for labor for the roguing of seed corn and the total number of acres rogued by each such operation;</para><para>(iii) The name of each nonexempt contractor, if any, with whom the producer contracted for labor for the roguing of seed corn and the total number of acres rogued by each such operation;</para><para>(iv) The name of each certified exempt contractor, if any, with whom the producer contracted for labor for the detasseling of seed corn and the total number of acres detasseled by each such operation; and</para><para>(v) The name of each nonexempt contractor, if any, with whom the producer contracted for labor for the detasseling of seed corn and the total number of acres detasseled by each such operation.</para><para>(2) The Director of Agriculture shall publish a report on the Department of Agriculture's website not later than September 30, 2025, and by each September 30 thereafter. Such report shall aggregate the following information provided by seed corn producers pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of this section for each crop year:</para><para>(a) The total number of acres of seed corn planted in this state;</para><para>(b) The total number of acres of seed corn detasseled by certified exempt contractors;</para><para>(c) The total number of acres of seed corn rogued by certified exempt contractors;</para><para>(d) The total number of acres of seed corn detasseled by nonexempt contractors;</para><para>(e) The total number of acres of seed corn rogued by nonexempt contractors; and</para><para>(f) The total number of acres of seed corn for which seed corn producers did not utilize detasseling or roguing services by any farm labor contractor.</para><para>(3)(a) By January 1, 2025, the Director of Agriculture shall publish a directory on the Department of Agriculture's website, updated by December 31 of each year, that contains:</para><para>(i) The name of each certified exempt contractor that provides detasseling or roguing services for seed corn;</para><para>(ii) The address of the headquarters for each such certified exempt contractor; and</para><para>(iii) Contact information for each such certified exempt contractor, including a telephone number if available.</para><para>(b) Beginning in 2025, the Director of Agriculture shall send, by registered mail, a copy of the most recently updated directory described in this subsection to the following:</para><para>(i) Within ten days after receiving a form described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section, to the seed corn producer that submitted such form; and</para><para>(ii) By January 15 of each year, to each seed corn producer that submitted the form described in subdivision (1)(b) of this section during the previous year.</para><para>(4) The Director of Agriculture shall prescribe the method by which any such seed corn producer may submit a form under subdivision (1)(a) of this section and receive a copy of the most recently updated directory described in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(5) Any form submitted by any seed corn producer under this section shall not be a public record subject to disclosure pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09.</para><para>(6) The Department of Agriculture may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB844, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>