<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1619"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1619</statuteno><catchline>One-stop career center; program and activity requirements; affiliate career centers.</catchline><para>(1) At least one comprehensive one-stop career center shall be established in each local area of the state. State agencies providing services at a comprehensive one-stop career center include the Department of Labor, Department of Health and Human Services, Department of Economic Development, State Department of Education, and community colleges in the area where the one-stop career center is located. The following minimum level of programs and activities shall be available at a comprehensive one-stop career center:</para><para>(a) Adult, youth, and dislocated workers employment and training programs provided under Title I of the federal Workforce Investment Act;</para><para>(b) Programs authorized under the Wagner-Peyser Act, 29 U.S.C. 49 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(c) Adult education and literacy activities authorized under Title II of the federal Workforce Investment Act;</para><para>(d) Programs authorized under Title I of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, 29 U.S.C. 720 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(e) Welfare to work programs authorized under section 403(a)(5) of the Social Security Act, 42 U.S.C. 603(a)(5), as the section existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(f) Older American community service programs authorized under Title V of the Older Americans Act of 1965, 42 U.S.C. 3056 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(g) Postsecondary education activities authorized under the Carl D. Perkins Vocational and Applied Technology Education Act, 20 U.S.C. 2301 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001. Preference shall be given to the applications of one-stop career centers which have submitted and obtained approval of a business plan to the local board;</para><para>(h) Trade adjustment assistance for workers authorized under Title II of the Trade Act of 1974, 19 U.S.C. 2271 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(i) Job counseling and training and placement services for veterans authorized under Chapter 41 of Title 38 of the United States Code, as such chapter existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(j) Employment and training activities carried out under the Community Services Block Grant Act, 42 U.S.C. 9901 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001;</para><para>(k) Employment and training activities carried out by the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development; and</para><para>(l) Unemployment benefit and reemployment services authorized under the Employment Security Law.</para><para>(2) In addition to the mandatory programs in subsection (1) of this section, a local board is encouraged to include participation by the Department of Correctional Services, youth programs authorized under section 129 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2854, the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, public and private postsecondary educational institutions, and secondary education activities authorized under the Carl D. Perkins Vocational and Applied Technology Education Act, 20 U.S.C. 2301 et seq., as the act existed on March 2, 2001.</para><para>(3) A local board may establish one or more affiliate career centers which offer one or more of the program services described in subsection (1) of this section and can provide a direct link to the comprehensive one-stop career center through technology.</para><para>(4) Comprehensive one-stop career centers shall utilize a common intake and common application system for persons applying for services or training offered at the one-stop career center.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Employment Security Law,</emphasis> see section 48-601.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 