<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1622"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1622</statuteno><catchline>One-stop career centers; core services; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) As a part of the core services required by section 134(d)(2)(E)(i) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2864(d)(2)(E)(i), one-stop career centers shall provide current listings of job opportunities.</para><para>(2) Funds allocated to a local area for adults and dislocated workers pursuant to the federal Workforce Investment Act shall be used to provide intensive services to adults and dislocated workers, respectively:</para><para>(a) Who are unemployed and are unable to obtain employment through core services provided in section 134(d)(2) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2864(d)(2), and have been determined by a one-stop career center partner to be in need of more intensive services in order to obtain employment; or</para><para>(b) Who are employed but who are determined by a one-stop career center operator to be in need of intensive services in order to obtain or retain employment that allows for self-sufficiency.</para><para>(3) Intensive services shall be provided through the one-stop delivery system:</para><para>(a) Directly through one-stop career center operators identified pursuant to section 121(d) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2841(d); or</para><para>(b) Through contracts with service providers, which may include contracts with public, private for-profit, and private nonprofit service providers, approved by the local board.</para><para>(4) Intensive services may include the following:</para><para>(a) Comprehensive and specialized assessments of the skill levels and service needs of adults and dislocated workers, which may include:</para><para>(i) Diagnostic testing and use of other assessment tools; and</para><para>(ii) Indepth interviewing and evaluation to identify employment barriers and appropriate employment goals;</para><para>(b) Development of an individual employment plan, to identify the employment goals, appropriate achievement objectives, and appropriate combination of services for the participant to achieve the employment goals;</para><para>(c) Group counseling;</para><para>(d) Individual counseling and career planning;</para><para>(e) Case management for participants seeking training services; and</para><para>(f) Short-term prevocational services, including development of learning skills, communication skills, interviewing skills, punctuality, personal maintenance skills, and professional conduct, to prepare individuals for employment or training.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in section 134(d)(4)(G)(ii) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2864(d)(4)(G)(ii), training services provided in accordance with section 134 of the federal act, 29 U.S.C. 2864, shall be provided through the use of individual training accounts and shall be provided to eligible individuals through the one-stop delivery system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 