<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1621"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1621</statuteno><catchline>Local boards; youth council; duties.</catchline><para>(1) There shall be established, as a subcommittee within each local board, a youth council appointed by the local board, in cooperation with the chief elected official for the local area.</para><para>(2) The membership of each youth council shall include:</para><para>(a) Members of the local board with special interest or expertise in youth policy;</para><para>(b) Representatives of youth service agencies, including juvenile justice and local law enforcement agencies;</para><para>(c) Representatives of local public housing authorities;</para><para>(d) Parents of youth, including, but not limited to, parents of eligible youth seeking assistance under the Nebraska Workforce Investment Act;</para><para>(e) Individuals, including former participants, and representatives of organizations, that have experience relating to youth activities;</para><para>(f) Representatives of the Job Corps, as appropriate; and</para><para>(g) Representatives of local kindergarten through grade twelve school boards, community colleges, and such other individuals as the chairperson of the local board, in cooperation with the chief elected official, determines to be appropriate.</para><para>(3) Members of the youth council who are not members of the local board shall be voting members of the youth council and nonvoting members of the local board.</para><para>(4) The duties of the youth council include:</para><para>(a) Developing the portions of the local plan relating to eligible youth, as determined by the chairperson of the local board;</para><para>(b) Subject to the approval of the local board and consistent with section 123 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2843:</para><para>(i) Recommending eligible providers of youth programs authorized under section 129 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2854, to be awarded grants or contracts on a competitive basis by the local board to carry out the youth programs; and</para><para>(ii) Conducting oversight with respect to the eligible providers of youth activities in the local area;</para><para>(c) Coordinating youth activities authorized under section 129 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2854, in the local area;</para><para>(d) The coordination of career preparation programs; and</para><para>(e) Other duties determined to be appropriate by the chairperson of the local board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 