<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1620"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1620</statuteno><catchline>Local workforce investment boards; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1) In each local area of the state a local workforce investment board shall be established and certified by the Governor. The local board shall set policy for the portion of the statewide workforce investment system within the local area. The chief elected official in a local area shall appoint the members of the local board for such area in accordance with the criteria established under subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) The Governor, in consultation with the state board, shall establish criteria for use by chief elected officials in the local areas for appointment of members of the local boards in such local areas. Such criteria shall require, at a minimum, that the membership of each local board:</para><para>(a) Shall include:</para><para>(i) Representatives of business in the local area who:</para><para>(A) Are owners of businesses, chief executives or operating officers of businesses, and other business executives or employers with optimum policymaking or hiring authority;</para><para>(B) Represent businesses with employment opportunities that reflect the employment opportunities of the local area; and</para><para>(C) Are appointed from among individuals nominated by local business organizations and business trade associations;</para><para>(ii) Representatives of local educational entities, including representatives of local educational agencies, local kindergarten through grade twelve school boards, career preparation education providers, entities providing adult education and literacy activities, and postsecondary educational institutions, including representatives of community colleges, where such entities exist, selected from among individuals to be nominated by regional or local educational agencies, institutions, or organizations representing such local educational entities;</para><para>(iii) Representatives of labor organizations, for a local area in which employees are represented by labor organizations, nominated by local labor federations, or for a local area in which no employees are represented by such organizations, nominated by other representatives of employees;</para><para>(iv) Representatives of community-based organizations, including organizations representing individuals with disabilities and veterans, for a local area in which such organizations are present;</para><para>(v) Representatives of economic development agencies, including private sector economic development entities; and</para><para>(vi) Representatives of each of the required one-stop career center partners. The required partners are those described in subsection (1) of section 48-1619; and</para><para>(b) May include such other individuals or representatives of entities as the chief elected official in the local area determines appropriate.</para><para>(3) Members of the local board that represent organizations, agencies, or other entities shall be individuals with optimum policymaking authority within the organizations, agencies, or entities.</para><para>(4) A majority of the members of the local board shall be representatives described in subdivision (2)(a)(i) of this section. The local board shall elect a chairperson for the local board from among the representatives described in such subdivision.</para><para>(5) To transact business at all meetings of the local board, a quorum of members must be present. A quorum of a local workforce investment board shall be a majority of its appointed members.</para><para>(6) A local board in partnership with the chief elected official shall develop and submit to the Governor and the state board a proposed comprehensive five-year local plan in accordance with section 118 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2833.</para><para>(7) The local plan is subject to approval by the Governor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 