<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id00" statutenumber="48-1102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1102</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Fair Employment Practice Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Person shall include one or more individuals, labor unions, partnerships, limited liability companies, associations, corporations, legal representatives, mutual companies, joint-stock companies, trusts, unincorporated organizations, trustees, trustees in bankruptcy, or receivers;</para><para>(2) Employer shall mean a person engaged in an industry who has fifteen or more employees for each working day in each of twenty or more calendar weeks in the current or preceding calendar year, any agent of such a person, and any party whose business is financed in whole or in part under the Nebraska Investment Finance Authority Act regardless of the number of employees and shall include the State of Nebraska, governmental agencies, and political subdivisions, but such term shall not include (a) the United States, a corporation wholly owned by the government of the United States, or an Indian tribe or (b) a bona fide private membership club, other than a labor organization, which is exempt from taxation under section 501(c) of the Internal Revenue Code;</para><para>(3) Labor organization shall mean any organization which exists wholly or in part for one or more of the following purposes: Collective bargaining; dealing with employers concerning grievances, terms, or conditions of employment; or mutual aid or protection in relation to employment;</para><para>(4) Employment agency shall mean any person regularly undertaking with or without compensation to procure employees for an employer or to procure for employees opportunities to work for an employer and shall include an agent of such a person but shall not include an agency of the United States, except that such term shall include the United States Employment Service and the system of state and local employment services receiving federal assistance;</para><para>(5) Covered entity shall mean an employer, an employment agency, a labor organization, or a joint labor-management committee;</para><para>(6) Privileges of employment shall mean terms and conditions of any employer-employee relationship, opportunities for advancement of employees, and plant conveniences;</para><para>(7) Employee shall mean an individual employed by an employer;</para><para>(8) Commission shall mean the Equal Opportunity Commission;</para><para>(9) Disability shall mean (a) a physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more of the major life activities of such individual, (b) a record of such an impairment, or (c) being regarded as having such an impairment. Disability shall not include homosexuality, bisexuality, transvestism, transsexualism, pedophilia, exhibitionism, voyeurism, gender-identity disorders not resulting in physical impairments, other sexual behavior disorders, problem gambling, kleptomania, pyromania, or psychoactive substance use disorders resulting from current illegal use of drugs;</para><para>(10)(a) Qualified individual with a disability shall mean an individual with a disability who, with or without reasonable accommodation, can perform the essential functions of the employment position that such individual holds or desires. Consideration shall be given to the employer's judgment as to what functions of a job are essential, and if an employer has prepared a written description before advertising or interviewing applicants for the job, this description shall be considered evidence of the essential functions of the job;</para><para>(b) Qualified individual with a disability shall not include any employee or applicant who is currently engaged in the illegal use of drugs when the covered entity acts on the basis of such use; and</para><para>(c) Nothing in this subdivision shall be construed to exclude as a qualified individual with a disability an individual who:</para><para>(i) Has successfully completed a supervised drug rehabilitation program or otherwise been rehabilitated successfully and is no longer engaging in the illegal use of drugs;</para><para>(ii) Is participating in a supervised rehabilitation program and is no longer engaging in such use; or</para><para>(iii) Is erroneously regarded as engaging in such use but is not engaging in such use;</para><para>(11) Reasonable accommodation, with respect to disability, shall include making existing facilities used by employees readily accessible to and usable by individuals with disabilities, job restructuring, part-time or modified work schedules, reassignment to a vacant position, acquisition or modification of equipment or devices, appropriate adjustment or modification of examinations, training manuals, or policies, the provision of qualified readers or interpreters, and other similar accommodations for individuals with disabilities. Reasonable accommodation, with respect to pregnancy, childbirth, or related medical conditions, shall include acquisition of equipment for sitting, more frequent or longer breaks, periodic rest, assistance with manual labor, job restructuring, light-duty assignments, modified work schedules, temporary transfers to less strenuous or hazardous work, time off to recover from childbirth, or break time and appropriate facilities for breast-feeding or expressing breast milk. Reasonable accommodation shall not include accommodations which the covered entity can demonstrate require significant difficulty or expense thereby posing an undue hardship upon the covered entity. Factors to be considered in determining whether an accommodation would pose an undue hardship shall include:</para><para>(a) The nature and the cost of the accommodation needed under the Nebraska Fair Employment Practice Act;</para><para>(b) The overall financial resources of the facility or facilities involved in the provision of the reasonable accommodation, the number of persons employed at such facility, the effect on expenses and resources, or the impact otherwise of such accommodation upon the operation of the facility;</para><para>(c) The overall financial resources of the covered entity, the overall size of the business of a covered entity with respect to the number of its employees, and the number, type, and location of its facilities; and</para><para>(d) The type of operation or operations of the covered entity, including the composition, structure, and functions of the work force of such entity, and the geographic separateness and administrative or fiscal relationship of the facility or facilities in question to the covered entity;</para><para>(12) Marital status shall mean the status of a person whether married or single;</para><para>(13) Because of sex or on the basis of sex shall include, but not be limited to, because of or on the basis of pregnancy, childbirth, or related medical conditions;</para><para>(14) Harass because of sex shall include making unwelcome sexual advances, requesting sexual favors, and engaging in other verbal or physical conduct of a sexual nature if (a) submission to such conduct is made either explicitly or implicitly a term or condition of an individual's employment, (b) submission to or rejection of such conduct by an individual is used as the basis for employment decisions affecting such individual, or (c) such conduct has the purpose or effect of unreasonably interfering with an individual's work performance or creating an intimidating, hostile, or offensive working environment;</para><para>(15) Unlawful under federal law or the laws of this state shall mean acting contrary to or in defiance of the law or disobeying or disregarding the law;</para><para>(16) Drug shall mean a controlled substance as defined in section 28-401;</para><para>(17) Illegal use of drugs shall mean the use of drugs, the possession or distribution of which is unlawful under the Uniform Controlled Substances Act, but shall not include the use of a drug taken under supervision by a licensed health care professional or any other use authorized by the Uniform Controlled Substances Act or other provisions of state law;</para><para>(18) Individual who is pregnant, who has given birth, or who has a related medical condition shall mean an individual with a known limitation who, with or without reasonable accommodation, can perform the essential functions of the employment position that such individual holds, desires, or may be temporarily assigned to. Consideration shall be given to the employer's judgment as to what functions of a job are essential, and if an employer has prepared a written description before advertising or interviewing applicants for the job, this description shall be considered evidence of the essential functions of the job;</para><para>(19) Race is inclusive of characteristics such as skin color, hair texture, and protective hairstyles; and</para><para>(20) Protective hairstyles includes braids, locks, and twists.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 276, &#167; 2, p. 783; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 306, &#167; 1, p. 829; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 120, &#167; 21, p. 551; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 265, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 266, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 161, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 67, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 626, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 14A, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 324, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1108, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 176, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 297; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 124, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 360, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB627, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB451, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Investment Finance Authority Act,</emphasis> see section 58-201.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Major life activities</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Drug use</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Major life activities</emphasis></para><para>Concentrating, thinking, and communicating are major life activities under subdivision (9) of this section. Marshall v. EyeCare Specialties, 293 Neb. 91, 876 N.W.2d 372 (2016).</para><para>Under subdivision (9) of this section, "major life activities" are those activities that are of central importance to daily life. Marshall v. EyeCare Specialties, 293 Neb. 91, 876 N.W.2d 372 (2016).</para><para>Under subdivision (9) of this section, to be substantially limited in the major life activity of working, the plaintiff must show that he or she was significantly restricted in the ability to perform either a class of jobs or a broad range of jobs in various classes as compared to the average person having comparable training, skills, and abilities. Marshall v. EyeCare Specialties, 293 Neb. 91, 876 N.W.2d 372 (2016).</para><para><emphasis>2. Drug use</emphasis></para><para>Drug addiction is an impairment under subdivision (9) of this section, but it is not a disability unless it substantially limits a major life activity or is perceived by the employer to substantially limit a major life activity. Marshall v. EyeCare Specialties, 293 Neb. 91, 876 N.W.2d 372 (2016).</para><para>A qualified individual with a disability includes an individual who has been rehabilitated successfully or who is erroneously regarded as engaging in the illegal use of drugs. Marshall v. EyeCare Specialties, 291 Neb. 264, 865 N.W.2d 343 (2015).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>To show that an employer regarded an employee as disabled under subdivision (9)(c) of this section, the employee must demonstrate either that (1) despite having no impairment at all, the employer mistakenly believed that the employee had an impairment that substantially limited one or more major life activities, or (2) the employee had a nonlimiting impairment that the employer mistakenly believed substantially limited one or more major life activities. Marshall v. EyeCare Specialties, 293 Neb. 91, 876 N.W.2d 372 (2016).</para><para>The threshold fact of consequence in a disability discrimination action is whether the plaintiff is a qualified individual with a disability⁚i.e., one who can perform the essential functions of the job with or without reasonable accommodations. Arens v. NEBCO, Inc., 291 Neb. 834, 870 N.W.2d 1 (2015).</para><para>The payroll method, in which an employee is counted on a given day if he or she was on the payroll on that day, should be used to determine whether an entity has the requisite number of employees to qualify as an employer as defined in subsection (2) of this section. Bluff's Vision Clinic v. Krzyzanowski, 251 Neb. 116, 555 N.W.2d 556 (1996).</para><para>Persons seeking relief under alleged violation of rights set out in section 48-1101 must be persons within the definitions set out in this section. Steier v. Crosier Fathers of Hastings, 242 Neb. 16, 492 N.W.2d 870 (1992).</para><para>Epilepsy is included within the definition of "disability," but only if the epilepsy is unrelated to the person's ability to engage in a particular occupation. Father Flanagan's Boys' Home v. Goerke, 224 Neb. 731, 401 N.W.2d 461 (1987).</para><para>These sections do not mandate the employment of firemen with visual defects which would affect their ability to engage in that occupation. McCrea v. Cunningham, 202 Neb. 638, 277 N.W.2d 52 (1979).</para><para>For purposes of subsection (2) of this section, to determine whether a person is an "employer", a "payroll method" shall be used, whereby a week is counted if an employer has 15 employees on the payroll for that week, regardless of whether or not each employee worked each day of the week in question. Bluff's Vision Clinic v. Krzyzanowski, 4 Neb. App. 380, 543 N.W.2d 761 (1996).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>