<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1624"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1624</statuteno><catchline>State board; duties.</catchline>
<para>The state board shall advise the Governor in:</para>
<para>(1) The development of the state plan;</para>
<para>(2) The development and continuous improvement of a statewide system
of services that are funded under the federal Workforce Investment Act carried
out through a one-stop delivery system described in section 134(c) of the
federal act, 29 U.S.C. 2864(c), that receives funds under the statewide workforce
investment system, including:</para>
<para>(a) The development of linkages in order to assure coordination and
nonduplication among the programs and activities described in section 48-1619;
and</para>
<para>(b) The review of local plans;</para>
<para>(3) Commenting at least once annually on the measures taken pursuant
to section 113(b)(14) of the federal Carl D. Perkins Vocational and Applied
Technology Education Act, 20 U.S.C. 2323(b), as such section existed on March
2, 2001. Such comments shall be included in the annual report provided for
in subsection (2) of section 48-1625;</para>
<para>(4) The designation of local areas as required in section 116 of the
federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2831;</para>
<para>(5) The development of allocation formulas for the distribution of funds
for adult employment and training activities and youth activities to local
areas as permitted under sections 128(b)(3)(B) and 133(b)(3)(B) of the federal
Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2853(b)(3)(B) and 29 U.S.C. 2863(b)(3)(B);</para>
<para>(6) The development and continuous improvement of comprehensive state
performance measures, including state adjusted levels of performance, to assess
the effectiveness of the workforce investment activities in the state as required
under section 136(b) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2871(b);</para>
<para>(7) The preparation of the annual report to the Secretary of Labor described
in section 136(d) of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 29 U.S.C. 2871(d);</para>
<para>(8) The development of the statewide employment statistics system described
in section 15(e) of the federal Wagner-Peyser Act, 29 U.S.C. 49 et seq., as
the section existed on March 2, 2001;</para>
<para>(9) The development of an application for an incentive grant under section
503 of the federal Workforce Investment Act, 20 U.S.C. 9273; and</para>
<para>(10) The development
of a plan which has a component to reduce the current and projected shortage
of health care workers in the state.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 193, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB502, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
