<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1903</statuteno><catchline>Test results; use; requirements.</catchline><para>Any results of any test performed on the body fluid or breath specimen of an employee, as directed by the employer, to determine the presence of drugs or alcohol shall not be used to deny any continued employment or in any disciplinary or administrative action unless the following requirements are met:</para><para>(1) A positive finding of drugs by preliminary screening procedures has been subsequently confirmed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry or other scientific testing technique which has been or may be approved by the department; and</para><para>(2) A positive finding of alcohol by preliminary screening procedures is subsequently confirmed by either:</para><para>(a) Gas chromatography with a flame ionization detector or other scientific testing technique which has been or may be approved by the department; or</para><para>(b) A breath-testing device operated by a breath-testing-device operator. Nothing in this subdivision shall be construed to preclude an employee from immediately requesting further confirmation of any breath-testing results by a blood sample if the employee voluntarily submits to give a blood sample taken by qualified medical personnel in accordance with the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department. If the confirmatory blood test results do not confirm a violation of the employer's work rules, any disciplinary or administrative action shall be rescinded.</para><para>Except for a confirmatory breath test as provided in subdivision (2)(b) of this section, all confirmatory tests shall be performed by a clinic, hospital, or laboratory which is certified pursuant to the federal Clinical Laboratories Improvement Act of 1967, 42 U.S.C. 263a.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 582, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 