<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-1116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-1116</statuteno><catchline>Equal Opportunity Commission; members; appointment; term; quorum; compensation; executive director; representation.</catchline><para>There is hereby established an Equal Opportunity Commission to consist of seven members to be appointed by the Governor. Terms of members shall be three years. As the terms of the members expire, the Governor shall appoint or reappoint the members of the commission for terms of three years to succeed the members whose terms expire. The commission shall elect one member to serve as chairperson of the commission.</para><para>Four members of the commission shall constitute a quorum for the purpose of conducting the business thereof. Any action of the commission shall require at least four votes. A vacancy in the commission shall not impair the right of the remaining members to exercise all the powers of the commission.</para><para>Members of the commission shall receive fifty dollars per day for their services and shall be reimbursed for their expenses actually and necessarily incurred in the performance of their duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. Reimbursement shall be for not more than two regular meetings per month and not more than three training sessions for any one fiscal year. Any member of the commission may be removed by the Governor for inefficiency, neglect of duty, misconduct, or malfeasance in office after being given a written statement of the charges and an opportunity to be heard thereon.</para><para>The commission shall establish and maintain its principal office in the city of Lincoln and such other offices within the state as it may deem necessary. The commission may meet and function at any place within the state. The commission shall appoint an executive director who shall be directly responsible to the commission. The executive director may appoint such assistants, clerks, agents, and other employees as such executive director may deem necessary, fix their compensation within the limitations provided by law, and prescribe duties of such employees. The executive director may appoint additional staff as the commission deems necessary.</para><para>The Attorney General shall represent and appear for the commission in all actions and proceedings involving any question under the Nebraska Fair Employment Practice Act, the Nebraska Fair Housing Act, or section 20-123, 20-124, or 20-132 and shall aid in any investigation or hearing had under either act or any of such sections. The commission shall have an official seal which shall be judicially noticed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 276, &#167; 16, p. 789; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 120, &#167; 22, p. 552; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 161, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 175, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 825, &#167; 49. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Fair Housing Act,</emphasis> see section 20-301.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 