
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id34" statutenumber="48-2105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id36">48-2105</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Registration;
application; contents; renewal.</catchline><para>Each contractor
shall apply to the department for a registration number on an application
form provided by the department. The application shall contain the following
information:</para>
<para>(1) The name and federal
employer identification number or, if the applicant is an individual,
the social security number of the contractor;</para>
<para>(2) The principal place of business of the contractor in Nebraska.
If the contractor's principal place of business is outside Nebraska, the application
shall state the address of the contractor's principal place of business and
the name and address of the contractor's registered agent in Nebraska;</para>
<para>(3) The telephone number of the contractor in the State of
Nebraska. If the contractor's principal place of business is outside Nebraska,
the application shall state the telephone number of the contractor's principal
place of business and the telephone number of the contractor's registered
agent in Nebraska;</para>
<para>(4) The type of business entity of the contractor such as
corporation, partnership, limited liability company, sole proprietorship,
or trust;</para>
<para>(5) The contractor
option election to collect and remit sales and use tax on purchases of building
materials and fixtures annexed to real property;</para><para>(6) The following information about the business
entity:</para>
<para>(a) If the contractor is a corporation, the name, address,
telephone number, and position of each officer of the corporation; and</para>
<para>(b) If the contractor is other than a corporation, the name,
address, and telephone number of each owner;</para>
<para>(7) Proof of (a) a certificate
or policy of insurance written by an insurance carrier duly authorized to
do business in this state which gives the effective dates of workers' compensation
insurance coverage indicating that it is in force, (b) a certificate evidencing
approval of self-insurance privileges as provided by the Nebraska Workers'
Compensation Court pursuant to section 48-145, or (c) a signed statement indicating
that the contractor is not required to carry workers' compensation insurance
pursuant to the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act; and</para>
<para>(8) A description of the business
which includes the employer's standard industrial classification code or the
principal products and services provided.</para>
<para>Each application shall be renewed annually upon payment of
the fee prescribed in section 48-2107.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 248, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 129; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB162, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1,110.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>