<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id12" statutenumber="48-2103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2103</statuteno><catchline id="id15">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Contractor Registration Act:</para><para>(1) Commissioner means the Commissioner of Labor;</para><para>(2) Construction means work on real property and annexations, including new work, additions, alterations, reconstruction, installations, and repairs performed at one or more different sites which may be dispersed geographically;</para><para>(3) Contractor means an individual, firm, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, or other association of persons engaged in the business of the construction, alteration, repairing, dismantling, or demolition of buildings, roads, bridges, viaducts, sewers, water and gas mains, streets, disposal plants, water filters, tanks and towers, airports, dams, levees and canals, water wells, pipelines, transmission and power lines, and every other type of structure, project, development, or improvement within the definition of real property and personal property, including such construction, repairing, or alteration of such property to be held either for sale or rental. Contractor also includes any subcontractor engaged in the business of such activities and any person who is providing or arranging for labor for such activities, either as an employee or as an independent contractor, for any contractor or person;</para><para>(4) Department means the Department of Labor; and</para><para>(5) Working days means Mondays through Fridays but does not include Saturdays, Sundays, or federal or state holidays. In computing fifteen working days, the day of receipt of any notice is not included and the last day of the fifteen working days is included.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 248, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB204, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB162, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB191, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>