<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id52" statutenumber="48-2107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2107</statuteno><catchline id="id55">Fees; exemption.</catchline><para>(1) Each application or renewal under section 48-2105 shall be signed by the applicant and accompanied by a fee not to exceed forty dollars. The commissioner may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish the criteria for acceptability of filing documents and making payments electronically. The criteria may include requirements for electronic signatures. The commissioner may refuse to accept any electronic filings or payments that do not meet the criteria established. The fee shall not be required when an amendment to an application is submitted. The commissioner shall remit the fees collected under this subsection to the State Treasurer for credit to the Contractor and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund.</para><para>(2) A contractor shall not be required to pay the fee under subsection (1) of this section if (a) the contractor is self-employed and does not pay more than three thousand dollars annually to employ other persons in the business and the application contains a statement made under oath or equivalent affirmation setting forth such information or (b) the contractor only engages in the construction of water wells or installation of septic systems. At any time that a contractor no longer qualifies for exemption from the fee, the fee shall be paid to the department. Any false statement made under subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall be a violation of section 28-915.01.</para><para>(3) The commissioner shall charge an additional fee of twenty-five dollars for the registration of each nonresident contractor and a fee of twenty-five dollars for the registration of each contract to which a nonresident contractor is a party if the total contract price or compensation to be received is more than ten thousand dollars. The commissioner shall remit the fees collected under this subsection to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 248, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB204, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB162, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB270, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1016, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>