
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Labor"  statutenumber="48-2605"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2605</statuteno><catchline>Registration as athlete agent; form;
requirements.</catchline><para>(1)
An applicant for registration shall submit an application for registration
to the Secretary of State in a form prescribed by the Secretary of State.
An application filed under this section is a public record. The application
must be in the name of an individual and, except as otherwise provided in
subsection (2) of this section, signed or otherwise authenticated by the applicant
under penalty of perjury and state or contain:</para>
<para>(a) The name of the applicant
and the address of the applicant's principal place of business;</para>
<para>(b) The name of the applicant's
business or employer, if applicable;</para><para>(c) Any business or occupation engaged in by the applicant
for the five years next preceding the date of submission of the application;</para>
<para>(d) A description of
the applicant's:</para><para>(i)
Formal training as an athlete agent;</para><para>(ii) Practical experience as an athlete agent; and</para>
<para>(iii) Educational background
relating to the applicant's activities as an athlete agent;</para>
<para>(e) The names and addresses
of three individuals not related to the applicant who are willing to serve
as references;</para><para>(f)
The name, sport, and last-known team for each individual for whom the applicant
acted as an athlete agent during the five years next preceding the date of
submission of the application;</para><para>(g) The names and addresses of all persons who are:</para>
<para>(i) With respect to the
athlete agent's business if it is not a corporation, the partners, members,
officers, managers, associates, or profit-sharers of the business; and</para>
<para>(ii) With respect to
a corporation employing the athlete agent, the officers, directors, and any
shareholder of the corporation having an interest of five percent or greater;</para>
<para>(h) Whether the applicant
or any person named pursuant to subdivision (g) of this subsection has been
convicted of a crime that, if committed in this state, would be a crime involving
moral turpitude or a felony, and identify the crime;</para><para>(i) Whether there has been any administrative
or judicial determination that the applicant or any person named pursuant
to subdivision (g) of this subsection has made a false, misleading, deceptive,
or fraudulent representation;</para><para>(j) Any instance in which the conduct of the applicant
or any person named pursuant to subdivision (g) of this subsection resulted
in the imposition of a sanction, suspension, or declaration of ineligibility
to participate in an interscholastic or intercollegiate athletic event on
a student-athlete or an educational institution;</para><para>(k) Any sanction, suspension, or
disciplinary action taken against the applicant or any person named pursuant
to subdivision (g) of this subsection arising out of occupational or professional
conduct; and</para><para>(l)
Whether there has been any denial of an application for, suspension or revocation
of, or refusal to renew, the registration or licensure of the applicant or
any person named pursuant to subdivision (g) of this subsection as an athlete
agent in any state.</para><para>(2)
An individual who has submitted an application for, and holds a certificate
of, registration or licensure as an athlete agent in another state may submit
a copy of the application and certificate in lieu of submitting an application
in the form prescribed pursuant to subsection (1) of this section. The Secretary
of State shall accept the application and the certificate from the other state
as an application for registration in this state if the application to the
other state:</para><para>(a)
Was submitted in the other state within six months next preceding the submission
of the application in this state and the applicant certifies that the information
contained in the application is current;</para><para>(b) Contains information substantially similar to
or more comprehensive than that required in an application submitted in this
state; and</para><para>(c)
Was signed by the applicant under penalty of perjury.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB292, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>