<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Labor"  statutenumber="48-2606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2606</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of registration; issuance
or denial; renewal.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) of this section, the Secretary
of State shall issue a certificate of registration to an individual who complies
with subsection (1) of section 48-2605 or whose application has been accepted
under subsection (2) of section 48-2605.</para>
<para>(2) The Secretary of
State may refuse to issue a certificate of registration if the Secretary of
State determines that the applicant has engaged in conduct that has a significant
adverse effect on the applicant's fitness to act as an athlete agent. In making
the determination, the Secretary of State may consider whether the applicant
has:</para><para>(a)
Been convicted of a crime that, if committed in this state, would be a crime
involving moral turpitude or a felony;</para><para>(b) Made a materially false, misleading, deceptive,
or fraudulent representation in the application or as an athlete agent;</para>
<para>(c) Engaged in conduct
that would disqualify the applicant from serving in a fiduciary capacity;</para>
<para>(d) Engaged in conduct
prohibited by section 48-2614;</para><para>(e) Had a registration or licensure as an athlete
agent suspended, revoked, or denied or been refused renewal of registration
or licensure as an athlete agent in any state;</para><para>(f) Engaged in conduct the consequence
of which was that a sanction, suspension, or declaration of ineligibility
to participate in an interscholastic or intercollegiate athletic event was
imposed on a student-athlete or an educational institution; or</para>
<para>(g) Engaged in conduct
that significantly adversely reflects on the applicant's credibility, honesty,
or integrity.</para><para>(3)
In making a determination under subsection (2) of this section, the Secretary
of State shall consider:</para><para>(a)
How recently the conduct occurred;</para><para>(b) The nature of the conduct and the context in which
it occurred; and</para><para>(c)
Any other relevant conduct of the applicant.</para><para>(4) An athlete agent may apply to
renew a registration by submitting an application for renewal in a form prescribed
by the Secretary of State. An application filed under this section is a public
record. The application for renewal must be signed by the applicant under
penalty of perjury and must contain current information on all matters required
in an original registration.</para><para>(5) An individual who has submitted an application
for renewal of registration or licensure in another state, in lieu of submitting
an application for renewal in the form prescribed pursuant to subsection (4)
of this section, may file a copy of the application for renewal and a valid
certificate of registration or licensure from the other state. The Secretary
of State shall accept the application for renewal from the other state as
an application for renewal in this state if the application to the other state:</para>
<para>(a) Was submitted in
the other state within six months next preceding the filing in this state
and the applicant certifies the information contained in the application for
renewal is current;</para><para>(b)
Contains information substantially similar to or more comprehensive than that
required in an application for renewal submitted in this state; and</para>
<para>(c) Was signed by the
applicant under penalty of perjury.</para><para>(6) A certificate of registration or a renewal of
a registration is valid for two years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB292, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>