<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor"  statutenumber="48-2503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2503</statuteno><catchline>Conveyance Advisory Committee; created; members; terms; expenses; meetings.</catchline><para>(1) The Conveyance Advisory Committee is created. One member shall be the state elevator inspector appointed pursuant to section 48-2512.01. One member shall be the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee. The Governor shall appoint the remaining members of the committee as follows: One representative from a major elevator manufacturing company; one representative from an elevator servicing company; one representative who is a building manager; one representative who is an elevator mechanic; and one representative of the general public from each county that has a population of more than one hundred thousand inhabitants. The committee shall be appointed within ninety days after January 1, 2008.</para><para>(2) The members of the committee appointed by the Governor shall serve for terms of three years, except that of the initial members appointed, two shall serve for terms of one year and three shall serve for terms of two years. The state elevator inspector and the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee shall serve continuously. The appointed members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses for service on the committee as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The members of the committee shall elect a chairperson who shall be the deciding vote in the event of a tie vote.</para><para>(3) The committee shall meet and organize within thirty days after the appointment of the members. The committee shall meet quarterly at a time and place to be fixed by the committee for the consideration of code regulations and for the transaction of such other business as properly comes before it. Special meetings may be called by the chairperson or at the request of two or more members of the committee. Any appointed committee member absent from three consecutive meetings shall be dismissed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB265, &#167; 28.</para></source></law></legaldoc>