<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id94">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" id="id96"  statutenumber="48-2706"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2706</statuteno><catchline>Co-employment relationship; restrictions;
rights and obligations; professional employer agreement; contents; written
notice to employee; posting of notice; responsibilities of client; liability;
sales tax liability; health benefit plan.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall knowingly enter into
a co-employment relationship in which less than a majority of the employees
of the client in this state are covered employees or in which less than one-half
of the payroll of the client in this state is attributable to covered employees.</para>
<para>(2) Except
as specifically provided in the Professional Employer Organization Registration
Act or in the professional employer agreement, in each co-employment relationship:</para>
<para>(a) The client
shall be entitled to exercise all rights and shall be obligated to perform
all duties and responsibilities otherwise applicable to an employer in an
employment relationship;</para><para>(b) The professional employer organization shall be entitled to
exercise only those rights and obligated to perform only those duties and
responsibilities specifically required by the act or in the professional employer
agreement. The rights, duties, and obligations of the professional employer
organization as co-employer with respect to any covered employee shall be
limited to those arising pursuant to the professional employer agreement and
the act during the term of co-employment by the professional employer organization
of such covered employee; and</para><para>(c) Unless otherwise expressly agreed by
the professional employer organization and the client in a professional employer
agreement, the client retains the exclusive right to direct and control the
covered employees as is necessary to conduct the client's business, to discharge
any of the client's fiduciary responsibilities, or to comply with any licensure
requirements applicable to the client or to the covered employees.</para>
<para>(3) Except
as specifically provided in the Professional Employer Organization Registration
Act, the co-employment relationship between the client and the professional
employer organization, and between each co-employer and each covered employee,
shall be governed by the professional employer agreement. Each professional
employer agreement shall include the following:</para><para>(a) The allocation of
rights, duties, and obligations as described in this section;</para>
<para>(b) A provision
that the professional employer organization shall have responsibility to pay
wages to covered employees; to withhold, collect, report, and remit payroll-related
and unemployment taxes; and, to the extent the professional employer organization
has assumed responsibility in the professional employer agreement, to make
payments for employee benefits for covered employees. For purposes of this
section, wages does not include any obligation between a client and a covered
employee for payments beyond or in addition to the covered employee's salary,
draw, or regular rate of pay, such as bonuses, commissions, severance pay,
deferred compensation, profit sharing, or vacation, sick, or other paid time
off pay, unless the professional employer organization has expressly agreed
to assume liability for such payments in the professional employer agreement;</para>
<para>(c) A provision
that the professional employer organization shall have a right to hire, discipline,
and terminate a covered employee as may be necessary to fulfill the professional
employer organization's responsibilities under the act and the professional
employer agreement. The client shall have a right to hire, discipline, and
terminate a covered employee; and</para><para>(d) A provision that the responsibility
to obtain workers' compensation coverage for covered employees and for other
employees of the client from an insurer licensed to do business in this state
and otherwise in compliance with all applicable requirements shall be specified
in the professional employer agreement in accordance with section 48-2709.
The client shall not be relieved of its obligations under the Nebraska Workers'
Compensation Act to provide workers' compensation coverage in the event that
the professional employer organization fails to obtain workers' compensation
insurance for which it has assumed responsibility.</para><para>(4) With respect to each
professional employer agreement entered into by a professional employer organization,
such professional employer organization shall provide written notice to each
covered employee affected by such agreement. The professional employer organization
shall provide, and the client shall post in a conspicuous place at the client's
worksite, the following:</para><para>(a) Notice of the general nature of the co-employment relationship
between and among the professional employer organization, the client, and
any covered employees; and</para><para>(b) Any notice required by the state relating to unemployment compensation
and the minimum wage.</para><para>(5) Except to the extent otherwise expressly provided by the applicable
professional employer agreement:</para><para>(a) A client shall be solely responsible
for the quality, adequacy, or safety of the goods or services produced or
sold in the client's business;</para><para>(b) A client shall be solely responsible
for (i) directing, supervising, training, and controlling the work of the
covered employees with respect to the business activities of the client or
when such employees are otherwise acting under the express direction and control
of the client and (ii) the acts, errors, or omissions of the covered employees
with regard to such activities or when such employees are otherwise acting
under the express direction and control of the client;</para>
<para>(c) A client
shall not be liable for the acts, errors, or omissions of a professional employer
organization or of any covered employee of the client and a professional employer
organization when such covered employee is acting under the express direction
and control of the professional employer organization;</para>
<para>(d) Nothing
in this subsection shall limit any contractual liability or obligation specifically
provided in a professional employer agreement; and</para><para>(e) A covered employee
is not, solely as the result of being a covered employee of a professional
employer organization, an employee of the professional employer organization
for purposes of general liability insurance, fidelity bonds, surety bonds,
employer's liability which is not covered by workers' compensation, or liquor
liability insurance carried by the professional employer organization unless
the covered employee is included for such purposes by specific reference in
the professional employer agreement and in any applicable prearranged employment
contract, insurance contract, or bond.</para><para>(6) When a professional employer organization
obtains workers' compensation coverage for its clients that is written by
an authorized insurer, it shall not be considered to be an insurer based on
its provision of workers' compensation insurance coverage to a client, even
if the professional employer organization charges the client a different amount
than it is charged by the authorized insurer.</para><para>(7) For purposes of this
state or any county, municipality, or other political subdivision thereof:</para>
<para>(a) Covered
employees whose services are subject to sales tax shall be deemed the employees
of the client for purposes of collecting and levying sales tax on the services
performed by the covered employee. Nothing contained in the Professional Employer
Organization Registration Act shall relieve a client of any sales tax liability
with respect to its goods or services;</para><para>(b) Any tax or assessment imposed upon
professional employer services or any business license or other fee which
is based upon gross receipts shall allow a deduction from the gross income
or receipts of the business derived from performing professional employer
services that is equal to that portion of the fee charged to a client that
represents the actual cost of wages and salaries, benefits, workers' compensation,
payroll taxes, withholding, or other assessments paid to or on behalf of a
covered employee by the professional employer organization under a professional
employer agreement;</para><para>(c) Any tax assessed or assessment or mandated expenditure on a
per capita or per employee basis shall be assessed against the client for
covered employees and against the professional employer organization for its
employees who are not covered employees co-employed with a client. Any benefit
or monetary consideration that meets the requirements of mandates imposed
on a client and that is received by covered employees through the professional
employer organization either through payroll or through benefit plans sponsored
by the professional employer organization shall be credited against the client's
obligation to fulfill such mandates; and</para><para>(d) In the case of a tax or an assessment
imposed or calculated upon the basis of total payroll, the professional employer
organization shall be eligible to apply any small business allowance or exemption
available to the client for the covered employees for the purpose of computing
the tax.</para><para>(8) A professional employer organization shall not offer its covered
employees any health benefit plan which is not fully insured by an authorized
insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB579, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1,110.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>