<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id134" statutenumber="48-2302"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2302</statuteno><catchline id="id137">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the New Hire Reporting Act:</para>
<para>(1) Date of hire means the day an employee begins employment with an
employer;</para>
<para>(2) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para>
<para>(3) Employee means an independent contractor or a person who is compensated
by or receives income from an employer or other payor, regardless of how such
income is denominated;</para>
<para>(4) Employer means any individual, partnership, limited liability company,
firm, corporation, association, political subdivision, or department or agency
of the state or federal government, labor organization, or any other entity
with an employee;</para>
<para>(5) Income means compensation paid, payable, due, or to be due for labor
or personal services, whether denominated as wages, salary, earnings, income,
commission, bonus, or otherwise;</para>
<para>(6) Payor includes a person, partnership, limited partnership, limited
liability partnership, limited liability company, corporation, or other entity
doing business or authorized to do business in the State of Nebraska, including
a financial institution, or a department or an agency of state, county, or
city government; and</para>
<para>(7) Rehire means the first day an employee begins employment with the
employer following a termination of employment with such employer. Termination
of employment does not include temporary separations from employment, such
as an unpaid medical leave, an unpaid leave of absence, a temporary layoff of less than sixty days in length,
or an absence for disability or maternity.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1058, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>