<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="48-2512.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2512.01</statuteno><catchline>State elevator inspector; qualifications; deputy inspectors; appointment; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) The Commissioner of Labor shall appoint a state elevator inspector, subject to the approval of the Governor, who shall work under the direct supervision of the commissioner. The state elevator inspector serving on January 1, 2008, shall continue to serve unless removed by the commissioner.</para><para>(2) The person so appointed shall be qualified by (a) not less than five years' experience in the installation, maintenance, and repair of elevators as determined by the commissioner, (b) certification as a qualified elevator inspector by an association accredited by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, or (c) not less than five years' journeyman experience in elevator installation, maintenance, and inspection as determined by the Commissioner of Labor and shall be familiar with the inspection process and rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the Conveyance Safety Act. </para><para>(3) The commissioner, subject to the approval of the Governor, may appoint deputy inspectors possessing the same qualifications as the state elevator inspector. A qualified individual may apply for the position of inspector or deputy inspector. The application shall include the applicant's social security number, but such social security number shall not be a public record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. IV, art. IV, &#167; 14, p. 561; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7695; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 48-414; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-418; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 283, &#167; 1, p. 810; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 297, &#167; 1, p. 810; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 320, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 659, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 36, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 126; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 35; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 48-418; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB265, &#167; 27.</para></source></law></legaldoc>