<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id41" statutenumber="48-2907"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2907</statuteno><catchline>Commissioner; citation; notice of penalty; contractor contest; hearing; unpaid administrative penalty, effect on government contracts.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to any other fines or penalties provided by law, the commissioner may issue a citation to a contractor when an investigation reveals that a contractor has violated the Employee Classification Act.</para><para>(2) When a citation is issued, the commissioner shall notify the contractor of the proposed administrative penalty, if any, by certified mail or any other manner of delivery by which the United States Postal Service can verify delivery or by any method of service recognized under Chapter 25, article 5. The administrative penalty shall be not more than five hundred dollars per misclassified individual for the first offense and not more than five thousand dollars per misclassified individual for each second or subsequent offense.</para><para>(3) The contractor has fifteen working days after the date of the citation or penalty to contest such citation or penalty. Notice of contest shall be sent to the commissioner who shall provide a hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(4) A contractor who is assessed an administrative penalty for a violation of the Employee Classification Act shall pay such administrative penalty no later than ten days after the date the penalty becomes final and not subject to further appeal. A contractor who has an unpaid administrative penalty in violation of this subsection shall be barred from contracting with the state or any political subdivision until such administrative penalty is paid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB563, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB953, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1016, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>