<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id570"><amendatorysection statutenumber="48-2803" chaptername="Labor"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2803</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Manufacturing Modernization and Workforce Development Pilot Investment Act:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Labor;</para><para>(2) Eligible manufacturing operation means a manufacturer of goods at a facility located in this state that:</para><para>(a) Has a North American Industry Classification System number within the manufacturing sector range of 31 to 33;</para><para>(b) Has been an established business for a minimum of three years prior to the date of application for the grant;</para><para>(c) Derives a minimum of fifty-one percent of the manufacturer's gross revenue from the sale of manufactured goods;</para><para>(d) Employs a minimum of three full-time employees; and</para><para>(e) Demonstrates the ability to provide private matching financial support for the manufacturer's manufacturing modernization investment project on a one-to-one basis;</para><para>(3) Manufacturing modernization investment project means a project that is intended to lead to the adoption and integration of smart technologies into existing manufacturing operations located in the state by mitigating the risk to the manufacturer of significant technology investments. Manufacturing modernization investment project includes, but is not limited to, an investment in the following that are intended to assist a manufacturer in increasing the manufacturer's productivity, efficiency, and competitiveness:</para><para>(a) Job training; and</para><para>(b) Specialized hardware, software, or other equipment; and</para><para>(4) Private matching financial support means any financial support derived from a source other than a direct appropriation from the State of Nebraska or its political subdivisions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB265, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>