<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-2112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2112</statuteno><catchline>Investigatory powers.</catchline><para>(1) The commissioner may make investigations he or she finds necessary or appropriate to determine if there is compliance with the Contractor Registration Act. Investigations shall take place at the times and places as the commissioner directs. For purposes of any investigation under this section, the commissioner may interview persons at the worksite, take photographs, and utilize other reasonable investigatory techniques. The conduct of the investigation shall be such as to preclude unreasonable disruption of the operations of the worksite. Investigations may be conducted, without prior notice, by correspondence, telephone conversations, or review of materials submitted to the department.</para><para>(2) For purposes of any investigation or proceeding under this section, the commissioner or any officer designated by him or her may administer oaths and affirmations, subpoena witnesses, compel their attendance, take evidence, and require the production of any books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, agreements, or other documents or records which the commissioner deems relevant or material to the inquiry.</para><para>(3) In case of contumacy by or refusal to obey a subpoena issued to any person, any court of competent jurisdiction, upon application by the commissioner, may issue to such person an order requiring him or her to appear before the commissioner or the officer designated by the commissioner and produce documentary evidence if so ordered or give evidence touching the matter under investigation or in question. Any failure to obey the order of the court may be punished by the court as a contempt.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 248, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 