<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id705"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-2804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>48-2804</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Eligible manufacturing operation; grant application; approval.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning October 1, 2025, through November 1, 2026, an eligible manufacturing operation may apply to the department for a grant. The application shall include, but not be limited to, the following information:</para><para>(a) A description of the manufacturing modernization investment project;</para><para>(b) The estimated cost of the manufacturing modernization investment project; and</para><para>(c) Documentation on the amount of private matching financial support available for the manufacturing modernization investment project that has been received or will be received by the eligible manufacturing operation. Such amount shall be at least equal to the amount of any grant received under the Manufacturing Modernization and Workforce Development Pilot Investment Act. The documentation provided under this subdivision does not need to identify any provider of private matching financial support.</para><para>(2) The department shall consider applications in the order in which they are received. If an applicant is an eligible manufacturing operation and otherwise qualifies for a grant, the department shall, subject to subsection (3) of this section, approve the application and notify the applicant of the approval.</para><para>(3) The department may approve applications within the limits of available funding under the Manufacturing Modernization and Workforce Development Pilot Investment Act. The amount of any grant approved shall be equal to the amount of money supplied by the eligible manufacturing operation from providers of private matching financial support, as documented under subdivision (1)(c) of this section, except that no grant shall be for more than fifty thousand dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB265, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>