<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" id="id64" statutenumber="48-3902" chaptername="Labor"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3902</statuteno><catchline>Training regarding issues in human trafficking.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that law enforcement agencies, prosecutors, public defenders, judges, juvenile detention center staff, and others involved in the juvenile justice system and the criminal justice system and other relevant officials be provided mandatory training regarding issues in human trafficking. Such training shall focus on:</para><para>(a) State and federal law regarding human trafficking;</para><para>(b) Methods used in identifying victims of human trafficking who are United States citizens and foreign nationals, including preliminary interview techniques and appropriate questioning methods;</para><para>(c) Methods for prosecuting human traffickers;</para><para>(d) Methods of increasing effective collaboration with nongovernmental organizations and other relevant social service organizations in the course of investigating and prosecuting a human trafficking case;</para><para>(e) Methods for protecting the rights of victims of human trafficking, taking into account the need to consider human rights and the special needs of women and minor victims;</para><para>(f) The necessity of treating victims of human trafficking as crime victims rather than as criminals; and</para><para>(g) Methods for promoting the safety and well-being of all victims of human trafficking.</para><para>(2) Employees of hotels and similar public lodging establishments may be provided training regarding issues in human trafficking. The Attorney General, the Department of Labor, and hotels and similar public lodging establishments may work together to approve such training and determine how such training should be provided. Such training may include:</para><para>(a) The definition of human trafficking and the commercial exploitation of children;</para><para>(b) Guidance on how to identify individuals at risk for human trafficking;</para><para>(c) Guidance on how to identify the signs of human trafficking and any individual potentially engaged in human trafficking;</para><para>(d) Differences between labor trafficking and sex trafficking, specific to the hotel and public lodging sector;</para><para>(e) Guidance on the role of hospitality employees in reporting and responding to potential or suspected human trafficking; and</para><para>(f) The contact information for the Nebraska Human Trafficking Hotline toll-free telephone number and text line and contact information for local law enforcement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1145, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB346, &#167; 54; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2025, &#167; 81-1431; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB320, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB905, &#167; 44. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB320, section 2, with LB905, section 44, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB320 became effective July 18, 2026. Changes made by LB905 became operative July 1, 2026.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>