<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id308"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-3404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3404</statuteno><catchline>Sector Partnership Program; created; Department of Labor; duties; Department of Economic Development; contracts authorized; completed studies; public information.</catchline><para>(1) The Sector Partnership Program is created. The program shall be administered by the Department of Labor in conjunction with the Department of Economic Development. In establishing and administering the program, the Department of Labor shall consult with the Nebraska Workforce Development Board, the Department of Economic Development, and the State Department of Education.</para><para>(2) The Department of Labor, in conjunction with the Department of Economic Development, shall:</para><para>(a) Establish a study process to conduct labor availability and skills gap studies;</para><para>(b) Determine the laborshed areas of the state; and</para><para>(c) Complete labor availability and skills gap studies for all laborshed areas of the state on a rotating basis as determined by the Department of Labor.</para><para>(3) The Department of Labor and the Department of Economic Development may contract with other entities to conduct additional labor availability, skills gap, and sector partnership studies.</para><para>(4) The Department of Labor, in conjunction with the Department of Economic Development, shall provide technical assistance to local sector partnerships and persons interested in forming partnerships. Technical assistance may include providing: (a) Direction and counseling on forming and sustaining partnerships; (b) professional development and capacity building through academies, toolkits, and peer sharing networks; (c) customized labor market and economic analysis; and (d) information on career pathways, worker training resources, skill standards, and industry-based certifications.</para><para>(5) Except to the extent otherwise provided in state or federal law, all completed labor availability and skills gap studies shall be public information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1110, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>