<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" id="id175" statutenumber="48-3901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3901</statuteno><catchline id="id178">Department of Labor; prevention of human trafficking; posters; placement; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Labor shall develop or select informational posters for placement around the state. The posters shall be in English, Spanish, and any other language deemed appropriate by the department. The posters shall include a toll-free telephone number a person may call for assistance, preferably the National Human Trafficking Resource Center Hotline (888)373-7888.</para><para>(2) Posters shall be placed in rest stops, strip clubs, casinos, and hotels and similar public lodging establishments. The department shall work with local businesses and nonprofit entities associated with the prevention of human trafficking to voluntarily place additional signs in high schools, postsecondary educational institutions, gas stations, hospitals, health care clinics, urgent care centers, airports, train stations, bus stations, and other locations around the state deemed appropriate by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1145, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB255, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB461, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB346, &#167; 53; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2025, &#167; 81-1430; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB320, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB905, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB1048, &#167; 22. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB320, section 1, with LB905, section 43, and LB1048, section 22, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB320 and LB1048 became effective July 18, 2026. Changes made by LB905 became operative July 1, 2026.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>