<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-3806"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3806</statuteno><catchline>Notice and posting.</catchline><para>(1) Employers shall give employees written notice of the following at the commencement of employment or by September 15, 2025, whichever is later: That beginning October 1, 2025, employees are entitled to paid sick time; the amount of paid sick time; the terms of its use guaranteed under the Nebraska Healthy Families and Workplaces Act; that retaliatory personnel action against employees who request or use paid sick time is prohibited; that each employee has the right to file a suit or complaint if paid sick time as required by the act is denied by the employer or the employee is subjected to retaliatory personnel action for requesting or taking paid sick time; and the contact information for the department where questions about rights and responsibilities under the act can be answered.</para><para>(2) The notices required in subsection (1) of this section shall be provided in:</para><para>(a) English; and</para><para>(b) Any language that is the first language spoken by at least five percent of the employer's workforce if the department has provided a model notice in such language.</para><para>(3) The amount of paid sick time available to the employee, the amount of paid sick time taken by the employee to date in the year, and the amount of pay the employee has received as paid sick time shall be recorded in, or on an attachment to, the employee's regular paycheck.</para><para>(4) Employers shall display a poster that contains the information required in subsection (1) of this section in a conspicuous and accessible place in each establishment where such employees are employed. If an employer does not maintain a physical workplace or an employee teleworks or performs work through a web-based or app-based platform, the employer shall provide notice of such information via electronic communication or a conspicuous posting in the web-based or app-based platform. The poster displayed shall be in:</para><para>(a) English; and</para><para>(b) Any language that is the first language spoken by at least five percent of the employer's workforce if the department has provided posters in such language.</para><para>(5) The department shall create and make available to employers, in all languages spoken by at least five percent of Nebraska's workforce and any language deemed appropriate by the department, model notices and posters that contain the information required under subsection (1) of this section and for employers' use in complying with subsections (1) and (4) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Initiative Law 2024, No. 436, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>