<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id747"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-3903"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3903</statuteno><catchline>Hotel or public lodging establishment; training and policies; liability.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Hotel means a facility in which the public may, for a consideration, obtain sleeping accommodations. Hotel includes hotels, motels, tourist homes, campgrounds, courts, lodging houses, inns, state-operated hotels, and nonprofit hotels but does not include hospitals, sanitariums, nursing homes, long-term care facilities, or dormitories or facilities operated by an educational institution and regularly used to house students; and</para><para>(b) Human trafficking means labor trafficking, labor trafficking of a minor, sex trafficking, or sex trafficking of a minor as those terms are defined in section 28-830.</para><para>(2) Any person, firm, or corporation that owns or operates a hotel or similar public lodging establishment may:</para><para>(a) Provide to all employees of such hotel or public lodging establishment within the State of Nebraska training on human trafficking that has been approved pursuant to subsection (2) of section 81-1431;</para><para>(b) Implement procedures for the reporting of suspected human trafficking to the Nebraska Human Trafficking Hotline or to a local enforcement agency; and</para><para>(c) Implement a human trafficking prevention policy for employees of the hotel or establishment within the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) An owner, operator, or employee of a hotel or similar public lodging establishment who implements the training and policies as prescribed in subsection (2) of this section shall not be liable for any act or omission arising out of or related to human trafficking committed by a third party occurring at such hotel or establishment unless the owner, operator, or employee of the hotel or establishment knowingly assists the commission of human trafficking, or has failed to act in a reasonable manner.</para><para>(4) The Department of Labor may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB320, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>