<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id81"><amendatorysection statutenumber="48-3203" chaptername="Labor"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3203</statuteno><catchline>Out-of-state business; applicability of state or local employment, licensing, or registration requirements; out-of-state employee; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) An out-of-state business that conducts operations within the state for purposes of assisting in repairing, renovating, installing, or building infrastructure or rendering services or other business activities related to a declared state disaster or emergency during the disaster period shall not be considered to have established a level of presence that would subject the out-of-state business or any of its out-of-state employees to any of the following state or local employment, licensing, or registration requirements:</para><para>(a) Registration with the Secretary of State;</para><para>(b) Withholding or income tax registration, filing, or remitting requirements; and</para><para>(c) Sales, use, or ad valorem tax on equipment brought into the state temporarily for use or consumption during the disaster period if such equipment does not remain in the state after the disaster period.</para><para>(2) An out-of-state employee shall not be considered to have established residency or a presence in the state that would require that person or that person's employer to file and pay income taxes, to be subjected to tax withholdings, or to file and pay any other state or local income or withholding tax or fee for work repairing, renovating, installing, or building infrastructure or rendering services or other business activities during the disaster period.</para><para>(3) After the conclusion of a disaster period, an out-of-state business or out-of-state employee that remains in the state is fully subject to the state or local employment, licensing, or registration requirements listed in this section or that were otherwise suspended under the Facilitating Business Rapid Response to State Declared Disasters Act during the disaster period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB913, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>