<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id54">
<sectno id="id55">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" id="id56" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="48-3006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3006</statuteno><catchline>Job training reimbursements; employer;
requirements; amount of reimbursements.</catchline><para>(1) Job training reimbursements shall be
made to any employer who has an approved application pursuant to the Teleworker
Job Creation Act and who trains at least four hundred qualifying employees
in a qualified training program within three hundred sixty-five calendar days
from the application filing date and offers employment to those qualifying
employees to work for the employer as a teleworker. The employer shall, to
the extent of available job positions, give a hiring priority preference,
over other similarly qualified applicants, to those applicants who (a) reside
in Nebraska counties of less than one hundred thousand inhabitants, as determined
by the most recent federal decennial census, with such residence as determined
by the statement of the qualifying employee on his or her employment application,
or (b) reside in areas of high concentration of poverty within the corporate
limits of a city or village consisting of one or more contiguous census tracts,
as determined by the most recent federal decennial census, which contain a
percentage of persons below the poverty line of greater than thirty percent,
and all census tracts contiguous to such tract or tracts, as determined by
the most recent federal decennial census. Such job positions shall pay a wage
of at least the then-required minimum hourly wage required by federal law.
If the employer fails to provide such a hiring priority preference to one
or more of the persons entitled to it, then the employer shall lose the right
to one job training reimbursement for each such failure.</para>
<para>(2) The amount
of the job training reimbursements allowed under subsection (1) of this section
shall be three hundred dollars for each new qualifying employee hired by the
employer after the application filing date, up to a total of five hundred
qualifying employees per project, resulting in a maximum reimbursement per
project of one hundred fifty thousand dollars.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1081, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>