<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" id="id22" statutenumber="48-3103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>48-3103</statuteno><catchline>Subsidized Employment Pilot Program;
created; Department of Health and Human Services; duties; Department of Labor;
powers; nonprofit organization; duties; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The Subsidized Employment
Pilot Program is created within the Department of Health and Human Services
to provide opportunities for employers and participants in the aid to dependent
children program to achieve subsidized employment.</para>
<para>(2) The department
shall establish a partnership between an entity which contracts with the department
pursuant to section 68-1722 to provide case management services in the aid
to dependent children program and a nonprofit organization.</para>
<para>(3) The Department
of Labor may establish a partnership with the nonprofit organization described
in subsection (2) of this section to assist in the referral of participants
and employers for the pilot program.</para><para>(4) The nonprofit organization described
in subsection (2) of this section shall:</para><para>(a) Establish an application process for
employers to participate in the pilot program. Such application process shall
include, but not be limited to, a requirement that employer applicants submit
a plan including, but not limited to, the following criteria:</para>
<para>(i) Initial client
assessment, job development, job placement, and employment retention services;</para>
<para>(ii) A strategy
to place participants in in-demand jobs; and</para><para>(iii) Other program guidelines
or criteria for the pilot program as needed;</para><para>(b) Recruit participants for
the pilot program, with assistance from the Department of Health and Human
Services, the Department of Labor, and an entity which contracts with the
department pursuant to section 68-1722 to provide case management services
in the aid to dependent children program;</para><para>(c) Recruit employers for the pilot program,
with assistance from the Department of Labor;</para><para>(d) Determine participant
eligibility for the pilot program and assist with employer and employee matching;</para>
<para>(e) Ensure that
the pilot program operates in both rural and urban areas. To ensure that the
pilot program operates in both rural and urban areas, such nonprofit organization
may enter into subcontracts with other nonprofit entities;</para>
<para>(f) Gather the
data and performance measures as described in section 48-3105; and</para>
<para>(g) Submit an electronic
report on or before September 15 of each year to the Health and Human Services
Committee of the Legislature containing the data and performance measures
described in section 48-3105.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB368, &#167; 3.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>