<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id515"><amendatorysection chaptername="Labor" statutenumber="48-4103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>48-4103</statuteno><catchline>Health care staffing agency; registration; application; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) A health care staffing agency operating in the state shall register annually with the department. As a condition of eligibility for registration, the applicant shall certify that the health care staffing agency is in compliance with section 48-4105.</para><para>(2) An applicant for registration and renewal of registration shall, for each separate physical location at which the applicant intends to operate as a health care staffing agency in Nebraska, file an application in a form prescribed by the department and pay an annual registration fee of one thousand five hundred dollars to the department, except that if the applicant is a health care staffing agency operating in Nebraska that does not maintain a physical location in Nebraska, the application shall be for the state generally and the annual registration fee shall be one thousand five hundred dollars for such application. An application for the renewal of a registration shall be made at least sixty days prior to the expiration of the then-current registration period. The department shall issue the applicant a separate certification of registration for each physical location at which the applicant intends to operate as a health care staffing agency in Nebraska upon approval of registration and payment of the fee, except that if the applicant is a health care staffing agency operating in Nebraska that does not maintain a physical location in Nebraska, the department shall issue one certificate of registration to the applicant for the state generally. The application shall include appropriate evidence of ability to comply with the requirements of section 48-4104. The department shall remit the fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the Contractor, Business, and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund.</para><para>(3) If the commissioner denies an application for registration or renewal of registration of a health care staffing agency, the commissioner shall issue a notice of denial. The health care staffing agency may file an appeal with the commissioner within twenty days after the date of mailing of the notice of denial. Except as otherwise provided in the Health Care Staffing Agency Registration Act, an appeal under this section shall be governed by the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB921, &#167; 9. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2027</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>