<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fees and Salaries" statutenumber="33-116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>33-116</statuteno><catchline>County surveyor; compensation; fees; mileage; equipment furnished.</catchline><para>Each county surveyor shall be entitled to receive the following fees: (1) For all services rendered to the county or state, a daily rate as determined by the county board; and (2) for each mile actually and necessarily traveled in going to and from work, the rate allowed by the provisions of section 81-1176. All expense of necessary assistants in the performance of the above work, the fees of witnesses, and material used for perpetuation and reestablishing lost exterior section and quarter corners necessary for the survey shall be paid for by the county and the remainder of the cost of the survey shall be paid for by the parties for whom the work may be done. All necessary equipment, conveyance, and repairs to such equipment, required in the performance of the duties of the office, shall be furnished such surveyor at the expense of the county, except that in any county with a population of less than fifty thousand the county board may, in its discretion, allow the county surveyor a salary fixed pursuant to section 23-1114, payable monthly, by warrant drawn on the general fund of the county. All fees received by surveyors so receiving a salary may, with the authorization of the county board, be retained by the surveyor, but in the absence of such authorization all such fees shall be turned over to the county treasurer monthly for credit to the county general fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 19, &#167; 16, p. 168; </para><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 1, p. 157; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 32, &#167; 1, p. 167; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 43, &#167; 12, p. 146; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 2440; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 75, &#167; 1, p. 194; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2380; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 114, &#167; 1, p. 321; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 33-119; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 65, &#167; 7, p. 180; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 33-119; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 90, &#167; 19, p. 305; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 33-116; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 122, &#167; 1, p. 357; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 117, &#167; 1, p. 372; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 70, &#167; 4, p. 296; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 158, &#167; 2, p. 482; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 160, &#167; 1, p. 485; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 272, &#167; 1, p. 1036; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 127, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1011, &#167; 21. </para></source><annotation><para>An agreement by a county surveyor to perform services required of him for a less compensation than that fixed by law is contrary to public policy and void. Hansen v. Cheyenne County, 139 Neb. 484, 297 N.W. 902 (1941); Fitch v. Cass County, 139 Neb. 483, 297 N.W. 905 (1941).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>