<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fees And Salaries" statutenumber="33-126.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>33-126.02</statuteno><catchline>County court; guardianships; conservatorships; fees; how determined.</catchline><para>In matters of guardianship and conservatorship, the county court shall be entitled to receive the following fees: Upon the filing of a petition for the appointment of a guardian, twenty-two dollars; upon the filing of a petition for the appointment of a conservator, twenty-two dollars; upon the filing of one petition for a consolidated appointment of both a guardian and conservator, twenty-two dollars; for the appointment of a successor guardian or conservator, twenty-two dollars; for the appointment of a temporary guardian or temporary or special conservator, twenty-two dollars; and for proceedings for a protective order in the absence of a guardianship or conservatorship, twenty-two dollars. If there is more than one ward listed in a petition for appointment of a guardian or conservator or both, only one filing fee shall be assessed. Two dollars of each twenty-two-dollar fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Retirement Fund for Judges. While such guardianship or conservatorship is pending, the court shall receive five dollars for filing and recording each report. When the appointment of a custodian as provided for in the Nebraska Uniform Transfers to Minors Act is made, the county court shall be entitled to receive a fee of twenty dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 19, &#167; 8, p. 164; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 41, &#167; 1, p. 460; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 56, &#167; 1, p. 231; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 288; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 2449; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 39, &#167; 1, p. 111; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 45, &#167; 1, p. 127; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 359; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2388; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 98, &#167; 1, p. 286; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 33-127; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 64, &#167; 1, p. 173; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 86, &#167; 1, p. 286; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 33-127; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 33-126; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 74, &#167; 4, p. 278; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 95, &#167; 1(2), p. 255; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 103, &#167; 1, p. 508; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 189, &#167; 1, p. 633; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 481, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 492, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 790, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 233, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 907, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 348, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Transfers to Minors Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2701.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>