<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Fees And Salaries" statutenumber="33-101"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>33-101</statuteno><catchline>Secretary of State; fees.</catchline>
<para>There shall be paid to the Secretary of State the following fees:</para>
<para>(1) For certificate or exemplification with seal, ten dollars;</para>
<para>(2) For copies of records, for each page, a fee of one dollar;</para>
<para>(3) For accessing records by electronic means:</para>
<para>(a) For batch requests of business entity information, fifteen dollars
for up to one thousand business entities accessed and an additional fifteen
dollars for each additional one thousand business entities accessed over one
thousand;</para>
<para>(b) For information in the Secretary of State's Uniform Commercial Code
Division data base, including records filed pursuant to the Uniform Commercial
Code, Chapter 52, article 2, 5, 7, 9, 10, 11, 12, or 14, Chapter 54, article
2, or the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act, for batch
requests searched by debtor location, fifteen dollars for up to one thousand
records accessed and an additional fifteen dollars for each additional one
thousand records accessed over one thousand;</para>
<para>(c) For an electronically transmitted certificate indicating whether
a business is properly registered with the Secretary of State and authorized
to do business in the state, six dollars and fifty cents;</para>
<para>(d) For the entire contents of the data base regarding corporations
and the Uniform Commercial Code, but excluding electronic images, three hundred
dollars weekly subscription rate, one thousand dollars monthly subscription
rate for a twice-monthly service, and eight hundred dollars monthly subscription
rate;</para>
<para>(e) For images of records accessed over the Internet or by other electronic
means other than facsimile machine, forty-five cents for each page or image
of a page, not to exceed two thousand dollars per request for batch requests;
and</para>
<para>(f) For the entire contents of the image data base regarding corporations
and the Uniform Commercial Code, eight hundred dollars monthly subscription
rate;</para>
<para>(4) For recording articles of association or incorporation, amendments,
revised or restated articles, changes of registered office or registered agent,
increase or decrease of capital stock, merger or consolidation, statement
of intent to dissolve, and consent to dissolution, revocation of dissolution,
articles of dissolution, domestic or foreign, profit or nonprofit, five dollars
per page;</para>
<para>(5) For taking acknowledgment, ten dollars;</para>
<para>(6) For administering oath, ten dollars;</para>
<para>(7) For filings by for-profit corporations and associations required
or permitted by law to file articles of incorporation or organization with
the Secretary of State, the fees provided in section 21-205 unless
otherwise specifically provided by law; and</para>
<para>(8) For filings by nonprofit corporations and associations required
or permitted by law to file articles of incorporation or organization with
the Secretary of State, the fees provided in section 21-1905 unless otherwise
specifically provided by law.</para>
<para>All fees collected pursuant to subdivision (3) of this section shall
be deposited in the Records Management Cash Fund and shall be distributed
as provided in any agreements between the State Records Board and the Secretary
of State.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 5, p. 196; </para><para>Laws 1897, c. 72, &#167; 1, p. 331; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 139, &#167; 1, p. 445; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 128, &#167; 1, p. 435; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 2423; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 104, &#167; 1, p. 374; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2364; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 33-103; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 33-101; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 118, &#167; 1, p. 349; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 63, &#167; 12, p. 207; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 156, &#167; 1, p. 477; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 183, &#167; 1, p. 569; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 268, &#167; 1, p. 1030; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 95, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1004, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 214; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 194; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 929, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 524, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB278, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 279.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB278, section 1, with LB749, section 279, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB278 became effective July 18, 2014. Changes made by LB749 became operative January 1, 2016.</note><note>The operative date of Laws 2014, LB 749, was amended by Laws 2015, LB157, and changed to January 1, 2017.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act,</emphasis> see section 77-3901.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Building and loan associations are not exempted from paying the fee required by this section for filing certificates of increase of capital stock. State ex rel. Equitable Building Loan &amp; Savings Assn. v. Amsberry, 104 Neb. 843, 178 N.W. 828 (1920).</para><para>Under the 1897 amendment to this section, a building and loan association was not required to file its articles of incorporation with the Secretary of State and pay him a fee as a condition precedent to obtaining a certificate of approval. State ex rel. Bullard v. Searle, 86 Neb. 259, 125 N.W. 590 (1910).</para><para>This section is cited in a footnote to the opinion to the effect that most state statutes measure domestic incorporation fees according to the amount or number of shares of capital stock authorized. Atlantic Refining Co. v. Virginia, 302 U.S. 22 (1837).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
