<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fees And Salaries" statutenumber="33-110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>33-110</statuteno><catchline>County clerks; fees for certificate and seal; when charged; marriage licenses and records; fees.</catchline><para>County clerks shall receive no fee for the performance of the following services: For issuing certificates of election; for performing the duties of clerk of the county board; for taking acknowledgments of claims against the county; for attesting or certifying any document authorized by the county board or required by the departments of the state; or for recording Army or Navy discharges or furnishing certified copies thereof to be used in connection with any claim for compensation or disability. A charge of twenty-five cents shall be made for any other certificate and seal unless otherwise provided. The fees collected shall be credited to the county general fund.</para><para>County clerks shall receive a fee of fifteen dollars for the entire proceedings of issuing a marriage license, administering the related oaths or affirmations, and recording a marriage certificate. An additional fee of five dollars shall be made for each certified copy of a marriage record on file in the office of the county clerk. Both such fees shall be deposited in the county general fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 19, &#167; 14, p. 167; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 2434; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2374; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 33-113; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 68, &#167; 1, p. 187; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 33-113; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 33-110; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 93, &#167; 6, p. 247; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 116, &#167; 1, p. 371; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 525, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1126, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 202, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>