<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Fees And Salaries" id="id00" statutenumber="33-106.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>33-106.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Clerk of the district court; fees; report; disposition.</catchline><para>(1) The clerk of the district court of each county shall not retain for his or her own use any fees, revenue, perquisites, or receipts, fixed, enumerated, or provided in this or any other section of the statutes of the State of Nebraska or any fees authorized by federal law to be collected or retained by a county official. The clerk shall on or before the fifteenth day of each month make a report to the county board, under oath, showing the different items of such fees, revenue, perquisites, or receipts received, from whom, at what time, and for what service, and the total amount received by such officer since the last report, and also the amount received for the current year.</para><para>(2) The clerk shall account for and pay any fees, revenue, perquisites, or receipts not later than the fifteenth day of the month following the calendar month in which such fees, revenue, perquisites, or receipts were received in the following manner:</para><para>(a) Of the forty-two-dollar docket fee imposed pursuant to section 33-106, one dollar shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund and six dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Retirement Fund for Judges through June 30, 2021. Beginning July 1, 2021, seven dollars of such forty-two-dollar docket fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Retirement Fund for Judges;</para><para>(b) Of the twenty-seven-dollar docket fee imposed for appeal of a criminal case to the district court pursuant to section 33-106, two dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Retirement Fund for Judges; and</para><para>(c) The remaining fees, revenue, perquisites, or receipts shall be credited to the general fund of the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 19, &#167; 3, p. 157; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 5, p. 217; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 31, &#167; 1, p. 164; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 68, &#167; 1, p. 363; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 55, &#167; 1, p. 280; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167;&#167; 2421, 2429; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 40, &#167; 1, p. 119; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 82, &#167; 1, p. 204; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167;&#167; 2362, 2369; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 81, &#167; 1, p. 255; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 118, &#167; 1, p. 328; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167;&#167; 33-101, 33-108; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 33-106; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 120, &#167; 1, p. 353; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 94, &#167; 1(3), p. 254; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 4, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 348, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 823, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB803, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB17, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>