<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fees and Salaries" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="33-157"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>33-157</statuteno><catchline>Conviction for misdemeanor or felony;
affirmation on appeal; additional assessment of cost; use; Nebraska Crime
Victim Fund; created; use.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to all other costs assessed according to
law, an assessment of one dollar shall be assessed for each conviction of
a person for any misdemeanor or felony in county court or district court and
each affirmation on appeal. No such assessment shall be collected in any juvenile
court proceeding. No county shall be liable for the assessment imposed pursuant
to this section. The assessments shall be remitted to the State Treasurer
on forms prescribed by the State Treasurer within ten days after the end of
the month. </para>
<para>(2) The Nebraska
Crime Victim Fund is created. The fund shall contain the amounts remitted
pursuant to subsection (1) of this section and section 83-184. The fund shall
be administered by the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal
Justice. As soon as funds become available, the commission shall direct the
State Treasurer to transfer money from the Nebraska Crime Victim Fund to the
Department of Correctional Services Facility Cash Fund and the Supreme Court
Automation Cash Fund to pay for the initial costs in implementing Laws 2010,
LB510, in amounts to be determined by the Department of Correctional Services
and the Supreme Court and certified to the commission. When such costs are
fully reimbursed, the Nebraska Crime Victim Fund shall terminate and the State
Treasurer shall distribute seventy-five percent of the funds remitted pursuant
to subsection (1) of this section and section 83-184 to the Victim's Compensation
Fund to be awarded as compensation for losses and expenses allowable under
the Nebraska Crime Victim's Reparations Act and shall distribute twenty-five
percent of such funds to the Reentry Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB510, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>