<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Fees And Salaries" statutenumber="33-105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>33-105</statuteno><catchline>Department of Natural Resources; fees.</catchline><para>There shall be paid to the Department of Natural Resources in advance for the services of the Director of Natural Resources by the party demanding or necessitating the service the following fees:</para><para>(1) For filing, recording, and examining each application for a storage reservoir, for the first five thousand acre-feet or fraction thereof, twenty-five dollars, and for each additional five thousand acre-feet or fraction thereof, ten dollars;</para><para>(2) For filing, recording, and examining each application for, or application for modification of permits to include, intentional or incidental underground water storage and recovery, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(3) For filing, recording, and examining each application for water for irrigation from a natural stream, for the first one thousand acres proposed for irrigation or fraction thereof, two hundred dollars, and for each additional one thousand acres or fraction thereof, one hundred dollars;</para><para>(4) For filing, recording, and examining each application for water for irrigation from a storage reservoir, for the first one thousand acres proposed for irrigation or fraction thereof, fifty dollars, and for each additional one thousand acres or fraction thereof, twenty-five dollars;</para><para>(5) For filing, recording, and examining each application for water for power purposes, for each theoretical fifty horsepower or fraction thereof, five dollars;</para><para>(6) For filing, recording, and examining each application for withdrawal of ground water for industrial purposes, for the first four thousand acre-feet or fraction thereof, one thousand five hundred dollars, and for each additional one thousand acre-feet or fraction thereof, seven hundred fifty dollars;</para><para>(7) For filing an application to amend a permit for withdrawal of ground water for industrial purposes, five hundred dollars;</para><para>(8) For filing any petition, affidavit, other paper, or application for which no fee has been fixed, ten dollars;</para><para>(9) For recording any deed or document pertaining to land covered in whole or in part by a water appropriation or any instrument other than an application, ten dollars; and</para><para>(10) For certificate and seal, one dollar.</para><para>The Director of Natural Resources shall keep a record of all money thus received and shall remit such money to the State Treasurer for credit to and use of the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1905, c. 167, &#167; 1, p. 652; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 153, &#167; 34, p. 519; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 2427-8; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2368; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 33-107; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 33-105; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 119, &#167; 1, p. 352; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 365, &#167; 7, p. 1235; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 131, &#167; 1, p. 445; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 773, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 547, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 56, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 198, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 103, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 488, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 309, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 45, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 132, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 335, &#167; 73. </para></source></law></legaldoc>