<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Fees And Salaries" statutenumber="33-107.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>33-107.02</statuteno><catchline>Paternity determination; parental support proceeding; certain marriage, child support, child custody, or parenting time actions; additional mediation fee and civil legal services fee.</catchline><para>(1) A mediation fee of fifty dollars and a civil legal services fee of fifteen dollars shall be collected by the clerk of the county court or the clerk of the district court for each paternity determination or parental support proceeding under sections 43-1401 to 43-1418, for each complaint or action to modify a decree of dissolution or annulment of marriage, and for each complaint or action to modify an award of child support, child custody, parenting time, visitation, or other access as defined in section 43-2922. Such fees shall be remitted to the State Treasurer on forms prescribed by the State Treasurer within ten days after the close of each month. The civil legal services fee shall be credited to the Legal Aid and Services Fund, and the mediation fee shall be credited to the Parenting Act Fund.</para><para>(2) Any proceeding filed by a county attorney or an authorized attorney, in a case in which services are being provided under Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, shall not be subject to the provisions of subsection (1) of this section. In any such proceeding, a mediation fee of fifty dollars and a civil legal services fee of fifteen dollars shall be collected by the clerk of the county court or the clerk of the district court for any pleading in such proceeding filed by any party, other than a county attorney or authorized attorney, subsequent to the paternity filing if such pleading is to modify an award of child support or to establish or modify custody, parenting time, visitation, or other access as defined in section 43-2922. Such fees shall be remitted to the State Treasurer on forms prescribed by the State Treasurer within ten days after the close of each month. The mediation fee shall be credited to the Parenting Act Fund and the civil legal services fee shall be credited to the Legal Aid and Services Fund.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, authorized attorney has the same meaning as in section 43-1704.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 729, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 19, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB307, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>