<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-302"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-302</statuteno><catchline>Board; officers; terms; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) Within thirty days after the appointment of the initial members of the Nebraska Grape and Winery Board, such board shall conduct its first regular meeting. During that meeting, the board members shall elect from among themselves, by majority vote, a chairperson, vice-chairperson, secretary, and treasurer, all to serve for terms of one year from the date of election. Subsequent board meetings shall take place at least once every six months and at such times as called by the chairperson or by any three board members.</para><para>(2) Each board member shall serve for a term of three years, except that at the expiration of the terms of the members in 2021, the Governor shall appoint one member for a term of one year, two members for a term of two years, and two members for a term of three years, and their successors shall be appointed for a term of three years. Upon completion of a term, a member may, at the Governor's discretion, be reappointed.</para><para>(3) All voting board members shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided for in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 while attending meetings of the board or while engaged in the performance of official responsibilities as determined by the board.</para><para>(4) A board member shall be removable by the Governor for cause. The board member shall first be given a written copy of the charges against him or her and also an opportunity to be heard publicly. In addition to all other causes, the failure of a board member to continue to meet any of the requirements for eligibility set out in section 53-301 shall be deemed sufficient cause for removal from office.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 477, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 46. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>