<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id338"><amendatorysection statutenumber="53-504" chaptername="Liquors"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-504</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Beer Industry Promotional Fund; created; use; investment; holder of craft brewery license; annual fee; use.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Beer Industry Promotional Fund is created. The fund shall consist of money credited pursuant to this section, fees received from shipping licenses issued to beer manufacturers pursuant to subsection (2) of section 53-123.15, gifts, grants, bequests, and any money appropriated by the Legislature. For administrative purposes, the fund shall be located in the Department of Agriculture.</para><para>(2) Beginning July 1, 2016, in addition to the annual license fee imposed by section 53-124.01, each holder of a craft brewery license shall pay an annual fee in the amount of two hundred fifty dollars to the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission or shall opt out of paying the additional fee on forms provided by the commission. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Beer Industry Promotional Fund.</para><para>(3) The Department of Agriculture, at the direction of and in cooperation with the Nebraska Craft Brewery Board, shall use the Nebraska Beer Industry Promotional Fund to develop and maintain programs for the research and advancement of the beer brewing process, the marketing and promotion of the beer industry in Nebraska, and the marketing and promotion of agricultural products and their byproducts grown and produced in Nebraska for use in the beer industry. Such expenditures may include, but are not limited to, all necessary funding for the employment of experts in the field of beer brewing and business development, as deemed necessary by the board, and programs to carry out the purposes of this subsection. None of the money credited to the Nebraska Beer Industry Promotional Fund may be used for lobbying purposes.</para><para>(4) Money in the Nebraska Beer Industry Promotional Fund not expended during any fiscal year may be reappropriated for the ensuing biennium. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>