<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id906"><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-124.17"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-124.17</statuteno><catchline>Promotional farmers market special designated license holder; permit to sell or dispense; application; issuance; conditions; local governing body; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The holder of a promotional farmers market special designated license issued under section 53-124.16 may apply to the local governing body of a city, village, or county for a permit to use the promotional farmers market special designated license to sell or dispense alcoholic liquor, which the holder is licensed to produce, for consumption at a farmers market located within the jurisdiction of the local governing body.</para><para>(2) A permit may be issued to the licensee for the duration of an annual farmers market without reapplying to the local governing body. The local governing body may issue multiple permits to a licensee for each separate farmers market location within the jurisdiction of the local governing body.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, local governing body means the governing body of the city or village within which the farmers market for which the permit is requested is located or, if such farmers market is not within the corporate limits of a city or village, local governing body means the governing body of the county within which the farmers market for which the permit is requested is located.</para><para>(4) No permit shall be granted under this section without the approval of the local governing body and the submission of a safety and security plan containing such information as the local governing body may require for use of the promotional farmers market special designated license. The local governing body may establish criteria for approving or denying a permit. The local governing body may designate an agent to determine whether a permit is to be approved or denied. Such agent shall follow criteria established by the local governing body in making the determination. The determination of the agent shall be considered the determination of the local governing body unless otherwise provided by the local governing body.</para><para>(5) The decision of the local governing body shall be final. If the applicant does not qualify for a permit to use the promotional farmers market special designated license to sell or dispense alcoholic liquor, including beer, for consumption at a farmers market, the permit shall be denied.</para><para>(6) The city, village, or county clerk shall deliver confirmation of the permit to use the promotional farmers market special designated license to sell or dispense alcoholic liquor, including beer, for consumption at a farmers market to the licensee upon receipt of any fee or tax imposed by such city, village, or county.</para><para>(7) The local governing body shall electronically notify the commission within five days after the authorization of any permit under this section for the holder of a promotional farmers market special designated license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB274, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>