<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-219"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-219</statuteno><catchline>Wholesaler's business; transfer; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) Upon written notice of intent to transfer the wholesaler's business, any individual owning or personal representative of a deceased individual who owned an interest in a wholesaler's business may transfer the wholesaler's business to a designated member or to any other person who meets the reasonable qualifications required by the supplier for Nebraska wholesalers. The consent or approval of the supplier shall not be required of any transfer of the wholesaler's business, including the assignment of wholesaler's rights under the agreement, to a designated member except as provided in this subsection and shall not be withheld or unreasonably delayed to a proposed transferee other than a designated member who meets such reasonable qualifications. The supplier shall have the burden of proving that the proposed transferee fails to meet such reasonable qualifications and that the qualifications are consistently applied to Nebraska wholesalers by the supplier. A designated member or transferee shall not be qualified as a transferee without the written approval or consent of the supplier if such proposed transferee:</para><para>(a) Has been insolvent, has filed a voluntary or involuntary petition under any bankruptcy or receivership law, or has executed an assignment for the benefit of creditors;</para><para>(b) Has had a license issued under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act revoked or suspended for a period of sixty-one days or more;</para><para>(c) Has been convicted of a felony under the United States Code or the laws of any state which reasonably may adversely affect the goodwill or interest of the wholesaler or supplier; or</para><para>(d) Has had an agreement involuntarily canceled, terminated, not renewed, or discontinued by a supplier for good cause.</para><para>(2) The supplier shall not interfere with, prevent, or unreasonably delay the transfer of the wholesaler's business, including an assignment of wholesaler's rights under the agreement, if the proposed transferee is a designated member or if the transferee other than a designated member meets the reasonable qualifications required by the supplier for Nebraska wholesalers. When the transferee is other than a designated member, the supplier may, in good faith and for good cause related to the reasonable qualifications, refuse to accept the transfer of the wholesaler's business or the assignment of wholesaler's rights under the agreement. The supplier shall have the burden of proving that it has acted in good faith and that there was good cause for failure to accept or consent to the transfer of the wholesaler's business or the assignment of wholesaler's rights under the agreement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 371, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 