<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-175"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-175</statuteno><catchline>Liquor; acquisition from other than licensed dealer; when unlawful; limitation; records.</catchline><para>It shall be unlawful for any person to purchase, receive, acquire, accept, or possess any alcoholic liquor acquired from any person other than one duly licensed to handle alcoholic liquor under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act unless within the specific exemptions or exceptions provided in the act. No licensed retailer of alcoholic liquor shall purchase such liquor other than from a licensed wholesaler who has his or her place of business within this state, except that a licensed retailer may purchase alcoholic liquor other than beer or wine from one or more retailers licensed to sell alcoholic liquor for consumption off the premises if the seller has the required federal wholesaler's basic permit and federal wholesale liquor dealer's special tax stamp and has filed proof of possession of the permit and tax stamp with the commission prior to engaging in any such sales for resale. Retailers making such sales and retailers making such purchases from retailers shall keep accurate records of such sales and purchases and shall report all such sales and purchases on a quarterly basis on forms and in such manner as prescribed by the commission. No licensed retailer shall purchase in the aggregate more than three hundred dollars of alcoholic liquor as allowed under this section in any calendar year. Nothing in this section shall prohibit the sale or exchange among collectors of commemorative bottles or uniquely designed decanters which contain alcoholic liquor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 32, p. 398; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-332; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-175; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 154, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 58. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 