<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id00" statutenumber="53-131.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>53-131.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">License; application; form; contents; criminal history record check; false statement; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The application for a new license shall be submitted upon such forms as the commission may prescribe. Such forms shall contain (a) the name and residence of the applicant and how long he or she has resided within the State of Nebraska, (b) the particular premises for which a license is desired designating the same by street and number if practicable or, if not, by such other description as definitely locates the premises, (c) the name of the owner of the premises upon which the business licensed is to be carried on, (d) a statement that the applicant is a resident of Nebraska and legally able to work in Nebraska, that the applicant and the spouse of the applicant are not less than twenty-one years of age, and that such applicant has never been convicted of or pleaded guilty to a felony or been adjudged guilty of violating the laws governing the sale of alcoholic liquor or the law for the prevention of gambling in the State of Nebraska, except that a manager for a corporation applying for a license shall qualify with all provisions of this subdivision as though the manager were the applicant, except that the provisions of this subdivision shall not apply to the spouse of a manager-applicant, (e) a statement that the applicant intends to carry on the business authorized by the license for himself or herself and not as the agent of any other persons and that if licensed he or she will carry on such business for himself or herself and not as the agent for any other person, (f) a statement that the applicant intends to superintend in person the management of the business licensed and that if so licensed he or she will superintend in person the management of the business, and (g) such other information as the commission may from time to time direct. The applicant shall also submit two legible sets of fingerprints to be furnished to the Federal Bureau of Investigation through the Nebraska State Patrol for a national criminal history record check and the fee for such record check payable to the patrol.</para><para>(2) If any false statement is made in any part of such application, the applicant or applicants shall be deemed guilty of perjury, and upon conviction thereof the license shall be revoked and the applicant subjected to the penalties provided by law for that crime.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 99, p. 427; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-399; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-142; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 249, &#167; 13, p. 872; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 224, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 848, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 267, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1204, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>