<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-223"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-223</statuteno><catchline>Civil actions authorized; damages; jurisdiction.</catchline><para>(1) If a supplier engages in conduct prohibited under sections 53-201 to 53-223, a wholesaler with whom the supplier has an agreement may maintain a civil action against the supplier to recover actual damages reasonably incurred as the result of the prohibited conduct. If a wholesaler engages in conduct prohibited under such sections, a supplier with whom the wholesaler has an agreement may maintain a civil action against the wholesaler to recover actual damages reasonably incurred as the result of the prohibited conduct.</para><para>(2) A supplier who violates any provision of such sections shall be liable for all actual damages, all court costs, and, in the court's discretion, reasonable attorney's fees incurred by a wholesaler as a result of the violation. A wholesaler who violates any provision of such sections shall be liable for all actual damages, all court costs, and, in the court's discretion, reasonable attorney's fees incurred by the supplier as a result of the violation.</para><para>(3) A supplier or wholesaler may bring an action for declaratory judgment for determination of any controversy arising pursuant to such sections.</para><para>(4) Upon proper application to the court, a supplier or wholesaler may obtain injunctive relief against any violation of such sections. If the court grants injunctive relief or issues a temporary restraining order, bond shall be posted.</para><para>(5) The remedies provided by such sections are not exclusive, and nothing contained in such sections shall abolish any cause of action or remedy available to the supplier or the wholesaler existing on April 18, 1989.</para><para>(6) Any legal action taken under such sections or relating to a dispute arising out of an agreement or breach thereof or over the provisions of an agreement shall be filed in a state or federal court located in Nebraska, which state court is located in, or which federal court has jurisdiction and venue of, the county in which the wholesaler maintains its principal place of business in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 371, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc>