<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-123.11"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.11</statuteno><catchline>Farm winery license; rights of licensee; removal of unsealed bottle of wine; conditions; sales for consumption off the premises; conditions; notice to commission, required.</catchline><para>(1) A farm winery license shall entitle the holder to:</para><para>(a) Sell wines produced at the farm winery onsite at wholesale and retail and to sell wines produced at the farm winery at off-premises sites holding the appropriate retail license;</para><para>(b) Sell wines produced at the farm winery at retail for consumption on the premises as designated pursuant to section 53-123.12;</para><para>(c) Permit a customer to remove one unsealed bottle of wine for consumption off the premises. The licensee or his or her agent shall (i) securely reseal such bottle and place the bottle in a bag designed so that it is visibly apparent that the resealed bottle of wine has not been opened or tampered with and (ii) provide a dated receipt to the customer and attach to such bag a copy of the dated receipt for the resealed bottle of wine. If the resealed bottle of wine is transported in a motor vehicle, it must be placed in the trunk of the motor vehicle or the area behind the last upright seat of such motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk;</para><para>(d) Ship wines produced at the farm winery by common carrier and sold at retail to recipients in and outside the State of Nebraska, if the output of such farm winery for each calendar year as reported to the commission by December 31 of each year does not exceed thirty thousand gallons. In the event such amount exceeds thirty thousand gallons, the farm winery shall be required to use a licensed wholesaler to distribute its wines for the following calendar year, except that this requirement shall not apply to wines produced and sold onsite at the farm winery pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section;</para><para>(e) Allow sampling and sale of the wine at the farm winery and at four branch outlets in the state in reasonable amounts;</para><para>(f) Sell wines produced at the farm winery to other Nebraska farm winery licensees, in bulk, bottled, labeled, or unlabeled, in accordance with 27 C.F.R. 24.308, 27 C.F.R. 24.309, and 27 C.F.R. 24.314, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2008;</para><para>(g) Purchase distilled spirits from licensed microdistilleries in Nebraska, in bulk or bottled, made entirely from Nebraska-licensed farm winery wine to be used in the production of fortified wine at the purchasing licensed farm winery;</para><para>(h) Store and warehouse products produced at the farm winery in a designated, secure, offsite storage facility if the holder of the farm winery license notifies the commission of the location of the facility and maintains, at the farm winery and at the facility, a separate perpetual inventory of the product stored at the facility. Consumption of alcoholic liquor at the facility is strictly prohibited; and</para><para>(i) Sell alcoholic liquor authorized under a farm winery license not in its original package, such as sangria or wine slushies, to a person twenty-one years of age or older for consumption off the premises if (i) the alcoholic liquor is (A) not partially consumed and (B) in a labeled and sealed container with a tamper-evident lid, cap, or seal, as approved by the commission, and (ii) for alcoholic liquor transported in a motor vehicle, the alcoholic liquor is placed in the trunk of the motor vehicle or the area behind the last upright seat of such motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk. A farm winery which sells alcoholic liquor authorized under a farm winery license not in its original package for consumption off the premises shall provide notice to the commission during a farm winery licensee's initial licensure or at the time of the annual renewal of such license regarding such sales.</para><para>(2) No farm winery shall manufacture wine in excess of fifty thousand gallons per year.</para><para>(3) A farm winery may manufacture and sell hard cider on its licensed premises. A farm winery shall not otherwise distribute the hard cider it manufactures except by sale to a wholesaler licensed under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act.</para><para>(4) A holder of a farm winery license may obtain a special designated license pursuant to section 53-124.11.</para><para>(5) A holder of a farm winery license may obtain an annual catering license pursuant to section 53-124.12.</para><para>(6) A holder of a farm winery license may obtain a promotional farmers market special designated license pursuant to section 53-124.16.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 279, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 479, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 536, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 562, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1103, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB330, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB592, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1056, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB274, &#167; 10. </para><operativedate>May 26, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>