<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id390"><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors"  statutenumber="53-138"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-138</statuteno><catchline>Pedal-pub vehicle license; activities authorized; licensee; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue a license to a person to operate a pedal-pub vehicle in this state. Each pedal-pub vehicle license shall expire on April 30 of each year. Each license shall be good throughout this state as a state license. Only one license shall be required for all pedal-pub vehicles operated in this state by the same owner. Each owner shall keep a duplicate of such license posted in each pedal-pub vehicle where alcoholic liquor is sold or consumed. No further license shall be required or tax levied by any county, city, or village for the privilege of operating a pedal-pub vehicle for the purpose of selling and allowing the consumption of alcoholic liquor while on or in a pedal-pub vehicle.</para><para>(2) The holder of a pedal-pub vehicle license may sell alcoholic liquor in individual drinks to customers who are twenty-one years of age or older to consume while they are on or in the pedal-pub vehicle and may allow such customers to consume alcoholic liquor not purchased from the licensee while the customers are on or in the pedal-pub vehicle. The licensee shall serve alcoholic liquor in opaque plastic containers that prominently display the licensee's trade name or logo or some other mark that is unique to the licensee under the licensee's pedal-pub vehicle license and shall require the use of such containers for the consumption of alcoholic liquor not purchased from the licensee.</para><para>(3) No customer shall take any open container of alcoholic liquor from the pedal-pub vehicle or consume the alcoholic liquor after leaving the pedal-pub vehicle. A customer may take unopened containers of alcoholic liquor not purchased from the licensee from the pedal-pub vehicle.</para><para>(4) The licensee shall not allow open containers of alcoholic liquor to leave the pedal-pub vehicle. The licensee shall be responsible for picking up and disposing of any litter or other waste or any personal property that originates from the pedal-pub vehicle and lands on public or private property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB330, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>