<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-169"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-169</statuteno><catchline>Manufacturer or wholesaler; craft brewery or microdistillery licensee; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) No manufacturer or wholesaler shall directly or indirectly: (a) Pay for any license to sell alcoholic liquor at retail or advance, furnish, lend, or give money for payment of such license; (b) purchase or become the owner of any note, mortgage, or other evidence of indebtedness of such licensee or any form of security therefor; (c) be interested in the ownership, conduct, or operation of the business of any licensee authorized to sell alcoholic liquor at retail; or (d) be interested directly or indirectly or as owner, part owner, lessee, or lessor thereof in any premises upon which alcoholic liquor is sold at retail.</para><para>(2) This section shall not apply to the holder of a farm winery license. The holder of a craft brewery license shall have the privileges and duties listed in section 53-123.14 with respect to the manufacture, distribution, and retail sale of beer, and the Nebraska Liquor Control Act shall not be construed to permit the holder of a craft brewery license to engage in the wholesale distribution of beer. The holder of a microdistillery license shall have the privileges and duties listed in section 53-123.16 with respect to the manufacture of alcoholic liquor, and the Nebraska Liquor Control Act shall not be construed to permit the holder of a microdistillery license to engage in the wholesale distribution of alcoholic liquor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 30, p. 396; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-330; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-169; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 187, &#167; 2, p. 619; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 182, &#167; 3, p. 574; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 258, &#167; 5, p. 765; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 751, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 483, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 183, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 279, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 750, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 17.</para></source></law></legaldoc>