<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-168.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-168.06</statuteno><catchline>General prohibition; exceptions.</catchline><para>No person shall manufacture, bottle, blend, sell, barter, transport, deliver, furnish, or possess any alcoholic liquor for beverage purposes except as specifically provided in the Nebraska Liquor Control Act. Nothing in the act shall prevent (1) the possession of alcoholic liquor legally obtained as provided in the act for the personal use of the possessor and his or her family and guests; (2) the making of wine, cider, or other alcoholic liquor by a person from fruits, vegetables, or grains, or the product thereof, by simple fermentation and without distillation, if made solely for the use of the maker and his or her family and guests; (3) any duly licensed practicing physician or dentist from possessing or using alcoholic liquor in the strict practice of his or her profession, any hospital or other institution caring for the sick and diseased persons from possessing and using alcoholic liquor for the treatment of bona fide patients of such hospital or other institution, or any drug store employing a licensed pharmacist from possessing or using alcoholic liquor in the compounding of prescriptions of licensed physicians; (4) the possession and dispensation of alcoholic liquor by an authorized representative of any religion on the premises of a place of worship, for the purpose of conducting any bona fide religious rite, ritual, or ceremony; (5) persons who are sixteen years old or older from carrying alcoholic liquor from licensed establishments when they are accompanied by a person not a minor; (6) persons who are sixteen years old or older from handling alcoholic liquor containers and alcoholic liquor in the course of their employment; (7) persons who are sixteen years old or older from removing and disposing of alcoholic liquor containers for the convenience of the employer and customers in the course of their employment; or (8) persons who are nineteen years old or older from serving or selling alcoholic liquor in the course of their employment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 1, p. 374; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-301; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-102; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 666, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 386, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 221, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 359, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 53-102; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 874, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 114, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Exemption accorded to possession of liquor for personal use of possessor, his family, or guests did not apply to business conducted as a common nuisance. State ex rel. Fitzgerald v. Kubik, 167 Neb. 219, 92 N.W.2d 533 (1958).</para><para>Possession of intoxicating liquor for personal use is authorized. State v. Kubik, 159 Neb. 509, 67 N.W.2d 755 (1954).</para><para>Purpose of Liquor Control Act was to govern and control sale and use of alcoholic liquors. State ex rel. Johnson v. Hash, 144 Neb. 495, 13 N.W.2d 716 (1944).</para><para>The Nebraska Liquor Control Commission is empowered to determine, by reasonable regulations, the hours for sale of beer outside the corporate limits of cities and villages, regardless of its alcoholic content. Griffin v. Gass, 133 Neb. 56, 274 N.W. 193 (1937).</para><para>It is a penal offense for owner and operator of a truck, not designated as a carrier or granted a permit therefor, to transport from another state a cargo of unstamped alcoholic liquors consigned to a bonded warehouse of liquors in this state. State v. Hyslop, 131 Neb. 681, 269 N.W. 512 (1936).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 