<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id13" statutenumber="53-110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-110</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Commissioners
and employees; qualifications;
employment by licensee authorized; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) No
person shall be appointed as a commissioner, the executive director of the
commission, or an employee of the commission who is not a citizen of the United
States and who has not resided within the State of Nebraska successively for
two years next preceding the date of his or her appointment.</para>
<para>(2) No person (a) convicted
of or who has pleaded guilty to a felony or any violation of any federal or
state law concerning the manufacture or sale of alcoholic liquor prior or
subsequent to the passage of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act, (b) who
has paid a fine or penalty in settlement of any prosecution against him or
her for any violation of such laws, or (c) who has forfeited his
or her bond to appear in court to answer charges for any such violation shall
be appointed commissioner.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except as otherwise provided in
subdivision (b) of this subsection, no commissioner or employee of the commission
may, directly or indirectly, individually, as a member of a partnership, as
a member of a limited liability company, or as a shareholder of a corporation,
have any interest whatsoever in the manufacture, sale, or distribution of
alcoholic liquor, receive any compensation or profit from such manufacture,
sale, or distribution, or have any interest whatsoever in the purchases or
sales made by the persons authorized by the act to purchase or to sell alcoholic
liquor.</para>
<para>(b) With the
written approval of the executive director, an employee of the commission,
other than the executive director or a division manager, may accept part-time
or seasonal employment with a person licensed or regulated by the commission.
No such employment shall be approved if the licensee receives more than fifty
percent of the licensee's gross revenue from the sale or dispensing of alcoholic
liquor.</para><para>(4) This
section shall not prevent any commissioner, the executive director, or any
employee from purchasing and keeping in his or her possession for the use
of himself, herself, or members of his or her family or guests any alcoholic
liquor which may be purchased or kept by any person pursuant to the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 11, p. 380; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-311; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-110; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 780, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 318; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB407, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
