<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-129</statuteno><catchline>Retail, bottle club, craft brewery, and microdistillery licenses; premises to which applicable; temporary expansion; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this section, retail, bottle club, craft brewery, and microdistillery licenses issued under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act apply only to that part of the premises described in the application approved by the commission and in the license issued on the application. For retail, bottle club, and microdistillery licenses, only one location shall be described in each license. For craft brewery licenses, up to five separate physical locations may be described in each license.</para><para>(2) After such license has been granted for the particular premises, the commission, with the approval of the local governing body and upon proper showing, may endorse upon the license permission to add to, delete from, or abandon the premises described in such license and, if applicable, to move from the premises to other premises approved by the local governing body. In order to obtain such approval, the retail, bottle club, craft brewery, or microdistillery licensee shall file with the local governing body a request in writing and a statement under oath which shows that the premises, as added to or deleted from or to which such move is to be made, comply in all respects with the requirements of the act. No such addition, deletion, or move shall be made by any such licensee until the license has been endorsed to that effect in writing by the local governing body and by the commission and the licensee furnishes proof of payment of the renewal fee prescribed in subsection (4) of section 53-131.</para><para>(3)(a) A retail, bottle club, craft brewery, or microdistillery licensee may apply to the local governing body for a temporary expansion of its licensed premises to an immediately adjacent area owned or leased by the licensee or to an immediately adjacent street, parking lot, or alley, not to exceed fifty days for calendar year 2020 and, for each calendar year thereafter, not to exceed fifteen days per calendar year. The temporary area shall otherwise comply with all requirements of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act.</para><para>(b) The licensee shall file an application with the local governing body which shall contain (i) the name of the applicant, (ii) the premises for which a temporary expansion is requested, identified by street and number if practicable and, if not, by some other appropriate description which definitely locates the premises, (iii) the name of the owner or lessee of the premises for which the temporary expansion is requested, (iv) sufficient evidence that the licensee will carry on the activities and business authorized by the license for himself, herself, or itself and not as the agent of any other person, group, organization, or corporation, for profit or not for profit, (v) a statement of the type of activity to be carried on during the time period for which a temporary expansion is requested, and (vi) sufficient evidence that the temporary expansion will be supervised by persons or managers who are agents of and directly responsible to the licensee.</para><para>(c) No temporary expansion provided for by this subsection shall be granted without the approval of the local governing body. The local governing body may establish criteria for approving or denying a temporary expansion. The local governing body may designate an agent to determine whether a temporary expansion is to be approved or denied. Such agent shall follow criteria established by the local governing body in making the determination. The determination of the agent shall be considered the determination of the local governing body unless otherwise provided by the local governing body.</para><para>(d) For purposes of this section, the local governing body shall be that of the city or village within which the premises for which the temporary expansion is requested are located or, if such premises are not within the corporate limits of a city or village, then the local governing body shall be that of the county within which the premises for which the temporary expansion is requested are located.</para><para>(e) The decision of the local governing body shall be final. If the applicant does not qualify for a temporary expansion, the temporary expansion shall be denied by the local governing body.</para><para>(f) The city, village, or county clerk shall deliver confirmation of the temporary expansion to the licensee upon receipt of any fee or tax imposed by such city, village, or county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 49, p. 405; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-349; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-129; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 386, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 848, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 213, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 781, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 183, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1292, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 267, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1056, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>If a named licensee desires to relocate the license, the licensee may do so under the provisions of this section by making application to either the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission or the local governing body. The relocation of a license from its issued premises to new premises is dependent upon approval by the local governing body. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska Liquor Control Comm., 208 Neb. 630, 304 N.W.2d 922 (1981).</para><para>An agreement between lessor and lessee that lessee will apply for a license for the premises, and will not seek permission to transfer it to another location, and upon expiration of the lease will assist lessor in obtaining a license for the premises is not void. Greco v. Bonacci, 194 Neb. 685, 234 N.W.2d 904 (1975).</para><para>Where licensee stored alcoholic beverages in an unauthorized area without permission of the commission and permitted part of licensed premises to be used for gambling, suspension of license was authorized and reasonable. O'Connor v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 191 Neb. 436, 215 N.W.2d 635 (1974).</para><para>Purpose of this section is to provide a short procedure for change of location of business of licensee. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 181 Neb. 277, 147 N.W.2d 803 (1967).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>