<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section><?Pub Caret?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-123.16"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.16</statuteno><catchline>Microdistillery license; rights
of licensee.</catchline><para>Any person who operates a microdistillery shall
obtain a license pursuant to the Nebraska Liquor Control Act. A license to
operate a microdistillery shall permit the licensee to produce on the premises
a maximum of ten thousand gallons of liquor per year. A microdistillery may
also sell to licensed wholesalers for sale and distribution to licensed retailers.
A microdistillery license issued pursuant to this section shall be the only
license required by the Nebraska Liquor Control Act for the manufacture and
retail sale of microdistilled product for consumption on or off the licensed
premises, except that the sale of any beer, wine, or alcoholic liquor, other
than microdistilled product manufactured by the microdistillery licensee,
by the drink for consumption on the microdistillery premises shall require
the appropriate retail license. Any license held by the operator of a microdistillery
shall be subject to the act. A holder of a microdistillery license may obtain
an annual catering license pursuant to section 53-124.12, a
special designated license pursuant to section 53-124.11, or an entertainment district license pursuant to section
53-123.17. The commission may, upon the conditions it determines,
grant to any microdistillery licensed under this section a special license
authorizing the microdistillery to purchase and to import, from such persons
as are entitled to sell the same, wines or spirits to be used solely as ingredients
and for the sole purpose of blending with and flavoring microdistillery products
as a part of the microdistillation process.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1130, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>