<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id767"><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-160.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-160.04</statuteno><catchline>Ready-to-drink cocktails; tax on manufacturer or wholesaler; amount; exemption; duties of commission.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act, for the purpose of raising revenue, a tax is imposed upon the privilege of engaging in business as a manufacturer or a wholesaler of ready-to-drink cocktails at a rate of ninety-five cents per gallon. The gallonage tax imposed by this section shall be imposed only on alcoholic liquor upon which a federal excise tax is imposed.</para><para>(2) Manufacturers or wholesalers of ready-to-drink cocktails shall be exempt from the payment of the gallonage tax imposed by this section on such products upon satisfactory proof, including bills of lading furnished to the commission by affidavit or otherwise as the commission may require, that such ready-to-drink cocktails were manufactured in this state but shipped out of this state for sale and consumption outside this state.</para><para>(3) The gallonage tax imposed by this section shall be in addition to all other occupation or privilege taxes imposed by this state or by any municipal corporation or political subdivision thereof.</para><para>(4) The commission shall collect the gallonage tax on ready-to-drink cocktails and shall account for and remit to the State Treasurer at least once each week all money collected pursuant to this section. If any spirits manufactured in or shipped into this state are sold to a licensed manufacturer or wholesaler of this state to be used solely as an ingredient in the manufacture of ready-to-drink cocktails for human consumption, the tax imposed upon such manufacturer or wholesaler shall be reduced by the amount of the taxes which have been paid as to such spirits so used under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act. The net proceeds of all revenue arising under this section shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB274, &#167; 6. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>