
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-123.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.04</statuteno><catchline>Retail license; rights of licensee; sampling; removal of unsealed bottle of wine; conditions; sales for consumption off the premises; conditions; notice to commission, required.</catchline><para>(1) A retail license shall allow the licensee to sell and offer for sale at retail either in the original package or otherwise, as prescribed in the retail license, on the premises specified in the retail license or the entertainment district license or on the premises where catering is occurring, alcoholic liquor or beer for use or consumption but not for resale in any form except as provided in section 53-175.</para><para>(2) Nothing in the Nebraska Liquor Control Act shall prohibit a holder of a Class D license from allowing the sampling of tax-paid wine for consumption on the premises by such licensee or his or her employees in cooperation with a licensed wholesaler in the manner prescribed by the commission.</para><para>(3)(a) A restaurant holding a license to sell alcoholic liquor at retail for consumption on the licensed premises may permit a customer to remove one unsealed bottle of wine for consumption off the premises if the customer has purchased a full-course meal and consumed a portion of the bottle of wine with such full-course meal on the licensed premises. The licensee or his or her agent shall (i) securely reseal such bottle and place the bottle in a bag designed so that it is visibly apparent that the resealed bottle of wine has not been opened or tampered with and (ii) provide a dated receipt to the customer and attach to such bag a copy of the dated receipt for the resealed bottle of wine and the full-course meal.</para><para>(b) If the resealed bottle of wine is transported in a motor vehicle, it must be placed in the trunk of the motor vehicle or the area behind the last upright seat of such motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk.</para><para>(c) For purposes of this subsection, full-course meal means a diversified selection of food which is ordinarily consumed with the use of tableware and cannot conveniently be consumed while standing or walking.</para><para>(4) The holder of a Class C liquor license as described in subdivision (6)(a)(iii) of section 53-124 may sell alcoholic liquor not in the original package, such as a mixed drink or cocktail, to a person twenty-one years of age or older for consumption off the premises if (a) the alcoholic liquor is (i) not partially consumed and (ii) in a labeled and sealed container with a tamper-evident lid, cap, or seal, as approved by the commission, and (b) for alcoholic liquor transported in a motor vehicle, the alcoholic liquor is placed in the trunk of the motor vehicle or the area behind the last upright seat of such motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk.</para><para>(5) The holder of a Class I liquor license as described in subdivision (6)(a)(v) of section 53-124 may sell alcoholic liquor not in the original package, such as a mixed drink or cocktail, to a person twenty-one years of age or older for consumption off the premises if (a) the alcoholic liquor is (i) not partially consumed, (ii) in a labeled and sealed container with a tamper-evident lid, cap, or seal, as approved by the commission, and (iii) purchased along with food, and (b) for alcoholic liquor transported in a motor vehicle, the alcoholic liquor is placed in the trunk of the motor vehicle or the area behind the last upright seat of such motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk.</para><para>(6) A licensee intending to sell alcoholic liquor in the manner authorized under subsections (4) and (5) of this section shall provide notice of such intention to the commission during initial licensure or upon the licensee's annual renewal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 25, p. 390; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-325; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-123; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 187, &#167; 1(4), p. 617; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 188, &#167; 1(4), p. 622; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 318, &#167; 5, p. 892; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 111, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 386, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 154, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 441, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 53, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 859, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 278, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 562, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1130, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB274, &#167; 9. </para><operativedate>May 26, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>