<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-135.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-135.02</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; renewal; no vested right.</catchline><para>Any licensee may renew his, her, or its license at the expiration thereof in the manner set forth in section 53-135 if the licensee is then qualified to receive a license and the premises for which such renewal license is sought are the same premises licensed under the license to be renewed and are suitable for such purpose. The renewal privilege provided for in this section shall not be construed as a vested right which shall in any case prevent the commission from decreasing the number of licenses to be issued within its jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 27, p. 394; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-327; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-150; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 249, &#167; 17, p. 874; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 53-150; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 42. </para></source><annotation><para>An appeal from the district court's decision reversing the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission's approval of a class D liquor license under this section was not moot despite the expiration of the original license during the pendency of an appeal, because a licensee has a constitutionally protected interest in obtaining the renewal of an existing license, and that interest would be jeopardized if the license were wrongfully taken away. Orchard Hill Neighborhood v. Orchard Hill Mercantile, 274 Neb. 154, 738 N.W.2d 820 (2007).</para><para>An administrative agency is limited in authority to those powers granted to it by statute. Thus, without a showing by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission or the objecting city that a renewal applicant did not meet one of the renewal requirements of this section and section 53-135, the commission could not demand that the applicant submit a long-form liquor license application. Grand Island Latin Club v. Nebraska Liq. Cont. Comm., 251 Neb. 61, 554 N.W.2d 778 (1996).</para><para>As the result of the renewal privilege established by this section, a licensee is entitled to renewal of a liquor license, that is, continuation of an existing license, if at the time for renewal the licensee meets the requirements which existed when the license to be renewed was initially issued. Pump &amp; Pantry, Inc. v. City of Grand Island, 233 Neb. 191, 444 N.W.2d 312 (1989).</para><para>The language of section 53-135 and this section discloses a legislative intent to codify a practice of approving an application for continuation of an existing liquor license in the absence of a change of circumstances indicated on the licensee's renewal application. Pump &amp; Pantry, Inc. v. City of Grand Island, 233 Neb. 191, 444 N.W.2d 312 (1989).</para><para>District court cannot enjoin hearing by municipality with respect to issuance or revocation of liquor license. Leeman v. Vocelka, 149 Neb. 702, 32 N.W.2d 274 (1948).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 