<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-168"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-168</statuteno><catchline>Receiving money, credit, discounts, rebates, or other inducement; unlawful acts; penalty; private or generic label permitted.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person having a retail license to sell beer to accept credit for the purchase of beer from any manufacturer or wholesaler of beer and for any person having a retail license to sell alcoholic liquor or any officer, associate, member, representative, or agent of such licensee to accept, receive, or borrow money or anything else of value or to accept or to receive credit, other than merchandising credit in the ordinary course of business for a period not to exceed thirty days, directly or indirectly, from (a) any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation engaged in manufacturing or wholesaling such liquor, (b) any person connected with or in any way representing such manufacturer or wholesaler, (c) any member of the family of such manufacturer or wholesaler, (d) any stockholders in any corporation engaged in manufacturing or wholesaling such liquor, or (e) any officer, manager, agent, member, or representative of such manufacturer or wholesaler.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any manufacturer or wholesaler to give or lend money or otherwise loan or extend credit, except the merchandising credit referred to in subsection (1) of this section, directly or indirectly, to any such licensee or to the manager, representative, agent, member, officer, or director of such licensee. It shall be unlawful for any wholesaler to participate in any manner in a merchandising and coupon plan of any manufacturer involving alcoholic liquor and the redemption in cash. The redemption of any merchandising and coupon plan involving cash shall be made by the manufacturer to the consumer.</para><para>(3) If any holder of a license to sell alcoholic liquor at retail or wholesale violates subsection (1) or (2) of this section, such license shall be suspended or revoked by the commission in the manner provided by the Nebraska Liquor Control Act.</para><para>(4) It shall not be a violation of subsection (1) or (2) of this section for a manufacturer or wholesaler to sell or provide alcoholic liquor exclusively or in minimum quantities in containers bearing a private label or to sell or provide alcoholic liquor in containers bearing a generic label to a wholesaler or retailer.</para><para>(5) It shall not be a violation of subsection (1) or (2) of this section for a wholesaler or retailer to accept or purchase from a manufacturer or wholesaler alcoholic liquor exclusively or in minimum quantities in containers bearing a private label or for a wholesaler or retailer to accept or purchase from a manufacturer or wholesaler alcoholic liquor in containers bearing a generic label.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 29, p. 395; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 104, &#167; 1, p. 424; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-329; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-168; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 182, &#167; 2, p. 573; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 181, &#167; 1, p. 571; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 335, &#167; 1, p. 896; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 441, &#167; 1, p. 1475; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 442, &#167; 1, p. 1478; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 443, &#167; 1, p. 1480; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 874, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 483, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 183, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 321; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 28. </para></source><annotation><para>The 1969 amendment making it unlawful for any manufacturer, distributor, or wholesaler of alcoholic liquor to give discounts to any retailer is constitutional. Central Markets West, Inc. v. State, 186 Neb. 79, 180 N.W.2d 880 (1970) supplemental opinion, 186 Neb. 276, 182 N.W.2d 898 (1971).</para><para>The 1967 amendment to this section prohibiting a retailer from accepting credit for the purchase of beer from a wholesaler is constitutional; exception as to baseball stadiums is unconstitutional. Tom &amp; Jerry, Inc. v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 183 Neb. 410, 160 N.W.2d 232 (1968).</para><para>Liquor Control Commission cannot adopt rules and regulations in conflict with Liquor Control Act. Terry Carpenter, Inc. v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 175 Neb. 26, 120 N.W.2d 374 (1963).</para><para>Provisions of rule promulgated by the Liquor Control Commission authorizing the giving away of advertising novelties were invalid. State ex rel. Nebraska Beer Wholesalers Assn. v. Young, 153 Neb. 395, 44 N.W.2d 806 (1950).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>