<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-122</statuteno><catchline>Sale of liquor by drink; election;
submission; procedure; when not required; prohibited acts; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue licenses for the sale of alcoholic liquor,
except beer, by the drink subject to all the terms and conditions of the Nebraska
Liquor Control Act in all cities and villages in this state, except in those
cases when it affirmatively appears that the issuance will render null and
void prior conveyances of land to such city or village for public uses and
purposes by purchase, gift, or devise, under the conditions and in the manner
provided in this section.</para>
<para>(2) If (a) a sufficient petition is signed by the registered voters
of any such city or village of such number as equals twenty percent of the
votes cast at the last general election held in such city or village, which
petition requests that the question of licensing the sale of alcoholic liquor,
except beer, by the drink in the city or village be submitted to the registered
voters of the city or village at a special election to be called for that
purpose and (b) such petition is presented to the clerk of the city or village,
the clerk shall cause to be published one time in a legal newspaper published
in or of general circulation in the city or village a notice of a special
election to be held not less than ten days nor more than twenty days after
the date of such publication. The notice shall state the proposition to be
submitted at such special election.</para>
<para>(3) The question of licensing the sale of alcoholic liquor either by
the drink or in the original package, or both by the drink and in the original
package, may also be submitted at any general municipal election, except as
otherwise provided in section 53-121, in any city or village in this state
subject to the following:</para>
<para>(a) Upon the filing with the clerk of the city or village of a petition
signed by registered voters of the city or village in a number equal to twenty
percent of the votes cast at the last general election held in the city or
village, such proposition or propositions shall be submitted;</para>
<para>(b) Each petition shall conform to the requirements of section 32-628;</para>
<para>(c) At the top of each sheet shall be stated the proposition or propositions
to be submitted and the date of the general municipal election at which it
is proposed to be submitted;</para>
<para>(d) No signature on the petition shall be valid unless appended to the
petition within the last ninety days prior to the date of filing the petition
with the clerk of the city or village; and</para>
<para>(e) The petition shall be filed thirty days prior to the day of the
general municipal election at which the proposition is to be submitted, and
during such thirty-day period no signature shall be withdrawn and no signature
shall be added.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who signs any proposal or petition contemplated under
this section knowing that he or she is not a registered voter in the place
where such proposal or petition is made, who signs any name other than his
or her own to such proposal or petition, or who aids or abets any other person
in doing any of the acts mentioned is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. Any
person who bribes or gives or pays any money or thing of value to any person
directly or indirectly to induce him or her to sign such proposal or petition,
who accepts money for signing such proposal or petition, or who aids or abets
any other person in doing any of such acts is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para>
<para>(5) Upon the ballot either at the special election or at any general
municipal election, the proposition or propositions shall be stated as follows:</para>
<para>Shall the sale of alcoholic liquor, except beer, by the drink be licensed
in (here insert the name of the city or village)?</para>
<para>.... For license to sell by drink.</para>
<para>.... Against license to sell by drink.</para>
<para>Shall the sale of alcoholic liquor, except beer, by the package be licensed
in (here insert the name of the city or village)?</para>
<para>.... For license to sell by the package.</para>
<para>.... Against license to sell by the package.</para>
<para>The provisions of the Election Act relating to election officers, voting
places, election apparatus and blanks, preparation and form of ballots, information
to voters, delivery of ballots, calling of elections, conduct of elections,
manner of voting, counting of votes, records and certificates of elections,
and recounts of votes, so far as applicable, shall apply to voting on the
proposition or propositions under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act, and a majority
vote of those voting on the question shall be mandatory upon the commission.</para>
<para>(6) If the question is to be submitted at a statewide primary or general
election, the petitions shall be filed with the clerk of the city or village
not less than sixty days prior to the election. The provisions for the required
number of signers and the form of petition shall be the same as for a special
election. The clerk of the city or village shall verify the signatures on
the petitions with the voter registration records in the office of the county
clerk or election commissioner. During the ten-day period while the petitions
are being checked, no signatures shall be withdrawn and no signatures shall
be added.</para>
<para>If the clerk of the city or village finds the petitions to be valid,
he or she shall, not less than fifty days prior to the statewide primary or
general election, give notice in writing to the county clerk or election commissioner
that the question is to be submitted at the time of the statewide primary
or general election. The election notices, issuing of the official ballots
on election day, issuing of the ballots for early voting, and counting and
canvassing of the ballots shall be conducted by the county clerk or election
commissioner as provided in the Election Act and the official results certified
to the clerk of the city or village.</para>
<para>(7) An election may not be held in the same city or village under this
section more often than once every twenty-three months. A Class I retail license under subdivision (6)(a)(v) of
section 53-124 is not subject to this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 48, p. 403; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-348; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-122; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 309, &#167; 1, p. 911; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 310, &#167; 2, p. 923; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 439, &#167; 1, p. 1469; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 556, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 311; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 920, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 781, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 183, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 570; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 267, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 278, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 51.</para></source><annotation><para>Percentage of votes required is based on last general municipal election. Allen v. Tobin, 155 Neb. 212, 51 N.W.2d 338 (1952).</para><para>Funds collected as state license fees are properly distributed for use of all school districts within state and should not be paid over to counties in which liquor licenses are granted. School District of Omaha v. Gass, 131 Neb. 312, 267 N.W. 528 (1936).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>