<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-403"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-403</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For
purposes of the Minor Alcoholic Liquor Liability Act:</para>
<para>(1) Alcoholic liquor has the definition found in section 53-103.02;</para>
<para>(2) Intoxication means an impairment of a person's mental or physical
faculties as a result of his or her use of alcoholic liquor so as to diminish
the person's ability to think and act in the manner of a reasonably prudent
person in full possession of his or her faculties using reasonable care under
the same or similar circumstances;</para>
<para>(3) Licensee means a person holding a license issued under the Nebraska
Liquor Control Act to sell alcoholic liquor at retail;</para>
<para>(4) Minor has the definition found in section 53-103.23;</para>
<para>(5) Retailer means a licensee, any agent or employee of the licensee
acting within the scope and course of his or her employment, or any person
who at the time of the events leading to an action under the Minor Alcoholic
Liquor Liability Act was required to have a license issued under the Nebraska
Liquor Control Act in order to sell alcoholic liquor at retail;</para>
<para>(6) Service of alcoholic liquor means any sale, gift, or other manner
of conveying possession of alcoholic liquor; and</para>
<para>(7) Social host means a person who knowingly allows consumption of alcoholic
liquor in his or her home or on property under his or her control by one or
more minors. Social host does not include (a) a parent providing alcoholic
liquor to only his or her minor child and to no other minors or (b) a religious
corporation, organization, association, or society, and any authorized representative
of such religious corporation, organization, association, or society, dispensing
alcoholic liquor as part of any bona fide religious rite, ritual, or ceremony.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB573, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 79.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>