<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-171"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>53-171</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; issuance of more than one kind to same person; when unlawful; craft brewery, manufacturer, or microdistillery licensee; limitations.</catchline><para>No person licensed as a wholesaler of alcoholic liquor shall be permitted to receive any retail license at the same time. No person licensed as a manufacturer shall be permitted to receive any retail license at the same time except as set forth in subsection (2) of section 53-123.01 with respect to the manufacture, distribution, and retail sale of beer, and the Nebraska Liquor Control Act shall not be construed to permit the holder of a manufacturer’s license issued pursuant to such subsection to engage in the wholesale distribution of alcoholic liquor. No person licensed as a retailer of alcoholic liquor shall be permitted to receive any manufacturer's or wholesale license at the same time. This section shall not apply to the holder of a farm winery license. The holder of a craft brewery license shall have the privileges and duties listed in section 53-123.14 with respect to the manufacture, distribution, and retail sale of beer, and the Nebraska Liquor Control Act shall not be construed to permit the holder of a craft brewery license to engage in the wholesale distribution of beer. The holder of a microdistillery license shall have the privileges and duties listed in section 53-123.16 with respect to the manufacture of alcoholic liquor, and the Nebraska Liquor Control Act shall not be construed to permit the holder of a microdistillery license to engage in the wholesale distribution of alcoholic liquor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 30, p. 397; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-330; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-171; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 182, &#167; 1, p. 573; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 441, &#167; 4, p. 1478; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 279, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 750, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 26. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>