<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id00"  statutenumber="53-134.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-134.01</statuteno><catchline>Class C license holder; limited bottling endorsement; application; fee; conditions of sale.</catchline><para>(1) The holder of a Class C license may obtain a limited bottling endorsement for such license as prescribed in this section. The endorsement shall be issued for the same period and may be renewed in the same manner as the Class C license. A limited bottling endorsement may not be used in conjunction with a special designated license.</para><para>(2) A licensee desiring to obtain a limited bottling endorsement for a license shall file with the commission an application upon such forms as the commission prescribes and a fee of three hundred dollars payable to the commission.</para><para>(3) The holder of a limited bottling endorsement may sell beer for consumption off the licensed premises in sealed containers filled as provided in this subsection if:</para><para>(a) The sale occurs on the licensed premises of the licensee during the hours the licensee is authorized to sell beer;</para><para>(b) The licensee uses sanitary containers purchased by the customer from the licensee or exchanged for containers previously purchased by the customer from the licensee. The containers shall prominently display the endorsement holder's trade name or logo or some other mark that is unique to the endorsement holder and shall hold no more than sixty-four ounces;</para><para>(c) The licensee seals the container in a manner designed so that it is visibly apparent whether the sealed container has been tampered with or opened or seals the container and places the container in a bag designed so that it is visibly apparent whether the sealed container has been tampered with or opened; and</para><para>(d) The licensee provides a dated receipt to the customer and attaches a copy of the dated receipt to the sealed container or, if the sealed container is placed in a bag, to the bag.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB330, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 18. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>