<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id922"><amendatorysection chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-124.16"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-124.16</statuteno><catchline>Promotional farmers market special designated license; issuance; conditions; applicaiton; fee; rights of licensee.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue a promotional farmers market special designated license to a craft brewery, microdistillery, or farm winery licensee to sell or dispense alcoholic liquor, which the holder is licensed to produce, at a farmers market outside of the manufacturer's designated premises under conditions specified in this section.</para><para>(2) A promotional farmers market special designated license issued under this section shall not be used without approval of the local governing body pursuant to section 53-124.17.</para><para>(3) The craft brewery, microdistillery, or farm winery licensee seeking a promotional farmers market special designated license under this section shall file an application on such forms as the commission may prescribe. Such forms shall contain, along with other information as required by the commission, (a) the name of the applicant, (b) the premises for which the applicant is licensed, identified by street and number if practicable and, if not, by some other appropriate description which definitely locates the premises, (c) sufficient evidence that the licensee will carry on the activities and business authorized by the license on behalf of the licensee, and not as the agent of any other person, group, organization, or corporation, for profit or not for profit, (d) a statement of the type of activity to be carried on during the time period for which a promotional farmers market special designated license is requested, (e) sufficient evidence that the activity will be supervised by persons or managers who are agents of and directly responsible to the holder of the promotional farmers market special designated license, and (f) information on a safety and security plan for use of the promotional farmers market special designated license as required by the commission.</para><para>(4) There shall be a fee of fifteen dollars for a promotional farmers market special designated license payable to the commission and submitted with the application. The applicant shall be exempt from the provisions of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act requiring an application or renewal fee and the provisions of the act requiring the expiration of forty-five days from the time the application is received by the commission prior to the issuance of a license, if granted by the commission. The promotional farmers market special designated license shall be issued for the same period and may be renewed in the same manner as the craft brewery, microdistillery, or farm winery license.</para><para>(5) If the applicant meets the requirements of this section, a promotional farmers market special designated license shall be granted and issued by the commission for use by the holder of the promotional farmers market special designated license. All statutory provisions and rules and regulations of the commission that apply to a retail license shall apply to the holder of a promotional farmers market special designated license with the exception of such statutory provisions and rules and regulations of the commission so designated by the commission and stated upon the issued promotional farmers market special designated license, except that the commission may not designate exemption from sections 53-180 to 53-180.07. The decision of the commission shall be final. If the applicant does not qualify for a promotional farmers market special designated license, the application shall be denied by the commission.</para><para>(6) A promotional farmers market special designated license issued by the commission shall be mailed or delivered to the licensee. The licensee shall comply with any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. Violation of any provision of this section or section 53-124.17 may be cause to revoke, cancel, or suspend the promotional farmers market special designated license or the class of retail license issued under section 53-124 held by such licensee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB274, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>May 26, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>