<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-138.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-138.01</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; disposition of fees.</catchline><para>The State Treasurer shall credit three hundred ninety-five dollars of each four-hundred-dollar application fee and forty dollars of each forty-five-dollar application fee and each renewal fee to the General Fund and the remaining five dollars to the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission Rule and Regulation Cash Fund to be used for providing licensees with materials pursuant to section 53-117.05. All retail and bottle club license fees received by the city or village treasurer, as the case may be, shall inure to the school fund of the district lying wholly or partially within the corporate limits of such city or village. Except as otherwise provided in section 53-123.15, the State Treasurer shall distribute license fees received by the commission for licenses issued pertaining to alcoholic liquor, including beer, in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska. All retail and bottle club license fees received by the county treasurer, as provided in section 53-124, shall be credited to the school fund of the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 92, p. 424; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-392; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-138; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 169, &#167; 2(2), p. 448; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 180, &#167; 2, p. 570; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 249, &#167; 12, p. 872; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 202, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 345, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 973, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB867, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 23. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>