<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-1,115"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-1,115</statuteno><catchline>Proceedings before commission; service upon parties; rehearings; costs.</catchline><para>(1) A copy of the rule, regulation, order, or decision of the commission denying an application or suspending, canceling, or revoking a license or of any notice required by any proceeding before it, certified under the seal of the commission, shall be served upon each party of record to the proceeding before the commission. Service upon any attorney of record for any such party shall be deemed to be service upon such party. Each party appearing before the commission shall enter his or her appearance and indicate to the commission his or her address for such service. The mailing of a copy of any rule, regulation, order, or decision of the commission or of any notice by the commission, in the proceeding, to such party at such address shall be deemed to be service upon such party.</para><para>(2) Within thirty days after the service of any rule, regulation, order, or decision of the commission denying an application or suspending, canceling, or revoking any license upon any party to the proceeding, as provided for by subsection (1) of this section, such party may apply for a rehearing with respect to any matters determined by the commission. The commission shall receive and consider such application for a rehearing within thirty days after its filing with the executive director of the commission. If such application for rehearing is granted, the commission shall proceed as promptly as possible to consider the matters presented by such application. No appeal shall be allowed from any decision of the commission except as provided in section 53-1,116.</para><para>(3) Upon final disposition of any proceeding, costs shall be paid by the party or parties against whom a final decision is rendered. Costs may be taxed or retaxed to local governing bodies as well as individuals. Only one rehearing referred to in subsection (2) of this section shall be granted by the commission on application of any one party.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, party of record means:</para><para>(a) In the case of an administrative proceeding before the commission on the application for a retail, bottle club, craft brewery, or microdistillery license:</para><para>(i) The applicant;</para><para>(ii) Each individual protesting the issuance of such license pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of section 53-133;</para><para>(iii) The local governing body if it is entering an appearance to protest the issuance of the license or if it is requesting a hearing pursuant to subdivision (1)(c) of section 53-133; and</para><para>(iv) The commission;</para><para>(b) In the case of an administrative proceeding before a local governing body to cancel or revoke a retail, bottle club, craft brewery, or microdistillery license:</para><para>(i) The licensee; and</para><para>(ii) The local governing body; and</para><para>(c) In the case of an administrative proceeding before the commission to suspend, cancel, or revoke a retail, bottle club, craft brewery, or microdistillery license:</para><para>(i) The licensee; and</para><para>(ii) The commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 781, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 183, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 267, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 29. </para></source><annotation><para>This section defines which parties qualify as parties of record in the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission's proceedings. Thus, it defines which parties are "parties of record" that must be included in the district court's review of the commission's proceedings pursuant to section 84-917 of the Administrative Procedure Act. Kozal v. Nebraska Liquor Control Comm., 297 Neb. 938, 902 N.W.2d 147 (2017).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>