<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id32" statutenumber="53-131"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-131</statuteno><catchline id="id35">Retail, bottle club, craft brewery, and microdistillery licenses; application; fees; notice of application to city, village, or county; cigar shop; information required; renewal; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Any person desiring to obtain a new license to sell alcoholic liquor at retail, a bottle club license, a craft brewery license, or a microdistillery license shall file with the commission:</para><para>(a) An application upon forms prescribed by the commission, including the information required by subsection (3) of this section for an application to operate a cigar shop;</para><para>(b) The license fee if under sections 53-124 and 53-124.01 such fee is payable to the commission, which fee shall be returned to the applicant if the application is denied; and</para><para>(c) The nonrefundable application fee in the sum of four hundred dollars, except that the nonrefundable application fee for an application for a cigar shop shall be one thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) The commission shall notify the clerk of the city or village in which such license is sought or, if the license sought is not sought within a city or village, the county clerk of the county in which such license is sought, of the receipt of the application and shall include one copy of the application with the notice. No such license shall be issued or denied by the commission until the expiration of the time allowed for the receipt of a recommendation of denial or an objection requiring a hearing under subdivision (1)(a) or (b) of section 53-133. During the period of forty-five days after the date of receipt by mail or electronic delivery of such application from the commission, the local governing body of such city, village, or county may make and submit to the commission recommendations relative to the granting or refusal to grant such license to the applicant.</para><para>(3) For an application to operate a cigar shop, the application shall include proof of the cigar shop's annual gross revenue as requested by the commission and such other information as requested by the commission to establish the intent to operate as a cigar shop. The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to regulate cigar shops. The rules and regulations existing on August 1, 2014, applicable to cigar bars shall apply to cigar shops until amended or repealed by the commission.</para><para>(4) For renewal of a license under this section, a licensee shall file with the commission an application, the license fee as provided in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, and a renewal fee of forty-five dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 82, p. 417; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-382; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-131; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 203, &#167; 1, p. 580; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 249, &#167; 6, p. 866; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 413, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 848, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 213, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 947, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 911, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 550, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 781, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 202, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 183, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 750, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 267, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 973, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 278, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB355, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB407, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB118, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB330, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 14. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The portion of this section amended by 1986 Neb. Laws, L.B. 911, is declared unconstitutional. Bosselman, Inc. v. State, 230 Neb. 471, 432 N.W.2d 226 (1988).</para><para>Failure to obtain approval to relocate a license pursuant to section 53-129, R.R.S.1943 does not mean that another license may not be sought under this section. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska Liquor Control Comm., 208 Neb. 630, 304 N.W.2d 922 (1981).</para><para>City council's resolution approving applicant's request for Class C license includes, by implication, a recommendation for a Class D license. Winkelmann v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 198 Neb. 481, 253 N.W.2d 307 (1977).</para><para>Applications to provide license were properly filed under this section. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 181 Neb. 277, 147 N.W.2d 803 (1967).</para><para>Application for package liquor license was properly made to Liquor Control Commission. Allen v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 179 Neb. 767, 140 N.W.2d 413 (1966).</para><para>This section provides for the issuance of a license to sell alcoholic liquor including beer at retail, and is controlling over another section declaring public policy in favor of separate sale. Hanson v. Gass, 130 Neb. 685, 267 N.W. 403 (1936).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>