<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id54">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id56" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="53-117.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-117.03</statuteno><catchline id="id59">Employee and
management training; commission; powers and duties; fees; certification.</catchline><para>(1) On or before January 1, 2007, the commission shall adopt
and promulgate rules and regulations governing programs which provide training
for persons employed in the sale and service of alcoholic liquor and management
of licensed premises. Such rules and regulations may include, but need not
be limited to:</para>
<para>(a) Minimum standards governing training of beverage servers,
including standards and requirements governing curriculum, program trainers,
and certification requirements;</para>
<para>(b) Minimum standards governing training in management of
licensed premises, including standards and requirements governing curriculum,
program trainers, and certification requirements;</para>
<para>(c) Minimum standards governing the methods allowed for training
programs which may include the Internet, interactive video, live training
in various locations across the state, and other means deemed appropriate
by the commission;</para>
<para>(d) Methods for approving beverage-server training organizations
and programs. All beverage-server training programs approved by the commission
shall issue a certificate of completion to all persons who successfully complete
the program and shall provide the names of all persons completing the program
to the commission;</para>
<para>(e) Enrollment fees in an amount determined by the commission
to be necessary to cover the administrative costs, including salary
and benefits, of enrolling in a training program offered by the
commission pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, but not to exceed thirty
dollars; and</para>
<para>(f) Procedures and fees for certification, which fees shall
be in an amount determined by the commission to be sufficient to defray the administrative costs, including salary and benefits, associated
with maintaining a list of persons certified under this section and issuing
proof of certification to eligible individuals but shall not exceed twenty
dollars.</para>
<para>(2) The commission may create a program to provide training
for persons employed in the sale and service of alcoholic liquor and management
of licensed premises. The program shall include training on the issues of
sales and service of alcoholic liquor to minors and to visibly inebriated
purchasers. The commission may charge each person enrolling in the program
an enrollment fee as provided in the rules and regulations, but such fee shall
not exceed thirty dollars. All such fees shall be collected by the commission
and remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Liquor Control
Commission Rule and Regulation Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(3) A person who has completed a training program which complies
with the rules and regulations, whether such program is offered by the commission
or by another organization, may become certified by the commission upon the
commission receiving evidence that he or she has completed such program and
the person seeking certification paying the certification fee established
under this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 845, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 22.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>