<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-135"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>53-135</statuteno><catchline>Retail or bottle club licenses; automatic renewal; conditions.</catchline><para>A retail or bottle club license issued by the commission and outstanding may be automatically renewed by the commission without formal application upon payment of the renewal fee and license fee if payable to the commission prior to or within thirty days after the expiration of the license. The payment shall be an affirmative representation and certification by the licensee that all answers contained in an application, if submitted, would be the same in all material respects as the answers contained in the last previous application. The commission may at any time require a licensee to submit an application, and the commission shall at any time require a licensee to submit an application if requested in writing to do so by the local governing body.</para><para>If a licensee files an application form upon seeking renewal of his or her license, the application shall be processed as set forth in section 53-131.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 86, p. 421; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-386; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-135; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 249, &#167; 10, p. 870; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 213, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 820, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1089, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB330, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1204, &#167; 7. </para></source><annotation><para>An appeal from the district court's decision reversing the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission's approval of a class D liquor license under section 53-135.02 was not moot despite the expiration of the original license during the pendency of an appeal, because a licensee has a constitutionally protected interest in obtaining the renewal of an existing license, and that interest would be jeopardized if the license were wrongfully taken away. Orchard Hill Neighborhood v. Orchard Hill Mercantile, 274 Neb. 154, 738 N.W.2d 820 (2007).</para><para>An administrative agency is limited in authority to those powers granted to it by statute. Thus, without a showing by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission or the objecting city that a renewal applicant did not meet one of the renewal requirements of this section and section 53-135.02, the commission could not demand that the applicant submit a long-form liquor license application. Grand Island Latin Club v. Nebraska Liq. Cont. Comm., 251 Neb. 61, 554 N.W.2d 778 (1996).</para><para>A liquor license which has been renewed by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission pursuant to this section cannot be revoked by action of a city council. Luet, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 247 Neb. 831, 530 N.W.2d 633 (1995).</para><para>The language of section 53-150 and this section discloses a legislative intent to codify a practice of approving an application for continuation of an existing liquor license in the absence of a change of circumstances indicated on the licensee's renewal application. Pump &amp; Pantry, Inc. v. City of Grand Island, 233 Neb. 191, 444 N.W.2d 312 (1989).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>