<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id6" statutenumber="53-123.15"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.15</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Shipping license;
when required; rights of licensee; application; contents; violation; disciplinary
action.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall order or receive alcoholic liquor
in this state which has been shipped directly to him or her from outside this
state by any person other than a holder of a shipping license issued by the
commission, except that a licensed wholesaler may receive not more than three
gallons of wine in any calendar year from any person who is not a holder of
a shipping license.</para>
<para>(2) The commission may issue a shipping license to a manufacturer. Such
license shall allow the licensee to ship alcoholic liquor only to a licensed
wholesaler, except that a licensed wholesaler may, without a shipping license
and for the purposes of subdivision (2) of section 53-161, receive beer in
this state which has been shipped from outside the state by a manufacturer
in accordance with the Nebraska Liquor Control Act to the wholesaler, then
transported by the wholesaler to another state for retail distribution, and
then returned by the retailer to such wholesaler. A person who receives a
license pursuant to this subsection shall pay the fee required in sections
53-124 and 53-124.01 for a manufacturer's shipping license. Such fee shall
be collected by the commission and be remitted to the State Treasurer for
credit to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(3) The commission may issue a shipping license to any person who deals
with vintage wines, which shipping license shall allow the licensee to distribute
such wines to a licensed wholesaler in the state. For purposes of distributing
vintage wines, a licensed shipper must utilize a designated wholesaler if
the manufacturer has a designated wholesaler. For purposes of this section,
vintage wine shall mean a wine verified to be ten years of age or older and
not available from a primary American source of supply. A person who receives
a license pursuant to this subsection shall pay the fee required in sections
53-124 and 53-124.01 for a vintage wine dealer's shipping license. Such fee
shall be collected by the commission and be remitted to the State Treasurer
for credit to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(4) The commission may issue a shipping license to any person who sells
and ships alcoholic liquor from another state directly to a consumer in this
state. A person who receives a license pursuant to this subsection shall pay
the fee required in sections 53-124 and 53-124.01 for a direct sales shipping
license. Such fee
shall be collected by the commission and remitted to the State Treasurer for
credit to the Winery and Grape Producers Promotional Fund.</para>
<para>(5) The application for a shipping license shall be in such form as
the commission prescribes. The application shall contain all provisions the
commission deems proper and necessary to effectuate the purpose of any section
of the act and the rules and regulations of the commission that apply to manufacturers
and shall include, but not be limited to, provisions that the applicant, in
consideration of the issuance of such shipping license, agrees:</para>
<para>(a) To comply with and be bound by section 53-164.01 in making and filing
reports, paying taxes, penalties, and interest, and keeping records;</para>
<para>(b) To permit and be subject to all of the powers granted by section
53-164.01 to the commission or its duly authorized employees or agents for
inspection and examination of the applicant's premises and records and to
pay the actual expenses, excluding salary, reasonably attributable to such
inspections and examinations made by duly authorized employees of the commission
if within the United States; and</para>
<para>(c) That if the applicant violates any of the provisions of the application
or the license, any section of the act, or any of the rules and regulations
of the commission that apply to manufacturers, the commission may revoke or
suspend such shipping license for such period of time as it may determine.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 416, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 874, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 671, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB441, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB867, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB286, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>