<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-1,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-1,104</statuteno><catchline>Violations by licensee; suspension,
cancellation, or revocation of license; cash penalty in lieu of suspending
sales; election authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Any licensee which sells
or permits the sale of any alcoholic liquor not authorized under the terms
of such license on the licensed premises or in connection with such licensee's
business or otherwise shall be subject to suspension, cancellation, or revocation
of such license by the commission.</para>
<para>(2) When an order suspending a license to sell alcoholic liquor becomes
final, the licensee may elect to pay a cash penalty to the commission in lieu
of suspending sales of alcoholic liquor for the designated period if such
election is not prohibited by order of the commission. Except as otherwise
provided in subsection (3) of this section, for the first such suspension
for any licensee, the penalty shall be fifty dollars per day, and for a second
or any subsequent suspension, the penalty shall be one hundred dollars per
day.</para>
<para>(3)(a) For a second suspension for violation of section 53-180 or 53-180.02
occurring within four years after the date of the first suspension, the commission,
in its discretion, may order that the licensee be required to suspend sales
of alcoholic liquor for a period of time not to exceed forty-eight hours and
that the licensee may not elect to pay a cash penalty. The commission may
use the required suspension of sales of alcoholic liquor penalty either alone
or in conjunction with suspension periods for which the licensee may elect
to pay a cash penalty. For purposes of this subsection, second suspension
for violation of section 53-180 shall include suspension for a violation of
section 53-180.02 following suspension for a violation of section 53-180 and
second suspension for violation of section 53-180.02 shall include suspension
for a violation of section 53-180 following suspension for a violation of
section 53-180.02;</para>
<para>(b) For a third or subsequent suspension for violation of section 53-180
or 53-180.02 occurring within four years after the date of the first suspension,
the commission, in its discretion, may order that the licensee be required
to suspend sales of alcoholic liquor for a period of time not to exceed fifteen
days and that the licensee may not elect to pay a cash penalty. The commission
may use the required suspension of sales of alcoholic liquor penalty either
alone or in conjunction with suspension periods for which the licensee may
elect to pay a cash penalty. For purposes of this subsection, third or subsequent
suspension for violation of section 53-180 shall include suspension for a
violation of section 53-180.02 following suspension for a violation of section
53-180 and third or subsequent suspension for violation of section 53-180.02
shall include suspension for a violation of section 53-180 following suspension
for a violation of section 53-180.02; and</para>
<para>(c) For a first suspension based upon a finding that a licensee or an
employee or agent of the licensee has been convicted of possession of a gambling
device on a licensee's premises in violation of sections 28-1107 to 28-1111,
the commission, in its discretion, may order that the licensee be required
to suspend sales of alcoholic liquor for thirty days and that the licensee
may not elect to pay a cash penalty. For a second or subsequent suspension
for such a violation of sections 28-1107 to 28-1111 occurring within four
years after the date of the first suspension, the commission shall order that
the license be canceled.</para>
<para>(4) For any licensee which has no violation for a period of four years
consecutively, any suspension shall be treated as a new first suspension.</para>
<para>(5) The election provided for in subsection (2) of this section shall
be filed with the commission in writing one week before the suspension is
ordered to commence and shall be accompanied by payment in full of the sum
required by this section. If such election has not been received by the commission
by the close of business one week before the day such suspension is ordered
to commence, it shall be conclusively presumed that the licensee has elected
to close for the period of the suspension and any election received later
shall be absolutely void and the payment made shall be returned to the licensee.
The election shall be made on a form prescribed by the commission. The commission
shall remit all funds collected under this section to the State Treasurer
for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution
of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 105, p. 429; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-3,105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-1,104; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 320; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 848, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 586, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 267, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 973, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 205, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 78.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>