<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="53-123.17"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.17</statuteno><catchline>Entertainment district license; rights of licensee; application; fee; commission; duties; occupation tax; local governing body; powers.</catchline><para>(1) A local governing body may designate an entertainment district in which a commons area may be used by retail, craft brewery, and microdistillery licensees and holders of a manufacturer's license which obtain an entertainment district license. The local governing body may, at any time, revoke such designation if it finds that the commons area threatens the health, safety, or welfare of the public or has become a common nuisance. The local governing body shall file the designation or the revocation of the designation with the commission.</para><para>(2) An entertainment district license allows the sale of alcoholic liquor for consumption on the premises within the confines of a commons area. The consumption of alcoholic liquor in the commons area shall only occur during the hours authorized for sale of alcoholic liquor for consumption on the premises under section 53-179 and while food service is available in the commons area. Only the holder of an entertainment district license or employees of such licensee may sell or dispense alcoholic liquor in the commons area.</para><para>(3) An entertainment district licensee shall serve alcoholic liquor to be consumed in the commons area in containers that prominently displays the licensee's trade name or logo or some other mark that is unique to the licensee under the licensee's retail license, craft brewery license, microdistillery license, or manufacturer's license. An entertainment district licensee may allow alcohol sold by another entertainment district licensee to enter the licensed premises of either licensee. No entertainment district licensee shall allow alcoholic liquor to leave the commons area or the premises licensed under its retail license, craft brewery license, microdistillery license, or manufacturer's license.</para><para>(4) If the licensed premises of the holder of a license to sell alcoholic liquor at retail issued under subsection (6) of section 53-124, a craft brewery license, a microdistillery license, or a manufacturer's license is adjacent to a commons area in an entertainment district designated by a local governing body pursuant to this section, the holder of the license may obtain an annual entertainment district license as prescribed in this section. The entertainment district license shall be issued for the same period and may be renewed in the same manner as the retail license, craft brewery license, microdistillery license, or manufacturer's license.</para><para>(5) In order to obtain an entertainment district license, a person eligible under subsection (4) of this section shall:</para><para>(a) File an application with the commission upon such forms as the commission prescribes; and</para><para>(b) Pay an additional license fee of three hundred dollars for the privilege of serving alcohol in the entertainment district payable to the clerk of the local governing body in the same manner as license fees under subdivision (4) of section 53-134.</para><para>(6) When an application for an entertainment district license is filed, the commission shall notify the clerk of the local governing body. The commission shall include with such notice one copy of the application by mail or electronic delivery. The local governing body and the commission shall process the application in the same manner as provided in section 53-132.</para><para>(7) The local governing body may impose an occupation tax on the business of an entertainment district licensee doing business within the liquor license jurisdiction of the local governing body as provided in subdivision (11)(b) of this section in accordance with section 53-132.</para><para>(8) The local governing body with respect to entertainment district licensees within its liquor license jurisdiction as provided in subdivision (11)(b) of this section may cancel an entertainment district license for cause for the remainder of the period for which such entertainment district license is issued. Any person whose entertainment district license is canceled may appeal to the commission in accordance with section 53-134.</para><para>(9) A local governing body may regulate by ordinance, not inconsistent with the Nebraska Liquor Control Act, any area it designates as an entertainment district.</para><para>(10) Violation of any provision of this section or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section by an entertainment district licensee may be cause to revoke, cancel, or suspend the retail license issued under subsection (6) of section 53-124, craft brewery license, microdistillery license, or manufacturer's license held by such licensee.</para><para>(11) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Commons area means an area:</para><para>(i) Within an entertainment district designated by a local governing body;</para><para>(ii) Shared by authorized licensees with entertainment district licenses;</para><para>(iii) Abutting the licensed premises of such licensees;</para><para>(iv) Having limited pedestrian accessibility by use of a physical barrier, either on a permanent or temporary basis; and</para><para>(v) Closed to vehicular traffic when used as a commons area.</para><para>Commons area may include any area of a public or private right-of-way if the area otherwise meets the requirements of this section; and</para><para>(b) Local governing body means the governing body of the city or village in which the entertainment district licensee is located.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1130, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>