<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-125"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>53-125</statuteno><catchline>Classes of persons to whom no license issued.</catchline><para>No license of any kind shall be issued to (1) a person who is not a resident of Nebraska, except in case of railroad, airline, or boat licenses, (2) a person who is not of good character and reputation in the community in which he or she resides, (3) a person who is not a Nebraska resident and legally able to work in Nebraska, (4) a person who has been convicted of or has pleaded guilty to a felony under the laws of this state, any other state, or the United States, (5) a person who has been convicted of or has pleaded guilty to any Class I misdemeanor pursuant to Chapter 28, article 3, 4, 7, 8, 10, 11, or 12, or any similar offense under a prior criminal statute or in another state, except that any additional requirements imposed by this subdivision on May 18, 1983, shall not prevent any person holding a license on such date from retaining or renewing such license if the conviction or plea occurred prior to May 18, 1983, (6) a person whose license issued under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act has been revoked for cause, (7) a person who at the time of application for renewal of any license issued under the act would not be eligible for such license upon initial application, (8) a partnership, unless one of the partners is a resident of Nebraska and unless all the members of such partnership are otherwise qualified to obtain a license, (9) a limited liability company, if any officer or director of the limited liability company or any member having an ownership interest in the aggregate of more than twenty-five percent of such company would be ineligible to receive a license under this section for any reason other than the reasons stated in subdivisions (1) and (3) of this section, or if a manager of a limited liability company licensee would be ineligible to receive a license under this section for any reason, (10) a corporation, if any officer or director of the corporation or any stockholder owning in the aggregate more than twenty-five percent of the stock of such corporation would be ineligible to receive a license under this section for any reason other than the reasons stated in subdivisions (1) and (3) of this section, or if a manager of a corporate licensee would be ineligible to receive a license under this section for any reason. This subdivision shall not apply to railroad licenses, (11) a person whose place of business is conducted by a manager or agent unless such manager or agent possesses the same qualifications required of the licensee, (12) a person who does not own the premises for which a license is sought or does not have a lease or combination of leases on such premises for the full period for which the license is to be issued, (13) except as provided in this subdivision, an applicant whose spouse is ineligible under this section to receive and hold a liquor license. Such applicant shall become eligible for a liquor license only if the commission finds from the evidence that the public interest will not be infringed upon if such license is granted. It shall be prima facie evidence that when a spouse is ineligible to receive a liquor license the applicant is also ineligible to receive a liquor license. Such prima facie evidence shall be overcome if it is shown to the satisfaction of the commission (a) that the licensed business will be the sole property of the applicant and (b) that such licensed premises will be properly operated, (14) a person seeking a license for premises which do not meet standards for fire safety as established by the State Fire Marshal, (15) a law enforcement officer, except that this subdivision shall not prohibit a law enforcement officer from holding membership in any nonprofit organization holding a liquor license or from participating in any manner in the management or administration of a nonprofit organization, or (16) a person less than twenty-one years of age.</para><para>When a trustee is the licensee, the beneficiary or beneficiaries of the trust shall comply with the requirements of this section, but nothing in this section shall prohibit any such beneficiary from being a minor or a person who is mentally incompetent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 28, p. 395; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-328; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-125; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 230, &#167; 1, p. 788; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 249, &#167; 3, p. 864; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 318, &#167; 7, p. 897; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 332, &#167; 7, p. 887; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 752, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 111, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 414, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 204, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 224, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 848, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 213, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 871, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 319; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1292, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB788, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1105, &#167; 19. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>One is unable to renew liquor license for premises when not in possession of either lease or deed to such premises. III Lounge, Inc. v. Gaines, 227 Neb. 585, 419 N.W.2d 143 (1988).</para><para>The phrase not of good character concerning eligibility for a license imports lack of good faith or honesty of purpose. C &amp; L Co. v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 190 Neb. 91, 206 N.W.2d 49 (1973).</para><para>In exercising discretion to refuse license, Nebraska Liquor Control Commission may consider factors in addition to those set out in this section. T &amp; N P Co., Inc. v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 189 Neb. 708, 204 N.W.2d 809 (1973).</para><para>A liquor license may be issued to a partnership. Stevens v. Fall, 133 Neb. 610, 276 N.W. 401 (1937).</para><para>A party who has tendered a guilty plea under a deferred judgment statute of another state has not necessarily been convicted of or pleaded guilty to an offense within the meaning of this statute. McHenry v. Nebraska Liquor Control Comm., 5 Neb. App. 95, 555 N.W.2d 350 (1996).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>