<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-169.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-169.01</statuteno><catchline>Manufacturer; interest in licensed
wholesaler; prohibitions; exception.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) Except as otherwise provided in
subsection (2) of this section, no manufacturer of alcoholic liquor
holding a manufacturer's license under section 53-123.01 and no manufacturer
of alcoholic liquor outside this state manufacturing alcoholic liquor for distribution
and sale within this state shall, directly or indirectly, as owner or part
owner, or through a subsidiary or affiliate, or by any officer, director,
or employee thereof, or by stock ownership, interlocking directors, trusteeship,
loan, mortgage, or lien on any personal or real property, or as guarantor,
endorser, or surety, be interested in the ownership, conduct, operation, or
management of any wholesaler holding an alcoholic liquor wholesale license under section
53-123.02 or a beer wholesale
license under section 53-123.03.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in subsection
(2) of this section, no manufacturer of alcoholic liquor holding
a manufacturer's license under section 53-123.01 and no manufacturer of alcoholic
liquor outside this state manufacturing alcoholic liquor for distribution and sale within
this state shall be interested directly or indirectly, as lessor or lessee,
as owner or part owner, or through a subsidiary or affiliate, or by any officer,
director, or employee thereof, or by stock ownership, interlocking directors,
or trusteeship in the premises upon which the place of business of a wholesaler holding an alcoholic
liquor wholesale license under section 53-123.02 or
a beer wholesale license under section 53-123.03 is located, established,
conducted, or operated in whole or in part unless such interest was acquired
or became effective prior to April 17, 1947.</para>
<para>(2) A manufacturer of
beer may acquire an ownership interest in a beer wholesaler, for a period
not to exceed two years, upon the death or bankruptcy of the beer wholesaler
with which the manufacturer is doing business or upon the beer wholesaler
with which the manufacturer is doing business becoming ineligible to hold
a license under section 53-125.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 116, &#167; 30, p. 396; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 53-330; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 53-169; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 187, &#167; 2, p. 619; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 182, &#167; 4, p. 575; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 250, &#167; 2, p. 876; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 441, &#167; 3, p. 1477; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB578, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB279, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>The interest forbidden by this section is a financial or business interest. Nebraska Liq. Distrib. v. Nebraska Liq. Cont. Comm., 269 Neb. 401, 693 N.W.2d 539 (2005).</para><para>While the forbidden interest in this section is worded as that of the manufacturer in the wholesaler and not the interest of the wholesaler in the manufacturer, the obvious intent of the Legislature is to forbid both types of interests. Nebraska Liq. Distrib. v. Nebraska Liq. Cont. Comm., 269 Neb. 401, 693 N.W.2d 539 (2005).</para><para>Amendments made to this section by Laws 2007, LB 578, contained a Grandfather Clause that violated the Equal Protection Clause and the Privileges and Immunities Clause of the United States Constitution and the Grandfather Clause was not severable from the other amendments. The section as amended is unconstitutional. Southern Wine &amp; Spirits of America Inc. v. Heineman, 534 F.Supp.2d 1001 (D.Neb.2008).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>