<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>53-304</statuteno><catchline>Winery; payments required; Winery
and Grape Producers Promotional Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>Each Nebraska winery shall pay to the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission
twenty dollars for every one hundred sixty gallons of juice produced or received
by its facility. Gifts, grants, or bequests may be received for the support
of the Nebraska Grape and Winery Board. Funds paid pursuant to the charge
imposed by this section and funds received pursuant to subsection (4) or (5) of section 53-123.15
and from gifts, grants, or bequests shall be remitted to the State Treasurer
for credit to the Winery and Grape Producers Promotional Fund which is hereby
created. For administrative purposes, the fund shall be located in the Department
of Agriculture. All revenue credited to the fund pursuant to the charge imposed
by this section and excise taxes collected pursuant to section 2-5603 and
any funds received as gifts, grants, or bequests and credited to the fund
shall be used by the department, at the direction of and in cooperation with
the board, to develop and maintain programs for the research and advancement
of the growing, selling, marketing, and promotion of grapes, fruits, berries,
honey, and other agricultural products and their byproducts grown and produced
in Nebraska for use in the wine industry. Such expenditures may include, but
are not limited to, all necessary funding for the employment of experts in
the fields of viticulture and enology, as deemed necessary by the board, and
programs aimed at improving the promotion of all varieties of wines, grapes,
fruits, berries, honey, and other agricultural products and their byproducts
grown and produced in Nebraska for use in the wine industry.</para>
<para>Funds credited to the fund shall be used for no other purposes than
those stated in this section and any transfers authorized pursuant to section
2-5604. Any funds not expended during a fiscal year may be maintained in the
fund for distribution or expenditure during subsequent fiscal years. Any money
in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment
officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State
Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 477, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 536, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB441, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB230, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>