<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="53-124.11"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>53-124.11</statuteno><catchline>Special designated license; issuance;
procedure; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue a special designated
license for sale or consumption of alcoholic liquor at a designated location
to a retail licensee, a craft brewery licensee, a microdistillery licensee,
a farm winery licensee, a municipal corporation, a fine arts museum incorporated
as a nonprofit corporation, a religious nonprofit corporation which has been
exempted from the payment of federal income taxes, a political organization
which has been exempted from the payment of federal income taxes, or any other
nonprofit corporation the purpose of which is fraternal, charitable, or public
service and which has been exempted from the payment of federal income taxes,
under conditions specified in this section. The applicant shall demonstrate
meeting the requirements of this subsection.</para>
<para>(2) No retail licensee, craft brewery licensee, microdistillery licensee,
farm winery licensee, organization, or corporation enumerated in subsection
(1) of this section may be issued a special designated license under this
section for more than six calendar days in any one calendar year. Only one
special designated license shall be required for any application for two or
more consecutive days. This subsection shall not apply to any holder of a
catering license.</para>
<para>(3) Except for any special designated license issued to a holder of
a catering license, there shall be a fee of forty dollars for each day identified
in the special designated license. Such fee shall be submitted with the application
for the special designated license, collected by the commission, and remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund. The applicant shall
be exempt from the provisions of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act requiring an application or renewal fee
and the provisions of the act requiring the expiration of forty-five days
from the time the application is received by the commission prior to the issuance
of a license, if granted by the commission. The retail licensees, craft brewery
licensees, microdistillery licensees, farm winery licensees, municipal corporations,
organizations, and nonprofit corporations enumerated in subsection (1) of
this section seeking a special designated license shall file an application
on such forms as the commission may prescribe. Such forms shall contain, along
with other information as required by the commission, (a) the name of the
applicant, (b) the premises for which a special designated license is requested,
identified by street and number if practicable and, if not, by some other
appropriate description which definitely locates the premises, (c) the name
of the owner or lessee of the premises for which the special designated license
is requested, (d) sufficient evidence that the holder of the special designated
license, if issued, will carry on the activities and business authorized by
the license for himself, herself, or itself and not as the agent of any other
person, group, organization, or corporation, for profit or not for profit,
(e) a statement of the type of activity to be carried on during the time period
for which a special designated license is requested, and (f) sufficient evidence
that the activity will be supervised by persons or managers who are agents
of and directly responsible to the holder of the special designated license.</para>
<para>(4) No special designated license provided for by this section shall
be issued by the commission without the approval of the local governing body.
The local governing body may establish criteria for approving or denying a
special designated license. The local governing body may designate an agent
to determine whether a special designated license is to be approved or denied.
Such agent shall follow criteria established by the local governing body in
making his or her determination. The determination of the agent shall be considered
the determination of the local governing body unless otherwise provided by
the local governing body. For purposes of this section, the local governing
body shall be the city or village within which the premises for which the
special designated license is requested are located or, if such premises are
not within the corporate limits of a city or village, then the local governing
body shall be the county within which the premises for which the special designated
license is requested are located.</para>
<para>(5) If the applicant meets the requirements of this section, a special
designated license shall be granted and issued by the commission for use by
the holder of the special designated license. All statutory provisions and
rules and regulations of the commission that apply to a retail licensee shall
apply to the holder of a special designated license with the exception of
such statutory provisions and rules and regulations of the commission so designated
by the commission and stated upon the issued special designated license, except
that the commission may not designate exemption of sections 53-180 to 53-180.07.
The decision of the commission shall be final. If the applicant does not qualify
for a special designated license, the application shall be denied by the commission.</para>
<para>(6) A special designated license issued by the commission shall be mailed
or delivered to the city, village, or county clerk who shall deliver such
license to the licensee upon receipt of any fee or tax imposed by such city,
village, or county.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 213, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 490, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1292, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 750, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 973, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 562, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167;  58.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>