<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" id="id6" statutenumber="53-123.15"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.15</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Shipping license;
when required; rights of licensee; application; contents; violation; disciplinary
action; holder of license;
duties; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) No person
shall order or receive alcoholic liquor in this state which has been shipped
directly to him or her from outside this state by any person other than a
holder of a shipping license issued by the commission, except that a licensed
wholesaler may receive not more than three gallons of wine in any calendar
year from any person who is not a holder of a shipping license.</para>
<para>(2) The commission may issue a shipping license to a manufacturer.
Such license shall allow the licensee to ship alcoholic liquor only to a licensed
wholesaler, except that a licensed wholesaler may, without a shipping license
and for the purposes of subdivision (2) of section 53-161, receive beer in
this state which has been shipped from outside the state by a manufacturer
in accordance with the Nebraska Liquor Control Act to the wholesaler, then
transported by the wholesaler to another state for retail distribution, and
then returned by the retailer to such wholesaler. A person who receives a
license pursuant to this subsection shall pay the fee required in sections
53-124 and 53-124.01 for a manufacturer's shipping license. Such fee shall
be collected by the commission and be remitted to the State Treasurer for
credit to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(3) The commission may issue a shipping license to any person
who deals with vintage wines, which shipping license shall allow the licensee
to distribute such wines to a licensed wholesaler in the state. For purposes
of distributing vintage wines, a licensed shipper must utilize a designated
wholesaler if the manufacturer has a designated wholesaler. For purposes of
this section, vintage wine shall mean a wine verified to be ten years of age
or older and not available from a primary American source of supply. A person
who receives a license pursuant to this subsection shall pay the fee required
in sections 53-124 and 53-124.01 for a vintage wine dealer's shipping license.
Such fee shall be collected by the commission and be remitted to the State
Treasurer for credit to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(4) The commission may issue a shipping license to any manufacturer who sells and ships alcoholic liquor
from another state directly to a consumer in this state if the manufacturer satisfies the requirements of subsections
(7) through (9) of this section. A manufacturer who
receives a license pursuant to this subsection shall pay the fee required
in sections 53-124 and 53-124.01 for a manufacture direct
sales shipping license. Such fee shall be collected by the commission and
remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Winery and Grape Producers
Promotional Fund.</para>
<para>(5) The commission
may issue a shipping license to any retailer who is licensed within or outside
Nebraska, who is authorized to sell alcoholic liquor at retail in the state
of domicile of the retailer, and who is not a manufacturer if such retailer
satisfies the requirements of subsections (7) through (9) of this section
to ship alcoholic liquor from another state directly to a consumer in this
state. A retailer who receives a license pursuant to this subsection shall
pay the fee required in sections 53-124 and 53-124.01 for a retail direct
sales shipping license. Such fee shall be collected by the commission and
remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Winery and Grape Producers
Promotional Fund.</para><para>(6) The
application for a shipping license under
subsection (2) or (3) of this section shall be in such form as
the commission prescribes. The application shall contain all provisions the
commission deems proper and necessary to effectuate the purpose of any section
of the act and the rules and regulations of the commission that apply to manufacturers
and shall include, but not be limited to, provisions that the applicant, in
consideration of the issuance of such shipping license, agrees:</para>
<para>(a) To comply with and be bound by sections
53-162 and 53-164.01 in making and filing reports, paying taxes,
penalties, and interest, and keeping records;</para>
<para>(b) To permit and be subject to all of the powers granted
by section 53-164.01 to the commission or its duly authorized employees or
agents for inspection and examination of the applicant's premises and records
and to pay the actual expenses, excluding salary, reasonably attributable
to such inspections and examinations made by duly authorized employees of
the commission if within the United States; and</para>
<para>(c) That if the applicant violates any of the provisions of
the application or the license, any section of the act, or any of the rules
and regulations of the commission that apply to manufacturers, the commission
may suspend, cancel, or revoke  such
shipping license for such period of time as it may determine.</para>
<para>(7) The application
for a shipping license under subsection (4) or (5) of this section shall be
in such form as the commission prescribes. The application shall require an
applicant which is a manufacturer, a craft brewery, a craft distillery, or
a farm winery to identify the brands of alcoholic liquor that the applicant
is requesting the authority to ship either into or within Nebraska. For all
applicants, unless otherwise provided in this section, the application shall
contain all provisions the commission deems proper and necessary to effectuate
the purpose of any section of the act and the rules and regulations of the
commission that apply to manufacturers or retailers and shall include, but
not be limited to, provisions that the applicant, in consideration of the
issuance of such shipping license, agrees:</para><para>(a) To comply with and be bound by sections
53-162 and 53-164.01 in making and filing reports, paying taxes, penalties,
and interest, and keeping records;</para><para>(b) To permit and be subject to all of the
powers granted by section 53-164.01 to the commission or its duly authorized
employees or agents for inspection and examination of the applicant's premises
and records and to pay the actual expenses, excluding salary, reasonably attributable
to such inspections and examinations made by duly authorized employees of
the commission if within the United States;</para><para>(c) That if the applicant violates any of
the provisions of the application or the license, any section of the act,
or any of the rules and regulations of the commission that apply to manufacturers
or retailers, the commission may suspend, cancel, or revoke such shipping
license for such period of time as it may determine;</para><para>(d) That the applicant
agrees to notify the commission of any violations in the state in which he
or she is domiciled and any violations of the direct shipping laws of any
other states. Failure to notify the commission within thirty days after such
a violation may result in a hearing before the commission pursuant to which
the license may be suspended, canceled, or revoked; and</para>
<para>(e) That the
applicant, if a manufacturer, craft brewery, craft distillery, or farm winery,
agrees to notify any wholesaler licensed in Nebraska that has been authorized
to distribute such brands that the application has been filed for a shipping
license. The notice shall be in writing and in a form prescribed by the commission.
The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as it reasonably
deems necessary to implement this subdivision, including rules and regulations
that permit the holder of a shipping license under this subdivision to amend
the shipping license by, among other things, adding or deleting any brands
of alcoholic liquor identified in the shipping license.</para>
<para>(8) Any manufacturer
or retailer who is granted a shipping license under subsection (4) or (5)
of this section shall:</para><para>(a) Only ship the brands of alcoholic liquor identified on the application;</para>
<para>(b) Only ship
alcoholic liquor that is owned by the holder of the shipping license;</para>
<para>(c) Only ship
alcoholic liquor that is properly registered with the Alcohol and Tobacco
Tax and Trade Bureau of the United States Department of the Treasury;</para>
<para>(d) Not ship
any alcoholic liquor products that the manufacturers or wholesalers licensed
in Nebraska have voluntarily agreed not to bring into Nebraska at the request
of the commission;</para><para>(e) Not ship more than nine liters of alcoholic liquor per month
to any person in Nebraska to whom alcoholic beverages may be lawfully sold.
All such sales and shipments shall be for personal consumption only and not
for resale; and</para><para>(f) Cause the direct shipment of alcoholic liquor to be by approved
common carrier only. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
pursuant to which common carriers may apply for approval to provide common
carriage of alcoholic liquor shipped by a holder of a shipping license issued
pursuant to subsection (4) or (5) of this section. The rules and regulations
shall include provisions that require (i) the recipient to demonstrate, upon
delivery, that he or she is at least twenty-one years of age, (ii) the recipient
to sign an electronic or paper form or other acknowledgement of receipt as
approved by the commission, and (iii) the commission-approved common carrier
to submit to the commission such information as the commission may prescribe.
The commission-approved common carrier shall refuse delivery when the proposed
recipient appears to be under the age of twenty-one years and refuses to present
valid identification. All holders of shipping licenses shipping alcoholic
liquor pursuant to this subdivision shall affix a conspicuous notice in sixteen-point
type or larger to the outside of each package of alcoholic liquor shipped
within or into the State of Nebraska, in a conspicuous location, stating:
CONTAINS ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES; SIGNATURE OF PERSON AT LEAST 21 YEARS OF AGE
REQUIRED FOR DELIVERY. Any delivery of alcoholic beverages to a minor by a
common carrier shall constitute a violation by the common carrier. The common
carrier and the holder of the shipping license shall be liable only for their
independent acts.</para><para>(9) For purposes of sections 53-160, 77-2703, and 77-27,142, each
shipment of alcoholic liquor by the holder of a shipping license under subsection
(3), (4), or (5) of this section shall constitute a sale in Nebraska by establishing
a nexus in the state. The holder of the shipping license shall collect all
the taxes due to the State of Nebraska and any political subdivision and remit
any excise taxes monthly to the commission and any sales taxes to the Department
of Revenue.</para><para>(10)
By July 1, 2014, the commission shall report to the General Affairs Committee
of the Legislature the number of shipping licenses issued for license years
2013-14 and 2014-15. The report shall be made electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 344, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 416, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 874, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 671, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB441, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB861, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB867, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB286, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB230, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>