<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liquors" statutenumber="53-123.16"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>53-123.16</statuteno><catchline>Microdistillery license; rights of licensee.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who operates a microdistillery shall obtain a license pursuant to the Nebraska Liquor Control Act. A license to operate a microdistillery shall permit the licensee to produce a maximum of one hundred thousand gallons of liquor per year in the aggregate from all physical locations comprising the licensed premises. For purposes of this section, licensed premises may include up to five separate physical locations. A microdistillery may also sell to licensed wholesalers for sale and distribution to licensed retailers. A microdistillery license issued pursuant to this section shall be the only license required by the Nebraska Liquor Control Act for the manufacture and retail sale of microdistilled product for consumption on or off the licensed premises, except that the sale of any beer, wine, or alcoholic liquor, other than microdistilled product manufactured by the microdistillery licensee, by the drink for consumption on the microdistillery premises shall require the appropriate retail license. Any license held by the operator of a microdistillery shall be subject to the act. A holder of a microdistillery license may obtain an annual catering license pursuant to section 53-124.12, a special designated license pursuant to section 53-124.11, an entertainment district license pursuant to section 53-123.17, or a promotional farmers market special designated license pursuant to section 53-124.16. The commission may, upon the conditions it determines, grant to any microdistillery licensed under this section a special license authorizing the microdistillery to purchase and to import, from such persons as are entitled to sell the same, wines or spirits to be used solely as ingredients and for the sole purpose of blending with and flavoring microdistillery products as a part of the microdistillation process.</para><para>(2) A holder of a microdistillery license may directly sell for resale up to five hundred gallons per calendar year of microdistilled products produced at its licensed premises directly to retail licensees located in the State of Nebraska which hold the appropriate retail license if the holder of the microdistillery license:</para><para>(a) Self-distributes its microdistilled products utilizing only persons employed by the microdistillery licensee; and</para><para>(b) Complies with all relevant statutes, rules, and regulations that apply to Nebraska wholesalers regarding distribution of microdistilled products.</para><para>(3) A holder of a microdistillery license may store and warehouse tax-paid products produced on such licensee's licensed premises in a designated, secure, offsite storage facility if the holder of the microdistillery license receives authorization from the commission and notifies the commission of the location of the storage facility and maintains, at the microdistillery and at the storage facility, a separate perpetual inventory of the product stored at the storage facility. Consumption of alcoholic liquor at the storage facility is strictly prohibited.</para><para>(4) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations relating to the distribution rights of microdistillery licensees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB549, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1130, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB274, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1236, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB376, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>