<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,115</statuteno><catchline>Livestock transportation permit; requirements.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any person, other than the owner or the owner's employee, using a motor vehicle or trailer to transport livestock or carcasses over any land within the brand inspection area not owned or rented by such person or who is so transporting such livestock upon a highway, public street, or thoroughfare within the brand inspection area shall have in his or her possession a livestock transportation permit, certificate of inspection, or shipping certificate from a registered feedlot or registered dairy, authorizing such movement as to each head of livestock transported by such vehicle.</para><para>(b) Any such person outside the brand inspection area transporting livestock shall have in his or her possession a livestock transportation permit or other proof of ownership acceptable to the peace officer, the number of livestock, and the destination of the livestock, which permit shall be delivered to the public market or anyone to whom the livestock are being delivered.</para><para>(2) A livestock transportation permit shall be in writing and shall state the name of the owner of the livestock, the owner's post office address, the place from which the livestock are being moved, including the name of the ranch, if any, the destination, the name and address of the carrier, the license number and make of motor vehicle to which consigned, together with the number of livestock and a description thereof including kind, sex, breed, color, and marks, if any, and in the case of livestock shipments originating within the brand inspection area, the brands, if there are any. The permit shall be signed by the owner of the livestock or the owner's authorized agent. Livestock transportation permits shall be made in quadruplicate: One to be delivered to the motor carrier or motor carrier's agent, one to be retained by the owner of the livestock to be shipped, one to be delivered to the agent of the yard company receiving such livestock, and one to be delivered to the consignee at destination upon delivery of the consignment. Such permits shall be on forms approved by the Nebraska Brand Committee.</para><para>(3) Any peace officer, based upon probable cause to question the ownership of the livestock being transported, may stop a motor vehicle or motor vehicle and trailer and request exhibition of any permit or certificate required by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 213, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Duty to care for livestock,</emphasis> violation, penalty, see section 54-7,104.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 