<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id42" statutenumber="54-1,110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,110</statuteno><catchline id="id45">Brand inspection area; brand inspection requirements; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, no person shall move, in any manner, cattle from a point within the brand inspection area to a point outside the brand inspection area unless such cattle first have a brand inspection by the Nebraska Brand Committee and a certificate of inspection is issued. A copy of such certificate shall accompany the cattle and shall be retained by all persons moving such cattle as a permanent record.</para><para>(2) Cattle in a registered feedlot registered under sections 54-1,120 to 54-1,122 are not subject to the brand inspection of subsection (1) of this section. Possession by the shipper or trucker of a shipping certificate from the registered feedlot constitutes compliance if the cattle being shipped are as represented on such shipping certificate.</para><para>(3) If the line designating the brand inspection area divides a farm or ranch or lies between noncontiguous parcels of land which are owned or operated by the same cattle owner or owners, a permit may be issued, at the discretion of the Nebraska Brand Committee, to the owner or owners of cattle on such farm, ranch, or parcels of land to move the cattle in and out of the brand inspection area without inspection. If the line designating the brand inspection area lies between a farm or ranch and nearby veterinary medical facilities, a permit may be issued, at the discretion of the brand committee, to the owner or owners of cattle on such farm or ranch to move the cattle in and out of the brand inspection area without inspection to obtain care from the veterinary medical facilities. The brand committee shall issue initial permits only after receiving an application which includes an application fee established by the brand committee which shall not be more than fifteen dollars. The brand committee shall mail all current permitholders an annual renewal notice, for January 1 renewal, which requires a renewal fee established by the brand committee which shall not be more than fifty dollars. If the permit conditions still exist, the cattle owner or owners may renew the permit.</para><para>(4) No person shall sell any cattle knowing that the cattle are to be moved, in any manner, in violation of this section. Proof of shipment or removal of the cattle from the brand inspection area by the purchaser or his or her agent is prima facie proof of knowledge that sale was had for removal from the brand inspection area.</para><para>(5) A violation of this section is an infraction. A peace officer shall have the authority to write a citation, which shall be waivable, to offenders in violation of this section. A fine under this section shall not exceed two hundred dollars per head for each offense. Violations shall be charged in the county of origin of the cattle or any other county through which the cattle were moved from the brand inspection area.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 213, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 589, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB768, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB600, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB572, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Brand Inspection Act is not special legislation and is constitutional. Satterfield v. State, 172 Neb. 275, 109 N.W.2d 415 (1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>