<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" id="id12" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="54-789"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>54-789</statuteno><catchline>Individual identification of cattle;
Department of Agriculture; powers; State Veterinarian; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except
as otherwise provided in this section, individual identification of cattle
imported into Nebraska shall not be required if (a) the cattle are identified
by a registered brand and accompanied by an official brand inspection certificate
issued by the recognized brand inspection authority of the state of origin
and (b) such cattle are imported directly from a mandatory brand inspection
area of any state.</para>
<para>(2) The Department
of Agriculture may require cattle imported into Nebraska to be identified
by individual identification to enter the state if the Director of Agriculture
determines that:</para><para>(a) The state of origin recognized brand registration or brand inspection
procedures and documentation are insufficient to enable the tracing of individual
animals to the animal's herd of origin;</para><para>(b) Identification by brand alone is in
conflict with a standard of federal law or regulation regarding identification
of cattle moved into Nebraska; or</para><para>(c) The cattle originate from a location
that is not a tuberculosis accredited-free state or zone pursuant to 9 C.F.R.
77.7 or is not designated a brucellosis Class Free or Class A state or area
pursuant to 9 C.F.R. 78.41, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2013.</para>
<para>(3) At no time
shall a registered brand inspection certificate be used in lieu of a certificate
of veterinary inspection.</para><para>(4) This section does not limit the authority of the State Veterinarian
to issue import orders imposing additional requirements for animals imported
into Nebraska from any state, country, zone, or other area, including requirements
relating to identification.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Individual
identification means a device or method approved by the Department of Agriculture
of uniquely identifying a specific animal to its herd of origin and is not
synonymous with official identification; and</para><para>(b) Official identification
means identifying an animal or group of animals using devices or methods approved
by the Veterinary Services Office of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection
Service of the United States Department of Agriculture, including, but not
limited to, official tags, tattoos, and registered brands when accompanied
by a certificate of inspection from a recognized brand inspection authority.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB647, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>