<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id141">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id143" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-7,107">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>54-7,107</statuteno><catchline id="id146">Records; contents;
access by department.</catchline><para>(1) An exotic animal auction
or exchange venue organizer shall
maintain records for each exotic animal auction or exchange
venue such organizer arranges, organizes, leases areas for, consigns, or otherwise coordinates
at least five years after the date of the exotic animal auction or exchange venue. The records shall include:</para>
<para>(a) The name, address, and telephone number of the exotic
animal auction or exchange venue organizer;</para>
<para>(b) The name and address of all persons who purchased, sold,
traded, bartered, gave away, or otherwise transferred an exotic animal at
the exotic animal auction or exchange venue;</para>
<para>(c) The number of and species or type of each exotic animal
purchased, sold, traded, bartered, given away, or otherwise transferred at
the exotic animal auction or exchange venue;</para>
<para>(d) The date of purchase, sale, trade, barter, or other transfer
of an exotic animal at the exotic animal auction or exchange
venue; and</para>
<para>(e) When required by the Animal Importation
Act or the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue Act, a copy
of the completed certificate of veterinary inspection for each exotic animal purchased,
sold, traded, bartered, given away, or otherwise transferred at the exotic
animal auction or exchange venue.</para>
<para>(2) An exotic animal auction or exchange
venue organizer shall, during all reasonable times, permit authorized
employees and agents of the department to have access to and to copy any or
all records relating to his or her exotic animal auction or exchange
venue business.</para>
<para>(3) When necessary for the enforcement of the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue Act or
any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to such act, the authorized employees and agents of
the department may access the records required by this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 16.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Animal Importation Act,</emphasis> see section 54-784.01.</para><para><emphasis>Definitions,</emphasis> see section 54-701.03.</para><para><emphasis>Department of Agriculture,</emphasis> State Veterinarian, powers, see sections 54-703 to 54-705.</para><para><emphasis>Violations,</emphasis> penalties, see section 54-752.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>