<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id34"><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,132</statuteno><catchline>Registered dairy heifer development facility; application; fee; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Any person, who operates a dairy heifer development facility that specializes in the raising and managing of dairy heifers from one day of age until such heifers are ready for entry into a qualified dairy, may apply to the brand committee for registration as a registered dairy heifer development facility. The application form shall be prescribed by the brand committee and shall be made available by the executive director of the brand committee for this purpose upon written request.</para><para>(2) After the brand committee has received a properly completed application, an agent of the brand committee shall within thirty days make an investigation to determine if the facility is suitable for registration as a registered dairy heifer development facility and the operator specializes in the raising and managing of dairy heifers from one day of age until such heifers are ready for entry into a qualified dairy.</para><para>(3) If the application is satisfactory, and upon payment of the registration fee by the applicant, the brand committee shall issue a registration number and registration certificate that are valid for one year unless rescinded for cause by the brand committee. If the registration is rescinded for cause, any registration fee shall be forfeited by the applicant.</para><para>(4) The registration fee for a registered dairy heifer development facility shall be an amount equal to twenty-five percent multiplied by the maximum capacity of the facility, as such capacity is authorized by the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment under the Livestock Waste Management Act. The registration fee shall be paid on an annual basis.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1187, &#167; 18. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Livestock Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2416.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>