<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id79"  statutenumber="54-628.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-628.01</statuteno><catchline>Director; stop-movement order; issuance; contents; hearing; department; powers; costs; reinspection; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The director may issue a stop-movement order if he or she has reasonable cause to believe that there exists (a) noncompliance with the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act, including, but not limited to, unreasonable sanitation or housing conditions, failure to comply with standards for handling, care, treatment, or transportation for dogs or cats, operating without a license, or interfering with the department in the performance of its duties, or (b) any condition that, without medical attention, provision of shelter, facility maintenance or improvement, relocation of animals, or other management intervention, poses a significant threat to the health or safety of the dogs or cats owned or harbored by a violator.</para><para>(2) Such stop-movement order may require the violator to maintain the dogs or cats subject to the order at the existing location or other department-approved premises until such time as the director has issued a written release from the stop-movement order. The stop-movement order shall clearly advise the violator that he or she may request in writing a hearing before the director pursuant to section 54-632. The order issued pursuant to this section shall be final unless modified or rescinded by the director pursuant to section 54-632 at a hearing requested under this subsection.</para><para>(3) Pursuant to the stop-movement order, the department shall have the authority to enter the premises to inspect and determine if the dogs or cats subject to the order or the facilities used to house or transport such dogs or cats are kept and maintained in compliance with the requirements of the act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act or if any management intervention imposed by the stop-movement order is being implemented to mitigate conditions posing a significant threat to the health or safety of dogs or cats harbored or owned by a violator. The department shall not be liable for any costs incurred by the violator or any personnel of the violator due to such departmental action or in enforcing the stop-movement order. The department shall be reimbursed by the violator for the actual costs incurred by the department in issuing and enforcing any stop-movement order.</para><para>(4) A stop-movement order shall include:</para><para>(a) A description of the nature of the violations of the act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act;</para><para>(b) If applicable, a description of conditions that pose a significant threat to the health or safety of the dogs or cats owned or harbored by the violator;</para><para>(c) The action necessary to bring the violator into compliance with the act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act or, if applicable, to mitigate conditions posing a significant threat to the health and safety of the dogs or cats harbored or owned by the violator;</para><para>(d) Notice that if violations of the act or any rule or regulation or any conditions that pose a significant threat to the health or safety of the dogs or cats owned or harbored by the violator persist, the department may refer the matter to appropriate law enforcement for investigation and potential prosecution pursuant to Chapter 28, article 10; and</para><para>(e) The name, address, and telephone number of the violator who owns or harbors the dogs or cats subject to the order.</para><para>(5) Before receipt of a written release, the person to whom the stop-movement order was issued shall:</para><para>(a) Provide the department with an inventory of all dogs or cats on the premises at the time of the issuance of the order;</para><para>(b) Provide the department with the identification tag number, the tattoo number, the microchip number, or any other approved method of identification for each individual dog or cat;</para><para>(c) Notify the department within forty-eight hours of the death or euthanasia of any dog or cat subject to the order. Such notification shall include the dog's or cat's individual identification tag number, tattoo number, microchip number, or other approved identification;</para><para>(d) Notify the department within forty-eight hours of any dog or cat giving birth after the issuance of the order, including the size of the litter; and</para><para>(e) Maintain on the premises any dog or cat subject to the order, except that a dog or cat under one year of age under contract to an individual prior to the issuance of the order may be delivered to the individual pursuant to the contractual obligation. The violator shall provide to the department information identifying the dog or cat and the name, address, and telephone number of the individual purchasing the dog or cat. The department may contact the purchaser to ascertain the date of the purchase agreement to ensure that the dog or cat was sold prior to the stop-movement order and to determine that he or she did purchase such dog or cat. No additional dogs or cats shall be transferred onto the premises without written approval of the department.</para><para>(6) The department shall reinspect the premises to determine compliance within ten business days after the initial inspection that resulted in the stop-movement order. At the time of reinspection pursuant to this subsection, if conditions that pose a significant threat to the health or safety of the dogs or cats harbored or owned by the violator or noncompliant conditions continue to exist, further reinspections shall be at the discretion of the department. The violator may request an immediate hearing with the director pursuant to any findings under this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB241, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB360, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>