<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id48">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id50" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-627"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>54-627</statuteno><catchline id="id53">License requirements;
fees; renewal; premises available for inspection.</catchline><para>(1)
A person shall not operate as a commercial dog
or cat breeder, a dealer, a boarding kennel, an animal control
facility, an animal shelter, an animal rescue, or a pet shop unless the person obtains the
appropriate license. A pet shop shall only
be subject to the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act and the rules
and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto in any area or areas
of the establishment used for the keeping and selling of pet animals. If a
facility listed in this subsection is not located at the owner's residence,
the name and address of the owner shall be posted on the premises.</para>
<para>(2) An applicant for a license shall submit an application
for the appropriate license to the department, on a form prescribed by the
department, together with the annual license fee. Such fee is nonreturnable.
Upon receipt of the application and annual license fee and upon completion
of a qualifying inspection if required pursuant to section 54-630 for an initial
license applicant or if a qualifying inspection is deemed appropriate by the
department before a license is issued for any other applicant, the appropriate
license may be issued by the department. Such license shall not be transferable
to another person or location.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the
annual license fee shall be determined according to the following fee schedule
based upon the daily average number of dogs or cats housed by the licensee
over the previous annual licensure period:</para>
<para>(i) Ten or fewer dogs or cats, one hundred fifty dollars;</para>
<para>(ii) Eleven to fifty dogs or cats, two hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(iii) Fifty-one to one hundred dogs or cats, two hundred fifty
dollars;</para>
<para>(iv) One hundred one to one hundred fifty dogs or cats, three
hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(v) One hundred fifty-one to two hundred dogs or cats, three
hundred fifty dollars;</para>
<para>(vi) Two hundred one to two hundred fifty dogs or cats, four
hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(vii) Two hundred fifty-one to three hundred dogs or cats,
four hundred fifty dollars;</para>
<para>(viii) Three hundred one to three hundred fifty dogs or cats,
five hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(ix) Three hundred fifty-one to four hundred dogs or cats,
five hundred fifty dollars;</para>
<para>(x) Four hundred one to four hundred fifty dogs or cats, six
hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(xi) Four hundred fifty-one to five hundred dogs or cats,
six hundred fifty dollars; and</para>
<para>(xii) More than five hundred dogs or cats, two thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(b) The initial license fee for any person required to be
licensed pursuant to the act shall be one hundred twenty-five dollars.</para>
<para>(c) The annual license fee for a licensee that does not house
dogs or cats shall be one hundred fifty dollars.</para>
<para>(d) The annual license fee for an animal rescue shall be one
hundred fifty dollars.</para>
<para>(e) The annual license
fee for a commercial dog or cat breeder shall be determined according to the
fee schedule set forth in subdivision (a) of this subsection based upon the
number of breeding dogs or cats owned or harbored by the commercial breeder.</para>
<para>(f) The fees charged under
this subsection may be increased or decreased by the director after a public
hearing is held outlining the reason for any proposed change in the fee. The
maximum fee that may be charged shall not result in a fee for any license
category that exceeds the license fee set forth in this subsection by more
than one hundred dollars.</para>
<para>(4) A license to operate as a commercial dog or cat breeder, dealer, boarding
kennel, or pet shop shall be renewed by filing with the department on
or before April 1 of each year a renewal application and the annual license
fee. A license to operate as an animal control facility, animal rescue, or
animal shelter shall be renewed by filing with the department on or before
October 1 of each year a renewal application and the annual license fee. Failure
to renew a license prior to the expiration of the license shall result in
a late renewal fee equal to twenty percent of the annual license fee due and
payable each month, not to exceed one hundred percent of such fee, in addition
to the license fee. The purpose of the late renewal fee is to pay for the
administrative costs associated with the collection of fees under this section.
The assessment of the late renewal fee shall not prohibit the director from
taking any other action as provided in the act.</para>
<para>(5) A licensee under this section shall make its premises
available for inspection pursuant to section 54-628 during normal business
hours.</para>
<para>(6) The state or any political subdivision of the state which
contracts out its animal control duties to a facility not operated by the
state or any political subdivision of the state may be exempted from the licensing
requirements of this section if such facility is licensed as an animal control
facility, animal rescue, or animal shelter for the full term of the contract
with the state or its political subdivision.</para>
<para>(7) Any fees collected pursuant to this section shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection
Program Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 825, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 233, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 274, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1002, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB12, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB241, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB910, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB427, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>