<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-860"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-860</statuteno><catchline>Violations; order of director or court; seizure of feed.</catchline><para>(1) When the director has reasonable cause to believe any lot of commercial feed is being distributed in violation of the Commercial Feed Act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto, he or she may issue and enforce a written or printed withdrawal-from-distribution order warning the distributor not to dispose of the lot of commercial feed in any manner until written permission is given by the director or a court of competent jurisdiction. The director shall release the lot of commercial feed so withdrawn when the provisions, rules, and regulations of the act have been complied with. If compliance is not obtained within thirty days, the director may begin, or upon request of the distributor or the person named on the label shall begin, proceedings for condemnation.</para><para>(2) Any lot of commercial feed not in compliance with the Commercial Feed Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto shall be subject to seizure on complaint of the director to a court of competent jurisdiction in the area in which such commercial feed is located. If the court finds the commercial feed to be in violation of the act or such rules and regulations and orders the condemnation of the commercial feed, such feed shall be disposed of in any manner consistent with the quality of the commercial feed and the laws of the state. In no instance shall the disposition of the commercial feed be ordered by the court without first giving the claimant an opportunity to apply to the court for release of such commercial feed or for permission to process or relabel the commercial feed to bring it into compliance with the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 322, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 366, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 