<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id63">
<sectno id="id64" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id65" statutenumber="54-628"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id67">54-628</statuteno><catchline id="id68">Inspection program; department; powers.</catchline>
<para> (1) The
department shall inspect all licensees at least once in a twenty-four-month
period to determine whether the licensee is in compliance with the Commercial
Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act. Any additional inspector or other field
personnel employed by the department to carry out inspections pursuant to
the act that are funded through General Fund appropriations to the Bureau
of Animal Industry shall be assigned to the Bureau of Animal Industry and
shall be available for temporary reassignment as needed to other activities
and functions of the Bureau of Animal Industry in the event of a livestock
disease emergency or any other threat to livestock or public health. When
an inspection produces evidence of a violation of the act or the rules and
regulations of the department, a copy of a written report of the inspection
and violations shown thereon, prepared by the inspector, shall be given to
the applicant or licensee, together with written notice to comply within the
time limit established by the department and set out in such notice.</para>
<para>(2) If deemed
necessary under the act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated
pursuant to the act, the department may, for purposes of inspection, enter
the premises of any applicant or licensee during normal business hours and
in a reasonable manner, including all premises in or upon which dogs or cats
are housed, sold, exchanged, or leased or are suspected of being housed, sold,
exchanged, or leased. For purposes of this subsection, premises includes all
buildings, vehicles, equipment, cages, kennels, containers, and pens and all
records on such premises. The department shall not be subject to any action
for trespass or damages resulting from compliance with this subsection. Pursuant
to an inspection under this subsection, the department may:</para>
<para>(a) Enter the
premises of any applicant for a license under the act to determine if the
applicant meets the requirements for licensure under the act;</para>
<para>(b) Access
all premises and examine and copy all records pertaining to compliance with
the act and the rules or regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.
The department shall have authority to gather evidence, including, but not
limited to, photographs;</para><para>(c) Inspect or reinspect any vehicle or carrier transporting or
holding dogs or cats that is in the state to determine compliance with the
act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated under the act;</para>
<para>(d) Obtain
an inspection warrant in the manner prescribed in sections 29-830 to 29-835
if any person refuses to allow the department to conduct an inspection pursuant
to this section; or</para><para>(e) Issue and enforce a written stop-movement order pursuant to
section 54-628.01.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, the private residence of any applicant
or licensee shall be available for purposes of inspection only if dogs or
cats are housed in a primary enclosure as defined in 9 C.F.R. 1.1 within the
residence, including a room in such residence, and only such portion of the
residence that is used as a primary enclosure shall be open to an inspection
pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 825, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB12, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB241, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>