<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-7,100"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-7,100</statuteno><catchline>Livestock certification program; removal from registry; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall remove the name of a livestock producer from a livestock certification registry if the livestock producer has issued false records or statements or has made misleading claims to the department with regard to livestock certification when such records, statements, or claims cause, or could cause, the department to incorrectly include the name of a livestock producer in the certification registry.</para><para>(2) Before removal, the department shall notify the livestock producer in writing of the department's intention and the reasons for the intended removal from the registry. The notice shall inform the applicant of his or her right to request an administrative hearing before the director regarding his or her removal from the registry. A request for hearing shall be in writing and shall be filed with the department within thirty days after the service of the notice is made. If a request for hearing is filed within the thirty-day period, at least twenty days before the hearing the director shall notify the livestock producer of the time, date, and place of the hearing. Such proceeding may be appealed as a contested case under the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(3) A livestock producer whose name is removed from a livestock certification registry for the first time shall not be eligible to reapply for twelve months from the date of removal. A livestock producer whose name is removed from a registry a subsequent time shall not be eligible to reapply for thirty-six months from the date of removal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 438, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Definitions,</emphasis> where found, see section 54-2902.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 