<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id66"><amendatorysection
amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id68" statutenumber="54-618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id70">54-618</statuteno><catchline
id="id71">Dangerous dogs; actions required; costs; limitations on transport;
permanent relocation; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A dangerous dog that
has been declared as such shall be spayed or neutered and implanted with a
microchip identification number by a licensed veterinarian within thirty days
after such declaration. The cost of both procedures is the responsibility
of the owner of the dangerous dog. Written proof of both procedures and the
microchip identification number shall be provided to the animal control authority
after the procedures are completed.</para><para>(2) No owner of a dangerous
dog shall permit the dog to go beyond the property of the owner unless the
dog is restrained securely by a chain or leash.</para><para>(3) Except as
provided in subsection (4) of this section or for a reasonable veterinary
purpose, no owner of a dangerous dog shall transport such dog or permit such
dog to be transported to another county, city, or village in this state.</para><para>(4)
An owner of a dangerous dog may transport such dog or permit such dog to be
transported to another county, city, or village in this state for the purpose
of permanent relocation of the owner if the owner has obtained written permission
prior to such relocation from the animal control authority of the county,
city, or village in which the owner resides and from the county, city, or
village in which the owner will reside. Each animal control authority may
grant such permission based upon a reasonable evaluation of both the owner
and the dog, including if the owner has complied with the laws of this state
and of the county, city, or village in which he or she resides with regard
to dangerous dogs after the dog was declared dangerous. An animal control
authority shall not grant permission under this subsection if the county,
city, or village has an ordinance or resolution prohibiting the relocation
of dangerous dogs. After the permanent relocation, the animal control authority
of the county, city, or village in which the owner resides shall monitor the
owner and such dog for a period of at least thirty days but not to exceed
ninety days to ensure the owner's compliance with the laws of this state and
of such county, city, or village with regard to dangerous dogs. Nothing in
this subsection shall permit the rescindment of the declaration of dangerous
dog.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 208, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1055, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
