<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-706.16"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-706.16</statuteno><catchline>Violations; department powers; hearing; order or other action; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever the Director of Agriculture or the State Veterinarian has reason to believe that any person has violated any of the provisions of the Bovine Tuberculosis Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, an order may be entered requiring such person to appear before the director and show cause why an order should not be entered requiring such person to cease and desist from the violations charged. Such order shall set forth the alleged violations, fix the time and place of the hearing, and provide for notice thereof which shall be given not less than twenty days before the date of such hearing. After a hearing, or if the person charged with such violation fails to appear at the time of such hearing, if the director finds such person to be in violation, the director shall enter an order requiring such person to cease and desist from the specific acts, practices, or omissions.</para><para>(2) Any person aggrieved by any order entered by the director or other action of the director under the Bovine Tuberculosis Act may appeal the order or action, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(3) This section does not prevent the department from first pursuing any other administrative, civil, or criminal actions provided in the Bovine Tuberculosis Act when there is a violation of the act or rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB110, &#167; 16. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>