<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id143" statutenumber="54-7,107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-7,107</statuteno><catchline id="id146">Records; contents; access by department.</catchline><para>(1) An exotic animal auction or exchange venue organizer shall maintain records for each exotic animal auction or exchange venue such organizer arranges, organizes, leases areas for, consigns, or otherwise coordinates at least five years after the date of the exotic animal auction or exchange venue. The records shall include:</para><para>(a) The name, address, and telephone number of the exotic animal auction or exchange venue organizer;</para><para>(b) The name and address of all persons who purchased, sold, traded, bartered, gave away, or otherwise transferred an exotic animal at the exotic animal auction or exchange venue;</para><para>(c) The number of and species or type of each exotic animal purchased, sold, traded, bartered, given away, or otherwise transferred at the exotic animal auction or exchange venue;</para><para>(d) The date of purchase, sale, trade, barter, or other transfer of an exotic animal at the exotic animal auction or exchange venue; and</para><para>(e) When required by the Animal Health and Disease Control Act or the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue Act, a copy of the completed certificate of veterinary inspection for each exotic animal purchased, sold, traded, bartered, given away, or otherwise transferred at the exotic animal auction or exchange venue.</para><para>(2) An exotic animal auction or exchange venue organizer shall, during all reasonable times, permit authorized employees and agents of the department to have access to and to copy any or all records relating to his or her exotic animal auction or exchange venue business.</para><para>(3) When necessary for the enforcement of the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue Act or any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to such act, the authorized employees and agents of the department may access the records required by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB344, &#167; 71. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Animal Health and Disease Control Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2901.</para><para><emphasis>Violations,</emphasis> prohibited acts, penalties, see sections 54-2953 to 54-2956.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>