<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id53">
<sectno id="id54">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" id="id55" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-908"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-908</statuteno><catchline>Employee of governmental livestock
animal control or animal abuse agency; duty to report suspected criminal activity;
immunity from liability; contents of report; form; failure to report; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes
of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Employee means any
employee of a governmental agency dealing with livestock animal control or
animal abuse; and</para><para>(b) Reasonably suspects means a basis for reporting knowledge or
a set of facts that would lead a person of ordinary care and prudence to believe
and conscientiously entertain a strong suspicion that criminal activity is
at hand or that a crime has been committed.</para><para>(2) Any employee, while acting in his or
her professional capacity or within the scope of his or her employment, who
observes or is involved in an incident which leads the employee to reasonably
suspect that a livestock animal has been abandoned, cruelly neglected, or
cruelly mistreated shall report such to the entity or entities that investigate
such reports in that jurisdiction.</para><para>(3) The report of an employee shall be made
within two working days of acquiring the information concerning the livestock
animal by facsimile transmission of a written report presented in the form
described in subsection (5) of this section or by telephone. When an immediate
response is necessary to protect the health and safety of the livestock animal
or others, the report of an employee shall be made by telephone as soon as
possible.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to impose a duty
to investigate observed or reasonably suspected livestock animal abandonment,
cruel neglect, or cruel mistreatment. Any person making a report under this
section is immune from liability except for false statements of fact made
with malicious intent.</para><para>(5) A report made by an employee pursuant to this section shall
include:</para><para>(a) The reporter's name and title, business address, and telephone
number;</para><para>(b) The name, if known, of the livestock animal owner or custodian,
whether a business or individual;</para><para>(c) A description of the livestock animal
or livestock animals involved, person or persons involved, and location of
the livestock animal or livestock animals and the premises; and</para>
<para>(d) The date,
the time, and a description of the observation or incident which led the reporter
to reasonably suspect livestock animal abandonment, cruel neglect, or cruel
mistreatment and any other information the reporter believes may be relevant.</para>
<para>(6) A report
made by an employee pursuant to this section may be made on preprinted forms
prepared by the entity or entities that investigate reports of livestock animal
abandonment, livestock animal cruel neglect, or livestock animal cruel mistreatment
in that jurisdiction. The form shall include space for the information required
under subsection (5) of this section.</para><para>(7) When two or more employees jointly have
observed or reasonably suspected livestock animal abandonment, livestock animal
cruel neglect, or livestock animal cruel mistreatment and there is agreement
between or among them, a report may be made by one person by mutual agreement.
Any such reporter who has knowledge that the person designated to report has
failed to do so shall thereafter make the report.</para><para>(8) Any employee failing
to report under this section shall be guilty of an infraction.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB865, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>