<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,122.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,122.02</statuteno><catchline>Registered dairy; cattle shipment
or receipt; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Cattle sold or shipped from
a registered dairy, for purposes other than direct slaughter or sale on any
terminal market, are subject to the brand inspection under sections 54-1,110
to 54-1,119 and the seller or shipper shall bear the cost of such inspection
at the regular fee.</para>
<para>(2) Any other cattle shipped from a registered dairy are not subject
to brand inspection at origin or destination, but the shipper must have a
shipping certificate from the registered dairy. The shipping certificate form
shall be prescribed by the Nebraska Brand Committee and shall show the registered
dairy operator's name and registration number, date shipped, destination,
agency receiving the cattle, number of head in the shipment, and sex of the
cattle. The shipping certificate shall be completed in triplicate by the registered
dairy operator at the time of shipment. One copy thereof shall be delivered
to the brand inspector at the market along with shipment, if applicable, one
copy shall be sent to the brand committee by the tenth day of the following
month, and one copy shall be retained by the registered dairy operator. If
a shipping certificate does not accompany a shipment of cattle from a registered
dairy to any destination where brand inspection is maintained by the brand
committee, all such cattle are subject to a brand inspection and the inspection fees and surcharge provided under section 54-1,108 shall
be charged for the service.</para>
<para>(3) Any cattle originating in a state that has a brand inspection agency
and which are accompanied by a certificate of inspection or brand clearance
issued by such agency may be moved directly from the point of origin into
a registered dairy. Any cattle not accompanied by such a certificate of inspection
or brand clearance or by satisfactory evidence of ownership from states or
portions of states not having brand inspection shall be inspected for brands
by the Nebraska Brand Committee within a reasonable time after arrival at
a registered dairy, and the inspection fee and
surcharge provided under section 54-1,108 shall be collected by
the brand inspector at the time the inspection is performed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 213, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB181, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
