<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id651"><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,133"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,133</statuteno><catchline>Registered dairy heifer development facility; records; audits.</catchline><para>(1) The operator of a registered dairy heifer development facility shall:</para><para>(a) Keep the following for all cattle in such registered dairy heifer development facility: Cattle inventory records, purchase records, certificates of inspection, and any other satisfactory evidence of ownership; and</para><para>(b) Make such records and satisfactory evidence of ownership available to the brand committee or its employees for purposes of: Performing audits under this section, investigating lost or stolen livestock, or investigating violations of the Livestock Brand Act.</para><para>(2)(a) This subdivision (a) applies unless otherwise provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection. The brand committee or its employees may audit each registered dairy heifer development facility twice during a calendar year. When performing an audit under this subsection, the brand committee or its employees shall audit a selection of up to ten percent of the lot files for the cattle in the registered dairy heifer development facility as of the commencement date of the audit.</para><para>(b) The brand committee or its employees may audit a registered dairy heifer development facility under subdivision (a) of this subsection more than twice during a calendar year if:</para><para>(i) The audit is approved by a majority vote of all of the members of the brand committee;</para><para>(ii) The brand committee finds the existence of reasonable cause of a violation by the registered dairy heifer development facility of the Livestock Brand Act or any rules and regulations that are adopted and promulgated under the act; and</para><para>(iii) The reasonable cause for the audit is specifically stated by the brand committee in a resolution authorizing the audit. The brand committee may adopt a resolution for purposes of this subdivision (iii).</para><para>(c) During an audit that is conducted under this subsection, the operator of the registered dairy heifer development facility shall show:</para><para>(i) The lot files selected for the audit; and</para><para>(ii) Cattle purchase records and other satisfactory evidence of ownership for cattle included in the lot files selected for the audit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1187, &#167; 19. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>