<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-633"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-633</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement powers; administrative fine.</catchline><para>(1) In order to ensure compliance with the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act, the department may apply for a restraining order, temporary or permanent injunction, or mandatory injunction against any person violating or threatening to violate the act, the rules and regulations, or any order of the director issued pursuant thereto. The district court of the county where the violation is occurring or is about to occur shall have jurisdiction to grant relief upon good cause shown. Relief may be granted notwithstanding the existence of any other remedy at law and shall be granted without bond.</para><para>The county attorney of the county in which such violations are occurring or about to occur shall, when notified of such violation or threatened violation, cause appropriate proceedings under this section to be instituted and pursued without delay.</para><para>(2) If alleged violations of the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act, the rules and regulations, or an order of the director or an offense against animals observed by an inspector in the course of performing an inspection under the act poses a significant threat to the health or safety of the dogs or cats harbored or owned by an applicant or licensee, the department may direct an inspector to impound the dogs or cats pursuant to sections 28-1011 and 28-1012 or may request any other law enforcement officer as defined in section 28-1008 to impound the dogs or cats pursuant to sections 28-1011 and 28-1012. The department shall cooperate and coordinate with law enforcement agencies, political subdivisions, animal shelters, humane societies, and other appropriate entities, public or private, to provide for the care, shelter, and disposition of animals impounded by the department pursuant to this section.</para><para>(3) The department may impose an administrative fine of not more than five thousand dollars for any violation of the act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act. Each violation of the act or such rules and regulations shall constitute a separate offense for purposes of this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 825, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB12, &#167; 8.</para></source></law></legaldoc>