<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id155">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id157" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-7,108">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>54-7,108</statuteno><catchline id="id160">Prohibited
transfers; certificate of veterinary
inspection; duties of exotic animal auction or exchange venue organizer; requirements
for certain animals.</catchline>
<para>(1) No beef
or dairy cattle, calves, swine, bison, or domesticated cervine animals shall
be, or offered to be, consigned, purchased, sold, bartered, traded, given
away, or otherwise transferred at an exotic animal auction or exchange venue.</para>
<para>(2) An exotic
animal auction or exchange venue organizer shall contact the department if
a particular animal cannot be readily identified as an animal that is prohibited
from being consigned, purchased, sold, bartered, traded, given away, or otherwise
transferred at an exotic animal auction or exchange venue under this section.</para>
<para>(3) No bovine,
camelid, caprine, ovine, or porcine animal shall be, or be offered to be,
consigned, purchased, sold, bartered, traded, given away, or otherwise transferred
at an exotic animal auction or exchange venue unless, prior to a change of
ownership or other transfer of the animal, a completed certificate of veterinary
inspection for such animal is presented to the exotic animal auction or exchange
venue organizer. Such certificate of veterinary inspection shall be signed
by an accredited veterinarian on the date of or no more than thirty days prior
to the date the exotic animal auction or exchange venue is held.</para>
<para>(4) An exotic
animal auction or exchange venue organizer shall contract with an accredited
veterinarian to be present during the exotic animal auction or exchange venue
for visually inspecting such exotic animals and to issue necessary certificates
of veterinary inspection for change of ownership when required by the Animal
Importation Act or the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue Act.</para>
<para>(5) All dairy
goats imported into Nebraska shall have an official tuberculin test prior
to import into Nebraska. All sheep and goats shall have official identification
as required under the Scrapie Control and Eradication Act.</para>
<para>(6) A copy
of the certificate of veterinary inspection shall be submitted to the department
by the exotic animal auction or exchange venue organizer within seven days
from the date the exotic animal auction or exchange venue was held.</para>
<para>(7) Any bovine,
camelid, caprine, ovine, or porcine animal which is not prohibited from transfer
at an exotic animal auction or exchange venue shall be officially identified
prior to change of ownership.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 17.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Animal Importation Act,</emphasis> see section 54-784.01.</para><para><emphasis>Definitions,</emphasis> see section 54-701.03.</para><para><emphasis>Department of Agriculture,</emphasis> State Veterinarian, powers, see sections 54-703 to 54-705.</para><para><emphasis>Scrapie Control and Eradication Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Violations,</emphasis> penalties, see section 54-752.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>