<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-856" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>54-856</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Inspection fees; administrative fee; statement and records required.</catchline><para>(1) There shall be paid to the director an inspection fee of ten cents per ton on all commercial feed distributed in the State of Nebraska during the six-month period following January 1, 1987. After the first six months of operation, the fee may be raised or lowered by the director after a public hearing is held outlining the reason for any proposed change in the rate. The maximum rate fixed by the director shall not exceed fifteen cents per ton. The inspection fee shall be paid on commercial feed distributed by the person whose name appears on the label as the manufacturer, guarantor, or distributor, except that a person other than the manufacturer, guarantor, or distributor may assume liability for the inspection fee, subject to the following:</para><para>(a) No fee shall be paid on a commercial feed if the payment has been made by a previous distributor;</para><para>(b) No fee shall be paid on customer-formula feed if the inspection fee is paid on the commercial feed which is used as ingredients therein;</para><para>(c) No fee shall be paid on commercial feed used as ingredients for the manufacture of other commercial feed. If the fee has already been paid, credit shall be given for such payment;</para><para>(d) In the case of a commercial feed which is distributed in the state only in packages of ten pounds or less, an annual fee fixed by the director, not to exceed twenty-five dollars, shall be paid in lieu of the inspection fee. The annual fee shall be paid not later than the last day of January each year; and</para><para>(e) The minimum inspection fee shall be five dollars for any six-month reporting period.</para><para>(2) If the director determines that it is necessary to adjust the rate of the inspection fee being paid to the department, all persons holding a valid license issued pursuant to section 54-850 shall be so notified and shall be given an opportunity to offer comment at a public hearing which shall be required prior to any inspection fee rate change.</para><para>(3) Each person who is liable for the payment of such fee shall:</para><para>(a) File, not later than January 31 and July 31 of each year, a semiannual statement setting forth the number of tons of commercial feed distributed in this state during the preceding six-month period, which statement shall cover the periods from July 1 to December 31 and January 1 to June 30, and upon filing such statement, pay the inspection fee at the rate specified by this section. Any person who holds a valid license issued pursuant to section 54-850 and whose name appears on the label as the manufacturer, guarantor, or distributor shall file such statement regardless of whether any inspection fee is due. Inspection fees which are due and owing and have not been remitted to the director within fifteen days following the date due shall have an administrative fee of twenty-five percent of the fees due added to the amount due when payment is made, and an additional administrative fee of twenty-five percent of the fees due shall be added if such inspection and administrative fees are not paid within thirty days of the due date. The purpose of the additional administrative fees is to cover the administrative costs associated with collecting fees. All money collected as an additional administrative fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Commercial Feed Administration Cash Fund. The assessment of this administrative fee shall not prevent the director from taking other actions as provided in the Commercial Feed Act; and</para><para>(b) Keep such records as may be necessary or required by the director to indicate accurately the tonnage of commercial feed distributed in this state. The director shall have the right to examine such records to verify statements of tonnage. Failure to make an accurate statement, to pay the inspection fee, or to comply as provided in this section shall constitute sufficient cause for the cancellation of all licenses on file.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 322, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 366, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB909, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>