<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id116">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id118" statutenumber="54-638"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id120">54-638</statuteno><catchline id="id121">Provision for
spaying or neutering; when.</catchline><para>Provision shall be
made for spaying or neutering all dogs and cats released for adoption or purchase
from any public or private animal shelter,
animal rescue, or animal control facility operated by a humane
society, a county, a city, or another political subdivision. Such provision
may be made by:</para>
<para>(1) Causing the dog or cat to be spayed or neutered by a
licensed veterinarian before releasing the dog or cat for adoption or purchase;
or</para>
<para>(2) Entering into a written agreement with the adopter or
purchaser of the dog or cat, guaranteeing that spaying or neutering will be
performed by a licensed veterinarian in compliance with an agreement which
shall contain the following information:</para>
<para>(a) The date of the agreement;</para>
<para>(b) The name, address, and signature of the releasing entity
and the adopter or purchaser;</para>
<para>(c) A description of the dog or cat to be adopted or purchased;</para>
<para>(d) A statement, in conspicuous bold print, that spaying
or neutering of the dog or cat is required pursuant to this section; and</para>
<para>(e) The date by which the spaying or neutering will be completed,
which date shall be (i) in the case of an adult dog or cat, the thirtieth
day after the date of adoption or purchase or (ii) in the case of a pup or
kitten, either (A) the thirtieth day after a specified date estimated to be
the date the pup or kitten will reach six months of age or (B) if the releasing
entity has a written policy recommending spaying or neutering of certain pups
or kittens at an earlier date, the thirtieth day after such date.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 274, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB910, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>