<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id5" statutenumber="54-744"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">54-744</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Dead animals; carcasses;
manner of disposition.</catchline><para>(1) Except as set out in
subsections (2) and (3) of this section and section 54-776, it is the duty
of the owner or custodian of any dead animal to cause such animal, within
thirty-six hours after receiving knowledge of the death of such animal, to
be:</para>
<para>(a) Buried
at least four feet below the surface of the ground or completely incinerated
or composted on the premises where such animal dies or on an adjacent property
under the ownership and control of the owner or custodian. Any vehicle used
by the owner or custodian to transport such dead animal shall be constructed
in such a manner that the contents are covered and will not fall, leak, or
spill therefrom. Violation of this subdivision is a traffic infraction as
defined in section 60-672; or</para><para>(b) Transported by a licensed rendering establishment
to either a rendering establishment licensed under the Nebraska Meat and Poultry
Inspection Law or to a facility with a permit to operate as a landfill under
the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act. The operator of a landfill is not
required by this subdivision to accept dead animals.</para><para>(2) The
Department of Agriculture shall regulate the composting of livestock carcasses
and shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the same. Any person incorporating livestock carcasses
into a composting facility shall follow the operating procedures established
by the Department of Agriculture in consultation with the University of Nebraska
Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources.</para>
<para>(3) An animal carcass or carcass part may be transported by
the owner or the owner's agent to a veterinary clinic or veterinary diagnostic
laboratory for purposes of performing diagnostic procedures.</para>
<para>(4) In addition to methods
listed in subsections (1) and (2) of this section, animal carcasses or carcass
parts may be disposed of by a veterinary clinic or veterinary diagnostic laboratory
by alkaline hydrolysis tissue digestion. For purposes of this section, alkaline
hydrolysis tissue digestion means a process that utilizes an alkaline agent
and heat to catalyze the decomposition and reduction of biological tissues.
This section shall not exempt the products of alkaline hydrolysis tissue digestion
from any applicable law, rule, or regulation governing disposal of wastes.</para>
<para>(5) Carcasses disposed of
in compliance with this section or section 54-744.01 are exempt from the requirements
for disposal of solid waste under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 12, art. VIII, &#167; 3, p. 92; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 54-940; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 54-744; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 267, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 870, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 438, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB99, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB882, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law,</emphasis> see section 54-1901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>