<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id38"><amendatorysection
amended="no" chaptername="Livestock" id="id40" 
statutenumber="54-506"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-506</statuteno><catchline>Release
from program; when; recovery of payments.</catchline><para>(1) A veterinarian
shall be released from the program contract without penalty if:</para><para>(a)
The veterinarian has completed the service requirements of the contract;</para><para>(b)
The veterinarian is unable to complete the service requirements of the contract
because of a permanent physical disability;</para><para>(c) The veterinarian
demonstrates extreme hardship or shows other good cause justifying the release;
or</para><para>(d) The veterinarian dies.</para><para>(2)(a) A veterinarian
shall be released from further performance of veterinary services under the
program contract if he or she is unable to perform his or her contractual
obligations to provide veterinary services due to the suspension or revocation
of his or her federal accreditation or denial, refusal of renewal, limitation,
suspension, revocation, or other disciplinary measure taken against his or
her license to practice in Nebraska pursuant to section 71-1,163 until December
1, 2008, and section 38-3324 on and after December 1, 2008.</para><para>(b)
If a veterinarian is released from his or her contract pursuant to subdivision
(a) of this subsection, the department may recover a portion of or all of
the payments made to such veterinarian under section 54-505. The department
shall remit any such funds to the State Treasurer for credit to the Food Supply
Animal Veterinary Incentive Fund. The department may use appropriate remedies
available to enforce this subdivision.</para><para>(3) The State of Nebraska
shall be released from any further obligation under the Food Supply Animal
Veterinary Incentive Program Act or any contract entered into with a veterinarian
under the act if the veterinarian is released from the program pursuant to
this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008,
LB1172, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
