<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,119" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,119</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Open market; designation; brand inspection requirements.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Any livestock market, whether within or outside of the state, or any meat packing plant which maintains brand inspection under the supervision of the Nebraska Brand Committee and under such rules and regulations as are specified by the United States Department of Agriculture, may be designated by the brand committee as an open market.</para><para id="id00">(2) When cattle originating from within the brand inspection area are consigned for sale to any commission company at any open market designated as such by the Nebraska Brand Committee where brand inspection is maintained, no brand inspection is required at the point of origin but is required at the point of destination unless the point of origin is a registered feedlot. If cattle are consigned to a commission company at an open market, the carrier transporting the cattle shall not allow the owner, shipper, or party in charge to change the billing to any point other than the commission company at the open market designated on the original billing, unless the carrier secures from the brand committee a certificate of inspection on the cattle so consigned. Any cattle originating in a registered feedlot consigned to a commission company at any terminal market destined for direct slaughter may be shipped in accordance with rules and regulations governing registered feedlots.</para><para id="id00">(3) Until the cattle are inspected for brands on the premises by the Nebraska Brand Committee, no person shall sell or cause to be sold or offer for sale (a) any cattle at a livestock auction market located within the brand inspection area or at a farm or ranch sale located within the brand inspection area or (b) any cattle originating within the brand inspection area consigned to an open market.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 213, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB600, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>