<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<?APT Element gi="legaldoc"?>
<?APT Element gi="law" attrs="type"?>
<?APT Element gi="section" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="sectno" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="amendatorysection" attrs="amended chaptername id statutenumber"?>
<?APT Element gi="bookinfo"?>
<?APT Element gi="statuteno" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="catchline" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="para"?>
<?APT Element gi="source"?>
<?APT Element gi="effectivedate"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id76"><sectno id="id77">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection
amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id78" statutenumber="54-619"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id80">54-619</statuteno><catchline
id="id81">Dangerous dogs; confinement required; warning signs.</catchline><para>(1)
No person, firm, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation shall
own, keep, or harbor or allow to be in or on any premises occupied by him,
her, or it or under his, her, or its charge or control any dangerous dog without
such dog being confined so as to protect the public from injury.</para><para>(2)
While unattended on the owner's property, a dangerous dog shall be securely
confined, in a humane manner, indoors or in a securely enclosed and locked
pen or structure suitably designed to prevent the entry of young children
and to prevent the dog from escaping. The pen or structure shall have secure
sides and a secure top. If the pen or structure has no bottom secured to the
sides, the sides shall be embedded into the ground at a depth of at least
one foot. The pen or structure shall also protect the dog from the elements.
The pen or structure shall be at least ten feet from any property line of
the owner. The owner of a dangerous dog shall post warning signs on the property
where the dog is kept that are clearly visible from all areas of public access
and that inform persons that a dangerous dog is on the property. Each warning
sign shall be no less than ten inches by twelve inches and shall contain the
words warning and dangerous animal in high-contrast lettering at least three
inches high on a black background.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1989, LB 208, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1055, &#167; 18.</para></source> </law></legaldoc>
