<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id137">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" id="id139"  statutenumber="54-641.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-641.02</statuteno><catchline>Commercial dog breeder; veterinary
care; review of health records; duties of breeder.</catchline><para>(1) A commercial dog breeder shall ensure
that each dog under his or her care, supervision, or control receives adequate
veterinary care. A commercial dog breeder's written veterinary care plan shall
provide for, in addition to requirements prescribed by rule and regulation
of the department:</para>
<para>(a)
The maintenance of individual health records for each dog bought, raised,
or otherwise obtained, held, kept, maintained, sold, donated, or otherwise
disposed of, including by death or euthanasia, except that litter health records
may be kept on litters when litter mates are treated with the same medication
or procedure;</para><para>(b) Establishment of a program of disease control and prevention,
pest and parasite control, before and after procedure care, nutrition, and
euthanasia supervised by the attending veterinarian. Such program shall provide
for regularly scheduled onsite visits to the facility by the veterinarian
and shall be annually reviewed and updated by the veterinarian at the time
of an onsite visit that includes the veterinarian's walk-through of the facility
and observation by the veterinarian of dogs under the commercial dog breeder's
care, supervision, or control; and</para><para>(c) A wellness examination by a licensed
veterinarian of each breeding dog at least once every three years, to include
a basic physical and dental examination and corresponding notations entered
into the dog's health records. Such examination shall not require laboratory
analysis unless directed by the veterinarian.</para><para>(2) During regularly scheduled
inspections of a commercial dog breeder's facility conducted by the department,
the health records of a random sample of at least five percent of the breeding
dogs shall be reviewed to verify that such records correspond to the dog's
permanent identification and verify that the health records are properly maintained.</para>
<para>(3) For each
dog under the commercial dog breeder's care, supervision, or control, the
breeder shall:</para><para>(a)
Ensure that all breeding dogs receive regular grooming. Coat matting shall
not exceed ten percent, and nails shall be trimmed short enough to ensure
the comfort of the dog;</para><para>(b)
Contact a licensed veterinarian without delay after an occurrence of a serious
or life-threatening injury or medical condition of such dog. The dog shall
be treated as prescribed by the veterinarian;</para><para>(c) Ensure that all surgical births
or other surgical procedures shall be performed by a licensed veterinarian
using anesthesia. Commercial dog breeders may remove dew claws and perform
tail docking under sterile conditions within the first seven days of the dog's
life. Wounds shall be treated and monitored by the breeder; and</para>
<para>(d) Ensure that, if euthanasia
is necessary, it shall be performed by a licensed veterinarian in accordance
with recommendations for the humane euthanization of dogs as published by
the American Veterinary Medical Association.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB427, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>