<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="54-766"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-766</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Anthrax Control Act:</para>
<para>(1) Accredited veterinarian
means a veterinarian approved by the Administrator of the Animal and Plant
Health Inspection Service of the United States Department of Agriculture in
accordance with the provisions of 9 C.F.R. part 161, as such regulation existed
on January 1, 2009;</para><para>(2) Affected herd means a herd which contains an animal
infected with or exposed to anthrax;</para><para>(3) Affected premises means the land on which is located
an animal infected with or exposed to anthrax and includes the buildings,
holding facilities, and equipment located on such land;</para>
<para>(4) Animal means all
vertebrate members of the animal kingdom except humans, fish, amphibians,
reptiles, and wild animals at large;</para><para>(5) Approved laboratory means a laboratory designated
by the department in rules and regulations;</para><para>(6) Department means the Department of Agriculture;</para>
<para>(7) Exposed means an
animal or herd having or suspected of having contact (a) with animals infected
with anthrax spores or organisms or (b) with premises which contain anthrax
spores or organisms;</para><para>(8)
Herd means (a) any group of livestock maintained on common ground for any
purpose or (b) two or more groups of livestock under common ownership or supervision
geographically separated but which have an interchange of livestock without
regard to whether the livestock are infected or exposed;</para>
<para>(9) Herd plan means a
written disease management plan that is designed by the herd owner or custodian
in conjunction with the State Veterinarian to control and eradicate anthrax
from an infected herd;</para><para>(10)
Livestock means cattle, bison, swine, sheep, goats, equines, and domesticated
cervine animals;</para><para>(11)
Quarantine means the restriction imposed by the department (a) on the movement
of an affected herd, (b) on the movement of an animal or a group of animals
infected with or exposed to anthrax, (c) on the use of an affected premises,
or (d) on the use of land where anthrax spores have been found and includes
restriction of the buildings, holding facilities, and equipment upon such
land; and</para><para>(12)
State Veterinarian means the veterinarian appointed pursuant to section 81-202.01
or his or her designee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB99, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>