<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id23" statutenumber="54-1,128"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,128</statuteno><catchline>Brand with brand recorded or registered in another state; application for out-of-state brand permit; contents; fee; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) An owner may brand cattle with a brand recorded or registered in another state when:</para><para>(a) Cattle are purchased at a livestock auction market licensed under the Livestock Auction Market Act or congregated at another location approved by the Nebraska Brand Committee;</para><para>(b) The cattle will be imminently exported from Nebraska;</para><para>(c) The cattle are branded at the livestock auction market or other approved location; and</para><para>(d) An out-of-state brand permit has been obtained prior to branding the cattle.</para><para>(2) An application for an out-of-state brand permit shall be made to a brand inspector and shall include a description of the brand, a written application, and a fee not to exceed fifty dollars as determined by the Nebraska Brand Committee. A brand inspector shall evaluate and may approve an out-of-state brand permit within a reasonable period of time.</para><para>(3) Cattle branded under an out-of-state brand permit shall remain subject to all other brand inspection requirements under the Livestock Brand Act.</para><para>(4) A violation of this section is an infraction. A peace officer shall have the authority to write a citation, which shall be waivable, to offenders in violation of this section. A fine under this section shall not exceed two hundred dollars per head for each offense. Violations shall be charged in the county in which the offense occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB435, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB572, &#167; 32. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Livestock Auction Market Act,</emphasis> see section 54-1156.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>