<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection
amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-401</statuteno><catchline>Estrays,
trespassing animals; damages; liability.</catchline><para>The owners of cattle,
horses, mules, swine, sheep, and goats in this state are liable for all damages
done by such stock upon the lands of another in this state as provided by
section 54-402 if the damages to the lands are not the result of negligent
or willful damage to the division fence by the person claiming damages to
the land.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1871, &#167; 1, p. 120; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 109; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 117; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 54-401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 54-401; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 149, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1174, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB925, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Persons
liable</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Lien</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3.
Remedies</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1.
Persons liable</emphasis></para><para>Joint owners of herd are liable jointly.
Wilson v. White, 77 Neb. 351, 109 N.W. 367 (1906).</para><para>Mortgagee,
without possession, is not owner within meaning of statute. Goff v. Byers
Bros. &amp; Co., 70 Neb. 1, 96 N.W. 1037 (1903).</para><para>The term owners
is construed to include depasturer. Laflin v. Svoboda, 37 Neb. 368, 55 N.W.
1049 (1893).</para><para><emphasis>2. Lien</emphasis></para><para>Owner of
land damaged by trespassing stock has lien thereon for damages done and for
care and feed while impounded. Angus Cattle Co. v. McLeod, 98 Neb. 108, 152
N.W. 322 (1915).</para><para><emphasis>3. Remedies</emphasis></para><para>Negligence
of plaintiff in maintenance of division fence immaterial in action for damages
by livestock upon cultivated lands. Fiene v. Robertson, 184 Neb. 668, 171
N.W.2d 179 (1969).</para><para>Action for damages by stock ranging at large
upon uncultivated land will not lie, but driving of animals thereon is actionable
wrong. Meyers v. Menter, 63 Neb. 427, 88 N.W. 662 (1902).</para><para>Remedy
herein is not exclusive, and common-law liability is not abrogated. Lorance
v. Hillyer, 57 Neb. 266, 77 N.W. 755 (1898).</para><para>Injunction will lie
to restrain threatened trespass of stock. State Bank of Nebraska of Seward
v. Rohren, 55 Neb. 223, 75 N.W. 543 (1898).</para><para>Where owner drives
his stock upon unenclosed and uncultivated lands of another he is liable for
trespass. Delaney v. Errickson, 11 Neb. 533, 10 N.W. 451 (1881).</para><para><emphasis>4.
Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The herd laws pertain to damage to property
and do not alter the common law liability for personal injuries caused by
trespassing bulls. Foland v. Malander, 222 Neb. 1, 381 N.W.2d 914 (1986).</para><para>A
fenced pasture planted to wheat grass and not surrounded by a plowed strip
constitutes "cultivated lands" for purposes of this statute. Fuchser v. Jacobson,
205 Neb. 786, 290 N.W.2d 449 (1980).</para><para>Section is not applicable
to uncultivated, unenclosed wild prairie lands of state. Delaney v. Errickson,
10 Neb. 492, 6 N.W. 600 (1880).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
