<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-415"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-415</statuteno><catchline>Estrays; distraint; sale; procedure; disposition of proceeds; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>Any person taking up an estray shall report the same within seven days thereafter to the Nebraska Brand Committee, if within the brand inspection area, or to the county sheriff of the county where the estray was taken up, if not within the brand inspection area. If the animal is determined to be an estray by a representative of the Nebraska Brand Committee or the county sheriff, as the case may be, such animal shall, as promptly as may be practicable, be sold through the most convenient livestock auction market. The proceeds of such sale, after deducting the selling expenses, shall be paid over to the Nebraska Brand Committee to be placed in the estray fund identified in section 54-1,118, if such estray was taken up within the brand inspection area, and otherwise to the treasurer of the county in which such estray was taken up. During the time such proceeds are impounded, any person taking up such estray may file claim with the Nebraska Brand Committee or the county treasurer, as the case may be, for the expense of feeding and keeping such estray while in his or her possession. When such claim is filed it shall be the duty of the Nebraska Brand Committee or the county board, as the case may be, to decide on the validity of the claim so filed and allow the claim for such amount as may be deemed equitable. When the estray originates within the brand inspection area such proceeds shall be impounded for one year, unless ownership is determined sooner by the Nebraska Brand Committee, and if ownership is not determined within such one-year period, the proceeds shall be paid into the permanent school fund, less the actual expenses incurred in the investigation and processing of the estray fund. Any amount deducted as actual expenses incurred shall be deposited in the Nebraska Brand Inspection and Theft Prevention Fund. When the estray is located outside the brand inspection area and ownership cannot be determined by the county board, the county board shall then order payment of the balance of the sale proceeds less expenses, to the permanent school fund. If the brand committee or the county board determines ownership of an estray sold in accordance with this section by means of evidence of ownership other than the owner's recorded Nebraska brand, an amount not to exceed the actual investigative costs or expenses may be deducted from the proceeds of the sale. Any person who violates this section is guilty of a Class II misdemeanor. The definitions found in sections 54-172 to 54-190 apply to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, p. 154; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 123; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 131; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 54-415; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 54-415; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 333, &#167; 1, p. 953; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 344, &#167; 1, p. 920; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 564, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 797, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 536, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 61. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 