<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id79" statutenumber="54-630"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>54-630</statuteno><catchline id="id82">Application; denial; grounds; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Before the department approves an application for a license, an inspector of the department shall inspect the operation of the applicant to determine whether the applicant qualifies to hold a license pursuant to the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act. Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, an applicant who qualifies shall be issued a license.</para><para>(2) The department may deny an application for a license as a commercial dog or cat breeder, a dealer, a boarding kennel, an animal control facility, an animal shelter, an animal rescue, or a pet shop upon a finding that the applicant is unsuited to perform the obligations of a licensee. The applicant shall be determined unsuited to perform the obligations of a licensee if the department finds that the applicant has deliberately misrepresented or concealed any information provided on or with the application or any other information provided to the department under this section or that within the previous five years the applicant:</para><para>(a) Has been convicted of any law regarding the disposition or treatment of dogs or cats in any jurisdiction; or</para><para>(b) Has operated a breeder facility under a license or permit issued by any jurisdiction that has been revoked, suspended, or otherwise subject to a disciplinary proceeding brought by the licensing authority in that jurisdiction if such proceeding resulted in the applicant having voluntarily surrendered a license or permit to avoid disciplinary sanctions.</para><para>(3) In addition to the application, the department may require the applicant to provide additional documentation pertinent to the department's determination of the applicant's suitability to perform the duties of a licensee under the act.</para><para>(4) An applicant who is denied a license under this section shall be afforded the opportunity for a hearing before the director or the director's designee to present evidence that the applicant is qualified to hold a license pursuant to the act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department and should be issued a license. All such hearings shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 825, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB12, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB427, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB360, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>