<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id21">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id23" statutenumber="54-742"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>54-742</statuteno><catchline id="id26">Diseased animals;
duty to report; livestock disease reporting system; animal infected with bovine trichomoniasis; report required;
notice to adjacent landowner or land manager; form or affidavit submitted
to department; department; duties; costs.</catchline><para>(1) It is the duty of any
person who discovers, suspects, or has reason to believe that any animal belonging
to him or her or which he or she has in his or her possession or custody or
which, belonging to another, may come under his or her observation is affected
with any dangerous, infectious, contagious, or otherwise transmissible disease
which affects livestock to immediately report such fact, belief, or suspicion
to the department or to any agent, employee, or appointee thereof.</para>
<para>(2) The
department shall work together with livestock health committees, livestock
groups, diagnostic laboratories, practicing veterinarians, producers, and
others who may be affected, to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to effectuate a workable livestock disease reporting system according to the
provisions of this section. The rules and regulations shall establish who
shall report diseases, what diseases shall be reported, how such diseases
shall be reported, to whom diseases shall be reported, the method by which
diseases shall be reported, and the frequency of reports required. For disease
reporting purposes, the department shall categorize livestock diseases according
to relative economic or health risk factors and may provide different reporting
measures for the various categories.</para>
<para>(3) Any person
who reasonably suspects that any beef or dairy breeding bull belonging to
him or her or which he or she has in his or her possession or custody is infected
with bovine trichomoniasis shall not sell or transport such animal, except
for consignment directly to a federally recognized slaughter establishment,
unless such person causes such animal to be tested for bovine trichomoniasis.
Any person who owns or has possession or custody of a beef or dairy breeding
bull, or who has a beef or dairy breeding bull belonging to another under
his or her observation, for which a laboratory confirmed diagnosis of bovine
trichomoniasis has been made, shall report such diagnosis to the department
within five business days after receipt of the laboratory confirmation. Any
such breeding bull for which a laboratory confirmation of bovine trichomoniasis
has been made shall not be sold or transported except for consignment directly
to a federally recognized slaughter establishment.</para><para>(4)(a) An owner or manager
of any beef or dairy breeding bull for which a laboratory confirmed diagnosis
of bovine trichomoniasis has been made shall notify each adjacent landowner
or land manager of the diagnosis if such land is capable of maintaining livestock
susceptible to bovine trichomoniasis. Such notification shall be made to each
landowner or land manager within fourteen days after the diagnosis even if
cattle are not currently maintained on the owner's or manager's land.</para>
<para>(b) The owner
or manager of the cattle shall submit to the department a form or affidavit
attesting to the fact that the notification required under this subsection
has occurred. The form or affidavit shall be submitted to the department within
fourteen days after the diagnosis and shall include the names of adjacent
landowners or land managers who were notified and their contact information.</para>
<para>(c) If an owner
or manager does not, within such fourteen-day period, submit the form or affidavit
indicating that adjacent landowners or land managers have been notified as
required under this subsection, the department shall notify each adjacent
landowner or land manager of the diagnosis. The department shall assess the
administrative costs of the department to notify the adjacent landowners or
land managers against the owner or manager that failed to comply with this
subsection. The department shall determine the definition of adjacent based
on the disease characteristics and modes of transmission. The department shall
remit any administrative costs collected under this subsection to the State
Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Agricultural Products Marketing Cash
Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 12, art. VIII, &#167; 1, p. 92; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 54-938; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 54-742; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 267, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 438, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB423, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Definitions for sections 54-742 to 54-753.05,</emphasis> see section 54-701.03.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>