<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id124">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" id="id126" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-641.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>54-641.01</statuteno><catchline>Commercial dog breeder; dogs; opportunity
for exercise.</catchline><para>(1)
A commercial dog breeder shall provide dogs with the opportunity for exercise
as follows:</para>
<para>(a) A primary
enclosure shall have an entry that allows each dog unfettered access to an
exercise area that is at least three times the size of the requirements for
a primary enclosure. The entry may be closed during cleaning, under direction
of a licensed veterinarian, or in the case of inclement weather. The exercise
area shall have solid surface flooring or a flooring material that if of mesh
or slatted construction does not allow the dog's feet to pass through any
openings in the floor. Any exercise area suspended floor constructed of metal
strands shall be required to have strands that are greater than one-eighth
of an inch in diameter (nine gauge) or coated with a material such as plastic
or fiberglass. All suspended flooring shall be strong enough so as not to
sag or bend between any structural supports and be of a surface that is easily
cleaned and disinfected. The exercise area shall have protection available
from wind, rain, and snow if access to the primary enclosure is unavailable;
and</para><para>(b) Any dog not housed in a primary enclosure that meets the exercise
area requirements of subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be provided
with the opportunity for exercise according to a plan approved by the attending
veterinarian, in writing. The opportunity for exercise shall be accomplished
by:</para><para>(i) Providing access to a run or open area at a frequency and duration
prescribed by the attending veterinarian; or</para><para>(ii) Removal of
the dogs from the primary enclosure at least twice daily to be walked, allowed
to move about freely in an open area, or placed in an exercise area that meets
the requirements of subdivision (a) of this subsection.</para>
<para>(2) Subsection
(1) of this section shall not apply to:</para><para>(a) Any dog that is less than six months
of age;</para><para>(b) The primary enclosure of a nursing facility that houses any
female dog that is due to give birth within the following two weeks or a nursing
dog and her puppies;</para><para>(c) Any dog that is injured or displays any clinical signs of disease.
In such case, any injury or clinical signs of disease shall be noted in the
dog's health records and the dog shall be returned to exercise upon recovery
from such injury or disease; or</para><para>(d) Any dog that is excluded from the exercise requirements
of subsection (1) of this section pursuant to a written directive of a licensed
veterinarian.</para><para>(3) Any primary enclosure newly constructed after October 1, 2012,
shall comply with subdivision (1)(a) of this section. A primary enclosure
in existence on October 1, 2012, shall not be required to comply with subdivision
(1)(a) of this section for the life of such facility.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB427, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>