<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="54-7,106">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>54-7,106</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Permit;
notification requirements;
application; denial; grounds; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Each exotic animal auction
or exchange venue organizer shall apply for a permit and notify
the department at least thirty
days prior to the date on which the exotic animal auction or exchange
venue is to be held. An
applicant for a permit shall verify upon the application that the applicant
has contracted the services of an accredited veterinarian to be present during
the exotic animal auction or exchange venue as required under subsection (4)
of section 54-7,108. Notification shall include the location,
time, and dates of the exotic animal auction or exchange
venue and the name and address of the exotic animal auction or exchange venue organizer. Notification shall
be made in writing or by facsimile transmission. If a livestock auction market holds an exotic animal auction
or exchange venue through its licensed livestock auction market, such livestock
auction market shall comply with the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue
Act for purposes of the exotic animal auction or exchange venue.</para>
<para>(2) The department
may deny an application for a permit if the application does not satisfy the
requirements of subsection (1) of this section, for previous acts or omissions
of the applicant in noncompliance with the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange
Venue Act, or upon a determination that the applicant is unable to fulfill
the duties and responsibilities of a permittee under the act.</para>
<para>(3) No person
shall conduct an exotic animal auction or exchange venue without a permit
issued pursuant to this section.</para><para>(4) No change of ownership of bovine, camelid,
caprine, ovine, or porcine animals may occur at private treaty on the premises
where the exotic animal auction or exchange venue is being held for the twenty-four-hour
period prior to commencement of the exotic animal auction or exchange venue,
nor for twenty-four hours following such event, unless such animals have a
certificate of veterinary inspection at change of ownership.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 15.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Definitions,</emphasis> see section 54-701.03.</para><para><emphasis>Department of Agriculture,</emphasis> State Veterinarian, powers, see sections 54-703 to 54-705.</para><para><emphasis>Violations,</emphasis> penalties, see section 54-752.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>