<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id168">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id170" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="54-646"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>54-646</statuteno><catchline id="id173">Seller; written
disclosure statement; contents; receipt; notice of purchaser's rights and
responsibilities; health certificate; retention of records.</catchline><para>(1) A seller shall deliver to the purchaser at the time of sale
of a pet animal a written disclosure statement containing the following information
regarding the pet animal:</para>
<para>(a) The name, address, and license number of any commercial dog or cat breeder or dealer
as such terms are defined in section 54-626 or, if applicable, the United
States Department of Agriculture license number of the breeder or any broker
who has had possession of the animal prior to the seller's possession;</para>
<para>(b) The date of the pet animal's birth, if known, the state
in which the pet animal was born, if known, and the date the seller received
the pet animal;</para>
<para>(c) The sex and color of the pet animal, any other identifying
marks apparent upon the pet animal, and the breed of the pet animal, if known,
or a statement that the breed of the pet animal is unknown or the pet animal
is of mixed breed;</para>
<para>(d) The pet animal's individual identifying tag, tattoo,
microchip number, or collar number;</para>
<para>(e) The names and registration numbers of the sire and dam
and the litter number, if applicable and if known;</para>
<para>(f) A record of any vaccination, worming treatment, or medication
administered to the pet animal while in the possession of the seller and,
if known, any such vaccination, treatment, or medication administered to the
pet animal prior to the date the seller received the pet animal; and</para>
<para>(g) The date or dates of any examination of the pet animal
by a licensed veterinarian while in the possession of the seller.</para>
<para>(2) The seller may include any of the following with the
written disclosure statement required by subsection (1) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) A statement that a veterinarian examined the pet animal
and, at the time of the examination, the pet animal had no apparent or clinical
symptoms of a serious health problem that would adversely affect the health
of the pet animal at the time of sale or that is likely to adversely affect
the health of the pet animal in the future; and</para>
<para>(b) A record of any serious health problem that adversely
affects the pet animal at the time of sale or that is likely to adversely
affect the health of the pet animal in the future.</para>
<para>(3) The written disclosure statement made pursuant to this
section shall be signed by the seller certifying the accuracy of the written
disclosure statement and by the purchaser acknowledging receipt of the written
disclosure statement. In addition to information required to be given to a
purchaser under this section, at the time of sale the seller shall provide
the purchaser with written notice of the existence of the purchaser's rights
and responsibilities under the Dog and Cat Purchase Protection Act or a legible
copy of the act.</para>
<para>(4) If the pet animal is sold to a purchaser who resides
outside of the state or intends that the pet animal will be relocated or permanently
domiciled outside of the state, the seller shall provide the purchaser with
a health certificate signed by a licensed veterinarian who has examined the
pet animal and is authorized to certify such certificate.</para>
<para>(5) The seller shall maintain a copy of any written disclosure
statements made and any other records on the health, status, or disposition
of each pet animal for at least one year after the date of sale to a purchaser.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB241, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB427, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>