<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,102</statuteno><catchline>Recorded brand; use; expiration date; renewal fee; expired brand; reinstated.</catchline><para>(1) A recorded brand may be applied by its owner until its expiration date.</para><para>(2) On and after January 1, 1994, the expiration date of a recorded brand is the last day of the calendar quarter of the renewal year as designated by the Nebraska Brand Committee in the records of the brand committee.</para><para>(3) The brand committee shall notify every owner of a recorded brand of its expiration date at least sixty days prior to the expiration date, and the owner of the recorded brand shall pay a renewal fee established by the brand committee which shall not be more than fifty dollars and furnish such other information as may be required by the brand committee. The renewal fee is due and payable on or before the expiration date and renews a recorded brand for a period of four years regardless of the number of locations on one side of an animal on which the brand is recorded. If any owner fails, refuses, or neglects to pay the renewal fee by the expiration date, the brand shall expire and be forfeited.</para><para>(4) The brand committee has the authority to hold an expired brand for one year following the date of expiration. An expired brand may be reinstated by the same owner during such one-year period upon return of a brand application form and payment of the recording fee for such brand established by the brand committee under section 54-199 plus a penalty of five dollars for each month or part of a month which has passed since the date of expiration. A properly reinstated brand may be transferred to another person during such one-year period upon completion of a transfer form, with a notarized bill of sale signed by the prior owner attached to such transfer form.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 589, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 