<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,108</statuteno><catchline>Brand inspections; when; fees; reinspection; when.</catchline><para>(1) All brand inspections provided for in the Livestock Brand Act or section 54-415 shall be from sunrise to sundown or during such other hours and under such conditions as the Nebraska Brand Committee determines.</para><para>(2) A fee, established by the Nebraska Brand Committee, of not more than seventy-five cents per head shall be charged for all cattle inspected in accordance with the Livestock Brand Act or section 54-415 or inspected within the brand inspection area by court order or at the request of any bank, credit agency, or lending institution with a legal or financial interest in such cattle. Such fee may vary to encourage inspection to be performed at times and locations that reduce the cost of performing the inspection but shall otherwise be uniform. The inspection fee for court-ordered inspections shall be paid from the proceeds of the sale of such cattle if ordered by the court or by either party as the court directs. For other inspections, the person requesting the inspection of such cattle is responsible for the inspection fee. If estray cattle are identified as a result of the inspection, such cattle shall be processed in the manner provided by section 54-415.</para><para>(3) Any person who has reason to believe that cattle were shipped erroneously due to an inspection error during a brand inspection may request a reinspection. The person making such request shall be responsible for the expenses incurred as a result of the reinspection unless the results of the reinspection substantiate the claim of inspection error, in which case the brand committee shall be responsible for the reinspection expenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 589, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 441, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>