<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-788"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-788</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of veterinary inspection; requirements; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section, all animals brought into this state shall be accompanied by a certificate of veterinary inspection. The certificate of veterinary inspection shall state on its face the destination of the animal and shall meet the requirements for issuance, approval, content, and filing prescribed by the Department of Agriculture through rules and regulations. The following animals are not required to be accompanied by a certificate of veterinary inspection: (a) Animals brought directly to a federally recognized slaughter establishment; (b) cattle, swine, horses, sheep, and goats brought from the farm or ranch of origin directly to an establishment approved under 9 C.F.R. part 71, 75, 78, 79, or 85; (c) poultry under eight weeks of age accompanied by a VS Form 9-3, "Report of Sales of Hatching Eggs, Chicks, and Poults", and classified prior to movement into Nebraska as pullorum and typhoid clean or equivalent status pursuant to 9 C.F.R. 145, the National Poultry Improvement Plan; and (d) animals moving directly to a veterinary clinic for diagnosis, treatment, or health examination.</para><para>(2) The bureau may require through rules and regulations that a prior entry permit be obtained for animals if the bureau deems such a permit necessary for the protection of the health of domestic animals in the state. If the bureau determines that a prior entry permit is required, the person importing or transporting the animals into the state shall obtain such a permit from the bureau.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 321, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 366, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 160, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 