<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id153">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id155" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="54-645"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>54-645</statuteno><catchline id="id158">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Dog and Cat Purchase Protection Act:</para>
<para>(1) Casual breeder means any person, other than a commercial dog or cat breeder as such terms are defined in
section 54-626, who offers for sale, sells, trades, or receives consideration
for one or more pet animals from a litter produced by a female dog or cat
owned by such casual breeder;</para>
<para>(2) Clinical symptom means indication of an illness or dysfunction
that is apparent to a veterinarian based on the veterinarian's observation,
examination, or testing of an animal or on a review of the animal's medical
records;</para>
<para>(3) Health certificate means the official small animal certificate
of veterinary inspection of the Bureau of Animal Industry of the Department
of Agriculture;</para>
<para>(4) Pet animal means a dog, wholly or in part of the species
Canis familiaris, or a cat, wholly or in part of the species Felis domesticus,
that is under fifteen months of age;</para>
<para>(5) Purchaser means the final owner of a pet animal purchased
from a seller. Purchaser does not include a person who purchases a pet animal
for resale;</para>
<para>(6) Seller means a casual breeder or any commercial establishment,
including a commercial dog
or cat breeder, dealer, or pet shop as such terms are defined
in section 54-626, that engages in a business of selling pet animals to a
purchaser. A seller does not include an animal control facility, animal rescue,
or animal shelter as defined in section 54-626 or any animal adoption activity
that an animal control facility, animal rescue, or animal shelter conducts
offsite at any pet store or other commercial establishment; and</para>
<para>(7)(a) Serious health problem means a congenital or hereditary
defect or contagious disease that causes severe illness or death of the pet
animal.</para>
<para>(b) Serious health problem does not include (i) parvovirus
if the diagnosis of parvovirus is made after the seven-business-day requirement
in subsection (1) of section 54-647 or (ii) any other contagious disease that
causes severe illness or death after ten calendar days after delivery of the
pet animal to the purchaser.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB241, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB910, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB427, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>