<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id944"><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,134"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,134</statuteno><catchline>Cattle moved from a registered dairy heifer development facility; brand inspection; required, when.</catchline><para>(1) Cattle that are sold or shipped from a registered dairy heifer development facility, for purposes other than entry into a qualified dairy, are subject to the brand inspection under sections 54-1,110 to 54-1,119, and the seller or shipper shall bear the cost of such inspection at the regular fee.</para><para>(2) Any cattle that are not described in subsection (1) of this section and that shipped from a registered dairy heifer development facility or qualified dairy are not subject to brand inspection at origin or destination, but the shipper shall have a shipping certificate from the registered dairy heifer development facility or qualified dairy. The shipping certificate form shall be prescribed by the brand committee and shall show the registered dairy heifer development facility or qualified dairy operator's name and registration number, date shipped, destination, agency receiving the cattle, number of head in the shipment, and sex of the cattle. The shipping certificate shall be completed in triplicate by the registered dairy heifer development facility or qualified dairy operator at the time of shipment. One copy thereof shall be delivered to the brand inspector at the market along with shipment, if applicable, one copy shall be sent to the brand committee by the tenth day of the following month, and one copy shall be retained by the registered dairy heifer development facility or qualified dairy operator. If a shipping certificate does not accompany a shipment of cattle from a registered dairy heifer development facility or qualified dairy to any destination where brand inspection is maintained by the brand committee, all such cattle shall be subject to a brand inspection and the inspection fees and surcharge provided under section 54-1,108 shall be charged for the service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1187, &#167; 20. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>