
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,113</statuteno><catchline>Sale, trade, use, or consumption of beef or veal; requirements; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Inside of the brand inspection area, no person shall sell or trade or offer for sale or trade the carcass of a beef or veal, or any portion thereof, including the hide of such carcass, unless a certificate of inspection is secured from a brand inspector. Such person shall exhibit the certificate of inspection upon the demand of any person.</para><para>(b) Outside of the brand inspection area, no person shall sell or offer for sale, except as a butcher bonded under section 54-1,114, the carcass of a beef or veal, or any portion thereof, without first exhibiting the intact hide of the same and exposing the brand upon the hide, if any, to the purchaser. A person selling or offering for sale any such carcass of beef or veal shall preserve the hide of the same for a period of fifteen days unless a certificate of inspection is secured from a brand inspector, and such person shall exhibit the certificate of inspection upon the demand of any person.</para><para>(2) No person shall kill for his, her, or its own use and consumption any cattle for beef or veal without preserving the hide of such animal intact with a complete unskinned tail attached thereto for a period of not less than fifteen days unless a certificate of inspection is secured from a brand inspector, and such hide shall be presented for inspection upon demand of any person.</para><para>(3) A violation of this section is an infraction. A peace officer shall have the authority to write a citation, which shall be waivable, to offenders in violation of this section. A fine under this section shall not exceed two hundred dollars per head for each offense. Violations shall be charged in the county in which the offense occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB572, &#167; 25. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>