<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id68" statutenumber="54-1,120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,120</statuteno><catchline id="id71">Registered feedlot; application; requirements; fees; inspections; records.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who operates a cattle feeding operation located within the brand inspection area may make application to the Nebraska Brand Committee for registration as a registered feedlot. The application form shall be prescribed by the brand committee and shall be made available by the executive director of the brand committee for this purpose upon written request. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. After the brand committee has received a properly completed application, an agent of the brand committee shall within thirty days make an investigation to determine if the following requirements are satisfied:</para><para>(a) The operator's feedlot must be permanently fenced; and</para><para>(b) The operator must commonly practice feeding cattle to finish for slaughter.</para><para>If the application is satisfactory, and upon payment of an initial registration fee by the applicant, the brand committee shall issue a registration number and registration certificate valid for one year unless rescinded for cause. If the registration is rescinded for cause, any registration fee shall be forfeited by the applicant. The initial fee for a registered feedlot shall be an amount for a registered feedlot having one thousand head or less capacity and an equal amount for each additional one thousand head capacity, or part thereof, of such registered feedlot. For each subsequent year, the renewal fee for a registered feedlot shall be an amount for the first one thousand head or portion thereof of average annual inventory of cattle on feed of the registered feedlot and an equal amount for each additional one thousand head or portion thereof of average annual inventory of cattle on feed of the registered feedlot. The brand committee shall set the fee per one thousand head capacity or average annual inventory so as to correspond with the inspection fee provided under section 54-1,108. The registration fee shall be paid on an annual basis.</para><para>(2) The brand committee may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the operation of registered feedlots to assure that brand laws are complied with, that registered feedlot shipping certificates are available, and that proper records are maintained. Violation of sections 54-1,120 to 54-1,122 subjects the operator to revocation or suspension of the feedlot registration issued. Sections 54-1,120 to 54-1,122 shall not be construed as prohibiting the operation of nonregistered feedlots.</para><para>(3) Registered feedlots are subject to inspection at any reasonable time at the discretion of the brand committee and its authorized agents, and the operator shall show cattle purchase records or certificates of inspection to cover all cattle in his or her feedlot. Cattle having originated from such registered feedlots may from time to time, at the discretion of the committee, be subject to a spot-check inspection and audit at destination to enable the brand committee to assure satisfactory compliance with the brand laws by the registered feedlot operator.</para><para>(4) The operator of a registered feedlot shall keep cattle inventory records. A form for such purpose shall be prescribed by the brand committee. The brand committee and its employees may from time to time make spot checks and audits of the registered feedlots and the records of cattle on feed in such feedlots.</para><para>(5) The brand committee may rescind the registration of any registered feedlot operator who fails to cooperate or violates the laws or rules and regulations of the brand committee covering registered feedlots.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB768, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB572, &#167; 29. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>