<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-631"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-631</statuteno><catchline>Licensee; duties; disciplinary actions.</catchline><para>(1) A licensee under the Commercial Dog and Cat Operator Inspection Act shall comply with the act, the rules and regulations, and any order of the director issued pursuant thereto. The licensee shall not interfere with the department in the performance of its duties.</para><para>(2) A licensee may be put on probation requiring such licensee to comply with the conditions set out in an order of probation issued by the director, may be ordered to cease and desist due to a failure to comply, or may be ordered to pay an administrative fine pursuant to section 54-633 after:</para><para>(a) The director determines the licensee has not complied with subsection (1) of this section;</para><para>(b) The licensee is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why an order should not be issued; and</para><para>(c) The director finds that issuing an order is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the licensee.</para><para>(3) A license may be suspended after:</para><para>(a) The director determines the licensee has not complied with subsection (1) of this section;</para><para>(b) The licensee is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the license should not be suspended; and</para><para>(c) The director finds that issuing an order suspending the license is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the licensee.</para><para>(4) A license may be immediately suspended and the director may order the operation of the licensee closed prior to hearing when:</para><para>(a) The director determines that there is a significant threat to the health or safety of the dogs or cats harbored or owned by the licensee; and</para><para>(b) The licensee receives written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the suspension should not be sustained. Within fifteen days after the suspension, the licensee may request in writing a date for a hearing, and the director shall consider the interests of the licensee when the director establishes the date and time of the hearing, except that no hearing shall be held sooner than is reasonable under the circumstances. When a licensee does not request a hearing date within the fifteen-day period, the director shall establish a hearing date and notify the licensee of the date and time of such hearing.</para><para>(5) A license may be revoked after:</para><para>(a) The director determines the licensee has committed serious, repeated, or multiple violations of any of the requirements of subsection (1) of this section;</para><para>(b) The licensee is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the license should not be revoked; and</para><para>(c) The director finds that issuing an order revoking the license is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the licensee.</para><para>(6) The operation of any licensee which has been suspended shall close and remain closed until the license is reinstated. Any operation for which the license has been revoked shall close and remain closed until a new license is issued.</para><para>(7) The director may terminate proceedings undertaken pursuant to this section at any time if the reasons for such proceedings no longer exist. A license which has been suspended may be reinstated, a person with a revoked license may be issued a new license, or a licensee may no longer be subject to an order of probation if the director determines the conditions which prompted the suspension, revocation, or probation no longer exist.</para><para>(8) Proceedings undertaken pursuant to this section shall not preclude the department from seeking other civil or criminal actions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 825, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB12, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>