<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,121"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,121</statuteno><catchline>Registered feedlot; cattle shipment;
requirements.</catchline><para>Cattle sold or shipped from a registered feedlot,
for purposes other than direct slaughter or sale on any terminal market, are
subject to the brand inspection under sections 54-1,110 to 54-1,119, and the
seller or shipper shall bear the cost of such inspection at the regular fee.</para>
<para>Any other cattle shipped from a registered feedlot are not subject to
brand inspection at origin or destination, but the shipper must have a shipping
certificate from the registered feedlot. The shipping certificate form shall
be prescribed by the Nebraska Brand Committee and shall show the registered
feedlot operator's name and registration number, date shipped, destination,
agency receiving the cattle, number of head in the shipment, and sex of the
cattle. The shipping certificate shall be completed in triplicate by the registered
feedlot operator at the time of shipment. One copy thereof shall be delivered
to the brand inspector at the market along with shipment, if applicable, one
copy shall be sent to the brand committee by the tenth day of the following
month, and one copy shall be retained by the registered feedlot operator.
If a shipping certificate does not accompany a shipment of cattle from a registered
feedlot to any destination where brand inspection is maintained by the brand
committee, all such cattle shall be subject to a brand inspection and the inspection fees and surcharge provided under section 54-1,108 shall
be charged for the service.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 213, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB181, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
