<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id678"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1,122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1,122</statuteno><catchline>Registered feedlot or backgrounding lot; brand inspection, when required; fees; backgrounding lots; guidelines.</catchline><para>(1) Cattle may be moved into a registered feedlot or a backgrounding lot without being subject to brand inspection if such cattle:</para><para>(a) Originate in a state, or a portion of a state, that has a brand inspection agency and are accompanied by satisfactory evidence of ownership;</para><para>(b) Originate in a state, or a portion of a state, that does not have brand inspection and are accompanied by satisfactory evidence of ownership;</para><para>(c) Originate from a backgrounding lot and are accompanied by satisfactory evidence of ownership; or</para><para>(d) Originate from a backgrounding lot and such cattle were subjected to brand inspection upon entering the originating backgrounding lot.</para><para>(2) Cattle that are moved into a registered feedlot or a backgrounding lot and that are not described in subsection (1) of this section shall be subject to physical inspection or electronic inspection within a reasonable time after arrival at the registered feedlot or backgrounding lot. The inspection fee and surcharge that is provided under section 54-1,108 shall be collected by the brand inspector at the time that the inspection is performed.</para><para>(3) The brand committee may issue guidelines for processes of and recordkeeping by backgrounding lots that may be used by backgrounding lots to prevent the commingling of cattle during transport to such backgrounding lots and to identify cattle that have become commingled during transport to such backgrounding lots.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB181, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB572, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB1187, &#167; 17. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Under this section, cattle that move from their point of origin to backgrounding lots and then later to registered feedlots do not avoid brand inspection. Adams Land &amp; Cattle v. Widdowson, 314 Neb. 358, 990 N.W.2d 542 (2023).</para><para>Under this section, if cattle move into registered feedlots from their points of origin with no other movement in between and are accompanied by paperwork that proves they have been so moved, they avoid brand inspection. Adams Land &amp; Cattle v. Widdowson, 314 Neb. 358, 990 N.W.2d 542 (2023).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>