<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1160"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1160</statuteno><catchline>Livestock Auction Market Board; creation; appointment of members; term; compensation; meetings; general powers.</catchline><para>There is hereby created in the Department of Agriculture a Livestock Auction Market Board consisting of three members. The board shall consist of the Director of Agriculture, the State Veterinarian, and a livestock auction market operator to be appointed by the Governor. The Director of Agriculture shall be chairperson of the board. The term of office of the appointed member shall be four years. The appointed member shall receive as compensation for his or her services the sum of fifty dollars per day or twenty-five dollars per half day and actual expenses incurred while in the discharge of his or her duties. The board shall meet for the ordinary transaction of official business and at the call of the director. A majority affirmative vote of the board shall be necessary to constitute an official act.</para><para>The board shall have power and duty to:</para><para>(1) Administer the Livestock Auction Market Act in respect to recommending the issuance, suspensions, and revocations of market licenses;</para><para>(2) Prescribe and adopt the forms of application for market licenses, the forms of notice of hearings on market license applications, and such other forms as necessary to perform and carry out its functions;</para><para>(3) Adopt and promulgate rules subject to the approval of the director governing the conduct of hearings before it for applications for market licenses, transfers, suspensions, and revocations consistent with the Livestock Auction Market Act and not contrary to the general laws of Nebraska governing hearings before administrative boards; and</para><para>(4) Administer section 54-1166 relating to terminations of market licenses and hearings regarding such terminations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 4, p. 963; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 97, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 