<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1371" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1371</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Brucellosis testing; owner responsibilities; violation; penalty; costs; administrative fee; Brucellosis Control Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever brucellosis testing is performed under section 54-1369 with respect to a sale at private treaty or under section 54-1370, the owner of the animals shall be responsible for gathering, confining, and restraining the animals to be tested and shall provide the necessary facilities and assistance. With respect to tests conducted at markets, concentration points, or slaughter establishments, the responsibility shall be borne by the owner of the establishment.</para><para>(2) Any person failing to carry out the responsibilities set out under subsection (1) of this section shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Whenever any person fails to carry out the responsibilities set out under subsection (1) of this section, the department shall perform such functions. Upon completion of the testing, the department shall determine its actual costs incurred in handling the livestock and conducting the testing and notify the responsible person in writing. The responsible person shall reimburse the department its actual costs within fifteen days following the date of the notice. Any person failing to reimburse the department as required shall be assessed an administrative fee of up to twenty-five percent of the amount due for each thirty days of delinquency. The purpose of the additional administrative fee is to cover the administrative costs associated with collecting the actual costs incurred and any administrative fees.</para><para>(4) All money received by the department under subsection (3) of this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Brucellosis Control Cash Fund, which fund is hereby created. Expenditures from the fund may be made to conduct brucellosis testing under the Nebraska Bovine Brucellosis Act. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 573, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB909, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>