<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id272">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id274" statutenumber="54-1180"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1180</statuteno><catchline id="id277">Inspection
of livestock; duties; fees; use; disposition; notice of change.</catchline>
<para>All cattle, calves, swine, sheep, and goats, upon entering
a livestock auction market, shall be inspected for health before being offered
for sale. Such inspection shall be made by a designated veterinarian. The
fees for such inspection shall be established by rules and regulations of
the department and shall be collected
by the operator of the livestock auction market. Such fees shall be used to
pay the fees of necessary inspections and for no other purpose and shall be
remitted as may be provided by regulation. The fees shall be remitted to the
State Treasurer for credit to the Livestock Auction Market Fund and shall
be expended exclusively to pay the fees of providing necessary inspections
at the livestock auction market which has remitted such fees. Each designated
veterinarian making market inspections shall be paid twenty-five dollars for
each regularly scheduled sale day in each calendar month as a guaranteed minimum
salary for providing adequate inspection services. If the fees collected each
calendar month by the market operator do not equal such amount, the market
operator shall make up the difference in his or her remittance to the state.
The rules and regulations establishing fees for such inspection shall not
be adopted, amended, or repealed until after notice by mail to each market
licensee and designated veterinarian of the time and place of hearing on the
question of adoption, amendment, or repeal of such rules and regulations;
such notice shall be mailed at least ten days prior to the date of hearing
and shall be sufficient if addressed to the last-known address of each market
licensee and designated veterinarian shown on the records of the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 24, p. 971; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 334, &#167; 5, p. 956; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 454, &#167; 1, p. 1543; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 30.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>