<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id106">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id108" statutenumber="54-1169"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1169</statuteno><catchline id="id111">Department; complaint; notice
of hearing; process; hearings; findings; suspension or revocation of license.</catchline><para>(1) The department may, upon its own motion, whenever
it has reason to believe the Livestock Auction Market Act has been
violated, or upon verified complaint of any person in writing, investigate
the actions of any market license holder, and if the
department finds probable cause to do so, shall file a complaint
against the market license holder which shall be set down for hearing before
the director and the State Veterinarian upon
fifteen days' notice served upon such market license holder either by personal
service upon him or her or by registered or certified mail or telegram prior
to such hearing.</para>
<para>(2) The
director shall have the power to administer oaths, certify to all official
acts, and subpoena any person in this state as a witness, to compel
the producing of books and papers, and to take the testimony of any person
on deposition in the same manner as is prescribed by law in the procedure
before the courts of this state in civil cases. Processes issued by the director
shall extend to all parts of the state and may be served by any person authorized
to serve processes. Each witness who shall appear by the order of the director
at any hearing shall
receive for such attendance the same fees allowed by law to witnesses in civil
cases appearing in the district court and mileage at the same rate provided
in section 81-1176, which amount shall be paid by the party at whose request
such witness is subpoenaed. When any witness has not been required to attend
at the request of any party, but has been subpoenaed by the director, his
or her fees and mileage shall be paid by the director in the same manner as
other expenses are
paid under the Livestock Auction
Market Act.</para>
<para>(3) All
powers of the director as provided in this section shall likewise be applicable
to hearings held on applications for the issuance of a market license.</para>
<para>(4) Formal
finding by the director and the State Veterinarian after
due hearing that any market license holder (a) has ceased
to conduct a livestock auction market business, (b) has been guilty of fraud or misrepresentation as to the titles,
charges, number, brands, weights, proceeds of sale, or ownership of livestock, (c) has violated any of the provisions of
the Livestock Auction Market Act, or (d) has
violated any of the rules or regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, shall be sufficient
cause for the suspension or revocation of the market license of the offending
livestock auction market operator.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 13, p. 966; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB78, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>