<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1181"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1181</statuteno><catchline>Veterinarians; agreement for services; contents; compensation; liability for torts, when.</catchline><para>The State Veterinarian shall make the designation of the veterinarians required by sections 54-1180 and 54-1182 by entering into an agreement with any accredited veterinarian for his or her professional services in performing necessary inspections. Such agreement shall provide that the State Veterinarian may terminate it at any time for what he or she deems to be just cause and shall further provide that the state pay such veterinarian a fee as established by section 54-1180, which amount shall be paid monthly from the Livestock Auction Market Fund. Such agreement shall make the designated veterinarian an agent for the Department of Agriculture to perform the duties assigned by sections 54-1180 and 54-1182, and the rules and regulations prescribed by the State Veterinarian, but shall not be deemed to make the designated veterinarian an officer or employee of the state. The orders of such designated veterinarian, issued in the performance of the duties assigned under sections 54-1180 and 54-1182 and the rules and regulations prescribed by the State Veterinarian, shall have the same force and effect as though such order had been made by the State Veterinarian. Designated veterinarians shall not be liable for reasonable acts performed to carry out the duties as set forth in sections 54-1180 and 54-1182 and the rules and regulations prescribed by the State Veterinarian pursuant to such sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 25, p. 971; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 334, &#167; 6, p. 957; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 454, &#167; 2, p. 1544; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 