<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1913" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1913</statuteno><catchline>Officer, inspector, employee of state; bribes, acceptances; interference; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any officer, inspector, or employee of this state authorized to perform any of the duties prescribed by the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law who shall accept any money, gift, or other thing of value from any person given with intent to influence his or her official action, or who shall receive or accept from any person engaged in intrastate commerce subject to the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law any gift, money, or other thing of value given with any purpose or intent whatsoever, shall be deemed guilty of a Class III misdemeanor and shall be summarily discharged from office.</para><para>(2) Any person who forcibly assaults, resists, opposes, impedes, intimidates, bribes or attempts to bribe, or interferes with any inspector or employee while engaged in or on account of the performance of his or her official duties under the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law, shall be deemed guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Any person who violates any provisions of the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law or any rules and regulations duly adopted and promulgated under such law, for which no other criminal penalty is provided by the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law, shall be deemed guilty of a Class II misdemeanor, but if such violation involves intent to defraud, or any distribution or attempted distribution of an article that is adulterated, such person shall be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 449, &#167; 13, p. 1518; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB324, &#167; 8. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>