<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id207">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id209" statutenumber="54-1159"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1159</statuteno><catchline id="id212">Exemptions from act.</catchline><para>(1) The Livestock Auction
Market Act shall not be construed to include:</para>
<para>(a) Any place or operation
where Future Farmers of America, 4-H groups, or private fairs conduct sales
of livestock;</para>
<para>(b) An animal
welfare organization as defined in section 54-2503;</para><para>(c) Any place or operation
conducted for a dispersal sale of the livestock of farmers, dairypersons,
or livestock breeders or feeders, where no other livestock is sold or offered
for sale; or</para>
<para>(d) Any place or operation
where a breeder or an association of breeders of livestock assemble and offer
for sale and sell under their own management any livestock, when such breeders
assume all responsibility of such sale and the title of livestock sold. This
shall apply to all purebred livestock association sales.</para>
<para>(2) An exotic
animal auction or exchange venue or an exotic animal auction or exchange venue
organizer as defined in section 54-7,105.01 is not required to be licensed
under the Livestock Auction Market Act if any bovine, camelid, caprine, ovine,
or porcine allowed to be sold under the Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange
Venue Act are accompanied by a certificate of veterinary inspection issued
by an accredited veterinarian and the exotic animal auction or exchange venue
organizer contracts for the services of an accredited veterinarian to issue
such certificates onsite during the auction or exchange venue for bovine,
camelid, caprine, ovine, or porcine present.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 3, p. 962; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 22.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Exotic Animal Auction or Exchange Venue Act,</emphasis> see section 54-7,105.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>