<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id190">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id192" statutenumber="54-1158"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1158</statuteno><catchline id="id195">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>As used in the Livestock Auction Market Act, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Accredited veterinarian has the same meaning as in section 54-701.03;</para>
<para>(2) Department means the Department of Agriculture;</para>
<para>(3) Designated veterinarian means an accredited veterinarian
who has been designated and authorized by the State Veterinarian to make inspections
of livestock at livestock auction markets as may be required by law or regulation
whether such livestock is moved in interstate or intrastate commerce;</para>
<para>(4) Director means the Director of Agriculture;</para>
<para>(5) Livestock means cattle, calves, swine, sheep, and goats;</para>
<para>(6) Livestock auction market means any place, establishment,
or facility commonly known as a livestock auction market, sales ring, or the
like, conducted or operated for compensation as an auction market for livestock,
consisting of pens or other enclosures, and their appurtenances, in which
livestock are received, held, sold, or kept for sale or shipment;</para>
<para>(7) Livestock auction market operator means any person engaged
in the business of conducting or operating a livestock auction market, whether
personally or through agents or employees;</para>
<para>(8) Market license means the license for a livestock auction
market authorized to be issued under the act;</para>
<para>(9) Person means any individual, firm, association, partnership,
limited liability company, or corporation; and</para>
<para>(10) State Veterinarian means the veterinarian in charge
of the Bureau of Animal Industry within the department or his or her designee,
subordinate to the director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 2, p. 962; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 340; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB78, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB884, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>