<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1705"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1705</statuteno><catchline>State Veterinarian; powers.</catchline><para>The State Veterinarian shall have the power to:</para><para>(1) Enter premises and buildings occupied by a licensee at any reasonable time to examine books and records maintained by the licensee;</para><para>(2) Require, by general or special order, livestock dealers to file with the State Veterinarian, in such forms as he may prescribe, regular or special reports or answers, in writing to specific questions, for the purpose of furnishing information concerning livestock movement and animal disease control. Such reports may be required to be made under oath and filed within a reasonable time;</para><para>(3) Defer the granting of a license as required by sections 54-1701 to 54-1711 or suspend or revoke any such license already issued if licensee has violated the laws or regulations of this state pertaining to disease control and eradication or has knowingly committed or participated in the violation of an order or quarantine or other disciplinary order issued by the department; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that before any license is suspended or revoked under this section, the licensee or applicant shall be furnished with a copy of the charges made against him and upon request of the licensee a hearing shall be had before the director or his designate; and</para><para>(4) Defer the granting of a license as required by sections 54-1701 to 54-1711 or suspend or revoke any such license already issued if the licensee has failed to pay the person or persons entitled thereto the purchase price of all livestock purchased for his own account or for the accounts of others; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that before any license is suspended or revoked under this section, the licensee or applicant shall be furnished with a copy of the charges made against him and upon request of the licensee a hearing shall be had before the director or his designate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 447, &#167; 5, p. 1495; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1361, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 