<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id180"><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1915.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1915.01</statuteno><catchline>Acquisition of meat from livestock by an informed end consumer; allowed; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) The acquisition of meat from livestock by an informed end consumer shall not constitute the sale of meat products in contravention of the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law and shall not be prohibited if all of the following conditions are met:</para><para>(a) The meat is made available pursuant to an animal share and is:</para><para>(i) Received by or on behalf of an owner of an animal share; and</para><para>(ii) Obtained from the particular livestock subject to the animal share;</para><para>(b) Ownership of the particular livestock is established by contract prior to slaughter;</para><para>(c) The name and address of each individual with an ownership interest in the particular livestock is presented to the processor prior to slaughter; and</para><para>(d) Information describing the standards used by the farm or ranch with respect to livestock health and in the processing of meat from the livestock is provided to the informed end consumer by the farmer or rancher.</para><para>(2) A farmer or rancher that sells an animal share shall:</para><para>(a) Be a resident of the State of Nebraska; and</para><para>(b) Maintain a record of each animal share sold under this section.</para><para>(3) No person who obtains meat in accordance with this section shall sell, donate, or commercially redistribute the meat in any way. No farmer or rancher shall publish any statement that implies the department's approval or endorsement of meat made available pursuant to an animal share. The requirement for a license under section 54-1904 or for inspection under the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law shall not apply to the sale of meat products pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB324, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>