<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1914"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1914</statuteno><catchline>Director of Agriculture; violations; investigations; powers; subpoenas.</catchline><para>The director shall have the following additional powers:</para><para>(1) Whenever he or she has reason to believe that any licensee may be in possession of information relevant to an investigation by him or her of suspected violations of the provisions of the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law or regulations promulgated thereunder, the director may require such person to file with him or her in such form as he or she may prescribe special reports or answers in writing to specific questions, furnishing such information. Such reports and answers shall be made under oath and shall be filed with the director within such reasonable period as the director may prescribe, unless additional time is granted in any case upon prompt application for same.</para><para>(2) To have access to all establishments, including any premises where a mobile or remote processing unit is located or utilized, for the purposes of examination or inspection or both at all times and the right to copy any documentary evidence of any person being investigated or proceeded against, and may require by subpoena the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of all documentary evidence of any person or the taking of a deposition relating to any matter under his or her investigation. The director may sign subpoenas and may administer oaths and affirmations, examine witnesses, and receive evidence in accordance with the provisions of section 54-1905. In case of disobedience to a subpoena, the director may invoke the aid of the district court of Lancaster County in requiring the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of documentary evidence. If any person fails to obey an order of the court, he or she may be punished by the court as for contempt thereof. Witnesses summoned or required to give depositions shall be paid the same fees that are paid witnesses in the district courts of this state and mileage at the same rate provided in section 81-1176 for state employees.</para><para>No person shall be excused from attending and testifying or from producing books, papers, schedules of charges, contracts, agreements, or other documentary evidence before the director or in obedience to the subpoena of the director, whether such subpoena be signed or issued by the director or his or her delegate, or in any cause or proceeding, criminal or otherwise, based upon or growing out of any alleged violation of the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law, or of any amendments thereto, on the ground or for the reason that the testimony or evidence, documentary or otherwise, required of him or her may tend to incriminate him or her or subject him or her to a penalty or forfeiture; but no individual shall be prosecuted or subjected to a penalty or forfeiture for or on account of any transaction, matter, or thing concerning which he or she is compelled, after having claimed his or her privilege against self-incrimination, to testify or produce evidence, documentary or otherwise, except that any individual so testifying shall not be exempt from prosecution and punishment for perjury committed in so testifying.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 449, &#167; 14, p. 1519; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 160, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 