<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1401</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined; exposed and infected flocks; requirements.</catchline><para>A scabies-free area shall be a county or group of counties in which a systematic inspection of all flocks of sheep including feed lots has been completed and no scabies is found to exist.</para><para>Scabies eradication area shall be a county or group of counties in which a systematic inspection of all flocks of sheep is being carried out but has not been completed.</para><para>Scabies quarantined area or premises shall be where scabies now exists or has existed and the required dipping procedures have not been completed.</para><para>All exposed flocks shall be quarantined and absolutely no animals removed from the premises until the flock has been dipped once in a permitted dip maintained at a required strength under the supervision of a state or federal inspector in accordance with the directions issued by the Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Animal Industry.</para><para>Exposed flocks shall mean flocks where no scabies exist but animals have been exposed to sheep affected with scabies.</para><para>All infected flocks shall be quarantined and absolutely no animals removed from the premises until the entire flock has been dipped twice ten to fourteen days apart in a permitted dip maintained at a required strength under the supervision of a state or federal inspector in accordance with the directions issued by the Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Animal Industry.</para><para>Infected flocks shall be flocks in which scabies exists or flocks to which animals have been added from a known infected source.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 327, &#167; 1, p. 937. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 