<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1169"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1169</statuteno><catchline>Livestock Auction Market Board; complaint; notice of hearing; process; hearings; findings; suspension or revocation of license.</catchline><para>The board may, upon its own motion, whenever it has reason to believe the provisions of the Livestock Auction Market Act have been violated, or upon verified complaint of any person in writing, investigate the actions of any market license holder, and if it finds probable cause to do so, shall file a complaint against the market license holder which shall be set down for hearing before the board upon fifteen days' notice served upon such market license holder either by personal service upon him or her or by registered or certified mail or telegram prior to such hearing.</para><para>The director shall have the power to administer oaths, certify to all official acts, and subpoena and bring before the board any person in this state as a witness, to compel the producing of books and papers, and to take the testimony of any person on deposition in the same manner as is prescribed by law in the procedure before the courts of this state in civil cases. Processes issued by the director shall extend to all parts of the state and may be served by any person authorized to serve processes. Each witness who shall appear by the order of the director at any hearing before the board shall receive for such attendance the same fees allowed by law to witnesses in civil cases appearing in the district court and mileage at the same rate provided in section 81-1176, which amount shall be paid by the party at whose request such witness is subpoenaed. When any witness has not been required to attend at the request of any party, but has been subpoenaed by the director, his or her fees and mileage shall be paid by the director in the same manner as other expenses of the board are paid.</para><para>All powers of the director as provided in this section shall likewise be applicable to hearings held on applications for the issuance of a market license.</para><para>Formal finding by the board after due hearing that any market license holder: (1) Has ceased to conduct a livestock auction market business; (2) has been guilty of fraud or misrepresentation as to the titles, charges, number, brands, weights, proceeds of sale, or ownership of livestock; (3) has violated any of the provisions of the Livestock Auction Market Act; or (4) has violated any of the rules or regulations adopted and published by the board, shall be sufficient cause for the suspension or revocation of the market license of the offending livestock auction market operator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 319, &#167; 13, p. 966; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 778, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 197, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 