<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1704" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1704</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Livestock dealer; license; application; bond; form; renewal; fee; disposition.</catchline><para>No person as defined in the Nebraska Livestock Dealer Licensing Act as a livestock dealer shall:</para><para>(1) Engage in the business of buying, selling, or otherwise dealing in livestock in this state without a valid and effective license issued by the Director of Agriculture under the provisions of this section. All applications for a livestock dealer license or renewal of such license shall be made on forms prescribed for that purpose by the State Veterinarian. The department may by rule and regulation prescribe additional information to be contained in such application. The application shall be filed annually with the department on or before October 1 of each year with the applicable fee of fifty dollars. The license fees collected as provided by the Nebraska Livestock Dealer Licensing Act shall be deposited in the state treasury, and by the State Treasurer placed in the Livestock Auction Market Fund. All money so collected shall be appropriated to the uses of the Department of Agriculture for the purpose of administering the provisions of the Nebraska Livestock Dealer Licensing Act;</para><para>(2)(a) Engage in the business of buying, selling, or otherwise dealing in livestock in this state without filing with the department, in connection with his or her application for a license, a fully executed duplicate of a valid and effective bond: (i) If he or she is registered and bonded under the provisions of the federal Packers and Stockyards Act of 1921, 7 U.S.C. 181 et seq., he or she shall file a statement in the form prescribed by the department evidencing that he or she is maintaining a valid and effective bond or its equivalent under such act; or (ii) if he or she is not registered and bonded under the provisions of the federal Packers and Stockyards Act, he or she shall furnish in connection with his or her application for a license a fully executed duplicate of a valid and effective bond in the amount of five thousand dollars or such larger amount as may be specified by regulations promulgated by the department. (b) The bond shall contain the following conditions: (i) That the principal shall pay when due to the person or persons entitled thereto the purchase price of all livestock purchased by such principal for his or her own account or for the accounts of others and such principal shall safely keep and properly disburse all funds, if any, which come into his or her hands for the purpose of paying for livestock purchased for the accounts of others; (ii) that any person damaged by failure of the principal to comply with the condition clause of the bond may maintain suit to recover on the bond; and (iii) that at least thirty days' notice in writing shall be given to the department by the party terminating the bond; or</para><para>(3) Continue in the business of a dealer after his or her license or bond has expired, or has been suspended or revoked.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 447, &#167; 4, p. 1494; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1361, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB909, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>