<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-1514"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-1514</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Hog Cholera Control and Eradication Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Hog cholera serum shall mean a serum which when injected into a susceptible hog will protect the animal for a variable time against hog cholera either from exposure to infected swine or from an injection of a minimum of two cubic centimeters of known virulent hog cholera virus;</para><para>(2) Virulent hog cholera virus shall mean a virus which when inoculated into a susceptible swine, in a minimum dose of two cubic centimeters, will cause hog cholera;</para><para>(3) Modified live hog cholera vaccine shall mean any vaccine prepared from a modified live hog cholera virus which will establish an immunity or resistance against hog cholera when the animal is exposed to infected swine or by injection of a minimum dose of two cubic centimeters of known virulent hog cholera virus;</para><para>(4) Killed or inactivated hog cholera virus shall mean any killed suspension of hog cholera virus which when inoculated into susceptible swine will not produce hog cholera;</para><para>(5) A virulent virus shall mean hog cholera virus which fails to cause hog cholera in swine, susceptible to such disease, when injected in doses of not more than two cubic centimeters;</para><para>(6) Impotent serum shall mean hog cholera serum which fails to protect swine against hog cholera when injected in doses as recommended on the label of the container, for the weight of swine indicated thereon, against a dose of virulent hog cholera virus of not less than two cubic centimeters;</para><para>(7) Person shall include individual, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, and association or any officer, partner, or member of same; and</para><para>(8) Director shall mean the Director of Agriculture.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 446, &#167; 2, p. 1490; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 342. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 