<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock"  statutenumber="54-2435"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2435</statuteno><catchline>Council; rules and regulations.</catchline>
<para>(1) The council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for
animal feeding operations under the Environmental Protection Act and the Livestock
Waste Management Act which provide for:</para>
<para>(a) Requirements for animal feeding operations which shall include:</para>
<para>(i) Location restrictions and setbacks to protect waters of the state;</para>
<para>(ii) Applications and inspection requests;</para>
<para>(iii) Identification of ownership;</para>
<para>(iv) Numbers, size, and types of animals;</para>
<para>(v) Type of waste control facility;</para>
<para>(vi) Design, construction, operation, and maintenance;</para>
<para>(vii) Monitoring of surface or ground water which may be necessary as
determined by the department where a significant risk to waters of the state
exists;</para>
<para>(viii) Nutrient management, a nutrient management plan to be submitted
with the application for a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System
permit or a construction and operating permit, and a description of the types
of changes made to the nutrient management plan required to be updated pursuant
to section 54-2426;</para>
<para>(ix) Closure and corrective action;</para>
<para>(x) Best management practices; and</para>
<para>(xi) Other such requirements deemed necessary to protect waters of the
state;</para>
<para>(b) A National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit process
for animal feeding operations;</para>
<para>(c) National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit issuance,
denial, renewal, revocation, suspension, reinstatement, termination,
or transfer;</para>
<para>(d) Training requirements for permitholders;</para>
<para>(e) Construction and operating permit issuance, denial, revocation, suspension, reinstatement, termination,
or transfer;</para>
<para>(f) Construction and operating permit and National Pollutant Discharge
Elimination System permit major modification issuance, denial, revocation, or termination;</para>
<para>(g) Public notice and hearing requirements;</para>
<para>(h) Requirements for existing livestock waste control facilities;</para>
<para>(i) Requirements for adequate area and proper methods and rates for
land application of waste and nutrients such as nitrogen and phosphorus;</para>
<para>(j) Requirements for record keeping and reporting;</para>
<para>(k) A fee schedule pursuant to sections 54-2423 and 54-2428;</para>
<para>(l) Procedures for collection of fees pursuant to this section and sections
54-2423 and 54-2428;</para>
<para>(m) Procedures for exemptions as provided for in the requirements of
the Environmental Protection Act and the Livestock Waste Management Act; and</para>
<para>(n) Procedures governing
proceedings to determine discharge violations under section 54-2431.</para>
<para>(2) Rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under this section
may be based upon the size of the animal feeding operation and the form of
waste management and may include more stringent requirements for larger animal
feeding operations and waste control technologies that are more likely to
cause adverse impacts.</para>
<para>(3) The council may adopt and promulgate any other rules and regulations
necessary to carry out the purposes of the Environmental Protection Act and
the Livestock Waste Management Act.</para>
<para>(4) Rules and regulations adopted pursuant to this section shall be
no less stringent than the federal Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. 1251 et seq.</para>
<para>(5) If a conflict arises between the authority of the council under
the Environmental Protection Act and the authority of the council under the
Livestock Waste Management Act, the authority of the council under the Livestock
Waste Management Act shall control.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1209, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 870, &#167; 14; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 54-2413; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 975, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB56, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Environmental Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1532.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>