<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2946" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2946</statuteno><catchline>Dead animal; proper disposal; what constitutes; effect; owner or custodian; duties; sheriff; powers and duties; suspicion of anthrax; owner or custodian; duties; acts prohibited; department powers.</catchline><para>(1) It is the duty of the owner or custodian of any dead animal to properly dispose of the animal within thirty-six hours after receiving knowledge of the animal's death unless a different timeframe is established in a herd or flock management plan or otherwise allowed by the State Veterinarian. Proper disposal of a dead animal is limited to:</para><para>(a) Burial on the premises where such animal died or on any adjacent property under the control of the animal's owner or custodian and coverage to a depth of at least four feet below the surface of the ground except as required in subsection (7) of this section;</para><para>(b) Complete incineration;</para><para>(c) Composting on the premises where such animal died or on an adjacent property under the ownership and control of the owner or custodian;</para><para>(d) Alkaline hydrolysis tissue digestion by a veterinary clinic or laboratory;</para><para>(e) Transportation by a licensed rendering establishment or other hauler approved by the State Veterinarian;</para><para>(f) Transportation to a veterinary clinic or laboratory for purposes of diagnostic testing; or</para><para>(g) Transportation with written permission of the State Veterinarian:</para><para>(i) To a rendering establishment licensed under the Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law;</para><para>(ii) To a compost site approved by the State Veterinarian;</para><para>(iii) To a facility with a permit to operate as a landfill under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act so long as the operator of the landfill agrees to accept the dead animal;</para><para>(iv) To any facility which lawfully disposes of dead animals;</para><para>(v) As specified in a herd or flock management plan; or</para><para>(vi) In the event of a disease, natural disaster, or other emergency event resulting in catastrophic livestock mortality or euthanization, to a location designated by a county or other local emergency management organization.</para><para>(2) A dead animal properly disposed of pursuant to this section is exempt from the requirements for disposal of solid waste under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act.</para><para>(3) Any vehicle used by the owner or custodian to transport a dead animal shall be constructed in such a manner that the contents are covered and will not fall, leak, or spill from the vehicle. Violation of this subsection is a traffic infraction as defined in section 60-672.</para><para>(4) It is hereby made the duty of the sheriff of each county to cause the proper disposal of the carcass of any animal or carcass part remaining unburied or otherwise disposed of after notice from the department that any such carcass has not been properly buried or disposed of in violation of this section. The sheriff may enter any premises where any such carcass is located for the purpose of carrying out this section and may cause each carcass to be properly buried or disposed of on such premises. The county board of commissioners or supervisors shall allow such sums for the services as it may deem reasonable, and such sums shall be paid to the persons rendering the services upon vouchers as other claims against the county are paid. The owner of such animal shall be liable to the county for the expense of such burial or disposal, to be recovered in a civil action, unless the owner pays such expenses within thirty days after notice and demand therefor.</para><para>(5) If anthrax is suspected in any animal death, the owner or custodian of the animal or herd shall be responsible to have samples submitted to an approved laboratory for confirmation.</para><para>(6) If an animal has or is suspected to have died of anthrax, it shall be unlawful to:</para><para>(a) Transport such animal or animal carcass, except as directed and approved by the department;</para><para>(b) Use the flesh or organs of such animal or animal carcass for food for livestock or human consumption; or</para><para>(c) Remove the skin or hide of such animal or animal carcass.</para><para>(7) The disposition of any anthrax-infected animal carcass shall be carried out under the direction of the department. It shall be the duty of the owner or custodian of an animal that has died of anthrax to bury or burn the carcass on the premises where the carcass is found, unless directed otherwise by the State Veterinarian. If such carcass is buried, no portion of the carcass shall be interred closer than six feet from the surface of the ground. The department may direct the owner or custodian of an infected herd to treat the herd and to clean and disinfect the premises in accordance with the herd plan.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB344, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB848, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Meat and Poultry Inspection Law,</emphasis> see section 54-1901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>