<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id949"><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2943"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2943</statuteno><catchline>Failure to carry out program disease activities; department powers and duties; costs; reimbursement; late fee; funds; expenditures authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any person fails to carry out program disease activities or other responsibilities required under the Animal Health and Disease Control Act, the department may perform such functions. Upon completion of any such required program disease activities, the department shall determine its actual administrative costs incurred in handling the affected animal, herd, or flock or affected premises and conducting necessary and related activities and notify the owner or custodian in writing. Such owner or custodian shall reimburse the department its actual administrative costs within thirty days following the date of the notice.</para><para>(2) Any person failing to reimburse the department shall be assessed a late fee of twenty-five percent of the amount due for each thirty days of delinquent nonpayment up to one hundred percent of the original amount. The purpose of the late fee is to cover administrative costs associated with collecting the amount overdue. All such payments assessed and collected pursuant to this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Animal Health and Disease Control Cash Fund.</para><para>(3) The department may provide funds from the Animal Health and Disease Control Cash Fund to or on behalf of herd owners for program disease activities or any portion thereof in connection with the implementation of the Animal Health and Disease Control Act if funds for such activities or any portion have been appropriated. The department may develop statewide priorities for the expenditure of state funds available for animal disease control and eradication program activities. If funds are not available, the owner of such animal shall continue the program at his or her own expense. A portion of such state funds may be used by the department to pay a portion of the costs of testing done by or for accredited veterinarians if such work is approved by the department.</para><para>(4) In administering program disease activities pursuant to this section, the department shall not pay for:</para><para>(a) Testing done for a change of ownership at private treaty or at concentration points;</para><para>(b) Costs of gathering, confining, and restraining animals subject to testing or costs of providing necessary facilities and assistance;</para><para>(c) Costs of testing to qualify or maintain herd accreditation, certification, validation, and monitored status; or</para><para>(d) Indemnity for any animal destroyed as a result of being affected with a program disease or other dangerous disease unless funding is specifically appropriated by the Legislature for such purpose.</para><para>(5) The department shall not be liable for actual or incidental costs incurred by any person due to departmental actions in enforcing this section, including any action for trespass or damages.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB344, &#167; 43. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>