<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2425" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2425</statuteno><catchline>National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) After an initial inspection has been conducted pursuant to section 54-2423 for each new application for a construction and operating permit or major modification submitted to the department, the department shall, within ten days, make a determination as to whether a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit is required for the proposed animal feeding operation. If an application has been submitted prior to an initial inspection being conducted pursuant to section 54-2423, such application shall be returned to the applicant without the department conducting any review of the application.</para><para>(2) If it is determined that a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit is required, the department shall contact the applicant to determine whether the applicant requests the department to delay review of the construction and operating permit or major modification application until an individual National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit application is submitted.</para><para>(3) If the applicant requests the department to delay review of the construction and operating permit or major modification application, upon receipt of the individual National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit application and the construction and operating permit or major modification application, the applications shall be reviewed simultaneously utilizing the processes and timelines for review of an individual National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit application.</para><para>(4) If (a) the department determines a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit is not required or (b) if the applicant requests the department to proceed with review of the construction and operating permit or major modification application independent of a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit application, the department shall, for both subdivisions (4)(a) and (4)(b) of this section:</para><para>(i) Within five days send a copy of the application to the natural resources district or districts and the county board or boards of the counties in which the livestock waste control facility is located or proposed to be located. The natural resources district or districts and the county board or boards shall have thirty days to comment to the department regarding any conditions that may exist at the proposed site which the department should consider regarding the content of the application for a construction and operating permit or major modification;</para><para>(ii) Within sixty days, (A) issue a proposed decision on the application for a construction and operating permit or major modification and (B) issue a notice providing an opportunity for any interested person to submit written comments on such proposed decision within thirty days after the first day of publication of such notice. The notice shall be published in a daily or weekly newspaper or other publication with general circulation in the area of the existing or proposed animal feeding operation, and a copy of the notice shall be provided to the applicant; and</para><para>(iii) Within one hundred ten days approve or deny the application and transmit its findings and conclusions to the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 975, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>