<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2432" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2432</statuteno><catchline>Acts prohibited.</catchline><para>Except as provided in section 54-2422, it shall be unlawful for any person to:</para><para>(1) Construct or operate an animal feeding operation prior to an inspection from the department, unless exempted from inspection by the Environmental Protection Act, the Livestock Waste Management Act, or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to such acts;</para><para>(2) Construct a livestock waste control facility without first obtaining a construction and operating permit from the department, unless exempted from the requirement for a construction and operating permit by the Environmental Protection Act, the Livestock Waste Management Act, or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to such acts. The use of a borrow site for construction of other components of the animal feeding operation does not constitute construction of the livestock waste control facility;</para><para>(3) Operate an animal feeding operation prior to construction of an approved livestock waste control facility, unless exempted from the requirement for a livestock waste control facility by the Environmental Protection Act, the Livestock Waste Management Act, or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to such acts;</para><para>(4) Discharge animal excreta, feed, bedding, spillage or overflow from the watering systems, wash and flushing waters, sprinkling water from livestock cooling, precipitation polluted by falling on or flowing onto an animal feeding operation, or other materials polluted by livestock waste in violation of or without first obtaining a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit, a construction and operating permit, or an exemption from the department, if required by the Environmental Protection Act, the Livestock Waste Management Act, or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to such acts; or</para><para>(5) Violate the terms of a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit or construction and operating permit or any provision of the Livestock Waste Management Act and rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 975, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Environmental Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1532.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>By enacting legislation that made it unlawful to discharge livestock waste without obtaining the appropriate permits or an exemption, the Legislature acknowledged that livestock waste is a potentially harmful substance that must be handled properly. Butler County Dairy v. Butler County, 285 Neb. 408, 827 N.W.2d 267 (2013).</para><para>By enacting legislation that made it unlawful to operate an animal feeding operation without having an approved livestock waste control facility, the Legislature acknowledged that livestock waste is a potentially harmful substance that must be handled properly. Butler County Dairy v. Butler County, 285 Neb. 408, 827 N.W.2d 267 (2013).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>