  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2311"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2311</statuteno><catchline>Notice or order; service; hearing; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Any notice or order under the Domesticated Cervine Animal Act shall be personally served on the permitholder or on the person authorized by the permitholder to receive notices and orders of the department or shall be sent by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the last-known address of the permitholder or the person authorized to receive such notices and orders. A copy of the notice and the order shall be filed in the records of the department.</para><para>(2) A notice to comply under section 54-2310 shall state the acts or omissions with which the permitholder is charged.</para><para>(3) A notice of the permitholder's right to a hearing under section 54-2310 shall state the time and place of the hearing except as provided in subsection (4) of section 54-2310 and shall include notice that the permitholder's right to a hearing may be waived pursuant to subsection (5) of this section. A notice of the permitholder's right to a hearing to show cause why the permit should not be revoked shall include notice to the permitholder that the permit may be revoked or suspended, that the permitholder may be subject to an order of probation, and that the permit may be suspended and the permitholder subject to an order of probation, if the director determines such action is appropriate. A notice of the permitholder's right to a hearing to show cause why the permit should not be suspended shall include notice to the permitholder that the permit may be suspended and that the permitholder may also be subject to an order of probation if the director determines such action is appropriate.</para><para>(4) The hearings provided for in the act shall be conducted by the director at the time and place the director designates. The director shall make a final finding based upon the complete hearing record and issue an order. If the director has suspended a permit pursuant to subsection (4) of section 54-2310, the director shall sustain, modify, or rescind the order. All hearings shall be in compliance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(5) A permitholder is deemed to waive the right to a hearing if such permitholder does not come to the hearing at the time and place set forth in the notice described in subsection (3) of this section without requesting the director at least two days before the designated time to change the time and place for the hearing, except that before an order of the director becomes final, the director may designate a different time and place for the hearing if the permitholder makes a showing to the director that the permitholder had a justifiable reason for not coming to the hearing and not timely requesting a change in the time and place for such hearing. If the permitholder waives the right to a hearing, the director shall make a final finding based upon available information and issue an order. If the director has suspended a permit pursuant to subsection (4) of section 54-2310, the director shall sustain, modify, or rescind the order.</para><para>(6) Any person aggrieved by the finding of the director has ten days from the entry of the director's order to request a new hearing if such person can show a mistake of fact has been made which affected the director's determination. Any order of the director becomes final upon the expiration of ten days after its entry if no request for a new hearing is made.</para><para>(7) Any person aggrieved by any order entered by the director or any other action taken by the department may appeal the order or action, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 404, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 