<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2310"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2310</statuteno><catchline>Permitholder; duties; probation; suspension; revocation; procedure; reinstatement.</catchline><para>(1) A permitholder under the Domesticated Cervine Animal Act shall comply with the act, the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto, and any order of the director issued pursuant thereto. The permitholder shall not interfere with the department in the performance of its duties.</para><para>(2) A permitholder may be put on probation requiring such person to comply with the conditions set out in an order of probation issued by the director after: (a) The director determines the permitholder has not complied with subsection (1) of this section; (b) the permitholder is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing and to show cause why an order of probation should not be issued; and (c) the director finds that issuing an order of probation is appropriate, based on the hearing record or on the available information, if the hearing is waived by the permitholder.</para><para>(3) A permit may be suspended after: (a) The director determines the permitholder has not complied with subsection (1) of this section; (b) the permitholder is given written notice to comply and written notice of a right to a hearing to show cause why the permit should not be suspended; and (c) the director finds that issuing an order suspending the permit is appropriate, based on the hearing record or on the available information, if the hearing is waived by the permitholder.</para><para>(4) A permit may be immediately suspended and the director may order the permitholder's facility closed prior to hearing when: (a) The director determines an immediate danger to the health of livestock exists due to infectious, contagious, transmissible diseases in or caused by the permitholder's facility; (b) the director determines that an immediate danger to the health of wildlife exists due to infectious, contagious, transmissible diseases in or caused by the permitholder's facility; and (c) the permitholder receives the written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the suspension should not be sustained. Within fifteen days after the suspension, the permitholder may request, in writing, a date for a hearing and the director shall consider the interests of the permitholder when the department establishes the date and time of the hearing, except that no hearing shall be held earlier than is reasonable under the circumstances. When a permitholder does not request a hearing date within such fifteen-day period, the director shall establish a hearing date and shall notify the permitholder of the date and time of such hearing.</para><para>(5) A permit may be revoked after: (a) The director determines the permitholder has committed serious, repeated, or multiple violations of any of the requirements of subsection (1) of this section; (b) the permitholder is given written notice to comply and written notice of the right to a hearing to show cause why the permit should not be revoked; and (c) the director finds that issuing an order revoking the permit is appropriate based on the hearing record or on the available record or on the available information if the hearing is waived by the permitholder.</para><para>(6) Any domesticated cervine animal facility for which a permit has been suspended may possess, while correcting the violation, but may not buy, sell, or barter animals, or parts thereof, until the permit is reinstated. Any domesticated cervine animal facility for which a permit has been revoked shall be permitted to dispose of all animals on its premises, with approval of the department, within thirty days after the issuance of the order of revocation and shall close and remain closed until a new permit is issued.</para><para>(7) The director may terminate proceedings to suspend or revoke a permit or to subject a permitholder to an order of probation at any time if the reasons for such proceedings no longer exist. A permit which has been suspended may be reinstated. A person with a revoked permit may be issued a new permit. A permitholder may no longer be subject to an order of probation if the director determines the conditions which prompted the suspension, revocation, or probation no longer exist.</para><para>(8) Proceedings for suspension, revocation, or probation shall not preclude the department from pursuing other civil or criminal actions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 404, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 