<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Livestock" id="id00"  statutenumber="54-2627.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2627.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Preemption by federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999; legislative findings; purpose of act; director; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Sections 54-2607 to 54-2627 are preempted by the federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999, 7 U.S.C. 1635 to 1636h, when such federal act is in effect.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds that the mandatory reporting of price and other terms in negotiated or contract procurement of livestock that has been in place under the federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999 is an important reform of livestock markets that contributes to greater market transparency, enhances the ability of livestock sellers to more competently and confidently market livestock, and lessens the existence of conditions under which market price manipulation and unfair preference or advantage in packer procurement practices can occur. It is a purpose of the Competitive Livestock Markets Act to provide for the continuation of mandatory price reporting for the benefit of Nebraska producers and protection of the integrity of livestock markets in Nebraska in the event of termination of the federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999 and its preemption of similar state price reporting laws as well as to provide for an orderly implementation of the state price reporting system authorized by the Competitive Livestock Markets Act, should Congress fail to reauthorize the federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999.</para><para>(3)(a) If Congress does not reauthorize the federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999 before December 1, 2006, the director shall, on December 1, 2006, or as soon before or after as practicable, prepare a budget and an appropriation request from the General Fund, from the Competitive Livestock Markets Cash Fund, or from other cash funds under the control of the director, for submission to the Legislature in an amount sufficient to enable the department to carry out its duties under sections 54-2607 to 54-2627, and such sections shall become applicable on October 1, 2007.</para><para>(b) If, on or after December 1, 2006, Congress does not reauthorize the federal Livestock Mandatory Reporting Act of 1999, the director shall prepare such budget and appropriation request on or before a date that is twelve calendar months after the date such federal act expires or is terminated, and sections 54-2607 to 54-2627 shall become applicable on the first day of the calendar quarter that is eighteen months after the date such sections are not preempted by the federal act. No General Funds shall be appropriated for implementation of sections 54-2607 to 54-2627 after the date of commencement provided for in this section of reporting of price and other data regarding livestock transactions pursuant to sections 54-2613 and 54-2623. It is the intent of the Legislature that any General Funds appropriated for purposes of this section shall be reimbursed to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 856, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB176, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>