<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2437" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2437</statuteno><catchline>Conditional use permit or special exception; county planning commission or county board; powers.</catchline><para>(1) A county planning commission or county board shall grant a conditional use permit or special exception to an existing animal feeding operation seeking to construct or modify a livestock waste control facility if the purpose is to comply with federal or state regulations pertaining to livestock waste management, the operation has complied with inspection requirements pursuant to section 54-2423, and the construction or modification of the livestock waste control facility will not increase the animal capacity of such operation. The number of conditional use permits or special exceptions granted to such an operation under this subsection is unlimited.</para><para>(2) A county planning commission or county board shall grant a conditional use permit or special exception to an existing beef cattle or dairy cattle animal feeding operation that has an animal capacity of five thousand or fewer beef cattle or three thousand five hundred or fewer dairy cattle that is seeking to construct or modify a livestock waste control facility if the purpose is to comply with federal or state regulations pertaining to livestock waste management, the operation has complied with inspection requirements pursuant to section 54-2423, and construction or modification of the livestock waste control facility would allow the animal capacity of the operation to increase not more than:</para><para>(a) Five hundred beef cattle if the operation has an existing animal capacity of three thousand beef cattle or fewer;</para><para>(b) Three hundred beef cattle if the operation has an existing animal capacity of more than three thousand beef cattle but no more than five thousand beef cattle;</para><para>(c) Three hundred fifty dairy cattle if the operation has an existing animal capacity of two thousand dairy cattle or fewer; or</para><para>(d) Two hundred ten dairy cattle if the operation has an existing animal capacity of more than two thousand dairy cattle but no more than three thousand five hundred dairy cattle.</para><para>Only one conditional use permit or special exception per operation is allowed under this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 975, &#167; 17.</para></source></law></legaldoc>