<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Livestock" statutenumber="54-2296"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>54-2296</statuteno><catchline>Testing; duties of owner; costs.</catchline><para>(1) When testing is to be performed pursuant to the Pseudorabies Control and Eradication Act, the owner of the swine shall be responsible for gathering, confining, and restraining such swine for testing and for providing the necessary facilities and assistance.</para><para>(2) The department may provide state funds for certain activities or any portion thereof in connection with the implementation of the act to or on behalf of swine herd owners if funds for such activities or any portion thereof have been appropriated and are available. The department shall develop statewide priorities for the expenditure of state funds available for program activities.</para><para>(3) Part of such state funds may be used by the department to pay a portion of the cost of testing done by or for accredited veterinarians if such work is approved by the department. All of such testing shall be performed by or under the direct supervision of the accredited veterinarian, except that nothing in this subsection shall restrict an employee of the state or federal government in the performance of such employee's duties under the act or federal law.</para><para>(4) In administering the act and programs pursuant thereto, the department shall not pay for (a) testing done for change of ownership at private treaty or at concentration points, (b) costs of gathering, confining, and restraining swine subjected to testing or costs of providing necessary facilities and assistance, and (c) the cost of testing to qualify or maintain a status swine herd.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 359, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 965, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 158, &#167; 70. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 