<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" id="id00" statutenumber="39-220"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>39-220</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Control of advertising visible from main-traveled way; permit; rules and regulations.</catchline><para id="id00">The Department of Transportation may at its discretion require permits for advertising signs, displays, or devices which are placed or allowed to exist along or upon the Highway Beautification Control System or which are at any point visible from the main-traveled way of the Highway Beautification Control System, except for on-premise signs, displays, and devices, as defined in the department's rules and regulations, for advertising activities conducted on the property on which the sign, display, or device is located. Such permits shall be renewed biennially. Each sign shall bear on the side facing the highway the permit number in a readily observable place for inspection purposes from the highway right-of-way. The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to implement and administer sections 39-212 to 39-226. The department may revoke the permit for noncompliance reasons and remove the sign if, after thirty days' notification to the sign owner, the sign remains in noncompliance. Printed sale bills not exceeding two hundred sixteen square inches in size shall not require a permit if otherwise conforming.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1181, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 490, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 213, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 39-1320.09; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB472, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>An injunction may properly be entered to require compliance with the statute making it unlawful to erect or maintain advertising signs along highways prior to determination of whether there is a right to damages resulting from application of the statute. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para><para>Sections 39-1320 to 39-1320.11 constitute a reasonable and valid exercise of the police power which bears a substantial relation to the public health, safety, and general welfare, and are constitutional. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>