<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-891"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-891</statuteno><catchline>Interstate bridges; declaration of purpose.</catchline><para>Recognizing that obstructions on or near the boundary of the State of Nebraska impede commerce and travel between the State of Nebraska and adjoining states, the Legislature hereby declares that bridges over these obstructions are essential to the general welfare of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>Providing bridges over these obstructions and for the safe and efficient operation of such bridges is deemed an urgent problem that is the proper concern of legislative action.</para><para>Such bridges, properly planned, designated, and managed, provide a safe passage for highway traffic to and from the state highway system and encourage commerce and travel between the State of Nebraska and adjoining states which increase the social and economic progress and general welfare of the state.</para><para>It is recognized that bridges between the State of Nebraska and adjoining states are not and cannot be the sole concern of the State of Nebraska. The nature of such bridges requires that a high degree of cooperation be exercised between the State of Nebraska and adjoining states in all phases of planning, construction, maintenance, and operation if proper benefits are to be realized.</para><para>It is also recognized that parties other than the State of Nebraska may wish to erect and control bridges between the State of Nebraska and adjoining states and that the construction, operation, and financing of such bridges have previously been authorized by the Legislature. Such bridges also benefit the State of Nebraska, and it is not the intent of the Legislature to abolish such power previously granted.</para><para>To this end, it is the intention of the Legislature to supplement sections 39-1301 to 39-1362, relating to state highways, in order that the powers and authority of the department relating to the planning, construction, maintenance, acquisition, and operation of interstate bridges upon the state highway system may be clarified within a single act.</para><para>Acting under the direction of the Director-State Engineer, the department, with the advice of the State Highway Commission and the consent of the Governor, is given the power to enter into agreements with the United States and adjoining states, subject to the limitations imposed by the Constitution and the provisions of the Interstate Bridge Act of 1959.</para><para>The Legislature intends to place a high degree of trust in the hands of those officials whose duty it may be to enter into agreements with adjoining states and the United States for the planning, development, construction, acquisition, operation, maintenance, and protection of interstate bridges.</para><para>In order that the persons concerned may understand the limitations and responsibilities for planning, constructing, acquiring, operating, and maintaining interstate bridges upon the state highway system, it is necessary that the responsibilities for such work shall be fixed, but it is intended that the department, acting under the Director-State Engineer, shall have sufficient freedom to enter into agreements with adjoining states regarding any phase of planning, constructing, acquiring, maintaining, and operating interstate bridges upon the state highway system in order that the best interests of the State of Nebraska may always be served. The authority of the department to enter into agreements with adjoining states, as granted in the act, is therefor essential.</para><para>The Legislature hereby determines and declares that the provisions of the act are necessary for the preservation of the public peace, health, and safety, for the promotion of the general welfare, and as a contribution to the national defense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 175, &#167; 1, p. 630; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 15, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>