<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-212" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>39-212</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Acquisition of interest in property; control of advertising outside of right-of-way; compensation; removal; costs; payment by department.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The Department of Transportation may acquire the interest in real or personal property necessary to exercise the power authorized by subdivision (2)(m) of section 39-1320 and to pay just compensation upon removal of the following outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices, as well as just compensation for the disconnection and removal of electrical service to the same:</para><para id="id00">(a) Those lawfully erected or in existence prior to March 27, 1972, and not conforming to the provisions of sections 39-212 to 39-222 except as otherwise authorized by such sections; and</para><para id="id00">(b) Those lawfully erected after March 27, 1972, which become nonconforming after being erected.</para><para id="id00">(2) Such compensation for removal of such signs, displays, and devices is authorized to be paid only for the following:</para><para id="id00">(a) The taking from the owner of such sign, display, or device or of all right, title, leasehold, and interest in connection with such sign, display, or device, or both; and</para><para id="id00">(b) The taking from the owner of the real property on which the sign, display, or device is located of the right to erect and maintain such signs, displays, and devices thereon.</para><para id="id00">(3) In all instances where signs, displays, or devices which are served electrically are taken under subdivision (2)(a) of this section, the department shall pay just compensation to the supplier of electricity for supportable costs of disconnection and removal of such service to the nearest distribution line or, in the event such sign, display, or device is relocated, just compensation for removal of such service to the point of relocation.</para><para id="id00">Except for expenditures for the removal of nonconforming signs erected between April 16, 1982, and May 27, 1983, the department shall not be required to expend any funds under sections 39-212 to 39-222 and 39-1320 unless and until federal-aid matching funds are made available for this purpose.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 195, &#167; 2, p. 596; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1181, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 490, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 545, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 120, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 848, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1994, &#167; 39-1320.01; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 94. </para></source><annotation><para>An injunction may properly be entered to require compliance with the statute making it unlawful to erect or maintain advertising signs along highways prior to determination of whether there is a right to damages resulting from application of the statute. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para><para>Sections 39-1320 to 39-1320.11 constitute a reasonable and valid exercise of the police power which bears a substantial relation to the public health, safety, and general welfare, and are constitutional. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para><para>Control of advertising within six hundred sixty feet of edge of right-of-way may be acquired by eminent domain. State v. Day, 181 Neb. 308, 147 N.W.2d 919 (1967).</para><para>Right to control advertising outside of right-of-way of highway may be acquired by eminent domain. Fulmer v. State, 178 Neb. 20, 131 N.W.2d 657 (1964). (Opinion withdrawn, 178 Neb. 664, 134 N.W.2d 798 (1965).)</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>