<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-220" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>39-220</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Control of advertising visible from main-traveled way; permit; fee; rules and regulations; exceptions.</catchline><para id="id00">The Department of Transportation may at its discretion require permits for advertising signs, displays, or devices which are placed or allowed to exist along or upon any interstate or primary highway or at any point visible from the main-traveled way, except for signs located within an area of fifty feet of any commercial or industrial building on the premises. Such permits shall be renewed biennially. Each sign shall bear on the side facing the highway the permit number in a readily observable place for inspection purposes from the highway right-of-way. The department is authorized to charge a fee to be not less than twenty-five cents or not to exceed fifteen dollars for each permit and renewal permit for each individual sign. The department shall promulgate rules and regulations establishing, and from time to time adjusting, the annual fees for the permits to cover the costs of administering sections 39-212 to 39-226 and may by rule and regulation provide exceptions from the payment of fees for signs advertising eleemosynary or nonprofit public service activities, signs designating historical sites, and farm and ranch directional signs. The department may revoke the permit for noncompliance reasons and remove the sign if, after thirty days' notification to the sign owner, the sign remains in noncompliance. Printed sale bills not exceeding two hundred sixteen square inches in size shall not require a permit if otherwise conforming.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1181, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 490, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 213, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 39-1320.09; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 101. </para></source><annotation><para>An injunction may properly be entered to require compliance with the statute making it unlawful to erect or maintain advertising signs along highways prior to determination of whether there is a right to damages resulting from application of the statute. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para><para>Sections 39-1320 to 39-1320.11 constitute a reasonable and valid exercise of the police power which bears a substantial relation to the public health, safety, and general welfare, and are constitutional. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>