<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" id="id53" statutenumber="39-210"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>39-210</statuteno><catchline id="id56">Sign panels; qualification of activities; minimum requirements; violation; effect.</catchline><para>To qualify to appear on a tourist-oriented directional sign panel, an activity shall be licensed and approved by the state and local agencies if required by law and be open to the public at least eight hours per day, five days per week, including Saturdays or Sundays, during the normal season of the activity, except that if the activity is a winery, the winery shall be open at least twenty hours per week. The activity, before qualifying to appear on a sign panel, shall provide to the Department of Transportation assurance of its conformity with all applicable laws relating to discrimination based on race, creed, color, sex, national origin, ancestry, political affiliation, or religion. If the activity violates any of such laws, it shall lose its eligibility to appear on a tourist-oriented directional sign panel. In addition, the qualifying activity shall be required to remove any advertising device which was unlawfully erected or which is in violation of section 39-202, 39-203, 39-204, 39-205, 39-206, 39-215, 39-216, or 39-220, any rule or regulation of the department, or any federal rule or regulation relating to tourist-oriented directional sign panels. The tourist-oriented directional sign panels shall conform to the requirements of the Federal Beautification Act and the Manual on Uniform Traffic Control Devices as adopted pursuant to section 60-6,118.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 108, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB926, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 92. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>