<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways and Bridges" id="id6" statutenumber="39-204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">39-204</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Informational signs;
erection; conform with rules and regulations; minimum service requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Signs, displays, and devices giving specific information
of interest to the traveling public shall be erected by or at the direction
of the Department of Roads and maintained within the right-of-way at appropriate
distances from interchanges on the National System of Interstate and Defense
Highways and from roads of the state primary system as shall conform with
the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department to carry
out this section and section 39-205. Such rules and regulations shall be consistent
with national standards promulgated from time to time by the appropriate authority
of the federal government pursuant to 23 U.S.C. 131(f).</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section, specific information of
interest to the traveling public shall mean only information about camping,
lodging, food, attractions, and
motor fuel and associated services, including trade names.</para>
<para>(3) The minimum service that is required to be available for
each type of service shall include:</para>
<para>(a) Motor fuel services including:</para>
<para>(i) Vehicle services, which shall include fuel, oil, and water;</para>
<para>(ii) Restroom facilities and drinking water;</para>
<para>(iii) Continuous operation of such services for at least sixteen
hours per day, seven days per week, for freeways and expressways and continuous
operation of such services for at least twelve hours per day, seven days per
week, for conventional roads; and</para>
<para>(iv) Telephone services;</para>
<para>(b) Attraction
services including:</para><para>(i) An attraction of regional significance with the primary purpose
of providing amusement, historical, cultural, or leisure activity to the public;</para>
<para>(ii) Restroom
facilities and drinking water; and</para><para>(iii) Adequate parking accommodations;</para>
<para>(c) Food services including:</para>
<para>(i) Licensing or approval of such services, when required;</para>
<para>(ii) Continuous operation of such services to serve at least two meals per day, six days
per week;</para>
<para>(iii) Modern
sanitary facilities; and</para><para>(iv) Telephone
services;</para>
<para>(d) Lodging services including:</para>
<para>(i) Licensing or approval of such services, when required;</para>
<para>(ii) Adequate sleeping accommodations; and</para>
<para>(iii) Telephone services; and</para>
<para>(e) Camping services including:</para>
<para>(i) Licensing or approval of such services, when required;</para>
<para>(ii) Adequate parking accommodations; and</para>
<para>(iii) Modern sanitary facilities and drinking water.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 213, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 741, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-634.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB926, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>