<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-892" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>39-892</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Interstate bridges; terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">For purposes of the Interstate Bridge Act of 1959, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para id="id00">(1) Approach shall mean that portion of any interstate bridge which allows the highway access to the bridge structure. It shall be measured along the centerline of the highway from the end of the bridge structure to the nearest right-of-way line of the closest street or road where traffic may leave the highway to avoid crossing the bridge, but in no event shall such approach exceed a distance of one mile. The term shall be construed to include all embankments, fills, grades, supports, drainage facilities, and appurtenances necessary therefor;</para><para id="id00">(2) Appurtenances shall include, but not be limited to, sidewalks, storm sewers, guardrails, handrails, steps, curb or grate inlets, fire plugs, retaining walls, lighting fixtures, and all other items of a similar nature which the department deems necessary for the proper operation of any interstate bridge or for the safety and convenience of the traveling public;</para><para id="id00">(3) Boundary line bridge shall mean any bridge upon which no toll, fee, or other consideration is charged for passage thereon and which connects the state highway systems of the State of Nebraska and an adjoining state in the same manner as an interstate bridge. Such bridges shall be composed of right-of-way, bridge structure, approaches, and road in the same manner as an interstate bridge but shall be distinguished from an interstate bridge in that no part of such bridge shall be a part of the state highway system, the title to such bridge being vested in a person other than the State of Nebraska, or the State of Nebraska and an adjoining state jointly. Any boundary line bridge purchased or acquired by the department, or the department and an adjoining state jointly, and added to the state highway system shall be deemed an interstate bridge;</para><para id="id00">(4) Boundary line toll bridge shall mean any boundary line bridge upon which a fee, toll, or other consideration is charged traffic for the use thereof. Any boundary line toll bridge purchased or acquired by the department, or by the department and an adjoining state jointly, and added to the state highway system shall be deemed an interstate bridge;</para><para id="id00">(5) Bridge structure shall mean the superstructure and substructure of any interstate bridge having a span of not less than twenty feet between undercopings of extreme end abutments, or extreme ends of openings of multiple boxes, when measured along the centerline of the highway thereon, and shall be construed to include the supports therefor and all appurtenances deemed necessary by the department;</para><para id="id00">(6) Construction shall mean the erection, fabrication, or alteration of the whole or any part of any interstate bridge. For purposes of this subdivision, alteration shall be construed to be the performance of construction by which the form or design of any interstate bridge is changed or modified;</para><para id="id00">(7) Department shall mean the Department of Transportation;</para><para id="id00">(8) Emergency shall include, but not be limited to, acts of God, invasion, enemy attack, war, flood, fire, storm, traffic accidents, or other actions of similar nature which usually occur suddenly and cause, or threaten to cause, damage requiring immediate attention;</para><para id="id00">(9) Expressway shall be defined in the manner provided by section 39-1302;</para><para id="id00">(10) Freeway shall be defined in the manner provided by section 39-1302;</para><para id="id00">(11) Highway shall mean a road, street, expressway, or freeway, including the entire area within the right-of-way, which has been designated a part of the state highway system;</para><para id="id00">(12) Interstate bridge shall mean the right-of-way, approaches, bridge structure, and highway necessary to form a passageway for highway traffic over the boundary line of the State of Nebraska from a point within the State of Nebraska to a point within an adjoining state for the purpose of spanning any obstruction or obstructions which would otherwise hinder the free and safe flow of traffic between such points, such bridge being a part of the state highway system with title vested in the State of Nebraska or in the State of Nebraska and an adjoining state jointly;</para><para id="id00">(13) Interstate bridge purposes shall include, but not be limited to, the applicable provisions of subdivisions (2)(a) through (l) of section 39-1320;</para><para id="id00">(14) Maintenance shall mean the act, operation, or continuous process of repair, reconstruction, or preservation of the whole or any part of any interstate bridge for the purpose of keeping it at or near its original standard of usefulness and shall include the performance of traffic services for the safety and convenience of the traveling public. For purposes of this subdivision, reconstruction shall be construed to be the repairing or replacing of any part of any interstate bridge without changing or modifying the form or design of such bridge;</para><para id="id00">(15) Person shall include bodies politic and corporate, societies, communities, the public generally, individuals, partnerships, limited liability companies, joint-stock companies, and associations;</para><para id="id00">(16) Right-of-way shall mean land, property, or interest therein, usually in a strip, acquired for or devoted to an interstate bridge;</para><para id="id00">(17) State highway system shall mean the highways within the State of Nebraska as shown on the map provided for in section 39-1311 and as defined by section 39-1302;</para><para id="id00">(18) Street shall be defined in the manner provided by section 39-1302;</para><para id="id00">(19) Title shall mean the evidence of right to property or the right itself; and</para><para id="id00">(20) Traffic services shall mean the operation of an interstate bridge facility, and the services incidental thereto, to provide for the safe and convenient flow of traffic over such bridge. Such services shall include, but not be limited to, erection of snow fence, snow and ice removal, painting, repairing, and replacing signs, guardrails, traffic signals, lighting standards, pavement stripes and markings, adding conventional traffic control devices, furnishing power for road lighting and traffic control devices, and replacement of parts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 175, &#167; 2, p. 631; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 210; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 116. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>