<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-213" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>39-213</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Control of advertising outside of right-of-way; agreements authorized; commercial and industrial zones; provisions.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) In order that this state may qualify for the payments authorized in 23 U.S.C. 131(c) and (e), and to comply with the provisions of 23 U.S.C. 131 as revised and amended on October 22, 1965, by Public Law 89-285, the Nebraska Department of Transportation, for and in the name of the State of Nebraska, is authorized to enter into an agreement, or agreements, with the Secretary of Transportation of the United States, which agreement or agreements shall include provisions for regulation and control of the erection and maintenance of advertising signs, displays, and other advertising devices and may include, among other things, provisions for preservation of natural beauty, prevention of erosion, landscaping, reforestation, development of viewpoints for scenic attractions that are accessible to the public without charge, and the erection of markers, signs, or plaques, and development of areas in appreciation of sites of historical significance.</para><para id="id00">(2) It is the intention of the Legislature that the state shall be and is hereby empowered and directed to continue to qualify for and accept bonus payments pursuant to 23 U.S.C. 131(j) and subsequent amendments as amended in the Federal Aid Highway Acts of 1968 and 1970 for controlling outdoor advertising within the area adjacent to and within six hundred sixty feet of the edge of the right-of-way of the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways constructed upon any part of the right-of-way the entire width of which is acquired subsequent to July 1, 1956, and, to this end, to continue any agreements with, and make any new agreements with the Secretary of Transportation, to accomplish the same. Such agreement or agreements shall also provide for excluding from application of the national standards segments of the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways which traverse commercial or industrial zones within the boundaries of incorporated municipalities as they existed on September 21, 1959, wherein the use of real property adjacent to the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways is subject to municipal regulation or control, or which traverse other areas where the land use, as of September 21, 1959, is clearly established by state law as industrial or commercial.</para><para id="id00">(3) It is also the intention of the Legislature that the state shall comply with 23 U.S.C. 131, as revised and amended on October 22, 1965, by Public Law 89-285, in order that the state not be penalized by the provisions of subsection (b) thereof, and that the Nebraska Department of Transportation shall be and is hereby empowered and directed to make rules and regulations in accord with the agreement between the Nebraska Department of Transportation and the United States Department of Transportation dated October 29, 1968.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 195, &#167; 3, p. 596; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 236, &#167; 1, p. 726; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1058, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1181, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 39-1320.02; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 95. </para></source><annotation><para>An injunction may properly be entered to require compliance with the statute making it unlawful to erect or maintain advertising signs along highways prior to determination of whether there is a right to damages resulting from application of the statute. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para><para>Sections 39-1320 to 39-1320.11 constitute a reasonable and valid exercise of the police power which bears a substantial relation to the public health, safety, and general welfare, and are constitutional. State v. Mayhew Products Corp., 204 Neb. 266, 281 N.W.2d 783 (1979).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>