<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-869"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-869</statuteno><catchline>Bridge commission; members; term of office; qualification; oath; officers; expenses; compensation.</catchline><para>(1) The bridge commission shall consist of not less than three nor more than five persons of well-known and successful business qualifications. The commissioners shall immediately enter upon their duties, and three of the commissioners shall hold office until the expiration of two, four, and six years, respectively, from the date or dates of their appointments. If more than three commissioners are appointed, the fourth commissioner shall hold office until the expiration of four years from the date of his or her appointment, and the fifth commissioner, if any, shall hold office until the expiration of six years from the date of his or her appointment. The term of each commissioner shall be designated by the governing body of the county. Except for the initial appointees, commissioners shall be appointed for terms of six years. Any person appointed to fill a vacancy shall serve only for the unexpired term. Before entering upon their duties, the commissioners shall take, subscribe, and file an oath of office as required by law.</para><para>(2) Such bridge commission shall elect a chairperson and vice-chairperson from its members and a secretary-treasurer who need not be a member of such commission. Each member of the commission shall serve without compensation but shall be paid his or her actual expenses while engaged in performing the duties of such office, with mileage to be computed at the rate provided in section 81-1176, and fees on a per diem basis which shall not exceed thirty-five dollars a day for each meeting attended on the specific call of the chairperson, except that they shall not be paid for more than three meetings per month. The commission shall fix the compensation of the secretary-treasurer in its discretion, but if the secretary-treasurer is a member of the commission, he or she shall receive compensation as secretary-treasurer and shall not receive his or her per diem compensation for attending meetings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 78, &#167; 2, p. 318; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-2107; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-869; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 94, &#167; 1, p. 317; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 137, &#167; 1, p. 425; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 234, &#167; 1, p. 723; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 459, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 640, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1011, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc>