<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-202" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>39-202</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Advertising signs, displays, or devices; visible from highway; prohibited; exceptions; permitted signs enumerated.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Except as provided in sections 39-202 to 39-205, 39-215, 39-216, and 39-220, the erection or maintenance of any advertising sign, display, or device beyond six hundred sixty feet of the right-of-way of the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways and visible from the main-traveled way of such highway system is prohibited.</para><para id="id00">(2) The following signs shall be permitted:</para><para id="id00">(a) Directional and official signs to include, but not be limited to, signs and notices pertaining to natural wonders, scenic attractions, and historical attractions. Such signs shall comply with standards and criteria established by regulations of the Department of Transportation as promulgated from time to time;</para><para id="id00">(b) Signs, displays, and devices advertising the sale or lease of property upon which such media are located;</para><para id="id00">(c) Signs, displays, and devices advertising activities conducted on the property on which such media are located; and</para><para id="id00">(d) Signs in existence in accordance with sections 39-212 to 39-222, to include landmark signs, signs on farm structures, markers, and plaques of historical or artistic significance.</para><para id="id00">(3) For purposes of this section, visible shall mean the message or advertising content of an advertising sign, display, or device is capable of being seen without visual aid by a person of normal visual acuity. A sign shall be considered visible even though the message or advertising content may be seen but not read.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 213, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-618.02; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 85. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>