<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-101" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>39-101</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of Chapter 39, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Alley means a highway intended to provide access to the rear or side of lots or buildings and not intended for the purpose of through vehicular traffic;</para><para>(2) Divided highway means a highway with separated roadways for traffic in opposite directions;</para><para>(3) Highway means the entire width between the boundary limits of any street, road, avenue, boulevard, or way which is publicly maintained when any part thereof is open to the use of the public for purposes of vehicular travel;</para><para>(4) Intersection means the area embraced within the prolongation or connection of the lateral curb lines or, if there are no lateral curb lines, the lateral boundary lines of the roadways of two or more highways which join one another at, or approximately at, right angles or the area within which vehicles traveling upon different highways joining at any other angle may come in conflict. When a highway includes two roadways thirty feet or more apart, then every crossing of each roadway of such divided highway by an intersecting highway shall be regarded as a separate intersection. In the event such intersecting highway also includes two roadways thirty feet or more apart, then every crossing of two roadways of such highways shall be regarded as a separate intersection. The junction of an alley with a highway shall not constitute an intersection;</para><para>(5) Mail means to deposit in the United States mail properly addressed and with postage prepaid;</para><para>(6) Maintenance means the act, operation, or continuous process of repair, reconstruction, or preservation of the whole or any part of any highway, including surface, shoulders, roadsides, traffic control devices, structures, waterways, and drainage facilities, for the purpose of keeping it at or near or improving upon its original standard of usefulness and safety;</para><para>(7) Motor vehicle means every self-propelled land vehicle, not operated upon rails, except mopeds as defined in section 60-637, self-propelled chairs used by persons who are disabled, electric personal assistive mobility devices as defined in section 60-618.02, and bicycles as defined in section 60-611;</para><para>(8) Park or parking means the standing of a vehicle, whether occupied or not, otherwise than temporarily for the purpose of and while actually engaged in loading or unloading merchandise or passengers;</para><para>(9) Pedestrian means any person afoot;</para><para>(10) Right-of-way means the right of one vehicle or pedestrian to proceed in a lawful manner in preference to another vehicle or pedestrian approaching under such circumstances of direction, speed, and proximity as to give rise to danger of collision unless one grants precedence to the other;</para><para>(11) Roadway means that portion of a highway improved, designed, or ordinarily used for vehicular travel, exclusive of the berm or shoulder. If a highway includes two or more separate roadways, the term roadway refers to any such roadway separately but not to all such roadways collectively;</para><para>(12) Shoulder means that part of the highway contiguous to the roadway and designed for the accommodation of stopped vehicles, for emergency use, and for lateral support of the base and surface courses of the roadway;</para><para>(13) Sidewalk means that portion of a highway between the curb lines, or the lateral lines of a roadway, and the adjacent property lines, intended for use by pedestrians;</para><para>(14) Traffic means pedestrians, ridden or herded animals, and vehicles and other conveyances either singly or together while using any highway for purposes of travel; and</para><para>(15) Vehicle means every device in, upon, or by which any person or property is or may be transported or drawn upon a highway, except devices moved solely by human power, devices used exclusively upon stationary rails or tracks, electric personal assistive mobility devices as defined in section 60-618.02, and bicycles as defined in section 60-611.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 436; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB95, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>The standard for determining whether a vehicle is "approaching" is whether or not the vehicle poses an immediate hazard; that is, whether the circumstances are such that there is a danger of collision if one vehicle does not grant precedence to the other. Springer v. Bohling, 259 Neb. 71, 607 N.W.2d 836 (2000).</para><para>The right-of-way does not include a right to encroach upon that half of the highway upon which cars coming from the opposite direction are entitled to travel. Generally, an unexcused vehicular encroachment on another's lane of traffic, such as driving to the left of the middle of a roadway, prevents acquisition of a right-of-way and precludes the unlawful encroachment from becoming a favored position in movement of traffic. Krul v. Harless, 222 Neb. 313, 383 N.W.2d 744 (1986).</para><para>A hospital driveway which is privately maintained and subject to use by patients, visitors, and others having legitimate business at the hospital is not a "highway," within the meaning of this section and, therefore, the rules of the road as set forth in sections 39-601 to 39-6,122 (now sections 60-601 to 60-6,377) do not apply to its use. However, common law applicable to users of public ways does apply. Bassinger v. Agnew, 206 Neb. 1, 290 N.W.2d 793 (1980).</para><para>Vehicle on the right has the favored position but does not have an absolute right to proceed regardless of the circumstances. Crink v. Northern Nat. Gas Co., 200 Neb. 460, 263 N.W.2d 857 (1978).</para><para>Intersection right-of-way is a qualified, not absolute, right to proceed, exercising due care, in a lawful manner in preference to an opposing vehicle. Reese v. Mayer, 198 Neb. 499, 253 N.W.2d 317 (1977).</para><para>Sidewalk is portion of street between curb lines, or lateral lines of roadway and adjacent property lines, intended for use by pedestrians. Therkildsen v. Gottsch, 194 Neb. 729, 235 N.W.2d 622 (1975).</para><para>Where highway includes two roadways thirty feet apart, each crossing thereof is a separate intersection. Therkildsen v. Gottsch, 194 Neb. 729, 235 N.W.2d 622 (1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>