<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-312" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>39-312</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Camping; permitted; where; violation; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">It shall be unlawful to camp on any state or county public highway, roadside area, park, or other property acquired for highway or roadside park purposes except at such places as are designated campsites by the Department of Transportation or the county or other legal entity of government owning or controlling such places. This provision shall not apply to lands originally acquired for highway purposes which have been transferred or leased to the Game and Parks Commission or a natural resources district or to other lands owned or controlled by the Game and Parks Commission where camping shall be controlled by the provisions of section 37-305 or by a natural resources district where camping shall be controlled by the provisions of section 2-3292.</para><para id="id00">For purposes of this section, camping means temporary lodging out of doors and presupposes the occupancy of a shelter designed or used for such purposes, such as a sleeping bag, tent, trailer, station wagon, pickup camper, camper-bus, or other vehicle, and the use of camping equipment and camper means an occupant of any such shelter.</para><para id="id00">Any person who camps on any state or county public highway, roadside area, park, or other property acquired for highway or roadside park purposes, which has not been properly designated as a campsite, or any person who violates any lawfully promulgated rules or regulations properly posted to regulate camping at designated campsites shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor and shall be ordered to pay any amount as determined by the court which may be necessary to reimburse the department or the county for the expense of repairing any damage to such campsite resulting from such violation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 306, &#167; 1, p. 1097; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 861, &#167; 18; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-712.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 404; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 109. </para></source><annotation><para>Establishment of a public road upon satisfaction of statutory requirements is a ministerial duty within the power of the county board. Burton v. Annett, 215 Neb. 788, 341 N.W.2d 318 (1983).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>