<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-311" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>39-311</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Rubbish on highways; prohibited; signs; enforcement; violation; penalties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) No person shall throw or deposit upon any highway:</para><para id="id00">(a) Any glass bottle, glass, nails, tacks, wire, cans, or other substance likely to injure any person or animal or damage any vehicle upon such highway; or</para><para id="id00">(b) Any burning material.</para><para id="id00">(2) Any person who deposits or permits to be deposited upon any highway any destructive or injurious material shall immediately remove such or cause it to be removed.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any person who removes a wrecked or damaged vehicle from a highway shall remove any glass or other injurious substance deposited on the highway from such vehicle.</para><para id="id00">(4) The Department of Transportation or a local authority as defined in section 60-628 may procure and place at reasonable intervals on the side of highways under its respective jurisdiction appropriate signs showing the penalty for violating this section. Such signs shall be of such size and design as to be easily read by persons on such highways, but the absence of such a sign shall not excuse a violation of this section.</para><para id="id00">(5) It shall be the duty of all Nebraska State Patrol officers, conservation officers, sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, and other law enforcement officers to enforce this section and to make prompt investigation of any violations of this section reported by any person.</para><para id="id00">(6) Any person who violates any provision of this section shall be guilty of (a) a Class III misdemeanor for the first offense, (b) a Class II misdemeanor for the second offense, and (c) a Class I misdemeanor for the third or subsequent offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1030, &#167; 40; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-683; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 570, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 495, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 403; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 108. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Littering,</emphasis> penalty, see section 28-523.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>