<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1333"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1333</statuteno><catchline>State highways; access; department; adopt rules and regulations; issue permits.</catchline><para>The department may adopt reasonable rules and regulations and issue permits for the construction or use of any private entrance or exit, approach road, facility, thing, or appurtenance upon or connected to highway rights-of-way. Such rules and regulations and such permits may include, but need not be limited to, provisions for construction of culverts, requirements as to depth of fills, and requirements for drainage facilities deemed necessary. Such a permit so issued may contain such terms and conditions as, in the judgment of the granting authority, may be in the best interest of the public. All construction under such permits shall be under the supervision of the granting authority and at the expense of the applicant. After completion of the construction of the particular private entrance or exit, approach road, facility, thing, or appurtenance, the same shall be maintained at the expense of the applicant and in accordance with the rules and regulations of the department. Nothing herein contained shall be determined or construed to grant any right for or authorize the construction of a private entrance or exit or approach road upon or connected to any facility, thing, or appurtenance on the right-of-way of any highway or section of highway for which the department has by gift, agreement, or eminent domain acquired the rights of access on a portion thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 148, &#167; 33, p. 432. </para></source><annotation><para>Application of this section was properly covered by instructions given by trial court. Chaloupka v. State, 176 Neb. 746, 127 N.W.2d 291 (1964).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>