<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-1719"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1719</statuteno><catchline>Isolated land; access road; award; appeal; procedure.</catchline><para>Any party to an award as provided by section 39-1718 may, within sixty days after the filing thereof, appeal therefrom to the district court of the county where the lands lie. The appeal shall be taken by serving upon the adverse party a notice of such appeal and filing such notice and proof of service thereof with the clerk of the court within the sixty days. Thereupon the appeal shall be set down for hearing at the next term of the court. It shall be heard and determined in like manner as appeals from awards in condemnations as provided in sections 76-704 to 76-724. Such appeal shall not affect the right or authority of the petitioner to the use of the access road under the award of the appraisers.</para><para>The applicant shall in case of appeal file such additional security as may be required by the county board for such costs and damages as may accrue against him or her by reason of such appeal. If on appeal the appellant does not obtain a more favorable judgment and award than was given by the appraisers, such appellant shall pay all the costs of such appeal. Either party to such suit may appeal from the decision of the district court to the Court of Appeals, and the sum deposited as provided in this section shall remain in the hands of the county treasurer until a final decision is had.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. IV, &#167; 19, p. 546; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 189, &#167; 8, p. 583; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 779, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc>