<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1725"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1725</statuteno><catchline>Order of county board; contents; conditions and vote required for vacation or abandonment; resolution; disposition.</catchline><para>After the public hearing the county board shall by resolution at its next meeting or as soon thereafter as may be practicable vacate or abandon or refuse vacation or abandonment, as in the judgment of the board the public good may require. Vacation and abandonment shall not be ordered except upon vote of two-thirds of all members of the board and the prior approval of the governing body of a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class has been obtained when any public road or any part thereof is within the area of the zoning jurisdiction of such city. If such road lies within a township in a county operating roads on a township basis the road shall not be vacated or abandoned unless an offer has been made to relinquish to the township in the manner provided in section 39-1726.</para><para>In the event that the county board decides to vacate or abandon, its resolution shall state upon what conditions, if any, the vacation or abandonment shall be qualified and particularly whether or not the title or right-of-way to any vacated or abandoned fragment or section of road shall be sold, revert to private ownership, or remain in the public. If the county board fails to specify in a resolution as to the disposition of right-of-way, and if there shall be nonuse of such right-of-way for any public purpose for a continuous period of not less than ten years, the right-of-way shall revert to the owners of the adjacent real estate, one-half on each side thereof. When the county vacates all or any portion of a road, the county shall, within thirty days after the effective date of the vacation, file a certified copy of the vacating resolution with the register of deeds for the county to be indexed against all affected lots.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. IV, &#167; 25, p. 548; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 167, &#167; 7, p. 611; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 192, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1277, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 607, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 483, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Effect of conveyances of tracts adjacent to vacated streets or alleys,</emphasis> see section 76-275.03.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>With respect to public roads, a county which vacates a road while retaining a right of way has a duty to exercise such degree of care as would be exercised by a reasonable county under the same circumstances. Blaser v. County of Madison, 285 Neb. 290, 826 N.W.2d 554 (2013).</para><para>County board's decision not to rebuild bridge upheld where no showing that such discretionary decision was arbitrary or capricious. State ex rel. Goossen v. Board of Supervisors, 198 Neb. 9, 251 N.W.2d 655 (1977).</para><para>Constitutionality of this section sustained. Emry v. Lake, 181 Neb. 568, 149 N.W.2d 520 (1967).</para><para>Title to abandoned road remained in county until a period of ten years of non-use had elapsed. Plischke v. Jameson, 180 Neb. 803, 146 N.W.2d 223 (1966).</para><para>The discretion exercised by a county board of commissioners under section 39-1722 and this section is not judicial in nature, and as such, the trial court did not have jurisdiction to hear a petition in error under section 25-1901. Camp Clarke Ranch v. Morrill Cty. Bd. of Comrs., 17 Neb. App. 76, 758 N.W.2d 653 (2008).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>