<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1724"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1724</statuteno><catchline>County board resolution ordering public hearing; publication; service of notice on adjacent landowners and municipality.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The county board shall adopt a resolution fixing the time, date, and place for a public hearing on the issue of vacating or abandoning a public road when:</para><para>(i) The county board receives the report described in section 39-1722; or</para><para>(ii) The county board by resolution proposes to vacate or abandon a public road that was previously declared a public road pursuant to section 39-1410 as such section existed prior to September 3, 2025.</para><para>(b) The resolution fixing the time, date, and place for the public hearing shall contain a clear and unambiguous description of the road to be vacated or abandoned.</para><para>(2) The county board shall cause such resolution to be published once a week for three consecutive weeks in a legal newspaper published in the county or, if none is published in the county, in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the county.</para><para>(3)(a) Whenever possible the county board shall cause copies of such resolution to be served by either registered or certified mail upon:</para><para>(i) The owners of land abutting on or adjacent to the road to be vacated or abandoned; and</para><para>(ii) The planning and public works directors of a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class when such road or any part thereof is within the area of the zoning jurisdiction of such city.</para><para>(b) Such copies shall be mailed to the last-known address of each person described in subdivision (a) of this subsection not less than two weeks in advance of the hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. IV, &#167; 24, p. 548; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 192, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 607, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB373, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>