<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1108</statuteno><catchline>State Highway Commission; meetings; quorum; minutes; open to public.</catchline><para>Regular meetings of the State Highway Commission shall be held upon call of the chairperson, but not less than six times per year. Special meetings may be held upon call of the chairperson or pursuant to a call signed by three other members, of which the chairperson shall have three days' written notice.</para><para>All regular meetings shall be held in suitable offices to be provided in Lincoln unless a majority of the members deem it necessary to hold a regular meeting at another location within this state. Members of the commission may participate by telephone conference call or videoconference as long as the chairperson or vice-chairperson conducts the meeting in an open forum where the public is able to participate by attendance at the scheduled meeting.</para><para>Five members of the commission constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. Every act of a majority of the members of the commission shall be deemed to be the act of the commission.</para><para>All meetings shall be open to the public and shall be conducted in accordance with the Open Meetings Act.</para><para>The minutes of the meetings shall show the action of the commission on matters presented. The minutes shall be open to public inspection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 334, &#167; 8, p. 1097; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 101, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 544, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 161, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 101, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>