<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1905"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1905</statuteno><catchline>Road tax; special levy by petition; limit; contributions; district road fund; authorized expenditures.</catchline><para>Fifty-one percent of the resident freeholders of any road district, precinct, or township in this state, as shown by the records of the register of deeds of the county in which such road district, precinct, or township is situated, may petition the county board of the county in which such district, precinct, or township is located to levy an assessment of not to exceed ten and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such road district, precinct, or township. Upon receipt of such petition, the county board shall make the assessment, as requested, upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such road district, precinct, or township to be levied and collected the same as other taxes. Such taxes and any voluntary contributions (1) shall be and become a part of the district road fund of the district, precinct, or township in which the taxes are levied, (2) shall be used exclusively in constructing or improving the public roads in such district, precinct, or township, and (3) shall not be transferred to any other fund. In counties under township organization, the township board shall designate the road or roads in such road district where such levy shall be expended. In other counties the county board shall designate the road or roads in such road district where such levy shall be expended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. VI, &#167; 5, p. 559; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 166; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 146. </para></source></law></legaldoc>