<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1601</statuteno><catchline>Special improvement districts; petition for organization; dissolution; procedure; disposition of funds.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever a petition, (a) containing a definite description of the territory to be embraced, (b) designating the name of the proposed district, and (c) signed by ten percent of the landowners within the limits of a proposed road improvement district is presented and filed with the county board of the county in which the greater portion of the area of the proposed district is located, the county board of any such county shall cause the question to be submitted to the legal voters of such proposed road improvement district as provided in section 39-1605. If fifty-five percent of those voting on the question are in favor of the proposition, the district shall be organized. No lands included within any municipal corporation shall be included in any road improvement district.</para><para>(2) Any road improvement district can be dissolved, if there are no outstanding debts, by the board of trustees of any such district, on its own motion or on the request in writing of ten electors, submitting at a special election, after due notice by publication in the manner provided for in subsection (1) of section 39-1604, the question of dissolution of the road improvement district. The special election shall be conducted by mail as provided in sections 32-953 to 32-959. If fifty-one percent of the votes cast on the question at such election are in favor of such dissolution, the board of trustees shall cause a record of such election and the vote thereon to be made in the office of the county clerk in the county in which the election was held to create the district, and the district shall thereupon stand dissolved. An election shall not be required for the dissolution of the district if a petition requesting the district be dissolved, signed by fifty percent of the owners of property located within the district, is presented to the county board of the county. The county board shall determine the sufficiency of the petition and dissolve the district by an order of such board.</para><para>(3) In case a district is dissolved pursuant to this section, the funds on hand or to be collected shall be held by the county treasurer in a separate fund, and the trustees of the district shall petition the district court of the county in which the election to form the district was held, for an order approving the distribution of funds to the landowners or easement owners as a dividend on the same basis as collected. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. III, &#167; 1, p. 523; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB248, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>