<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-1716"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1716</statuteno><catchline>Isolated land; access road; damages; powers of county board; costs; maintenance.</catchline><para>(1) The county board shall, if it finds (a) that the conditions set forth in section 39-1713 or 39-1714 exist, (b) that the isolated land was not isolated at the time it was purchased by the owner or that the owner acquired the land directly from the State of Nebraska, (c) that the isolation of the land was not caused by the owner or by any other person with the knowledge and consent of the owner, and (d) that access is necessary for existing utilization of the isolated land, proceed to provide an access road and, if it finds that the amount of use and the number of persons served warrants such action, may lay out a public road to such real estate.</para><para>(2) The county board shall appraise the damages to be suffered by the owner or owners of the real estate over or through which the access road will be provided. Such damages shall be paid by the person petitioning that the access road be provided. For any real estate purchased or otherwise acquired after January 1, 1982, for which public access is granted pursuant to sections 39-1713 to 39-1719, the person petitioning for such access shall also reimburse the county for all engineering and construction costs incurred in providing such access.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding any other provisions of law, an access road provided in accordance with this section shall not be subject to Chapter 39, article 20 or 21. The designation of such an access road shall not impose on the State of Nebraska or any political subdivision any obligation of design, construction, or maintenance for the access road nor give rise to any cause of action against the state or any political subdivision with respect to the access road.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. IV, &#167; 16, p. 545; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 239, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 779, &#167; 7. </para></source><annotation><para>This section provides that the county board may lay out a public road of not more than 4 nor less than 2 rods in width to isolated real estate, if it finds that the amount of use and the number of persons served warrant such action. Lewis v. Board of Cmrs. of Loup Cty., 247 Neb. 655, 529 N.W.2d 745 (1995).</para><para>A writ of mandamus is the proper remedy to compel a county board, in accordance with this section and section 39-1713, to lay out a public road for access to isolated land. This section applies prospectively, that is, to real estate acquired after January 1, 1982. Young v. Dodge Cty. Bd. of Supervisors, 242 Neb. 1, 493 N.W.2d 160 (1992).</para><para>The duty of the board of county commissioners under this section, to lay out a public road upon a showing that the statutory conditions of section 39-1713, R.R.S.1943, exist, is ministerial. Singleton v. Kimball County Board of Commissioners, 203 Neb. 429, 279 N.W.2d 112 (1979).</para><para>A road established as provided herein is a public road. Moritz v. Buglewicz, 187 Neb. 819, 194 N.W.2d 215 (1972).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>