<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1339"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1339</statuteno><catchline>State highway system; connecting links, defined; duty of department.</catchline><para>Except as provided in section 39-1372, the responsibility of the department for the maintenance of connecting links on the state highway system shall be determined in accordance with the following provisions:</para><para>(1) The department shall be liable for the cost of surface maintenance of the traveled way of connecting links, not including the parking lanes thereon, in cities of the metropolitan, primary, and first classes; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> such connecting links were constructed under the authority of the department and construction costs were paid in whole or in part with county, state or federal-aid funds. The department shall not be responsible for the maintenance of any connecting link or portion thereof which was not built in whole or in part with county, state or federal-aid funds;</para><para>(2) The department shall be liable for all of the surface maintenance of the traveled way of connecting links, including parking lanes thereon, in cities of the second class and villages; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> such connecting links were constructed under the authority of the department and construction costs were paid in whole or in part with county, state or federal-aid funds. The department shall not be responsible for the maintenance of any connecting link or portion thereof which was not built with county, state or federal-aid funds;</para><para>(3) The responsibility of the department for the maintenance of the connecting links, described in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section, shall be limited to such things as are caused either by wear and tear of travel on such connecting links or by acts of God. Maintenance shall not be construed to include (a) snow removal, (b) maintenance caused by constructing, placing, replacing, repairing, or servicing water mains, sewers, gas lines, pipes, utility equipment, or other similar things placed beneath, across, or upon the surface of any portion of a connecting link, or (c) repairs or reconstruction going beyond the scope of normal surface maintenance or wear and tear of travel;</para><para>(4) The maintenance of structures, on the connecting links described in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section, shall not be limited to the traveled way but shall include the entire structure; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> the department shall have no responsibility for the maintenance of appurtenances to such connecting links and the structures thereon, except by special agreement with the city or village in which the connecting link is situated. Appurtenances shall include, but are not limited to, sidewalks, storm sewers, guardrails, handrails, steps, curb or grate inlets, driveways, fire plugs, or retaining walls;</para><para>(5) The department shall maintain and keep in repair all public bridges and the approaches thereto when located in cities of the first class and on connecting links which were constructed under the authority of the department and construction costs were paid in whole or in part with state or federal funds;</para><para>(6) Nothing contained in this section shall be construed to prevent the department from entering into special agreements with cities or villages regarding the reconstruction and maintenance of connecting links in such cities and villages; and</para><para>(7) As used in this section, unless the context otherwise requires, connecting link shall mean a street now designated as a state highway.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 148, &#167; 39, p. 434; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 181, &#167; 7, p. 539; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 184, &#167; 35, p. 565; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 239, &#167; 1, p. 637. </para></source></law></legaldoc>