<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-1623"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1623</statuteno><catchline>Improvements; plat; benefits; schedule of proposed assessments; notice; hearing.</catchline><para>After the completion of any improvements, the engineer shall file with the clerk of the district a complete statement of all the costs of such improvement, a plat of the property in the district especially benefited thereby, and a schedule of the amount proposed to be assessed against each separate piece of property. A copy of the plat and schedule of proposed assessment shall be filed in the office of the county clerk of the county in which the greater portion of the area of the district is located for public inspection. The trustees of the district shall then order the clerk of the district to give notice that the plat and schedule are on file with the county clerk where the same are kept for examination, and that all objections thereto or to prior proceedings on account of errors, irregularities, or inequalities not made in writing and filed with the clerk of the district within twenty days after first publication of the notice shall be deemed to have been waived. Such notice shall be given by publication, once each week during two consecutive weeks, in a newspaper of general circulation in the district and whenever possible by giving notice in writing by either registered or certified mail to the owner of each separate piece of property against which an assessment is proposed. The notice shall state the time and place where objections are to be filed. The time of such hearing shall be determined in the manner stated in section 39-1624. Any objections so filed shall be considered by the trustees of the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. III, &#167; 23, p. 534. </para></source></law></legaldoc>