<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-1010"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1010</statuteno><catchline>Mailboxes; location; violation; duty
of Department of Roads.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this
subsection, all mailboxes shall be placed such that no part of
the mailbox extends beyond the shoulder line of any highway and the mailbox
support shall be placed a minimum of one foot outside the shoulder line of
any gravel-surfaced highway, and of any hard-surfaced highway having a shoulder
width of six feet or more as measured
from the edge of the hard surfacing. Along hard-surfaced highways having a
shoulder width of less than six feet, the Department of Roads shall, on new
construction or reconstruction, where feasible, provide a shoulder width of
not less than six feet, or provide for a minimum clear traffic lane of ten
feet in width at mailbox
turnouts. On highways built before October 9, 1961, having a shoulder width
of less than six feet, the Department of Roads may, where feasible and deemed
advisable, provide a shoulder width of not less than six feet or provide for
minimum clear traffic lane of ten feet in width at mailbox turnouts. For a hard-surfaced highway having either a mailbox turnout
or a hard-surfaced shoulder width of eight feet or more, the mailbox shall
be placed such that no part of the mailbox extends beyond the outside edge
of the mailbox turnout or hard-surfaced portion of the shoulder and the mailbox
support shall be placed a minimum of one foot outside the outside edge of
the mailbox turnout or hard-surfaced portion of the shoulder.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be the duty of
the Department of Roads to notify the owner of all mailboxes in violation
of the provisions of this section, and
the department may remove such mailboxes if the owner fails or refuses to
remove the same after a reasonable time after he or she is notified of such violations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 194, &#167; 1, p. 593; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB757, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>