<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1311.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1311.03</statuteno><catchline>Corridor; proposed subdivision plat; building permit; notice; statement of intent; issuance.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the filing of a request for a review of a proposed subdivision plat on a parcel located within a corridor, the officer responsible for reviewing subdivision plats or, if the review of a subdivision plat is required only by virtue of sections 39-1311 to 39-1311.05, the county clerk shall give the department notice of the filing of a request for a review of a preliminary subdivision plat. The officer responsible for review of subdivision plats shall not approve or forward for approval a subdivision plat for a period of sixty days from the date of mailing notice of the filing of the request with the department unless the department waives in writing the time period. Within the sixty-day period, the department may if it wishes file with such officer a statement of intent to negotiate with the owner of the land involved. Upon the filing of such statement of intent, the department shall be allowed six months for negotiations with the landowner. At the end of such six-month period, if the landowner has not withdrawn his or her request for review of a subdivision plat, the officer responsible for review of subdivision plats shall proceed with consideration of such preliminary plat if it meets all other applicable codes, ordinances, and laws.</para><para>(2) Upon the filing of a request for a building permit on a parcel located within a corridor, the officer responsible for issuance of building permits or, if a building permit is required only by virtue of sections 39-1311 to 39-1311.05, the county clerk shall give the department notice of the filing of the request for a building permit. The officer responsible for issuance of building permits shall not issue a permit for a period of sixty days from the date of mailing notice of the filing of the request with the department unless the department waives in writing the time period. Within the sixty-day period, the department may if it wishes file with such officer a statement of intent to negotiate with the owner of the land involved. Upon the filing of such statement of intent, the department shall be allowed six months for negotiations with the landowner. At the end of such six-month period, if the landowner has not withdrawn his or her application for a permit, it shall be issued if it meets all other applicable codes, ordinances, and laws.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 805, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>