<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1390"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1390</statuteno><catchline>State Recreation Road Fund; created; use; preferences; maintenance; investment.</catchline><para>The State Recreation Road Fund is created. The money in the fund shall be transferred by the State Treasurer, on the first day of each month, to the Department of Roads and shall be expended by the Director-State Engineer with the approval of the Governor for construction and maintenance of dustless-surface roads to be designated as state recreation roads as provided in this section, except that (1) transfers may be made from the fund to the State Park Cash Revolving Fund at the direction of the Legislature through July 31, 2016, and (2) if the balance in the State Recreation Road Fund exceeds fourteen million dollars on the first day of each month, the State Treasurer shall transfer the amount greater than fourteen million dollars to the Game and Parks State Park Improvement and Maintenance Fund. Except as to roads under contract as of March 15, 1972, those roads, excluding state highways, giving direct and immediate access to or located within state parks, state recreation areas, or other recreational or historical areas, shall be eligible for designation as state recreation roads. Such eligibility shall be determined by the Game and Parks Commission and certified to the Director-State Engineer, who shall, after receiving such certification, be authorized to commence construction on such recreation roads as funds are available. In addition, those roads, excluding state highways, giving direct and immediate access to a state veteran cemetery are state recreation roads. After construction of such roads they shall be shown on the map provided by section 39-1311. Preference in construction shall be based on existing or potential traffic use by other than local residents. Unless the State Highway Commission otherwise recommends, such roads upon completion of construction shall be incorporated into the state highway system. If such a road is not incorporated into the state highway system, the Department of Roads and the county within which such road is located shall enter into a maintenance agreement establishing the responsibility for maintenance of the road, the maintenance standards to be met, and the responsibility for maintenance costs. Any money in the State Recreation Road Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 348, &#167; 2, p. 1119; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 225, &#167; 1, p. 649; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 501, &#167; 1, p. 1595; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 42, p. 2369; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 408, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB749, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB906, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB661, &#167; 30. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>