<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-1606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-1606</statuteno><catchline>Board of trustees; members; election; filing fee; term; compensation; district; name.</catchline><para>(1) Any resident property owner desiring to file for the office of trustee of a road improvement district may file for such office with the county clerk or election commissioner of the county in which the greater proportion in area of the district is located, not later than forty-five days before the election, by paying a filing fee of five dollars. </para><para>(2)(a) The term of office of every member of a board of trustees of a road improvement district existing on January 1, 2008, shall be extended to the first Monday in October following the expiration of the original term. Their successors shall be elected for terms of six years at elections held on the first Tuesday after the second Monday in September of odd-numbered years. The term of office shall begin on the first Monday in October after the election.</para><para>(b) The successors to the initial board of trustees of a road improvement district shall be elected on the first Tuesday after the second Monday in September of the first odd-numbered year which is at least fifteen months after the organization of the district pursuant to section 39-1605. One trustee shall be elected for a term of two years, one trustee for a term of four years, and one trustee for a term of six years, and thereafter their respective successors shall be elected for terms of six years at succeeding elections held on the first Tuesday after the second Monday in September of odd-numbered years. The term of office shall begin on the first Monday in October after the election.</para><para>(c) Elections under this subsection shall be conducted by mail as provided in sections 32-953 to 32-959.</para><para>(3) At the first meeting of the trustees of such district after the election of one or more members, the board shall elect one of their number president. Such district shall be a body corporate and politic by name of Road Improvement District No. ........ of ........... County or ....... Counties, as the case may be, with power to sue, be sued, contract, acquire and hold property, and adopt a common seal. Each trustee shall receive as his or her salary the sum of five dollars for each meeting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 155, art. III, &#167; 6, p. 527; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 552; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB248, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>