<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" id="id00" statutenumber="39-2106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2106</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards; established; members; number; appointment; qualifications; compensation; expenses.</catchline><para id="id00">To assist in developing the functional classification system, there is hereby established the Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards which shall consist of eleven members to be appointed by the Governor with the approval of the Legislature. Of the members of such board, two shall be representatives of the Department of Transportation, three shall be representatives of the counties, one of whom shall be a licensed county highway superintendent in good standing and two of whom shall be county board members, three shall be representatives of the municipalities who shall be either public works directors or licensed city street superintendents in good standing, and three shall be lay citizens who shall represent the three congressional districts of the state. The county members on the board shall represent the various classes of counties, as defined in section 23-1114.01, in the following manner: One shall be a representative from either a Class 1 or Class 2 county; one shall be a representative from either a Class 3 or Class 4 county; and one shall be a representative from either a Class 5, Class 6, or Class 7 county. The municipal members of the board shall represent municipalities of the following sizes by population: One shall be a representative from a municipality of less than two thousand five hundred inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census; one shall be a representative from a municipality of two thousand five hundred to fifty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census; and one shall be a representative from a municipality of over fifty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census. In making such appointments, the Governor shall consult with the Director-State Engineer and with the appropriate county and municipal officials and may consult with organizations representing such officials or representing counties or municipalities as may be appropriate. At the expiration of the existing term, one member from the county representatives, the municipal representatives, and the lay citizens shall be appointed for a term of two years; and two members from the county representatives, the municipal representatives, and the lay citizens shall be appointed for terms of four years. One representative from the department shall be appointed for a two-year term and the other representative shall be appointed for a four-year term. Thereafter, all such appointments shall be for terms of four years each. Members of such board shall receive no compensation for their services as such, except that the lay members shall receive the same compensation as members of the State Highway Commission, and all members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 for state employees. All expenses of such board shall be paid by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 312, &#167; 6, p. 1122; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 100, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 147. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB113, section 43, with LB339, section 147, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB339 became operative July 1, 2017. Changes made by LB113 became effective August 24, 2017.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>