<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2602" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2602</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">For purposes of sections 39-2601 to 39-2612, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para id="id00">(1) Junk means old or scrap copper, brass, rope, rags, batteries, paper, trash, rubber debris, waste or junked, dismantled, or wrecked automobiles, or parts thereof, iron, steel, and other old or scrap ferrous or nonferrous material;</para><para id="id00">(2) Automobile graveyard means any establishment or place of business which is maintained, operated, or used for storing, keeping, buying, or selling wrecked, scrapped, ruined, or dismantled motor vehicles or motor vehicle parts;</para><para id="id00">(3) Junkyard means an establishment or place of business which is maintained, operated, or used for storing, keeping, buying, or selling junk or for the maintenance or operation of an automobile graveyard, and includes garbage dumps and sanitary fills;</para><para id="id00">(4) Highway Beautification Control System has the same meaning as in section 39-201.01;</para><para id="id00">(5) Scenic byway has the same meaning as in section 39-201.01;</para><para id="id00">(6) Main-traveled way means the traveled portion of an interstate or primary highway on which through traffic is carried and, in the case of a divided highway, the traveled portion of each of the separated roadways;</para><para id="id00">(7) Person means any natural person, partnership, limited liability company, association, corporation, or governmental subdivision; and</para><para id="id00">(8) Department means the Department of Transportation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 398, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 214; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 171. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2017</operativedate></source><annotation><para>For purposes of subsection (2) of this section, a scrapped vehicle is an automobile which has no value whatsoever as a vehicle, but the only worth of which is in the value of its metal for remelting or remanufacturing. For purposes of subsection (2) of this section, a ruined vehicle is one which, through destruction or disintegration, has become formless, useless, or valueless. For purposes of subsection (2) of this section, a wrecked vehicle is one which is seriously damaged in its outward appearance. For purposes of subsection (2) of this section, a dismantled vehicle is one which is stripped of furnishings or equipment. For purposes of subsection (2) of this section, a junked vehicle is one no longer intended or in condition for legal use upon a public highway. State v. Melcher, 240 Neb. 592, 483 N.W.2d 540 (1992).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>