<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2504" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2504</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Incentive payment; reduction; when; consulting engineer; when; contracting with another political subdivision; payment.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A reduced incentive payment shall be made to any county or municipal county having in its employ either (a) a licensed county highway superintendent for only a portion of the calendar year preceding the year in which the payment is made or (b) two or more successive licensed county highway superintendents for the calendar year preceding the year in which the payment is made. Such reduced payment shall be in the proportion of the payment amounts listed in section 39-2503 as the number of full months each such licensed superintendent was employed is of twelve.</para><para id="id00">(2) Any county or municipal county that contracts for the services of a consulting engineer licensed under the County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act or any other person licensed under the act to perform the duties outlined in section 39-2502 rather than employing a licensed county highway superintendent shall be entitled to an incentive payment equal to two-thirds the payment amount provided in section 39-2503 or two-thirds of the reduced incentive payment provided in subsection (1) of this section, as determined by the Department of Transportation pursuant to section 39-2505.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any county or municipal county that contracts with another county or municipal county or with any city or village for the services of a licensed county highway superintendent as provided in section 39-2114 shall be entitled to the incentive payment provided in section 39-2503 or the reduced incentive payment provided in subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 315, &#167; 4, p. 1134; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 51, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 500, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 163. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act,</emphasis> see section 39-2301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>