<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-2819"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2819</statuteno><catchline>Submission of proposals; sealed; rank of construction managers; negotiation of contract.</catchline><para>(1) Construction managers shall submit proposals as required by the request for proposals.</para><para>(2) Proposals shall be sealed and shall not be opened until expiration of the time established for making the proposals as set forth in the request for proposals.</para><para>(3) Proposals may be withdrawn at any time prior to signing a contract for preconstruction services. The contracting agency shall have the right to reject any and all proposals at no cost to the contracting agency. The contracting agency may thereafter solicit new proposals or may cancel the construction manager-general contractor procurement process.</para><para>(4) The contracting agency shall rank the construction managers in accordance with the qualification-based selection process and pursuant to the criteria in the request for proposals. The contracting agency may meet with construction managers prior to the ranking.</para><para>(5) The contracting agency may attempt to negotiate a contract for preconstruction services with the highest ranked construction manager and may enter into a contract for preconstruction services after negotiations. If the contracting agency is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract for preconstruction services with the highest ranked construction manager, the contracting agency may terminate negotiations with that construction manager. The contracting agency may then undertake negotiations with the second highest ranked construction manager and may enter into a contract for preconstruction services after negotiations. If the contracting agency is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract with the second highest ranked construction manager, the contracting agency may undertake negotiations with the third highest ranked construction manager, if any, and may enter into a contract for preconstruction services after negotiations.</para><para>(6) If the contracting agency is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract for preconstruction services with any of the ranked construction managers, the contracting agency may either revise the request for proposals and solicit new proposals or cancel the construction manager-general contractor contract process under sections 39-2808 to 39-2824.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB960, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB583, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>