
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id37"><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-2907"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2907</statuteno><catchline>Infrastructure Development Investment Program Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Infrastructure Development Investment Program Fund is created. The commission shall administer the fund. The fund shall consist of any:</para><para>(a) Transfer authorized by the Legislature;</para><para>(b) Federal money, including, but not limited to, any loan, grant, or cooperative agreement proceeds;</para><para>(c) State or local grant;</para><para>(d) Contribution, donation, endowment, or grant from any public or private source;</para><para>(e) Repayment, interest, or fee, or other income generated by investment program assistance;</para><para>(f) Bond proceeds or other financing proceeds; and</para><para>(g) Lawful source that is approved by the commission.</para><para>(2) Money in the fund may be used by the commission for any purpose that is described in section 39-2908.</para><para>(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(4) All repayments of money provided from the fund and all investment earnings from money in the fund shall be credited to the fund.</para><para>(5) It is the intent of the Legislature that all money in the fund shall be appropriated each fiscal year for the purposes that are described in section 39-2908.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1126, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>