<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" id="id00" statutenumber="39-2106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2106</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards; established; members; number; appointment; qualifications; compensation; expenses.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) To assist in developing the functional classification system, there is hereby established the Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards which shall consist of eleven members to be appointed by the Governor with the approval of the Legislature.</para><para id="id00">(2) Of the members of such board:</para><para id="id00">(a) Two shall be representatives of the Department of Transportation;</para><para id="id00">(b) Three shall be representatives of the counties. One of such members shall be a county highway superintendent licensed pursuant to the County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act and two of such members shall be county board members;</para><para id="id00">(c) Three shall be representatives of the municipalities. Each of such members shall be a city engineer, village engineer, public works director, city manager, city administrator, street commissioner, or city street superintendent licensed pursuant to the County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act; and</para><para id="id00">(d) Three shall be lay citizens, with one representing each of the three congressional districts of the state.</para><para id="id00">(3) The county members on the board shall represent the various classes of counties, as defined in section 23-1114.01, in the following manner:</para><para id="id00">(a) One shall be a representative from either a Class 1 or Class 2 county;</para><para id="id00">(b) One shall be a representative from either a Class 3 or Class 4 county; and</para><para id="id00">(c) One shall be a representative from either a Class 5, Class 6, or Class 7 county.</para><para id="id00">(4) The municipal members of the board shall represent municipalities of the following sizes by population, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census:</para><para id="id00">(a) One shall be a representative from a municipality of less than two thousand five hundred inhabitants;</para><para id="id00">(b) One shall be a representative from a municipality of two thousand five hundred to fifty thousand inhabitants; and</para><para id="id00">(c) One shall be a representative from a municipality of over fifty thousand inhabitants.</para><para id="id00">(5) In making such appointments, the Governor shall consult with the Director-State Engineer and with the appropriate county and municipal officials and may consult with organizations representing such officials or representing counties or municipalities as may be appropriate.</para><para id="id00">(6) At the expiration of the existing term, one member from the county representatives, the municipal representatives, and the lay citizens shall be appointed for a term of two years; and two members from the county representatives, the municipal representatives, and the lay citizens shall be appointed for terms of four years. One representative from the department shall be appointed for a two-year term and the other representative shall be appointed for a four-year term. Thereafter, all such appointments shall be for terms of four years each.</para><para id="id00">(7) Members of such board shall receive no compensation for their services as such, except that the lay members shall receive the same compensation as members of the State Highway Commission, and all members shall be reimbursed for expenses incurred in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. All expenses of such board shall be paid by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 312, &#167; 6, p. 1122; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 100, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 147; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB174, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act,</emphasis> see section 39-2301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>