<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2119"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2119</statuteno><catchline>Counties and municipalities; plan or program for specific improvements; hearing; duty to certify compliance; penalty; funds placed in escrow.</catchline><para>Each county and municipality shall annually develop, adopt, and maintain as a public record, a one-year plan or program for specific highway, road, or street improvements for the current year. No such plan or program, or revision to such plan or program, shall be adopted until after a public hearing thereon and its approval by the governing body. Each county and municipality shall schedule and hold the public hearing each year, and such hearing may be held prior to or in conjunction with that entity's annual public hearing on its proposed budget statement in any year such budget statement hearing is held pursuant to section 13-506. Each county and municipality shall annually certify compliance with the requirements of this section to the Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards using the certification form developed by the board pursuant to section 39-2120. If any county or municipality shall fail to comply with the provisions of this section, the board shall so notify the local governing board, the Governor, and the State Treasurer, who shall suspend distribution of any highway-user revenue allocated to such county or municipality until there has been compliance. Such funds shall be held in escrow for six months until the county or municipality complies. If the county or municipality complies within the six-month period it shall receive the money in escrow, but after six months, if the county or municipality fails to comply, the money in the escrow account shall be lost to the county or municipality and shall be distributed to other counties or municipalities, as appropriate, in the manner provided by law for allocation of highway-user revenue.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 312, &#167; 19, p. 1126; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 100, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 137, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 724, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB277, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB82, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>