<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2115" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2115</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Six-year plan or program; basis; certification form; failure to file; penalty; funds placed in escrow.</catchline><para id="id00">The Department of Transportation and each county and municipality shall develop, adopt, maintain as a public record, and annually update a long-range, six-year plan or program of highway, road, and street improvements based on priority of needs and calculated to contribute to the orderly development of an integrated statewide system of highways, roads, and streets. The department and each county and municipality shall annually certify compliance with the requirements of this section to the Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards using the certification form developed by the board pursuant to section 39-2120. If any county or municipality, or the department, shall fail to file its certification form on or before its due date, the board shall so notify the local governing board, the Governor, and the State Treasurer, who shall suspend distribution of any highway-user revenue allocated to such county or municipality, or the department, until the certification form has been filed. Such funds shall be held in escrow for six months until the county or municipality complies. If the county or municipality complies within the six-month period it shall receive the money in escrow, but after six months, if the county or municipality fails to comply, the money in the escrow account shall be lost to the county or municipality and shall be distributed to other counties or municipalities, as appropriate, in the manner provided by law for allocation of highway-user revenue.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 312, &#167; 15, p. 1124; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 100, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 137, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 724, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 153; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB82, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>