<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2120" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2120</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Certification form for annual filing; Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards; develop; contents.</catchline><para id="id00">The Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards shall develop and schedule for implementation a certification form for annual filing pursuant to section 39-2121 by the Department of Transportation and each county and municipality. The certification form shall include:</para><para>(1) A statement from the department and each county or municipality that it has developed, adopted, and included in its public records the plans, programs, or standards required by sections 39-2115 to 39-2119;</para><para>(2) A statement that the department and each county or municipality:</para><para>(a) Meets the plans, programs, or standards of design, construction, and maintenance for its highways, roads, or streets;</para><para>(b) Expends all tax revenue for highway, road, or street purposes in accordance with approved plans, programs, or standards, including county and municipal tax revenue as well as highway-user revenue allocations;</para><para>(c) Uses a system of revenue and cost accounting which clearly includes a comparison of receipts and expenditures for approved budgets, plans, programs, and standards;</para><para>(d) Uses a system of budgeting which reflects uses and sources of funds in terms of plans, programs, or standards and accomplishments;</para><para>(e) Uses an accounting system including an inventory of machinery, equipment, and supplies; and</para><para>(f) Uses an accounting system that tracks equipment operation costs; and</para><para>(3) The information required under subsection (2) of section 39-2510 or subsection (2) of section 39-2520, when applicable.</para><para>The certification by the department shall be signed by the Director-State Engineer. The certification by each county and municipality shall be signed by the board chairperson or mayor and shall include a copy of the resolution or ordinance of the governing body of the county or municipality authorizing the signing of the certification form.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 312, &#167; 20, p. 1126; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 100, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 156; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB82, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>March 8, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>