<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2502</statuteno><catchline>County highway superintendent, defined; duties; incentive payment.</catchline><para>An incentive payment shall be made to each county having in its employ a county highway superintendent licensed under the County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act, during the calendar year preceding the year in which payment is made. For purposes of sections 39-2501 to 39-2510, county highway superintendent means a person who actually performs the following duties:</para><para>(1) Developing and annually updating a long-range plan based on needs and coordinated with adjacent local governmental units;</para><para>(2) Developing an annual program for design, construction, and maintenance;</para><para>(3) Developing an annual budget based on programmed projects and activities;</para><para>(4) Submitting such plans, programs, and budgets to the local governing body for approval;</para><para>(5) Implementing the capital improvements and maintenance activities provided in the approved plans, programs, and budgets; and</para><para>(6) Preparing and submitting annually to the Board of Public Roads Classifications and Standards the county's one-year plans, six-year plans, or annual metropolitan transportation improvement programs for highway, road, and street improvements under sections 39-2115 to 39-2117, 39-2119, and 39-2119.01 and a report showing the actual receipts, expenditures, and accomplishments compared with those budgeted and programmed in the county's annual plans as set forth in section 39-2120.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 315, &#167; 2, p. 1133; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 724, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 500, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB277, &#167; 7.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act,</emphasis> see section 39-2301.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>