<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2507" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2507</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Allocation of funds for road purposes; factors used.</catchline><para id="id00">The following factors and weights shall be used in determining the amount to be allocated to each of the counties or municipal counties for road purposes each year:</para><para id="id00">(1) Rural population of each county or municipal county, as determined by the most recent federal census, twenty percent;</para><para id="id00">(2) Total population of each county or municipal county, as determined by the most recent federal census, ten percent;</para><para id="id00">(3) Lineal feet of bridges twenty feet or more in length and all overpasses in each county or municipal county, as determined by the most recent inventory available within the Department of Transportation, ten percent, and for purposes of this subdivision a bridge or overpass located partly in one county or municipal county and partly in another shall be considered as being located one-half in each county or municipal county;</para><para id="id00">(4) Total motor vehicle registrations, other than prorated commercial vehicles, in the rural areas of each county or municipal county, as determined from the most recent information available from the Department of Motor Vehicles, twenty percent;</para><para id="id00">(5) Total motor vehicle registrations, other than prorated commercial vehicles, in each county or municipal county as determined from the most recent information available from the Department of Motor Vehicles, ten percent;</para><para id="id00">(6) Total miles of county or municipal county and township roads within each county or municipal county, as determined by the most recent inventory available within the Department of Transportation, twenty percent; and</para><para id="id00">(7) Value of farm products sold from each county or municipal county, as determined from the most recent federal Census of Agriculture, ten percent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 315, &#167; 7, p. 1135; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 165. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>