<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" id="id6" statutenumber="39-2215"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2215</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Highway Trust Fund; created; credit to the State Highway Capital Improvement Fund; allocation of remainder; investment; State Treasurer; transfer; disbursements.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created in the state treasury a special fund to be known as the Highway Trust Fund.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, all funds credited to the Highway Trust Fund pursuant to sections 66-489.02, 66-499, 66-4,140, 66-4,147, 66-6,108, and 66-6,109.02, and related penalties and interest, shall be allocated as provided in such sections.</para><para>(3) All sums of money credited to the Highway Trust Fund pursuant to subdivision (2)(c) of section 77-27,132 shall only be allocated to the Highway Cash Fund and shall not be used for the purposes described in subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(4) The State Treasurer shall monthly credit, from those portions of the Highway Trust Fund otherwise allocated to the Highway Cash Fund, to the State Highway Capital Improvement Fund an amount equal to the sums of money credited to the Highway Trust Fund by subdivision (2)(c) of section 77-27,132, but in no event less than seventy million dollars annually. Such credit shall occur prior to allocating funds from the Highway Trust Fund to the Highway Cash Fund. Such credited funds shall only be derived from revenue closely related to the use of highways, including, but not limited to, motor vehicle fuel taxes, diesel fuel taxes, compressed fuel taxes, and alternative fuel fees related to highway use retained by the state, all motor vehicle registration fees retained by the state other than those fees credited to the State Recreation Road Fund, and other highway-user taxes, fees, and penalties imposed by state law. The remainder of such funds shall thereafter be credited to the Highway Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) All other motor vehicle fuel taxes, diesel fuel taxes, compressed fuel taxes, and alternative fuel fees related to highway use retained by the state, all motor vehicle registration fees retained by the state other than those fees credited to the State Recreation Road Fund pursuant to subdivision (3) of section 60-3,156, and other highway-user taxes imposed by state law and allocated to the Highway Trust Fund, except for the proceeds of the sales and use taxes derived from motor vehicles, trailers, and semitrailers credited to the fund pursuant to section 77-27,132, are hereby irrevocably pledged for the terms of the bonds issued prior to January 1, 1988, to the payment of the principal, interest, and redemption premium, if any, of such bonds as they mature and become due at maturity or prior redemption and for any reserves therefor and shall, as received by the State Treasurer, be deposited in the fund for such purpose.</para><para>(6) Of the money in the fund specified in subsection (5) of this section which is not required for the use specified in such subsection, (a) an amount to be determined annually by the Legislature through the appropriations process may be transferred to the Motor Fuel Tax Enforcement and Collection Cash Fund for use as provided in section 66-739 on a monthly or other less frequent basis as determined by the appropriation language, (b) an amount to be determined annually by the Legislature through the appropriations process shall be transferred to the License Plate Cash Fund as certified by the Director of Motor Vehicles, and (c) the remaining money may be used for the purchase for retirement of the bonds issued prior to January 1, 1988, in the open market.</para><para>(7) The State Treasurer shall monthly transfer, from the proceeds of the sales and use taxes credited to the Highway Trust Fund and any money remaining in the fund after the requirements of subsections (2) through (6) of this section are satisfied, thirty thousand dollars to the Grade Crossing Protection Fund.</para><para>(8) Except as provided in subsection (9) of this section, the balance of the Highway Trust Fund shall be allocated fifty-three and one-third percent, less the amount provided for in section 39-847.01, to the Department of Transportation, twenty-three and one-third percent, less the amount provided for in section 39-847.01, to the various counties for road purposes, and twenty-three and one-third percent to the various municipalities for street purposes. If bonds are issued pursuant to subsection (2) of section 39-2223, the portion allocated to the department shall be credited monthly to the Highway Restoration and Improvement Bond Fund, and if no bonds are issued pursuant to such subsection, the portion allocated to the department shall be credited monthly to the Highway Cash Fund. The portions allocated to the counties and municipalities shall be credited monthly to the Highway Allocation Fund and distributed monthly as provided by law. Vehicles accorded prorated registration pursuant to section 60-3,198 shall not be included in any formula involving motor vehicle registrations used to determine the allocation and distribution of state funds for highway purposes to political subdivisions.</para><para>(9) If it is determined by December 20 of any year that a county will receive from its allocation of state-collected highway revenue and from any funds relinquished to it by municipalities within its boundaries an amount in such year which is less than such county received in state-collected highway revenue in calendar year 1969, based upon the 1976 tax rates for highway-user fuels and registration fees, the department shall notify the State Treasurer that an amount equal to the sum necessary to provide such county with funds equal to such county's 1969 highway allocation for such year shall be transferred to such county from the Highway Trust Fund. Such makeup funds shall be matched by the county as provided in sections 39-2501 to 39-2510. The balance remaining in the fund after such transfer shall then be reallocated as provided in subsection (8) of this section.</para><para>(10) The State Treasurer shall disburse the money in the Highway Trust Fund as directed by resolution of the commission. All disbursements from the fund shall be made by electronic funds transfer by the Director of Administrative Services. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act and the earnings, if any, credited to the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 309, &#167; 15, p. 1111; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 53, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 571, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 22, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 118, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1089, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 599, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 632, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 258, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 602, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 319, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 182, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 563, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1144, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 228; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB846, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB170, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB289, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 159; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB509, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB727, &#167; 37. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>