<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2308.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2308.02</statuteno><catchline>Class A license; renewal; professional development required.</catchline><para>(1) As a condition for renewal of a license issued pursuant to section 39-2308.01, the holder of a Class A license shall be required to have successfully completed twenty hours of professional development within the preceding three years. Any license holder who completes in excess of twenty hours of professional development within the preceding three years may have the excess, not to exceed ten hours, applied to the requirement for the next triennium.</para><para>(2) The board of examiners shall not renew the Class A license of a license holder who has failed to complete the professional development requirements pursuant to subsection (1) of this section unless he or she can show good cause why he or she was unable to comply with such requirements. If the board determines that good cause was shown, the board shall permit such license holder to make up all outstanding required hours of professional development. If the board determines that good cause was not shown or if the license holder requests renewal as a Class B licensee, the board shall issue a Class B license. Renewal of such Class B license shall be governed by section 39-2308.</para><para>(3) A holder of a Class B license who previously held a Class A license may be reissued a Class A license by:</para><para>(a) Electing to either:</para><para>(i) Complete one and one-half of the triennial requirements for professional development as set forth in the rules and regulations of the board; or</para><para>(ii) Reapply under section 39-2308.01; and</para><para>(b) Paying the seventy-five-dollar Class A application fee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 500, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>