<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id787"><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways and Bridges" statutenumber="39-2819"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2819</statuteno><catchline>Submission of proposals; sealed; rank of construction managers; negotiation of contract.</catchline><para>(1) Construction managers shall submit proposals as required by the request for proposals.</para><para>(2) Proposals shall be sealed and shall not be opened until expiration of the time established for making the proposals as set forth in the request for proposals.</para><para>(3) Proposals may be withdrawn at any time prior to signing a contract for preconstruction services. The department shall have the right to reject any and all proposals at no cost to the department. The department may thereafter solicit new proposals or may cancel the construction manager-general contractor procurement process.</para><para>(4) The department shall rank the construction managers in accordance with the qualification-based selection process and pursuant to the criteria in the request for proposals. The department may meet with construction managers prior to the ranking.</para><para>(5) The department may attempt to negotiate a contract for preconstruction services with the highest ranked construction manager and may enter into a contract for preconstruction services after negotiations. If the department is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract for preconstruction services with the highest ranked construction manager, the department may terminate negotiations with that construction manager. The department may then undertake negotiations with the second highest ranked construction manager and may enter into a contract for preconstruction services after negotiations. If the department is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract with the second highest ranked construction manager, the department may undertake negotiations with the third highest ranked construction manager, if any, and may enter into a contract for preconstruction services after negotiations.</para><para>(6) If the department is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract for preconstruction services with any of the ranked construction managers, the department may either revise the request for proposals and solicit new proposals or cancel the construction manager-general contractor contract process under sections 39-2808 to 39-2823.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB960, &#167; 19. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>