<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2304</statuteno><catchline>Board of Examiners for County Highway and City Street Superintendents; created; members; qualifications; appointment; term; vacancy; expenses.</catchline><para>The Board of Examiners for County Highway and City Street Superintendents is created. The board shall consist of seven members to be appointed by the Governor, four of whom shall be county representatives, and three of whom shall be municipal representatives.</para><para>Immediately preceding appointment to the board, each county and municipal representative shall hold a current license as a county highway or city street superintendent pursuant to the County Highway and City Street Superintendents Act. Of the county representatives, no more than one member shall be appointed from each class of county as defined in section 23-1114.01, and of the municipal representatives, no more than one shall be appointed from each congressional district, one of whom shall be a representative of a city of the metropolitan or primary class, one of whom shall be a representative of a city of the first class, and one of whom shall be a representative of a city of the second class or a village.</para><para>In making such appointments, the Governor may give consideration to a list of licensed county highway engineers, county highway superintendents, and county surveyors submitted by the Nebraska Association of County Officials and to a list of licensed city street superintendents or street commissioners, city engineers, and public works directors submitted by the League of Nebraska Municipalities. Two county representatives shall initially be appointed for terms of two years each, and two county representatives shall initially be appointed for terms of four years each. One municipal representative shall initially be appointed for a term of two years, and two municipal representatives shall initially be appointed for terms of four years each. Thereafter, all such appointments shall be for terms of four years each.</para><para>In the event a county or municipal representative loses his or her license as a county highway or city street superintendent, such person shall no longer be qualified to serve on the board and such seat shall be vacant. In the event of a vacancy occurring on the board for any reason, such vacancy shall be filled by appointment by the Governor for the remainder of the unexpired term. Such appointed person shall meet the same requirements and qualifications as the member whose vacancy he or she is filling.</para><para>Members of the board shall receive no compensation for their services as members of the board but shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred while engaged in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 144, &#167; 4, p. 666; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 175, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 500, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>