<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Highways And Bridges" statutenumber="39-2223"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>39-2223</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; issuance; amount.</catchline><para>(1) Under the authority granted by Article XIII, section 1, of the Constitution of Nebraska, the Legislature hereby authorizes the issuance of bonds in the principal amount of twenty million dollars in 1969 and in the principal amount of twenty million dollars on or before June 30, 1977, with the proceeds thereof to be used for the construction of highways in this state, the Legislature expressly finding that the need for such construction requires such action. Such bonds shall in all respects comply with the provisions of Article XIII, section 1, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(2) Under the authority granted by Article XIII, section 1, of the Constitution of Nebraska, the Legislature hereby authorizes after July 1, 1988, the issuance of bonds in a principal amount to be determined by the commission, not to exceed fifty million dollars. The outstanding principal amount of such bonds may exceed such limit if and to the extent that the commission determines that the issuance of advance refunding bonds under section 39-2226 in a principal amount greater than the bonds to be refunded would reduce the aggregate bond principal and interest requirements payable from the bond fund. The proceeds of such issues shall be used exclusively (a) for the construction, resurfacing, reconstruction, rehabilitation, and restoration of highways in this state, the Legislature expressly finding that the need for such construction and reconstruction work and the vital importance of the highway system to the welfare and safety of all Nebraskans requires such action, or (b) to eliminate or alleviate cash-flow problems resulting from the receipt of federal funds. Such bonds shall in all respects comply with the provisions of Article XIII, section 1, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) Under the authority granted by Article XIII, section 1, of the Constitution of Nebraska, the Legislature hereby authorizes after July 1, 2023, in addition to the authority granted in subsections (1) and (2) of this section, the issuance of bonds in one or more series in an aggregate principal amount to be determined by the commission, not to exceed four hundred fifty million dollars. The outstanding principal amount of such bonds may exceed such limit if and to the extent that the commission determines that the issuance of advance refunding bonds under section 39-2226 in a principal amount greater than the bonds to be refunded would reduce the aggregate bond principal and interest requirements payable from the State Highway Capital Improvement Fund. The proceeds of such issues shall be used exclusively for purposes of the Build Nebraska Act, the Legislature expressly finding that the need for such construction and reconstruction work and the vital importance of the highway system to the welfare and safety of all Nebraskans requires such action. Such bonds shall in all respects comply with the provisions of Article XIII, section 1, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 314, &#167; 1, p. 1132; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 401, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 632, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB727, &#167; 41. </para><operativedate>June 7, 2023</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>