<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-154"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-154</statuteno><catchline>Director; information; disclosure;
confidentiality; privilege.</catchline><para>(1) Unless otherwise expressly
prohibited by Chapter 44, the director may:</para>
<para>(a) Share documents, materials, or other information, including otherwise
confidential and privileged documents, materials, or information, with other
state, federal, foreign, and international regulatory and law enforcement
agencies, the International
Association of Insurance Supervisors, the Bank for International Settlements, and the National Association
of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries if the recipient
agrees to maintain the confidential or privileged status of the document,
material, or other information;</para>
<para>(b) Receive documents, materials, or other information, including otherwise
confidential and privileged documents, materials, or information, from other
state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies, the International Association of Insurance
Supervisors, the Bank for International Settlements, and the National Association
of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries. The director
shall maintain as confidential or privileged any document, material, or other
information received pursuant to an information-sharing agreement entered
into pursuant to this section with notice or the understanding that the document,
material, or other information is confidential or privileged under the laws
of the jurisdiction that is the source of the document, material, or information;
and</para>
<para>(c) Enter into agreements governing sharing and use of information consistent
with this subsection.</para>
<para>(2)(a) All confidential and privileged information obtained by or disclosed
to the director by other state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory
and law enforcement agencies,
the International Association of Insurance Supervisors, the Bank for International
Settlements, or the
National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries
pursuant to this section with notice or the understanding that it is confidential
or privileged under the laws of the jurisdiction that is the source of the
document, material, or other information shall:</para>
<para>(i) Be confidential and privileged;</para>
<para>(ii) Not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant
to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09;</para>
<para>(iii) Not be subject to subpoena; and</para>
<para>(iv) Not be subject to discovery or admissible in evidence in any private
civil action.</para>
<para>(b) Notwithstanding the provisions of subdivision (2)(a) of this section,
the director may use the documents, materials, or other information in any
regulatory or legal action brought by the director.</para>
<para>(3) The director, and any other person while acting under the authority
of the director who has received information from other state, federal, foreign,
or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies, the International Association of Insurance Supervisors,
the Bank for International Settlements, or the National Association of Insurance Commissioners
or its affiliates and subsidiaries pursuant to this section, may not, and
shall not be required to, testify in any private civil action concerning such
information.</para>
<para>(4) Nothing in this section shall constitute a waiver of any applicable
privilege or claim of confidentiality in the documents, materials, or other
information received from state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory
and law enforcement agencies,
the International Association of Insurance Supervisors, the Bank for International
Settlements, or the
National Association of Insurance Commissioners or its affiliates and subsidiaries
pursuant to this section as a result of disclosure to the director or as a
result of information sharing authorized by this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>