<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id24"  statutenumber="44-7,103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7,103</statuteno><catchline>Continuing coverage for children
to age thirty; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, health benefit plan means
any expense-incurred individual or group sickness and accident insurance policy,
health maintenance organization contract, subscriber contract, or self-funded
employee benefit plan to the extent not preempted by federal law, except for
any policy or contract that provides coverage only for excepted benefits as
defined in the federal Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act
of 1996, 29 U.S.C. 1191b, and regulations adopted pursuant to the act, as
such act and regulations existed on January 1, 2009, or any policy or contract
that provides coverage for a specified disease or other limited-benefit coverage.</para>
<para>(2) Notwithstanding
section 44-3,131, any health benefit plan that provides coverage for children
shall provide for continuing coverage for such children as follows:</para>
<para>(a) If coverage
under the health benefit plan would otherwise terminate because a covered
child ceases to be a dependent, ceases to be a full-time student, or attains
an age which exceeds the specified age at which coverage ceases pursuant to
the plan, the health benefit plan shall provide the option to the insured
to continue coverage for such child through the end of the month in which
the child (i) marries, (ii) ceases to be a resident of the state, unless the
child is under nineteen years of age or is enrolled on a full-time basis in
any college, university, or trade school, (iii) receives coverage under another
health benefit plan or a self-funded employee benefit plan that is not included
in the definition of a health benefit plan under subsection (1) of this section
but provides similar coverage, or (iv) attains thirty years of age; and</para>
<para>(b) The health
benefit plan may require:</para><para>(i) A written election from the insured; and</para>
<para>(ii) An additional
premium for the child. Such premium shall not vary based upon the health status
of the child and shall not exceed the amount the health benefit plan would
receive for an identical individual for a single adult insured. No employer
shall be required to contribute to any additional premium under this subdivision.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB551, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>