<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-416.09" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-416.09</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Rules and regulations.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out sections 44-416.05 to 44-416.10.</para><para>(2)(a) The director may also adopt and promulgate rules and regulations applicable only to reinsurance arrangements described in subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para><para>(b) Any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to this subsection shall only apply to reinsurance relating to:</para><para>(i) Life insurance policies with guaranteed nonlevel gross premiums or guaranteed nonlevel benefits;</para><para>(ii) Universal life insurance policies with provisions resulting in the ability of a policyholder to keep a policy in force over a secondary guarantee period;</para><para>(iii) Variable annuities with guaranteed death or living benefits;</para><para>(iv) Long-term care insurance policies; or</para><para>(v) Such other life and health insurance and annuity products as determined by the director.</para><para>(c) Any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to subdivision (b)(i) or (b)(ii) of this subsection may apply to any treaty containing (i) policies issued prior to January 1, 2015, if risk pertaining to such policies is ceded in connection with the treaty, in whole or in part, on or after January 1, 2015, or (ii) policies issued on or after January 1, 2015.</para><para>(d) Any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to this subsection may require the ceding insurer, in calculating the amounts or forms of security required to be held, to use the valuation manual prescribed by the director pursuant to section 44-8908.</para><para>(e) Any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to this subsection shall not apply to a cession to an assuming insurer that:</para><para>(i) Is a certified reinsurer in this state pursuant to subdivision (6)(a) of section 44-416.06; or</para><para>(ii) Maintains at least two hundred fifty million dollars in capital and surplus when determined in accordance with accounting practices and procedures manuals as prescribed by the director in substantial conformity with the Accounting Practices and Procedures Manual adopted by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and is determined by the director to be:</para><para>(A) Licensed to transact insurance or reinsurance in at least twenty-six states; or</para><para>(B) Licensed to transact insurance or reinsurance in at least ten states and either licensed to transact insurance or is an accredited reinsurer in a total of at least thirty-five states.</para><para>(f) The authority to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations pursuant to this subsection does not limit the director’s general authority to adopt rules and regulations pursuant to subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB815, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>