<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-767"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-767</statuteno><catchline>Sickness and accident insurance; other insurance not affected.</catchline><para>Nothing in sections 44-709 to 44-767 shall apply to or affect (1) any policy of workers' compensation insurance or any policy of liability insurance with or without supplementary coverage therein, (2) any policy or contract of reinsurance, or (3) life insurance, endowment or annuity contracts, or contracts supplemental thereto which contain only such provisions relating to sickness and accident insurance as (a) provide additional benefits in case of death, dismemberment, or loss of sight by accident and (b) operate to safeguard such contracts against lapse, or to give a special surrender value or special benefit or annuity in the event that the insured or annuitant shall become totally and permanently disabled, as defined by the contract or supplemental contract. Sections 44-710.03 to 44-710.09, 44-710.12, and 44-710.16 shall not apply to those forms of sickness and accident policies enumerated in section 44-758 or sections 44-760 to 44-765, except that no such policy shall contain any provision relative to notice or proof of loss, the time for paying benefits, or the time within which suit may be brought upon the policy, which in the opinion of the Director of Insurance is less favorable to the insured than would be permitted by the policy provisions set forth in sections 44-710.03 and 44-710.04.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 164, &#167; 19, p. 471; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 188, &#167; 21, p. 660; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 359, &#167; 26, p. 1278; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 157. </para></source><annotation><para>In accordance with this section, a group health insurance policy may contain contractual limitations periods so long as they are not "less favorable to the insured than would be permitted" under section 44-710.03. Brodine v. Blue Cross Blue Shield, 272 Neb. 713, 724 N.W.2d 321 (2006).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 