<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-913"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-913</statuteno><catchline>Opt out exception for service providers and joint marketing.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The opt out requirements in sections 44-907 and 44-910 do not apply when a licensee provides nonpublic personal financial information to a nonaffiliated third party to perform services for the licensee or functions on the licensee's behalf, if the licensee:</para><para>(i) Provides the initial notice in accordance with section 44-904; and</para><para>(ii) Enters into a contractual agreement with the third party that prohibits the third party from disclosing or using the information other than to carry out the purposes for which the licensee disclosed the information, including use under an exception in section 44-914 or 44-915 in the ordinary course of business to carry out those purposes.</para><para>(b) If a licensee discloses nonpublic personal financial information under this section to a financial institution with which the licensee performs joint marketing, the licensee's contractual agreement with that institution meets the requirements of subdivision (1)(a)(ii) of this section if it prohibits the institution from disclosing or using the nonpublic personal financial information except as necessary to carry out the joint marketing or under an exception in section 44-914 or 44-915 in the ordinary course of business to carry out that joint marketing.</para><para>(2) The services a nonaffiliated third party performs for a licensee under subsection (1) of this section may include marketing of the licensee's own products or services or marketing of financial products or services offered pursuant to joint agreements between the licensee and one or more financial institutions.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, joint agreement means a written contract pursuant to which a licensee and one or more financial institutions jointly offer, endorse, or sponsor a financial product or service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc>