<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-251"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-251</statuteno><catchline>Plan of exchange; approval; submit to shareholders.</catchline><para>(1) Such plan of exchange shall then be submitted to the Director of Insurance for his or her approval after a hearing at which the shareholders of the company to be acquired shall have an opportunity to be heard upon at least ten days' notice to be given by the company to its shareholders of record at the time of mailing such notice. The director shall approve such plan within twenty days after such hearing unless he or she finds that the terms and conditions thereof for the issuance and exchange of securities or other consideration are unfair to the shareholders of the company to be acquired or if he or she finds that any of the conditions set forth in subsection (1) of section 44-2127 exist.</para><para>(2) After having obtained the approval of the Director of Insurance, the plan of exchange shall be submitted to a vote at a meeting of the shareholders of the company to be acquired. Such meeting may be either an annual or a special meeting. Notice shall be given not less than twenty days before such meeting to each shareholder of record as of the time of mailing such notice. Such notice shall be deemed to be delivered when deposited in the United States mail with postage prepaid, addressed to the shareholder at his or her address as it appears on the records of the company. A copy or summary of the plan of exchange shall be included in or enclosed with such notice. Each outstanding share of such company shall be entitled to vote on the proposed plan, whether or not such share has voting rights under the provisions of the articles of incorporation of such company. The affirmative vote of two-thirds of all of the outstanding shares, in person or by proxy, shall be necessary for the approval of any such plan by such shareholders.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 296, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 44-133.04; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 38. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 