<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-910"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-910</statuteno><catchline>Disclosure of financial information to nonaffiliated third party; when.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as otherwise authorized in the Privacy of Insurance Consumer Information Act, a licensee may not, directly or through any affiliate, disclose any nonpublic personal financial information about a consumer to a nonaffiliated third party unless:</para><para>(i) The licensee has provided to the consumer an initial notice as required under section 44-904;</para><para>(ii) The licensee has provided to the consumer an opt out notice as required in section 44-907;</para><para>(iii) The licensee has given the consumer a reasonable opportunity, before it discloses the information to the nonaffiliated third party to opt out of the disclosure; and</para><para>(iv) The consumer does not opt out.</para><para>(b) A licensee shall be deemed to provide a consumer with a reasonable opportunity to opt out pursuant to subdivision (1)(a)(iii) of this section if:</para><para>(i) The licensee mails the notices required in subdivision (1)(a) of this section to the consumer and allows the consumer to opt out by mailing a form, calling a toll-free telephone number, or any other reasonable means within thirty days from the date the licensee mailed the notices;</para><para>(ii) A customer opens an online account with a licensee and agrees to receive the notices required in subdivision (1)(a) of this section electronically, and the licensee allows the customer to opt out by any reasonable means within thirty days after the date that the customer acknowledges receipt of the notices in conjunction with opening the account; or</para><para>(iii) For an isolated transaction such as providing the consumer with an insurance quote, a licensee provides the consumer with a reasonable opportunity to opt out if the licensee provides the notices required in subdivision (1)(a) of this section at the time of the transaction and requests that the consumer decide, as a necessary part of the transaction, whether to opt out before completing the transaction.</para><para>(c) For purposes of this section, opt out means a direction by the consumer that the licensee not disclose nonpublic personal financial information about that consumer to a nonaffiliated third party other than as permitted by sections 44-913 to 44-915.</para><para>(2) A licensee shall comply with this section, regardless of whether the licensee and the consumer have established a customer relationship. Unless a licensee complies with this section, the licensee may not, directly or through any affiliate, disclose any nonpublic personal financial information about a consumer that the licensee has collected, regardless of whether the licensee collected it before or after receiving the direction to opt out from the consumer.</para><para>(3) A licensee may allow a consumer to select certain nonpublic personal financial information or certain nonaffiliated third parties with respect to which the consumer wishes to opt out.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 