<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-425"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-425</statuteno><catchline>Actuarial opinions; supporting memorandum; confidentiality.</catchline><para>Every opinion required by section 44-421 shall be governed by the following provisions in addition to the provisions of section 44-424:</para><para>(1) A memorandum, in form and substance acceptable to the director, shall be prepared to support each actuarial opinion and made available to the director upon request;</para><para>(2) If the insurance company fails to provide a supporting memorandum at the request of the director within a period specified by rule or regulation or the director determines that the supporting memorandum provided by the insurance company fails to meet the standards prescribed or is otherwise unacceptable to the director, the director may engage a qualified actuary at the expense of the company to review the opinion and the basis for the opinion and prepare such supporting memorandum as is required by the director;</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subdivisions (4) and (5) of this section, any memorandum in support of the opinion, and any other material provided by the company to the director in connection with the opinion, shall be kept confidential by the director and shall not be made public and shall not be subject to subpoena, other than for the purpose of defending an action seeking damages from any person by reason of any action required by this section or by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated hereunder, except that the memorandum or other material may otherwise be released by the director (a) with the written consent of the company or (b) to the American Academy of Actuaries upon request stating that the memorandum or other material is required for the purpose of professional disciplinary proceedings and setting forth procedures satisfactory to the director for preserving the confidentiality of the memorandum or other material. Once any portion of the confidential memorandum is released by the company to the news media or other governmental agency other than a state insurance department or is cited by the company in its marketing, all portions of the memorandum become public information and are no longer confidential;</para><para>(4) The director may provide the memorandum in support of the opinion, and any other material provided by the company to the director in connection with the opinion, to other state, federal, foreign, and international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality of the information, documents, and copies; and</para><para>(5) The director may receive memorandums in support of an opinion, and any other material provided by the company to the director in connection with an opinion, from other state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and from the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries. The director shall maintain information received pursuant to this subdivision as confidential or privileged if received with notice or the understanding that it is confidential or privileged under the laws of the jurisdiction that is the source of the information. Such information shall not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, subject to subpoena, subject to discovery, or admissible in evidence in any private civil action, except that the director may use such information in any regulatory or legal action brought by the director. The director, and any other person while acting under the authority of the director who has received information pursuant to this subdivision, may not, and shall not be required to, testify in any private civil action concerning any information subject to this section. Nothing in this section shall constitute a waiver of any applicable privilege or claim of confidentiality in the information received pursuant to this subdivision as a result of information sharing authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 978, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 45. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 