<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-796"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-796</statuteno><catchline>Coverage for certain hearing screening tests; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding section 44-3,131:</para><para>(a) Under a health insurance plan which provides coverage for hearing screening tests for newborns and infants, such coverage shall be subject to copayment, coinsurance, deductible, and dollar-limit provisions to the extent that other medical services covered by the health insurance plan are subject to such provisions; and</para><para>(b) This section applies to health insurance plans delivered, issued for delivery, or which become effective on or after April 11, 2000, and also applies to all renewals or changes which are effective on or after April 11, 2000.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, health insurance plan means a plan which includes dependent coverage for children which is delivered, issued for delivery, renewed, extended, or modified in this state. A health insurance plan includes any such group or individual sickness and accident insurance policy, health maintenance organization contract, subscriber contract, employee medical, surgical, or hospital care benefit plan, or self-funded employee benefit plan to the extent not preempted by federal law. Health insurance plan includes any policy, contract, or plan offered or administered by the state or its political subdivisions. Health insurance plan does not include policies providing coverage for a specified disease, accident-only coverage, hospital indemnity coverage, disability income coverage, medicare supplement coverage, long-term care coverage, or other limited-benefit coverage.</para><para>(3) The Department of Insurance shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to implement this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 950, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 