<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3,158"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3,158</statuteno><catchline>Workers' compensation insurance; assigned risk system; director; powers; certain actions of employer; effect.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Assigned risk employer means a Nebraska employer that is in good faith entitled to, but is unable to obtain, workers' compensation insurance through ordinary methods; and </para><para>(b) Director means the Director of Insurance.</para><para>(2)(a) The director shall enter into an agreement with one or more workers' compensation insurers to provide workers' compensation insurance to assigned risk employers. In selecting an insurer to become an assigned risk insurer, the director shall consider the cost of coverage to assigned risk employers, the loss control and claims handling services available from the workers' compensation insurer, the financial condition of the workers' compensation insurer, and any other relevant factors. An agreement entered into under this subsection may not exceed five years.</para><para>(b) If the director determines that the cost of workers' compensation insurance premiums for an insurer to provide assigned risk coverage pursuant to such an agreement would be unreasonably high, the director may enter into an agreement in which the assigned risk insurer covers a portion of the losses incurred by the assigned risk employer. Any agreement that involves an average rate level of less than two and one-half times the prospective loss costs approved for an advisory organization pursuant to section 44-7511 shall not be considered unreasonably high for the purposes of this section. Pursuant to any such agreement, remaining losses shall be assessed against all workers' compensation insurers writing workers' compensation insurance in this state and risk management pools created under the Intergovernmental Risk Management Act based on their workers' compensation premiums written in this state or contributions made to risk management pools. Assigned risk premiums shall be excluded from the basis for such assessments.</para><para>(c) If the assigned risk system described in subdivisions (2)(a) and (b) of this section ceases to be viable because no qualified insurer is willing to provide workers' compensation coverage at an average rate level of two and one-half times the prospective loss costs approved for an advisory organization pursuant to section 44-7511 without also requiring substantial sharing of losses with all other workers' compensation insurers writing workers' compensation insurance in this state and risk management pools created under the Intergovernmental Risk Management Act, then the director may, after consultation with insurers authorized to issue workers' compensation insurance policies in this state, create a reasonable alternative assigned risk system involving the sharing of premiums and losses for assigned risk employers among all such workers' compensation insurers writing workers' compensation insurance in this state and such risk management pools. If established, such alternative assigned risk system shall not utilize an average rate level of less than two and one-half times the prospective loss costs approved for an advisory organization pursuant to section 44-7511.</para><para>(3) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para><para>(4) An employer shall not be considered to be in good faith entitled to be covered by workers' compensation insurance under this section if:</para><para>(a) The employer is required to establish a safety committee pursuant to sections 48-443 to 48-445 and is not in compliance with such sections;</para><para>(b) The employer is in default on workers' compensation premiums;</para><para>(c) The employer has failed to reimburse an insurer for amounts to be repaid pursuant to workers' compensation insurance written on a policy with a deductible;</para><para>(d) The employer has failed to provide an insurer reasonable access to books and records necessary for a premium audit;</para><para>(e) The employer has defrauded or attempted to defraud an insurer; or</para><para>(f) The employer is found to have been owned or controlled by persons who owned or controlled a prior employer that is or would be ineligible for coverage pursuant to subdivisions (4)(b) through (e) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 572, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 757, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 42; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 48-146.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Intergovernmental Risk Management Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4301.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>