<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-798"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-798</statuteno><catchline>Coverage for dental care requiring hospitalization and general anesthesia; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding section 44-3,131, (a) any employer group sickness and accident insurance policy or subscriber contract delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state and any employer group hospital, medical, or surgical expense-incurred policy, except for policies that provide coverage for a specified disease or other limited-benefit coverage, and (b) any self-funded employee benefit plan to the extent not preempted by federal law shall include coverage for the reasonable cost of hospitalization and general anesthesia in order for a covered person to safely receive dental care if he or she is under eight years of age or is developmentally disabled.</para><para>(2)(a) This section does not prevent application of deductible or copayment provisions contained in the group policy, contract, or benefit plan or require that coverage under a group policy, contract, or benefit plan be extended to any other procedures, including dental care.</para><para>(b) This section does not prevent application of prior authorization requirements or other requirements of a managed care plan as established by the group policy, contract, or benefit plan, including a requirement that coverage under subsection (1) of this section shall be provided only through a contracted network of providers.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, the reasonable determination that hospitalization and general anesthesia are necessary for safe dental care shall be made by the entity providing coverage under subsection (1) of this section. Medical necessity shall be as defined by the group policy, contract, or benefit plan.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, hospital and hospitalization includes ambulatory surgical center and care at an ambulatory surgical center.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1253, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 