<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id467"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7,122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7,122</statuteno><catchline>Biomarker testing; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 44-7,122 to 44-7,124:</para><para>(1) Biomarker means a characteristic that is objectively measured and evaluated as an indicator of normal biological processes, pathogenic processes, or pharmacologic responses to a specific therapeutic intervention, including known gene-drug interactions for medications being considered for use or already being administered. Biomarkers include, but are not limited to, gene mutations, characteristics of genes, or protein expression;</para><para>(2) Biomarker testing means the analysis of tissue, blood, or other biospecimen for the presence of a biomarker. Biomarker testing includes, but is not limited to, single-analyte tests, multi-plex panel tests, protein expression, and whole exome, whole genome, and whole transcriptome sequencing;</para><para>(3) Clinical utility means sufficient medical and scientific evidence indicating that the use of a biomarker test will provide meaningful information that affects treatment decisions and guides improvement of net health outcomes including an improved quality of life or longer survival;</para><para>(4) Consensus statements means statements developed by an independent, multidisciplinary panel of experts utilizing a transparent methodology and reporting structure and with a conflict of interest policy. These statements are aimed at specific clinical circumstances and based on the best available evidence for the purpose of optimizing the outcomes of clinical care;</para><para>(5) Health carrier has the same meaning as in section 44-1303; and</para><para>(6) Nationally recognized clinical practice guidelines means evidence-based clinical practice guidelines developed by independent organizations or medical professional societies utilizing a transparent methodology and reporting structure and with a conflict of interest policy. Clinical practice guidelines establish standards of care informed by a systematic review of evidence and an assessment of the benefits and risks of alternative care options and include recommendations intended to optimize patient care.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB77, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>