<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-101.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-101.01</statuteno><catchline>Department of Insurance; general powers; director; duties.</catchline><para>The Department of Insurance shall have general supervision, control, and regulation of insurance companies, associations, and societies and the business of insurance in Nebraska, including companies in process of organization. The Director of Insurance shall be the chief administrative officer of the department. The director shall have the power and duty to enforce and execute all the insurance laws of this state and to adopt and promulgate all needful rules and regulations for the purpose of carrying out the true spirit and meaning of Chapter 44 and all laws relating to the business of insurance and, to that end, may authorize and empower an assistant or employee to do any and all things that he or she may do and on his or her behalf, and he or she shall see that all laws respecting insurance companies and insurance agents are faithfully executed. The director or his or her representative shall issue all certificates and licenses as provided for in Chapter 44. If the applicant is an individual, the application for a certificate or license shall include the applicant's social security number. The director and his or her authorized representative shall have the power and authority to do all things and to perform all acts the department is given the power and authority to do.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 3, p. 396; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3139; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. III, &#167; 1, p. 576; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7745; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-201; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-104; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-501; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 360, &#167; 3, p. 1284; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 113, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 109. </para></source><annotation><para>The Legislature has granted the director of the Department of Insurance statutory power to perform all acts the department has the power and authority to do. CenTra, Inc. v. Chandler Ins. Co., 248 Neb. 844, 540 N.W.2d 318 (1995).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 