<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-416.07" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-416.07</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Asset or reduction from liability for reinsurance; limitations; security required.</catchline><para>An asset or a reduction from liability for the reinsurance ceded by a domestic insurer to an assuming insurer not meeting the requirements of section 44-416.06 shall be allowed in an amount not exceeding the liabilities carried by the ceding insurer subject to any additional requirements contained in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Director of Insurance pursuant to subsection (2) of section 44-416.09 relating to or setting forth the valuation of assets or reserve credits, the amount and form of security supporting reinsurance arrangements, or the circumstances pursuant to which credit will be reduced or eliminated. The reduction shall be in the amount of funds held by or on behalf of the ceding insurer, including funds held in trust for the ceding insurer, under a reinsurance contract with the assuming insurer as security for the payment of obligations thereunder, if the security is held in the United States subject to withdrawal solely by, and under the exclusive control of, the ceding insurer, or, in the case of a trust, held in a qualified United States financial institution. This security may be in the form of:</para><para>(1) Cash;</para><para>(2) Securities approved by the Director of Insurance. The director may use the list of securities furnished by the Securities Valuation Office of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners, including those deemed exempt from filing as defined by the Purposes and Procedures Manual of the Securities Valuation Office, and qualifying as admitted assets;</para><para>(3)(a) Clean, irrevocable, unconditional letters of credit, issued or confirmed by a qualified United States financial institution effective no later than December 31 of the year for which the filing is being made, and in the possession of, or in trust for, the ceding insurer on or before the filing date of its annual statement; or</para><para>(b) Letters of credit meeting applicable standards of issuer acceptability as of the dates of their issuance or confirmation shall, notwithstanding the issuing or confirming institution's subsequent failure to meet applicable standards of issuer acceptability, continue to be acceptable as security until their expiration, extension, renewal, modification, or amendment, whichever first occurs; or</para><para>(4) Any other form of security acceptable to the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB298, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB815, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>