<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-513.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-513.02</statuteno><catchline>Reimbursement for prescription drugs and other pharmacy services; prohibited provisions.</catchline><para>(1) A medical benefit contract which provides reimbursement for prescription drugs, including contracts by health maintenance organizations and preferred provider organizations, shall not require a person to obtain prescription drugs from a mail-order pharmacy as a condition to obtaining reimbursement for such drugs. This subsection shall apply to contracts delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state on or after July 10, 1990.</para><para>(2)(a) A medical benefit contract, including any contract by a preferred provider organization but excluding any contract by a health maintenance organization, which provides reimbursement for prescription drugs and other pharmacy services shall not impose upon any person who is a party to or beneficiary of the contract a fee or copayment not equally imposed upon any party or beneficiary utilizing a mail-order pharmacy, and no such contract shall provide differences in coverage or impose any different conditions upon any person who is a party to or beneficiary of the contract not equally imposed upon any party or beneficiary utilizing a mail-order pharmacy. This subsection shall apply to contracts delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state on or after July 16, 1994.</para><para>(b) This subsection shall not apply to reimbursement for long-term maintenance drugs. Long-term maintenance drugs means medications which are dispensed pursuant to a single prescription for a period of no less than one hundred eighty days, exclusive of authorized refills, for the ongoing treatment of a chronic medical condition or disease or congenital condition or disorder.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 718, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 531, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 