<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-407.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-407.04</statuteno><catchline>Policies issued on or after operative date of law; adjusted premiums; basis of calculation; exception.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in subsection (c) of this section, the adjusted premiums for any policy shall be calculated on an annual basis and shall be such uniform percentage of the respective premiums specified in the policy for each policy year, excluding any extra premiums charged because of impairments or special hazards, that the present value, at the date of the policy, of all such adjusted premiums shall be equal to the sum of (i) the then present value of the future guaranteed benefits provided for by the policy, (ii) two percent of the amount of insurance, if the insurance be uniform in amount, or of the equivalent uniform amount, as hereinafter defined, if the amount of insurance varies with duration of the policy, (iii) forty percent of the adjusted premium for the first policy year, and (iv) twenty-five percent of either the adjusted premium for the first policy year or the adjusted premium for a whole life policy of the same uniform or equivalent uniform amount with uniform premiums for the whole of life issued at the same age for the same amount of insurance, whichever is less; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that in applying the percentages specified in (iii) and (iv) above, no adjusted premium shall be deemed to exceed four percent of the amount of insurance or uniform amount equivalent thereto. The date of a policy for the purpose of this section shall be the date as of which the rated age of the insured is determined.</para><para>(b) In the case of a policy providing an amount of insurance varying with duration of the policy, the equivalent uniform amount thereof for the purpose of this section shall be deemed to be the uniform amount of insurance provided by an otherwise similar policy, containing the same endowment benefit or benefits, if any, issued at the same age and for the same term, the amount of which does not vary with duration and the benefits under which have the same present value at the date of issue as the benefits under the policy; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that in the case of a policy providing a varying amount of insurance issued on the life of a child under age ten, the equivalent uniform amount may be computed as though the amount of insurance provided by the policy prior to the attainment of age ten were the amount provided by such policy at age ten.</para><para>(c) The adjusted premiums for any policy providing term insurance benefits by rider or supplemental policy provision shall be equal to (1) the adjusted premiums for an otherwise similar policy issued at the same age without such term insurance benefits, increased, during the period for which premiums for such term insurance benefits are payable, by (2) the adjusted premiums for such term insurance, the foregoing items (1) and (2) being calculated separately and as specified in subsections (a) and (b) of this section except that, for the purposes of (ii), (iii), and (iv) of subsection (a), the amount of insurance or equivalent uniform amount of insurance used in the calculation of the adjusted premiums referred to in (2) shall be equal to the excess of the corresponding amount determined for the entire policy over the amount used in the calculation of the adjusted premiums in subdivision (1) of this subsection.</para><para>(d) Except as provided in sections 44-407.08 and 44-407.09, all adjusted premiums and present values referred to in sections 44-407 to 44-407.09 and 44-407.24 to 44-407.26, shall for all policies of ordinary insurance be calculated on the basis of the Commissioners 1941 Standard Ordinary Mortality Table and such calculations for all policies of industrial insurance shall be made on the basis of the 1941 Standard Industrial Mortality Table; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that for any category of ordinary insurance issued on female risks, adjusted premiums and present values may be calculated according to an age not more than three years younger than the actual age of the insured. All calculations shall be made on the basis of the rate of interest, not exceeding three and one-half percent per annum, specified in the policy for calculating cash surrender values and paid-up nonforfeiture benefits; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that in calculating the present value of any paid-up term insurance with accompanying pure endowment, if any, offered as a nonforfeiture benefit, the rates of mortality assumed may be not more than one hundred and thirty percent of the rates of mortality according to such applicable table; <emphasis type="italic">and provided further,</emphasis> that for insurance issued on a substandard basis, the calculation of any such adjusted premiums and present values may be based on such other table of mortality as may be specified by the company and approved by the Department of Insurance.</para><para>This section shall not apply to policies issued on or after the operative date of section 44-407.24 as defined therein.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 106, &#167; 5(4), p. 365; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-407.04; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 206, &#167; 2, p. 719; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 222, &#167; 2, p. 661; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 262, &#167; 6, p. 737; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 355, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Mortality tables,</emphasis> see Appendix, Nebraska Revised Statutes, Volume 2A.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 