<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-210"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-210</statuteno><catchline>Annual meeting; special meeting; voting rights; proxies; preferred stock; limitation on right to vote; quorum requirements; when.</catchline><para>Every domestic stock and mutual company and assessment association shall hold an annual meeting of its shareholders, if a stock company, or of its members, if a mutual company or an assessment association, on or before the 30th day of June in each and every calendar year, for the purpose of receiving the report of its officers and directors, to elect directors whose terms expire, and to transact such other business as may be lawful for it to do. Special meetings of the shareholders or members may be held as may be provided in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws and as otherwise provided by law. Each outstanding share of stock in a stock company and each member in a mutual company or assessment association shall be entitled to one vote on each matter submitted to a vote at an annual or special meeting of the shareholders or members, except as otherwise provided by law and except that any such stock company in its articles of incorporation may provide that the holders of preferred shares of stock shall have no right to vote and, in such event, such shares of stock shall not be entitled to vote. A shareholder or member may vote either in person or by proxy executed in writing by the shareholder or member or by his or her duly authorized attorney in fact appointing any director, officer, shareholder, or member for such purpose. In the case of a mutual company or an assessment association, such proxy may be incorporated into a member's application for insurance or policy. All such proxies shall be filed or on file with the stock or mutual company or assessment association at least five days prior to the day of the meeting, and they shall expire eleven months from their effective date, unless otherwise provided in such proxy, application, or policy. Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit or limit the right of a shareholder or member to vote in person or otherwise revoke any such proxy at any time prior to any exercise thereof. In the case of a mutual company or an assessment association, there shall be no quorum requirements for any meeting of members except as set forth in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws of such mutual company or assessment association.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 63, p. 422; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3199; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. IV, &#167; 33, p. 602; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7798; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-333; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-210; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 265, &#167; 1, p. 794; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 254, &#167; 1, p. 720; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1222, &#167; 47. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 