<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id17"  statutenumber="44-7,106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7,106</statuteno><catchline>Coverage for screening, diagnosis,
and treatment of autism spectrum disorder; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of
this section:</para>
<para>(a) Applied
behavior analysis means the design, implementation, and evaluation of environmental
modifications, using behavioral stimuli and consequences, to produce socially
significant improvement in human behavior, including the use of direct observation,
measurement, and functional analysis of the relationship between environment
and behavior;</para><para>(b) Autism spectrum disorder means any of the pervasive developmental
disorders or autism spectrum disorder as defined by the Diagnostic and Statistical
Manual of Mental Disorders, as the most recent edition of such manual existed
on July 18, 2014;</para><para>(c) Behavioral health treatment means counseling and treatment programs,
including applied behavior analysis, that are: (i) Necessary to develop, maintain,
or restore, to the maximum extent practicable, the functioning of an individual;
and (ii) provided or supervised, either in person or by telehealth, by a behavior
analyst certified by a national certifying organization or a licensed psychologist
if the services performed are within the boundaries of the psychologist's
competency;</para><para>(d) Diagnosis means a medically necessary assessment, evaluation,
or test to diagnose if an individual has an autism spectrum disorder;</para>
<para>(e) Pharmacy
care means a medication that is prescribed by a licensed physician and any
health-related service deemed medically necessary to determine the need or
effectiveness of the medication;</para><para>(f) Psychiatric care means a direct or consultative
service provided by a psychiatrist licensed in the state in which he or she
practices;</para><para>(g) Psychological care means a direct or consultative service provided
by a psychologist licensed in the state in which he or she practices;</para>
<para>(h) Therapeutic
care means a service provided by a licensed speech-language pathologist, occupational
therapist, or physical therapist; and</para><para>(i) Treatment means evidence-based care,
including related equipment, that is prescribed or ordered for an individual
diagnosed with an autism spectrum disorder by a licensed physician or a licensed
psychologist, including:</para><para>(i) Behavioral health treatment;</para><para>(ii) Pharmacy care;</para><para>(iii) Psychiatric care;</para>
<para>(iv) Psychological
care; and</para><para>(v) Therapeutic care.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding section 44-3,131, (a)
any individual or group sickness and accident insurance policy or subscriber
contract delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state and any
hospital, medical, or surgical expense-incurred policy, except for policies
that provide coverage for a specified disease or other limited-benefit coverage,
and (b) any self-funded employee benefit plan to the extent not preempted
by federal law, including any such plan provided for employees of the State
of Nebraska, shall provide coverage for the screening, diagnosis, and treatment
of an autism spectrum disorder in an individual under twenty-one years of
age. To the extent that the screening, diagnosis, and treatment of autism
spectrum disorder are not already covered by such policy or contract, coverage
under this section shall be included in such policies or contracts that are
delivered, issued for delivery, amended, or renewed in this state or outside
this state if the policy or contract insures a resident of Nebraska on or
after January 1, 2015. No insurer shall terminate coverage or refuse to deliver,
issue for delivery, amend, or renew coverage of the insured as a result of
an autism spectrum disorder diagnosis or treatment. Nothing in this subsection
applies to non-grandfathered plans in the individual and small group markets
that are required to include essential health benefits under the federal Patient
Protection and Affordable Care Act or to medicare supplement, accident-only,
specified disease, hospital indemnity, disability income, long-term care,
or other limited benefit hospital insurance policies.</para><para>(3) Except as provided
in subsection (4) of this section, coverage for an autism spectrum disorder
shall not be subject to any limits on the number of visits an individual may
make for treatment of an autism spectrum disorder, nor shall such coverage
be subject to dollar limits, deductibles, copayments, or coinsurance provisions
that are less favorable to an insured than the equivalent provisions that
apply to a general physical illness under the policy.</para><para>(4) Coverage for behavioral
health treatment, including applied behavior analysis, shall be subject to
a maximum benefit of twenty-five hours per week until the insured reaches
twenty-one years of age. Payments made by an insurer on behalf of a covered
individual for treatment other than behavioral health treatment, including
applied behavior analysis, shall not be applied to any maximum benefit established
under this section.</para><para>(5) Except in the case of inpatient service, if an individual is
receiving treatment for an autism spectrum disorder, an insurer shall have
the right to request a review of that treatment not more than once every six
months unless the insurer and the individual's licensed physician or licensed
psychologist execute an agreement that a more frequent review is necessary.
Any such agreement regarding the right to review a treatment plan more frequently
shall apply only to a particular individual being treated for an autism spectrum
disorder and shall not apply to all individuals being treated for autism spectrum
disorder by a licensed physician or licensed psychologist. The cost of obtaining
a review under this subsection shall be borne by the insurer.</para>
<para>(6) This section
shall not be construed as limiting any benefit that is otherwise available
to an individual under a hospital, surgical, or medical expense-incurred policy
or health maintenance organization contract. This section shall not be construed
as affecting any obligation to provide services to an individual under an
individualized family service plan, individualized education program, or individualized
service plan.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB254, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>