<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-211</statuteno><catchline>Incorporators; manage business until
first meeting of shareholders; board of directors; election; number; qualifications;
powers.</catchline><para>The business and affairs of an insurance corporation
shall be managed by the incorporators until the first meeting of shareholders
or members and then and thereafter by a board of directors elected by the
shareholders or members and as otherwise provided by law. The board of directors
shall consist of not less than five persons, and one of them shall be a resident
of the State of Nebraska. At least one-fifth of the directors of an insurance
company, which is not subject to section 44-2135, shall be persons who are
not officers or employees of such company. A person convicted of a felony
may not be a director, and all directors shall be of good moral character
and known professional, administrative, or business ability, such business
ability to include a practical knowledge of insurance, finance, or investment.
No person shall hold the office of director unless he or she is a policyholder,
if the company is a mutual company or assessment association. Unless otherwise
provided in the articles of incorporation, the board of directors shall make
all bylaws. A director shall discharge his or her duties as a director in
accordance with section 21-2,102.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 82, p. 429; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3219; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. V, &#167; 5, p. 609; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7818; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-211; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 145, &#167; 1, p. 469; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 195, &#167; 1, p. 702; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 212, &#167; 1, p. 630; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 255, &#167; 1, p. 722; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 263, &#167; 1, p. 706; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 259, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB191, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 283.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>