<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7,102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7,102</statuteno><catchline>Coverage for screening for colorectal cancer.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding section 44-3,131, (a) any individual or group sickness and accident insurance policy, certificate, or subscriber contract delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state and any hospital, medical, or surgical expense-incurred policy, except for short-term major medical policies of six months or less duration and policies that provide coverage for a specified disease or other limited-benefit coverage, and (b) any self-funded employee benefit plan to the extent not preempted by federal law shall include screening coverage for a colorectal cancer examination and laboratory tests for cancer for any nonsymptomatic person forty-five years of age or older covered under such policy, certificate, contract, or plan. Such screening coverage shall include a maximum of one stool-based preventive screening test as approved by the United States Preventive Services Task Force annually and a flexible sigmoidoscopy every five years, a colonoscopy every ten years, or a barium enema every five to ten years, or any combination, or the most reliable, medically recognized screening test available. The screenings selected shall be as deemed appropriate by a health care provider and the patient.</para><para>(2) On or after December 31, 2023, no policy, certificate, or contract, delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state, or any self-funded employee benefit plan, to the extent not preempted by federal law, shall impose a deductible, coinsurance, or any other cost-sharing requirements for screening colonoscopies as recommended by the United States Preventive Services Task Force, including those performed as a result of a positive noncolonoscopy stool-based preventive screening test.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB863, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 55. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>