<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-407.09"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-407.09</statuteno><catchline>Industrial policies issued on or after operative date of law; premiums and values; how calculated; tables used; written notice filed with department; election; exception.</catchline><para>This section shall not apply to industrial policies issued on or after the operative date of section 44-407.24 as defined therein.</para><para>In the case of industrial policies issued on or after the operative date of this section, all adjusted premiums and present values referred to in sections 44-407 to 44-407.09 and 44-407.24 to 44-407.26, shall be calculated on the basis of the Commissioners 1961 Standard Industrial Mortality Table and the rate of interest, specified in the policy for calculating cash surrender values and paid-up nonforfeiture benefits; such rate of interest shall not exceed three and one-half percent per annum except that a rate of interest not exceeding four percent per annum may be used for policies issued on or after September 2, 1973, and prior to August 24, 1979, and a rate of interest not exceeding five and one-half percent per annum may be used for policies issued on or after August 24, 1979; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that in calculating the present value of any paid-up term insurance with accompanying pure endowment, if any, offered as a nonforfeiture benefit, the rates of mortality assumed may be not more than those shown in the Commissioners 1961 Industrial Extended Term Insurance Table; <emphasis type="italic">and provided further,</emphasis> that for insurance issued on a substandard basis, the calculations of any such adjusted premiums and present values may be based on such other table of mortality as may be specified by the company and approved by the Department of Insurance. After September 18, 1965, any company may file with the Department of Insurance a written notice of its election to comply with the provisions of this section after a specified date before January 1, 1968. After the filing of such notice, then upon such specified date, which shall be the operative date of this section for such company, this section shall become operative with respect to the industrial policies thereafter issued by such company. If a company makes no such election, the operative date of this section for such company shall be January 1, 1968.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 262, &#167; 10, p. 741; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 309, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 354, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 355, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For determination of operative date,</emphasis> see section 44-407.23.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>