<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-514"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-514</statuteno><catchline>Automobile liability policy; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 44-514 to 44-521, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Policy shall mean an automobile liability policy providing all or part of the coverage defined in subdivision (2) of this section, delivered or issued for delivery in this state, insuring a natural person as named insured or one or more related individuals resident of the same household, and under which the insured vehicles designated in the policy are of the following types only: (a) A motor vehicle of the private passenger or station wagon type that is not used as a public or livery conveyance for passengers nor rented to others; or (b) any other four-wheel motor vehicle of the pickup, panel, or delivery type which is not used in the occupation, profession, or business of the insured, except that sections 44-514 to 44-521 shall not apply (i) to any policy issued under an automobile assigned risk plan; (ii) to any policy subject to section 44-523; (iii) to any policy covering garage, automobile sales agency, repair shop, service station, or public parking place operation hazards; or (iv) to any policy of insurance issued principally to cover personal or premises liability of an insured even though such insurance may also provide some incidental coverage for liability arising out of the ownership, maintenance, or use of a motor vehicle on the premises of such insured or on the way immediately adjoining such premises;</para><para>(2) Automobile liability coverage shall include only coverage of bodily injury and property damage liability, medical payments, uninsured motorist coverage, and underinsured motorist coverage;</para><para>(3) Renewal or to renew shall mean the issuance and delivery by an insurer of a policy replacing at the end of the policy period a policy previously issued and delivered by the same insurer or the issuance and delivery of a certificate or notice extending the term of a policy beyond its policy period or term, except that (a) any policy with a policy period or term of less than six months shall be considered as if written for a policy period or term of six months and (b) any policy written for a term longer than one year or any policy with no fixed expiration date shall be considered as if written for successive policy periods or terms of one year, and such policy may be terminated at the expiration of any annual period upon giving twenty days' notice of cancellation prior to such anniversary date, and such cancellation shall not be subject to any other provisions of sections 44-514 to 44-521; and</para><para>(4) Nonpayment of premium shall mean failure of the named insured to discharge when due any of his or her obligations in connection with the payment of any premium on a policy or any installment of such premium, whether the premium is payable directly to the insurer or its agent or indirectly under any premium finance plan or extension of credit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1396, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB115, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Sections 44-358 and 44-514 to 44-521 relate to different matters and are therefore not in conflict. As such, the right to rescission as limited by section 44-358 is still available to an insurer regarding policies of the type defined in this section. Glockel v. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co., 224 Neb. 598, 400 N.W.2d 250 (1987).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>