<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-787"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-787</statuteno><catchline>Individual health insurance policies and contracts; renewal; exceptions; failure to renew; effect; certificate of creditable coverage.</catchline><para>(1) All individual health insurance policies and contracts issued by health carriers providing benefits consisting of medical care, which are provided directly, through insurance or reimbursement, under any hospital or medical service policy, hospital or medical service plan contract, or health maintenance organization contract shall be renewable at the option of the covered individual, except in any of the following cases:</para><para>(a) The covered individual has failed to pay premiums or contributions in accordance with the terms of the individual policy or contract or the health carrier has not received timely premium payments;</para><para>(b) The covered individual has performed an act or practice that constitutes fraud or made an intentional misrepresentation of material fact under the terms of the coverage;</para><para>(c) A health carrier decides to discontinue offering a particular type of individual policy or contract in this state. A health carrier discontinuing such individual policy or contract shall:</para><para>(i) Provide advance notice of its decision to the commissioner of insurance in each state in which it is licensed;</para><para>(ii) Provide notice of the decision not to renew coverage to all covered individuals, and to the commissioner of insurance in each state in which a covered individual is known to reside, at least ninety days prior to the nonrenewal of any individual policies or contracts by the health carrier. Notice to the director shall be provided at least three working days prior to the notice to the covered individuals;</para><para>(iii) Offer to each covered individual provided the type of individual policy or contract the option to purchase all other individual policies or contracts currently being offered by the health carrier to individuals in this state; and</para><para>(iv) In exercising the option to discontinue the particular type of individual policy or contract and in offering the option of coverage under subdivision (1)(c)(iii) of this section, act uniformly without regard to any health-status-related factor relating to any covered individual who may become eligible for such coverage;</para><para>(d) A health carrier decides to discontinue offering and nonrenews all its individual policies and contracts delivered or issued for delivery to individuals in this state. A health carrier that discontinues such individual policies and contracts shall:</para><para>(i) Provide advance notice of its decision to the commissioner of insurance in each state in which it is licensed;</para><para>(ii) Provide notice of the decision not to renew coverage to all covered individuals, and to the commissioner of insurance in each state in which a covered individual is known to reside, at least one hundred eighty days prior to the nonrenewal of any individual policies or contracts by the health carrier. Notice to the director shall be provided at least three working days prior to the notice to the covered individuals; and</para><para>(iii) Discontinue all health insurance issued or delivered for issuance in the state's individual market and not renew coverage under any individual policy or contract issued to an individual; and</para><para>(e) The director finds that the continuation of the coverage would:</para><para>(i) Not be in the best interests of the covered individuals; or</para><para>(ii) Impair the health carrier's ability to meet its contractual obligations.</para><para>(2) A health carrier that elects not to renew all of its individual policies or contracts in the state under subdivision (1)(d) of this section shall be prohibited from writing new business in the individual market in this state for a period of five years after the date of notice to the director.</para><para>(3) A health carrier offering coverage through a network plan shall not be required to offer coverage or accept applications pursuant to subsection (1) of this section in the case of an individual who no longer resides, lives, or works in the service area of the health carrier or in an area for which the health carrier is authorized to do business, but only if coverage is terminated under this section uniformly without regard to any health-status-related factor of covered individuals.</para><para>(4)(a) Health carriers shall provide written certification of creditable coverage to individuals covered under an individual health insurance policy or contract at the time:</para><para>(i) An individual ceases to be covered under the health insurance policy or contract; and</para><para>(ii) A request is made on behalf of an individual if the request is made not later than twenty-four months after the date of cessation of coverage.</para><para>(b) The certificate of creditable coverage shall contain:</para><para>(i) Written certification of the period of creditable coverage of the individual under the health insurance policy or contract; and</para><para>(ii) The waiting period, if any, and, if applicable, affiliation period imposed with respect to the individual for any coverage under the health insurance policy or contract.</para><para>(c) The entity providing the information pursuant to subdivision (4)(a) of this section may charge the requesting group health plan the reasonable cost of disclosing the information.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Director means the Director of Insurance;</para><para>(b) Health carrier means any entity that issues a health insurance policy or contract, including an insurance company, a fraternal benefit society, a health maintenance organization, and any other entity providing a plan of health insurance or health benefits subject to state insurance regulation;</para><para>(c) Health-status-related factor means any of the following factors:</para><para>(i) Health status;</para><para>(ii) Medical condition, including both physical and mental illnesses;</para><para>(iii) Claims experience;</para><para>(iv) Receipt of health care;</para><para>(v) Medical history;</para><para>(vi) Genetic information;</para><para>(vii) Evidence of insurability, including conditions arising out of acts of domestic violence; and</para><para>(viii) Disability;</para><para>(d)(i) Individual policy or contract does not include one or more, or any combination, of the following:</para><para>(A) Coverage only for accident or disability income insurance, or any combination thereof;</para><para>(B) Coverage issued as a supplement to liability insurance;</para><para>(C) Liability insurance, including general liability insurance and automobile liability insurance;</para><para>(D) Workers' compensation or similar insurance;</para><para>(E) Automobile medical payment insurance;</para><para>(F) Credit-only insurance;</para><para>(G) Coverage for onsite medical clinics; and</para><para>(H) Other similar insurance coverage, specified in federal regulations, under which benefits for medical care are secondary or incidental to other insurance benefits.</para><para>(ii) Individual policy or contract does not include the following benefits if they are provided under a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance or are otherwise not an integral part of the policy or contract:</para><para>(A) Limited-scope dental or vision benefits;</para><para>(B) Benefits for long-term care, nursing home care, home health care, community-based care, or any combination thereof; and</para><para>(C) Such other similar, limited benefits as are specified in federal regulations.</para><para>(iii) Individual policy or contract does not include the following benefits if the benefits are provided under a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance:</para><para>(A) Coverage only for a specified disease or illness; and</para><para>(B) Hospital indemnity or other fixed indemnity insurance.</para><para>(iv) Individual policy or contract does not include the following if it is offered as a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance:</para><para>(A) Medicare supplemental health insurance as defined under section 1882(g)(1) of the Social Security Act, 42 U.S.C. 1395ss, as such section existed on January 1, 2002;</para><para>(B) Coverage supplemental to the coverage provided under 10 U.S.C. chapter 55, as such chapter existed on January 1, 2002;</para><para>(C) Similar supplemental coverage provided to coverage under a group health plan; and</para><para>(D) Short-term limited duration insurance that has an expiration date specified in the contract that is within twelve months of the effective date of the contract; and</para><para>(e) Network plan means health insurance coverage offered by a health carrier under which the financing and delivery of medical care including items and services paid for as medical care are provided, in whole or in part, through a defined set of providers under contract with the health carrier.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 55, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1035, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 259, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc>