
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id00" statutenumber="44-416.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-416.06</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Credit for reinsurance; when allowed; suspension or revocation of accreditation or certification; director; powers; duties; notice; hearing; insurer duties.</catchline><para>(1) Credit for reinsurance shall be allowed a domestic ceding insurer as either an asset or a reduction from liability on account of reinsurance ceded only when the reinsurer meets the requirements of subsection (2), (3), (4), (5), (6), (7), or (8) of this section and any additional requirements contained in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Director of Insurance pursuant to subsection (2) of section 44-416.09 relating to or setting forth (a) the valuation of assets or reserve credits, (b) the amount and form of security supporting reinsurance arrangements, or (c) the circumstances pursuant to which credit will be reduced or eliminated. Except as otherwise provided in section 44-224.11, credit shall be allowed under subsection (2), (3), or (4) of this section only for cessions of those kinds or classes of business which the assuming insurer is licensed or otherwise permitted to write or assume in its state of domicile or, in the case of a United States branch of an alien assuming insurer, in the state through which it is entered and licensed to transact insurance or reinsurance. Credit shall be allowed under subsection (4) or (5) of this section only if the applicable requirements of subsection (9) of this section have been satisfied.</para><para>(2) Credit shall be allowed when the reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer that is licensed to transact insurance in this state.</para><para>(3) Credit shall be allowed when the reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer that is accredited by the Director of Insurance as a reinsurer in this state. In order to be eligible for accreditation, a reinsurer must:</para><para>(a) File with the director evidence of its submission to this state's jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) Submit to this state's authority to examine its books and records;</para><para>(c) Be licensed to transact insurance or reinsurance in at least one state, or in the case of a United States branch of an alien assuming insurer, be entered through and licensed to transact insurance or reinsurance in at least one state;</para><para>(d) File annually with the director a copy of its annual statement filed with the insurance department of its state of domicile and a copy of its most recent audited financial statement; and</para><para>(e) Demonstrate to the satisfaction of the director that it has adequate financial capacity to meet its reinsurance obligations and is otherwise qualified to assume reinsurance from domestic insurers. An assuming insurer is deemed to meet this requirement as of the time of its application if it maintains a surplus as regards policyholders in an amount not less than twenty million dollars and its accreditation has not been denied by the director within ninety days after submission of its application.</para><para>(4)(a) Credit shall be allowed when the reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer that is domiciled in, or in the case of a United States branch of an alien assuming insurer is entered through, a state that employs standards regarding credit for reinsurance substantially similar to those applicable under this section and the assuming insurer or United States branch of an alien assuming insurer:</para><para>(i) Maintains a surplus as regards policyholders in an amount not less than twenty million dollars; and</para><para>(ii) Submits to the authority of this state to examine its books and records.</para><para>(b) The requirement of subdivision (4)(a)(i) of this section does not apply to reinsurance ceded and assumed pursuant to pooling arrangements among insurers in the same holding company system.</para><para>(5)(a) Credit shall be allowed when the reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer that maintains a trust fund in a qualified United States financial institution for the payment of the valid claims of its United States ceding insurers and their assigns and successors in interest. To enable the director to determine the sufficiency of the trust fund, the assuming insurer shall report annually to the director information substantially the same as that required to be reported on the National Association of Insurance Commissioners Annual Statement form by licensed insurers. The assuming insurer shall submit to examination of its books and records by the director and bear the expense of examination.</para><para>(b)(i) Credit for reinsurance shall not be granted under this subsection unless the form of the trust and any amendments to the trust have been approved by:</para><para>(A) The commissioner of the state where the trust is domiciled; or</para><para>(B) The commissioner of another state who, pursuant to the terms of the trust instrument, has accepted principal regulatory oversight of the trust.</para><para>(ii) The form of the trust and any trust amendments also shall be filed with the commissioner of every state in which the ceding insurer beneficiaries of the trust are domiciled. The trust instrument shall provide that contested claims shall be valid and enforceable upon the final order of any court of competent jurisdiction in the United States. The trust shall vest legal title to its assets in its trustees for the benefit of the assuming insurer's United States ceding insurers, their assigns, and successors in interest. The trust and the assuming insurer shall be subject to examination as determined by the director.</para><para>(iii) The trust shall remain in effect for as long as the assuming insurer has outstanding obligations due under the reinsurance agreements subject to the trust. No later than February 28 of each year the trustee of the trust shall report to the director in writing the balance of the trust and listing the trust's investments at the preceding year end and shall certify the date of termination of the trust, if so planned, or certify that the trust will not expire prior to the following December 31.</para><para>(c) The following requirements apply to the following categories of assuming insurer:</para><para>(i) The trust fund for a single assuming insurer shall consist of funds in trust in an amount not less than the assuming insurer's liabilities attributable to reinsurance ceded by United States ceding insurers and, in addition, the assuming insurer shall maintain a trusteed surplus of not less than twenty million dollars except as provided in subdivision (5)(c)(ii) of this section;</para><para>(ii) At any time after the assuming insurer has permanently discontinued underwriting new business secured by the trust for at least three full years, the commissioner with principal regulatory oversight of the trust may authorize a reduction in the required trusteed surplus, but only after a finding, based on an assessment of the risk, that the new required surplus level is adequate for the protection of United States ceding insurers, policyholders, and claimants in light of reasonably foreseeable adverse loss development. The risk assessment may involve an actuarial review, including an independent analysis of reserves and cash flows, and shall consider all material risk factors, including when applicable the lines of business involved, the stability of the incurred loss estimates, and the effect of the surplus requirements on the assuming insurer's liquidity or solvency. The minimum required trusteed surplus may not be reduced to an amount less than thirty percent of the assuming insurer's liabilities attributable to reinsurance ceded by United States ceding insurers covered by the trust; and</para><para>(iii)(A) In the case of a group including incorporated and individual unincorporated underwriters:</para><para>(I) For reinsurance ceded under reinsurance agreements with an inception, amendment, or renewal date on or after January 1, 1993, the trust shall consist of a trusteed account in an amount not less than the respective underwriters' several liabilities attributable to business ceded by United States domiciled ceding insurers to any underwriter of the group;</para><para>(II) For reinsurance ceded under reinsurance agreements with an inception date on or before December 31, 1992, and not amended or renewed after that date, notwithstanding the other provisions of sections 44-416.05 to 44-416.10, the trust shall consist of a trusteed account in an amount not less than the respective underwriters' several insurance and reinsurance liabilities attributable to business written in the United States; and</para><para>(III) In addition to these trusts, the group shall maintain in trust a trusteed surplus of which one hundred million dollars shall be held jointly for the benefit of the United States domiciled ceding insurers of any member of the group for all years of account;</para><para>(B) The incorporated members of the group shall not be engaged in any business other than underwriting as a member of the group and shall be subject to the same level of regulation and solvency control by the group's domiciliary regulator as are the unincorporated members; and</para><para>(C) Within ninety days after its financial statements are due to be filed with the group's domiciliary regulator, the group shall provide to the director an annual certification by the group's domiciliary regulator of the solvency of each underwriter member, or if a certification is unavailable, financial statements, prepared by independent public accountants, of each underwriter member of the group.</para><para>(6)(a) Credit shall be allowed when the reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer that has been certified by the director as a reinsurer in this state and secures its obligations in accordance with the requirements of this subsection.</para><para>(b) In order to be eligible for certification, the assuming insurer shall meet the following requirements:</para><para>(i) The assuming insurer must be domiciled and licensed to transact insurance or reinsurance in a qualified jurisdiction, as determined by the director pursuant to subdivision (6)(d) of this section;</para><para>(ii) The assuming insurer must maintain minimum capital and surplus, or its equivalent, in an amount to be determined by the director pursuant to rules and regulations;</para><para>(iii) The assuming insurer must maintain financial strength ratings from two or more rating agencies deemed acceptable by the director pursuant to rules and regulations;</para><para>(iv) The assuming insurer must agree to submit to the jurisdiction of this state, appoint the director as its agent for service of process in this state, and agree to provide security for one hundred percent of the assuming insurer's liabilities attributable to reinsurance ceded by United States ceding insurers if it resists enforcement of a final United States judgment;</para><para>(v) The assuming insurer must agree to meet applicable information filing requirements as determined by the director, both with respect to an initial application for certification and on an ongoing basis; and</para><para>(vi) The assuming insurer must satisfy any other requirements for certification deemed relevant by the director.</para><para>(c) An association including incorporated and individual unincorporated underwriters may be a certified reinsurer. In order to be eligible for certification, in addition to satisfying requirements of subdivision (6)(b) of this section:</para><para>(i) The association shall satisfy its minimum capital and surplus requirements through the capital and surplus equivalents, net of liabilities, of the association and its members, which shall include a joint central fund that may be applied to any unsatisfied obligation of the association or any of its members, in an amount determined by the director to provide adequate protection;</para><para>(ii) The incorporated members of the association shall not be engaged in any business other than underwriting as a member of the association and shall be subject to the same level of regulation and solvency control by the association's domiciliary regulator as are the unincorporated members; and</para><para>(iii) Within ninety days after its financial statements are due to be filed with the association's domiciliary regulator, the association shall provide to the director an annual certification by the association's domiciliary regulator of the solvency of each underwriter member or, if a certification is unavailable, financial statements, prepared by independent public accountants, of each underwriter member of the association.</para><para>(d)(i) The director shall create and publish a list of qualified jurisdictions under which an assuming insurer licensed and domiciled in such jurisdiction is eligible to be considered for certification by the director as a certified reinsurer.</para><para>(ii) In order to determine whether the domiciliary jurisdiction of a non-United-States assuming insurer is eligible to be recognized as a qualified jurisdiction, the director shall evaluate the appropriateness and effectiveness of the reinsurance supervisory system of the jurisdiction, both initially and on an ongoing basis, and consider the rights, benefits, and the extent of reciprocal recognition afforded by the non-United-States jurisdiction to reinsurers licensed and domiciled in the United States. A qualified jurisdiction must agree to share information and cooperate with the director with respect to all certified reinsurers domiciled within that jurisdiction. A jurisdiction may not be recognized as a qualified jurisdiction if the director has determined that the jurisdiction does not adequately and promptly enforce final United States judgments and arbitration awards. Additional factors may be considered in the discretion of the director.</para><para>(iii) A list of qualified jurisdictions shall be published through the National Association of Insurance Commissioners committee process. The director shall consider this list in determining qualified jurisdictions. If the director approves a jurisdiction as qualified that does not appear on the list of qualified jurisdictions, the director shall provide thoroughly documented justification in accordance with criteria to be developed under rules and regulations.</para><para>(iv) United States jurisdictions that meet the requirement for accreditation under the National Association of Insurance Commissioners financial standards and accreditation program shall be recognized as qualified jurisdictions.</para><para>(v) If a certified reinsurer's domiciliary jurisdiction ceases to be a qualified jurisdiction, the director has the discretion to suspend the reinsurer's certification indefinitely, in lieu of revocation.</para><para>(e) The director shall assign a rating to each certified reinsurer, giving due consideration to the financial strength ratings that have been assigned by rating agencies deemed acceptable to the director pursuant to rules and regulations. The director shall publish a list of all certified reinsurers and their ratings.</para><para>(f)(i) A certified reinsurer shall secure obligations assumed from United States ceding insurers under this subsection at a level consistent with its rating, as specified in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director.</para><para>(ii) In order for a domestic ceding insurer to qualify for full financial statement credit for reinsurance ceded to a certified reinsurer, the certified reinsurer shall maintain security in a form acceptable to the director and consistent with the provisions of section 44-416.07 or in a multibeneficiary trust in accordance with subsection (5) of this section, except as otherwise provided in this subsection.</para><para>(iii) If a certified reinsurer maintains a trust to fully secure its obligations subject to subsection (5) of this section and chooses to secure its obligations incurred as a certified reinsurer in the form of a multibeneficiary trust, the certified reinsurer shall maintain separate trust accounts for its obligations incurred under reinsurance agreements issued or renewed as a certified reinsurer with reduced security as permitted by this subsection or comparable laws of other United States jurisdictions and for its obligations subject to subsection (5) of this section. It shall be a condition to the grant of certification under this subsection that the certified reinsurer shall have bound itself, by the language of the trust and agreement with the commissioner with principal regulatory oversight of each such trust account, to fund, upon termination of any such trust account, out of the remaining surplus of such trust any deficiency of any other such trust account.</para><para>(iv) The minimum trusteed surplus requirements provided in subsection (5) of this section are not applicable with respect to a multibeneficiary trust maintained by a certified reinsurer for the purpose of securing obligations incurred under this subsection, except that such trust shall maintain a minimum trusteed surplus of ten million dollars.</para><para>(v) With respect to obligations incurred by a certified reinsurer under this subsection, if the security is insufficient, the director shall reduce the allowable credit by an amount proportionate to the deficiency and has the discretion to impose further reductions in allowable credit upon finding that there is a material risk that the certified reinsurer's obligations will not be paid in full when due.</para><para>(vi)(A) For purposes of this subsection, a certified reinsurer whose certification has been terminated for any reason shall be treated as a certified reinsurer required to secure one hundred percent of its obligations.</para><para>(B) As used in subdivision (6)(f)(vi)(A) of this section, the term "terminated" refers to revocation, suspension, voluntary surrender, and inactive status.</para><para>(C) If the director continues to assign a higher rating as permitted by other provisions of this section, the requirement in subdivision (6)(f)(vi)(A) of this section does not apply to a certified reinsurer in inactive status or to a reinsurer whose certification has been suspended.</para><para>(g) If an applicant for certification has been certified as a reinsurer in a National Association of Insurance Commissioners-accredited jurisdiction, the director has the discretion to defer to that jurisdiction's certification and has the discretion to defer to the rating assigned by that jurisdiction, and such assuming insurer shall be considered to be a certified reinsurer in this state.</para><para>(h) A certified reinsurer that ceases to assume new business in this state may request to maintain its certification in inactive status in order to continue to qualify for a reduction in security for its in-force business. An inactive certified reinsurer shall continue to comply with all applicable requirements of this subsection, and the director shall assign a rating that takes into account, if relevant, the reasons why the reinsurer is not assuming new business.</para><para>(7)(a) Credit shall be allowed when reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer meeting each of the conditions set forth below:</para><para>(i) Such assuming insurer shall have its head office or be domiciled in, as applicable, and be licensed in a reciprocal jurisdiction. A reciprocal jurisdiction is a jurisdiction that meets one of the following:</para><para>(A) A jurisdiction, other than a jurisdiction of the United States, that is subject to an in-force covered agreement with the United States, each within its legal authority, or, in the case of a covered agreement between the United States and European Union, is a member state of the European Union. For purposes of this subsection, a covered agreement is an agreement entered into pursuant to the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act, 31 U.S.C. 313 and 314, as such sections existed on January 1, 2020, that is currently in effect or in a period of provisional application and that addresses the elimination, under specified conditions, of collateral requirements as a condition for entering into any reinsurance agreement with a ceding insurer domiciled in this state or for allowing the ceding insurer to recognize credit for reinsurance;</para><para>(B) A jurisdiction of the United States that meets the requirements for accreditation under the National Association of Insurance Commissioners financial standards and accreditation program; or</para><para>(C) A qualified jurisdiction as determined by the director pursuant to subdivision (6)(d)(i) of this section that is not otherwise described in subdivision (7)(a)(i)(A) or (B) of this section and that meets certain additional requirements, consistent with the terms and conditions of in-force covered agreements, as specified in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09;</para><para>(ii) Such assuming insurer shall have and maintain, on an ongoing basis, the minimum capital and surplus or the equivalent, calculated according to the methodology of its domiciliary jurisdiction, as set forth in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09. If such assuming insurer is an association, including an incorporated or individual unincorporated underwriter, such assuming insurer shall have and maintain, on an ongoing basis, minimum capital and surplus equivalents, net of liabilities and calculated according to the methodology of its domiciliary jurisdiction, and a central fund containing a minimum balance as set forth in the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09;</para><para>(iii) Such assuming insurer shall have and maintain, on an ongoing basis, the minimum solvency or capital ratio, as applicable, as set forth in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09. If such assuming insurer is an association, including incorporated and individual unincorporated underwriters, such assuming insurer shall have and maintain, on an ongoing basis, a minimum solvency or capital ratio in the reciprocal jurisdiction where such assuming insurer has its head office or is domiciled, as applicable, and is also licensed;</para><para>(iv) Such assuming insurer shall agree and provide adequate assurance to the director, in a form specified pursuant to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09, as follows:</para><para>(A) Such assuming insurer shall provide prompt written notice and explanation to the director if such assuming insurer falls below the minimum requirements set forth in subdivisions (7)(a)(ii) and (iii) of this section or if any regulatory action is taken against such assuming insurer for serious noncompliance with applicable law;</para><para>(B) Such assuming insurer shall consent in writing to the jurisdiction of the courts of this state and to the appointment of the director as the agent for service of process. The director may require that consent for service of process be provided to the director and included in each reinsurance agreement. Nothing in this subdivision shall limit, or in any way alter, the capacity of parties to a reinsurance agreement to agree to alternative dispute resolution mechanisms except to the extent such agreements are unenforceable under applicable insolvency or delinquency laws;</para><para>(C) Such assuming insurer shall consent in writing to pay all final judgments, wherever enforcement is sought, obtained by a ceding insurer or its legal successor, that have been declared enforceable in the jurisdiction where the judgment was obtained;</para><para>(D) Each reinsurance agreement shall include a provision requiring such assuming insurer to provide security in an amount equal to one hundred percent of such assuming insurer's liabilities attributable to reinsurance ceded pursuant to such agreement if such assuming insurer resists enforcement of a final judgment that is enforceable under the law of the jurisdiction in which such judgment was obtained or a properly enforceable arbitration award, whether obtained by the ceding insurer or by its legal successor on behalf of its resolution estate; and</para><para>(E) Such assuming insurer shall confirm that such assuming insurer is not presently participating in any solvent scheme of arrangement that involves this state's ceding insurers and agree to notify the ceding insurer and the director and to provide security in an amount equal to one hundred percent of such assuming insurer's liabilities to the ceding insurer if such assuming insurer enters into such a solvent scheme of arrangement. Such security shall be in a form consistent with the provisions of subsection (6) of this section and section 44-416.07 and as specified in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09;</para><para>(v) Such assuming insurer or its legal successor shall provide, if requested by the director, on behalf of itself and any legal predecessors, certain documentation to the director as specified in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09;</para><para>(vi) Such assuming insurer shall maintain a practice of prompt payment of claims under reinsurance agreements pursuant to criteria set forth in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09; and</para><para>(vii) Such assuming insurer's supervisory authority shall confirm to the director on an annual basis, as of the preceding December 31 or at the annual date otherwise statutorily reported to the reciprocal jurisdiction, that such assuming insurer complies with the requirements set forth in subdivisions (7)(a)(ii) and (iii) of this section.</para><para>(b) Nothing in this subsection precludes an assuming insurer from providing the director with information on a voluntary basis.</para><para>(c)(i) The director shall timely create and publish a list of reciprocal jurisdictions.</para><para>(ii) The director's list shall include any reciprocal jurisdiction as defined under subdivisions (7)(a)(i)(A) and (B) of this section, and the director shall consider including any other reciprocal jurisdiction included on the most current list published through the National Association of Insurance Commissioners' committee process. The director may approve a jurisdiction that does not appear on the National Association of Insurance Commissioners' list of reciprocal jurisdictions in accordance with criteria developed under rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09.</para><para>(iii) The director may remove a jurisdiction from the list of reciprocal jurisdictions upon a determination that the jurisdiction no longer meets the requirements of a reciprocal jurisdiction in accordance with the process set forth in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09, except that the director shall not remove a reciprocal jurisdiction as defined under subdivision (7)(a)(i)(A) or (B) of this section from such list. Upon removal of a reciprocal jurisdiction from the list, credit for reinsurance ceded to an assuming insurer that has its home office or is domiciled in such jurisdiction shall be allowed if otherwise allowed pursuant to sections 44-416.05 to 44-416.10.</para><para>(d) The director shall timely create and publish a list of assuming insurers that have satisfied the conditions set forth in this subsection and to which cessions shall be granted credit in accordance with this subsection. The director may add an assuming insurer to such list if a jurisdiction accredited by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners pursuant to accreditation standards has added such assuming insurer to such jurisdiction's list of assuming insurers or if, upon initial eligibility, such assuming insurer submits the information to the director as required under subdivision (7)(a)(iv) of this section and complies with any additional requirements that the director may impose by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09 except to the extent that any such rules and regulations conflict with an applicable covered agreement.</para><para>(e)(i) If the director determines that an assuming insurer no longer meets one or more of the requirements under this subsection, the director may revoke or suspend the eligibility of such assuming insurer for recognition as an assuming insurer under this subsection in accordance with procedures set forth in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the director pursuant to section 44-416.09.</para><para>(ii) While an assuming insurer's eligibility is suspended, no reinsurance agreement issued, amended, or renewed after the effective date of the suspension qualifies for credit except to the extent that such assuming insurer's obligations under the contract are secured in accordance with section 44-416.07.</para><para>(iii) If an assuming insurer's eligibility is revoked, no credit for reinsurance may be granted after the effective date of the revocation with respect to any reinsurance agreements entered into by such assuming insurer, including reinsurance agreements entered into prior to the date of revocation, except to the extent that such assuming insurer's obligations under the contract are secured in a form acceptable to the director and consistent with the provisions of section 44-416.07.</para><para>(f) If subject to a legal process of rehabilitation, liquidation, or conservation, as applicable, the ceding insurer or its representative may seek and, if determined appropriate by the court in which the proceedings are pending, may obtain an order requiring that such assuming insurer post security for all outstanding ceded liabilities.</para><para>(g) Nothing in this subsection shall limit or in any way alter the capacity of parties to a reinsurance agreement to agree on requirements for security or other terms in such reinsurance agreement except as expressly prohibited by sections 44-416.05 to 44-416.10 or other applicable law or rules and regulations.</para><para>(h) Credit may be taken under this subsection only for reinsurance agreements entered into, amended, or renewed on or after November 14, 2020, and only with respect to losses incurred and reserves reported on or after the later of the date on which such assuming insurer has met all eligibility requirements pursuant to subdivision (7)(a) of this section or the effective date of such reinsurance agreement, amendment, or renewal.</para><para>(i) This subdivision (7)(h) does not alter or impair a ceding insurer's right to take credit for reinsurance to the extent that credit is not available under this subdivision (7)(h) and the reinsurance qualifies for credit under any other applicable provision of sections 44-416.05 to 44-416.10.</para><para>(ii) Nothing in this subdivision (7)(h) shall authorize an assuming insurer to withdraw or reduce the security provided under any reinsurance agreement except as permitted by the terms of such agreement.</para><para>(iii) Nothing in this subdivision (7)(h) shall limit, or in any way alter, the capacity of parties to any reinsurance agreement to renegotiate such agreement.</para><para>(8) Credit shall be allowed when the reinsurance is ceded to an assuming insurer not meeting the requirements of subsection (2), (3), (4), (5), (6), or (7) of this section, but only as to the insurance of risks located in jurisdictions where the reinsurance is required by applicable law or regulation of that jurisdiction.</para><para>(9) If the assuming insurer is not licensed, accredited, or certified to transact insurance or reinsurance in this state, the credit permitted by subsections (4) and (5) of this section shall not be allowed unless the assuming insurer agrees in the reinsurance agreements:</para><para>(a)(i) That in the event of the failure of the assuming insurer to perform its obligations under the terms of the reinsurance agreement, the assuming insurer, at the request of the ceding insurer, shall submit to the jurisdiction of any court of competent jurisdiction in any state of the United States, will comply with all requirements necessary to give the court jurisdiction, and will abide by the final decision of the court or of any appellate court in the event of an appeal; and</para><para>(ii) To designate the director or a designated attorney as its true and lawful attorney upon whom may be served any lawful process in any action, suit, or proceeding instituted by or on behalf of the ceding insurer.</para><para>(b) This subsection is not intended to conflict with or override the obligation of the parties to a reinsurance agreement to arbitrate their disputes, if this obligation is created in the agreement.</para><para>(10) If the assuming insurer does not meet the requirements of subsection (2), (3), (4), or (7) of this section, the credit permitted by subsection (5) or (6) of this section shall not be allowed unless the assuming insurer agrees in the trust agreements to the following conditions:</para><para>(a) Notwithstanding any other provisions in the trust instrument, if the trust fund is inadequate because it contains an amount less than the amount required by subdivision (5)(c) of this section, or if the grantor of the trust has been declared insolvent or placed into receivership, rehabilitation, liquidation, or similar proceedings under the laws of its state or country of domicile, the trustee shall comply with an order of the commissioner with regulatory oversight over the trust or with an order of a court of competent jurisdiction directing the trustee to transfer to the state insurance commissioner with regulatory oversight all of the assets of the trust fund;</para><para>(b) The assets shall be distributed by and claims shall be filed with and valued by the state insurance commissioner with regulatory oversight in accordance with the laws of the state in which the trust is domiciled that are applicable to the liquidation of domestic insurance companies;</para><para>(c) If the state insurance commissioner with regulatory oversight determines that the assets of the trust fund or any part thereof are not necessary to satisfy the claims of the United States ceding insurers of the grantor of the trust, the assets or part thereof shall be returned by the state insurance commissioner with regulatory oversight to the trustee for distribution in accordance with the trust agreement; and</para><para>(d) The grantor shall waive any right otherwise available to it under United States law that is inconsistent with this provision.</para><para>(11)(a) If an accredited or certified reinsurer ceases to meet the requirements for accreditation or certification, the director may suspend or revoke the reinsurer's accreditation or certification.</para><para>(b) The director must give the reinsurer notice and opportunity for hearing. The suspension or revocation may not take effect until after the director's order on hearing unless:</para><para>(i) The reinsurer waives its right to hearing;</para><para>(ii) The director's order is based on regulatory action by the reinsurer's domiciliary jurisdiction or the voluntary surrender or termination of the reinsurer's eligibility to transact insurance or reinsurance business in its domiciliary jurisdiction or in the primary certifying state of the reinsurer under subdivision (6)(g) of this section; or</para><para>(iii) The director finds that an emergency requires immediate action and a court of competent jurisdiction has not stayed the director's action.</para><para>(c) While a reinsurer's accreditation or certification is suspended, no reinsurance contract issued or renewed after the effective date of the suspension qualifies for credit except to the extent that the reinsurer's obligations under the contract are secured in accordance with section 44-416.07. If a reinsurer's accreditation or certification is revoked, no credit for reinsurance may be granted after the effective date of the revocation except to the extent that the reinsurer's obligations under the contract are secured in accordance with subdivision (6)(f) of this section or section 44-416.07.</para><para>(12)(a) A ceding insurer shall take steps to manage its reinsurance recoverables proportionate to its own book of business. A domestic ceding insurer shall notify the director within thirty days after reinsurance recoverables from any single assuming insurer, or group of affiliated assuming insurers, exceeds fifty percent of the domestic ceding insurer's last reported surplus to policyholders, or after it is determined that reinsurance recoverables from any single assuming insurer, or group of affiliated assuming insurers, is likely to exceed this limit. The notification shall demonstrate that the exposure is safely managed by the domestic ceding insurer.</para><para>(b) A ceding insurer shall take steps to diversify its reinsurance program. A domestic ceding insurer shall notify the director within thirty days after ceding to any single assuming insurer, or group of affiliated assuming insurers, more than twenty percent of the ceding insurer's gross written premium in the prior calendar year, or after it has determined that the reinsurance ceded to any single assuming insurer, or group of affiliated assuming insurers, is likely to exceed this limit. The notification shall demonstrate that the exposure is safely managed by the domestic ceding insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB298, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB815, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB774, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>