<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id956"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7,119"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7,119</statuteno><catchline>Self-funded health benefit plan; not considered insurance; when; certification; required; reinsurance; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) A health benefit plan is not insurance and except as provided in this section is not subject to any law regarding insurance if:</para><para>(a) The health benefit plan provides health benefits under a self-funded arrangement administered by an entity licensed as a third-party administrator under the Third-Party Administrator Act; and</para><para>(b) The health benefit plan is sponsored by a nonprofit agricultural organization or an affiliate of a nonprofit agricultural organization that:</para><para>(i) Is domiciled in this state;</para><para>(ii) Was created primarily to promote programs for the development of rural communities and the economic stability and sustainability of farmers in this state pursuant to its articles of incorporation;</para><para>(iii) Provides membership opportunities for eligible persons in each county of this state;</para><para>(iv) Collects annual dues from its members;</para><para>(v) Holds regular meetings to further the purposes of its members;</para><para>(vi) Provides its members with representation on its governing board and any committees of such board; and</para><para>(vii) Contracts with the third-party administrator described in subdivision (a) of this subsection for administration of the health benefit plan.</para><para>(2) Before providing health benefits under a self-funded plan, an organization shall file a certification with the Department of Insurance verifying that the organization meets the requirements of this section. Such certification shall be filed at a time and in a manner prescribed by the Department of Insurance.</para><para>(3) The risk assumed by a health benefit plan under health care benefit coverage under this section may be reinsured by a company authorized to do business in this state.</para><para>(4) Any health benefit plan application for coverage and any contract provided to a member shall prominently state the following:</para><para>(a) The health benefit plan is not insurance;</para><para>(b) The health benefit plan is not provided by an insurance company;</para><para>(c) The health benefit plan is not subject to the laws and rules governing insurance; and</para><para>(d) The health benefit plan is not subject to the jurisdiction of the Department of Insurance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1313, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Third-Party  Administrator Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>