<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-785"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>44-785</statuteno><catchline>Coverage for screening mammography, digital breast tomosynthesis, bilateral whole breast ultrasound, and diagnostic magnetic resonance imaging; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding section 44-3,131, (a) any individual or group sickness and accident insurance policy or subscriber contract delivered, issued for delivery, or renewed in this state and any hospital, medical, or surgical expense-incurred policy, except for policies that provide coverage for a specified disease or other limited-benefit coverage, and (b) any self-funded employee benefit plan to the extent not preempted by federal law shall include coverage for screening mammography, digital breast tomosynthesis, bilateral whole breast ultrasound, and diagnostic magnetic resonance imaging as follows:</para><para>(i) For a woman who is thirty-five years of age or older but younger than forty years of age, one base-line mammogram between thirty-five and forty years of age;</para><para>(ii) For a woman who is younger than forty years of age and who, based on the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Guidelines for Breast Cancer Screening and Diagnosis version 1.2022 and the recommendation of the woman's health care provider, has an increased risk of breast cancer due to (A) a family or personal history of breast cancer or prior atypical breast biopsy, (B) positive genetic testing, or (C) heterogeneous or dense breast tissue based on a breast imaging, at least one mammogram each year and additional mammograms if necessary;</para><para>(iii) For a woman who is forty years of age or older, one mammogram every year;</para><para>(iv) For a woman who, based on the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Guidelines for Breast Cancer Screening and Diagnosis version 1.2022 and the recommendation of the woman's health care provider, has an increased risk for breast cancer due to (A) a family or personal history of breast cancer or prior atypical breast biopsy, (B) positive genetic testing, or (C) heterogeneous or dense breast tissue based on a breast imaging, one digital breast tomosynthesis each year;</para><para>(v) For a woman who, based on the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Guidelines for Breast Cancer Screening and Diagnosis version 1.2022 and the recommendation of the woman's health care provider, has an increased risk for breast cancer due to (A) a family or personal history of breast cancer or prior atypical breast biopsy, (B) positive genetic testing, or (C) heterogeneous or dense breast tissue based on a breast imaging, one bilateral whole breast ultrasound each year;</para><para>(vi) For a woman who, based on the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Guidelines for Breast Cancer Screening and Diagnosis version 1.2022 and the recommendation of the woman's health care provider, has an increased risk for breast cancer due to (A) a family or personal history of breast cancer or prior atypical breast biopsy, (B) positive genetic testing, or (C) a history of chest radiation, one diagnostic magnetic resonance imaging each year; and</para><para>(vii) For a woman who, based on national standard risk models or the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Guidelines for Breast Cancer Screening and Diagnosis, has an increased risk of breast cancer and heterogeneous or dense breast tissue, one diagnostic magnetic resonance imaging each year.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, this section prohibits the application of deductible, coinsurance, copayment, or other cost-sharing requirements contained in the policy or health benefit plan for such services.</para><para>(b) This section does not prevent application of deductible or copayment provisions contained in the policy or health benefit plan for diagnostic magnetic resonance imaging for a woman based on heterogeneous or dense breast tissue.</para><para>(c) This section does not require that coverage under an individual or group policy or health benefit plan be extended to any other procedures. The coverage provided by this section shall not be less favorable than for other radiological examinations.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, screening mammography shall mean radiological examination of the breast of asymptomatic women for the early detection of breast cancer, which examination shall include (a) a cranio-caudal and a medial lateral oblique view of each breast and (b) a licensed radiologist's interpretation of the results of the procedure. Screening mammography shall not include diagnostic mammography, additional projections required for lesion definition, breast ultrasound, or any breast interventional procedure. Screening mammography shall be performed by a mammogram supplier who meets the standards of the federal Mammography Quality Standards Act of 1992.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 68, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 54. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>