<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-150"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-150</statuteno><catchline>Reciprocal licenses; retaliation; penalties; taxes; domicile of alien insurer.</catchline><para>(1) When by or pursuant to the laws of any other state or foreign country any taxes, licenses and other fees, in the aggregate, or any fines, penalties, deposit requirements, or other material obligations, prohibitions, or restrictions, are or would be imposed upon Nebraska insurers, or upon the agents or representatives of such insurers, which are in excess of such taxes, licenses and other fees, in the aggregate, or which are in excess of the fines, penalties, deposit requirements, or other obligations, prohibitions, or restrictions directly imposed upon similar insurers, or upon the agents or representatives of such insurers, of such other state or country under the statutes of this state, so long as such laws of such other state or country continue in force or are so applied, the same taxes, licenses and other fees, in the aggregate, or fines, penalties, deposit requirements, or other material obligations, prohibitions, or restrictions of whatever kind shall be imposed by the Director of Insurance upon the insurers, or upon the agents or representatives of such insurers, of such other state or country doing business or seeking to do business in Nebraska. Any tax, license or other fee, or other obligation imposed by any city, county, or other political subdivision or agency of such other state or country on Nebraska insurers or their agents or representatives shall be deemed to be imposed by such state or country within the meaning of this section.</para><para>(2) This section shall not apply as to personal income taxes, nor as to ad valorem taxes on real or personal property nor as to special-purpose obligations or assessments heretofore imposed by another state in connection with particular kinds of insurance, other than property insurance; except that deductions, from premium taxes or other taxes otherwise payable, allowed on account of real estate or personal property taxes paid shall be taken into consideration by the Director of Insurance in determining the propriety and extent of retaliatory action under this section.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section shall require retaliatory action because of fees, obligations, or prohibitions imposed on Nebraska insurance producers licensed pursuant to the Insurance Producers Licensing Act.</para><para>(4) For the purposes of this section the domicile of an alien insurer, other than insurers formed under the laws of Canada, shall be that state designated by the insurer in writing filed with the Director of Insurance at time of admission to this state or within twelve months after September 28, 1959, whichever date is the later, and may be any one of the following states: (a) That in which the insurer was first authorized to transact insurance; (b) that in which is located the insurer's principal place of business in the United States; or (c) that in which is held the larger deposit of trusteed assets of the insurer for the protection of its policyholders and creditors in the United States.</para><para>If the insurer makes no such designation its domicile shall be deemed to be that state in which is located its principal place of business in the United States.</para><para>In the case of an insurer formed under the laws of Canada or a province thereof, its domicile shall be deemed to be that province in which its head office is situated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 24, p. 408; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3160; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 72, &#167; 1, p. 176; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. III, &#167; 17, p. 586; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7761; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-217; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 100, &#167; 1, p. 348; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 44-217; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-150; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 194, &#167; 1, p. 700; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 260, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 51, &#167; 23. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Producers Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4047.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 