<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-113</statuteno><catchline>Department; report; contents.</catchline>
<para>The Department of Insurance shall transmit to the Governor, ten days
prior to the opening of each session of the Legislature, a report of its official
transactions, containing in a condensed form the statements made to the department
by every insurance company authorized to do business in this state pursuant
to Chapter
44, as audited and corrected by it, arranged in tabular form or in abstracts,
in classes according to the kind of insurance, which report shall also contain
(1) a statement of all insurance companies authorized to do business in this
state during the year ending December 31 next preceding, with their names,
locations, amounts of capital, dates of incorporation, and of the commencement
of business and kinds of insurance in which they are engaged respectively;
and (2) a statement of the insurance companies whose business has been closed
since making the last report, and the reasons for closing such
businesses, with the amount of their assets and liabilities, so
far as the amount of their assets and liabilities are
known or can be ascertained by the department. The report shall also be transmitted electronically to the Clerk
of the Legislature. Each member of the Legislature shall receive a copy of
such report by making a request for it to the director. The department may
transmit the report by electronic format through the portal established under section 84-1204 after
notification of such type of delivery is given to the recipient. The department
shall maintain the report in a form capable of accurate duplication on paper.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 18, p. 405; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3154; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. III, &#167; 11, p. 583; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7755; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-211; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-113; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 359, &#167; 2, p. 1268; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 216, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 53.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>