<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-416.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-416.08</statuteno><catchline>Qualified United States financial institution, defined.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of subdivision (3) of section 44-416.07, qualified United States financial institution means an institution that:</para><para>(a) Is organized or, in the case of a United States office of a foreign banking organization, licensed under the laws of the United States or any state thereof;</para><para>(b) Is regulated, supervised, and examined by United States federal or state authorities having regulatory authority over banks and trust companies; and</para><para>(c) Has been determined by either the Director of Insurance or the Securities Valuation Office of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners to meet such standards of financial condition and standing as are considered necessary and appropriate to regulate the quality of financial institutions whose letters of credit will be acceptable to the director.</para><para>(2) For purposes of those provisions of sections 44-416.05 to 44-416.10 specifying those institutions that are eligible to act as a fiduciary of a trust, qualified United States financial institution means an institution that:</para><para>(a) Is organized or, in the case of a United States branch or agency office of a foreign banking organization, licensed under the laws of the United States or any state thereof and has been granted authority to operate with fiduciary powers; and</para><para>(b) Is regulated, supervised, and examined by federal or state authorities having regulatory authority over banks and trust companies.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 33. </para></source></law></legaldoc>