<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id531"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7,109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7,109</statuteno><catchline>Network provider; legislative findings; facility; prohibited acts; contract voidable.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds and declares that:</para><para>(a) Nebraskans who have a plan of health insurance, health benefits, or health care services provided through a health insurer and who receive health care services from a network provider receive such health care services at rates negotiated by the health insurer;</para><para>(b) As part of such negotiations, network providers agree to accept set reimbursement from the health insurer for the health care services provided by the network provider;</para><para>(c) The person covered by the health insurer is protected by the contract between the health insurer and the network provider from receiving a bill for the balance between the negotiated rate and a billed charge;</para><para>(d) Nebraskans need to know the network status of the provider in order to understand the plan of health insurance, health benefits, or health care services applicable to the health care services being provided by the provider; and</para><para>(e) It is necessary to regulate communication by providers to avoid communication that may mislead or cause confusion for Nebraskans receiving care from providers about their network status.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Facility means an institution providing health care services or a health care setting, including, but not limited to, a hospital or other licensed inpatient center, an ambulatory surgical or treatment center, a skilled nursing center, a residential treatment center, a diagnostic, laboratory, or imaging center, or any rehabilitation or other therapeutic health setting. Facility does not include a physician's office;</para><para>(b) Health insurer means an entity that contracts, offers to contract, or enters into an agreement to provide, deliver, arrange for, pay for, or reimburse any of the costs of health care services, including a sickness and accident insurance company, a health maintenance organization, a prepaid limited health service organization, a prepaid dental service corporation, or any other entity providing a plan of health insurance, health benefits, or health care services. Health insurer does not include a self-funded employee benefit plan to the extent preempted by federal law or a workers' compensation insurer, risk management pool, or self-insured employer who contracts for services to be provided through a managed care plan certified pursuant to section 48-120.02; and</para><para>(c) Network provider means a facility providing services under a plan of health insurance, health benefits, or health care services if the plan either requires a person covered by the health insurer to use, or creates a financial incentive by providing a more favorable deductible, coinsurance, or copayment level for a person covered by the health insurer to use, a health care provider managed, owned, under contract with, or employed by the health insurer which administers the plan.</para><para>(3) A facility shall not advertise or hold itself out as a network provider, including any statement that the facility takes or accepts any health insurer, unless the facility is a network provider of the health insurer. A facility that advertises itself as a network provider of a health insurer shall provide a clarifying statement if the facility is not a network provider for all insurance products offered by the health insurer.</para><para>(4) Any contract entered into between a facility and a person covered by a health insurer is voidable at the option of the covered person if the facility violates this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB774, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>