<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id330"><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Insurance" id="id332"  statutenumber="44-1117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1117</statuteno><catchline>Fraudulent viatical settlement act; additional prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) With respect to any viatical settlement contract or insurance policy, no viatical settlement broker shall knowingly solicit an offer from, effectuate a viatical settlement with, or make a sale to any viatical settlement provider, viatical settlement purchaser, financing entity, or related provider trust that is controlling, controlled by, or under common control with such viatical settlement broker.</para><para>(2) With respect to any viatical settlement contract or insurance policy, no viatical settlement provider shall knowingly enter into a viatical settlement contract with a viator if, in connection with such viatical settlement contract, anything of value will be paid to a viatical settlement broker that is controlling, controlled by, or under common control with such viatical settlement provider or the viatical settlement purchaser, financing entity, or related provider trust that is involved in such viatical settlement contract.</para><para>(3) A violation of subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall be a fraudulent viatical settlement act.</para><para>(4) No viatical settlement provider shall enter into a viatical settlement contract unless the viatical settlement promotional, advertising, and marketing materials as may be prescribed by rule and regulation have been filed with the director. In no event shall any marketing materials expressly reference that the insurance is free for any period of time. The inclusion of any reference in the marketing materials that would cause a viator to reasonably believe that the insurance is free for any period of time shall be considered a violation of the Viatical Settlements Act.</para><para>(5) No life insurance producer, insurance company, viatical settlement broker, or viatical settlement provider shall make any statement or representation to the applicant or policyholder in connection with the sale or financing of a life insurance policy to the effect that the insurance is free or without cost to the policyholder for any period of time unless provided in the policy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB853, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
