<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id140"><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Insurance" id="id142"  statutenumber="44-1606.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1606.03</statuteno><catchline>Group life insurance; policy; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Group life insurance offered to a resident of this state under a group life insurance policy issued to a group other than one described in sections 21-1740, 44-1602 to 44-1606.02, and 44-1615 shall be subject to the following requirements:</para><para>(a) A group life insurance policy shall not be delivered in this state unless the Director of Insurance finds that:</para><para>(i) The issuance of the group policy is not contrary to the best interests of the public;</para><para>(ii) The issuance of the group policy would result in economies of acquisition or administration; and </para><para>(iii) The benefits are reasonable in relation to the premiums charged;</para><para>(b) A group life insurance policy shall not be offered in this state by an insurer under a policy issued in another state unless this state or another state having requirements substantially similar to those contained in subdivision (1)(a) of this section has made a determination that the requirements have been met;</para><para>(c) The premium for the policy shall be paid either from the policyholder's funds or from funds contributed by the covered persons, or from both; and</para><para>(d) An insurer may exclude or limit the coverage on any person as to whom evidence of individual insurability is not satisfactory to the insurer.</para><para>(2)(a) In the case of a program of insurance which, if issued on a group basis, would not qualify under sections 21-1740, 44-1602 to 44-1606.02, and 44-1615, the insurer shall cause to be distributed to prospective insureds a written notice that compensation shall or may be paid, if compensation of any kind shall or may be paid, to:</para><para>(i) A policyholder or sponsoring or endorsing entity in the case of a group policy; or</para><para>(ii) A sponsoring or endorsing entity in the case of an individual, blanket, or franchise policy marketed by means of direct response solicitation.</para><para>(b) The notice shall be distributed:</para><para>(i) Whether compensation is direct or indirect; and</para><para>(ii) Whether the compensation is paid to or retained by the policyholder or sponsoring or endorsing entity, or paid to or retained by a third party at the direction of the policyholder or sponsoring or endorsing entity, or an entity affiliated therewith by way of ownership, contract, or employment.</para><para>(c) The notice required by this section shall be placed on or accompany an application or enrollment form provided to prospective insureds.</para><para>(d) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(i) Direct response solicitation means a solicitation by a sponsoring or endorsing entity through the mail, telephone, or other mass communications media; and</para><para>(ii) Sponsoring or endorsing entity means an organization that has arranged for the offering of a program of insurance in a manner that communicates that eligibility for participation in the program is dependent upon affiliation with the organization or that it encourages participation in the program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167;  15.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>