  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-1606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1606</statuteno><catchline>Life insurance; policy issued to an association of public employees; requirements.</catchline><para>A policy issued to an association of public employees having, when the policy is placed in force, a membership in the classes eligible for insurance of not less than seventy-five percent of the number of employees eligible for membership in such classes, which association shall be deemed the policyholder, to insure members of such association for the benefit of persons other than the association or any of its officials, shall be subject to the following requirements:</para><para>(1) The persons eligible for insurance under the policy shall be all of the members of the association, or all of any class or classes thereof determined by conditions pertaining to their employment, or to membership in the association, or both.</para><para>(2) The premium for the policy shall be paid by the policyholder, either from the association's own funds, or from charges collected from the insured members specifically for the insurance, or from both. Any charges collected from the insured members specifically for the insurance, and the dues of the association if they include the cost of the insurance, shall be collected through deductions by the employer from the salaries of the members. Such deductions from salary may be paid by the employer to the association or directly to the insurer. No policy may be placed in force unless and until at least seventy-five percent of the then eligible members of the association, excluding any as to whom evidence of individual insurability is not satisfactory to the insurer, have elected to be covered and have authorized their employer to make the required deductions from salary.</para><para>(3) The policy must cover at least twenty-five persons at date of issue.</para><para>(4) As used in this section, public employees mean employees of the United States Government, or of any state, county, city, village, or political subdivision thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 150, &#167; 1(5), p. 382. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 