<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-1998"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1998</statuteno><catchline>Form filing.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A title insurer or rate service organization shall not deliver or issue for delivery or permit any of its title insurance agents to deliver in this state any form, in connection with title insurance business written, unless it has been filed with the director and approved by the director or thirty days have elapsed and it has not been disapproved. The waiting period may be extended for an additional period not to exceed thirty days if the director gives written notice within such waiting period to the title insurer or authorized rate service organization which made the filing that additional time is needed for consideration of the filing.</para><para>(b) Forms shall not (i) be unjust, unfair, or inequitable, (ii) be misleading, be deceptive, or encourage misrepresentation of the coverage, (iii) be contrary to public policy, or (iv) provide coverage that is of such a limited nature so as to be contrary to public interest.</para><para>(2) Forms covered by this section shall include:</para><para>(a) Title insurance policies, including standard form endorsements; and</para><para>(b) Title insurance commitments.</para><para>(3) After notice and opportunity to be heard are given to the title insurer or rate service organization which submitted a form for approval, the director may withdraw approval of the form on finding that the use of the form is contrary to the legal requirements applicable at the time of withdrawal. The effective date of withdrawal of approval shall not be less than ninety days after notice of withdrawal is given.</para><para>(4) An approved title insurance policy form or endorsement providing coverage for which no identifiable premium is assessed shall be incorporated into every applicable title insurance policy. The title insurer shall disclose any additional coverage to the insured. The provisions of this section shall not operate to eliminate any underwriting standard of conditions relating to the approved title insurance policy forms or endorsements.</para><para>(5) Any term or condition related to insurance coverage provided by an approved title insurance policy or any exception to the coverage, except those ascertained from a search and examination of records relating to a title or an inspection or survey of a property to be insured, may only be included in the title insurance policy after the term, condition, or exception has been filed with the director and approved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 53, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 