<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-1993"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1993</statuteno><catchline>Duties of title insurers utilizing the services of title insurance agents; liability.</catchline><para>(1) A title insurer shall not accept title insurance business from a title insurance agent unless there is in force a written contract between the parties which sets forth the responsibilities of each party and, when both parties share responsibility for a particular function, specifies the division of responsibilities.</para><para>(2) For each title insurance agent under contract with a title insurer, the title insurer shall have on file a statement of financial condition of each title insurance agent as of the end of the previous calendar year setting forth an income statement of title insurance business done during the preceding year and a balance sheet showing the condition of its affairs as of the prior December 31 certified by the title insurance agent as being a true and accurate representation of the title insurance agent's financial condition. Attorneys actively engaged in the practice of law, other than that related to title insurance business, are exempt from the requirements of this subsection.</para><para>(3) A title insurer shall, at least annually, conduct a review of the underwriting, claims, and escrow practices of the title insurance agent which shall include a review of the title insurance agent's title insurance policy form inventory and processing operations. If the title insurance agent does not maintain separate financial institution or trust accounts for each title insurer it represents, the title insurer shall verify that the funds held on its behalf are reasonably ascertainable from the books of account and records of the title insurance agent.</para><para>(4) Within thirty days after executing or terminating a contract with a title insurance agent, a title insurer shall provide written notification of the appointment or termination and the reason for termination to the director. Notices of appointment of a title insurance agent shall be made on a form prescribed or approved by the director.</para><para>(5) A title insurer shall maintain an inventory of all title insurance policy forms or title insurance policy numbers allocated to each title insurance agent.</para><para>(6) A title insurer shall have on file proof that each title insurance agent is licensed by this state.</para><para>(7) A title insurer shall establish the underwriting guidelines and, when applicable, limitations on title claims settlement authority to be incorporated into contracts with its title insurance agents.</para><para>(8)(a) A title insurer is liable for the defalcation, conversion, or misappropriation by a title insurance agent appointed by or under written contract with such title insurer of escrow, settlement, closing, or security deposit funds handled by such title insurance agent in contemplation of or in conjunction with the issuance of a title insurance commitment or title insurance policy by such title insurer. However, if no such title insurance commitment or title insurance policy was issued, each title insurer which appointed or maintained a written contract with such title insurance agent at the time of the discovery of the defalcation, conversion, or misappropriation shares in the liability for the defalcation, conversion, or misappropriation in the same proportion that the premium remitted to the title insurer by such title insurance agent during the twelve-month period immediately preceding the date of the discovery of the defalcation, conversion, or misappropriation bears to the total premium remitted to all title insurers by such title insurance agent during the twelve-month period immediately preceding the date of the discovery of the defalcation, conversion, or misappropriation.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this subsection, title insurance agent includes (i) a person with whom a title insurer maintains a title insurance agency agreement and (ii) an employer or employee of a title insurance agent or of a person with whom a title insurer maintains a title insurance agency agreement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 53, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 155, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 56. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>