<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id114"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id116" statutenumber="44-1605"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id118">44-1605</statuteno><catchline id="id119">Life insurance; policy issued to trust or trustees of a fund; requirements.</catchline><para>A policy issued to a trust or to the trustees of a fund established or adopted by two or more employers or by one or more labor unions or similar employee organizations, or by one or more employers and one or more labor unions or similar employee organizations, which trust or trustees shall be deemed the policyholder, to insure employees of the employers or members of the unions or organizations for the benefit of persons other than the employers or the unions or organizations shall be subject to the following requirements:</para><para>(1) The persons eligible for insurance shall be all of the employees of the employers or all of the members of the unions or organizations, or all of any class or classes thereof. The policy may provide that the term employees shall include the employees of one or more subsidiary corporations and the employees, individual proprietors, members, and partners of one or more affiliated corporations, proprietorships, or partnerships if the business of the employer and of the affiliated corporations, proprietorships, or partnerships is under common control. The policy may provide that the term employees shall include the individual proprietor or partners if the employer is an individual proprietorship or partnership. The policy may provide that the term employees may include retired employees, former employees, and directors of a corporate employer. The policy may provide that the term employees shall include the trustees or their employees, or both, if their duties are principally connected with such trusteeship; and</para><para>(2) The premium for the policy shall be paid from funds contributed by the employer or employers of the insured persons, by the union or unions or similar employee organizations, or by both, or from funds contributed by the insured persons or from both the insured persons and the employers or unions or similar employee organizations. A policy on which no part of the premium is to be derived from funds contributed by the insured persons specifically for their insurance shall insure all eligible persons, except those who reject the coverage in writing, or all except any as to whom evidence of individual insurability is not satisfactory to the insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 150, &#167; 1(4), p. 380; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 192, &#167; 4, p. 674; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 376, &#167; 1, p. 1336; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 176; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 235; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
