<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id185"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id187" statutenumber="44-1106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id189">44-1106</statuteno><catchline id="id190">Reporting requirements; confidentiality.</catchline><para>(1) Each viatical settlement provider shall file with the director on or before March 1 of each year an annual statement containing such information as the director may prescribe by rule and regulation. Such information shall be limited to only those transactions where the viator is a resident of this state. Individual transaction data regarding the business of viatical settlements or data that could compromise the privacy of personal, financial, or health information of the viator or insured shall be filed with the director on a confidential basis.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise allowed or required by law, a viatical settlement provider, viatical settlement broker, insurance company, insurance producer, information bureau, rating agency or company, or any other person with actual knowledge of an insured's identity shall not disclose that identity as an insured or the insured's financial or medical information to any other person unless the disclosure:</para><para>(a) Is necessary to effect a viatical settlement between the viator and a viatical settlement provider and the viator and insured have provided prior written consent to the disclosure;</para><para>(b) Is provided in response to an investigation or examination by the director or any other governmental officer or agency or pursuant to the requirements of subsection (3) of section 44-1112;</para><para>(c) Is a term of or condition to the transfer of a policy by one viatical settlement provider to another viatical settlement provider;</para><para>(d) Is necessary to permit a financing entity, related provider trust, or special purpose entity to finance the purchase of policies by a viatical settlement provider and the viator and insured have provided prior written consent to the disclosure;</para><para>(e) Is necessary to allow the viatical settlement provider or viatical settlement broker or his or her authorized representative to make contacts for the purpose of determining health status; or</para><para>(f) Is required to purchase stop-loss or financial guaranty coverage.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 216, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB853, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
