<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id159"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id161" statutenumber="44-1104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id163">44-1104</statuteno><catchline id="id164">Disciplinary actions.</catchline><para>(1) The director may suspend, revoke, or refuse to issue or renew a license issued under the Viatical Settlements Act or that of a life insurance producer operating as a viatical settlement broker under subdivision (1)(b) of section 44-1103 if the director finds that:</para><para>(a) There was any material misrepresentation in the application for the license;</para><para>(b) The applicant or licensee or any officer, partner, member, or key management personnel is subject to a final administrative action or is otherwise shown to be untrustworthy or incompetent;</para><para>(c) The viatical settlement provider demonstrates a pattern of unreasonable payments to viators;</para><para>(d) The applicant or licensee or any officer, partner, member, or key management personnel has been found guilty of, or has pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to, any felony or a Class I, II, or III misdemeanor, regardless of whether a judgment of conviction has been entered by the court;</para><para>(e) The viatical settlement provider has entered into any viatical settlement contract that has not been approved pursuant to the Viatical Settlements Act;</para><para>(f) The viatical settlement broker or viatical settlement provider has failed to honor contractual obligations set out in a viatical settlement contract;</para><para>(g) The licensee no longer meets the requirements for initial licensure;</para><para>(h) The viatical settlement provider has assigned, transferred, or pledged a viaticated policy to a person other than a viatical settlement provider licensed in this state, a viatical settlement purchaser, an accredited investor or qualified institutional buyer as defined in Rule 144A of the federal Securities Act of 1933, as the act existed on January 1, 2008, a financing entity, a special purpose entity, or a related provider trust;</para><para>(i) The applicant or licensee or any officer, partner, member, or key management personnel has violated any provision of the Viatical Settlements Act or has otherwise engaged in bad faith conduct with one or more viators; or</para><para>(j) The licensee has failed to respond to the department within fifteen working days after receipt of an inquiry from the department.</para><para>(2) The director may suspend or revoke a license pursuant to subsection (1) of this section after notice and a hearing held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(3) If the director denies a license application or refuses to renew a license pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, he or she shall notify the applicant or licensee of the reason for such denial or refusal of renewal. The applicant or licensee has thirty days after receipt of such notification to demand a hearing. The hearing shall be held within thirty days after receipt of such demand by the director and shall be held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB853, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc>
