<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id123"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id125" statutenumber="44-1606.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id127">44-1606.01</statuteno><catchline id="id128">Life insurance; policy issued to association or trust; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A policy may be issued to an association or to a trust or to the trustees of a fund established, created, or maintained for the benefit of members of one or more associations. The association or associations shall have at the outset a minimum of one hundred persons, shall have been organized and maintained in good faith for purposes other than that of obtaining insurance, shall have been in active existence for at least two years, and shall have a constitution and bylaws which provide that (a) the association or associations shall hold regular meetings not less than annually to further the purposes of the members, (b) except for credit unions, the association or associations shall collect dues or solicit contributions from members, and (c) the members shall have voting privileges and representation on the governing board and committees.</para><para>(2) The policy shall be subject to the following requirements:</para><para>(a) The policy may insure members of the association or associations, employees thereof or employees of members, or one or more of the preceding or all of any class or classes thereof for the benefit of persons other than the employee's employer;</para><para>(b) The premium for the policy shall be paid from funds contributed by the association or associations, by the employer members, or by both, or from funds contributed by the covered persons or from both the covered persons and the associations or employer members; and</para><para>(c) A policy on which no part of the premium is to be derived from funds contributed by the covered persons specifically for their insurance must insure all eligible persons, except those who reject the coverage in writing, or all except any as to whom evidence of individual insurability is not satisfactory to the insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 192, &#167; 5, p. 675; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 274, &#167; 1, p. 739; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1189, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 13.</para></source><annotation><para>Where policy issued was not life policy but accident policy, insurer could deny certain coverage to wife of member. Simmons v. Continental Cas. Co., 410 F.2d 881 (8th Cir. 1969).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
