<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id514"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-1552"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1552</statuteno><catchline>Administrative, civil, or criminal liability; immunity; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer or trained individual who, acting reasonably and in good faith, complies with section 44-1551 or the Insurance Fraud Act shall be immune from any administrative or civil liability that might otherwise arise from such delay in a disbursement or transaction or any other actions or omissions related to the administration of the Nebraska Protection of Seniors from Insurance Exploitation Act. An insurer or trained individual shall be immune from administrative or civil liability for not choosing to implement a program to comply with section 44-1551. An insurer or trained individual shall not be liable for the actions of a permissible third party.</para><para>(2) An insurer or trained individual shall be immune from any civil, criminal, or administrative liability for declining to interact with a permissible third party if the insurer or trained individual reasonably believes that:</para><para>(a) The permissible third party is, may be, or may have been engaged in the financial exploitation of the eligible adult; or</para><para>(b) Such interaction is not in the best interests of the eligible adult.</para><para>(3) A permissible third party who acts in good faith and exercises reasonable care in providing information to the insurer or trained individual, or in assisting the insurer, trained individual, or law enforcement in an investigation of suspected financial exploitation, shall be immune from any administrative, civil, or criminal liability that might otherwise arise from such actions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB967, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Fraud Act,</emphasis> see section 44-6601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>