
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id444"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-1402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-1402</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Right to Shop Act:</para><para>(1) Allowed amount means the contractually agreed upon amount paid by an insurance carrier to a health care entity participating in the insurance carrier’s network or the amount the health plan is required to pay under the health plan policy or certificate of insurance for out-of-network covered benefits provided to the patient;</para><para>(2) Department means the Department of Insurance;</para><para>(3) Director means the Director of Insurance;</para><para>(4) Enrollee means an individual receiving health insurance coverage from an insurance carrier;</para><para>(5) Health care entity means:</para><para>(a) A facility licensed under the Health Care Facility Licensure Act;</para><para>(b) A health care professional licensed under the Uniform Credentialing Act; and</para><para>(c) An organization or association of health care professionals licensed under the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para><para>(6) Incentive payment means a payment described in section 44-1407 that is made by an insurance carrier to an enrollee;</para><para>(7) Insurance carrier means any entity that provides health insurance in this state. Insurance carrier includes (a) an insurance company, (b) a fraternal benefit society, (c) a health maintenance organization, and (d) any other entity providing a plan of health insurance or health benefits subject to state insurance regulation;</para><para>(8) Shared savings incentive payment program means a program established by an insurance carrier pursuant to section 44-1407 to provide incentive payments to enrollees; and</para><para>(9) Shoppable health care service means a health care service for which an insurance carrier offers incentive payments under a shared savings incentive payment program established by the insurance carrier. Shoppable health care service includes, at a minimum, health care services in the following categories:</para><para>(a) Physical and occupational therapy services;</para><para>(b) Obstetrical and gynecological services;</para><para>(c) Radiology and imaging services;</para><para>(d) Laboratory services;</para><para>(e) Infusion therapy;</para><para>(f) Inpatient or outpatient surgical procedures; and</para><para>(g) Outpatient nonsurgical diagnostic tests or procedures.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1119, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>