<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2810"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2810</statuteno><catchline>Malpractice or professional negligence, defined.</catchline><para>Malpractice or professional negligence shall mean that, in rendering professional services, a health care provider has failed to use the ordinary and reasonable care, skill, and knowledge ordinarily possessed and used under like circumstances by members of his profession engaged in a similar practice in his or in similar localities. In determining what constitutes reasonable and ordinary care, skill, and diligence on the part of a health care provider in a particular community, the test shall be that which health care providers, in the same community or in similar communities and engaged in the same or similar lines of work, would ordinarily exercise and devote to the benefit of their patients under like circumstances.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 434, &#167; 10. </para></source><annotation><para>The applicable standard of care in medical malpractice cases is established by the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act and has a locality focus, but otherwise is consistent with the general common-law standard of care. Hemsley v. Langdon, 299 Neb. 464, 909 N.W.2d 59 (2018).</para><para>Hospital policies and rules do not conclusively determine the standard of care owed. Green v. Box Butte General Hosp., 284 Neb. 243, 818 N.W.2d 589 (2012).</para><para>This section of the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act specifically provides for use of the locality rule. Fales v. Books, 253 Neb. 491, 570 N.W.2d 841 (1997).</para><para>Plaintiff failed to allege that defendants, in rendering professional services, failed to use the ordinary and reasonable care, skill, and knowledge ordinarily possessed and used under like circumstances by health care providers practicing in the community. Hitzemann v. Adam, 246 Neb. 201, 518 N.W.2d 102 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>