<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2821"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2821</statuteno><catchline>Health care provider; failure to qualify under act; liability under common law; qualified under act; remedy; election not to be bound by act; procedure; post sign; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Any health care provider who fails to qualify under the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act shall not be covered by the provisions of such act and shall be subject to liability under doctrines of common law. If a health care provider shall not so qualify, the patient's remedy shall not be affected by the terms and provisions of the act.</para><para>(2) If a health care provider shall qualify under the act, the patient's exclusive remedy against the health care provider or his or her partner, limited liability company member, employer, or employees for alleged malpractice, professional negligence, failure to provide care, breach of contract relating to providing medical care, or other claim based upon failure to obtain informed consent for an operation or treatment shall be as provided by the act unless the patient shall have elected not to come under the provisions of the act. Unless the patient or his or her representative shall have (a) elected not to be bound by the terms of the act, (b) filed such election with the director in advance of any treatment, act, or omission upon which any claim or cause of action is based, and (c) notified the health care provider of election as soon as is reasonable under the circumstances that such patient has so elected, it shall be conclusively presumed that the patient has elected to be bound by the terms and provisions of the act. Such election may be made by either legal parent for an unborn or newborn child. Unless a legal parent of an unborn child or the guardian or other representative of a minor or incompetent makes the election in the manner provided in the act for such unborn person, minor, or incompetent, such person shall be deemed to be subject to the terms and provisions of the act.</para><para>(3) An election of a patient not to be bound by the act shall be effective for a period of two years after filing unless such election is withdrawn by the patient and shall be ineffective after such two-year period unless renewed in writing and filed with the director. The patient or his or her representative may revoke the election in writing at any time and a copy of such revocation shall be forwarded to the director within five days after the same is made.</para><para>(4) Each health care provider who has qualified under the act shall post and keep posted in his or her waiting room or other suitable location a sign of a size and type to be prescribed by the director stating: (name of health care provider) has qualified under the provisions of the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act. Patients will be subject to the terms and provisions of that act unless they file a refusal to be bound by the act with the Director of Insurance of the State of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 434, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 692, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 246; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 58. </para></source><annotation><para>Whether or not a hospital did in fact qualify under the act was unimportant as no prejudice resulted from the standard of care instruction given to the jury. Gilbert v. Archbishop Bergan Mercy Hospital, 228 Neb. 148, 421 N.W.2d 760 (1988).</para><para>The health care provider and patient both remain subject to the act until disposition, if the claim arose when both were so subject. Prendergast v. Nelson, 199 Neb. 97, 256 N.W.2d 657 (1977).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>