<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2408"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2408</statuteno><catchline>Association; plan of operation; amendments; submit to director.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The association shall submit to the director a plan of operation and any amendments thereto necessary or suitable to assure the fair, reasonable, and equitable administration of the affairs of the association. The plan of operation and any amendments thereto shall become effective upon approval in writing by the director.</para><para>(b) If the association fails to submit suitable amendments to the plan, the director shall, after allowing the association the opportunity to present its views, adopt and promulgate reasonable rules and regulations as are necessary and advisable to effectuate the Nebraska Property and Liability Insurance Guaranty Association Act. Such rules and regulations shall continue in force until modified by the director or superseded by a plan submitted by the association and approved by the director.</para><para>(2) All member insurers shall comply with the plan of operation.</para><para>(3) The plan of operation shall:</para><para>(a) Establish the procedures whereby all the powers and duties of the association under the act will be performed;</para><para>(b) Establish procedures for handling the assets of the association;</para><para>(c) Establish the amount and method of reimbursing members of the board of directors under section 44-2405;</para><para>(d) Establish procedures by which claims may be filed with the association and establish acceptable forms of proof of covered claims;</para><para>(e) Establish regular places and times for meetings of the board of directors;</para><para>(f) Establish procedures for records to be kept of all financial transactions of the association, its agents, and the board of directors;</para><para>(g) Provide that any member insurer aggrieved by any final action or decision of the association may appeal to the director within sixty days after the action or decision;</para><para>(h) Establish the procedures whereby selection of the board of directors will be submitted to the director for approval; and</para><para>(i) Contain additional provisions necessary or proper for the execution of the powers and duties of the association.</para><para>(4) The plan of operation may provide that any or all powers and duties of the association are delegated to a corporation, association, or other organization which performs, or will perform, functions similar to those of the association, or its equivalent, in two or more states. Such corporation, association, or organization shall be reimbursed as a servicing facility would be reimbursed and shall be paid for its performance of any other functions of the association. A delegation under this subsection shall take effect only with the approval of both the board of directors and the director and may be made only to a corporation, association, or organization which extends protection not substantially less favorable and effective than that provided by the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 722, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 200. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 