<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2831"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2831</statuteno><catchline>Excess Liability Fund; special surcharge; reinsurance.</catchline><para>(1) The director may, at any time, analyze the fund to determine if the amount in such fund is inadequate to pay in full all claims allowed or to be allowed during the calendar year. Upon such determination, the director shall have the power to levy a special surcharge on all health care providers who have qualified under the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act, which special surcharge shall be an amount sufficient to permit full payment of all claims allowed against the fund during a calendar year. The special surcharge shall be levied against all health care providers who have qualified under the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act on the date of the special surcharge or at any time during the preceding twelve months and shall be in an amount proportionate to the surcharge each health care provider has paid to the fund. Such special surcharge shall be due and payable within thirty days after the same is levied.</para><para>(2) The director shall have authority to cause all or any part of the potential liability of the Excess Liability Fund to be reinsured, if such reinsurance is available, on a fair and reasonable basis. The cost of such reinsurance shall be paid by the fund and the fact of the reinsurance shall be taken into account in determining the surcharge as provided in sections 44-2829 and 44-2830, but in no event shall the surcharge exceed fifty percent of the annual premium paid by a health care provider for maintenance of current financial responsibility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 434, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 692, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 146, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 998, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 