<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2135"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2135</statuteno><catchline>Management of domestic insurer.</catchline>
<para>(1) Notwithstanding the control of a domestic insurer by any person,
the officers and directors of the insurer shall not thereby be relieved of
any obligation or liability to which they would otherwise be subject by law,
and the insurer shall be managed so as to assure its separate operating identity
consistent with the Insurance Holding Company System Act.</para>
<para>(2) Nothing in this section shall preclude a domestic insurer from having
or sharing a common management or cooperative or joint use of personnel, property,
or services with one or more other persons under arrangements meeting the
standards of subsection (1) of section 44-2133.</para>
<para>(3) Not less than one-third of the directors of a domestic insurer which
is a member of an insurance holding company system shall be persons who are
not officers or employees of such insurer or of any entity controlling, controlled
by, or under common control with such insurer and who are not beneficial owners
of a controlling interest in the voting stock of such insurer or any such
entity. At least one such person shall be included in any quorum for the transaction
of business at any meeting of the board of directors.</para>
<para>(4) Subsection (3) of this section shall not apply to a domestic insurer
if the person controlling such insurer,
such as an insurer, a mutual insurance holding company, or a publicly held
corporation, has a board of directors that meets the requirements
of such subsection with respect
to such controlling entity.</para>
<para>(5) An insurer may make
application to the director for a waiver from the requirements of this section
if the insurer's annual direct written and assumed premium, excluding premiums
reinsured with the Federal Crop Insurance Corporation and the national flood
insurance program as defined in section 31-1014, is less than three hundred
million dollars. An insurer may also make application to the director for
a waiver from the requirements of this section based upon unique circumstances.
The director may consider various factors including, but not limited to, the
type of business entity, volume of business written, availability of qualified
board members, or ownership or organizational structure of the entity.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>