<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2710"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2710</statuteno><catchline>Director; powers and duties; enumerated.</catchline><para>In addition to the powers and duties enumerated in the Nebraska Life and Health Insurance Guaranty Association Act:</para><para>(1) The director shall:</para><para>(a) Notify the board of directors of the existence of an impaired or insolvent insurer not later than three days after a determination of impairment or insolvency is made or he or she receives notice of impairment or insolvency;</para><para>(b) Upon request of the board of directors, provide the association with a statement of the premiums in the appropriate states for each member insurer;</para><para>(c) When an impairment is declared and the amount of the impairment is determined, serve a demand upon the impaired insurer to make good the impairment within a reasonable time. Notice to the impaired insurer shall constitute notice to its shareholders, if any. The failure of the insurer to promptly comply with such demand shall not excuse the association from the performance of its powers and duties under the act;</para><para>(d) In any liquidation or rehabilitation proceeding under Nebraska law involving a domestic insurer, be appointed as the liquidator or rehabilitator. If a foreign or alien member insurer is subject to a liquidation proceeding in its domiciliary jurisdiction or state of entry, the director shall be appointed conservator; and</para><para>(e) Transmit to the association all claims on covered policies timely filed with him or her pursuant to the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act. The association shall then be considered to have been designated as the director's representative pursuant to the act, and it shall proceed to investigate, hear, settle, and determine such claims unless the claimant shall, within thirty days from the date the claim is filed with the director, file with the director a written demand that the claim be processed in the liquidation proceedings as a claim not covered by the Nebraska Life and Health Insurance Guaranty Association Act. In regard to those claims transmitted to the association by the director, the association and claimants shall have all of the rights and obligations and be subject to the same limitations and procedures as are specified in the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act for the determination of claims;</para><para>(2) The director may suspend or revoke, after notice and hearing, the certificate of authority to transact insurance in this state of any member insurer which fails to pay an assessment when due or fails to comply with the plan of operation. As an alternative, the director may levy a forfeiture on any member insurer which fails to pay an assessment when due. Such forfeiture shall not exceed five percent of the unpaid assessment per month, but no forfeiture shall be less than one hundred dollars per month;</para><para>(3) Any action of the board of directors or the association may be appealed to the director by any member insurer if such appeal is taken within thirty days of the action being appealed. Any final action or order of the director may be appealed, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act; and</para><para>(4) The liquidator, rehabilitator, or conservator of any impaired or insolvent insurer may notify all interested persons of the effect of the Nebraska Life and Health Insurance Guaranty Association Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 217, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 593, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 74. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4862.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 