<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2827.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2827.01</statuteno><catchline>General acute hospital; psychiatric or mental hospital operated by Board of Regents; physician employed by Board of Regents; risk-loss trust authorized; requirements; director; powers and duties; surcharge.</catchline><para>(1) Any general acute hospital as defined in section 71-412 or a psychiatric or mental hospital as defined in section 71-426 operated by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska or any physician employed by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska may, in addition to the methods of establishing financial responsibility provided in section 44-2827, establish financial responsibility by a risk-loss trust.</para><para>(2) In order to establish financial responsibility through the use of a risk-loss trust, the risk-loss trust shall be approved in writing by the director. Such approval shall expire on the last day of April in each year and shall be renewed annually thereafter if the risk-loss trust continues to comply with the requirements of the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act and any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated thereunder.</para><para>(3) The director shall approve the use of a risk-loss trust to establish financial responsibility if he or she determines from a review of the plan of operation or feasibility study for the risk-loss trust that (a) the risk-loss trust will comply with all of the applicable requirements of the act, (b) the risk-loss trust has a financial plan which provides for adequate funding and adequate reserves to establish and maintain financial responsibility, and (c) the risk-loss trust has a plan of management designed to provide for its competent operation and management.</para><para>(4) Any risk-loss trust shall be established and maintained only on an occurrence basis, shall maintain reserves for payment of claims, and shall process and act upon claims in accordance with guidelines acceptable for Nebraska domestic insurance companies. The funds, or any part thereof, of any risk-loss trust may be invested as authorized under the Insurers Investment Act for any domestic property and casualty insurance company.</para><para>(5) Any risk-loss trust shall file with the director, on or before March 1 of each year, a financial statement under oath for the year ending December 31 immediately preceding which shall include an actuarial or loss reserve specialist's opinion. The trust shall annually be audited by an independent accountant, and such audit shall be filed with the director.</para><para>(6) The director may examine the business affairs, records, and assets of such risk-loss trust to assure that it will be able to establish and maintain financial responsibility. Any examination conducted by the director or his or her authorized representative shall be at the expense of the risk-loss trust.</para><para>(7) If the director finds after notice to the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and a hearing that the risk-loss trust is not maintaining financial responsibility, he or she may order the board to take such action as is necessary to establish financial responsibility and upon failure by the board to comply therewith may revoke approval of such trust.</para><para>(8) If any hospital or physician establishes financial responsibility as provided in subsection (1) of this section, the annual surcharge amount which shall be levied against the board pursuant to section 44-2829 shall be established annually by the director after giving consideration to the following factors:</para><para>(a) The surcharge rate for hospitals and physicians set by the director pursuant to such section;</para><para>(b) The average rates charged by insurers of Nebraska hospitals and physicians;</para><para>(c) Variations in coverage provisions, liability limits, or deductibles between insurance provided by private insurers and the coverage provided by the risk-loss trust; and</para><para>(d) The loss experience of the board.</para><para>(9) The director may adopt and promulgate reasonable rules and regulations necessary and proper to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 542, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1035, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 74. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurers Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 