<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2138"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2138</statuteno><catchline>Information; confidential treatment; sharing of information; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) All information, documents, and copies thereof obtained by or disclosed to the director or any other person in the course of an examination or investigation made pursuant to section 44-2137 and all information reported or provided to the director pursuant to sections 44-2132 to 44-2136 and 44-2155 shall be given confidential treatment, shall not be subject to subpoena, and shall not be made public by the director, the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries, or any other person, except to other state, federal, foreign, and international regulatory and law enforcement agencies if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality of the information, without the prior written consent of the insurer to which it pertains unless the director, after giving the insurer and its affiliates who would be affected thereby notice and opportunity to be heard, determines that the interest of policyholders, shareholders, or the public will be served by the publication thereof, in which event he or she may publish all or any part thereof in such manner as he or she may deem appropriate.</para><para>(2) The director may receive information, documents, and copies of information and documents disclosed to other state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and from the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries pursuant to an examination of an insurance holding company system. The director shall maintain information, documents, and copies of information and documents received pursuant to this subsection as confidential or privileged if received with notice or the understanding that it is confidential or privileged under the laws of the jurisdiction that is the source of the information. Such information shall not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, subject to subpoena, subject to discovery, or admissible in evidence in any private civil action, except that the director may use such information in any regulatory or legal action brought by the director. The director, and any other person while acting under the authority of the director who has received information pursuant to this subsection, may not, and shall not be required to, testify in any private civil action concerning any information subject to this section. Nothing in this section shall constitute a waiver of any applicable privilege or claim of confidentiality in the information received pursuant to this subsection as a result of information sharing authorized by this section.</para><para>(3) In order to assist in the performance of the director's duties, the director may share information with state, federal, and international regulatory agencies, the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries, state, federal, and international law enforcement authorities, including members of any supervisory college described in section 44-2137.01, the International Association of Insurance Supervisors, and the Bank for International Settlements under the conditions set forth in section 44-154 if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality and privileged status of the document, material, or other information and has verified in writing the legal authority to maintain confidentiality. The director may only share confidential and privileged documents, material, or information reported pursuant to subsection (12) of section 44-2132 with directors or commissioners of states having statutes or regulations substantially similar to subsection (1) of this section and who have agreed in writing not to disclose such information.</para><para>(4) The director shall enter into written agreements with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners governing sharing and use of information provided pursuant to this section that shall:</para><para>(a) Specify procedures and protocols regarding the confidentiality and security of information shared with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries pursuant to this section, including procedures and protocols for sharing by the association with other state, federal, or international regulators;</para><para>(b) Specify that ownership of information shared with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries pursuant to this section remains with the director and the association's use of the information is subject to the direction of the director;</para><para>(c) Require prompt notice to be given to an insurer whose confidential information in the possession of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners pursuant to this section is subject to a request or subpoena to the association for disclosure or production; and</para><para>(d) Require the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries to consent to intervention by an insurer in any judicial or administrative action in which the association and its affiliates and subsidiaries may be required to disclose confidential information about the insurer shared with the association and its affiliates and subsidiaries pursuant to this section.</para><para>(5) The sharing of information by the director pursuant to this section shall not constitute a delegation of regulatory authority or rulemaking, and the director is solely responsible for the administration, execution, and enforcement of this section.</para><para>(6) No waiver of any applicable privilege or claim of confidentiality in the documents, materials, or information shall occur as a result of disclosure to the director under this section or as a result of sharing as authorized by this section.</para><para>(7) Documents, materials, or other information in the possession or control of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners pursuant to this section shall be confidential and privileged, shall not be subject to public disclosure under section 84-712, shall not be subject to subpoena, and shall not be subject to discovery or admissible as evidence in any private civil action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB772, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>