<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2132</statuteno><catchline>Registration of insurers.</catchline><para>(1) Every insurer which is authorized to do business in this state and which is a member of an insurance holding company system shall register with the director, except that registration shall not be required for a foreign insurer subject to registration requirements and standards adopted by statute or regulation in the jurisdiction of its domicile which are substantially similar to those contained in this section, subsection (1) of section 44-2133, sections 44-2134 and 44-2136, and either subsection (2) of section 44-2133 or a provision such as the following: Each registered insurer shall keep current the information required to be disclosed in its registration statement by reporting all material changes or additions within fifteen days after the end of the month in which it learns of each such change or addition. Any insurer which is subject to registration under this section shall register within fifteen days after it becomes subject to registration and annually thereafter by May 1 of each year for the previous calendar year unless the director for good cause shown extends the time for such initial or annual registration and then within such extended time. The director may require any insurer which is authorized to do business in the state, which is a member of an insurance holding company system, and which is not subject to registration under this section to furnish a copy of the registration statement, the summary specified in subsection (3) of this section, or other information filed by such insurer with the insurance regulatory authority of its domiciliary jurisdiction.</para><para>(2) Every insurer subject to registration shall file the registration statement on a form prescribed by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners which shall contain the following current information:</para><para>(a) The capital structure, general financial condition, ownership, and management of the insurer and any person controlling the insurer;</para><para>(b) The identity and relationship of every member of the insurance holding company system;</para><para>(c) The following agreements in force and transactions currently outstanding or which have occurred during the last calendar year between such insurer and its affiliates:</para><para>(i) Loans, other investments, or purchases, sales, or exchanges of securities of the affiliates by the insurer or of the insurer by its affiliates;</para><para>(ii) Purchases, sales, or exchanges of assets;</para><para>(iii) Transactions not in the ordinary course of business;</para><para>(iv) Guarantees or undertakings for the benefit of an affiliate which result in an actual contingent exposure of the insurer's assets to liability, other than insurance contracts entered into in the ordinary course of the insurer's business;</para><para>(v) All management agreements, service contracts, and cost-sharing arrangements;</para><para>(vi) Reinsurance agreements;</para><para>(vii) Dividends and other distributions to shareholders; and</para><para>(viii) Consolidated tax allocation agreements;</para><para>(d) Any pledge of the insurer's stock, including stock of any subsidiary or controlling affiliate, for a loan made to any member of the insurance holding company system; and</para><para>(e) Other matters concerning transactions between registered insurers and any affiliates as may be included from time to time in any registration forms adopted or approved by the director.</para><para>(3) All registration statements shall contain a summary outlining all items in the current registration statement representing changes from the prior registration statement.</para><para>(4) It shall not be necessary to disclose on the registration statement information which is not material for the purposes of this section. Unless the director by rule, regulation, or order provides otherwise, sales, purchases, exchanges, loans, or extensions of credit, investments, or guarantees involving one-half of one percent or less of an insurer's admitted assets as of December 31 next preceding shall not be deemed material for purposes of this section.</para><para>(5) Subject to the requirements of section 44-2134, each registered insurer shall give notice to the director of all dividends and other distributions to shareholders within five business days following the declaration thereof and shall not pay any such dividends or other distributions to shareholders within ten business days following receipt of such notice by the director unless for good cause shown the director has approved such payment within such ten-business-day period.</para><para>(6) Any person within an insurance holding company system subject to registration shall be required to provide complete and accurate information to an insurer when such information is reasonably necessary to enable the insurer to comply with the Insurance Holding Company System Act.</para><para>(7) The director shall terminate the registration of any insurer which demonstrates that it no longer is a member of an insurance holding company system.</para><para>(8) The director may require or allow two or more affiliated insurers subject to registration under this section to file a consolidated registration statement.</para><para>(9) The director may allow an insurer which is authorized to do business in this state and which is part of an insurance holding company system to register on behalf of any affiliated insurer which is required to register under subsection (1) of this section and to file all information and material required to be filed under this section.</para><para>(10) This section shall not apply to any insurer, information, or transaction if and to the extent that the director by rule, regulation, or order exempts the same from this section.</para><para>(11) Any person may file with the director a disclaimer of affiliation with any authorized insurer or such a disclaimer may be filed by such insurer or any member of an insurance holding company system. The disclaimer shall fully disclose all material relationships and bases for affiliation between such person and such insurer as well as the basis for disclaiming such affiliation. After a disclaimer has been filed, the insurer shall be relieved of any duty to register or report under this section which may arise out of the insurer's relationship with such person unless and until the director disallows such a disclaimer. The director shall disallow such a disclaimer only after furnishing all parties in interest with notice and opportunity to be heard and after making specific findings of fact to support such disallowance.</para><para>(12) The failure to file a registration statement or any summary of the registration statement thereto required by this section within the time specified for such filing shall be a violation of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 689, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc>