<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2138"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2138</statuteno><catchline>Information; confidential treatment.</catchline><para>(1) All information, documents, and copies thereof obtained by or disclosed to the director or any other person in the course of an examination or investigation made pursuant to section 44-2137 and all information reported pursuant to sections 44-2132 to 44-2136 shall be given confidential treatment, shall not be subject to subpoena, and shall not be made public by the director, the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries, or any other person, except to other state, federal, foreign, and international regulatory and law enforcement agencies if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality of the information, without the prior written consent of the insurer to which it pertains unless the director, after giving the insurer and its affiliates who would be affected thereby notice and opportunity to be heard, determines that the interest of policyholders, shareholders, or the public will be served by the publication thereof, in which event he or she may publish all or any part thereof in such manner as he or she may deem appropriate.</para><para>(2) The director may receive information, documents, and copies of information and documents disclosed to other state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and from the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries pursuant to an examination of an insurance holding company system. The director shall maintain information, documents, and copies of information and documents received pursuant to this subsection as confidential or privileged if received with notice or the understanding that it is confidential or privileged under the laws of the jurisdiction that is the source of the information. Such information shall not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, subject to subpoena, subject to discovery, or admissible in evidence in any private civil action, except that the director may use such information in any regulatory or legal action brought by the director. The director, and any other person while acting under the authority of the director who has received information pursuant to this subsection, may not, and shall not be required to, testify in any private civil action concerning any information subject to this section. Nothing in this section shall constitute a waiver of any applicable privilege or claim of confidentiality in the information received pursuant to this subsection as a result of information sharing authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 47. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 