  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2843"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2843</statuteno><catchline>Medical review panel; access to information; written opinion; issuance; basis for.</catchline><para>(1) The panel shall have the right and duty to request all necessary information. The panel may consult with medical authorities and may examine reports of such health care providers as may be necessary to fully inform itself regarding the issue to be decided. Both parties shall have full access to any material submitted to the panel.</para><para>(2) The panel shall have the sole duty to express its expert opinion in writing to each of the parties as to whether or not the evidence supports the conclusion that the defendant or defendants acted or failed to act within the appropriate standards of care as charged in the complaint and as to the issue of damages proximately caused by failure to act in accordance with such standards. Any issue relating to informed consent shall be considered as a charge of failure to act within the appropriate standard of care.</para><para>(3) After reviewing all evidence and, unless waived, after argument by counsel representing either party, the panel shall, within thirty days, render one or more of the following expert opinions which shall be in writing and mailed to each of the parties:</para><para>(a) The evidence supports the conclusion that the defendant failed to comply with the appropriate standard of care as charged in the complaint in specified particulars;</para><para>(b) The evidence supports the conclusion that the defendant involved met the applicable standard of care required under the circumstances; or</para><para>(c) There is a material issue of fact, not requiring expert opinion, bearing on liability for consideration by the court or jury in specified particulars.</para><para>(4) No dollar amounts or percentages of disability shall be provided by the panel. A majority vote of the voting members shall control action by the panel. The report of the panel shall be signed only by the chairman who shall certify that the report reflects the opinion of a majority of the voting members. If requested, a minority report shall be provided to any party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 434, &#167; 43. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 