<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id00" statutenumber="44-2006"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2006</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Attorney General; powers; terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">The Attorney General upon request of the Director of Insurance may proceed in the courts of this state or any reciprocal state to enforce an order or decision in any court proceeding or in any administrative proceeding before the director.</para><para id="id00">(1) As used in this section:</para><para id="id00">(a) Reciprocal state shall mean any state or territory of the United States the laws of which contain procedures substantially similar to those specified in this section for the enforcement of decrees or orders in equity issued by courts located in other states or territories of the United States against any insurer incorporated or authorized to do business in such state or territory;</para><para id="id00">(b) Foreign decree shall mean any decree or order in equity of a court located in a reciprocal state, including a court of the United States located in such reciprocal state, against any insurer incorporated or authorized to do business in this state; and</para><para id="id00">(c) Qualified party shall mean a state regulatory agency acting in its capacity to enforce the insurance laws of its state.</para><para id="id00">(2) The Director of Insurance shall determine which states and territories qualify as reciprocal states and shall maintain at all times an up-to-date list of such states.</para><para id="id00">(3) A copy of any foreign decree authenticated in accordance with the statutes of this state may be filed in the office of the clerk of any district court of this state. The clerk shall record the foreign decree in the same manner as a decree of a district court of this state. A foreign decree so filed shall have the same effect and shall be deemed as a decree of a district court of this state, shall be subject to the same procedures, defenses, and proceedings for reopening, vacating, or staying as a decree of a district court of this state, and may be enforced or satisfied in like manner.</para><para id="id00">(4)(a) At the time of the filing of the foreign decree, the Attorney General shall make and file with the clerk of the court an affidavit setting forth the name and last-known post office address of the defendant.</para><para id="id00">(b) Promptly upon the filing of the foreign decree and the affidavit, the clerk of the court shall mail notice of the filing of the foreign decree to the defendant at the address given and to the Director of Insurance and shall file notice of the mailing on the record. In addition, the Attorney General may mail a notice of the filing of the foreign decree to the defendant and to the Director of Insurance and may file proof of mailing with the clerk. Lack of mailing notice of filing by the clerk shall not affect the enforcement proceedings if proof of mailing by the Attorney General has been filed.</para><para id="id00">(c) No execution or other process for enforcement of a foreign decree filed under this section shall issue until thirty days after the date the decree is filed.</para><para id="id00">(5)(a) If the defendant shows the district court that an appeal from the foreign decree is pending or will be taken or that a stay of execution has been granted, the court shall stay enforcement of the foreign decree until the appeal is concluded, the time for appeal expires, or the stay of execution expires or is vacated, upon proof that the defendant has furnished the security for the satisfaction of the decree required by the state in which it was rendered.</para><para id="id00">(b) If the defendant shows the district court any ground upon which enforcement of a decree of any district court of this state would be stayed, the court shall stay enforcement of the foreign decree for an appropriate period, upon requiring the same security for satisfaction of the decree which is required in this state.</para><para id="id00">(6) Any person filing a foreign decree shall pay to the clerk of the district court the docket fee established in section 33-106. Fees for transcribing or other enforcement proceedings shall be as provided for decrees of the district court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 351, &#167; 6, p. 1229; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 279, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 82. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>