<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2137"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2137</statuteno><catchline>Examination by director; director; powers; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) Subject
to the limitation contained in this section and in addition to the powers
which the director has under the Insurers Examination Act relating to the
examination of insurers, the director may
examine any insurer registered under section 44-2132 and its affiliates to
ascertain the financial condition of the insurer, including the enterprise
risk to the insurer by the ultimate controlling party, by any entity or combination
of entities within the insurance holding company system, or by the insurance
holding company system on a consolidated basis.</para>
<para>(b) The director may order
any insurer registered under section 44-2132 to produce such records, books,
or other information papers in the possession of the insurer or its affiliates
as are reasonably necessary to determine compliance
with Chapter 44.</para>
<para>(c) To determine compliance
with Chapter 44, the director may order any insurer registered under section
44-2132 to produce information not in the possession of the insurer if the
insurer can obtain access to such information pursuant to contractual relationships,
statutory obligations, or another method. If the insurer cannot obtain the
information requested by the director, the insurer shall provide the director
a detailed explanation of the reason that the insurer cannot obtain the information
and the identity of the holder of the information. If it appears to the director
that the detailed explanation is without merit, the director may require,
after notice and hearing, the insurer to pay a penalty of one hundred dollars
for each day's delay, not to exceed an aggregate penalty of ten thousand dollars,
or may suspend or revoke the insurer's certificate of authority.</para>
<para>(2) The director may retain at the registered insurer's expense such
attorneys, actuaries, accountants, and other experts who are not employees
of the Department of Insurance as shall be reasonably necessary to assist
in the conduct of the examination under this section. Any persons so retained
shall be under the direction and control of the director and shall act in
a purely advisory capacity.</para>
<para>(3) Each registered insurer producing for examination records, books,
and papers pursuant to this section shall be liable for and shall pay the
expense of such examination in accordance with the Insurers Examination Act.</para>
<para>(4) If the insurer fails
to comply with an order, the director may examine the affiliates to obtain
the information. The director may also issue subpoenas, administer oaths,
and examine under oath any person for purposes of determining compliance with
this section. Upon the failure or refusal of any person to obey a subpoena,
the director may petition a court of competent jurisdiction, and upon proper
showing, the court may enter an order compelling the witness to appear and
testify or produce documentary evidence. Failure to obey the court order shall
be punishable by contempt of court. Every person shall be obliged to attend
as a witness at the place specified in the subpoena, when subpoenaed, anywhere
within the state. He or she shall be entitled to the same fees and mileage,
if claimed, as a witness in the district court, which fees, mileage, and actual
expenses, if any, necessarily incurred in securing the attendance of witnesses
and their testimony, shall be itemized, charged against, and paid by the entity
being examined.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 11.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurers Examination Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>