<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id6" statutenumber="44-2825"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2825</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Action for injury or death; maximum amount recoverable; settlement; manner; coverage; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) The total amount recoverable under the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act from any and all health care providers and the Excess Liability Fund for any occurrence resulting in any injury or death of a patient may not exceed (a) five hundred thousand dollars for any occurrence on or before December 31, 1984, (b) one million dollars for any occurrence after December 31, 1984, and on or before December 31, 1992, (c) one million two hundred fifty thousand dollars for any occurrence after December 31, 1992, and on or before December 31, 2003, (d) one million seven hundred fifty thousand dollars for any occurrence after December 31, 2003, and on or before December 31, 2014, and (e) two million two hundred fifty thousand dollars for any occurrence after December 31, 2014.</para><para>(2) A health care provider qualified under the act shall not be liable to any patient or his or her representative who is covered by the act for an amount in excess of eight hundred thousand dollars for all claims or causes of action arising from any occurrence during the period that the act is effective with reference to such patient.</para><para>(3) Subject to the overall limits from all sources as provided in subsection (1) of this section, any amount due from a judgment or settlement which is in excess of the total liability of all liable health care providers shall be paid from the Excess Liability Fund pursuant to sections 44-2831 to 44-2833.</para><para>(4) Nothing in the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act shall be construed to require the Excess Liability Fund to provide coverage for the first eight hundred thousand dollars per occurrence or to provide a defense for or on behalf of a qualified health care provider after the provider's annual aggregate limit of liability amount set forth in sections 44-2824 and 44-2827 has been exhausted. A qualified health care provider's purchase of coverage with an aggregate limit of liability higher than required by sections 44-2824 and 44-2827 shall not affect the obligation of payment from the Excess Liability Fund pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 434, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 692, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1005, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 146, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 998, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB961, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 58. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2025</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The cap on damages in subsection (1) of this section does not violate principles of special legislation, equal protection, the open courts provision, the right to a remedy, the right to a jury trial, the taking of property, and the separation of powers. Gourley v. Nebraska Methodist Health Sys., 265 Neb. 918, 663 N.W.2d 43 (2003).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>