  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2003"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2003</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of authority; failure to procure; violation; injunction; cease and desist order; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever the Director of Insurance believes, from evidence satisfactory to him or her, that any insurer is violating or about to violate section 44-2002, the director may, through the Attorney General, cause a complaint to be filed in the district court to enjoin and restrain such insurer from continuing such violation or engaging therein or doing any act in furtherance thereof. The court shall have jurisdiction of the proceeding and shall have the power to make and enter an order or judgment awarding such preliminary or final injunctive relief as in its judgment is proper.</para><para>(2) Whenever the Director of Insurance believes that any insurer is violating or about to violate section 44-2002, the director may, without notice, and before a hearing, issue a summary cease and desist order. At the same time the order is issued, the director shall serve notice to the insurer of the reasons for such order and that the insurer may request a hearing in writing within ten business days after receipt of the order. If a hearing is requested, the director shall schedule a hearing within ten business days after receipt of the request. The hearing shall be conducted in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. If a hearing is not requested and none is ordered by the director, the order shall remain in effect until modified or vacated by the director. Any insurer aggrieved by a final order of the director may appeal the order. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. In the event of noncompliance with a summary cease and desist order, the director may, through the Attorney General, cause a complaint to be filed in the district court to enforce the order. For purposes of this subsection, insurer shall include a person or other entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 351, &#167; 3, p. 1226; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 162, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 