<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-2627"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-2627</statuteno><catchline>Insurance consultant's license; contents; expiration; reissuance.</catchline><para>(1) The license shall state the name and resident address of the licensee, date of issuance, whether the licensee is qualified to consult in property and casualty, life, health, and annuities, and such other information as the director considers proper.</para><para>(2) All corporate, partnership, and limited liability company licenses shall expire on June 30 of each year, and all individual licenses shall expire on the last day of the month of the licensee's birthday in the first year after issuance in which his or her age is divisible by two and such individual licenses may be reissued within the ninety-day period before their expiration dates and all individual licenses also may be reissued within the thirty-day period after their expiration dates upon payment of a late reissuance fee as established by the director not to exceed one hundred twenty-five dollars in addition to the applicable fee otherwise required for reissuance of individual licenses as established by the director pursuant to section 44-2621. All individual licenses reissued within the thirty-day period after their expiration dates pursuant to this subsection shall be deemed to have been reissued before their expiration dates. The department shall establish procedures for the reissuance of licenses.</para><para>(3) Every licensed consultant shall notify the department within thirty days of any change in his or her residential or business address.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 481, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 211; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 243; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 260, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 