<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3303" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3303</statuteno><catchline>Insurance laws; situations; not applicable.</catchline><para>The insurance laws of this state, including sections 44-3301 to 44-3327, do not apply to:</para><para>(1) Retainer contracts made by attorneys at law with individual clients with fees based on estimates of the nature and amount of services to be provided to the specific client and similar contracts made with a group of clients involved in the same or closely related legal matters;</para><para>(2) Plans providing no benefits other than consultation and advice in connection with or in combination with referral services;</para><para>(3) The furnishing of limited legal assistance on an informal basis, involving neither an express contractual obligation nor reasonable expectations, in the context of an employment, membership, education, or similar relationship;</para><para>(4) The furnishing of legal assistance by labor unions and other employee organizations to their members in matters relating to employment or occupation;</para><para>(5) Employee welfare benefit plans to the extent that state laws are superseded by Section 514 of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974;</para><para>(6) Automobile club service contracts which supply incidental or limited legal services or reimbursement for legal services in automobile related matters; and</para><para>(7) Plans that do not include the assumption of risk or obligation to pay or reimburse for specified legal services or specified legal expenses. The payment of only an administrative fee to an attorney shall not be considered payment or reimbursement for specified legal services or a specified legal expense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 52, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB26, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>