<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id269"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3527"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3527</statuteno><catchline>Motor vehicle service contract; filing; form; requirements; enforcement of act; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, conspicuously means writing, displaying, or presenting a term in such a way that a reasonable person against whom it is to operate shall notice. Conspicuously stated terms include:</para><para>(a) A heading in capitals equal to or greater in size than the surrounding text, or in contrasting type, font, or color to the surrounding text of the same or lesser size; and</para><para>(b) Language in the body of a record or display in larger type than the surrounding text, or in contrasting type, font, or color to the surrounding text of the same size, or set off from surrounding text of the same size by symbols or other marks that call attention to the language.</para><para>(2) It is the responsibility of the motor vehicle service contract provider issuing the motor vehicle service contract to file a true and correct copy of the motor vehicle service contract form, motor vehicle service contract reimbursement insurance policy, and the notice of filing form with the Department of Insurance. Such notice of filing shall be made on a form provided by the department and must contain the name and address of the business entity filing the form as well as a contact person, the names and addresses of entities from which the service contract forms were purchased, the names and addresses of insurers insuring the provider's contractual liability, and the names and addresses of sales personnel. It is the responsibility of the motor vehicle service contract provider to notify the department on a continuing basis of any changes in the filings.</para><para>(3) Every motor vehicle service contract shall be written in clear, understandable language and shall be printed or typed in easy-to-read type, size, and style, and shall not be issued, sold, or offered for sale in this state unless the contract:</para><para>(a) Identifies the motor vehicle service contract provider and the service contract holder;</para><para>(b) Conspicuously states that the obligations of the motor vehicle service contract provider to the service contract holder are guaranteed under a service contract reimbursement insurance policy;</para><para>(c) Conspicuously states the name and address of the insurance company issuing the reimbursement insurance policy;</para><para>(d) Sets forth the total purchase price and the terms under which it is to be paid;</para><para>(e) Sets forth the procedure for making a claim, including an address and telephone number for claim assistance;</para><para>(f) Conspicuously states the existence of a deductible amount, if any;</para><para>(g) Clearly specifies the merchandise or services, or both, to be provided and any limitations, exceptions, or exclusions;</para><para>(h) Sets forth all of the obligations and duties of the service contract holder, including, but not limited to, the duty to prevent any further damage to the vehicle and the obligation to notify the provider in advance of any repair, if any;</para><para>(i) Sets forth any terms, restrictions, or conditions governing transferability of a service contract, if any;</para><para>(j) Sets forth applicable cancellation requirements; and</para><para>(k) States that the service contract holder has the right to file a claim directly with the insurer in the event of nonperformance by the motor vehicle service contract provider in the event covered service is not provided by the motor vehicle service contract provider within sixty days of proof of loss being filed by the service contract holder with the service contract provider, along with the method, requirements, and instructions for making such a claim.</para><para>(4) If the director determines that a motor vehicle service contract provider has failed to comply with the Motor Vehicle Service Contract Reimbursement Insurance Act, the director may issue an order to cease and desist from selling or offering for sale motor vehicle service contracts. Accompanied with that order shall be a notice of hearing setting forth the time, date, place, and issues to be heard. Such hearing shall take place not less than ten days nor more than thirty days from the date from the issuance of the order to cease and desist. Upon the failure of a motor vehicle service contract provider to obey an order to cease and desist issued by the director, the director may give notice in writing of the failure to the Attorney General, who may commence an action against the provider to enjoin that provider from selling or offering for sale motor vehicle service contracts.</para><para>(5) If any provision of this section is declared invalid, the remainder shall not be affected.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB774, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>