<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id228"><sectno id="id229" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 23.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id230" statutenumber="44-3904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id232">44-3904</statuteno><catchline id="id233">Licensee; requirements; furnish evidence of continuing education.</catchline><para>(1)(a)(i) Licensees qualified to solicit property and casualty insurance shall be required to complete twenty-one hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period commencing before January 1, 2010. Licensees qualified to solicit life, accident and health or sickness, property, casualty, or personal lines property and casualty insurance shall be required to complete six hours of approved continuing education activities for each line of insurance, including each miscellaneous line, in which he or she is licensed in each two-year period commencing before January 1, 2010. Licensees qualified to solicit life, accident and health or sickness, property, casualty, or personal lines property and casualty insurance shall be required to complete twenty-one hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period commencing on or after January 1, 2010.</para><para>(ii) Licensees qualified to solicit only crop insurance shall be required to complete three hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period.</para><para>(iii) Licensees qualified to solicit any lines of insurance other than those described in subdivisions (i) and (ii) of subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be required to complete six hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period for each line of insurance, including each miscellaneous line, in which he or she is licensed. Licensees qualified to solicit variable life and variable annuity products shall not be required to complete additional continuing education activities because the licensee is qualified to solicit variable life and variable annuity products.</para><para>(b) Licensees who are not insurance producers shall be required to complete twenty-one hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period commencing on or after January 1, 2000.</para><para>(c) In each two-year period, every licensee shall furnish evidence to the director that he or she has satisfactorily completed the hours of approved continuing education activities required under this subsection for each line of insurance in which he or she is licensed as a resident insurance producer, except that no licensee shall be required to complete more than twenty-four cumulative hours required under this subsection in any two-year period commencing on or after January 1, 2000.</para><para>(d) A licensee shall not repeat a continuing education activity for credit within a two-year period.</para><para>(2) In each two-year period, licensees required to complete approved continuing education activities under subsection (1) of this section shall, in addition to such activities, be required to complete three hours of approved continuing education activities on insurance industry ethics.</para><para>(3) When the requirements of this section have been met, the licensee shall furnish to the department evidence of completion for the current two-year period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 274, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 48, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1114, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 244; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 279, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 91; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 978, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 260, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 23.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
