<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id6"  statutenumber="44-3521"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3521</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Motor Vehicle Service Contract Reimbursement
Insurance Act:</para>
<para>(1) Director means the Director of Insurance;</para>
<para>(2) Incidental
costs means expenses specified in a motor vehicle service contract that are
incurred by the service contract holder due to the failure of a vehicle protection
product to perform as provided in the contract. Incidental costs include,
but are not limited to, insurance policy deductibles, rental vehicle charges,
the difference between the actual value of the stolen vehicle at the time
of theft and the cost of a replacement vehicle, sales taxes, registration
fees, transaction fees, and mechanical inspection fees. Incidental costs may
be reimbursed in either a fixed amount specified in the motor vehicle service
contract or sales agreement or by use of a formula itemizing specific incidental
costs incurred by the service contract holder;</para><para>(3) Mechanical breakdown insurance means a policy,
contract, or agreement that undertakes to perform or provide repair or replacement
service, or indemnification for such service, for the operational or structural
failure of a motor vehicle due to defect in materials or workmanship or normal
wear and tear and that is issued by an insurance company authorized to do
business in this state;</para>
<para>(4) Motor vehicle means any
motor vehicle as defined in section 60-339;</para>
<para>(5)(a) Motor vehicle service
contract means a contract or agreement given for consideration over and above
the lease or purchase price of a motor vehicle that undertakes to perform
or provide repair or replacement service, or indemnification for such service,
for the operational or structural failure of a motor vehicle due to defect
in materials or workmanship or normal wear and tear but does not include mechanical
breakdown insurance.</para>
<para>(b) Motor vehicle
service contract also includes a contract or agreement that is effective for
a specified duration and paid for by means other than the purchase of a motor
vehicle to perform any one or more of the following:</para><para>(i) The repair or replacement
of tires or wheels on a motor vehicle damaged as a result of coming into contact
with road hazards;</para><para>(ii) The removal of dents, dings, or creases on a motor vehicle
that can be repaired using the process of paintless dent removal without affecting
the existing paint finish and without replacing vehicle body panels, sanding,
bonding, or painting;</para><para>(iii) The repair of chips or cracks in or replacement of motor vehicle
windshields as a result of damage caused by road hazards;</para>
<para>(iv) The replacement
of a motor vehicle key or keyfob in the event the key or keyfob becomes inoperable
or is lost;</para><para>(v) The payment of specified incidental costs as the result of a
failure of a vehicle protection product to perform as specified; and</para>
<para>(vi) Other
products and services approved by the director;</para><para>(6) Motor vehicle service contract provider
means a person who issues, makes, provides, sells, or offers to sell a motor
vehicle service contract, except that motor vehicle service contract provider
does not include an insurer as defined in section 44-103;</para>
<para>(7) Motor vehicle service
contract reimbursement insurance policy means a policy of insurance meeting
the requirements in section 44-3523 that provides coverage for all obligations
and liabilities incurred by a motor vehicle service contract provider under
the terms of motor vehicle service contracts issued by the provider;</para>
<para>(8) Road hazards
means hazards that are encountered during normal driving conditions, including,
but not limited to, potholes, rocks, wood debris, metal parts, glass, plastic,
curbs, or composite scraps;</para><para>(9) Service
contract holder means a person who purchases a motor vehicle service contract; and</para>
<para>(10)(a) Vehicle
protection product means a vehicle protection device, system, or service that:</para>
<para>(i) Is installed
on or applied to a vehicle;</para><para>(ii) Is designed to prevent loss or damage
to a vehicle from a specific cause; and</para><para>(iii) Includes a written warranty.</para>
<para>(b) Vehicle
protection product includes, but is not limited to, chemical additives, alarm
systems, body part marking products, steering locks, window etch products,
pedal and ignition locks, fuel and ignition kill switches, and electronic,
radio, and satellite tracking devices.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 230; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 875, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1054, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>