<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id230" statutenumber="44-3904"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3904</statuteno><catchline id="id233">Licensee; requirements; furnish evidence of continuing education.</catchline><para>(1)(a)(i) Licensees qualified to solicit property and casualty insurance shall be required to complete twenty-one hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period commencing before January 1, 2010. Licensees qualified to solicit life, accident and health or sickness, property, casualty, or personal lines property and casualty insurance shall be required to complete six hours of approved continuing education activities for each line of insurance, including each miscellaneous line, in which he or she is licensed in each two-year period commencing before January 1, 2010. Licensees qualified to solicit life, accident and health or sickness, property, casualty, or personal lines property and casualty insurance shall be required to complete twenty-one hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period commencing on or after January 1, 2010.</para><para>(ii) Licensees qualified to solicit only crop insurance shall be required to complete three hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period.</para><para>(iii) Licensees qualified to solicit only limited line pre-need funeral insurance shall be required to complete (A) three hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period if such licensee holds a license as a funeral director and embalmer under the Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act or (B) six hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period if such licensee does not hold a license as a funeral director and embalmer under the Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act.</para><para>(iv) Licensees qualified to solicit any lines of insurance other than those described in subdivisions (i), (ii), and (iii) of subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be required to complete six hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period for each line of insurance, including each miscellaneous line, in which he or she is licensed. Licensees qualified to solicit variable life and variable annuity products shall not be required to complete additional continuing education activities because the licensee is qualified to solicit variable life and variable annuity products.</para><para>(b) Licensees who are not insurance producers shall be required to complete twenty-one hours of approved continuing education activities in each two-year period commencing on or after January 1, 2000.</para><para>(c) In each two-year period, every licensee shall furnish evidence to the director that he or she has satisfactorily completed the hours of approved continuing education activities required under this subsection for each line of insurance in which he or she is licensed as a resident insurance producer, except that no licensee shall be required to complete more than twenty-four cumulative hours required under this subsection in any two-year period commencing on or after January 1, 2000.</para><para>(d) A licensee shall not repeat a continuing education activity for credit within a two-year period.</para><para>(2) In each two-year period, licensees required to complete approved continuing education activities under subsection (1) of this section shall, in addition to such activities, be required to complete three hours of approved continuing education activities on insurance industry ethics.</para><para>(3)(a) Active participation may be approved for up to six hours of continuing education credit to be applied to the twenty-one-hour requirement in subdivision (1)(a)(i) of this section or to the twenty-one-hour requirement in subdivision (1)(b) of this section for life, accident and health or sickness, property, casualty, and personal lines property and casualty insurance for each two-year period for a licensee who is a member of a professional insurance association. A licensee may not use continuing education credit granted for active participation to satisfy other continuing education requirements or the requirement in subsection (2) of this section for three hours of approved continuing education activities on insurance industry ethics. Regardless of the number of associations in which a licensee has demonstrated active participation, a licensee shall not be granted more than six credit hours of continuing education credit for active participation for each two-year period.</para><para>(b) Each professional insurance association shall verify active participation separately for each licensee in the form and manner prescribed by the director. Upon receipt of such verification and payment, the director shall grant continuing education hours.</para><para>(4) When the requirements of this section have been met, the licensee shall furnish to the department evidence of completion for the current two-year period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 274, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 48, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1114, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 244; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 279, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 91; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 978, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 260, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB198, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB486, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>