<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-32,152"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-32,152</statuteno><catchline>Examinations; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Director of Insurance may make an examination of the affairs of any health maintenance organization in accordance with the Insurers Examination Act and any provider with whom such health maintenance organization has contracts, agreements, or other arrangements as often as is reasonably necessary for the protection of the interests of the people of this state. The Department of Health and Human Services may make an examination concerning the quality assurance program of any health maintenance organization and any provider with whom such health maintenance organization has contracts, agreements, or other arrangements as often as is reasonably necessary for the protection of the interests of the people of this state but not less frequently than once every three years.</para><para>(2) Every health maintenance organization and provider shall submit its books and records for an examination and in every way facilitate the completion of the examination. For the purpose of an examination, the Director of Insurance and the Department of Health and Human Services may administer oaths to and examine the officers and agents of the health maintenance organization and the principals of a provider concerning the business. An examination shall not involve the confidential communications between physicians and patients.</para><para>(3) The expenses of an examination shall be assessed against the health maintenance organization being examined and remitted to the Director of Insurance or the Department of Health and Human Services for whom the examination is being conducted in the manner provided in the Insurers Examination Act.</para><para>(4) In lieu of an examination, the Director of Insurance or the Department of Health and Human Services may accept the report of an examination made by the insurance commissioner, insurance director, insurance superintendent, or equivalent official or director of health or equivalent official of another state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 251; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 190.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurers Examination Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5901.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>