<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3308"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3308</statuteno><catchline>Insurer; transacting legal expense insurance; deposit of securities or surety bond; purpose; release; reduction.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer whose purposes according to its articles of incorporation are restricted to transacting legal expense insurance and business reasonably related thereto shall deposit with the director securities eligible for deposit by an insurance company, which shall have at all times a market value of not less than one hundred fifty thousand dollars, or as provided by subsection (7) of this section. A deposit under this section shall be held to assure the faithful performance of the insurer's obligations to its policyholders.</para><para>(2) In lieu of any deposit of securities required under subsection (1) of this section, the insurer may file with the director a surety bond in the amount of one hundred fifty thousand dollars, or as provided by subsection (7) of this section. The bond shall be one issued by an insurance company authorized to do business in the State of Nebraska. The bond shall be for the same purposes as the deposit in lieu of which it is filed, and it shall be subject to the director's approval. No such bond shall be canceled or subject to cancellation unless at least thirty days' advance notice thereof, in writing, is filed with the director.</para><para>(3) Securities or bond posted by the insurer pursuant to subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall be for the benefit of and subject to action thereon in the event of insolvency of the insurer by any person or persons sustaining an actionable injury due to the failure of the insurer to faithfully perform its obligations to its policyholders.</para><para>(4) The State of Nebraska shall be responsible for the safekeeping of all securities deposited with the director under this section. The securities shall not, on account of being in this state, be subject to taxation.</para><para>(5) The depositing insurer shall, during its solvency, have the right to exchange or substitute other securities of a like quality and value for securities on deposit, to receive the interest and other income accruing on such securities, and to inspect the deposit at all reasonable times.</para><para>(6) The deposit or bond shall be maintained unimpaired as long as the insurer continues in business in this state. Whenever the insurer ceases to do business and furnishes to the director proof satisfactory to the director that the insurer adequately provided for all of its obligations to its policyholders or contract holders in this state, the director shall release the deposited securities to the parties entitled thereto, on presentation of the director's receipts for such securities, or shall release any bond filed with it in lieu of such deposit.</para><para>(7) The director may reduce the minimum market value of securities required under subsection (1) of this section or the amount of the surety bond required under subsection (2) of this section if he or she finds that the reduction is justified by:</para><para>(a) The terms and number of existing contracts with subscribers;</para><para>(b) Support by financially sound public or private organizations or agencies;</para><para>(c) Agreements with lawyers or paralegal personnel for the providing of legal services;</para><para>(d) Agreements with other persons for insuring the payment of the cost of legal services or the provision for alternative coverage in the event the insurer is unable to perform its obligations; or</para><para>(e) Other reliable financial guarantees.</para><para>(8) No part of the securities or bond to be filed under this section shall be supplied directly or indirectly by dues payments made for the purpose of meeting requirements to practice a profession.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 52, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 