<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id642"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3614"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3614</statuteno><catchline>Medicare supplement policy or certificate; eligibility by reason of disability; availability; premiums.</catchline><para>(1) An issuer that makes a medicare supplement policy or certificate available to an individual who is sixty-five years of age and eligible for medicare benefits as described in 42 U.S.C. 1395c(1), as such section existed on January 1, 2024, shall make at least one medicare supplement policy or certificate that meets the requirements of the Medicare Supplement Insurance Minimum Standards Act, available to an individual who is under sixty-five years of age and eligible for and enrolled in medicare by reason of disability as described in 42 U.S.C. 1395c(2), as such section existed on January 1, 2024.</para><para>(2) Premium rates for medicare supplement insurance policies or certificates may differ between an individual who qualifies for medicare who is sixty-five years of age or older and an individual who qualifies for medicare by reason of disability and who is under sixty-five years of age. Such differences in premiums shall not be excessive, inadequate, or unfairly discriminatory and shall be based on sound actuarial principles and be reasonable in relation to the benefits provided. The premium for an individual who is under sixty-five years of age shall not exceed one hundred fifty percent of the premium for a similarly situated individual who is sixty-five years of age.</para><para>(3) An individual who is under sixty-five years of age and is eligible for a medicare supplement policy or certificate by reason of disability as described in subsection (1) of this section shall be subject to the same open enrollment rules applicable to an individual who is sixty-five years of age and eligible for a medicare supplement policy or certificate as described in subsection (1) of this section beginning on the first day of the first month that the individual turns sixty-five years of age.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB852, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>