  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3110</statuteno><catchline>Administrative fee; payment, when; how computed; license; rescission; notice; hearing; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to the premium tax prescribed in Chapter 77, article 9, every professional association mutual insurance company licensed pursuant to the Nebraska Professional Association Mutual Insurance Company Act shall, on or before March 1 of each year, pay an administrative fee to the director in the amount of three-tenths of one percent of the gross amount of direct writing premiums received by it during the preceding calendar year for business done in this state.</para><para>(2) The computation of the administrative fee shall be made on forms furnished by the Department of Insurance, and the fee shall be forwarded to the department together with a sworn statement by an appropriate officer of the company attesting the accuracy of the fee computation. The department shall furnish such forms prior to the end of the year for which the fees are payable.</para><para>(3) The director shall rescind or refuse to reissue the license of any company which fails to remit the administrative fee in conformity with this section. Prior to rescinding such license, the director shall issue an order to the company directing the company to show cause why such rescission should not be made. The director shall give not less than ten days' notice of a rescission hearing before the department. Should the company be aggrieved by such determination, an appeal may be taken, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 656, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1114, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 68. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 