<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-32,139"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-32,139</statuteno><catchline>Deposit requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, each health maintenance organization shall deposit with the director, or at the discretion of the director with any organization or trustee acceptable to him or her through which a custodial or controlled account is utilized, cash, securities, or any combination of cash or securities or other measures that are acceptable to the director which at all times have a value of not less than three hundred thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) A health maintenance organization that is in operation under prior law on July 10, 1990, shall make a deposit equal to one hundred fifty thousand dollars for the first year and three hundred thousand dollars for the second year.</para><para>(3) The deposit made pursuant to this section shall be an admitted asset of the health maintenance organization in the determination of net worth. All income from a deposit shall be an asset of the health maintenance organization. A health maintenance organization that has made a securities deposit may withdraw that deposit or any part thereof after making a substitute deposit of cash, securities, or any combination of cash or securities or other measures of equal amount and value. Any securities or other measures shall be approved by the director before being deposited or substituted.</para><para>(4) The deposit made pursuant to this section shall be used to protect the interests of the health maintenance organization's enrollees and to assure continuation of health care services to enrollees of a health maintenance organization which is in rehabilitation or conservation. The director may use the deposit for administrative costs directly attributable to a receivership or liquidation. If the health maintenance organization is placed in receivership or liquidation, the deposit shall be an asset subject to the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act.</para><para>(5) The director may reduce or eliminate the deposit requirement if the health maintenance organization deposits with the state treasurer, insurance commissioner, insurance director, insurance superintendent, or equivalent official of the state or jurisdiction of domicile for the protection of all subscribers and enrollees of such health maintenance organization, wherever located, cash, acceptable securities, or surety and delivers to the director a certificate to such effect duly authenticated by the appropriate official holding the deposit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 48. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4862.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>