<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-3716"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-3716</statuteno><catchline>Motor club representative; registration; qualifications; examination; termination of representative's authority; fees.</catchline><para>(1) No individual shall act as a club representative in Nebraska without the club having registered such individual with the director within thirty days after the date of designation as a club representative. Application for registration as a club representative shall be made to the director upon forms prescribed and furnished by him or her. The director may require a club representative to take a written examination, for a fee, on the services customarily offered by motor clubs. A club representative licensed as an insurance agent for sickness, accident, and health insurance pursuant to Chapter 44 shall not be required to be examined.</para><para>(2) The club representative shall furnish information concerning his or her identity, business address, personal history, business experience, and such other information that the director deems pertinent and germane. A club representative shall (a) be at least eighteen years of age, (b) be a trustworthy person of good repute, and (c) have received training from the club or have otherwise qualified by experience in the business of clubs rendering motor club services.</para><para>(3) Any willful misrepresentation of any information required to be disclosed in any application for registration shall be subject to the sanctions provided for in sections 44-3701 to 44-3721.</para><para>(4) Upon termination of any club representative's authority to act on behalf of the club, the club shall notify the director in writing within thirty days of such termination.</para><para>(5) The fee to be paid to the director at the time registration is made annually on a day specified by the director for the renewal of such registration shall be five dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 113, &#167; 16. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 