<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id556"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4614"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4614</statuteno><catchline>Choice of pharmacy services; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) A health benefit plan, health carrier, or pharmacy benefit manager shall not:</para><para>(a) Require a covered person, as a condition of payment or reimbursement, to obtain pharmacist services exclusively through the mail-order pharmacy or pharmacy benefit manager affiliate;</para><para>(b) Prohibit or limit a covered person from selecting a network pharmacist or network pharmacy of the covered person's choice;</para><para>(c) Transfer a covered person's prescriptions from a network pharmacy to another pharmacy unless requested by the covered person;</para><para>(d) Use financial incentives, including, but not limited to, adjustments in cost-sharing obligations of a covered person, to the exclusive benefit of the pharmacy benefit manager affiliate pharmacy; or</para><para>(e) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(b) of this section, auto-enroll a covered person in mail-order pharmacist services.</para><para>(2) Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a health benefit plan, health carrier, or pharmacy benefit manager from:</para><para>(a) Requiring a covered person to use a network specialty pharmacy;</para><para>(b) Auto-enrolling a covered person in mail-order pharmacist services for a maintenance medication, provided that a covered person:</para><para>(i) Shall not be auto-enrolled for the first ninety days of a new maintenance medication; and</para><para>(ii) Shall have the ability to opt out of mail-order pharmacist services at any time;</para><para>(c) Informing a covered person of an ability to obtain pharmacist services at a lower cost; or</para><para>(d) Requiring a covered person to obtain pharmacist services from a mail-order pharmacy or pharmacy benefit manager affiliate when such services are not otherwise available from another network pharmacy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB198, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>