 <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4906" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4906</statuteno><catchline>Insurer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The insurer shall have on file an independent audited financial examination or reports for the two most recent fiscal years that prove that the managing general agent has a positive net worth. If the managing general agent has been in existence for less than two fiscal years, the managing general agent shall include financial statements or reports, certified by an officer of the managing general agent and prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles, for any completed fiscal years and for any month during the current fiscal year for which such financial statements or reports have been completed. An audited financial/annual report prepared on a consolidated basis shall include a columnar consolidating or combining worksheet that shall be filed with the report and include the following: (a) Amounts shown on the consolidated audited financial/annual report shall be shown on the worksheet; (b) amounts for each entity shall be stated separately; and (c) explanations of consolidating and eliminating entries.</para><para>(2) If a managing general agent establishes loss reserves, the insurer shall annually obtain the opinion of an actuary attesting to the adequacy of loss reserves established for losses incurred and outstanding on business produced by the managing general agent. The opinion shall be in addition to any other required loss reserve certification.</para><para>(3) The insurer shall periodically, at least semiannually, conduct an onsite review of the underwriting and claims-processing operations of the managing general agent.</para><para>(4) Binding authority for all reinsurance contracts or participation in insurance or reinsurance syndicates shall rest with an officer of the insurer who is not affiliated with the managing general agent.</para><para>(5) Within thirty days of entering into or termination of a contract with a managing general agent, the insurer shall provide written notification of such appointment or termination to the director. Notices of appointment of a managing general agent shall include a statement of duties which the applicant is expected to perform on behalf of the insurer, the lines of insurance for which the applicant is to be authorized to act, and any other information the director may request.</para><para>(6) An insurer shall each quarter review its books and records to determine if any producer has become a managing general agent. If the insurer determines that a producer has become a managing general agent, the insurer shall promptly notify the producer and the director of such determination and the insurer and producer shall fully comply with the Managing General Agents Act within thirty days.</para><para>(7) No officer, director, employee, subproducer, or controlling shareholder of the insurer's managing general agent shall be appointed to its board of directors. This subsection shall not apply to relationships governed by the Insurance Holding Company System Act.</para><para>(8) The insurer shall keep the bond required by subdivision (7) of section 44-4904 on file for review by any applicable state insurance director, superintendent, or commissioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 875, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Holding Company System Act,</emphasis> see section 44-2120.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>