<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4708"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4708</statuteno><catchline>Changes in rates or benefits; material modifications; addition of a limited health service; notices; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) A prepaid limited health service organization shall file with the director prior to use a notice of any change in rates, charges, or benefits and of any material modification of any matter or document furnished pursuant to section 44-4704, together with such supporting documents as are necessary to fully explain the change or modification. If the director does not disapprove such filing within thirty days of its filing, such filing shall be deemed approved.</para><para>(2) If a prepaid limited health service organization desires to add one or more limited health services, it shall file a notice with the director and, at the same time, shall submit the information required by section 44-4704 if different from that filed with the prepaid limited health service organization's application and shall demonstrate compliance with sections 44-4717, 44-4718, and 44-4724. If the director does not disapprove such filing within thirty days of its filing, such filing shall be deemed approved.</para><para>(3) If the director does not approve the change, modification, or addition of a limited health service, the director shall notify the prepaid limited health service organization by certified mail and shall specify the reasons for disapproval in the notice. The prepaid limited health service organization shall have ten days from the date of receipt of the notice to request a hearing before the director pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 320, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 