<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4233</statuteno><catchline>Member; offset tax liability.</catchline><para>(1) Any member subject to premium and related retaliatory tax liability imposed by section 44-150 or 77-908 may offset assessments paid to the pool by such member against its tax liability in the year of payment or subsequent years. The member may offset such paid assessments against (a) subsequent premium tax prepayments imposed by section 77-918, (b) subsequent premium tax payments imposed by section 77-908, and (c) related retaliatory tax liability imposed by section 44-150. Prior to January 1, 2004, no individual member shall be subject to any liability of the pool in excess of its premium and related retaliatory tax liability which may be offset under this section.</para><para>(2) Commencing with assessments imposed or paid in 1991 and for all subsequent years prior to January 1, 2004, whenever it reasonably appears to the satisfaction of the board that a member has during a calendar year paid assessments that exceed that member's premium and related retaliatory tax liability for that calendar year, the board shall, upon request from such member, order the refund to that member of the amount of the assessment that exceeded that member's premium and related retaliatory tax liability. A member's request for a refund shall be filed with the board not later than thirty days after the due date of the member's premium tax return filed with the department. If the refund is not made by the board within thirty days after receipt of the refund request, the member may within thirty days thereafter initiate a suit in district court for the amount claimed. The suit shall be heard by the district court de novo. In the event that an assessment against a member is limited by reason of that member's premium and related retaliatory tax liability, the amount by which the assessment is limited may be assessed against the other members in a manner consistent with the basis for assessments specified in subsection (3) of section 44-4225.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 391, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1114, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 302, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 835, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 10, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 837, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 55, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 862, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 355, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1253, &#167; 32. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 