<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance"  statutenumber="44-4222"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4222</statuteno><catchline>Purchase of pool coverage; ineligibility.</catchline>
<para>(1) An individual shall not be eligible for initial or continued pool
coverage if:</para>
<para>(a) He or she is eligible for medicare benefits by reason of age or
medical assistance established pursuant to the Medical Assistance Act;</para>
<para>(b) He or she is a resident or inmate of a correctional facility, except
that this subdivision shall not apply if such individual is eligible for pool
coverage under subdivision (1)(b) of section 44-4221;</para>
<para>(c) He or she has terminated pool coverage unless twelve months have
elapsed since such termination, except that this subdivision shall not apply
if such individual has received and become ineligible for medical assistance
pursuant to the Medical Assistance Act during the immediately preceding twelve
months, if such individual is eligible for pool coverage under subdivision
(1)(b) of section 44-4221, or if such individual is eligible for waiver of
any waiting period or preexisting condition exclusions pursuant to section
44-4228;</para>
<para>(d) The pool has paid out one million dollars in claims for the individual;</para>
<para>(e) He or she is no longer a resident of Nebraska; or</para>
<para>(f) The premium for his
or her pool coverage is paid for by a person other than the following:</para>
<para>(i) The individual;</para>
<para>(ii) An individual related
to the individual by blood, marriage, or adoption; or</para><para>(iii) An entity operating under
the federal Ryan White HIV/AIDS Treatment Modernization Act of 2006, Public
Law 109-415, as such act existed on August 30, 2009.</para><para>(2)
Pool coverage shall terminate for any individual on the date the individual
becomes ineligible under subsection (1) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 391, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 319, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 279, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 106; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 862, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1035, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1253, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB358, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Medical Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 68-901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>