  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4852"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4852</statuteno><catchline>Domiciliary liquidators in other states; claims of residents.</catchline><para>(1) The domiciliary liquidator of an insurer domiciled in a reciprocal state shall, except as to special deposits and security on secured claims under subsection (3) of section 44-4853, be vested by operation of law with the title to all of the assets, property, contracts, and rights of action, agents' balances, and all of the books, accounts, and other records of the insurer located in this state. The date of vesting shall be the date of the filing of the petition if that date is specified by the domiciliary law for the vesting of property in the domiciliary state. Otherwise, the date of vesting shall be the date of entry of the order directing possession to be taken. The domiciliary liquidator shall have the immediate right to recover balances due from agents and to obtain possession of the books, accounts, and other records of the insurer located in this state. He or she also shall have the right to recover all other assets of the insurer located in this state subject to section 44-4853.</para><para>(2) If a domiciliary liquidator is appointed for an insurer not domiciled in a reciprocal state, the director shall be vested by operation of law with the title to all of the property, contracts, and rights of action and all of the books, accounts, and other records of the insurer located in this state at the same time that the domiciliary liquidator is vested with title in the domicile. The director may petition for a conservation or liquidation order under section 44-4850 or 44-4851 or for an ancillary receivership under section 44-4853 or, after approval by the district court of Lancaster County, may transfer title to the domiciliary liquidator as the interests of justice and the equitable distribution of the assets require.</para><para>(3) Claimants residing in this state may file claims with the liquidator or ancillary receiver, if any, in this state or with the domiciliary liquidator if the domiciliary law permits. The claims shall be filed on or before the last date fixed for the filing of claims in the domiciliary liquidation proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 52. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 