<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4053" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4053</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Licensure application; approval requirements; program of instruction.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A person applying for a resident insurance producer license shall make application to the director on the uniform application and declare under penalty of denial, suspension, or revocation of the license that the statements made in the application are true, correct, and complete to the best of the individual's knowledge and belief. Before approving the application, the director shall find that the individual:</para><para id="id00">(a) Is at least eighteen years of age. Notwithstanding the provisions of section 43-2101, if any person is issued a license pursuant to the Insurance Producers Licensing Act, his or her minority ends;</para><para id="id00">(b) Has not committed any act that is a ground for denial, suspension, or revocation set forth in section 44-4059;</para><para id="id00" /><para id="id00">(c) Has paid the fees set forth in section 44-4064; and</para><para id="id00">(d) Has successfully passed the examinations for the lines of authority for which the person has applied.</para><para id="id00">(2) A business entity acting as an insurance producer is required to obtain an insurance producer license. Application shall be made using the uniform business entity application. Before approving the application, the director shall find that:</para><para id="id00">(a) The business entity has paid the fees set forth in section 44-4064; and</para><para id="id00">(b) The business entity has designated a licensed producer responsible for the business entity's compliance with the insurance laws, rules, and regulations of this state.</para><para id="id00">(3) The director may require any documents reasonably necessary to verify the information contained in an application.</para><para id="id00">(4) Each insurer that sells, solicits, or negotiates any form of limited line credit insurance shall provide to each individual whose duties will include selling, soliciting, or negotiating limited line credit insurance a program of instruction that may be approved by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 51, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 24. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>