<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id666"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4608"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4608</statuteno><catchline>Contract; pharmacy benefit manager; cost price list; duties; disputes; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) With respect to each contract and contract renewal between a pharmacy benefit manager and a pharmacy, the pharmacy benefit manager shall:</para><para>(a) Update any maximum allowable cost price list at least every seven business days, noting any price change from the previous list, and provide a means by which a network pharmacy may promptly review a current price in an electronic, print, or telephonic format within one business day of any such change at no cost to the pharmacy;</para><para>(b) Maintain a procedure to eliminate a product from the maximum allowable cost price list in a timely manner to remain consistent with any change in the marketplace; and</para><para>(c) Make the maximum allowable cost price list available to each contracted pharmacy in a format that is readily accessible and usable to the contracted pharmacy.</para><para>(2) A pharmacy benefit manager shall not place a prescription drug on a maximum allowable cost price list unless the drug is available for purchase by pharmacies in this state from a national or regional drug wholesaler and is not obsolete.</para><para>(3) Each contract between a pharmacy benefit manager and a pharmacy shall include a process to appeal, investigate, and resolve disputes regarding any maximum allowable cost price. The process shall include:</para><para>(a) A fifteen-business-day limit on the right to appeal following submission of an initial claim by a pharmacy;</para><para>(b) A requirement that any appeal be investigated and resolved within seven business days after the appeal is received by the pharmacy benefit manager; and</para><para>(c) A requirement that the pharmacy benefit manager provide a reason for any denial of an appeal and identify the national drug code for the drug that may be purchased by the pharmacy at a price at or below the price on the maximum allowable cost price list as determined by the pharmacy benefit manager.</para><para>(4) If an appeal is determined to be valid by the pharmacy benefit manager, the pharmacy benefit manager shall:</para><para>(a) Make an adjustment in the drug price no later than one day after the appeal is resolved; and</para><para>(b) Permit the appealing pharmacy to reverse and rebill the claim in question, using the date of the original claim.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB767, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>