<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance"  statutenumber="44-4068" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4068</statuteno><catchline>Travel insurance; limited lines travel insurance producer; license; duties; travel retailer; duties; director; powers.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Limited lines travel insurance producer means a licensed insurance producer, including a limited lines producer, who is designated by an insurer as the travel insurance supervising entity;</para><para>(b) Offer and disseminate means to provide general information about travel insurance, including a description of the coverage and price, as well as processing the application, collecting premiums, and performing other nonlicensable activities permitted by the state;</para><para>(c) Travel insurance means insurance coverage for personal risks incident to planned travel, including interruption or cancellation of a trip or event, loss of baggage or personal effects, damages to accommodations or rental vehicles, and sickness, accident, disability, or death occurring during travel. Travel insurance does not include major medical plans that provide comprehensive medical protection for travelers with trips lasting six months or longer, including those working overseas as an expatriate or as deployed military personnel; and</para><para>(d) Travel retailer means a business entity that makes, arranges, or offers travel services and that offers and disseminates travel insurance as a service to its customers on behalf of and under the direction of a limited lines travel insurance producer.</para><para>(2)(a) The director may issue a limited lines travel insurance producer license to an individual or business entity that authorizes the limited lines travel insurance producer to sell, solicit, or negotiate travel insurance through a licensed insurer in a form and manner prescribed by the director.</para><para>(b) A travel retailer, its employees, and its authorized representatives may offer and disseminate travel insurance as a service to the travel retailer's customers, on behalf of and under the direction of an individual or a business entity that holds a limited lines travel insurance producer license. In doing so, the travel retailer must provide to prospective purchasers of travel insurance:</para><para>(i) A description of the material terms or the actual material terms of the insurance coverage;</para><para>(ii) A description of the process for filing a claim;</para><para>(iii) A description of the review or cancellation process for the travel insurance policy; and</para><para>(iv) The identity and contact information of the insurer and limited lines travel insurance producer.</para><para>(c) At the time of licensure, the limited lines travel insurance producer shall establish and maintain a register of each travel retailer that offers travel insurance on the limited lines travel insurance producer's behalf on a form prescribed by the director. The limited lines travel insurance producer must maintain and update the register annually and include: The name, address, and contact information of each travel retailer; the name, address, and contact information of an officer or person who directs or controls the travel retailer's operations; and the travel retailer's federal tax identification number. The limited lines travel insurance producer must submit the register to the director upon request. The limited lines travel insurance producer must also certify that the travel retailer registered is not in violation of 18 U.S.C. 1033.</para><para>(d) The limited lines travel insurance producer must designate one of its employees who is a licensed individual producer as the person responsible for the limited lines travel insurance producer's compliance with the travel insurance laws, rules, and regulations of the state.</para><para>(e) The limited lines travel insurance producer shall require each employee and authorized representative of the travel retailer whose duties include offering and disseminating travel insurance to receive a program of instruction or training, which may be subject to review by the director. The training material must include, at minimum, instructions on the types of insurance offered, ethical sales practices, and required disclosures to prospective customers.</para><para>(3) A limited lines travel insurance producer and those registered under its license are exempt from the examination requirements in section 44-4052 and the continuing education requirements in sections 44-3901 to 44-3908.</para><para>(4) Any travel retailer offering or disseminating travel insurance shall make brochures or other written materials available to prospective purchasers that:</para><para>(a) Provide the identity and contact information of the insurer and the limited lines travel insurance producer;</para><para>(b) Explain that the purchase of travel insurance is not required in order to purchase any other product or service from the travel retailer; and</para><para>(c) Explain that an unlicensed travel retailer is permitted to provide general information about the insurance offered by the travel retailer, including a description of the coverage and price, but is not qualified or authorized to answer technical questions about the terms and conditions of the insurance offered by the travel retailer or to evaluate the adequacy of the customer's existing insurance coverage.</para><para>(5) A travel retailer's employee or authorized representative who is not licensed as an insurance producer may not:</para><para>(a) Evaluate or interpret the technical terms, benefits, or conditions of the offered travel insurance coverage;</para><para>(b) Evaluate or provide advice concerning a prospective purchaser's existing insurance coverage; or</para><para>(c) Hold himself or herself out as a licensed insurer, licensed producer, or insurance expert.</para><para>(6) A travel retailer whose insurance-related activities, and those of its employees and authorized representatives, are limited to offering and disseminating travel insurance on behalf of and under the direction of a limited lines travel insurance producer meeting the conditions stated in this section is authorized to receive related compensation for the services upon registration by the limited lines travel insurance producer.</para><para>(7) Travel insurance may be provided under an individual policy or under a group or master policy.</para><para>(8) The limited lines travel insurance producer is responsible for the acts of the travel retailer and shall use reasonable means to ensure that the travel retailer complies with this section.</para><para>(9) The director may take disciplinary action against a limited lines travel insurance producer pursuant to section 44-4059.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB458, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 26. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>