<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id5" statutenumber="44-4805"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4805</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Injunctions and
orders.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (3) of
this section, any receiver appointed in a proceeding under the
Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act may at
any time apply for, and the court may grant, such restraining orders, preliminary
and permanent injunctions, and other orders as may be deemed necessary and
proper to prevent:</para>
<para>(a) The transaction of further business;</para>
<para>(b) The transfer of property;</para><?Pub Caret?>
<para>(c) Interference with the receiver or with a proceeding under
the act;</para>
<para>(d) Waste of the insurer's assets;</para>
<para>(e) Dissipation and transfer of bank accounts;</para>
<para>(f) The institution or further prosecution of any actions
or proceedings;</para>
<para>(g) The obtaining of preferences, judgments, attachments,
garnishments, or liens against the insurer, its assets, or its insureds;</para>
<para>(h) The levying of execution against the insurer, its assets,
or its insureds;</para>
<para>(i) The making of any sale or deed for nonpayment of taxes
or assessments that would lessen the value of the assets of the insurer;</para>
<para>(j) The withholding from the receiver of books, accounts,
documents, or other records relating to the business of the insurer; or</para>
<para>(k) Any other threatened or contemplated action that might
lessen the value of the insurer's assets or prejudice the rights of insureds,
creditors, or shareholders or the administration of any proceeding under the
act.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3) of
this section, the receiver may apply to any court outside of the
state for the relief described in subsection (1) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) A Federal
Home Loan Bank shall not be stayed, enjoined, or prohibited from exercising
or enforcing any right or cause of action regarding collateral pledged under
any security agreement, or any pledge, security, collateral or guarantee agreement
or any other similar arrangement or credit enhancement relating to such Federal
Home Loan Bank security agreement.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB337, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>