<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4404</statuteno><catchline>Risk retention group; charter and license requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A risk retention group seeking to be chartered and licensed in this state shall be chartered and licensed as a liability insurance company under Chapter 44 and, except as provided elsewhere in the Risk Retention Act, shall comply with all of the laws, rules, and regulations applicable to such insurers chartered and licensed in this state and with sections 44-4405 to 44-4413 to the extent such requirements are not a limitation on laws, rules, or regulations of this state.</para><para>(2) Before a risk retention group may offer insurance in any state, it shall submit for approval to the director a plan of operation and revisions of such plan if the group intends to offer any additional lines of liability insurance.</para><para>(3) At the time of filing its application for a charter and license, the risk retention group shall provide to the director in summary form the following information: The identity of the initial members of the group; the identity of those individuals who organized the group or who will provide administrative services or otherwise influence or control the activities of the group; the amount and nature of initial capitalization; the coverages to be afforded; and the states in which the group intends to operate. Upon receipt of this information, the director shall forward such information to the National Association of Insurance Commissioners. Providing notification to the National Association of Insurance Commissioners shall be in addition to and shall not be sufficient to satisfy the requirements of section 44-4405 or any other sections of the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 514, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 47. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 