  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4058"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4058</statuteno><catchline>Temporary license; requirements; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) The director may issue a temporary insurance producer license for a period not to exceed one hundred eighty days without requiring an examination if the director deems that the temporary license is necessary for the servicing of an insurance business in the following cases:</para><para>(a) To the surviving spouse or court-appointed personal representative of a licensed insurance producer who dies or becomes mentally or physically disabled to allow adequate time for the sale of the insurance business owned by the producer or for the recovery or return of the producer to such business or to provide for the training and licensing of new personnel to operate the producer's business;</para><para>(b) To a member or employee of a business entity licensed as an insurance producer, upon the death or disability of an individual designated in the business entity application or the license;</para><para>(c) To the designee of a licensed insurance producer entering active service in the armed forces of the United States of America; or</para><para>(d) In any other circumstance in which the director deems that the public interest will best be served by the issuance of the license.</para><para>(2) The director may by order limit the authority of any temporary licensee in any way deemed necessary to protect insureds and the public. The director may require the temporary licensee to have a suitable sponsor who is a licensed producer or insurer and who assumes responsibility for all acts of the temporary licensee and may impose other similar requirements designed to protect insureds and the public. The director may by order revoke a temporary license if the interest of insureds or the public are endangered, or for the grounds set forth in section 44-4059. A temporary license may not continue after the owner or the personal representative disposes of the business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 51, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 