<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4806"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4806</statuteno><catchline>Cooperation of officers, owners, and employees; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any officer, manager, director, trustee, owner, employee, or agent of any insurer or any other persons with authority over or in charge of any segment of the insurer's affairs shall cooperate with the director in any proceeding under the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act or any investigation preliminary to the proceeding. For purposes of this section, the term person shall include any person who exercises control directly or indirectly over activities of the insurer through a management contract or any holding company or other affiliate of the insurer. To cooperate shall include, but shall not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) To reply promptly in writing to any inquiry from the director requesting such a reply; and</para><para>(b) To make available to the director any books, accounts, documents, or other records or information or property of or pertaining to the insurer and in his or her possession, custody, or control.</para><para>(2) No person shall obstruct or interfere with the director in the conduct of any delinquency proceeding or any investigation preliminary or incidental thereto.</para><para>(3) This section shall not be construed to abridge otherwise existing legal rights, including the right to resist a petition for liquidation or other delinquency proceedings, or other orders.</para><para>(4) Any person included within subsection (1) of this section who fails to cooperate with the director or any person who obstructs or interferes with the director in the conduct of any delinquency proceeding or any investigation preliminary or incidental thereto or who violates any order the director issued validly under the act shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor or may, after a hearing, be subject to the imposition by the director of a civil penalty not to exceed ten thousand dollars and shall be subject further to the revocation or suspension of any insurance licenses issued by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 984, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 