<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4814"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4814</statuteno><catchline>Director; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The director as rehabilitator may appoint one or more special deputies who shall have all the powers and responsibilities of the rehabilitator granted under this section, and the director may employ such counsel, clerks, and assistants as deemed necessary. The compensation of the special deputy, counsel, clerks, and assistants and all expenses of taking possession of the insurer and of conducting the proceedings shall be fixed by the director, with the approval of the court, and shall be paid out of the funds or assets of the insurer. The persons appointed under this section shall serve at the pleasure of the director. The director, as rehabilitator, may, with the approval of the court, appoint an advisory committee of policyholders, claimants, or other creditors, including guaranty associations, should such a committee be deemed necessary. Such committee shall serve at the pleasure of the director and shall serve without compensation other than reimbursement for reasonable travel and per diem living expenses. No other committee of any nature shall be appointed by the director or the court in rehabilitation proceedings conducted under the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act.</para><para>(2) The rehabilitator may take such action as he or she deems necessary or appropriate to reform and revitalize the insurer. He or she shall have all the powers of the directors, officers, and managers of the insurer, whose authority shall be suspended, except as they are redelegated by the rehabilitator. He or she shall have full power to direct and manage, to hire and discharge employees subject to any contract rights they may have, and to deal with the property and business of the insurer.</para><para>(3) If it appears to the rehabilitator that there has been criminal or tortious conduct or breach of any contractual or fiduciary obligation detrimental to the insurer by any officer, manager, agent, broker, employee, or other person, he or she may pursue all appropriate legal remedies on behalf of the insurer.</para><para>(4)(a)(i) If the rehabilitator determines that reorganization, consolidation, conversion, reinsurance, merger, or other transformation of the insurer is appropriate, he or she shall prepare a plan to effect such changes.</para><para>(ii) Such plan may include the establishment of a trust to be treated as an insurer with the trustee serving as liquidator under the act retaining all liabilities and assets except the charter and licenses and shall include provisions requiring the rehabilitator to petition the court to convert the rehabilitation proceedings to a liquidation. Such trust shall be considered an insurer for the purposes of the act. Such plan may include provisions for cancellation of all outstanding stock and other securities of, and other equity interests in, the insurer and court approval of the issuance and sale of new stock or other securities for the purpose of transferring to one or more buyers control and ownership of the insurer together with any or all of its licenses and certificates to do business and such other assets as the rehabilitator deems appropriate to the transaction. The proceeds of such sale shall be assets of the trust. The order of the court approving such a sale may provide that the sale is free and clear of all claims and interests of the insurer's insureds, creditors, shareholders, and members and all other persons interested in the insurer and may discharge the insurer and all property which is the subject of the sale from all claims and interests of the insurer's insureds, creditors, shareholders, and members and all other persons interested in the insurer, except that such a discharge shall not affect the rights of the insurer's insureds, creditors, shareholders, and members and all other persons interested in the insurer's estate to participate in distributions from the trust as otherwise provided in the act.</para><para>(b) Upon application of the rehabilitator for approval of the plan and after such notice and hearings as the court may prescribe, the court may either approve or disapprove the plan proposed or may modify it and approve it as modified. Any plan approved under this section shall be, in the judgment of the court, fair and equitable to all parties concerned. If the plan is approved, the rehabilitator shall carry out the plan. In the case of a life insurer, the plan proposed may include the imposition of liens upon the policies of the company if all rights of shareholders are first relinquished. A plan for a life insurer may also propose the imposition of a moratorium upon loan and cash surrender rights under policies for such period and to such an extent as may be necessary.</para><para>(5) The rehabilitator shall have the power under sections 44-4826 and 44-4827 to avoid fraudulent transfers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>