<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id293" statutenumber="44-4521"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4521</statuteno><catchline id="id296">Sale, solicitation, or negotiation of long-term care insurance; license required; training course; insurer; duties; records.</catchline><para>(1) On or after August 1, 2008, an individual may not sell, solicit, or negotiate long-term care insurance unless the individual is licensed as an insurance producer for health or sickness and accident insurance and has completed a one-time training course and ongoing training every twenty-four months thereafter. All training shall meet the requirements of subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) The one-time training course required by subsection (1) of this section shall be no less than eight hours in length, and the required ongoing training shall be no less than four hours in length. All training required under subsection (1) of this section shall consist of topics related to long-term care insurance, long-term care services, and, if applicable, qualified state long-term insurance partnership programs, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(a) State and federal regulations and requirements and the relationship between qualified state long-term care insurance partnership programs and other public and private coverage of long-term care services, including medicaid;</para><para>(b) Available long-term care services and providers;</para><para>(c) Changes or improvements in long-term care services or providers;</para><para>(d) Alternatives to the purchase of private long-term care insurance;</para><para>(e) The effect of inflation on benefits and the importance of inflation protection; and</para><para>(f) Consumer suitability standards and guidelines.</para><para>Training required by subsection (1) of this section shall not include any sales or marketing information, materials, or training other than those required by state or federal law.</para><para>(3)(a) Insurers subject to the Long-Term Care Insurance Act shall obtain verification that the insurance producer receives training required by subsection (1) of this section before a producer is permitted to sell, solicit, or negotiate the insurer's long-term care insurance products. Records shall be maintained in accordance with section 44-5905 and shall be made available to the director upon request.</para><para>(b) Insurers subject to the act shall maintain records with respect to the training of its producers concerning the distribution of its partnership policies that will allow the director to provide assurance to the Department of Health and Human Services that producers have received the training required by subsection (1) of this section and that producers have demonstrated an understanding of the partnership policies and their relationship to public and private coverage of long-term care, including medicaid, in this state. These records shall be maintained in accordance with section 44-5905 and shall be made available to the director upon request.</para><para>(4) The satisfaction of the training requirements in any state shall be deemed to satisfy the training requirements of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(5) The training requirements of subsection (1) of this section may be approved as continuing education activities pursuant to sections 44-3901 to 44-3908.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 27. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>