<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4904" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4904</statuteno><catchline>Contract; requirements.</catchline><para>No person acting in the capacity of a managing general agent shall place business with an insurer unless there is in force a written contract between the parties which sets forth the responsibilities of each party and, if both parties share responsibility for a particular function, specifies the division of such responsibilities and which contains the following minimum provisions:</para><para>(1) The insurer may terminate the contract for cause upon written notice to the managing general agent. The insurer may suspend the underwriting authority of the managing general agent during the pendency of any dispute regarding the cause for termination;</para><para>(2) The managing general agent will render accounts to the insurer detailing all transactions and remit all funds due under the contract to the insurer on not less than a monthly basis;</para><para>(3) All funds collected for the account of an insurer will be held by the managing general agent in a fiduciary capacity in an institution that is insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation. The account shall be used for all payments on behalf of the insurer. The managing general agent may retain no more than three months' estimated claims payments and allocated loss adjustment expenses;</para><para>(4) Separate records of business written by the managing general agent will be maintained. The insurer shall have access and right to copy all accounts and records related to its business in a form usable by the insurer, and the director shall have access to all books, bank accounts, and records of the managing general agent in a form usable to the director. Such records shall be retained as determined by the director;</para><para>(5) The contract may not be assigned in whole or in part by the managing general agent;</para><para>(6) Appropriate underwriting guidelines, including:</para><para>(a) The maximum annual premium volume;</para><para>(b) The basis of the rates to be charged;</para><para>(c) The types of risks which may be written;</para><para>(d) Maximum limits of liability;</para><para>(e) Applicable exclusions;</para><para>(f) Territorial limitations;</para><para>(g) Policy cancellation provisions; and</para><para>(h) The maximum policy period. The insurer shall have the right to cancel or nonrenew any policy of insurance subject to applicable insurance statutes and regulations;</para><para>(7) The insurer shall require the managing general agent to obtain and maintain a surety bond for the protection of the insurer. The bond amount shall be at least one hundred thousand dollars or ten percent of the managing general agent's total annual written premium nationwide produced by the managing general agent for the insurer in the prior calendar year, whichever is greater, but not greater than five hundred thousand dollars;</para><para>(8) The insurer may require the managing general agent to maintain an errors and omissions policy;</para><para>(9) If the contract permits the managing general agent to settle claims on behalf of the insurer:</para><para>(a) All claims must be reported to the insurer in a timely manner;</para><para>(b) A copy of the claim file will be sent to the insurer at its request or as soon as it becomes known that the claim:</para><para>(i) Has the potential to exceed an amount determined by the director or exceeds the limit set by the insurer, whichever is less;</para><para>(ii) Involves a coverage dispute;</para><para>(iii) May exceed the managing general agent's claims settlement authority;</para><para>(iv) Is open for more than six months; or</para><para>(v) Is closed by payment of an amount set by the director or an amount set by the insurer, whichever is less;</para><para>(c) All claim files will be the joint property of the insurer and the managing general agent. Upon an order of liquidation of the insurer, such files shall become the sole property of the insurer or its estate, and the managing general agent shall have reasonable access to and the right to copy the files on a timely basis; and</para><para>(d) Any settlement authority granted to the managing general agent may be terminated for cause upon the insurer's written notice to the managing general agent or upon the termination of the contract. The insurer may suspend the settlement authority during the pendency of any dispute regarding the cause for termination;</para><para>(10) If electronic claims files are in existence, the contract must address the timely transmission of the data; </para><para>(11) The managing general agent shall use only advertising material pertaining to the business issued by an insurer that has been approved in writing by the insurer in advance of its use; and </para><para>(12) If the contract provides for a sharing of interim profits by the managing general agent and the managing general agent has the authority to determine the amount of the interim profits by establishing loss reserves or controlling claim payments or in any other manner, interim profits will not be paid to the managing general agent until one year after they are earned for property insurance business and five years after they are earned on casualty business and not until the profits have been verified pursuant to section 44-4906.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 1136, &#167; 115; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 875, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc>