<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4804"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4804</statuteno><catchline>Jurisdiction; venue.</catchline><para>(1) No delinquency proceeding shall be commenced under the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act by anyone other than the director, and no court shall have jurisdiction to entertain, hear, or determine any proceeding commenced by any other person.</para><para>(2) No court of this state shall have jurisdiction to entertain, hear, or determine any complaint praying for the dissolution, liquidation, rehabilitation, sequestration, conservation, or receivership of any insurer or praying for an injunction or restraining order or other relief preliminary to, incidental to, or relating to such proceedings other than in accordance with the act.</para><para>(3) In addition to other grounds for jurisdiction provided by the law of this state, a court of this state having jurisdiction of the subject matter has jurisdiction over a person served pursuant to sections 25-505.01 to 25-530.08 or other applicable provisions of law in an action brought by the receiver of a domestic insurer or an alien insurer domiciled in this state:</para><para>(a) If the person served is an agent, broker, or other person who has at any time written policies of insurance for or has acted in any manner whatsoever on behalf of an insurer against which a delinquency proceeding has been instituted, in any action resulting from or incident to such a relationship with the insurer;</para><para>(b) If the person served is a reinsurer who has at any time entered into a contract of reinsurance with an insurer against which a delinquency proceeding has been instituted or is an agent or broker of or for the reinsurer, in any action on or incident to the reinsurance contract;</para><para>(c) If the person served is or has been an officer, manager, trustee, organizer, promoter, or person in a position of comparable authority or influence in an insurer against which a rehabilitation or liquidation order is in effect when the action is commenced, in any action resulting from such a relationship with the insurer;</para><para>(d) If the person served is or was at the time of the institution of the delinquency proceeding against the insurer holding assets in which the receiver claims an interest on behalf of the insurer, in any action concerning the assets; or</para><para>(e) If the person served is obligated to the insurer in any way whatsoever, in any action on or incident to the obligation.</para><para>(4) If the court on motion of any party finds that any action should as a matter of substantial justice be tried in a forum outside this state, the court may enter an appropriate order to stay further proceedings on the action in this state.</para><para>(5) All actions authorized by the act shall be brought in the district court of Lancaster County.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 61. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 