<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id165"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4611"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4611</statuteno><catchline>Act; enforcement; director; powers and duties; monetary penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall enforce compliance with the requirements of the Pharmacy Benefit Manager Licensure and Regulation Act.</para><para>(2)(a) Pursuant to the Insurers Examination Act, the director may examine or audit the books and records of a pharmacy benefit manager providing a claims processing service or other prescription drug or device service for a health benefit plan to determine compliance with the act.</para><para>(b) Information or data acquired during an examination under subdivision (2)(a) of this section is:</para><para>(i) Considered proprietary and confidential;</para><para>(ii) Not subject to sections 84-712, 84-712.01, and 84-712.03 to 84-712.09;</para><para>(iii) Not subject to subpoena; and</para><para>(iv) Not subject to discovery or admissible as evidence in any private civil action.</para><para>(3) The director may use any document or information provided pursuant to subsection (3) or (4) of section 44-4606 in the performance of the director's duties to determine compliance with the Pharmacy Benefit Manager Licensure and Regulation Act.</para><para>(4) The director may impose a monetary penalty on a pharmacy benefit manager or the health carrier with which a pharmacy benefit manager is contracted for a violation of the Pharmacy Benefit Manager Licensure and Regulation Act. The director shall establish the monetary penalty for a violation of the act in an amount not to exceed one thousand dollars per entity for each violation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB767, &#167; 11. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2023</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurers Examination Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>