<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4711"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4711</statuteno><catchline>Construction with other laws.</catchline><para>(1) A prepaid limited health service organization shall be subject to the Unfair Insurance Trade Practices Act and the Unfair Insurance Claims Settlement Practices Act. No other provision of Chapter 44 shall apply unless specifically mentioned in the Prepaid Limited Health Service Organization Act or unless prepaid limited health service organizations are specifically mentioned in the provisions of Chapter 44.</para><para>(2) The provision of limited health services by a prepaid limited health service organization or other entity pursuant to the Prepaid Limited Health Service Organization Act shall not be deemed to be the practice of medicine or other healing arts.</para><para>(3) Solicitation to arrange for or provide limited health services in accordance with the Prepaid Limited Health Service Organization Act shall not be construed to violate any provision of law relating to solicitation or advertising by health professionals.</para><para>(4) A prepaid limited health service organization organized under the laws of this state shall be deemed to be a domestic insurer for purposes of the Insurance Holding Company System Act unless specifically exempted in writing from one or more of the provisions of the act by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 320, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 234, &#167; 38. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Holding Company System Act,</emphasis> see section 44-2120.</para><para><emphasis>Unfair Insurance Claims Settlement Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 44-1536.</para><para><emphasis>Unfair Insurance Trade Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 44-1521.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 