<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4054" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4054</statuteno><catchline id="id00">License; lines of authority; renewal; procedure; licensee; duties; director; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Unless denied licensure pursuant to section 44-4059, a person who has met the requirements of sections 44-4052 and 44-4053 shall be issued an insurance producer license. An insurance producer may receive qualification for a license in one or more of the following lines of authority:</para><para>(a) Life insurance coverage on human lives, including benefits of endowment and annuities, and may include benefits in the event of death or dismemberment by accident and benefits for disability income;</para><para>(b) Accident and health or sickness, insurance coverage for sickness, bodily injury, or accidental death and may include benefits for disability income;</para><para>(c) Property insurance coverage for the direct or consequential loss or damage to property of every kind;</para><para>(d) Casualty insurance coverage against legal liability, including that for death, injury, or disability or damage to real or personal property;</para><para>(e) Variable life and variable annuity products, insurance coverage provided under variable life insurance contracts, and variable annuities;</para><para>(f) Limited line credit insurance;</para><para>(g) Limited line pre-need funeral insurance;</para><para>(h) Personal lines property and casualty insurance coverage sold to individuals and families for primarily noncommercial purposes; and</para><para>(i) Any other line of insurance permitted under Nebraska laws, rules, or regulations.</para><para>(2) An insurance producer license shall remain in effect unless revoked or suspended if the fee set forth in section 44-4064 is paid and education requirements for resident individual producers are met by the due date.</para><para>(3) All business entity licenses issued under the Insurance Producers Licensing Act shall expire on April 30 of each year, and all producers licenses shall expire on the last day of the month of the producer's birthday in the first year after issuance in which his or her age is divisible by two. Such producer licenses may be renewed within the ninety-day period before their expiration dates. Business entity and producer licenses also may be renewed within the thirty-day period after their expiration dates upon payment of a late renewal fee as established by the director pursuant to section 44-4064 in addition to the applicable fee otherwise required for renewal of business entity and producer licenses as established by the director pursuant to such section. All business entity and producer licenses renewed within the thirty-day period after their expiration dates pursuant to this subsection shall be deemed to have been renewed before their expiration dates.</para><para>(4) The director may establish procedures for renewal of licenses by rule and regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(5) An individual insurance producer who allows his or her license to lapse may, within twelve months from the due date of the renewal fee, reinstate the same license without the necessity of passing a written examination. Producer licenses reinstated pursuant to this subsection shall be issued only after payment of a reinstatement fee as established by the director pursuant to section 44-4064 in addition to the applicable fee otherwise required for renewal of producer licenses as established by the director pursuant to such section.</para><para>(6) The director may grant a licensed insurance producer who is unable to comply with license renewal procedures due to military service or some other extenuating circumstance, including, but not limited to, a long-term medical disability, a waiver of those procedures. The director may grant a producer a waiver of any examination requirement or any other fine, fee, or sanction imposed for failure to comply with renewal procedures.</para><para>(7) The license shall contain the licensee's name, address, and personal identification number, the date of issuance, the lines of authority, the expiration date, and any other information the director deems necessary.</para><para>(8) Licensees shall inform the director by any means acceptable to the director of a change of legal name or address within thirty days after the change. Any person failing to provide such notification shall be subject to a fine by the director of not more than five hundred dollars per violation, suspension of the person's license until the change of address is reported to the director, or both.</para><para>(9) The director may contract with nongovernmental entities, including the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or any affiliates or subsidiaries that the National Association of Insurance Commissioners oversees, to perform any ministerial functions, including the collection of fees, related to producer licensing that the director may deem appropriate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 51, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB198, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>