
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4059" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4059</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Disciplinary actions; administrative fine; procedure.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The director may suspend, revoke, or refuse to issue or renew an insurance producer's license or may levy an administrative fine in accordance with subsection (4) of this section, or any combination of actions, for any one or more of the following causes:</para><para id="id00">(a) Providing incorrect, misleading, incomplete, or materially untrue information in the license application;</para><para id="id00">(b) Violating any insurance law or violating any rule, regulation, subpoena, or order of the director or of another state's insurance commissioner or director;</para><para id="id00">(c) Obtaining or attempting to obtain a license through misrepresentation or fraud;</para><para id="id00">(d) Improperly withholding, misappropriating, or converting any money or property received in the course of doing insurance business;</para><para id="id00">(e) Intentionally misrepresenting the terms of an actual or proposed insurance contract or application for insurance;</para><para id="id00">(f) Having been convicted of a felony or a Class I, II, or III misdemeanor;</para><para id="id00">(g) Having admitted or been found to have committed any insurance unfair trade practice, any unfair claims settlement practice, or fraud;</para><para id="id00">(h) Using fraudulent, coercive, or dishonest practices, or demonstrating incompetence, untrustworthiness, or financial irresponsibility in the conduct of business in this state or elsewhere;</para><para id="id00">(i) Having an insurance producer license, or its equivalent, denied, suspended, placed on probation, or revoked in Nebraska or in any other state, province, district, or territory;</para><para id="id00">(j) Forging another's name to an application for insurance or to any document related to an insurance transaction;</para><para id="id00">(k) Improperly using notes or any other reference material to complete an examination for an insurance license;</para><para id="id00">(l) Knowingly accepting insurance business from an individual who is not licensed;</para><para id="id00">(m) Failing to comply with an administrative or court order imposing a child support obligation pursuant to the License Suspension Act;</para><para id="id00">(n) Failing to pay state income tax or comply with any administrative or court order directing payment of state income tax; and</para><para>(o) Failing to maintain in good standing a resident license in the insurance producer's home state.</para><para id="id00">(2) If the director does not renew or denies an application for a license, the director shall notify the applicant or licensee and advise, in writing, the applicant or licensee of the reason for the denial or nonrenewal of the applicant's or licensee's license. The applicant or licensee may make written demand upon the director within thirty days for a hearing before the director to determine the reasonableness of the director's action. The hearing shall be held within thirty days and shall be held pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para id="id00">(3) The license of a business entity may be suspended, revoked, or refused if the director finds, after notice and hearing, that an individual licensee's violation was known or should have been known by one or more of the partners, officers, or managers acting on behalf of the business entity and the violation was neither reported to the director nor corrective action taken.</para><para id="id00">(4) In addition to or in lieu of any applicable denial, suspension, or revocation of a license, any person violating the Insurance Producers Licensing Act may, after notice and hearing, be subject to an administrative fine of not more than one thousand dollars per violation. Such fine may be enforced in the same manner as civil judgments. Any person charged with a violation of the act may waive his or her right to a hearing and consent to such discipline as the director determines is appropriate. The Administrative Procedure Act shall govern all hearings held pursuant to such act.</para><para id="id00">(5) The director shall retain the authority to enforce the provisions of and impose any penalty or remedy authorized by the Insurance Producers Licensing Act against any person who is under investigation for or charged with a violation of the act even if the person's license or registration has been surrendered or has lapsed by operation of law. No disciplinary proceeding shall be instituted against any licensed person after the expiration of three years from the termination of such license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 51, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB231, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>License Suspension Act,</emphasis> see section 43-3301.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under the Insurance Producers Licensing Act, fraud means any act, omission, or concealment which involves a breach of legal or equitable duty, trust, or confidence justly reposed, and injurious to another or by which an undue and unconscientious advantage is taken of another. Diamond v. State, 302 Neb. 892, 926 N.W.2d 71 (2019).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>