<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4823"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4823</statuteno><catchline>Duties of agents; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Every person who receives notice in the form prescribed in section 44-4822 that an insurer which he or she represents as an agent is the subject of a liquidation order shall, within fifteen days of such notice, give notice of the liquidation order. The notice shall be sent by first-class mail to the last address contained in the agent's records to each policyholder or other person named in any policy issued through the agent by the insurer if he or she has a record of the address of the policyholder or other person. A policy shall be deemed issued through an agent if the agent has a property interest in the expiration of the policy or if the agent has had in his or her possession a copy of the declarations of the policy at any time during the life of the policy except when the ownership of the expiration of the policy has been transferred to another. The written notice shall include the name and address of the insurer, the name and address of the agent, identification of the policy impaired, and the nature of the impairment, including termination of coverage as described in section 44-4819. Notice by a general agent satisfies the notice requirement for any agents under contract to him or her. Each agent obligated to give notice under this section shall file a report of compliance with the liquidator.</para><para>(2) Any agent failing to give notice or file a report of compliance as required in subsection (1) of this section may be subject to payment of a civil penalty of not more than one thousand dollars and may have his or her license suspended. The penalty shall be imposed after a hearing held by the director.</para><para>(3) The liquidator may waive the duties imposed by this section if he or she determines that other notice to the policyholders of the insurer under liquidation is adequate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 