<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id4"><sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id6" statutenumber="44-4317"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">44-4317</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Public agency; tax levy; agreements; authorized.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any public agency which has the authority to levy a tax shall be authorized to levy a tax, to contract indebtedness, and to issue general obligation bonds payable from such a tax levy to pay the premium costs of general liability insurance, property insurance, workers' compensation insurance, health, dental, or accident insurance, life insurance, and any other insurance to protect against any of the losses described in section 44-4304 and to pay all costs and expenses associated with membership in a risk management pool, including, but not limited to, standard insurance coverages, group self-insurance coverages, assessments levied by the pool, retirement of debt incurred by the pool, and operating expenses of the pool.</para><para>(b) A member of a risk management pool which has the authority to levy a tax shall be authorized to enter into agreements obligating the member to make payments beyond its current budget year for any of such purposes.</para><para>(c) Taxes levied by a public agency other than an educational service unit or school district for the payment of the principal of, premium of, or interest on such a general obligation bond of such public agency, the payment of such insurance premium costs, and the payment of all costs and expenses associated with membership in a risk management pool may be levied in excess of any tax limitation imposed by statute.</para><para>(d) Except as permitted in subdivision (1)(e) of this section, taxes levied by an educational service unit or school district on or after April 3, 2008, for the payment of the principal of, premium of, or interest on such a general obligation bond of such public agency, the payment of such insurance premium costs, and the payment of all costs and expenses associated with membership in a risk management pool shall be subject to the levy limit applicable to such public agency under section 77-3442.</para><para>(e) Taxes levied by an educational service unit or school district for the payment of the principal of, premium of, or interest on such a general obligation bond of such educational service unit or school district issued prior to April 3, 2008, shall be excluded from the levy limit applicable to such public agency under section 77-3442.</para><para>(2) Nothing in the Intergovernmental Risk Management Act shall be construed or interpreted as permitting the State of Nebraska, represented by the Risk Manager, to enter into any agreement or contract or do any act in contravention of the Constitution of the State of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 398, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 664, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167;  1.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
