<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-4811"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-4811</statuteno><catchline>Confidentiality of hearings.</catchline><para>(1) In all proceedings and judicial review thereof under section 44-4810, all records of the insurer, other documents, all department files, and court records and papers, so far as they pertain to or are a part of the record of the proceedings, shall be and remain confidential except as is necessary to obtain compliance therewith unless and until the court, after hearing arguments from the parties in chambers, orders otherwise or unless the insurer requests that the matter be made public. Until such court order, all papers filed with the clerk of the district court shall be held by him or her in a confidential file.</para><para>(2)(a) The records described in subsection (1) of this section may be provided to other state, federal, foreign, and international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality of the records.</para><para>(b) The director may receive supervision, rehabilitation, and liquidation records from other state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and from the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries. The director shall maintain as confidential or privileged records received pursuant to this subdivision with notice or the understanding that they are confidential or privileged under the laws of the jurisdiction that is the source of the information. Such information shall not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, subject to subpoena, subject to discovery, or admissible in evidence in any private civil action, except that the director may use such information in any regulatory or legal action brought by the director. The director, and any other person while acting under the authority of the director who has received information pursuant to this subdivision, may not, and shall not be required to, testify in any private civil action concerning any information subject to this section. Nothing in this section shall constitute a waiver of any applicable privilege or claim of confidentiality in the information received pursuant to this subdivision as a result of information sharing authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 319, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 236, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 52, &#167; 49. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 