<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id35" statutenumber="44-5504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5504</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Nonadmitted insurer;
surplus lines license; application; fee; expiration; renewal.</catchline>
<para>(1) No person, other than an exempt commercial purchaser, shall place, procure,
or effect insurance for
or on behalf of an insured whose home state is the State of Nebraska in
any nonadmitted insurer until such person has first been issued a surplus
lines license from the department as provided in section 44-5503.</para>
<para>(2) Application for a surplus lines license shall be made
to the department on forms designated and furnished by the department and
shall be accompanied by a license fee as established by the director not to
exceed two hundred fifty dollars for each individual and corporate surplus
lines license.</para>
<para>(3)(a) All corporate surplus lines licenses shall expire on
April 30 of each year, and all individual surplus lines licenses shall expire
on the licensee's birthday in the first year after issuance in which his or
her age is divisible by two, and all individual surplus lines licenses may
be renewed within the ninety-day period before their expiration dates and
all individual surplus lines licenses also may be renewed within the thirty-day
period after their expiration dates upon payment of a late renewal fee as
established by the director not to exceed two hundred dollars in addition
to the applicable fee otherwise required for renewal of individual surplus
lines licenses as established by the director pursuant to subsection (2) of
this section. All individual surplus lines licenses renewed within the thirty-day
period after their expiration dates pursuant to this subdivision shall be
deemed to have been renewed before their expiration dates. The department
shall establish procedures for the renewal of surplus lines licenses.</para>
<para>(b) Every licensee shall notify the department within thirty
days of any changes in the licensee's residential or business address.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 25, p. 408; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3161; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. III, &#167; 18, p. 587; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7762; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-218; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-140; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 836, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 801, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1990, &#167; 44-140; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 260, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB70, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
