<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5103</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Insurers Investment Act:</para><para>(1) Admitted assets means the investments authorized under the act and stated at values at which they are permitted to be reported in the insurer's financial statement filed under section 44-322, except that admitted assets does not include assets of separate accounts, the investments of which are not subject to the act;</para><para>(2) Agent means a national bank, state bank, trust company, or broker-dealer that maintains an account in its name in a clearing corporation or that is a member of the Federal Reserve System and through which a custodian participates in a clearing corporation including the Treasury/Reserve Automated Debt Entry Securities System and Treasury Direct system, except that with respect to securities issued by institutions organized or existing under the laws of a foreign country or securities used to meet deposit requirements pursuant to the laws of a foreign country as a condition of doing business therein, agent may include a corporation that is organized or existing under the laws of a foreign country and that is legally qualified under those laws to accept custody of securities;</para><para>(3) Business entity means a sole proprietorship, corporation, limited liability company, association, partnership, limited liability partnership, joint-stock company, joint venture, mutual fund, trust, joint tenancy, or other similar form of business organization, whether organized for profit or not for profit;</para><para>(4) Clearing corporation means a clearing corporation as defined in subdivision (a)(5) of section 8-102, Uniform Commercial Code, that is organized for the purpose of effecting transactions in securities by computerized book-entry, except that with respect to securities issued by institutions organized or existing under the laws of a foreign country or securities used to meet the deposit requirements pursuant to the laws of a foreign country as a condition of doing business therein, clearing corporation may include a corporation that is organized or existing under the laws of a foreign country and which is legally qualified under those laws to effect transactions in securities by computerized book-entry. Clearing corporation also includes Treasury/Reserve Automated Debt Entry Securities System and Treasury Direct system;</para><para>(5) Custodian means:</para><para>(a) A national bank, state bank, Federal Home Loan Bank, or trust company that shall at all times during which it acts as a custodian pursuant to the Insurers Investment Act be no less than adequately capitalized as determined by the standards adopted by the regulator charged with establishing such standards and assessing the solvency of such institutions and that is regulated by federal or state banking laws or the Federal Home Loan Bank Act or is a member of the Federal Reserve System and that is legally qualified to accept custody of securities in accordance with the standards set forth below, except that with respect to securities issued by institutions organized or existing under the laws of a foreign country, or securities used to meet the deposit requirements pursuant to the laws of a foreign country as a condition of doing business therein, custodian may include a bank or trust company incorporated or organized under the laws of a country other than the United States that is regulated as such by that country's government or an agency thereof that shall at all times during which it acts as a custodian pursuant to the Insurers Investment Act be no less than adequately capitalized as determined by the standards adopted by international banking authorities and that is legally qualified to accept custody of securities; or</para><para>(b) A broker-dealer that shall be registered with and subject to jurisdiction of the Securities and Exchange Commission, maintains membership in the Securities Investor Protection Corporation, and has a tangible net worth equal to or greater than two hundred fifty million dollars;</para><para>(6) Custodied securities means securities held by the custodian or its agent or in a clearing corporation, including the Treasury/Reserve Automated Debt Entry Securities System and Treasury Direct system;</para><para>(7) Direct when used in connection with the term obligation means that the designated obligor is primarily liable on the instrument representing the obligation;</para><para>(8) Director means the Director of Insurance;</para><para>(9) Insurer is defined as provided in section 44-103, and unless the context otherwise requires, insurer means domestic insurer;</para><para>(10) Mortgage means a consensual interest created by a real estate mortgage, a trust deed on real estate, or a similar instrument;</para><para>(11) Obligation means a bond, debenture, note, or other evidence of indebtedness or a participation, certificate, or other evidence of an interest in any of the foregoing;</para><para>(12) Policyholders surplus means the amount obtained by subtracting from the admitted assets (a) actual liabilities and (b) any and all reserves which by law must be maintained. In the case of a stock insurer, the policyholders surplus also includes the paid-up and issued capital stock;</para><para>(13) Primary credit source means the credit source to which an insurer looks for payment as to an investment and against which an insurer has a claim for full payment;</para><para>(14) Securities Valuation Office means the Securities Valuation Office of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or any successor office established by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners;</para><para>(15) Security certificate has the same meaning as defined in subdivision (a)(16) of section 8-102, Uniform Commercial Code;</para><para>(16) State means any state of the United States, the District of Columbia, or any territory organized by Congress;</para><para>(17) Tangible net worth means shareholders equity, less intangible assets, as reported in the broker-dealer's most recent Annual or Transition Report pursuant to section 13 or 15(d) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, S.E.C. Form 10-K, filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission; and</para><para>(18) Treasury/Reserve Automated Debt Entry Securities System and Treasury Direct system mean the book-entry securities systems established pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 301, 12 U.S.C. 391, and 31 U.S.C. 3101 et seq. The operation of the systems are subject to 31 C.F.R. part 357 et seq.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 259, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB192, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB863, &#167; 25. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>