<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5609"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5609</statuteno><catchline>Reinsurer; prohibited acts; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A reinsurer shall not engage the services of any person, firm, association, or corporation to act as a reinsurance intermediary-manager on its behalf unless such person, firm, association, or corporation is licensed as required by subsection (2) of section 44-5603.</para><para>(2) The reinsurer shall annually obtain a copy of statements of the financial condition of each reinsurance intermediary-manager which such reinsurer has engaged prepared by an independent certified public accountant in a form acceptable to the director.</para><para>(3) If a reinsurance intermediary-manager establishes loss reserves, the reinsurer shall annually obtain the opinion of an independent actuary attesting to the adequacy of loss reserves established for losses incurred and outstanding on business produced by the reinsurance intermediary-manager. The opinion shall be in addition to any other required loss reserve certification.</para><para>(4) Binding authority for all retrocessional contracts or participation in reinsurance syndicates shall rest with an officer of the reinsurer who is not affiliated with the reinsurance intermediary-manager.</para><para>(5) Within thirty days of termination of a contract with a reinsurance intermediary-manager, the reinsurer shall provide written notification of such termination to the director.</para><para>(6) A reinsurer shall not appoint to its board of directors, any officer, director, employee, controlling shareholder, or subproducer of its reinsurance intermediary-manager. This subsection shall not apply to relationships governed by the Insurance Holding Company System Act or the Producer-Controlled Property and Casualty Insurer Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 63. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Holding Company System Act,</emphasis> see section 44-2120.</para><para><emphasis>Producer-Controlled Property and Casualty Insurer Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5701.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 