<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5814"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5814</statuteno><catchline>Annual report; filing; contents; fee; failure to file; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Each third-party administrator shall file an annual report for the preceding calendar year with the director on or before March 1 of each year or within such extension of time therefor as the director for good cause may grant. The annual report shall be in the form and contain such matters as the director prescribes and shall be verified by at least two officers of the third-party administrator.</para><para>(2) The annual report shall include the complete names and addresses of all insurers with which the third-party administrator had a written agreement during the preceding fiscal year.</para><para>(3) At the time of filing its annual report, the third-party administrator shall pay to the director a filing fee of two hundred dollars.</para><para>(4)(a) Within seven business days after the failure of a third-party administrator to comply with the requirements of this section, the director shall notify the third-party administrator of such failure.</para><para>(b) Subject to subdivision (4)(c) of this section, if a third-party administrator fails to comply with the requirements of this section and any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under this section and any orders issued under this section:</para><para>(i) Such third-party administrator shall pay a fine of fifty dollars for each day thereafter such failure continues and the third-party administrator continues to transact any business of insurance; and</para><para>(ii) In addition to the fine required under subdivision (4)(b)(i) of this section, the director may suspend the certificate of authority of the third-party administrator until it has complied with the requirements of this section, any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under this section, and any orders issued under this section. The director shall remit all such fines to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(c) For good and sufficient cause shown, the director may grant a reasonable extension of time not to exceed thirty days within which the annual report may be filed as required under this section without the fine required under subdivision (4)(b)(i) of this section and without any suspension authorized under subdivision (4)(b)(ii) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 216, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB21, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>