<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5153"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5153</statuteno><catchline>Additional authorized investments.</catchline><para>(1)(a)(i) A life insurer may make investments not otherwise authorized under the Insurers Investment Act in an amount, in the aggregate, not exceeding the lesser of five percent of the first five hundred million dollars of its admitted assets plus ten percent of its admitted assets exceeding five hundred million dollars or one hundred percent of its policyholders surplus.</para><para>(ii) An insurer other than a life insurer may make investments not otherwise authorized under the act in an amount, in the aggregate, not exceeding the lesser of twenty-five percent of the amount by which its admitted assets exceed its total liabilities, excluding capital, or five percent of the first five hundred million dollars of its admitted assets plus ten percent of its admitted assets exceeding five hundred million dollars.</para><para>(b) Investments authorized under this subsection shall not include obligations having 3, 4, 5, and 6 designations from the Securities Valuation Office.</para><para>(2)(a) In addition to the provisions of subdivision (1)(a)(i) of this section, a life insurer may make investments not otherwise authorized under the act in an amount not exceeding that portion of its policyholders surplus which is in excess of ten percent of its admitted assets.</para><para>(b) In addition to the provisions of subdivisions (1)(a)(ii) and (b) of this section, an insurer other than a life insurer may make investments not otherwise authorized under the act in an amount not exceeding that portion of its policyholders surplus which is in excess of fifty percent of its annual net written premiums as shown by the most recent annual financial statement filed by the insurer pursuant to section 44-322.</para><para>(3) Investments authorized under subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall not include assets held by a ceding insurer as security supporting reinsurance arrangements through which credit for reinsurance has been allowed.</para><para>(4) Investments authorized under subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall not include insurance agents' balances or amounts advanced to or owing by insurance agents.</para><para>(5) The limitations set forth in this section shall be applied at the time the investment in question is made and at the end of each calendar quarter. An insurer's investment, which at the time of its acquisition was authorized only under the provisions of this section but which has subsequently and while held by such insurer become of such character as to be authorized elsewhere under the act, shall not be included in determining the amount of such insurer's investments, in the aggregate, authorized under this section, and investments otherwise authorized under the act at the time of their acquisition shall not be included in making such determination.</para><para>(6) Derivative instruments described in subsections (1), (2), and (3) of section 44-5149 shall not be authorized investments under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB863, &#167; 36. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>