<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5808"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5808</statuteno><catchline>Funds collected; held in fiduciary capacity; accounting.</catchline><para>(1) All charges and premiums collected by a third-party administrator on behalf of or for an insurer or insurers and the return of premiums received from that insurer or insurers shall be held by the third-party administrator in a fiduciary capacity. Such funds shall be immediately remitted to the person or persons entitled to them or shall be deposited promptly in a fiduciary account established and maintained by the third-party administrator in a federally insured or state-insured financial institution. The written agreement between the third-party administrator and the insurer shall provide for the third-party administrator to periodically render an accounting to the insurer detailing all transactions performed by the third-party administrator pertaining to the insurance business underwritten by the insurer.</para><para>(2) If charges and premiums deposited in a fiduciary account have been collected on behalf of or for one or more insurers, the third-party administrator shall keep records clearly recording the deposits in and withdrawals from the fiduciary account on behalf of each insurer. The third-party administrator shall keep copies of all the records pertaining to such deposits and withdrawals and, upon request of an insurer, shall furnish the insurer with copies of the records.</para><para>(3) The third-party administrator shall not pay any claim by withdrawals from a fiduciary account in which charges and premiums are deposited. Withdrawals from such account shall be made as provided in the written agreement between the third-party administrator and the insurer. The written agreement shall address, but not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) Remittance to an insurer entitled to remittance;</para><para>(b) Deposit in an account maintained in the name of the insurer;</para><para>(c) Transfer to and deposit in a claims-paying account, with claims to be paid as provided for in subsection (4) of this section;</para><para>(d) Payment to a group policyholder or group contract holder for remittance to the insurer entitled to such remittance;</para><para>(e) Payment to the third-party administrator of its commissions, fees, or charges; and</para><para>(f) Remittance of return of premium to the person or persons entitled to such return of premium.</para><para>(4) All claims paid by the third-party administrator from funds collected on behalf of or for an insurer shall be paid only on drafts or checks of and as authorized by the insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 83. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 