<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5803"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5803</statuteno><catchline>Third-party administrator; written agreement; requirements; suspension during dispute.</catchline><para>(1) No third-party administrator shall act as such without a written agreement between the third-party administrator and the insurer, and such written agreement shall be retained as part of the official records of both the insurer and the third-party administrator for the duration of the agreement and for five years thereafter. The agreement shall contain all provisions required by the Third-Party Administrator Act except insofar as those provisions do not apply to the functions performed by the third-party administrator.</para><para>(2) The written agreement shall include a statement of duties which the third-party administrator is expected to perform on behalf of the insurer and the lines, classes, or types of insurance for which the third-party administrator is to be authorized to administer. The written agreement shall make provision with respect to underwriting or other standards pertaining to the insurance business underwritten by such insurer.</para><para>(3) The insurer or third-party administrator may, with written notice, terminate the written agreement for cause as provided in the written agreement. The insurer may suspend the underwriting authority of the third-party administrator during the pendency of any dispute regarding the cause for termination of the written agreement. The insurer shall fulfill any lawful obligations with respect to policies affected by the written agreement, regardless of any dispute between the insurer and the third-party administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 78. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 