<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id59">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id61" statutenumber="44-5702"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5702</statuteno><catchline id="id64">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Producer-Controlled Property and Casualty
Insurer Act:</para>
<para>(1) Accredited state shall mean a state in which the insurance
department or regulatory agency has qualified as meeting the minimum financial
regulatory standards established and promulgated from time to time by the
National Association of Insurance Commissioners;</para>
<para>(2) Captive insurers shall mean insurance companies owned
by another organization the exclusive purpose of which is to insure risks
of the parent organization and affiliated companies or, in the case of groups
and associations, insurance organizations owned by the insureds the exclusive
purpose of which is to insure risks to member organizations or group members
and their affiliates;</para>
<para>(3) Control or controlled shall have the same meaning as in
section 44-2121;</para>
<para>(4) Controlled insurer shall mean an insurer which is controlled,
directly or indirectly, by a producer;</para>
<para>(5) Controlling producer shall mean a producer which, directly
or indirectly, controls an insurer;</para>
<para>(6) Director shall mean the Director of Insurance;</para>
<para>(7) Insurer shall mean any person, firm, association, or corporation
holding a certificate of authority to transact property and casualty insurance
business in this state. Insurer shall not include:</para>
<para>(a) Residual market pools
and joint underwriting authorities or associations; and</para>
<para>(b) Captive insurers other than risk retention groups as defined
in 15 U.S.C. 3901 et seq. and 42 U.S.C. 9671, as such sections existed on
January 1, 2014; and</para>
<para>(8) Producer shall mean an insurance broker or any other person,
firm, association, or corporation when, for any compensation, commission,
or other thing of value, such person, firm, association, or corporation acts
or aids in any manner in soliciting, negotiating, or procuring the making
of any insurance contract on behalf of an insured other than the person, firm,
association, or corporation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB700, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>