<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5512" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5512</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Violations; director; hearing; orders; penalty; appeal.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever the director has reason to believe that any person has engaged in any activities in violation of the Surplus Lines Insurance Act, the director may:</para><para id="id00">(a) Issue an order and notice of hearing directing such person to cease and desist from engaging in such activities; or</para><para id="id00">(b) Issue a statement of the charges of violation and a notice of hearing to be held within thirty days to determine whether or not such violation occurred.</para><para id="id00">(2) Any hearing held pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, and any appeal therefrom, shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para id="id00">(3) If, after any hearing held pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the director finds that the person charged has committed a violation as alleged, he or she shall reduce his or her findings to writing and serve a copy of the findings on the person charged and, in addition, the director may order any one or more of the following:</para><para id="id00">(a) That such person cease and desist from engaging in such activities;</para><para id="id00">(b) Payment of a fine of not more than five thousand dollars; and</para><para id="id00">(c) Suspension or revocation of any surplus lines license held by such person for such period of time as the director determines.</para><para id="id00">(4) Any person who violates a cease and desist order may, after notice and hearing and upon order of the director, be subject to:</para><para id="id00">(a) Payment of a fine of not more than ten thousand dollars; and</para><para id="id00">(b) Suspension or revocation of each insurance license held by such person for such period of time as the director determines.</para><para id="id00">(5) For purposes of this section, person shall include a nonadmitted insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 836, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 37; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1990, &#167; 44-147.04; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB799, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>