<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5140"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5140</statuteno><catchline>Preferred stock.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer may invest in the preferred stock of any corporation which:</para><para>(a) Has retained earnings of not less than one million dollars;</para><para>(b) Has earned and paid regular dividends at the regular prescribed rate each year upon its preferred stock, if any is or has been outstanding, for not less than five years immediately preceding the purchase of such preferred stock or during such part of such five-year period as it has had preferred stock outstanding; and</para><para>(c) Has had no material defaults in principal payments of or interest on any obligations of such corporation and its subsidiaries having a priority equal to or higher than those purchased during the period of five years immediately preceding the date of acquisition or, if outstanding for less than five years, at any time since such obligations were issued.</para><para>The earnings of and the regular dividends paid by all predecessor, merged, consolidated, or purchased corporations may be included through the use of consolidated or pro forma statements.</para><para>(2) Except as authorized under the Insurance Holding Company System Act, an insurer shall not own more than five percent of the total issued shares of stock of any corporation other than an insurer.</para><para>(3) A life insurer's investments authorized under this section shall not exceed the greater of twenty-five percent of its admitted assets or one hundred percent of its policyholders surplus, nor shall a life insurer's investments authorized under this section that are not rated P-1 or P-2 by the Securities Valuation Office exceed ten percent of its admitted assets.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 17.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Holding Company System Act,</emphasis> see section 44-2120.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>