<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id148"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5004"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5004</statuteno><catchline>Health insurance plan; coverage required; items and services; exemption from act.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2020, except as provided in subsection (4) of this section and notwithstanding section 44-3,131, any health insurance plan delivered, issued for delivery, renewed, extended, or modified in this state shall provide coverage pursuant to the Children of Nebraska Hearing Aid Act to each insured child. Such coverage shall be subject to subsection (2) of this section and shall include, for each ear affected by a hearing impairment, the following items and services:</para><para>(a) A hearing aid purchased from a licensed audiologist with the medical clearance from an otolaryngologist and costs related to dispensing such hearing aid;</para><para>(b) Evaluation for a hearing aid;</para><para>(c) Fitting of a hearing aid;</para><para>(d) Programming of a hearing aid;</para><para>(e) Probe microphone measurements for verification that hearing aid gain and output meet the prescribed targets;</para><para>(f) Hearing aid repairs;</para><para>(g) Follow-up adjustments, servicing, and maintenance of a hearing aid;</para><para>(h) Ear mold impressions;</para><para>(i) Ear molds; and</para><para>(j) Auditory rehabilitation and training.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the items and services listed in subsection (1) of this section shall be covered on a continual basis to the extent that benefits paid for such items and services during the immediately preceding forty-eight-month period have not exceeded three thousand dollars.</para><para>(b) Coverage pursuant to the act shall allow for the replacement of a hearing aid and the associated services within three months of the dispensing date if the hearing aid gain and output fail to meet prescribed targets or the hearing aid is unable to be repaired or adjusted. If an insured child uses a hearing aid on September 1, 2019, and the hearing aid has been deemed unrepairable or obsolete by the manufacturer of the device, the insured child shall be eligible to use the benefits required by the act towards the acquisition of a new hearing aid, parts, and associated services.</para><para>(c) Coverage provided to an insured child pursuant to the act shall be subject to the same deductible, copayment, and coinsurance as similar covered items and services under the health insurance plan.</para><para>(3) A health insurance plan shall not refuse or deny coverage, refuse to renew or reissue coverage, or terminate coverage for an individual with a hearing impairment who is less than nineteen years of age based on such hearing impairment.</para><para>(4) A health insurance plan shall be exempt from the act for a plan year if, using a calculation method approved by the Department of Insurance, the cost of coverage would likely exceed one percent of all premiums collected under such plan for such plan year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB15, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>