<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id50">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id52" statutenumber="44-5506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5506</statuteno><catchline id="id55">Surplus lines
licensee; quarterly statement; tax payment; director; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) For purposes of carrying out
the Nonadmitted and Reinsurance Reform Act of 2010, which is Subtitle B of
the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act, Public Law
111-203, as such act existed on January 1, 2011, the director may enter into
the Nonadmitted Insurance Multi-State Agreement in order to facilitate the
collection, allocation, and disbursement of premium taxes attributable to
the placement of nonadmitted insurance, provide for uniform methods of allocation
and reporting among nonadmitted insurance risk classifications, and share
information among states relating to nonadmitted insurance premium taxes.</para>
<para>(2) The director may
participate in the clearinghouse established through the Nonadmitted Insurance
Multi-State Agreement for the purpose of collecting and disbursing to reciprocal
states any funds collected applicable to properties, risks, or exposures located
or to be performed outside of this state. To the extent that other states
where portions of the properties, risks, or exposures reside have failed to
enter into a compact or reciprocal allocation procedure with the State of
Nebraska, the net premium tax shall be retained by the State of Nebraska.
If the director chooses to participate in the clearinghouse for the purpose
authorized by this subsection, the director may also participate in such clearinghouse
for purposes of surplus lines policies applicable to risks located solely
within this state.</para><para>(3)
Every surplus lines licensee transacting business under the Surplus Lines
Insurance Act shall, on or before February 15 for the quarter ending the preceding
December 31, May 15 for the quarter ending the preceding March 31, August
15 for the quarter ending the preceding June 30, and November 15 for the quarter
ending the preceding September 30 of each year, make and file with the department
a verified statement upon a form prescribed by the department or a designee
of the director which shall exhibit the true amount of all such business transacted
during that period.</para><para>(4)(a)
Every surplus lines licensee transacting business under the Surplus Lines
Insurance Act shall collect and pay to the director or the director's designee,
at the time the statement required under subsection (3) of this section is
filed, a sum based on the total gross premiums charged, less any return premiums,
for surplus lines insurance provided by the licensee pursuant to the license.
In no event shall such taxes be determined on a retaliatory basis pursuant
to section 44-150.</para><para>(b)
When the insurance covers properties, risks, or exposures located or to be
performed solely in this state on behalf of an insured whose home state is
the State of Nebraska, the sum payable shall be computed based on an amount
equal to three percent of the premiums to be remitted to the State Treasurer
in accordance with section 77-912.</para><para>(c) When the insurance covers properties, risks, or
exposures located or to be performed both in and out of this state, the sum
payable shall be computed based on:</para><para>(i) For purposes of the portion that is attributable
to instate risks, an amount and rate equal to that set forth in subdivision
(4)(b) of this section; plus</para><para>(ii) For purposes of the portion that is attributable
to out-of-state risks, an amount equal to the portion of the premiums allocated
to each of the other states or territories and at a rate as established by
each state or territory as being applicable to the properties, risks, or exposures
located or performed outside of this state. The tax on any portion of the
premium unearned at termination of insurance having been credited by the state
to the licensee shall be returned to the policyholder directly by the surplus
lines licensee or through the producing broker, if any. The surplus lines
licensee is prohibited from rebating, for any reason, any portion of the tax.</para>
<para>(5) The director may
utilize or adopt the allocation schedule included in the Nonadmitted Insurance
Multi-State Agreement for the purpose of allocating risk and computing the
tax due on the portion of premium attributable to each risk classification
and to each state in which properties, risks, or exposures are located.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 25, p. 409; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3161; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. III, &#167; 18, p. 588; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7762; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-218; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-142; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 836, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 302, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 32; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1990, &#167; 44-142; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB70, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
