<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<sectno id="id41">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id42" statutenumber="44-5307"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id44">44-5307</statuteno><catchline id="id45">Policy or contract;
benefits required; coverage
authorized; prohibitions.</catchline><para>(1) An uninsured access coverage policy or contract may include hospital-only and surgical-only
benefits which shall mean:</para>
<para>(a) Inhospital benefits for not less than thirty continuous
days nor more than ninety continuous days for each spell of illness; and</para>
<para>(b) Surgical benefits for both inpatient and outpatient surgery.</para>
<para>(2) An uninsured
access coverage policy or contract may include prescription drug benefit coverage.</para>
<para>(3) An uninsured
access coverage policy or contract may include preventative health care coverage,
including, but not limited to, primary care physician visits, immunizations
for adults and children, laboratory and X-ray procedures, and preventative
cancer screenings such as mammograms, cervical cancer screenings, and noninvasive
colorectal or prostate screenings.</para><para>(4) An uninsured access coverage policy or contract
may not:</para>
<para>(a) Use a definition of spell of illness more restrictive
than the definition found in section 44-5303; or</para>
<para>(b) Use a definition of preexisting condition more restrictive
than the definition normally used by the insurer for its regular individual
health insurance contracts.</para>
<para>(5) Every uninsured access
coverage policy or contract shall provide that the benefit payment shall be
accepted as payment in full by the provider and there shall be no deductible
or coinsurance charged to the insured.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 419, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB445, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>