<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5261"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5261</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Small Employer Health Reinsurance Program; created; powers; board; members; terms; vacancy; powers and duties; small employer carrier; filing required; plan of operation; reinsuring carrier; reinsure with program; when; requirements; premium rates; assessment to fund losses; limitation on liability; exemption from taxation.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created a nonprofit entity to be known as the Nebraska Small Employer Health Reinsurance Program.</para><para>(2)(a) The program shall operate subject to the supervision and control of the board. Subject to this subsection, the board shall consist of eight members appointed by the director and the director or his or her designated representative who shall serve as an ex officio member of the board.</para><para>(b) In selecting the members of the board, the director shall include representatives of small employers and small employer carriers and such other individuals determined to be qualified by the director. At least five members of the board shall be representatives of carriers and shall be selected from individuals nominated in this state pursuant to procedures and guidelines developed by the director.</para><para>(c) The initial board members shall be appointed as follows: Two of the members to serve terms of two years; three of the members to serve terms of four years; and three of the members to serve terms of six years. Subsequent board members shall serve for terms of three years. A board member's term shall continue until his or her successor is appointed.</para><para>(d) A vacancy in the board shall be filled by the director. A board member may be removed by the director for cause.</para><para>(3) Within sixty days after January 1, 1995, each small employer carrier shall make a filing with the director containing the carrier's net health insurance premium derived from health benefit plans delivered or issued for delivery to small employers in this state in the previous calendar year.</para><para>(4) Within one hundred eighty days after the appointment of the initial board, the board shall submit to the director a plan of operation and thereafter any amendments thereto necessary or suitable to assure the fair, reasonable, and equitable administration of the program. The director may, after notice and hearing, approve the plan of operation if the director determines it to be suitable to assure the fair, reasonable, and equitable administration of the program and to provide for the sharing of program gains or losses on an equitable and proportionate basis in accordance with the provisions of this section. The plan of operation shall become effective upon written approval by the director.</para><para>(5) If the board fails to submit a suitable plan of operation within one hundred eighty days after its appointment, the director shall, after notice and hearing, adopt and promulgate a temporary plan of operation. The director shall amend or rescind any plan adopted under this subsection at the time a plan of operation is submitted by the board and approved by the director.</para><para>(6) The plan of operation shall:</para><para>(a) Establish procedures for handling and accounting of program assets and money and for an annual fiscal reporting to the director;</para><para>(b) Establish procedures for selecting an administering carrier and setting forth the powers and duties of the administering carrier;</para><para>(c) Establish procedures for reinsuring risks in accordance with the provisions of this section;</para><para>(d) Establish procedures for collecting assessments from reinsuring carriers to fund claims and administrative expenses incurred or estimated to be incurred by the program;</para><para>(e) Establish a methodology for applying the dollar thresholds contained in this section in the case of carriers that pay or reimburse health care providers through capitation or salary; and</para><para>(f) Provide for any additional matters necessary for the implementation and administration of the program.</para><para>(7) The program shall have the general powers and authority granted under the laws of this state to insurance companies and health maintenance organizations licensed to transact business except the power to issue health benefit plans directly to either groups or individuals. In addition thereto, the program shall have the specific authority to:</para><para>(a) Enter into contracts as are necessary or proper to carry out the provisions and purposes of the Small Employer Health Insurance Availability Act, including the authority, with the approval of the director, to enter into contracts with similar programs of other states for the joint performance of common functions or with persons or other organizations for the performance of administrative functions;</para><para>(b) Sue or be sued, including taking any legal actions necessary or proper to recover any assessments and penalties for, on behalf of, or against the program or any reinsuring carriers;</para><para>(c) Take any legal action necessary to avoid the payment of improper claims against the program;</para><para>(d) Define the health benefit plans for which reinsurance will be provided and issue reinsurance policies, in accordance with the requirements of the act;</para><para>(e) Establish rules, conditions, and procedures for reinsuring risks under the program;</para><para>(f) Establish actuarial functions as appropriate for the operation of the program;</para><para>(g) Assess reinsuring carriers in accordance with the provisions of subsection (11) of this section, and make advance interim assessments as may be reasonable and necessary for organizational and interim operating expenses. Any interim assessments shall be credited as offsets against any regular assessments due following the close of the fiscal year;</para><para>(h) Appoint appropriate legal, actuarial, and other committees as necessary to provide technical assistance in the operation of the program, policy and other contract design, and any other function within the authority of the program; and</para><para>(i) Borrow money to effect the purposes of the program. Any notes or other evidence of indebtedness of the program not in default shall be legal investments for carriers and may be carried as admitted assets.</para><para>(8) A reinsuring carrier may reinsure with the program as provided for in this subsection:</para><para>(a) With respect to a basic health benefit plan or a standard health benefit plan, the program shall reinsure the level of coverage provided and, with respect to other plans, the program shall reinsure up to the level of coverage provided in a basic health benefit plan or standard health benefit plan.</para><para>(b) A small employer carrier may reinsure an entire employer group within sixty days of the commencement of the group's coverage under a health benefit plan.</para><para>(c) A reinsuring carrier may reinsure an eligible employee or dependent within a period of sixty days following the commencement of coverage with the small employer. A newly eligible employee or dependent of the reinsured small employer may be reinsured within sixty days of the commencement of his or her coverage.</para><para>(d)(i) The program shall not reimburse a reinsuring carrier with respect to the claims of a reinsured employee or dependent until the carrier has incurred an initial level of claims for such employee or dependent of five thousand dollars in a calendar year for benefits covered by the program. In addition, the reinsuring carrier shall be responsible for ten percent of the next fifty thousand dollars of benefit payments during a calendar year and the program shall reinsure the remainder. A reinsuring carrier's liability under this subdivision shall not exceed a maximum limit of ten thousand dollars in any one calendar year with respect to any reinsured individual.</para><para>(ii) The board annually shall adjust the initial level of claims and the maximum limit to be retained by the reinsuring carrier to reflect increases in costs and utilization within the standard market for health benefit plans within the state. The adjustment shall not be less than the annual change in the medical component of the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers of the United States Department of Labor, Bureau of Labor Statistics, unless the board proposes and the director approves a lower adjustment factor.</para><para>(e) A small employer carrier may terminate reinsurance with the program for one or more of the reinsured employees or dependents of a small employer on any anniversary of the health benefit plan.</para><para>(f) Premium rates charged for reinsurance by the program to a health maintenance organization that is federally qualified under 42 U.S.C. 300e(c)(2)(A), as such section existed on January 1, 2002, and as such is subject to requirements that limit the amount of risk that may be ceded to the program that is more restrictive than those specified in subdivision (d) of this subsection, shall be reduced to reflect that portion of the risk above the amount set forth in subdivision (d) of this subsection that may not be ceded to the program, if any.</para><para>(g) A reinsuring carrier shall apply all managed care and claims handling techniques, including utilization review, individual case management, restricted network provisions, and other managed care provisions or methods of operation consistently with respect to reinsured and nonreinsured business.</para><para>(9)(a) The board, as part of the plan of operation, shall establish a methodology for determining premium rates to be charged by the program for reinsuring small employers and individuals pursuant to this section. The methodology shall include a system for classification of small employers that reflects the types of case characteristics commonly used by small employer carriers in the state. The methodology shall provide for the development of base reinsurance premium rates which shall be multiplied by the factors set forth in this subsection to determine the premium rates for the program. The base reinsurance premium rates shall be established by the board, subject to the approval of the director, and shall be set at levels which reasonably approximate gross premiums charged to small employers by small employer carriers for health benefit plans with benefits similar to the standard health benefit plan adjusted to reflect retention levels required under the act.</para><para>(b) Premiums for the program shall be as follows:</para><para>(i) An entire small employer group may be reinsured for a rate that is one and one-half times the base reinsurance premium rate for the group established pursuant to this subsection; and</para><para>(ii) An eligible employee or dependent may be reinsured for a rate that is five times the base reinsurance premium rate for the individual established pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(c) The board periodically shall review the methodology established under subdivision (a) of this subsection, including the system of classification and any rating factors, to assure that it reasonably reflects the claims experience of the program. The board may propose changes to the methodology which shall be subject to the approval of the director.</para><para>(d) The board may consider adjustments to the premium rates charged by the program to reflect the use of effective cost containment and managed care arrangements.</para><para>(10) If a health benefit plan for a small employer is entirely or partially reinsured with the program, the premium charged to the small employer for any rating period for the coverage issued shall meet the requirements relating to premium rates set forth in section 44-5258.</para><para>(11)(a) Prior to April 1 of each year, the board shall determine and report to the director the program net loss for the previous calendar year, including administrative expenses and incurred losses for the year, taking into account investment income and other appropriate gains and losses.</para><para>(b) Any net loss for the year shall be recouped by assessments of reinsuring carriers.</para><para>(i) The board shall establish, as part of the plan of operation, a formula by which to make assessments against reinsuring carriers. The assessment formula shall be based on:</para><para>(A) Each reinsuring carrier's share of the total premiums earned in the preceding calendar year from health benefit plans delivered or issued for delivery to small employers in this state by reinsuring carriers; and</para><para>(B) Each reinsuring carrier's share of the premiums earned in the preceding calendar year from newly issued health benefit plans delivered or issued for delivery during the calendar year to small employers in this state by reinsuring carriers.</para><para>(ii) The formula established pursuant to this subsection shall not result in any reinsuring carrier having an assessment share that is less than fifty percent nor more than one hundred fifty percent of an amount which is based on the proportion of (A) the reinsuring carrier's total premiums earned in the preceding calendar year from health benefit plans delivered or issued for delivery to small employers in this state by reinsuring carriers to (B) the total premiums earned in the preceding calendar year from health benefit plans delivered or issued for delivery to small employers in this state by all reinsuring carriers.</para><para>(iii) The board may, with approval of the director, change the assessment formula established pursuant to this subsection from time to time as appropriate. The board may provide for the shares of the assessment base attributable to total premium and to the previous year's premium to vary during a transition period.</para><para>(iv) Subject to the approval of the director, the board shall make an adjustment to the assessment formula for reinsuring carriers that are approved health maintenance organizations which are federally qualified under 42 U.S.C. 300e et seq., as such section existed on January 1, 2002, to the extent, if any, that restrictions are placed on them that are not imposed on other small employer carriers.</para><para>(c)(i) Prior to April 1 of each year, the board shall determine and file with the director an estimate of the assessments needed to fund the losses incurred by the program in the previous calendar year.</para><para>(ii) If the board determines that the assessments needed to fund the losses incurred by the program in the previous calendar year will exceed the amount specified in subdivision (c)(iii) of this subsection, the board shall evaluate the operation of the program and report its findings, including any recommendations for changes to the plan of operation, to the director within ninety days following the end of the calendar year in which the losses were incurred. The evaluation shall include an estimate of future assessments and consideration of the administrative costs of the program, the appropriateness of the premiums charged, the level of insurer retention under the program, and the costs of coverage for small employers. If the board fails to file a report with the director within ninety days following the end of the applicable calendar year, the director may evaluate the operations of the program and implement such amendments to the plan of operation as the director deems necessary to reduce future losses and assessments.</para><para>(iii) For any calendar year, the amount specified in this subdivision is one percent of total premiums earned in the previous calendar year from health benefit plans delivered or issued for delivery to small employers in this state by reinsuring carriers.</para><para>(d) If the assessment in any calendar year exceeds the amount specified in subdivision (c)(iii) of this subsection, the board shall notify the director who shall, within ten days of receipt of such notice, suspend the guarantee-issue requirement of subdivision (2)(b)(i) of section 44-5260 until such time as the board has implemented changes to the reinsurance program which the board, with the director's approval, determines will be sufficient to fully fund future program liabilities and administrative expenses.</para><para>(e) If assessments exceed net losses of the program, the excess shall be held at interest and used by the board to offset future losses or to reduce program premiums. Future losses shall include reserves for incurred but not reported claims.</para><para>(f) Each reinsuring carrier's proportion of the assessment shall be determined annually by the board based on annual statements and other reports deemed necessary by the board and filed by the reinsuring carriers with the board.</para><para>(g) The plan of operation shall provide for the imposition of an interest penalty for late payment of assessments.</para><para>(h) A reinsuring carrier may seek from the director a deferment from all or part of an assessment imposed by the board. The director may defer all or part of the assessment of a reinsuring carrier if the director determines that the payment of the assessment would place the reinsuring carrier in a financially impaired condition. If all or part of an assessment against a reinsuring carrier is deferred, the amount deferred shall be assessed against the other participating carriers in a manner consistent with the basis for assessment set forth in this subsection. The reinsuring carrier receiving the deferment shall remain liable to the program for the amount deferred and shall be prohibited from reinsuring any individuals or groups with the program until such time as it pays the assessment.</para><para>(12) Neither the participation in the program as reinsuring carriers, the establishment of rates, forms, or procedures, nor any other joint or collective action required by the act shall be the basis of any legal action, criminal or civil liability, or penalty against the program or any of its reinsuring carriers either jointly or separately.</para><para>(13) The board, as part of the plan of operation, shall develop standards setting forth the manner and level of compensation to be paid to agents and brokers for the sale of basic health benefit plans and standard health benefit plans. In establishing such standards, the board shall take into consideration the need to assure the broad availability of coverages, the objectives of the program, the time and effort expended in placing the coverage, the need to provide ongoing service to the small employer, the levels of compensation currently used in the industry, and the overall costs of coverage to small employers selecting these plans.</para><para>(14) The program shall be exempt from any and all taxes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1222, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 862, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 35. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 