<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5138"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5138</statuteno><catchline>Short-term investments.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer may invest in:</para><para>(a) Bank certificates of deposit, banker's acceptances, or corporate promissory notes with a remaining term of no more than one year; and</para><para>(b) Shares, interests, or participation certificates in any management type of investment trust, corporate or otherwise, registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940, as amended, as a diversified open-end investment company, that invests solely in such investments as described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(2) Any investment in corporate promissory notes authorized under subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall have a 1 or 2 designation from the Securities Valuation Office. If the Securities Valuation Office does not rate the investment in question but does rate an obligation of the obligor having a priority equal to or lower than the investment in question, the insurer may apply such rating to the investment. If the Securities Valuation Office does not rate the investment in question or an outstanding obligation of the obligor having a priority equal to or lower than the investment in question, the investment shall have a minimum short-term quality rating of P-2 by Moody's Investors Service, Inc., A-2 by Standard and Poor's Corporation, or the corresponding investment grade rating from any nationally recognized statistical rating organization recognized by the Securities Valuation Office. If the obligor of an investment is authorized by, established by, or incorporated under the laws of Canada or any province thereof and the Securities Valuation Office does not rate the investment in question, the minimum quality rating shall be R-2 by the Dominion Bond Rating Service, A-1 by the Canadian Bond Rating Service, or the corresponding rating of any successor organization approved by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 216, &#167; 16. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 