<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id57">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id59" statutenumber="44-5508"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5508</statuteno><catchline id="id62">Surplus lines
licensee; requirements;
duties of licensee; violations; penalty; nonadmitted insurer; requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1) A surplus
lines licensee shall not place coverage with a nonadmitted insurer unless,
at the time of placement, the surplus lines licensee has determined that the
nonadmitted insurer:</para><para>(a) Is authorized to write such insurance in its domiciliary jurisdiction;</para>
<para>(b) Has established
satisfactory evidence of good repute and financial integrity; and</para>
<para>(c)(i) Possesses
capital and surplus or its equivalent under the laws of its domiciliary jurisdiction
that equals the greater of the minimum capital and surplus requirements under
the laws of this state or fifteen million dollars; or</para><para>(ii) If minimum capital
and surplus does not meet the requirements of subdivision (1)(c)(i) of this
section, then upon an affirmative finding of acceptability by the director.
The finding shall be based upon such factors as quality of management, capital
and surplus of any parent company, company underwriting profit and investment
income trends, market availability, and company record and reputation within
the industry. The director shall not make an affirmative finding of acceptability
if the nonadmitted insurer's capital and surplus is less than four million
five hundred thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) No surplus lines licensee shall place
nonadmitted insurance with or procure nonadmitted insurance from a nonadmitted
insurer domiciled outside the United States unless the insurer is listed on
the Quarterly Listing of Alien Insurers maintained by the International Insurers
Department of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners.</para>
<para>(3) Any surplus lines licensee
violating this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(4)(a) No nonadmitted foreign
or alien insurer shall transact business under the Surplus
Lines Insurance Act if it does not comply with the surplus and capital requirements of subsection (1) of
this section.</para>
<para>(b) In addition to the requirements of subdivision (a) of
this subsection, no nonadmitted alien insurer shall transact business under
the act if it does not comply with the requirements of subsection (2) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 154, &#167; 26, p. 410; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3162; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. V, art. III, &#167; 19, p. 589; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7763; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 44-219; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 44-147; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 135, &#167; 2, p. 558; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 757, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 230; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 836, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 92, &#167; 33; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1990, &#167; 44-147; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 978, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB70, &#167; 6.</para></source><annotation><para>The procuring of insurance with nonexistent and spurious fire insurance companies violated this section. Naeve v. Shea, 132 Neb. 787, 273 N.W. 265 (1937).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
