<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5120</statuteno><catchline>Lending of securities.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer may lend its securities if:</para><para>(a) The securities are created or existing under the laws of the United States and, simultaneously with the delivery of the loaned securities, the insurer receives collateral from the borrower consisting of cash or securities backed by the full faith and credit of the United States or an agency or instrumentality of the United States, except that any securities provided as collateral shall not be of lesser quality than the quality of the loaned securities. Any investment made by an insurer with cash received as collateral for loaned securities shall be made in the same kinds, classes, and investment grades as those authorized under the Insurers Investment Act and in a manner that recognizes the liquidity needs of the transaction or is used by the insurer for its general corporate purposes. The securities provided as collateral shall have a market value when the loan is made of at least one hundred two percent of the market value of the loaned securities;</para><para>(b) The securities are created or existing under the laws of Canada or are securities described in section 44-5137 and, simultaneously with the delivery of the loaned securities, the insurer receives collateral from the borrower consisting of cash or securities backed by the full faith and credit of the foreign country, except that any securities provided as collateral shall not be of lesser quality than the quality of the loaned securities. Any investment made by an insurer with cash received as collateral for loaned securities shall be made in the same kinds, classes, and investment grades as those authorized under the Insurers Investment Act and in a manner that recognizes the liquidity needs of the transaction or is used by the insurer for its general corporate purposes. The securities provided as collateral shall have a market value when the loan is made of at least one hundred two percent of the market value of the loaned securities;</para><para>(c) Prior to the loan, the borrower or any indemnifying party furnishes the insurer with or the insurer otherwise obtains the most recent financial statement of the borrower or any indemnifying party;</para><para>(d) The insurer receives a reasonable fee related to the market value of the loaned securities and to the term of the loan;</para><para>(e) The loan is made pursuant to a written loan agreement; and</para><para>(f) The borrower is required to furnish by the close of each business day during the term of the loan a report of the market value of all collateral and the market value of all loaned securities as of the close of trading on the previous business day. If at the close of any business day the market value of the collateral for any loan outstanding to a borrower is less than one hundred percent of the market value of the loaned securities, the borrower shall deliver by the close of the next business day an additional amount of cash or securities. The market value of the additional securities, together with the market value of all previously delivered collateral, shall equal at least one hundred two percent of the market value of the loaned securities for that loan.</para><para>(2) An insurer shall effect securities lending only through the services of a custodian bank or similar entity as approved by the director.</para><para>(3) An insurer's investments authorized under this section shall not exceed twenty percent of its admitted assets.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 216, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB863, &#167; 27. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>