  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5115</statuteno><catchline>Limitation in any one person.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) through (4) of this section, an insurer's investments authorized under the Insurers Investment Act in any one person shall not exceed five percent of the insurer's admitted assets.</para><para>(2) Subsection (1) of this section shall not apply to:</para><para>(a) Investments authorized under sections 44-5123, 44-5125, 44-5142, and 44-5153;</para><para>(b) Investments authorized under sections 44-5124, 44-5126 to 44-5129, and 44-5132 if collateralized by obligations or mortgages for which the full faith and credit of the United States or Canada is pledged for the payment of all principal and interest;</para><para>(c) Loans made pursuant to section 44-5106; and</para><para>(d) Real estate held pursuant to subsection (2) or (3) of section 44-5144.</para><para>(3)(a) An insurer's investments authorized under section 44-5124 or 44-5126 in any one agency or instrumentality of the United States or Canada shall not exceed twenty-five percent of the insurer's admitted assets, and (b) an insurer's investments authorized under section 44-5132 in any one person if collateralized by mortgages for which the full faith and credit of an agency or instrumentality of the United States or Canada is pledged for the payment of all principal and interest shall not exceed twenty-five percent of the insurer's admitted assets. An insurer's investments authorized under section 44-5124 or 44-5126 in any one agency or instrumentality of the United States or Canada and the insurer's investments authorized under section 44-5132 collateralized by mortgages for which the full faith and credit of such agency or instrumentality of the United States or Canada is pledged for the payment of all principal and interest, in the aggregate, shall not exceed twenty-five percent of the insurer's admitted assets.</para><para>(4)(a) An insurer's investments in any one person whose senior obligations have a 3 designation from the Securities Valuation Office, in the aggregate, shall not exceed three percent of the insurer's admitted assets.</para><para>(b) An insurer's investments in any one person whose senior obligations have a 4 designation from the Securities Valuation Office, in the aggregate, shall not exceed two percent of the insurer's admitted assets.</para><para>(c) An insurer's investments in any one person whose senior obligations have a 5 designation from the Securities Valuation Office, in the aggregate, shall not exceed one percent of the insurer's admitted assets.</para><para>(d) An insurer's investments in any one person whose senior obligations have a 6 designation from the Securities Valuation Office, in the aggregate, shall not exceed one-half percent of the insurer's admitted assets.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, person shall mean an individual or entity or group of individuals or entities so related as in fact to constitute a single venture, institution, corporation, association, company, partnership, limited liability company, syndicate, trust, society, or other legal entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 259; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1035, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 