<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5105</statuteno><catchline>Authorization and approval; investment records; board of directors; duties.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer shall not make any investment, sale, loan, or exchange, except loans on its own policies or contracts, unless authorized, approved, or ratified by a majority of the members of the board of directors or by a committee of its members charged by the board of directors or bylaws with the duty of making such investment, sale, loan, or exchange. The board of directors shall further determine by formal resolution at least annually whether all investments have been made in accordance with the delegations, standards, limitations, and investment objectives prescribed by the board of directors or a committee of the board of directors charged with the responsibility to direct its investments.</para><para>(2) The board of directors, after reviewing and assessing the insurer's technical investment and administrative capabilities and expertise, shall adopt a written plan for making investments and for engaging in investment practices. The plan shall specify, unless otherwise authorized by the Director of Insurance, the quality, maturity, and diversification of investments, including investment strategies intended to assure that the investments and investment practices are appropriate for the business conducted by the insurer, its liquidity needs, and its capital and surplus.</para><para>(3) On no less than a quarterly basis, and more often if deemed appropriate, the board of directors or committee of the board of directors shall:</para><para>(a) Receive and review a summary report on the insurer's investment portfolio, investment activities, and investment practices engaged in under delegated authority, in order to determine whether the investment activity of the insurer is consistent with its written plan; and</para><para>(b) Review and revise, as appropriate, the written plan.</para><para>(4) The board of directors shall require that records of authorizations, approvals or other documentation as the board of directors may require, and reports of any action taken under authority delegated under the written plan shall be made available on a regular basis to the board of directors.</para><para>(5) The board of directors shall perform its duties in good faith and with that degree of care that ordinarily prudent individuals in like positions would use under similar circumstances.</para><para>(6) Each insurer shall maintain a record of its investments in a form and manner as prescribed by the Director of Insurance. Such record shall include an indication by the insurer of the provision of law under which an investment is held.</para><para>(7) For purposes of this section, board of directors includes the governing body of an insurer having authority equivalent to that of a board of directors.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 