<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5812"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5812</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of authority; required; application; contents; fee; issuance; director; powers; term; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall act as, offer to act as, or hold himself or herself out to be a third-party administrator in this state without a valid certificate of authority as a third-party administrator issued by the director.</para><para>(2) An applicant for a certificate of authority as a third-party administrator shall make application to the director upon a form to be furnished by the director. The application shall include or be accompanied by an application fee of two hundred dollars and by the following information and documents:</para><para>(a) All basic organizational documents of the applicant, including any articles of incorporation, articles of association, articles of organization, partnership agreement, trade name certificate, trust agreement, shareholder agreement, and other applicable documents and all amendments to such documents;</para><para>(b) The bylaws, rules, regulations, or similar documents regulating the internal affairs of the applicant;</para><para>(c) The names, addresses, official positions, and professional qualifications of the individuals who are responsible for the conduct of affairs of the applicant, including all members of the board of directors, board of trustees, executive committee, or other governing board or committee, the principal officers in the case of a corporation or the partners or members in the case of a partnership, limited liability company, or association, shareholders holding directly or indirectly ten percent or more of the voting securities of the applicant, and any other person who exercises control or influence over the affairs of the applicant;</para><para>(d) Annual financial statements or reports for the two most recent years which prove that the applicant is solvent and such information as the director may require in order to review the current financial condition of the applicant;</para><para>(e) A statement describing the business plan including information on staffing levels and activities proposed in this state and nationwide. The business plan shall provide details setting forth the applicant's capability for providing a sufficient number of experienced and qualified personnel in the areas of claims processing, record keeping, and underwriting;</para><para>(f) If the applicant will be managing the solicitation of new or renewal business, proof that it employs or has contracted with an agent licensed in this state for solicitation and taking of applications. Any applicant which intends to directly solicit insurance contracts or to otherwise act as an insurance agent shall provide proof that it has a license as an insurance agent in this state; and</para><para>(g) Such other pertinent information as may be required by the director.</para><para>(3) The applicant shall make available for inspection by the director copies of all written agreements with insurers and contracts with other persons utilizing the services of the applicant.</para><para>(4) The director may refuse to issue a certificate of authority as a third-party administrator if the director determines that the applicant or any individual responsible for the conduct of affairs of the applicant as described in subdivision (2)(c) of this section is not competent, trustworthy, financially responsible, or of good personal and business reputation or has had an insurance license or certificate of authority or a third-party administrator license or certificate of authority denied or revoked for cause by any state.</para><para>(5) A certificate of authority as a third-party administrator issued under this section shall remain valid, unless surrendered to or suspended or revoked by the director, for so long as the third-party administrator continues in business in this state and remains in compliance with the Third-Party Administrator Act.</para><para>(6) A third-party administrator shall not be required to hold a certificate of authority as a third-party administrator in this state if all of the following conditions are met:</para><para>(a) The third-party administrator has its principal place of business in another state;</para><para>(b) The third-party administrator is not soliciting business as a third-party administrator in this state; and</para><para>(c) In the case of any group policy, group contract, or plan of insurance serviced by the third-party administrator, the lesser of five percent or one hundred certificate holders or subscribers reside in this state.</para><para>(7) A person shall not be required to hold a certificate of authority as a third-party administrator in this state if the person exclusively provides services to one or more bona fide employee benefit plans each of which is established by an employer or an employee organization, or both, and for which the insurance laws of this state are preempted pursuant to the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974. Such person shall register with the director annually and verify his or her status as described in this section.</para><para>(8) A third-party administrator shall immediately notify the director of any material change in its ownership or control or other fact or circumstance affecting its qualification for a certificate of authority as a third-party administrator in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1006, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 262; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 114. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 