<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5242"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5242</statuteno><catchline>Health benefit plan, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Health benefit plan shall mean any hospital or medical policy or certificate, major medical expense insurance, or health maintenance organization subscriber contract.</para><para>(2) Health benefit plan shall not include one or more, or any combination, of the following:</para><para>(a) Coverage only for accident or disability income insurance, or any combination thereof;</para><para>(b) Coverage issued as a supplement to liability insurance;</para><para>(c) Liability insurance, including general liability insurance and automobile liability insurance;</para><para>(d) Workers' compensation or similar insurance;</para><para>(e) Automobile medical payment insurance;</para><para>(f) Credit-only insurance;</para><para>(g) Coverage for onsite medical clinics; and</para><para>(h) Other similar insurance coverage, specified in federal regulations, under which benefits for medical care are secondary or incidental to other insurance benefits.</para><para>(3) Health benefit plan shall not include the following benefits if they are provided under a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance or are otherwise not an integral part of the plan:</para><para>(a) Limited-scope dental or vision benefits;</para><para>(b) Benefits for long-term care, nursing home care, home health care, community-based care, or any combination thereof; and</para><para>(c) Such other similar, limited benefits as are specified in federal regulations.</para><para>(4) Health benefit plan shall not include the following benefits if the benefits are provided under a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance, there is no coordination between the provision of the benefits and any exclusion of benefits under any group health benefit plan maintained by the same plan sponsor, and such benefits are paid with respect to an event without regard to whether benefits are provided with respect to such an event under any group health plan maintained by the same plan sponsor:</para><para>(a) Coverage only for a specified disease or illness; and</para><para>(b) Hospital indemnity or other fixed indemnity insurance.</para><para>(5) Health benefit plan shall not include the following if it is offered as a separate policy, certificate, or contract of insurance:</para><para>(a) Medicare supplemental health insurance as defined under section 1882(g)(1) of the Social Security Act;</para><para>(b) Coverage supplemental to the coverage provided under 10 U.S.C. chapter 55, as such chapter existed on January 1, 2003; and</para><para>(c) Similar supplemental coverage provided to coverage under a group health plan.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1222, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 862, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 6, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 