<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-5137"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-5137</statuteno><catchline>Foreign securities.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer may invest in securities or other investments (a) issued in, (b) located in, (c) denominated in the currency of, (d) whose ultimate payment amounts of principal or interest are subject to fluctuations in the currency of, or (e) whose obligors are domiciled in countries other than the United States or Canada, which are substantially of the same kinds and classes as those authorized for investment under the Insurers Investment Act.</para><para>(2) Subject to the limitations in subsection (3) of this section:</para><para>(a) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section in any one foreign jurisdiction whose sovereign debt has a 1 designation from the Securities Valuation Office shall not exceed ten percent of the insurer's admitted assets;</para><para>(b) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section in any one foreign jurisdiction whose sovereign debt has a 2 or 3 designation from the Securities Valuation Office shall not exceed five percent of the insurer's admitted assets;</para><para>(c) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section in any one foreign jurisdiction whose sovereign debt has a 4, 5, or 6 designation from the Securities Valuation Office shall not exceed three percent of the insurer's admitted assets;</para><para>(d) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section denominated in any one foreign currency shall not exceed two percent of the insurer's admitted assets;</para><para>(e) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section denominated in foreign currencies, in the aggregate, shall not exceed five percent of the insurer's admitted assets; and </para><para>(f) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section shall not be considered denominated in a foreign currency if the acquiring insurer enters into one or more contracts in transactions permitted under section 44-5149 to exchange all payments made on the foreign currency denominated investments for United States currency at a rate which effectively insulates the investment cash flows against future changes in currency exchange rates during the period the contract or contracts are in effect.</para><para>(3) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (1) of this section shall not exceed, in the aggregate, twenty percent of its admitted assets.</para><para>(4) An insurer which is authorized to do business in a foreign country or which has outstanding insurance, annuity, or reinsurance contracts on lives or risks resident or located in a foreign country may, in addition to the investments authorized by subsection (1) of this section, invest in securities and investments (a) issued in, (b) located in, (c) denominated in the currency of, (d) whose ultimate payment amounts of principal and interest are subject to fluctuations in the currency of, or (e) whose obligors are domiciled in such foreign countries, which are substantially of the same kinds and classes as those authorized for investment under the act.</para><para>(5) An insurer's investments authorized under subsection (4) of this section and cash in the currency of such country which is at any time held by such insurer, in the aggregate, shall not exceed the greater of (a) one and one-half times the amount of its reserves and other obligations under such contracts or (b) the amount which such insurer is required by law to invest in such country.</para><para>(6) Any investment in debt obligations authorized under this section shall have a minimum quality rating as described in subdivision (2) of section 44-5112.</para><para>(7) An insurer's investments made under this section shall be aggregated with investments of the same kinds and classes made under the Insurers Investment Act except section 44-5153 for purposes of determining compliance with the limitations contained in other sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 273, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 16.</para></source></law></legaldoc>