<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-6125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-6125</statuteno><catchline>Domestic mutual insurer; foreign insurer; transfer domicile; reorganization authorized; effect; holding company; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) A domestic mutual insurer, upon approval of the director, may reorganize (a) by forming a mutual insurance holding company, (b) by merging its policyholders' membership interests into the mutual insurance holding company, and (c) by continuing the mutual insurer's corporate existence as a stock insurer subsidiary of the mutual insurance holding company.</para><para>(2) A domestic mutual insurer, upon the approval of the director, may reorganize by merging its policyholders' membership interests into an existing mutual insurance holding company formed under subsection (1) of this section and by continuing the mutual insurer's corporate existence as a stock insurer subsidiary of the mutual insurance holding company.</para><para>(3) All of the initial shares of the capital stock of a reorganized stock insurer which has reorganized as described in subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall be issued to the mutual insurance holding company or to one or more intermediate stock holding companies.</para><para>(4) Policyholders of a domestic mutual insurer which has reorganized as described in subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall be members of the mutual insurance holding company and their voting rights shall be determined in accordance with the articles of incorporation and bylaws of the mutual insurance holding company. The mutual insurance holding company shall provide its members with the same membership rights as were provided to policyholders of the mutual insurer immediately prior to reorganization. The reorganization shall not reduce, limit, or affect the number or identity of the policyholders who may become members of the mutual insurance holding company or secure for individuals comprising management any unfair advantage through or connected with the reorganization.</para><para>(5) If an insurer which is organized under the laws of another state transfers its domicile to this state in accordance with section 44-161 and is a direct or indirect subsidiary of a mutual insurance holding company organized under the laws of such other state, then, in connection with the transfer of the domicile of such insurer, upon approval of the director of a plan of merger and transfer, the foreign mutual insurance holding company may form a mutual insurance holding company under this section, and the foreign mutual insurance holding company may merge into such domestic mutual insurance holding company simultaneously with the transfer of domicile of the insurer to this state. Until the merger takes effect, the foreign mutual insurance holding company shall be the sole member of the domestic mutual insurance holding company. When the merger takes effect, the separate existence of the foreign mutual insurance holding company shall cease, the domestic mutual insurance holding company shall survive and have all the assets and liabilities formerly held by the foreign mutual insurance holding company, all of the members of the foreign mutual insurance holding company shall become members of the domestic mutual insurance holding company, policyholders of the insurer shall be members of the domestic mutual insurance holding company, and their voting rights shall be determined in accordance with the articles of incorporation and bylaws of the domestic mutual insurance holding company. After the transfer and merger take effect, for purposes of the Mutual Insurance Holding Company Act, the insurer shall be deemed to be a reorganized stock insurer. If the foreign mutual insurance holding company owns a majority of the voting stock of a stock holding company organized under the laws of another state that in turn owns all of the voting stock of the insurer, then the plan of merger and transfer may provide that the stock holding company shall continue as a corporation organized under the laws of the other state.</para><para>(6)(a) A mutual insurance holding company or any intermediate stock holding company formed under the Mutual Insurance Holding Company Act shall not be authorized to transact the business of insurance.</para><para>(b) A mutual insurance holding company formed under the act shall not issue stock.</para><para>(c) The director shall have jurisdiction over a mutual insurance holding company and any intermediate stock holding company to ensure that policyholder interests are protected.</para><para>(d) A mutual insurance holding company and any intermediate stock holding company shall be treated as domestic insurers subject to the Insurers Demutualization Act, the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act, Chapter 44, article 2, and section 44-301, except that a foreign intermediate stock holding company shall not be subject to Chapter 44, article 2, and section 44-301.</para><para>(e) Except with the approval of the director, the aggregate pledges and encumbrances of a mutual insurance holding company's assets shall not affect more than forty-nine percent of the mutual insurance holding company's stock in an intermediate stock holding company or a reorganized stock insurer.</para><para>(f) At least fifty percent of the net worth of a mutual insurance holding company, as determined by generally accepted accounting practices, shall be invested in insurers or any other subsidiaries or investments authorized by the Insurance Holding Company System Act.</para><para>(g) If any proceeding under the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act is brought against a reorganized stock insurer, the mutual insurance holding company and intermediate stock holding company shall become parties to the proceedings. All of the assets of the mutual insurance holding company are deemed assets of the estate of the reorganized stock insurer to the extent necessary to satisfy policy claims against the reorganized stock insurer.</para><para>(h) No distribution to members of a mutual insurance holding company may occur without prior written approval of the director and only upon the director's satisfaction that such distribution is fair and equitable to policyholders as members of the mutual insurance holding company.</para><para>(i) No solicitation for the sale of the stock of an intermediate stock holding company or a reorganized stock insurer may be made without the director's prior written approval.</para><para>(j) A mutual insurance holding company or an intermediate stock holding company shall not voluntarily dissolve without the approval of the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 740, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1047, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 23. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurance Holding Company System Act,</emphasis> see section 44-2120.</para><para><emphasis>Insurers Demutualization Act,</emphasis> see section 44-6101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4862.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>