<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-6207"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-6207</statuteno><catchline>Policyholder rights.</catchline><para>(1) Every policyholder shall have the right to reject the transfer and novation of his or her contracts of insurance. Policyholders electing to reject the assumption transaction shall return to the transferring insurer the preaddressed, postage-paid response card or other written notice and indicate thereon that the assumption is rejected.</para><para>(2) Payment of the next premium after notice is received to the assuming insurer shall be deemed to indicate the policyholder's acceptance of the transfer to the assuming insurer and a novation shall be deemed to have been effected if the premium notice clearly states that payment of the premium to the assuming insurer shall constitute acceptance of the transfer. Such a premium notice shall also provide a method for the policyholder to pay the premium while reserving the right to reject the transfer.</para><para>(3) After no fewer than twelve months after the mailing of the initial notice of transfer required under section 44-6205, if positive acceptance to the transfer and assumption has not been received or acceptance has not been deemed to have occurred under subsection (2) of this section, the transferring insurer shall send to the policyholder a second and final notice of transfer. If the policyholder does not reject the transfer during the two-month period immediately following the date on which the transferring insurer mails the second and final notice of transfer, the policyholder's acceptance will be deemed to have occurred and novation of the contract of insurance will be effected.</para><para>(4) The transferring insurer will be deemed to have received the response card on the date it is postmarked. A policyholder may also send a response card by facsimile or other electronic transmission or by registered mail, express delivery, or courier service, in which case the response card shall be deemed to have been received by the assuming insurer on the date of actual receipt by the transferring insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 68. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 