<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id654"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-6144"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>44-6144</statuteno><catchline>Notice of annual meeting, requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A mutual insurance holding company shall provide notice of its annual meeting to its members as provided by the company's bylaws or, if the bylaws are silent, in a manner that is reasonable. Electronic notice, either by direct electronic transmission, publication on a designated website, or comparable technology, is reasonable if:</para><para>(a) For notice by direct electronic transmission, the notice is sent to an electronic address or account that the member has designated for receipt of notices or to an electronic address the company reasonably believes will reach the recipient; or</para><para>(b) For notice published on a designated website, the company has previously informed its members of the time, location, and procedure for accessing notices published on a designated website.</para><para>(2) The notice described in subsection (1) of this section shall include all information otherwise required by law, including instructions for accessing meeting materials and for voting or participating in the meeting if electronic participation or voting is permitted.</para><para>(3) Notice shall be effective on the date that such notice is sent, or if published on a designated website, on the date the notice is published. The company shall demonstrate delivery to the electronic address or account or publication on a designated website, by contemporaneous logs, delivery receipts, or portal access records.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section precludes a company from using electronic means or publication on its website to provide meeting materials, proxies, ballots, or other member communications if the company complies with the requirements of this section.</para><para>(5) After receipt of notice, a member may contact the company to request that printed meeting materials be sent via United States mail at no cost to the member.</para><para>(6) A mutual insurance holding company may also provide notice of an annual meeting to members as part of policy language, a policy endorsement, a rider, or an amendment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB967, &#167; 9. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>