<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-6129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-6129</statuteno><catchline>Plan of reorganization; policyholders vote.</catchline><para>(1) Within forty-five days after the date of the director's approval of a plan of reorganization pursuant to section 44-6128, unless extended by the director for good cause, the mutual insurer shall hold a meeting of its policyholders at a reasonable time and place to vote upon the plan of reorganization. The mutual insurer shall give notice at least thirty days before the time fixed for the meeting, by first-class mail to the last-known address of each policyholder, that the plan of reorganization will be voted upon at a regular or special meeting of the policyholders. The notice shall include a brief description of the plan of reorganization and a statement that the director has approved the plan of reorganization. The notice to each policyholder shall also include a written proxy permitting the policyholder to vote for or against the plan of reorganization. The entity to which any group insurance policy is issued, and not any person covered under the group insurance policy, shall be considered the policyholder for purposes of voting. A plan of reorganization shall be approved only if not less than two-thirds of the policyholders voting in person or by proxy at the meeting vote in favor of such plan of reorganization. Each policyholder shall be entitled to only one vote regardless of the number of policies owned by the policyholder. The director shall supervise and direct the conduct of the vote on the plan of reorganization as necessary to ensure that the vote is fair and consistent with the requirements of this section.</para><para>(2) If a mutual insurer complies substantially and in good faith with the notice requirements of this section, the mutual insurer's failure to give any policyholder any required notice does not impair the validity of any action taken under this section.</para><para>(3) If the meeting of policyholders to vote upon the plan of reorganization is held coincident with the mutual insurer's annual meeting of the policyholders, only one combined notice of meeting is required.</para><para>(4) The form of any proxy shall be filed with and approved by the director.</para><para>(5) For purposes of voting, policyholders means the policyholders of the mutual insurer on the day the plan of reorganization is initially approved by the board of directors of the mutual insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 740, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 