<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-6143"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-6143</statuteno><catchline>Expansion of business; activities authorized; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A mutual insurance holding company or an intermediate stock holding company may engage in actions and activities related to expanding the business of any company into other insurance, insurance-related, and financial services businesses. Any such expansion may be accomplished through acquisition, merger, consolidation, strategic alliance, joint venture, or other business combination. A mutual insurance holding company may:</para><para>(a) Merge or consolidate with, or acquire the assets of, a mutual insurance holding company formed under the laws of the State of Nebraska or any similar entity or organization formed under the laws of any other state;</para><para>(b) Either alone or together with one or more intermediate stock holding companies, or other subsidiaries, directly or indirectly acquire the stock of a stock insurance company or a mutual insurance company that reorganizes as a mutual insurance holding company under the laws of the State of Nebraska or the laws of its state of organization;</para><para>(c) Together with one or more of its stock insurance company subsidiaries, acquire the assets of a stock insurance company or a mutual insurance company;</para><para>(d) Acquire a stock insurance company through the merger of such stock insurance subsidiary with a stock insurance company or intermediate stock insurance company subsidiary of the mutual insurance holding company; or</para><para>(e) Acquire the stock or assets of any other person to the same extent as would be permitted for a mutual insurance company.</para><para>(2) A plan and agreement for merger or consolidation in accordance with subsection (1) of this section shall be submitted to and approved by two-thirds of the members of each domestic mutual insurance holding company or mutual insurance company involved in the merger or consolidation who vote either in person or by proxy thereon at meetings called for such purposes pursuant to such reasonable notice and procedure as has been approved by the director.</para><para>(3) No such merger or consolidation shall be effectuated unless in advance thereof the plan and agreement therefor have been filed with the director and approved by the director.</para><para>(4) All of the initial shares of the capital stock of the reorganized stock insurer shall be issued either to the mutual insurance holding company or to an intermediate stock holding company that is a subsidiary of the mutual insurance holding company. The membership interests of the policyholders of the reorganized stock insurer shall become membership interests in the mutual insurance holding company in accordance with the plan and agreement of merger or consolidation. Policyholders of the reorganized stock insurer shall be members of the mutual insurance holding company in accordance with the plan and agreement of merger or consolidation and the articles of incorporation and bylaws of the mutual insurance holding company. The mutual insurance holding company shall at all times directly or indirectly own a majority of the voting shares of the capital stock of any reorganized stock insurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 24. </para></source></law></legaldoc>