<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-6019"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-6019</statuteno><catchline>Mandatory control level event.</catchline><para>(1) Mandatory control level event means any of the following events:</para><para>(a) The filing of a risk-based capital report which indicates that the insurer's or health organization's total adjusted capital is less than its mandatory control level risk-based capital;</para><para>(b) The notification by the director to the insurer or health organization of an adjusted risk-based capital report that indicates the event described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section unless the insurer or health organization challenges the adjusted risk-based capital report under section 44-6020; or</para><para>(c) If, pursuant to section 44-6020, the insurer or health organization challenges an adjusted risk-based capital report that indicates the event described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section, the notification by the director to the insurer or health organization that the director has, after a hearing, rejected the insurer's or health organization's challenge.</para><para>(2) In the event of a mandatory control level event, the director shall take such actions as are necessary to place the insurer or health organization under regulatory control under the Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act or, in the case of a property and casualty insurer which is writing no business and which is running off its existing business, may allow the insurer to continue its run-off under the supervision of the director. In the event the director takes such actions, the mandatory control level event shall be deemed sufficient grounds for the director to take action under the act, and the director shall have the rights, powers, and duties with respect to the insurer or health organization as are set forth in the act. In the event the director takes actions under this subsection pursuant to an adjusted risk-based capital report, the insurer or health organization shall be entitled to such protections as are afforded to insurers or health organizations under the provisions of the act pertaining to summary proceedings. Notwithstanding the provisions of this subsection, the director may forego action for up to ninety days after the mandatory control level event if he or she finds there is a reasonable expectation that the mandatory control level event may be eliminated within the ninety-day period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 583, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 978, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 258, &#167; 24. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4862.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 