<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7527"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7527</statuteno><catchline>Statistical data; collection and exchange; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to assure that the experience of all insurers is provided to the director at least annually in such form and detail as is necessary to aid in effecting the purposes of the Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act. The director may designate one or more statistical agents to assist in gathering such experience and making compilations thereof. The scope of such rules and regulations may include the data which must be reported by insurers, definitions of data elements, the timing and frequency of statistical reporting by insurers, data quality standards, data edit and audit requirements, data retention requirements, reports to be generated by statistical agents to fulfill the requirements of this section, and the timing of such reports.</para><para>(2) Should the director choose to designate more than one statistical agent to assist for a line or type of insurance, the director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to ensure that statistical data that the director has required is combined for reports to the director.</para><para>(3) The following provisions apply only to the disclosure of data and reports provided to the director pursuant to this section and to the disclosure of reports produced by the director from data and reports provided pursuant to this section:</para><para>(a) The director shall not disclose data that identifies individual insurers;</para><para>(b) The director shall not disclose data that is likely to identify individual policyholders or claimants or when there is reason to suspect that individual open claim reserves may be identified with individual policyholders or claimants;</para><para>(c) The director may agree in advance to withhold data from public disclosure when confidentiality is requested by the statistical agent providing the data to the director, but only if the data include data elements that the director had not required, prior to their writing or occurrence, to be recorded by insurers; and</para><para>(d) All other data contained in reports made pursuant to this section shall be subject to public disclosure.</para><para>(4) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the interchange of data necessary for the application of rating plans.</para><para>(5) In order to further uniform administration of rate regulatory laws, the director and every insurer and advisory organization may exchange information and experience data with insurance supervisory officials, insurers, and advisory organizations in other states and may consult with them with respect to the application of rating systems.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 