<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7008"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7008</statuteno><catchline>Health care professional's right to review credentialing verification information.</catchline><para>(1) A health carrier shall provide a health care professional the opportunity to review and correct information submitted in support of that health care professional's credentialing verification application as set forth below.</para><para>(2)(a) Each health care professional who is subject to the credentialing verification process shall have the right to review all information, including the source of that information, obtained by the health carrier to satisfy the requirements of the Health Care Professional Credentialing Verification Act during the health carrier's credentialing process.</para><para>(b) A health carrier shall notify a health care professional of any information obtained during the health carrier's credentialing verification process that does not meet the health carrier's credentialing verification standards or that varies substantially from the information provided to the health carrier by the health care professional, except that the health carrier shall not be required to reveal the source of information if the information is not obtained to meet the requirements of the act or if disclosure is prohibited by law.</para><para>(c) A health care professional shall have the right to correct any erroneous information. A health carrier shall have a formal process by which a health care professional may submit supplemental or corrected information to the health carrier's credentialing verification committee and request a reconsideration of the health care professional's credentialing verification application if the health care professional feels that the health carrier's credentialing verification committee has received information that is incorrect or misleading. Supplemental information shall be subject to confirmation by the health carrier.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1162, &#167; 33. </para></source></law></legaldoc>