<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7511"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7511</statuteno><catchline>Rating systems; filing requirements for lines subject to prior approval; hearings.</catchline><para>(1) Each insurer to which this section applies as provided in section 44-7506 shall file with the director every rating system and every modification of such rating system that it proposes to use. No insurer shall issue a contract or policy except in accordance with the filings that are in effect for such insurer as provided in the Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act, except:</para><para>(a) As provided in subsections (6) and (7) of this section;</para><para>(b) As provided by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 44-7515; or</para><para>(c) For types of inland marine risks that have, by custom of the industry, not been written according to manual rates or rating plans. For types of inland marine risks for which the custom of the industry has not been established, the director shall consider the similarity of the new insurance to existing types of insurance and classes of risk and whether it would be reasonably practical to create and file rating systems prior to use.</para><para>(2) Every filing shall state its proposed effective date, which shall not be prior to the date that the director receives the filing. Instead of a specific date, a filing may indicate that it will be effective a reasonable specified period of time after approval or that the insurer will notify the director of the effective date within ninety days after approval.</para><para>(3) Every filing shall provide an objective description of the risks and the coverages to which the rating system will apply. If the insurer has another rating system on file or pending that applies to some or all of these same risks, the filing shall disclose this and shall objectively identify those risks to which each rating system will apply. Filings shall include a list of manual pages and other rating system elements that will be replaced when the approval of a filing will result in the replacement or alteration of previously approved rating systems. In addition, insurers shall maintain listings of manual pages and other rating system elements that have been approved by the director so that such listings can be provided upon request.</para><para>(4) Each insurer shall file or incorporate by reference to material filed with the director all supporting information relating to a rating system. If a filing is not accompanied by such information or if additional information is required to complete review of the filing, the director may require the filer to furnish the information, and in that event the review period in subsection (10) of this section shall commence on the date such information is received by the director. If a filer fails to furnish the required information within ninety days, the director may, by written notice sent to the insurer, deem the filing as withdrawn and not available for use.</para><para>(5) An insurer may authorize the director to accept rating system filings and prospective loss cost filings made on its behalf by an advisory organization. The insurer shall file additional information as is necessary to complete its rating systems on file with the director.</para><para>(6)(a) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (6)(b) of this section for medical professional liability insurance, a rate or premium in excess of that provided by a filing otherwise applicable may be used on any specific risk upon the prior written application of the insured that describes the insured's unusual or extrahazardous exposures that are not otherwise contemplated by the rates on file for that class of risk, filed with and approved by the director.</para><para>(b) For medical professional liability insurance, a rate or premium in excess of that provided by a filing otherwise applicable may be used for any specific medical professional upon the prior written consent of the medical professional that describes its unusual or extrahazardous exposures that are not otherwise contemplated by the rates on file for that medical professional's rate classification. Such signed consent shall be filed with the director no later than thirty days after the effective date of the insurance to which it applies. The director shall monitor such rate applications to assure compliance with this subdivision. The director may, after a hearing, require by order that such applications for an insurer that has demonstrated a pattern of using this rating device for medical professionals that do not possess unusual or extrahazardous exposures, or that otherwise fails to comply with this subdivision, shall be subject to prior approval pursuant to subdivision (6)(a) of this section. Upon application by an insurer affected by such order, demonstrating that its filings made subsequent to the order have been in compliance with this subdivision, the director shall vacate such order. The director shall consider any such application within thirty days after its receipt for any order that has been in effect for more than nine months since its inception or since it was last reviewed by the director pursuant to an application by the insurer.</para><para>(7) The director may by rules and regulations or by order suspend or modify the filing requirements of this section as to any type of insurance or class of risk for which rating systems cannot practicably be filed before they are used. In making this finding, the director shall ascertain whether a system of rating classifications and exposure bases that would equitably reflect the differences in expense requirements and expected losses between individual risks has been developed or appears reasonably capable of being developed. The director may examine insurers as is necessary to ascertain whether any rating systems affected by such rules and regulations meet the standards contained in this section.</para><para>(8) No filing or any supporting information provided by an insurer pursuant to this section shall be open to public inspection pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09 before the approval or disapproval of the filing unless publicly disclosed in an open court, open administrative proceeding, or open meeting or disclosed by the director pursuant to statute. Correspondence specifically relating to individual risks shall be confidential and may not be made public by the director except as may be compiled in summaries of such activity.</para><para>(9) The director shall review filings as soon as reasonably possible after they have been made. The director shall disapprove a filing if:</para><para>(a) The filing fails to meet the standards contained in section 44-7510;</para><para>(b) The insurer has more than one rating system applicable to the line or type of insurance and the insurer fails to specify objective differences between risks to determine the risks and the coverages to which the rating system will apply;</para><para>(c) The filing proposes to discriminate between risks based on optional commission differences for agents; or</para><para>(d) The filing discriminates between risks based on subjective factors, except that (i) an experience rating plan may use loss reserves without being considered as subjective and (ii) a fire insurance rating plan applying to commercial risks filed for the sole use by an advisory organization may be approved even though it contains subjective rating factors.</para><para>(10) Within thirty days after receipt, the director shall approve a filing that meets the requirements of the act, except that this review period may be extended for an additional period not to exceed thirty days if the director gives written notice within the original review period to the insurer or advisory organization. A filing shall be deemed to meet the requirements of the act unless disapproved by the director within the review period or any extension thereof.</para><para>(11) If, within the review period provided by subsection (10) of this section or any extension thereof, the director finds that a filing does not meet the requirements of the act, a written disapproval notice shall be sent to the insurer. Such notice shall specify in what respects the filing fails to meet these requirements and state that such filing shall not become effective.</para><para>(12) Filings shall become effective on their proposed effective date if approved or deemed approved on or before that date. Filings approved or deemed approved after their proposed effective dates shall become effective after notification by the insurer of a revised effective date, which shall not be prior to the date that the insurer mails the notification to the director. If an insurer fails to furnish a revised effective date within a reasonable period of time not less than ninety days, the director may, by written notice sent to the insurer, deem the filing as withdrawn and not available for use.</para><para>(13) An insurer or advisory organization whose filing is disapproved may, within thirty days after receipt of a disapproval notice, request a hearing in accordance with section 44-7532.</para><para>(14) If, at any time after approval, the director finds that a rating system or modification thereof does not meet or no longer meets the requirements of the act, the director shall hold a hearing in accordance with section 44-7532.</para><para>(15) Any insured aggrieved with respect to any filing may make written application to the director for a hearing on such filing. The hearing application shall specify the grounds to be relied upon by the applicant. If the director finds that the hearing application is made in good faith, that a remedy would be available if the grounds are established, or that such grounds otherwise justify holding a hearing, the director shall hold a hearing in accordance with section 44-7532.</para><para>(16) If, after a hearing initiated pursuant to subsection (14) or (15) of this section, the director finds that a filing does not meet the requirements of the act, the director shall issue an order stating in what respects such filing fails to meet the requirements and when, within a reasonable period thereafter, such rating system or aspect of a rating system shall no longer be used. Copies of the order shall be sent to the applicant, if applicable, and to every affected insurer and advisory organization. The order shall not affect any contract or policy made or issued prior to the expiration of the period set forth in the order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 29. </para></source></law></legaldoc>