<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7605"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7605</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of registration; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A multiple employer welfare arrangement seeking to offer a health benefit plan that is not fully insured shall apply for a certificate of registration in a form prescribed by the director. The application shall be completed and submitted to the director together with a one-thousand-dollar fee and the following:</para><para>(a) Copies of all articles, bylaws, agreements, and other documents or instruments describing the organizational structure of the applicant;</para><para>(b) Copies of all materials and documents describing the rights and obligations of participating employers and covered employees with respect to the applicant;</para><para>(c) A copy of the trust agreement of the applicant;</para><para>(d) A copy of the unaudited financial statement required by section 44-7613;</para><para>(e) A statement showing in full detail the plan for offering a health benefit plan by the applicant;</para><para>(f) Copies of all contracts and other instruments proposed to be made, offered, or sold by the applicant to its participating employers, together with a copy of its summary plan description and the proposed advertising matter to be used in the solicitation of participating employers;</para><para>(g) A copy of the contract with the third-party administrator retained, if any, to administer the health benefit plan;</para><para>(h) A copy of the stop-loss insurance policy required by section 44-7609; and</para><para>(i) Any other reasonable information requested by the director.</para><para>(2) The director shall deny a certificate of registration if the applicant does not meet the requirements of the Multiple Employer Welfare Arrangement Act. Notice of denial shall be in writing and shall set forth the basis for the denial. If the applicant submits a written request for reconsideration within thirty days after the notice was sent by the director, the director shall conduct a hearing on the denial pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 