<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7505"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7505</statuteno><catchline>Applicability of act.</catchline><para>(1) The Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act applies to any insurer holding a certificate of authority issued by the director to transact insurance business in this state for the lines of insurance specified in subdivisions (5) through (14) and (16) through (20) of section 44-201 and to any combination of any of the foregoing on risks or operations in this state.</para><para>(2) The act does not apply to:</para><para>(a) Reinsurance, except as provided in section 44-7525 for joint reinsurance pools;</para><para>(b) Ocean marine insurance;</para><para>(c) Rating systems for insurance against loss or damage to aircraft or against liability, other than workers' compensation and employers liability, arising out of the ownership, maintenance, or use of aircraft;</para><para>(d) Rating systems or policy forms used by insurers to provide warranties or service contracts, or rating systems or policy forms used by insurers to provide coverage for the risk assumed by businesses that provide warranties or service contracts for their customers;</para><para>(e) Rating systems or policy forms for financial guaranty insurance as defined in subdivision (19) of section 44-201, except that the act applies to financial guaranty coverage for loss of value for motor vehicles leased or sold on credit to private parties;</para><para>(f) Rating systems for the lines of insurance specified in subdivisions (5), (7), and (18) of section 44-201 for insurance written by domestic assessment associations doing business under Chapter 44, article 8; and</para><para>(g) Policy forms or rates for contracts of suretyship, except that policy forms and prospective loss costs developed or filed by advisory organizations are subject to the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 49. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 