<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7903</statuteno><catchline>Statement of Actuarial Opinion; supporting documents; disclosure allowed; when.</catchline><para>(1) The Statement of Actuarial Opinion shall be provided with the annual statement in accordance with the appropriate National Association of Insurance Commissioners Property and Casualty Annual Statement Instructions and shall be a public document.</para><para>(2)(a) Documents, materials, or other information in the possession or control of the Department of Insurance that are considered an actuarial report, workpapers, or actuarial opinion summary provided in support of the opinion, and any other material provided by the company to the Director of Insurance in connection with the actuarial report, workpapers, or actuarial opinion summary, shall be confidential by law and privileged, shall not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, shall not be subject to subpoena, and shall not be subject to discovery or admissible in evidence in any private civil action.</para><para>(b) This section shall not be construed to limit the director's authority to release the documents to the Actuarial Board for Counseling and Discipline if the material is required for the purpose of professional disciplinary proceedings and that the Actuarial Board for Counseling and Discipline establishes procedures satisfactory to the director for preserving the confidentiality of the documents, nor shall this section be construed to limit the director's authority to use the documents, materials or other information in furtherance of any regulatory or legal action brought as part of the director's official duties.</para><para>(3) Neither the director nor any person who received documents, materials, or other information while acting under the authority of the director shall be permitted or required to testify in any private civil action concerning any confidential documents, materials, or information subject to subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) The director:</para><para>(a) May share documents, materials, or other information, including the confidential and privileged documents, materials, or information subject to subsection (2) of this section with other state, federal, and international regulatory agencies, with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries, and with state, federal, and international law enforcement authorities, if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality and privileged status of the document, material, or other information and has the legal authority to maintain confidentiality; and</para><para>(b) May receive documents, materials, or information, including otherwise confidential and privileged documents, materials, or information from other state, federal, foreign, or international regulatory and law enforcement agencies and from the National Association of Insurance Commissioners and its affiliates and subsidiaries. The director shall maintain information received pursuant to this subdivision as confidential or privileged if received with notice or the understanding that it is confidential or privileged under the laws of the jurisdiction that is the source of the information. Such information shall not be a public record subject to disclosure by the director pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, subject to subpoena, subject to discovery, or admissible in evidence in any private civil action, except that the director may use such information in any regulatory or legal action brought by the director. The director, and any other person while acting under the authority of the director who has received information pursuant to this subdivision, may not, and shall not be required to, testify in any private civil action concerning any information subject to this section. Nothing in this section shall constitute a waiver of any applicable privilege or claim of confidentiality in the information received pursuant to this subdivision as a result of information sharing authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 41. </para></source></law></legaldoc>