  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7519"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7519</statuteno><catchline>Insurers, advisory organizations, and statistical agents; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) No insurer, advisory organization, or statistical agent shall attempt to monopolize or combine or conspire with any other person to monopolize an insurance market or to engage in a boycott, on a concerted basis, of an insurance market.</para><para>(2) No insurer shall agree with any other insurer or with any advisory organization or statistical agent to require adherence to or to require use of any aspect of any rating system, form, prospective loss cost, dividend payment practice, underwriting rule or practice, survey, inspection, or similar material except as required by section 44-7524 or as is necessary to develop statistical plans. This subsection shall not apply to agreements between insurers under the same ownership.</para><para>(3) No advisory organization or statistical agent shall agree with any insurer or with another advisory organization or statistical agent to require adherence to or to require use of any aspect of any rating system, form, prospective loss cost, dividend payment practice, underwriting rule or practice, survey, inspection, or similar material except as required by section 44-7524 or as is necessary to develop statistical plans.</para><para>(4) The fact that two or more insurers, whether or not members or subscribers of an advisory organization, consistently or intermittently use the same rates, rating systems, forms, prospective loss costs, underwriting rules or practices, surveys, inspections, or similar materials shall not be sufficient basis to establish a violation of this section.</para><para>(5) No insurer, advisory organization, or statistical agent shall make any arrangement with any other insurer, advisory organization, statistical agent, or other person which has the purpose or effect of unreasonably restraining trade or of substantially lessening competition in the business of insurance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 