<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7107</statuteno><catchline>Intermediaries.</catchline><para>(1) A contract between a health carrier and an intermediary shall satisfy all the requirements contained in this section.</para><para>(2)(a) Intermediaries and participating providers with whom they contract shall comply with all the applicable requirements of section 44-7106.</para><para>(b) A health carrier's statutory responsibility to monitor the offering of covered benefits to covered persons shall not be delegated or assigned to the intermediary.</para><para>(c) A health carrier shall have the right to approve or disapprove participation status of a subcontracted provider in its own or a contracted network for the purpose of delivering covered benefits to the health carrier's covered persons.</para><para>(d) A health carrier shall maintain copies of all intermediary health care subcontracts at its principal place of business in the state, or ensure that it has access to all intermediary subcontracts, including the right to make copies to facilitate regulatory review, upon twenty days' prior written notice from the health carrier. A health carrier may meet the requirements of this subdivision by maintaining a copy of the intermediary health care subcontract forms used by its intermediaries, and if the health carrier does so, the health carrier shall also maintain a copy of any portion of an intermediary health care subcontract which substantially differs from the intermediary health care subcontract form in subject areas other than reimbursement.</para><para>(e) If applicable, an intermediary shall transmit utilization documentation and claims paid documentation to the health carrier. The health carrier shall monitor the timeliness and appropriateness of payments made to providers and health care services received by covered persons.</para><para>(f) If applicable, an intermediary shall maintain the books, records, financial information, and documentation of health care services provided to covered persons at its principal place of business in the state and preserve them for five years in a manner that facilitates regulatory review.</para><para>(g) An intermediary shall allow the director and a health maintenance organization shall allow the director and the Department of Health and Human Services access to the intermediary's books, records, financial information, and any documentation of health care services provided to covered persons, as necessary to determine compliance with the Managed Care Plan Network Adequacy Act.</para><para>(h) A health carrier shall have the right, in the event of the intermediary's insolvency, to require the assignment to the health carrier of the provisions of a provider's contract addressing the provider's obligation to furnish covered services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1162, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 199.</para></source></law></legaldoc>