<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id578"><sectno id="id579" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 49.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" id="id580" statutenumber="44-7508.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id582">44-7508.02</statuteno><catchline id="id583">Policy forms; filing; director; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) For policy forms to which this section applies as provided in section 44-7508.01, each insurer shall file with the director every policy form and related attachment rule and every modification thereof which it proposes to use. For policy forms to which this section applies, no insurer shall issue a contract or policy except in accordance with the filings that are in effect for such insurer as provided in the Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act except as provided in subsection (10) or (11) of this section or as provided by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 44-7514 or 44-7515.</para><para>(2) Every filing shall state its effective date, which shall not be prior to the date that the director receives such filing.</para><para>(3) Every policy form filing shall explain the intended use of such policy forms. Filings shall include a list of policy forms that will be replaced when the approval of a filing will result in the replacement of previously approved policy forms. In addition, insurers shall maintain listings of policy forms that have been filed so that such listings can be provided upon request.</para><para>(4) The director shall acknowledge receipt of a policy form filing as soon as practical. A review of the filing by the director is not required to issue this acknowledgment, and acknowledgment shall not constitute an approval by the director.</para><para>(5) The director may review a policy form filing at any time after it has been made. The director shall review a policy form filing for insurance covering risks of a personal nature, including insurance for homeowners, tenants, private passenger nonfleet automobiles, mobile homes, and other property and casualty insurance for personal, family, or household needs, within thirty days after the filing has been made. Following such review, the director shall disapprove a filing that contains provisions, exceptions, or conditions that: (a) Are unjust, unfair, ambiguous, inconsistent, inequitable, misleading, deceptive, or contrary to public policy; (b) are written so as to encourage the misrepresentation of coverage; (c) fail to reasonably provide the general coverage for policies of that type; (d) fail to comply with the provisions or the intent of the laws of this state; or (e) would provide coverage contrary to the public interest.</para><para>(6) If, within thirty days after its receipt, the director disapproves a filing that requires disapproval pursuant to subsection (5) of this section, then a written disapproval notice shall be sent to the insurer. The disapproval notice shall specify in what respects the filing fails to meet these requirements. Upon receipt of the notice of disapproval, the insurer shall cease use of the filing as soon as practical but may use the form for policies that have already been issued or when pending coverage proposals are outstanding.</para><para>(7) If, within thirty days after its receipt, the director requests additional information to complete review of a policy form filing, the thirty-day review period allowed in subsection (6) of this section shall commence on the date such information is received by the director. If a filer fails to furnish the required information within ninety days, the director may disapprove the filing based on the insurer's failure to provide the requested information. Disapproval shall be by written notice sent to the insurer ordering discontinuance of the filing within thirty days after the date of notice.</para><para>(8) An insurer whose filing is disapproved pursuant to subsection (6) of this section may, within thirty days after receipt of a disapproval notice, request a hearing in accordance with section 44-7532.</para><para>(9) An insurer may authorize the director to accept policy form filings made on its behalf by an advisory organization.</para><para>(10)(a) Subject to the requirements of this subsection, policy forms unique in character and designed for and used with regard to an individual risk under common ownership subject to the rate filing provisions of section 44-7508 shall be exempt from subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(b) At the earliest practical opportunity, but no later than thirty days after the effective date of the policy using unfiled provisions, the insurer shall provide the prospective insured with a written listing of the policy forms that have not been filed with the director. This requirement does not apply to renewals using the same unfiled policy forms.</para><para>(c) A policy form that has been used in this state or elsewhere by the insurer for another risk shall not be subject to the exemption provided by this subsection, except that an insurer may use a policy form previously developed for a single risk for a second risk if the policy form is filed within sixty days after its second usage.</para><para>(d) The exemption provided by this subsection shall not apply to policy forms that, prior to their use by the insurer, had been filed by an advisory organization in this state or had been filed by the insurer in any jurisdiction, regardless of whether approval was received.</para><para>(e) The director may by rule and regulation or by order make specific restrictions relating to the exemption provided by this subsection and may require the informational filing of policy forms subject to such exemption within a reasonable time after their use. Any such informational filings specifically relating to individual risks shall be confidential and may not be made public by the director except as may be compiled in summaries of such activity.</para><para>(11) The director may by rule and regulation suspend or modify the filing requirements of this section as to any type of insurance or class of risk for which policy forms cannot practicably be filed before they are used. The director may examine insurers as is necessary to ascertain whether any policy forms affected by such rules and regulations meet the standards contained in the Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act.</para><para>(12) If, at any time after the expiration of the review period provided by subsection (6) of this section or any extension thereof, the director finds that a policy form, attachment rule, or modification thereof does not meet or no longer meets the requirements of subsection (5) of this section, the director shall hold a hearing in accordance with section 44-7532.</para><para>(13) Any insured aggrieved with respect to any policy form filing subject to this section may make written application to the director for a hearing on such filing. The hearing application shall specify the grounds to be relied upon by the applicant. If the director finds that the hearing application is made in good faith, that a remedy would be available if the grounds are established, or that such grounds otherwise justify holding a hearing, the director shall hold a hearing in accordance with section 44-7532.</para><para>(14) If, after a hearing held pursuant to subsection (12) or (13) of this section, the director finds that a filing does not meet the requirements of subsection (5) of this section, the director shall issue an order stating in what respects such filing fails to meet the requirements and when, within a reasonable period thereafter, such policy form or attachment rule shall no longer be used. Copies of the order shall be sent to the applicant, if applicable, and to every affected insurer and advisory organization. The order shall not affect any contract or policy made or issued prior to the expiration of the period set forth in the order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 216, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 49.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
