<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id774"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7618</statuteno><catchline>Compliance with provisions of federal law, required; trust; surplus; amount required.</catchline><para>(1) A multiple employer welfare arrangement that provides health care coverage to self-employed individuals shall comply with the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act, Public Law 111-148, as amended by the Health Care and Education Reconciliation Act of 2010, Public Law 111-152, as such acts existed on January 1, 2020, and the following protections for covered individuals that would otherwise be required under the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974:</para><para>(a) Fiduciary duties in section 404 of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974, 29 U.S.C. 1104;</para><para>(b) Claims and appeal procedures in section 503 of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974, 29 U.S.C. 1133;</para><para>(c) The Paul Wellstone and Pete Domenici Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008, 29 U.S.C. 1185a;</para><para>(d) The Newborns' and Mothers' Health Protection Act of 1996, 29 U.S.C. 1185; and</para><para>(e) The Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act of 2008, 29 U.S.C. 1182.</para><para>(2) A multiple employer welfare arrangement that provides health care coverage to covered individuals who are self-employed individuals shall establish and maintain a surplus in the trust established pursuant to section 44-7607 in an amount equal to at least seven hundred fifty thousand dollars. The director may increase the amount required to be deposited in the trust based on the director's determination that such an increase is necessary after considering the level of aggregate and specific stop-loss insurance provided with respect to such multiple employer welfare arrangement and other factors related to solvency risk, such as the multiple employer welfare arrangement's projected levels of participation or claims, the nature of the multiple employer welfare arrangement's liabilities, and the types of assets available to assure that such liabilities are met.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1014, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>