<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7510" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7510</statuteno><catchline>Standards for rating systems and prospective loss costs for lines subject to prior approval.</catchline><para>(1) Rating systems shall not produce premiums that are excessive. A premium level is excessive if it is likely to produce a profit that is unreasonably high for the insurance provided or if expenses are unreasonably high in relation to services rendered. In the evaluation of a premium level, due consideration shall be given to loss experience within and outside this state; reasonably anticipated trends; investment income; special assessments, conflagration, and catastrophe hazards; a reasonable margin for profit; dividends, savings, or unabsorbed premium deposits allowed or returned by insurers to policyholders, members, or subscribers; expense experience both countrywide and specially applicable to this state; and other relevant factors.</para><para>(2) Rating systems shall not produce premiums that are inadequate. A premium level is inadequate only if (a) it would endanger the solvency of the insurer or (b) it would not be expected to generate a profit on a direct basis and would be likely to have the effect of diminishing competition.</para><para>(3)(a) Rating systems shall not produce premiums that are unfairly discriminatory. Premiums are unfairly discriminatory if, after allowing for practical limitations, price differentials fail to equitably reflect differences in expense requirements or expected losses.</para><para>(b) Risks may be grouped by classification groupings that identify objective risk differences for the establishment of rates and prospective loss costs and for the use of rating systems.</para><para>(c) Rates and premiums may be modified for individual risks or groups of risks in accordance with objective standards for measuring differences among risks or groups of risks that can be demonstrated to have a probable effect upon losses or expenses. The fact that experience rating plans use loss reserves shall not be interpreted as making experience rating plans subjective.</para><para>(d) Notwithstanding subdivisions (3)(b) and (c) of this section, fire insurance rating plans applying to commercial risks for the sole use by advisory organizations that contain reasonable subjective rating factors, but that otherwise meet the standards contained in the Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act, shall be approved.</para><para>(e) A rate is not unfairly discriminatory if it is averaged broadly among persons insured under a group, franchise, or blanket policy or a mass marketed plan. Mass marketed plan means a method of selling property liability insurance wherein:</para><para>(i) The insurance is offered to employees of particular employers, members of particular associations or organizations, or stockholders of publicly held corporations or to persons grouped in other ways, except groupings formed principally for the purpose of obtaining such insurance; and</para><para>(ii) The employer or other organization has agreed to, or otherwise affiliated itself with, the sale of such insurance to its employees or other groupings of persons affiliated with it.</para><para>(f) An insurer may have different rate levels for otherwise similar insureds based on expense differences between coverage sold:</para><para>(i) Through direct sales using employees of the insurer;</para><para>(ii) Through direct sales by the insurer using the Internet; and</para><para>(iii) Through agents that are not employees of the insurer.</para><para>(g) No risk classification or grouping may be based upon the race, creed, national origin, or religion of the insured.</para><para>(h) No rating system may violate the Unfair Discrimination Against Subjects of Abuse in Insurance Act.</para><para>(i) No risk classification or grouping may be based solely upon the fact that the insured is deployed in the military on Title 10 orders that require the insured to be mobilized outside of the United States, United States territories, and the District of Columbia for a period of six months or greater.</para><para>(4) Prospective loss costs shall be as near as is practical to the expected cost of future losses, including loss adjustment expenses. Anticipated special assessments may be included with prospective loss costs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1139, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB77, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Unfair Discrimination Against Subjects of Abuse in Insurance Act,</emphasis> see section 44-7401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>