<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7206</statuteno><catchline>Quality assessment; infrastructure and disclosure systems.</catchline><para>A health carrier that provides managed care plans shall develop and maintain the infrastructure and disclosure systems necessary to measure the quality of health care services provided to covered persons on a regular basis and appropriate to the types of managed care plans offered by the health carrier. A health carrier shall:</para><para>(1) Establish a system designed to assess the quality of health care provided to covered persons and appropriate to the types of managed care plans offered by the health carrier. The system shall include systematic collection, analysis, and reporting of relevant data in accordance with statutory and regulatory requirements;</para><para>(2) Communicate findings in a timely manner to applicable regulatory agencies, providers, and consumers as provided in section 44-7209;</para><para>(3) Report to the appropriate licensing authority any persistent pattern of problematic care provided by a provider that is sufficient to cause the health carrier to terminate or suspend contractual arrangements with the provider. A health carrier acting in good faith shall be granted immunity from any cause of action under state law in making the report; and</para><para>(4) Develop a written description of the quality assessment program available for review by the director, which shall include a signed certification by a corporate officer of the health carrier that the filing meets the requirements of the Quality Assessment and Improvement Act. The written description of the quality assessment program of a health maintenance organization shall also be available for review by the Department of Health and Human Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1162, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 200.</para></source></law></legaldoc>