
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7514" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7514</statuteno><catchline>Policy form approval requirements applying to qualifying multistate commercial policyholder; exemption.</catchline><para>(1) The policy form approval requirements set forth in section 44-7513 shall not apply to policies written for individual commercial risks of a qualifying multistate commercial policyholder. For the purposes of this section, a qualifying multistate commercial policyholder is an entity that meets the following qualifications:</para><para>(a) The policyholder is commercial in nature;</para><para>(b) If the policyholder is comprised of multiple corporations or other entities, there is common or majority ownership of each of the members by the same parent entity. Qualifying multistate commercial policyholder does not include franchise arrangements or other groups where individual members of the group are under different ownership; and</para><para>(c) The office with the largest number of the officers and senior management of the policyholder is located outside of Nebraska. If this criteria is not meaningful or is ambiguous for a policyholder, then the total premiums for lines of insurance subject to the Property and Casualty Insurance Rate and Form Act that are attributable to another jurisdiction must exceed those premiums attributable to Nebraska.</para><para>(2) Policy forms for commercial risks exempted by this section may include language that conflicts with sections 44-357, 44-358, and 44-501.02. If a conflict results between a policy form and the requirements of such sections, such sections shall apply.</para><para>(3) Policy forms for commercial risks exempted by this section may include language that conflicts with sections 44-349, 44-350, 44-501, 44-514 to 44-518, 44-520 to 44-523, and 44-6408 and the provision of section 44-601 that prohibits policies with a term longer than five years. If a conflict results between a policy form and the requirements of any of these sections, the language in the policy form shall apply to the extent that it is inconsistent with such sections.</para><para>(4) Except as set forth in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, the policy forms exempted from policy form approval requirements shall not violate any law of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1119, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB469, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>