<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7006</statuteno><catchline>Health carrier; credentialing verification duties.</catchline><para>(1) A health carrier shall:</para><para>(a) Establish written policies and procedures for credentialing verification of all health care professionals with whom the health carrier contracts and apply these standards consistently;</para><para>(b) Verify the credentials of a health care professional before entering into a contract with that health care professional. The medical director of the health carrier or other designated health care professional shall have responsibility for, and shall participate in, credentialing verification;</para><para>(c) Establish a credentialing verification committee consisting of licensed physicians and other health care professionals to review credentialing verification information and supporting documents and make decisions regarding credentialing verification;</para><para>(d) Make available for review by the applying health care professional upon written request all application and credentialing verification policies and procedures;</para><para>(e) Retain all records and documents relating to a health care professional's credentialing verification process for at least five years; and</para><para>(f) Keep confidential all information obtained in the credentialing verification process except as otherwise provided by law.</para><para>(2) Nothing in the Health Care Professional Credentialing Verification Act shall be construed to require a health carrier to select a provider as a participating provider solely because the provider meets the health carrier's credentialing verification standards or to prevent a health carrier from utilizing separate or additional criteria in selecting the health care professionals with whom it contracts.</para><para>(3) The policies and procedures for credentialing verification shall be available for review by the director, and, in the case of a health maintenance organization, shall also be available for review by the chief medical officer, if one is appointed pursuant to section 81-3115, and if not, then the Director of Public Health.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1162, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 198.</para></source></law></legaldoc>