<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-7902"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-7902</statuteno><catchline>Statement of Actuarial Opinion; filing; supporting documents; appointed actuary; immunity.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2007, every property and casualty insurance company doing business in this state, unless otherwise exempted by the domiciliary commissioner, shall annually submit the opinion of an appointed actuary entitled Statement of Actuarial Opinion. This opinion shall be filed in accordance with the appropriate National Association of Insurance Commissioners Property and Casualty Annual Statement Instructions.</para><para>(2)(a) Every property and casualty insurance company domiciled in this state that is required to submit a Statement of Actuarial Opinion shall annually submit an actuarial opinion summary, written by the company's appointed actuary. This actuarial opinion summary shall be filed in accordance with the appropriate National Association of Insurance Commissioners Property and Casualty Annual Statement Instructions and shall be considered as a document supporting the Statement of Actuarial Opinion required in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(b) A property and casualty insurance company authorized to do business in this state but not domiciled in this state shall provide the actuarial opinion summary to the Director of Insurance upon request.</para><para>(3)(a) An actuarial report and underlying workpapers as required by the appropriate National Association of Insurance Commissioners Property and Casualty Annual Statement Instructions shall be prepared to support each Statement of Actuarial Opinion.</para><para>(b) If the insurance company fails to provide a supporting actuarial report or workpapers at the request of the director or the director determines that the supporting actuarial report or workpapers provided by the insurance company is otherwise unacceptable to the director, the director may engage a qualified actuary at the expense of the company to review the opinion and the basis for the opinion and prepare the supporting actuarial report or workpapers.</para><para>(4) The appointed actuary shall not be liable for damages to any person, other than the insurance company or the director, for any act, error, omission, decision, or conduct with respect to the actuary's opinion, except in cases of fraud or willful misconduct on the part of the appointed actuary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 119, &#167; 40. </para></source></law></legaldoc>