<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-8216"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8216</statuteno><catchline>Creation of special purpose financial
captive insurers; applicability of section; form of organization;
powers; duties; powers of director; limitation on dividends; confidentiality.</catchline>
<para>(1) This section provides for the creation of special purpose financial
captive insurers to diversify and broaden insurers' access to sources of capital.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Counterparty means a special purpose financial captive insurer's
parent or affiliated entity, which is an insurer domiciled in Nebraska that
cedes life insurance risks to the special purpose financial captive insurer
pursuant to the special purpose financial captive insurer contract;</para>
<para>(b) Guaranty of a parent
means an agreement to pay specified obligations of the special purpose financial
captive insurer by a parent of the special purpose financial captive insurer
approved by the director that is not a counterparty and the guarantor has
sufficient equity, less the equity of all counterparties that are subsidiaries
of the guarantor, to satisfy the agreement during the life of the guaranty;</para>
<para>(c) Insolvency or insolvent
means that the special purpose financial captive insurer is unable to pay
its obligations when they are due, unless those obligations are the subject
of a bona fide dispute;</para>
<para>(d) Insurance securitization
means a package of related risk transfer instruments, capital market offerings,
and facilitating administrative agreements, under which a special purpose
financial captive insurer obtains proceeds either directly or indirectly through
the issuance of securities, and may hold the proceeds in trust to secure the
obligations of the special purpose financial captive insurer under one or
more special purpose financial captive insurer contracts, in that the investment
risk to the holders of the securities is contingent upon the obligations of
the special purpose financial captive insurer to the counterparty under the
special purpose financial captive insurer contract in accordance with the
transaction terms and pursuant to the Captive Insurers Act;</para>
<para>(e) Organizational document
means the special purpose financial captive insurer's articles of incorporation,
articles of organization, bylaws, operating agreement, or other foundational
documents that establish the special purpose financial captive insurer as
a legal entity or prescribes its existence;</para>
<para>(f) Permitted investments
means those investments that meet the qualifications set forth in section
44-8211;</para>
<para>(g) Securities means debt
obligations, equity investments, surplus certificates, surplus notes, funding
agreements, derivatives, and other legal forms of financial instruments;</para>
<para>(h) Special purpose financial
captive insurer means a captive insurer which has received a certificate of
authority from the director for the limited purposes provided for in this
section;</para>
<para>(i) Special purpose financial
captive insurer contract means a contract between the special purpose financial
captive insurer and the counterparty pursuant to which the special purpose
financial captive insurer agrees to provide insurance or reinsurance protection
to the counterparty for risks associated with the counterparty's insurance
or reinsurance business; and</para>
<para>(j) Special purpose financial
captive insurer securities means the securities issued by a special purpose
financial captive insurer.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The provisions of the Captive Insurers Act, other than those
in subdivision (3)(b) of this section, apply to a special purpose financial
captive insurer. If a conflict occurs between a provision of the act not in
this section and a provision of this section, the latter controls.</para>
<para>(b) The requirements of this section shall not apply to specific special
purpose financial captive insurers if the director finds a specific requirement
is inappropriate due to the nature of the risks to be insured by the special
purpose financial captive insurer and if the special purpose financial captive
insurer meets criteria established by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated
by the director.</para>
<para>(c) In determining whether
to issue a certificate of authority or to approve an amended plan of operation
for a special purpose financial captive insurer required under section 44-8205,
the director may consider any additional factors the director may deem relevant,
including the specific type of life insurance risks insured by the special
purpose financial captive insurer, the financial ability of a parent that
issues a guaranty pursuant to this section to satisfy such guaranty, and any
actuarial opinions or other statements or documents required by the director
to evaluate such application.</para><para>(d) At the time a special purpose financial captive
insurer files an application for a certificate of authority or submits an
amended plan of operation in accordance with section 44-8205, and on each
date the special purpose financial captive insurer is required to file an
annual financial statement in this state, a senior actuarial officer of each
ceding insurer shall file with the director a certification that the ceding
insurer's transactions with the special purpose financial captive insurer
are not being used to gain an unfair advantage in the pricing of the ceding
insurer's products. A ceding insurer shall not be deemed to have gained an
unfair advantage if the pricing of the policies and contracts reinsured by
the special purpose financial captive insurer reflects, at the time those
policies and contracts were issued, a reasonable long-term estimate of the
cost to the ceding insurer of an alternative third-party transaction and utilizes
current pricing assumptions.</para><para>(4) A special purpose
financial captive insurer may be established as a stock corporation, limited
liability company, partnership, or other form of organization approved by
the director.</para>
<para>(5)(a) A special purpose financial captive insurer may not issue a contract
for assumption of risk or indemnification of loss other than a special purpose
financial captive insurer contract. However, the special purpose financial
captive insurer may cede risks assumed through a special purpose financial
captive insurer contract to third-party reinsurers through the purchase of
reinsurance or retrocession protection if approved by the director.</para>
<para>(b) A special purpose financial captive insurer may enter into contracts
and conduct other commercial activities related or incidental to and necessary
to fulfill the purposes of the special purpose financial captive insurer contract,
insurance securitization, and this section. Those activities may include,
but are not limited to: Entering into special purpose financial captive insurer
contracts; entering into agreements
in connection with obtaining guaranties of its parent; issuing
securities of the special purpose financial captive insurer in accordance
with applicable securities law; complying with the terms of these contracts
or securities; entering into trust, swap, tax, administration, reimbursement,
or fiscal agent transactions; or complying with trust indenture, reinsurance,
retrocession, and other agreements necessary or incidental to effectuate a special purpose financial captive insurer
contract or an insurance securitization in compliance with this
section and in the plan of operation approved by the director.</para>
<para>(6)(a) A special purpose financial captive insurer may issue securities,
subject to and in accordance with applicable law, its approved plan of operation,
and its organization documents.</para>
<para>(b) A special purpose financial captive insurer, in connection with
the issuance of securities, may enter into and perform all of its obligations
under any required contracts to facilitate the issuance of these securities.</para>
<para>(c) The obligation to repay principal or interest, or both, on the securities
issued by the special purpose financial captive insurer shall be designed
to reflect the risk associated with the obligations of the special purpose
financial captive insurer to the counterparty under the special purpose financial
captive insurer contract.</para>
<para>(7) A special purpose financial captive insurer may enter into swap
agreements, or other forms of asset management agreements, including guaranteed
investment contracts, or other transactions that have the objective of leveling
timing differences in funding of up-front or ongoing transaction expenses
or managing asset, credit, prepayment, or interest rate risk of the investments
in the trust to ensure that the investments are sufficient to assure payment
or repayment of the securities, and related interest or principal payments,
issued pursuant to a special purpose financial captive insurer insurance securitization
transaction or the obligations of the special purpose financial captive insurer
under the special purpose financial captive insurer contract or for any other
purpose approved by the director. All asset management agreements entered
into by the special purpose financial captive insurer must be approved by
the director.</para>
<para>(8)(a) A special purpose financial captive insurer, at any given time,
may enter into and effectuate a special purpose financial captive insurer
contract with a counterparty if the special purpose financial captive insurer
contract obligates the special purpose financial captive insurer to indemnify
the counterparty for losses and contingent obligations of the special purpose
financial captive insurer under the special purpose financial captive insurer
contract are securitized through a special purpose financial captive insurer
insurance securitization, which security for such obligations may be funded
and secured with assets held in trust for the benefit of the counterparty
pursuant to agreements contemplated by this section and invested in a manner
that meet the criteria as provided in section 44-8211.</para>
<para>(b) A special purpose financial captive insurer may enter into agreements
with affiliated companies and third parties and conduct business necessary
to fulfill its obligations and administrative duties incidental to the insurance
securitization and the special purpose financial captive insurer contract.
The agreements may include management and administrative services agreements
and other allocation and cost-sharing agreements, or swap and asset management
agreements, or both, or agreements for other contemplated types of transactions
provided in this section.</para>
<para>(c) A special purpose financial captive insurer contract must contain
provisions that:</para>
<para>(i) Require the special purpose financial captive insurer to either
(A) enter into a trust agreement specifying what recoverables or reserves,
or both, the agreement is to cover and to establish a trust account for the
benefit of the counterparty and the security holders or (B) establish such
other method of security acceptable to the director, including letters of credit or guaranties of a parent
as described in subsection (9) of this section;</para>
<para>(ii) Stipulate that assets deposited in the trust account must be valued
in accordance with their current fair market value and must consist only of
permitted investments;</para>
<para>(iii) If a trust arrangement is used, require the special purpose financial
captive insurer, before depositing assets with the trustee, to execute assignments,
to execute endorsements in blank, or to take such actions as are necessary
to transfer legal title to the trustee of all shares, obligations, or other
assets requiring assignments, in order that the counterparty, or the trustee
upon the direction of the counterparty, may negotiate whenever necessary the
assets without consent or signature from the special purpose financial captive
insurer or another entity; and</para>
<para>(iv) If a trust arrangement is used, stipulate that the special purpose
financial captive insurer and the counterparty agree that the assets in the
trust account, established pursuant to the provisions of the special purpose
financial captive insurer contract, may be withdrawn by the counterparty,
or the trustee on its behalf, at any time, only in accordance with the terms
of the special purpose financial captive insurer contract, and must be utilized
and applied by the counterparty or any successor of the counterparty by operation
of law, including, subject to the provisions of this section, but without
further limitation, any liquidator, rehabilitator, or receiver of the counterparty,
without diminution because of insolvency on the part of the counterparty or
the special purpose financial captive insurer, only for the purposes set forth
in the credit for reinsurance laws and rules and regulations of this state.</para>
<para>(d) The special purpose financial captive insurer contract may contain
provisions that give the special purpose financial captive insurer the right
to seek approval from the counterparty to withdraw from the trust all or part
of the assets, or income from them, contained in the trust and to transfer
the assets to the special purpose financial captive insurer if such provisions
comply with the credit for reinsurance laws and rules and regulations of this
state.</para>
<para>(9) A special purpose financial captive insurer contract meeting the
provisions of this section must be granted credit for reinsurance treatment
or otherwise qualify as an asset or a reduction from liability for reinsurance
ceded by a domestic insurer to a special purpose financial captive insurer
as an assuming insurer for the benefit of the counterparty if and only to
the extent:</para>
<para>(a)(i) Of
the value of:</para>
<para>(A) The assets held in trust;</para>
<para>(B) Clean, or irrevocable, unconditional letters of
credit, issued or confirmed by a qualified United States financial institution
as defined in section 44-416.08, or as approved by the director; or</para>
<para>(C) Guaranties of the parent; and</para>
<para>(ii) For the benefit of the
counterparty under the special purpose financial captive insurer contract;
and </para>
<para>(b) Assets of the special purpose financial
captive insurer are held or invested in one or more of the forms
allowed in section 44-8211.</para>
<para>(10)(a)(i) Notwithstanding the provisions of the Nebraska Insurers Supervision,
Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act, the director may apply to the district
court of Lancaster County for an order authorizing the director to rehabilitate
or liquidate a special purpose financial captive insurer domiciled in this
state on one or more of the following grounds:</para>
<para>(A) There has been embezzlement, wrongful sequestration, dissipation,
or diversion of the assets of the special purpose financial captive insurer
intended to be used to pay amounts owed to the counterparty or the holders
of special purpose financial captive insurer securities; or</para>
<para>(B) The special purpose financial captive insurer is insolvent and the
holders of a majority in outstanding principal amount of each class of special
purpose financial captive insurer securities request or consent to conservation,
rehabilitation, or liquidation pursuant to the provisions of this section.</para>
<para>(ii) The court may not grant relief provided by subdivision (10)(a)(i)
of this section unless, after notice and a hearing, the director establishes
that relief must be granted.</para>
<para>(b) Notwithstanding any other applicable law, rule, or regulation, upon
any order of rehabilitation or liquidation of a special purpose financial
captive insurer, the receiver shall manage the assets and liabilities of the
special purpose financial captive insurer pursuant to the provisions of subsection
(11) of this section.</para>
<para>(c) With respect to amounts recoverable under a special purpose financial
captive insurer contract, the amount recoverable by the receiver must not
be reduced or diminished as a result of the entry of an order of conservation,
rehabilitation, or liquidation with respect to the counterparty, notwithstanding
another provision in the contracts or other documentation governing the special
purpose financial captive insurer insurance securitization.</para>
<para>(d) An application or petition, or a temporary restraining order or
injunction issued pursuant to the provisions of the Nebraska Insurers Supervision,
Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act, with respect to a counterparty does not
prohibit the transaction of a business by a special purpose financial captive
insurer, including any payment by a special purpose financial captive insurer
made pursuant to a special purpose financial captive insurer security, or
any action or proceeding against a special purpose financial captive insurer
or its assets.</para>
<para>(e) Notwithstanding the provisions of any applicable law or rule or
regulation, the commencement of a summary proceeding or other interim proceeding
commenced before a formal delinquency proceeding with respect to a special
purpose financial captive insurer, and any order issued by the court, does
not prohibit the payment by a special purpose financial captive insurer made
pursuant to a special purpose financial captive insurer security or special
purpose financial captive insurer contract or the special purpose financial
captive insurer from taking any action required to make the payment.</para>
<para>(f) Notwithstanding the provisions of any other applicable law, rule,
or regulation:</para>
<para>(i) A receiver of a counterparty may not void a nonfraudulent transfer
by a counterparty to a special purpose financial captive insurer of money
or other property made pursuant to a special purpose financial captive insurer
contract; and</para>
<para>(ii) A receiver of a special purpose financial captive insurer may not
void a nonfraudulent transfer by the special purpose financial captive insurer
of money or other property made to a counterparty pursuant to a special purpose
financial captive insurer contract or made to or for the benefit of any holder
of a special purpose financial captive insurer security on account of the
special purpose financial captive insurer security.</para>
<para>(g) With the exception of the fulfillment of the obligations under a
special purpose financial captive insurer contract, and notwithstanding the
provisions of any other applicable law or rule or regulation, the assets of
a special purpose financial captive insurer, including assets held in trust,
must not be consolidated with or included in the estate of a counterparty
in any delinquency proceeding against the counterparty pursuant to the provisions
of this section for any purpose including, without limitation, distribution
to creditors of the counterparty.</para>
<para>(11) A special purpose financial captive insurer may not declare or
pay dividends in any form to its owners other than in accordance with the
insurance securitization transaction agreements, and in no instance shall
the dividends decrease the capital of the special purpose financial captive
insurer below two hundred fifty thousand dollars, and, after giving effect
to the dividends, the assets of the special purpose financial captive insurer,
including any assets held in trust pursuant to the terms of the insurance
securitization, must be sufficient to satisfy the director that it can meet
its obligations. Approval by the director of an ongoing plan for the payment
of dividends, interest on securities, or other distribution by a special purpose
financial captive insurer must be conditioned upon the retention, at the time
of each payment, of capital or surplus equal to or in excess of amounts specified
by, or determined in accordance with formulas approved for the special purpose
financial captive insurer by, the director.</para>
<para>(12) Information submitted pursuant to the provisions of this section
shall be given confidential treatment, shall not be subject to subpoena, and
shall not be made public by the director or any other person, except to other
state, federal, foreign, and international regulatory and law enforcement
agencies if the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality
of the information, without the prior written consent of the special purpose
financial captive insurer unless the director, after giving the special purpose
financial captive insurer notice and opportunity to be heard, determines that
the best interest of policyholders, shareholders, or the public will be served
by the publication thereof, in which event he or she may publish all or any
part thereof in such manner as he or she may deem appropriate.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 30.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Insurers Supervision, Rehabilitation, and Liquidation Act,</emphasis> see section 44-4862.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>