<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id458"><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Insurance" id="id460"  statutenumber="44-8307"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8307</statuteno><catchline>Director; examination or investigation; powers; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The director may examine or investigate the business and affairs of any discount medical plan organization to protect the interests of the residents of this state based on the following reasons, including, but not limited to, complaint indices, recent complaints, information from other states, or as the director deems necessary.</para><para>(2) An examination or investigation conducted as provided in subsection (1) of this section shall be performed in accordance with the provisions of the Insurers Examination Act.</para><para>(3) The director may:</para><para>(a) Order any discount medical plan organization or applicant that operates a discount medical plan organization to produce any records, books, files, advertising and solicitation materials, or other information; and</para><para>(b) Take statements under oath to determine whether the discount medical plan organization or applicant is in violation of the law or is acting contrary to the public interest.</para><para>(4) The discount medical plan organization or applicant that is the subject of the examination or investigation shall pay the expenses incurred in conducting the examination or investigation. Failure by the discount medical plan organization or applicant to pay such expenses is grounds for denial of a certificate of registration to operate as a discount medical plan organization or revocation of a certificate of registration to operate as a discount medical plan organization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 39. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Insurers Examination Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5901.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>
