<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="44-8108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8108</statuteno><catchline>Insurance producer; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) An insurance producer
shall not solicit the sale of an annuity product unless the insurance producer
has adequate knowledge of the product to recommend the annuity and the insurance
producer is in compliance with the insurer's standards for product training.
An insurance producer may rely on insurer-provided product-specific training
standards and materials to comply with this subsection.</para>
<para>(2)(a)(i) An insurance
producer who engages in the sale of annuity products shall complete a one-time
four-credit training course approved by the Department of Insurance and provided
by a department-approved education provider.</para><para>(ii) Insurance producers who hold
a life insurance line of authority on July 19, 2012, and who desire to sell
annuities shall complete the requirements of this subsection within six months
after July 19, 2012. Individuals who obtain a life insurance line of authority
on or after July 19, 2012, shall not engage in the sale of annuities until
the annuity training course required under this subsection has been completed.</para>
<para>(b) The minimum length
of the training required under this subsection shall be sufficient to qualify
for at least four continuing education credits, but may be longer.</para>
<para>(c) The training required
under this subsection shall include information on the following topics:</para>
<para>(i) The types of annuities
and various classifications of annuities;</para><para>(ii) Identification of the parties to an annuity;</para>
<para>(iii) How fixed, variable,
and indexed annuity contract provisions affect consumers;</para>
<para>(iv) The application
of income taxation of qualified and nonqualified annuities;</para>
<para>(v) The primary uses
of annuities; and</para><para>(vi)
Appropriate sales practices and replacement and disclosure requirements.</para>
<para>(d) Providers of courses
intended to comply with this subsection shall cover all topics listed in the
prescribed outline and shall not present any marketing information or provide
training on sales techniques or specific information about a particular insurer's
products. Additional topics may be offered in conjunction with and in addition
to the required outline.</para><para>(e)
A provider of an annuity training course intended to comply with this subsection
shall register as a continuing education provider in this state and comply
with the requirements applicable to insurance producer continuing education
courses as set forth in section 44-3905.</para><para>(f) Annuity training courses may be conducted and
completed by classroom or self-study methods in accordance with sections 44-3901
to 44-3908.</para><para>(g)
Providers of annuity training shall comply with the reporting requirements
and shall issue certificates of completion in accordance with sections 44-3901
to 44-3908.</para><para>(h)
The satisfaction of training requirements of another state that are substantially
similar to the provisions of this subsection shall be deemed to satisfy the
training requirements of this subsection.</para><para>(i) An insurer shall verify that an insurance producer
has completed the annuity training course required under this subsection before
allowing the producer to sell an annuity product for that insurer. An insurer
may satisfy its responsibility under this subsection by obtaining certificates
of completion of the training course or obtaining reports provided by National
Association of Insurance Commissioners-sponsored data base systems or vendors
or from a reasonably reliable commercial data base vendor that has a reporting
arrangement with approved insurance education providers.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>