<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-8008"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8008</statuteno><catchline>Compliance with act; unfair payment pattern; director; powers and duties; enforcement; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) An insured, a representative of an insured, or a health care provider acting on behalf of the insured may notify the director of activities related to an unfair payment pattern. The director shall compile a record of notices, and if it appears to the director that an insurer, or a third party working on behalf of an insurer, may be engaged in an unfair payment pattern or that an insurer has filed a prompt payment act compliance statement that the insurer knows or has reason to know is false, the director may examine and investigate the affairs of such insurer or third party, either as part of a regularly scheduled examination or as part of an examination called solely for the purposes of determining compliance with the Health Care Prompt Payment Act. The insurer shall reimburse the Department of Insurance for the expense of the examination of the insurer or third party working on behalf of the insurer in the same manner as provided for examination of insurance companies in the Insurers Examination Act.</para><para>(2) If as a result of an examination conducted under subsection (1) of this section, the director finds that any insurer doing business in this state is engaged in any unfair payment pattern, or that the insurer has filed a prompt payment act compliance statement that the insurer knows or has reason to know is false, and that a proceeding in respect thereto would be in the public interest, the director shall issue and serve upon such insurer a statement of the charges in that respect and a notice of hearing thereon, which notice shall set a hearing date not less than ten days from the date of the notice.</para><para>(3) If, after a hearing conducted pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act, the director finds that an insurer or a third party working on behalf of an insurer has engaged in an unfair payment pattern or that the insurer has filed a prompt payment act compliance statement that the insurer knows or has reason to know is false, the director shall reduce the findings to writing and shall issue and cause to be served upon the insurer a copy of the findings and an order requiring the insurer or any third party working on behalf of the insurer to cease and desist from engaging in the act or practice and the director may order any one or more of the following:</para><para>(a) Payment of a monetary penalty of not more than one thousand dollars for each violation, not to exceed an aggregate penalty of thirty thousand dollars, unless the violation was committed flagrantly and in conscious disregard of the Health Care Prompt Payment Act, in which case the penalty shall not be more than fifteen thousand dollars for each violation, not to exceed an aggregate penalty of one hundred fifty thousand dollars;</para><para>(b) Suspension or revocation of the insurer's license or certificate of authority if the insurer knew or reasonably should have known it was in violation of the act; and</para><para>(c) Withdrawal of the insurer's prompt payment act compliance statement for such time as the director determines.</para><para>(4) Any insurer who violates a cease and desist order under subsection (3) of this section may, after notice and hearing and upon order of the director, be subject to:</para><para>(a) A monetary penalty of not more than thirty thousand dollars for each violation, not to exceed an aggregate penalty of one hundred fifty thousand dollars; and</para><para>(b) Suspension or revocation of the insurer's license or certificate of authority.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 389, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Insurers Examination Act,</emphasis> see section 44-5901.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>