<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id25">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id27" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="44-8804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8804</statuteno><catchline>Individual navigator registration;
application; form; contents; fee; entity navigator registration; application;
form; contents; fee; notice of federal action; list of employees.</catchline><para>(1) An individual
applying for an individual navigator registration shall make application to
the director on a form developed by the director which, unless preempted by
federal law, is accompanied by the initial individual registration fee in
an amount not to exceed twenty-five dollars as established by the director.
The individual shall declare in the application under penalty of refusal,
suspension, or revocation of the registration that the statements made in
the application are true, correct, and complete to the best of the individual's
knowledge and belief. Before approving the application, the director shall
find that the individual:</para>
<para>(a) Is at least
eighteen years of age;</para><para>(b) Has successfully passed an examination prescribed by an exchange
established or operating in this state and has been authorized to act as a
navigator; and</para><para>(c) Has identified any entity navigator with which he or she is
affiliated and supervised.</para><para>(2) An entity applying for an entity navigator registration shall
make application on a form developed by the director and which contains the
information prescribed by the director and which, unless preempted by federal
law, is accompanied by the initial entity registration fee in an amount not
to exceed fifty dollars as established by the director.</para>
<para>(3) The director
may require any documents deemed necessary to verify the information contained
in an application submitted in accordance with subsections (1) and (2) of
this section.</para><para>(4) A registered navigator shall, in a manner prescribed by the
director, notify the director within thirty days of any federal action that
restricts or terminates the navigator's authorization to act as a navigator.</para>
<para>(5) A registered
entity navigator shall, in a manner prescribed by the director, provide the
director with a list of all individual navigators that it employs, supervises,
or is affiliated with.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB568, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>