<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id939"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-8605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8605</statuteno><catchline>Post-loss assignment of rights or benefits; requirements; Department of Insurance; duties.</catchline><para>(1) A post-loss assignment of rights or benefits to a residential contractor under a property and casualty insurance policy insuring residential real estate shall comply with the following:</para><para>(a) The assignment may authorize a residential contractor to be named as a copayee for the payment of benefits under a property and casualty insurance policy covering residential real estate;</para><para>(b) The assignment shall be provided to the insurer of the residential real estate within five business days after execution;</para><para>(c) The assignment shall include a statement that the residential contractor has made no assurances that the claimed loss will be fully covered by an insurance contract and shall include the following notice in capitalized fourteen-point type:</para><para>YOU ARE AGREEING TO ASSIGN CERTAIN RIGHTS YOU HAVE UNDER YOUR INSURANCE POLICY. WITH AN ASSIGNMENT, THE RESIDENTIAL CONTRACTOR SHALL BE ENTITLED TO PURSUE ANY RIGHTS OR REMEDIES THAT YOU, THE INSURED HOMEOWNER, HAVE UNDER YOUR INSURANCE POLICY. PLEASE READ AND UNDERSTAND THIS DOCUMENT BEFORE SIGNING.</para><para>THE INSURER MAY ONLY PAY FOR THE COST TO REPAIR OR REPLACE DAMAGED PROPERTY CAUSED BY A COVERED PERIL, SUBJECT TO THE TERMS OF THE POLICY.</para><para>(d) The assignment shall not impair the interest of a mortgagee listed on the declarations page of the property and casualty insurance policy which is the subject of the assignment; and</para><para>(e) The assignment shall not prevent or inhibit an insurer from communicating with the named insured or mortgagee listed on the declarations page of the property and casualty insurance policy that is the subject of the assignment.</para><para>(2) The Department of Insurance shall strictly enforce the provisions of subdivision (13) of section 44-1540, which requires insurers to provide a named insured a reasonable and accurate explanation of the basis for the denial of a claim or an offer of a compromise settlement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 32. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>