<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="44-8403"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8403</statuteno><catchline>Qualified health insurance plan offered
through health insurance exchange; abortion coverage; restriction; health
insurance plan, contract or policy; optional rider.</catchline><para>(1) No abortion coverage shall be provided
by a qualified health insurance plan offered through a health insurance exchange
created pursuant to the federal Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act,
Public Law 111-148, within the State of Nebraska. This subsection shall not
apply to coverage for an abortion which is verified in writing by the attending
physician as necessary to prevent the death of the woman or to coverage for
medical complications arising from an abortion.</para>
<para>(2) No health insurance
plan, contract, or policy delivered or issued for delivery in the State of
Nebraska shall provide coverage for an elective abortion except through an
optional rider to the policy for which an additional premium is paid solely
by the insured. This subsection applies to any health insurance plan, contract,
or policy delivered or issued for delivery in the State of Nebraska by any
health insurer, any nonprofit hospital, medical, surgical, dental, or health
service corporation, any group health insurer, and any health maintenance
organization subject to the laws of insurance in this state and any employer
providing self-funded health insurance for his or her employees. This subsection
also applies to any plan provision of hospital, medical, surgical, or funeral
benefits or of coverage against accidental death or injury if such benefits
or coverage are incidental to or a part of any other insurance plan delivered
or issued for delivery in the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) The issuer of a health insurance
plan, contract, or policy in the State of Nebraska shall not provide any incentive
or discount to an insured if the insured elects abortion coverage.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this
section, elective abortion means an abortion (a) other than a spontaneous
abortion or (b) that is performed for any reason other than to prevent the
death of the female upon whom the abortion is performed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB22, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>