<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id467"><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Insurance" id="id469"  statutenumber="44-8308"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8308</statuteno><catchline>Charges authorized; right to cancel membership; plan sold in conjunction with other products; duties.</catchline><para>(1) A discount medical plan organization may charge a periodic charge as well as a reasonable one-time processing fee for a discount medical plan.</para><para>(2)(a)(i) If a member cancels his or her membership in the discount medical plan organization within thirty days after the date of receipt of the written document for the discount medical plan described in subsection (4) of section 44-8311, the member shall receive a reimbursement of all periodic charges and the amount of any one-time processing fee that exceeds thirty dollars upon return of the discount medical plan card to the discount medical plan organization.</para><para>(ii)(A) Cancellation occurs when notice of cancellation is given to the discount medical plan organization.</para><para>(B) Notice of cancellation is deemed given when delivered by hand or deposited in a mailbox, properly addressed, and postage prepaid to the mailing address of the discount medical plan organization.</para><para>(iii) A discount medical plan organization shall return any periodic charge charged or collected after the member has returned the discount medical plan card or given the discount medical plan organization notice of cancellation.</para><para>(b) If the discount medical plan organization cancels a membership for any reason other than nonpayment of charges by the member, the discount medical plan organization shall make a pro rata reimbursement of all periodic charges to the member.</para><para>(3) When a marketer or discount medical plan organization sells a discount medical plan in conjunction with any other products, the marketer or discount medical plan organization shall:</para><para>(a) Provide the charges for each discount medical plan in writing to the member; or</para><para>(b) Reimburse the member for all periodic charges for the discount medical plan if the member cancels his or her membership in accordance with subdivision (2)(a) of this section.</para><para>(4) Any discount medical plan organization that is a health carrier that provides a discount medical plan product that is incidental to the insured product is not subject to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167;  40.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
