<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Insurance" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="44-8106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8106</statuteno><catchline>Recommendation; purchase, exchange, or replacement of annuity;
requirements; insurer; duties;
insurance producer; prohibited acts; Director of Insurance; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) The insurance producer, or insurer if an insurance producer is not
involved, shall have reasonable grounds to believe that the recommendation
is suitable for the consumer based on the facts disclosed by the consumer
before making a recommendation to a consumer under the Nebraska Protection
in Annuity Transactions Act. The recommendation shall be based on the facts
disclosed by the consumer relating to his or her investments, other insurance
products, and the financial situation and needs of the consumer. This information shall include the consumer's
suitability information, and, if there is a reasonable basis to believe the
information, all of the following:</para>
<para>(a) That the consumer
has been reasonably informed of various features of the annuity, such as the
potential surrender period and surrender charge, potential tax penalty if
the consumer sells, exchanges, surrenders, or annuitizes the annuity, mortality
and expense fees, investment advisory fees, potential charges for and features
of riders, limitations on interest returns, insurance and investment components,
and market risk;</para><para>(b)
That the consumer would benefit from certain features of the annuity, such
as tax-deferred growth, annuitization, or death or living benefit;</para>
<para>(c) That the particular
annuity as a whole, the underlying subaccounts to which funds are allocated
at the time of purchase or exchange of the annuity, and riders and similar
product enhancements, if any, are suitable, and in the case of an exchange
or replacement, the transaction as a whole is suitable for the particular
consumer based on his or her suitability information; and</para>
<para>(d) In the case of an
exchange or replacement of an annuity, the exchange or replacement is suitable,
including the consideration as to whether:</para><para>(i) The consumer will incur a surrender charge, be
subject to the commencement of a new surrender period, lose existing benefits,
such as death, living, or other contractual benefits, or be subject to increased
fees, investment advisory fees, or charges for riders and similar product
enhancements;</para><para>(ii)
The consumer would benefit from product enhancements and improvements; and</para>
<para>(iii) The consumer has
had another annuity exchange or replacement and, in particular, an exchange
or replacement within the preceding thirty-six months.</para>
<para>(2) Before the execution of a purchase, exchange, or replacement of an annuity resulting from
a recommendation, an insurance producer, or an insurer if an insurance producer
is not involved, shall make reasonable efforts to obtain the consumer's suitability information.</para>
<para>(3) Except as expressly
permitted under subsection (4) of this section, an insurer shall not issue
an annuity recommended to a consumer unless there is a reasonable basis to
believe the annuity is suitable based on the consumer's suitability information.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Except as provided
under subdivision (4)(b) of this section, neither
an insurance producer, nor an insurer, shall
have any obligation to a consumer under subsection (1) or (3) of this section related to any annuity transaction if:</para>
<para>(i) No recommendation
is made;</para><para>(ii)
A recommendation was made and was later found to have been prepared based
on materially inaccurate information provided by the consumer;</para>
<para>(iii) A consumer refuses to provide relevant suitability information and the annuity transaction is not recommended;
or </para>
<para>(iv) A consumer decides
to enter into an annuity transaction that is not based on a recommendation
of the insurer or the insurance producer.</para><para>(b) An insurer's issuance of an annuity subject to
subdivision (4)(a) of this section shall be reasonable under all the circumstances
actually known to the insurer at the time the annuity is issued.</para>
<para>(5) An insurance producer,
or if no insurance producer is involved, the responsible insurer representative,
shall at the time of sale:</para><para>(a) Make a record of any recommendation subject to
subsection (1) of this section;</para><para>(b) Obtain a customer-signed statement documenting
a customer's refusal to provide suitability information, if any; and</para>
<para>(c) Obtain a customer-signed
statement acknowledging that an annuity transaction is not recommended if
a customer decides to enter into an annuity transaction that is not based
on the insurance producer's or insurer's recommendation.</para>
<para>(6)(a) An insurer shall
establish a supervision system that is reasonably designed to achieve the
insurer's and its insurance producers' compliance with this section, including,
but not limited to, the following requirements:</para><para>(i) The insurer shall maintain reasonable
procedures to inform its insurance producers of the requirements of this section
and shall incorporate such requirements into relevant insurance producer training
manuals;</para><para>(ii)
The insurer shall establish standards for insurance producer product training
and shall maintain reasonable procedures to require its insurance producers
to comply with the requirements of section 44-8108;</para><para>(iii) The insurer shall provide
product-specific training and training materials which explain all material
features of its annuity products to its insurance producers;</para>
<para>(iv) The insurer shall
maintain procedures for review of each recommendation prior to issuance of
an annuity that are designed to ensure that there is a reasonable basis to
determine that a recommendation is suitable. Such review procedures may apply
a screening system for the purpose of identifying selected transactions for
additional review and may be accomplished electronically or through other
means including, but not limited to, physical review. Such an electronic or
other system may be designed to require additional review only of those transactions
identified for additional review by the selection criteria;</para>
<para>(v) The insurer shall
maintain reasonable procedures to detect recommendations that are not suitable,
including, but not limited to, confirmation of consumer suitability information,
systematic customer surveys, interviews, confirmation letters, and programs
of internal monitoring. Nothing in this subdivision shall prevent an insurer
from complying with this subdivision by applying sampling procedures or by
confirming suitability information after issuance or delivery of the annuity;
and</para><para>(vi)
The insurer shall annually provide a report to senior management, including
the senior manager responsible for audit functions, which details a review,
with appropriate testing, reasonably designed to determine the effectiveness
of the supervision system, the exceptions found, and corrective action taken
or recommended, if any.</para><para>(b)(i)
Nothing in this subsection restricts an insurer from contracting for performance
of a function, including maintenance of procedures, required under subdivision
(a) of this subsection. An insurer is responsible for taking appropriate corrective
action and may be subject to sanctions and penalties pursuant to section 44-8107
regardless of whether the insurer contracts for performance of a function
and regardless of the insurer's compliance with subdivision (b)(ii) of this
subsection.</para><para>(ii)
An insurer's supervision system under subdivision (a) of this subsection shall
include supervision of contractual performance under this subsection. This
includes, but is not limited to, the following:</para><para>(A) Monitoring and, as appropriate,
conducting audits to assure that the contracted function is properly performed;
and</para><para>(B)
Annually obtaining a certification from a senior manager who has responsibility
for the contracted function that the manager has a reasonable basis to represent,
and does represent, that the function is properly performed.</para>
<para>(c) An insurer is not required to supervise an insurance producer's
recommendations to consumers of products other than the annuities offered
by the insurer.</para>
<para>(7) An insurance producer
shall not dissuade, or attempt to dissuade, a consumer from:</para>
<para>(a) Truthfully responding
to an insurer's request for confirmation of suitability information;</para>
<para>(b) Filing a complaint;
or</para><para>(c)
Cooperating with the investigation of a complaint.</para><para>(8)(a) Compliance with the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority Rules
pertaining to suitability and
supervision of annuity transactions shall satisfy the requirements
under this section if the insurer
complies with the requirements of subdivision (6)(b) of this section. This
subsection applies to Financial Industry Regulatory Authority broker-dealer
sales of variable annuities and fixed annuities if the suitability and supervision
is similar to those applied to variable annuity sales. However,
nothing in this subsection shall limit the ability of the Director of Insurance
to investigate potential violations
of and enforce the Nebraska Protection in Annuity Transactions
Act.</para>
<para>(b) An insurer seeking
to comply with the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority broker-dealer sales
of variable annuities and fixed annuities to satisfy the requirements of this
section shall:</para><para>(i)
Monitor the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority member broker-dealer using
information collected in the normal course of an insurer's business; and</para>
<para>(ii) Provide to the Financial
Industry Regulatory Authority member broker-dealer information and reports
that are reasonably appropriate to assist the Financial Industry Regulatory
Authority member broker-dealer to maintain its supervision system.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 875, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB887, &#167; 26.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>