<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id79"  statutenumber="44-8508" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8508</statuteno><catchline>Insurer; rights; duties; notice; policy; termination; vendor; duties.</catchline><para>Notwithstanding any other provision of law:</para><para>(1) An insurer may terminate or otherwise change the terms and conditions of a policy of portable electronics insurance only upon providing the vendor and enrolled customers with at least thirty days' notice, except that:</para><para>(a) An insurer may terminate an enrolled customer's insurance policy upon fifteen days' notice for:</para><para>(i) Discovery of fraud or material misrepresentation in obtaining coverage or in the presentation of a claim under such policy; or</para><para>(ii) Nonpayment of premium; or</para><para>(b) An insurer may immediately terminate an enrolled customer's insurance policy:</para><para>(i) If the enrolled customer ceases to have active service with the vendor of portable electronics; or</para><para>(ii) If an enrolled customer exhausts the aggregate limit of liability, if any, under the portable electronics insurance policy and the insurer sends notice of termination to the customer within thirty days after exhaustion of the limit. If such notice is not sent within the thirty-day period, the customer shall continue to be enrolled in such insurance policy notwithstanding the aggregate limit of liability until the insurer sends notice of termination to the customer;</para><para>(2) If the insurer changes the terms and conditions, the insurer shall provide the vendor with a revised policy or endorsement and each enrolled customer with a revised certificate, endorsement, updated brochure, or other evidence indicating a change in the terms and conditions has occurred and a summary of the material changes;</para><para>(3) If a portable electronics insurance policy is terminated by a vendor, the vendor shall mail or deliver written notice to each enrolled customer at least thirty days prior to the termination advising the customer of such termination and of the effective date of termination; and</para><para>(4) If notice is required under this section, it shall be:</para><para>(a) In writing and may be mailed or delivered to a vendor at the vendor's mailing address and to an enrolled customer at such customer's last-known mailing address on file with the insurer. The insurer or vendor, as applicable, shall maintain proof of mailing in a form authorized or accepted by the United States Postal Service or a commercial mail delivery service; or</para><para>(b) In electronic form. Disclosure of notice in electronic form to the enrolled customer shall be provided within thirty days after the purchase of the portable electronics. If notice is delivered in electronic form, the insurer or vendor, as applicable, shall maintain proof that the notice was sent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB535, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB306, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>