<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id42">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id44" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="44-8705"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8705</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Exchange Stakeholder Commission;
duties.</catchline><para>The
Nebraska Exchange Stakeholder Commission shall:</para>
<para>(1) Work with state
and federal agencies and policymakers to provide recommendations regarding
implementation and operation of the exchange, including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) Improving access
to high-quality, affordable health coverage options and improving policies
and processes on the exchange to ensure a positive and seamless consumer experience;</para>
<para>(b) Promoting competitiveness
of the exchange, minimizing administrative burden for issuers, and ensuring
consumer protections;</para><para>(c) Incorporating existing state policies, capabilities, and infrastructure
that can also assist in exchange implementation and operations;</para>
<para>(d) Ensuring
the effectiveness of the navigator grant program;</para><para>(e) Promoting a seamless
integration with the medicaid program and continuity of care for those transitioning
between publicly funded coverage and private coverage; and</para>
<para>(f) Ensuring
the small business health options program or SHOP Exchange meets the needs
and provides value to small businesses;</para><para>(2) Create technical and advisory groups
as needed to discuss issues related to the exchange and make recommendations
to the commission, state or federal agencies, and the Legislature;</para>
<para>(3) Assist the
exchange in meeting the stakeholder consultation requirements established
in 45 C.F.R. 155.130, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2013;</para>
<para>(4) Identify challenges
and problems in the implementation and operation of the exchange and prepare
recommendations to alleviate the problems identified; and</para>
<para>(5) Provide a report
on or before December 1, 2013, and each December 1 thereafter, to the Governor
and the Legislature concerning the implementation and operation of the exchange,
challenges and problems identified in the implementation and operation of
the exchange, and recommendations to address such problems and challenges.
The report to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB384, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>May 17, 2013</effectivedate><terminationdate>July 1, 2017</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>