<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id8">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id10" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="44-8502"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8502</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the
Portable Electronics Insurance Act: </para>
<para>(1) Customer
means a person who purchases portable electronics;</para><para>(2) Covered customer means
a customer who elects coverage pursuant to a portable electronics insurance
policy issued to a vendor of portable electronics;</para><para>(3) Director means the
Director of Insurance;</para><para>(4) Location means any physical location in this state or any web
site, call center, or other site or similar location to which Nebraska customers
may be directed;</para><para>(5) Portable electronics means a device that is personal, self-contained,
easily carried by an individual, and battery-operated and includes devices
used for electronic communication, viewing, listening, recording, computing,
or global positioning. Portable electronics does not include telecommunications
switching equipment, transmission wires, cellular site transceiver equipment,
or other equipment or system used by a telecommunications company to provide
telecommunications service to consumers;</para><para>(6)(a) Portable electronics insurance means
insurance that provides coverage for the repair or replacement of portable
electronics and may provide coverage for portable electronics that are lost,
stolen, damaged, or inoperable due to mechanical failure or malfunction or
suffer other similar causes of loss; and</para><para>(b) Portable electronics insurance does
not include:</para><para>(i) A service contract under the Motor Vehicle Service Contract
Reimbursement Insurance Act;</para><para>(ii) A service contract or extended warranty
providing coverage as described in subdivision (2) of section 44-102.01;</para>
<para>(iii) A policy
of insurance providing coverage for a seller's or manufacturer's obligations
under a warranty; or</para><para>(iv) A homeowner's, renter's, private passenger automobile, commercial
multiperil, or other similar policy;</para><para>(7) Portable electronics transaction means
the sale or lease of portable electronics by a vendor to a customer or the
sale of a service related to the use of portable electronics by a vendor to
a customer;</para><para>(8) Supervising entity means a business entity that is a licensed
insurance producer or insurer; and</para><para>(9) Vendor means a person in the business
of engaging in portable electronics transactions directly or indirectly.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB535, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Service Contract Reimbursement Insurance Act,</emphasis> see section 44-3520.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>