<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" id="id14" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="44-8703" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8703</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Exchange Stakeholder Commission; created; members; terms; vacancy; removal; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Exchange Stakeholder Commission is created. For administrative and budgetary purposes only, the commission shall be housed within the Department of Insurance. The commission shall be composed of eleven members as follows:</para><para>(a) Nine members shall be appointed by the Governor in the following manner:</para><para>(i) Four members to represent the interests of consumers who will access health insurance in the exchange with at least one of such members to represent the interests of rural consumers who will access health insurance in the exchange;</para><para>(ii) One member to represent the interests of small businesses who are qualified to purchase health insurance in the exchange;</para><para>(iii) Two members to represent the interests of health care providers in the state;</para><para>(iv) One member to represent the interests of health insurance carriers who are eligible to offer health plans in the exchange; and</para><para>(v) One member to represent the interests of health insurance agents. This member shall not be a captive agent of any health insurance carrier;</para><para>(b) The Director of Insurance or his or her designee is a nonvoting, ex officio member of the commission; and</para><para>(c) The director of the Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee is a nonvoting, ex officio member of the commission.</para><para>(2) The terms of appointed members of the commission shall commence on July 1, 2013.</para><para>(3) The appointed members of the commission shall serve for terms of three years, except that of the members first appointed, the Governor shall designate:</para><para>(a) One of the members representing the interests of health care providers in the state to serve a term of three years and the other to serve a term of two years;</para><para>(b) The member representing the interests of health insurance carriers to serve a term of two years;</para><para>(c) The member representing the interests of health insurance agents to serve a term of three years; and</para><para>(d) All other members to serve for terms of three years.</para><para>(4) A member may be reappointed at the expiration of his or her term. All succeeding appointments to the commission shall be made in the same manner as the original appointments are made, and succeeding appointees shall have the same qualifications as their predecessors.</para><para>(5) An individual appointed to fill a vacancy occurring other than by the expiration of a term of office shall be appointed for the unexpired term of the member such individual succeeds and shall be eligible for appointment to subsequent full terms thereafter.</para><para>(6) All appointments whether initial or subsequent shall be subject to the approval of a majority of the members of the Legislature, if the Legislature is in session, and, if the Legislature is not in session, any appointment shall be temporary until the next session of the Legislature, at which time a majority of the members of the Legislature may approve or disapprove such appointment.</para><para>(7) A member shall have his or her membership terminated if he or she ceases to meet the qualification for his or her appointment. A member may be removed from the commission for good cause upon written notice and upon an opportunity to be heard before the Governor. After the hearing, the Governor shall file in the office of the Secretary of State a complete statement of the charges and the findings and disposition together with a complete record of the proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB384, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB770, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>April 7, 2016</effectivedate><terminationdate>July 1, 2016</terminationdate></source></law>
</legaldoc>