<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-8205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-8205</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of authority; application; fee; plan of operation; filings required; director; powers; subsequent amendments; books and records.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall transact the business of insurance as a captive insurer without first applying for and obtaining from the director a certificate of authority. An applicant shall submit a nonrefundable application fee of five hundred dollars with a plan of operation which includes:</para><para>(a) Articles of incorporation and bylaws or other documents of organization;</para><para>(b) Pro forma financial statements for two years;</para><para>(c) The source and nature of initial and ongoing capital;</para><para>(d) A feasibility study which discloses the types and adequacy of the insurance programs of the captive insurer, the identity of the parent and affiliated entities benefiting from such insurance program, and the relationships to the captive insurer as well as all projected expenses, contracts, and a holding company system chart identifying the ownership and relationship of the parent and affiliated entities;</para><para>(e) Copies of all insurance and reinsurance agreements of the captive insurer as well as disclosure of all transactions material to the insurance operations;</para><para>(f) Financial condition of the parent and, if requested by the director, any affiliated entities, benefiting from the captive insurance program;</para><para>(g) A management overview including competence, experience, and integrity of those controlling the insurance operations;</para><para>(h) A statement submitting to the jurisdiction of the director; and</para><para>(i) An explanation of how the operation of the captive insurer promotes the development of a Nebraska business.</para><para>(2) If the plan of operation is accepted and approved by the director, the articles and other documents of organization shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. A copy of the articles or other documents of organization, certified by the Secretary of State, shall be filed with the director. Amendments to organizational documents shall be deemed a change to the plan of operation and shall be filed with and approved by the director before they are submitted to the Secretary of State.</para><para>(3) The director may refuse to issue a certificate of authority until he or she is reasonably satisfied that the plan of operation contains sufficient indication of a successful insurance operation and that the captive insurer will be able to meet expected or ongoing policy obligations.</para><para>(4) A captive insurer shall obtain prior written approval of any subsequent amendments to any components of the original plan of operation. The director shall deem that any captive insurer that has failed to disclose a transaction or a series of transactions that would circumvent the Captive Insurers Act to be in hazardous financial condition with respect to the public or its policyholders and subject to suspension or revocation of the certificate of authority of the captive insurer.</para><para>(5) Except as otherwise authorized in section 44-8216, a captive insurer may only transact any line or lines of insurance specified in subdivisions (5), (7), (8), (9), (10), and (18) of section 44-201. A captive insurer shall not transact directors and officers insurance.</para><para>(6) Every captive insurer shall provide to the director books and records in the state as to enable the financial examination of the captive insurer by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 39. </para></source></law></legaldoc>