<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id98"><amendatorysection statutenumber="44-9104" chaptername="Insurance"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9104</statuteno><catchline>Corporate governance annual disclosure; submission to director; review; cross reference to other documents.</catchline><para>(1) An insurer, or the insurance group of which the insurer is a member, shall, no later than June 1 of each calendar year, submit to the director a corporate governance annual disclosure that contains the information described in section 44-9105. Notwithstanding any request from the director made pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, if the insurer is a member of an insurance group, the insurer shall submit the disclosure required by this section to the director of the lead state for the insurance group, in accordance with the laws of the lead state, as determined by the procedures outlined in the Financial Analysis Handbook adopted by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners.</para><para>(2) The corporate governance annual disclosure must include a signature of the insurer’s or insurance group’s chief executive officer or corporate secretary attesting to the best of that individual’s belief and knowledge that the insurer or insurance group has implemented the corporate governance practices contained in the corporate governance annual disclosure and that a copy of the disclosure has been provided to the insurer’s board of directors or the appropriate committee thereof. </para><para>(3) An insurer not required to submit a corporate governance annual disclosure under this section shall do so upon the director’s request.</para><para>(4) For purposes of completing the corporate governance annual disclosure, the insurer or insurance group may provide information regarding corporate governance at the ultimate controlling parent level, an intermediate holding company level, or the individual legal entity level, depending upon how the insurer or insurance group has structured its system of corporate governance. The insurer or insurance group is encouraged to make the corporate governance annual disclosure at the level at which the insurer’s or insurance group’s risk appetite is determined, the level at which the earnings, capital, liquidity, operations, and reputation of the insurer are overseen collectively and at which the supervision of those factors are coordinated and exercised, or the level at which legal liability for failure of general corporate governance duties would be placed. If the insurer or insurance group determines the level of reporting based on one of these three criteria, it shall indicate which of the three criteria was used to determine the level of reporting and explain any subsequent changes in the level of reporting.</para><para>(5) The review of the corporate governance annual disclosure and any additional requests for information shall be made through the lead state as determined by the procedures within the Financial Analysis Handbook adopted by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners.</para><para>(6) Insurers providing information substantially similar to the information required by the Corporate Governance Annual Disclosure Act in other documents provided to the director, including proxy statements filed in conjunction with the requirements of section 44-2132 or other state or federal filings provided to the director, shall not be required to duplicate such information in the corporate governance annual disclosure, but shall only be required to cross reference the document in which such information is included.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB772, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>