<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id156"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-9206"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9206</statuteno><catchline>Nonresident public adjuster license; application; qualifications; fee; director; verify status; termination of license; when.</catchline><para>(1) An individual applying for a nonresident public adjuster license shall make application to the director in the manner prescribed by the director and declare under penalty of denial, suspension, or revocation of the license that the statements made in the application are true, correct, and complete to the best of such individual's knowledge and belief. Before approving an application for a nonresident public adjuster license, the director shall find that the applicant:</para><para>(a) Is licensed as a resident public adjuster and in good standing in such individual’s home state and that such home state awards nonresident public adjuster licenses to residents of this state on the same basis as provided for in the Public Adjusters Licensing Act; and</para><para>(b) Has paid the nonresident licensing fee, not to exceed one hundred dollars, prescribed by the director.</para><para>(2) The director may verify the licensing status of a nonresident public adjuster through the producer data base maintained by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners, its affiliates, or subsidiaries.</para><para>(3) As a condition to continuation of a nonresident public adjuster license, a licensed nonresident public adjuster shall maintain a resident public adjuster license in good standing in his or her home state.</para><para>(4) A nonresident public adjuster license issued pursuant to this section shall terminate and be surrendered immediately to the director if the home state public adjuster license terminates for any reason, unless the individual has been issued a license as a resident public adjuster in a new home state and such new home state has reciprocity with this state. A licensed nonresident public adjuster shall notify the director of any change to a new home state as soon as possible, but no later than thirty days after receiving a license as a resident public adjuster from the new home state. The nonresident public adjuster shall include both the new and the old addresses in the notice to the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>