<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id684"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-9204"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9204</statuteno><catchline>License required; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not operate as or represent that such person is a public adjuster in this state unless such person is licensed as a public adjuster in accordance with the Public Adjusters Licensing Act.</para><para>(2) A public adjuster shall not misrepresent to any insured that such public adjuster is an adjuster representing an insurer in any capacity, including acting as an employee of the insurer or acting as an independent adjuster unless so appointed by an insurer in writing to act on behalf of the insurer for that specific claim or purpose. A public adjuster is prohibited from charging any insured a fee when appointed by the insurer and the appointment is accepted by the public adjuster.</para><para>(3) A public adjuster shall not, directly or indirectly, solicit, or enter into, an agreement for the repair or replacement of damaged property on which such public adjuster has engaged to adjust or settle claims for losses or damages of the insured.</para><para>(4) Notwithstanding subsection (1) of this section, licensing as a public adjuster shall not be required for:</para><para>(a) An attorney admitted to practice in this state, when acting in the attorney’s professional capacity as an attorney;</para><para>(b) A person who negotiates or settles claims arising under a life or health insurance policy or an annuity contract;</para><para>(c) A person employed only for the purpose of obtaining facts surrounding a loss or furnishing technical assistance to a licensed public adjuster, including, but not limited to, a photographer, estimator, private investigator, engineer, or handwriting expert;</para><para>(d) A licensed health care provider, or an employee of a licensed health care provider, who prepares or files a health claim form on behalf of a patient; or</para><para>(e) A person who settles subrogation claims between insurers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>