<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id258"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-9107"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9107</statuteno><catchline>Review of corporate governance annual disclosure; third-party consultants; National Association of Insurance Commissioners; written agreement; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The director may retain, at the insurer's expense, third-party consultants, including attorneys, actuaries, accountants, and other experts not otherwise a part of the director's staff, as may be reasonably necessary to assist the director in reviewing the corporate governance annual disclosure and related information or the insurer's compliance with the Corporate Governance Annual Disclosure Act.</para><para>(2) Any persons retained under subsection (1) of this section shall be under the direction and control of the director and shall act in a purely advisory capacity.</para><para>(3) The National Association of Insurance Commissioners and third-party consultants shall be subject to the same confidentiality standards and requirements as the director.</para><para>(4) As part of the retention process, a third-party consultant shall verify to the director, with notice to the insurer, that the third-party consultant is free of a conflict of interest and that it has internal procedures in place to monitor compliance with a conflict of interest and to comply with the confidentiality standards and requirements of the Corporate Governance Annual Disclosure Act.</para><para>(5) A written agreement with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant governing sharing and use of information provided pursuant to the Corporate Governance Annual Disclosure Act shall contain the following provisions and expressly require the written consent of the insurer prior to making public information provided under the act:</para><para>(a) Specific procedures and protocols for maintaining the confidentiality and security of information related to the corporate governance annual disclosure that is shared with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant pursuant to the act;</para><para>(b) Procedures and protocols for sharing by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners only with other state regulators from states in which the insurance group has domiciled insurers. The agreement shall provide that the recipient agrees in writing to maintain the confidentiality and privileged status of the documents, materials, or other information related to the corporate governance annual disclosure and has verified in writing the legal authority to maintain confidentiality.</para><para>(c) A provision specifying that (i) ownership of the information related to the corporate governance annual disclosure that is shared with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant remains with the Department of Insurance and (ii) the National Association of Insurance Commissioners’ or third-party consultant’s use of the information is subject to the direction of the director;</para><para>(d) A provision that prohibits the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant from storing the information shared pursuant to the Corporate Governance Annual Disclosure Act in a permanent data base after the underlying analysis is completed;</para><para>(e) A provision requiring the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or third-party consultant to provide prompt notice to the director and to the insurer or insurance group regarding any subpoena, request for disclosure, or request for production of the insurer’s or insurance group’s information related to the corporate governance annual disclosure; and</para><para>(f) A requirement that the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant consent to intervention by an insurer in any judicial or administrative action in which the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant may be required to disclose confidential information about the insurer shared with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or a third-party consultant pursuant to the Corporate Governance Annual Disclosure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB772, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>