<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id162"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-9216"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9216</statuteno><catchline>Records; contents; retention; inspection.</catchline><para>(1) A public adjuster shall maintain a complete record of each transaction as a public adjuster. The records required by this section shall include the following:</para><para>(a) The name of the insured;</para><para>(b) The date, location, and amount of the loss;</para><para>(c) A copy of the contract between the public adjuster and the insured;</para><para>(d) The name of the insurer, amount, expiration date, and policy number for each policy carried with respect to the loss;</para><para>(e) An itemized statement of the amount recovered for the insured;</para><para>(f) An itemized statement of all compensation received by the public adjuster, from any source whatsoever, in connection with the loss;</para><para>(g) A register of all money received, deposited, disbursed, or withdrawn in connection with a transaction with an insured, including fees, transfers, and disbursements from a trust account and all transactions concerning all interest-bearing accounts;</para><para>(h) The name of the public adjuster who executed the contract;</para><para>(i) The name of the attorney representing the insured, if applicable, and the name of the claims representative of the insurer; and</para><para>(j) Evidence of financial responsibility in a format prescribed by the director.</para><para>(2) Records shall be maintained for at least five years after the termination of the transaction with an insured and shall be open to examination by the department at all times.</para><para>(3) Records submitted to the department in accordance with this section that contain information identified in writing as proprietary by the public adjuster shall be treated as confidential by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>