<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id374"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-9210"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9210</statuteno><catchline>Individual; issuance of license; expiration; renewal; fee; lapsed license; reinstatement; business entity; license; expiration; renewal; fee; lapsed license; reinstatement; license; contents; licensee; duties; director; powers; renewal procedures.</catchline><para>(1)(a) An individual who meets the requirements for a resident public adjuster license shall be issued such license. An individual who meets the requirements for a nonresident public adjuster license shall be issued such license.</para><para>(b) Each resident public adjuster license and each nonresident public adjuster license shall expire on the last day of the month of such public adjuster’s birthday in the first year after issuance of such license in which his or her age is divisible by two.</para><para>(c) Each resident public adjuster license and each nonresident public adjuster license may be renewed within the ninety-day period immediately preceding the expiration date upon payment of the renewal fee, not to exceed one hundred dollars, prescribed by the director. A resident public adjuster or nonresident public adjuster who allows his or her license to lapse may, within the twelve-month period immediately following the expiration date, reinstate the same license without the necessity of passing a written examination upon payment of a reinstatement fee, not to exceed one hundred twenty-five dollars, prescribed by the director in addition to the renewal fee.</para><para>(d) The director may grant an individual licensee who is unable to comply with license renewal procedures due to military service or some other extenuating circumstance, including, but not limited to, a long-term medical disability, a waiver of any examination requirement or any other fine, fee, or sanction imposed for failure to comply with renewal procedures.</para><para>(2)(a) A business entity that has met the requirements of the Public Adjusters Licensing Act shall be issued a business entity public adjuster license.</para><para>(b) Each business entity public adjuster license shall expire on April 30 of each year.</para><para>(c) A business entity public adjuster license may be renewed within the ninety-day period immediately preceding the expiration date upon payment of the renewal fee, not to exceed one hundred fifty dollars, prescribed by the director. A business entity public adjuster that allows its license to lapse may, within the thirty-day period immediately following the expiration date, renew the same license upon payment of a late renewal fee, not to exceed one hundred twenty-five dollars, prescribed by the director in addition to the renewal fee.</para><para>(d) Any business entity public adjuster license renewed within the thirty-day period immediately following the expiration date pursuant to this subsection shall be deemed to have been renewed before the expiration date.</para><para>(3)(a) Each license issued pursuant to the Public Adjusters Licensing Act shall contain the licensee's name, address, and license number, the date of issuance, the lines of authority, the expiration date, and any other information the director deems necessary.</para><para>(b) Each licensee shall inform the director, by any means acceptable to the director, of any change of legal name, address, or other information submitted on the application within thirty days after the change. Any licensee failing to provide such notification shall be subject to a fine by the director of not more than five hundred dollars per violation, suspension of the license until the change is reported to the director, or both.</para><para>(c) Each licensee doing business under any name other than the licensee's legal name shall notify the director prior to using the assumed name.</para><para>(d) Each licensee shall be subject to the Unfair Insurance Trade Practices Act and the Unfair Insurance Claims Settlement Practices Act.</para><para>(e) Each licensee shall report to the director any administrative action taken against such licensee in another jurisdiction or by another governmental agency in this state within thirty days of the final disposition of the matter. This report shall include a copy of the order, consent to order, or other relevant legal documents.</para><para>(f) Each licensee shall report to the director any criminal prosecution of such licensee taken in any jurisdiction within thirty days of arraignment. The report shall include a copy of the initial complaint filed, the order resulting from the hearing, and any other relevant legal documents.</para><para>(4) The director may contract with nongovernmental entities, including the National Association of Insurance Commissioners or any affiliates or subsidiaries that the National Association of Insurance Commissioners oversees, to perform any ministerial functions, including the collection of fees, related to the administration of the Public Adjusters Licensing Act.</para><para>(5) The director may establish license renewal procedures by rule and regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Unfair Insurance Claims Settlement Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 44-1536.</para><para><emphasis>Unfair Insurance Trade Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 44-1521.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>