<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id575"><amendatorysection chaptername="Insurance" statutenumber="44-9205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>44-9205</statuteno><catchline>Resident public adjuster license; application; qualifications; fee; examination.</catchline><para>An individual applying for a resident public adjuster license shall make application to the director on the uniform individual application and declare under penalty of denial, suspension, or revocation of the license that the statements made in the application are true, correct, and complete to the best of such individual's knowledge and belief. Before approving an application for a resident public adjuster license, the director shall find that such individual:</para><para>(1) Is at least eighteen years of age. Notwithstanding the provisions of section 43-2101, if an individual is issued a license pursuant to the Public Adjusters Licensing Act, his or her minority ends;</para><para>(2) Has his or her principal place of residence or principal place of business in this state;</para><para>(3) Has not committed any act that is a ground for denial, suspension, or revocation set forth in section 44-9211;</para><para>(4) Has paid the resident licensing fee, not to exceed one hundred dollars, prescribed by the director;</para><para>(5) Except as otherwise provided under the act, has passed the examinations required by section 44-9208;</para><para>(6) Is trustworthy, reliable, and of good reputation, evidence of which may be determined by the director;</para><para>(7) Is financially responsible to exercise the license and has provided proof of financial responsibility as required in section 44-9212; and</para><para>(8) Maintains an office in this state with public access to such office by reasonable appointment or regular business hours.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB743, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>