<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-404</statuteno><catchline>Structures; erection, maintenance in excess of one hundred fifty feet; application; form; contents; permit; issuance; considerations.</catchline><para>The application for the permit, required by section 3-403, shall be made in writing on forms prescribed by the Department of Aeronautics and shall contain or be accompanied by details as to the location, construction, height, and dimensions of the proposed structure, the nature of its intended use, and such other information as the Director of Aeronautics may require. Upon the filing of such application the director shall make an investigation and an aeronautical study of such proposed construction and its effect, if any, upon air navigation, and the health, welfare, and safety of the public. If the director, upon such investigation, shall determine that such proposed structure will not constitute a hazard to air navigation and will not interfere unduly with the public right of freedom of transit in commerce through the air space affected thereby, he shall issue to the applicant a permit, required by section 3-403, authorizing the erection and construction of such structure, subject to such conditions as to marking and lighting as the department may prescribe by its rules and regulations, authorized by section 3-407. If he does not so determine, he shall deny the application. In making such investigation, aeronautical study, and determination, the director shall consider (1) the character of flying operations expected to be conducted in the area concerned, (2) the nature of the terrain, (3) the character of the neighborhood, (4) the uses to which the property concerned is devoted or adaptable, (5) the proximity to existing airports, airways, control areas, and control zones, (6) the height of existing, adjacent structures, and (7) all the facts and circumstances existing. He shall impose only such restrictions or requirements as may be reasonably necessary to effectuate the purpose of sections 3-401 to 3-409.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 7, &#167; 4, p. 68.</para></source></law></legaldoc>