<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-215"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-215</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Municipality; general powers; rules and regulations; adopt.</catchline><para id="id00">In addition to the general power conferred in the Revised Airports Act and section 18-1502 and without limitation thereof, a municipality which has established or may hereafter establish airports, restricted landing areas, or other air navigation facilities, or which has acquired or set apart or may hereafter acquire or set apart real property for such purpose or purposes, is hereby authorized:</para><para id="id00">(1) To vest authority for the construction, enlargement, improvement, maintenance, equipment, operation, and regulation thereof in an officer, a board, or a body of such municipality by ordinance or resolution which shall prescribe the powers and duties of such officer, board, or body. The expense of such construction, enlargement, improvement, maintenance, equipment, operation, and regulation shall be a responsibility of the municipality;</para><para id="id00">(2) To adopt and amend all needful rules, regulations, and ordinances for the management, government, and use of any properties under its control, whether within or without the territorial limits of the municipality; to appoint airport guards or police, with full police powers; to fix by ordinance or resolution, as may be appropriate, penalties for the violation of the rules, regulations, and ordinances, and enforce the penalties in the same manner in which penalties prescribed by other rules, regulations, and ordinances of the municipality are enforced. For purposes of such management, government, and direction of public use, such part of all highways, roads, streets, avenues, boulevards, and territory as adjoins or lies within five hundred feet of the limits of any airport or restricted landing area acquired or maintained under the Revised Airports Act and section 18-1502 shall be under like control and management of the municipality. It may also adopt and enact rules, regulations, and ordinances designed to safeguard the public upon or beyond the limits of private airports or landing strips within such municipality or its police jurisdiction against the perils and hazards of instrumentalities used in aerial navigation. Rules, regulations, and ordinances shall be published as provided by general law or the charter of the municipality for the publication of similar rules, regulations, and ordinances. They must conform to and be consistent with the laws of this state and the rules and regulations of the Division of Aeronautics of the Department of Transportation and shall be kept in conformity, as nearly as may be, with the then current federal legislation governing aeronautics and the regulations duly promulgated thereunder and rules and standards issued from time to time pursuant thereto;</para><para id="id00">(3) To lease for a term not exceeding ten years such airports, other air navigation facilities, or real property acquired or set apart for airport purposes to private parties, any municipal or state government, the national government, or any department of any such government for operation; to lease or assign space, area, improvements, or equipment on such airports for a term not exceeding ten years to private parties, any municipal or state government, the national government, or any department of any such government for operation or use consistent with the purposes of the Revised Airports Act and section 18-1502; to sell any part of such airports, other air navigation facilities, or real property to any municipal or state government, or to the United States or any department or instrumentality thereof, for aeronautical purposes or purposes incidental thereto, and to confer the privileges or concessions of supplying upon its airports goods, commodities, things, services, and facilities, so long as, in each case, the public is not thereby deprived of its rightful, equal, and uniform use thereof;</para><para id="id00">(4) To sell or lease any real or personal property, acquired for airport purposes and belonging to the municipality, which, in the judgment of its governing body, may not be required for aeronautic purposes, in accordance with the laws of this state, or the provisions of the charter of the municipality, governing the sale or leasing of similar municipally owned property. The proceeds of the sale of any property the purchase price of which was obtained by the sale of bonds shall be deposited in the sinking fund from which funds have been authorized to be taken to finance such bonds. In the event all the proceeds of such sale are not needed to pay the principal of the bonds remaining unpaid, the remainder shall be paid into the general fund of the municipality. The proceeds of sales of property the purchase price of which was paid from appropriations shall be paid into the general fund of the municipality;</para><para id="id00">(5) To determine the charges or rental for the use of any properties under its control and the charges for any services or accommodations, and the terms and conditions under which such properties may be used, so long as in all cases the public shall not be deprived of its rightful, equal, and uniform use of such property. Charges shall be reasonable and uniform for the same class of service and established with due regard to the property and improvements used and the expense of operation to the municipality. To enforce the payment of charges, the municipality shall have a lien and may enforce it, substantially as is provided by law for liens and the enforcement thereof, for repairs to or the improvement, storage, or care of any personal property; and</para><para id="id00">(6) To exercise all powers necessarily incidental to the exercise of the general and special powers granted in the Revised Airports Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 34, &#167; 8, p. 161; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 57. </para></source><annotation><para>The Legislature has empowered municipalities to impose use charges for the privilege of using municipal airport facilities. City of Ord v. Biemond, 175 Neb. 333, 122 N.W.2d 6 (1963).</para><para>City is given power to enact rules and regulations governing use of airport. Brasier v. Cribbett, 166 Neb. 145, 88 N.W.2d 235 (1958).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>