<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-156"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>3-156</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Aeronautics Trust Fund; created; real property; proceeds of sale; how used; investment.</catchline><para id="id00">The Aeronautics Trust Fund is created. The necessary expenses incurred in the sale of property under section 3-155 shall be paid from the Aeronautics Cash Fund, and the proceeds from the sale of such property shall be credited to the Aeronautics Trust Fund after reimbursement of costs of sale have been made to the Aeronautics Cash Fund. The net proceeds from the disposal of such property shall be used by the division in conformance with any agreements upon which the Federal Aviation Administration conditions its consent to the sale of the aforementioned land and the quit claim deeds (1) filed in the office of the register of deeds of Dodge County on November 17, 1947, and recorded in Deeds Record 89 on page 342 and September 16, 1948, and recorded in Deeds Record 89 on page 578, (2) filed in the office of the register of deeds of Red Willow County on September 16, 1948, in Deeds Record 71 on page 17, September 14, 1966, in Deeds Record 91 on page 281, and December 17, 1968, in Deeds Record 93 on page 549, (3) filed in the office of the register of deeds of Clay County on November 17, 1947, in Deeds Record 86 on page 561, September 16, 1948, in Deeds Record 87 on page 148, and March 14, 1968, in Deeds Record 95 on page 321, (4) filed in the office of the register of deeds of Fillmore County on September 16, 1948, in Deeds Record 39 on page 229, February 21, 1968, in Deeds Record 25 on page 90, January 26, 1948, in Deeds Record 39 on page 189, September 21, 1948, in Deeds Record 39 on page 236, and February 13, 1968, in Deeds Record 25 on page 83, and (5) filed in the office of the register of deeds of Thayer County on January 31, 1948, in Deeds Record 48 on page 493, September 16, 1948, in Deeds Record 48 on page 581, and December 29, 1967, in Deeds Record 58 on page 531, and the rules and regulations of the Federal Aviation Administration, part 155, adopted December 7, 1962. Any money in the Aeronautics Trust Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the Department of Aeronautics Trust Fund on July 1, 2017, to the Aeronautics Trust Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 23, &#167; 2, p. 200; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 165, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 46. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2017</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>