<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-503</statuteno><catchline>Airport authority; acquisition of property; terms; eminent domain; relinquishment; insurance.</catchline><para>(1) Any city creating an authority shall by resolution convey or transfer to it any existing airport or any other property of the city for use in connection with a project, including real and personal property owned or leased by the city and used or useful in connection therewith. In case of real property so conveyed, the title thereto shall remain in the city, but the authority shall have the use and occupancy of such real property for so long as its corporate existence shall continue. In the case of personal property so conveyed, the title shall pass to the authority. Any conveyance of an existing airport shall be subject to any leases or agreements duly and validly made by the city affecting such airports or the property so conveyed, except that any such lease or agreement which is inconsistent with the ability of the authority to issue negotiable bonds may be renegotiated by the authority.</para><para>(2) Such city may acquire by purchase or condemnation real property in the name of the city for the projects or for the widening of existing roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways, or for new roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways to a project, or partly for such purposes and partly for other city purposes, by purchase or condemnation in the manner provided by law for the acquisition of real property by such city, except that if property is to be acquired outside the zoning jurisdiction of the city creating the authority when such city is of the metropolitan class, approval shall be obtained from the county board of the county where the property is located before the right of eminent domain may be exercised. Such city may also close any roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways as may be necessary or convenient to facilitate the construction or operation of a project.</para><para>(3) Contracts may be entered into between the city and an authority, or between other political subdivisions of the State of Nebraska and such city or authority, or between each and any of them, providing for the conveyance of property to such city or authority for use in connection with a project, and for the closing of streets, roads, parkways, avenues, or highways. The amounts, terms, and conditions of payment if any shall be made by such city or authority in connection with the conveyances. The contracts may also contain covenants by such city or such political subdivision, as to the road, street, parkway, avenue, or highway improvements to be made by such city or such political subdivision. Any city council may authorize such contracts between the city and the authority by resolution, and no other authorization on the part of the city for such contracts shall be necessary. All obligations of the city for the payment of money to an authority incurred in carrying out the Cities Airport Authorities Act shall be included in and provided for by each annual or biennial budget of such city thereafter made until fully discharged. In the case of other political subdivisions of the state, such contracts shall be authorized as provided by law.</para><para>(4) An authority operating under the act may acquire real property for a project in the name of the city in which it was established at the cost and expense of the authority by purchase or condemnation pursuant to the laws relating to the condemnation of land by cities and subdivision (4) of section 3-504, except that if property is to be acquired outside the zoning jurisdiction of the city creating the authority when such city is of the metropolitan class, approval shall be obtained from the county board of the county where the property is located before the right of eminent domain may be exercised. The authority shall have the use and occupancy of such real property so long as its corporate existence shall continue.</para><para>(5) In case an authority shall have the use and occupancy of any real property which it shall determine is no longer required for a project then, if such real property was acquired at the cost and expense of the city, the authority shall have the power to surrender its use and occupancy thereof to the city. If such real property was acquired at the cost and expense of the authority, then the authority shall have power to sell, lease, or otherwise dispose of the real property. The authority shall retain the proceeds of sale, rentals, or other money derived from the disposition of such real property for its corporate purposes.</para><para>(6) If the authority does not provide insurance coverage for the real property improvements to real property and the real property of which it has the use and occupancy and the city provides insurance coverage for such improvements and property and names the authority as the named insured, the authority shall reimburse the city for purchasing the insurance coverage if reimbursement is requested by the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 9, &#167; 3, p. 113; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 22, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 354, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 123, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1116, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>An airport authority acquiring real property must bring an action in the name of the city in which it was established for and on behalf, of the airport authority. Airport Auth. of Village of Greeley v. Dugan, 259 Neb. 860, 612 N.W.2d 913 (2000).</para><para>Municipal airport authorities are authorized to acquire property by condemnation for establishing airports. Seward County Board of Commissioners v. City of Seward, 196 Neb. 266, 242 N.W.2d 849 (1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>