<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-107"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>3-107</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Division; general supervision; Highway Cash Fund; use for administration of the division; projects; state funds; expenditure; recovery.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The division shall have general supervision over aeronautics within this state. It is empowered and directed to encourage, foster, and assist in the development of aeronautics in this state and encourage the establishment of airports and other air navigation facilities.</para><para id="id00">(2) The Department of Transportation may budget for and pay any of the costs related to the administration of the division, including, but not limited to, employee salaries and benefits, out of the Highway Cash Fund, as the Director-State Engineer determines, in his or her sole discretion, to be in the best interest of transportation in Nebraska. Such costs do not include costs related to the construction, reconstruction, repair, operation, or maintenance of airport infrastructure, including runways, concrete surfacing, hangers or capital improvements, buildings, and structures.</para><para id="id00">(3) No state funds for the acquisition, engineering, construction, improvement, or maintenance of airports shall be expended upon any project or for any work upon any such project which is not done under the supervision of the division. When any airport which has received state grant funds pursuant to the State Aeronautics Act ceases to be an airport or a privately owned public use airport, the division shall, consistent with all other provisions of state and federal law, seek to recover so much of the state funds provided to the airport as it may and shall deposit any such funds so recovered into the Aeronautics Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 5, &#167; 6(1), p. 83; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 609, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB138, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>A county should not be able to thwart the strong interest of the state in the promotion of aviation through the medium of its zoning authority. Seward County Board of Commissioners v. City of Seward, 196 Neb. 266, 242 N.W.2d 849 (1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>