<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-612</statuteno><catchline>Property; county; authority; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any county creating an authority shall by resolution or resolutions, convey or transfer to it any existing airport or any other property of the county for use in connection with a project, including real and personal property owned or leased by the county and used or useful in connection therewith. In case of real property so conveyed, the title thereto shall remain in the county, but the authority shall have the use and occupancy thereof for so long as its corporate existence shall continue. In the case of personal property so conveyed, the title shall pass to the authority. Any conveyance of an existing airport shall be subject to any leases or agreements duly and validly made by the county affecting such airport or the property so conveyed; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that any such lease or agreement which is inconsistent with the ability of the authority to issue negotiable bonds may be renegotiated by the authority.</para><para>(2) Such county may acquire by purchase or condemnation real property in the name of the county for the projects or for the widening of existing roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways, or for new roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways to a project, or partly for such purposes and partly for other county purposes, by purchase or condemnation in the manner provided by law for the acquisition of real property by such county. Such county may also close any roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways as may be necessary or convenient to facilitate the construction or operation of a project.</para><para>(3) Contracts may be entered into between the county and an authority, or between other political subdivisions of the State of Nebraska and such county or authority, or between each and any of them, providing for the conveyance of property to such county or authority for use in connection with a project, and for the closing of streets, roads, parkways, avenues, or highways. The amounts, terms, and conditions of payment if any shall be made by such county or authority in connection with such conveyances. Such contracts may also contain covenants by such county, or such political subdivision, as to the road, street, parkway, avenue, or highway improvements to be made by such county or such political subdivision. Any county board may authorize such contracts between the county and the authority by resolution, and no other authorization on the part of such county for such contracts shall be necessary. All obligations of such county for the payment of money to an authority incurred in carrying out the provisions of sections 3-601 to 3-622 shall be included in and provided for by each annual budget of such county thereafter made until fully discharged. In the case of other political subdivisions of the state, such contracts shall be authorized as provided by law.</para><para>(4) An authority operating under the provisions of sections 3-601 to 3-622 may acquire real property for a project in the name of the county in which it was established at the cost and expense of the authority by purchase or condemnation pursuant to the laws relating to the condemnation of land by counties and subdivision (4) of section 3-613. The authority shall have the use and occupancy of such real property so long as its corporate existence shall continue.</para><para>(5) In case an authority shall have the use and occupancy of any real property which it shall determine is no longer required for a project then, if such real property was acquired at the cost and expense of the county, the authority shall have the power to surrender its use and occupancy thereof to the county. If such real property was acquired at the cost and expense of the authority, then the authority shall have power to sell, lease, or otherwise dispose of such real property. Such authority shall retain the proceeds of sale, rentals, or other money derived from the disposition thereof for its corporate purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 141, &#167; 12, p. 652; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 22, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>