<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-705"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-705</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; expenses; quorum; delegation; term of existence; disposition of rights and properties; jurisdiction.</catchline><para>The members of the board shall not be entitled to compensation for their services, but shall be entitled to reimbursement for expenses paid or incurred in the performance of the duties imposed upon them by the provisions of sections 3-701 to 3-716 with reimbursement to be made in the same manner as provided in section 23-1112 for county officers and employees. A majority of the members of the board then in office shall constitute a quorum. The board may delegate to one or more of its members, or to its officers, agents, and employees, such powers and duties as it may deem proper. The joint authority and its corporate existence shall continue only for a period of thirty years from the date of its initial organization and thereafter until all its liabilities have been met and its bonds have been paid in full or such liabilities and bonds have otherwise been discharged or arrangements for such payment or discharge duly made and provided for. When all liabilities incurred by the joint authority of every kind and character have been met and all its bonds have been paid in full, or such liabilities and bonds have otherwise been discharged or arrangements for such payment or discharge duly made and provided for, all rights and properties of the joint authority shall pass to and be vested in such public body as the board may deem advisable and in the best public interest, and the board may make such agreements and take such actions as it shall determine upon with respect thereto. Provision for ultimate disposition of the rights and properties of the joint authority may also be set forth in the agreement pursuant to which the joint authority is organized, and any such provisions shall be controlling. The joint authority shall have and retain full and exclusive jurisdiction and control over all projects under its jurisdiction, with the right and duty to charge and collect revenue therefrom, for the benefit of the holders of any of its bonds or other liabilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 24, &#167; 5, p. 205; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 15.</para></source></law></legaldoc>