<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-103</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Division of Aeronautics; director; appointment; qualifications; duties; oath.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The Division of Aeronautics shall be a division of the Department of Transportation.</para><para id="id00">(2)(a) Until December 31, 2017, the chief administrative officer of the division shall be the director, to be known as the Director of Aeronautics, and shall be appointed by the Governor, subject to confirmation by the Legislature, with due regard to his or her fitness through aeronautical education and by knowledge of and recent practical experience in aeronautics. The director shall devote full time to the performance of his or her official duties and shall not have any pecuniary interest in, stock in, or bonds of any civil aeronautics enterprise. The director shall, before assuming the duties of the office, take and subscribe an oath, such as is required by state officers. The director shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201. The director shall receive such compensation as the Governor, with the approval of the commission, shall determine, subject to the provisions of the legislative appropriations bill.</para><para>(b) Beginning January 1, 2018, the chief administrative officer of the division shall be the Director of Aeronautics who shall be appointed by and report directly to the Director-State Engineer, subject to confirmation by the Legislature, with due regard to his or her fitness through aeronautical education and by knowledge of and recent practical experience in aeronautics. The director shall devote full time to the performance of his or her official duties and shall not have any pecuniary interest in, stock in, or bonds of any civil aeronautics enterprise. The director shall, before assuming the duties of the office, take and subscribe an oath, such as is required by state officers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 5, &#167; 3(1), p. 80; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 95; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Director of Aeronautics has no definite term and is removable at will by Governor. State ex rel. Beck v. Obbink, 172 Neb. 242, 109 N.W.2d 288 (1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>