<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id18">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id20" statutenumber="3-106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>3-106</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Department; office;
location; aircraft; purchase; use; employees;
department; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Suitable offices shall
be provided for the department in the State Capitol. It may maintain offices
at such other places in the state as it may designate and may incur the necessary
expense for office furniture, stationery, printing, and other incidental or necessary expenses
for the enforcement of the
State Aeronautics Department Act and the general promotion of
aeronautics within the state.</para>
<para>(2) The department may purchase
aircraft for the use of state
government and may sell any state aircraft that is not needed or suitable
for state uses. State aircraft shall be subject at all times to
the written orders of the Governor for use and service in any branch of the
state government. The department
shall establish an hourly rate for use of a state aircraft by a state official
or agency. The hourly rate shall not include an amount to recover the cost
of acquisition by purchase, but shall include amounts for items such as variable
fuel and oil costs, routine maintenance costs, landing fees, and preventive
maintenance reserves.</para>
<para>(3) The department may employ
such clerical and other employees and assistants as it may deem necessary
for the proper transaction of its business.</para>
<para>(4) It is the intent
of the Legislature that the use of state-owned, chartered, or rented aircraft
by the department shall be for the sole purpose of state business. The department
shall electronically file with the Clerk of the Legislature a quarterly report
on the department's use of all state-owned, chartered, or rented aircraft
that includes the following information for each trip: The name of the agency
or other entity traveling; the name of each individual passenger; all purposes
of the trip; the destination and intermediate stops; the miles flown; and
the duration of the trip.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 5, &#167; 5, p. 82; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1016, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>