<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-204"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-204</statuteno><catchline>Airport hazards; municipality; easements; acquire; right of eminent domain; effect on zoning.</catchline><para>Where necessary, in order to provide unobstructed air space for the landing and taking off of aircraft utilizing airports or restricted landing areas acquired or operated under the provisions of sections 3-201 to 3-238 and 18-1502, every municipality is authorized to acquire, in the same manner as is provided for the acquisition of property for airport purposes, easements through or other interests in air spaces over land or water, interests in airport hazards outside the boundaries of the airports or restricted landing areas and such other airport protection privileges as are necessary to insure safe approaches to the landing areas of said airports or restricted landing areas and the safe and efficient operation thereof. It is also hereby authorized to acquire, in the same manner, the right or easement, for a term of years or perpetually, to place or maintain suitable marks for the daytime marking and suitable lights for the nighttime marking of airport hazards, including the right of ingress and egress to or from such airport hazards, for the purpose of maintaining and repairing such lights and marks. This authority shall not be so construed as to limit any right, power or authority to zone property adjacent to airports and restricted landing areas under the provisions of any law of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 34, &#167; 2(3), p. 157.</para></source><annotation><para>Airport authority was authorized to acquire by eminent domain an aviation easement. Johnson v. Airport Authority, 173 Neb. 801, 115 N.W.2d 426 (1962).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>