<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id6" statutenumber="3-301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>3-301</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Airport Zoning Act, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1)(a) Airport
means an area of land or water that is used or intended to be used for
the landing and takeoff of aircraft and includes
any related buildings and facilities;</para>
<para>(b) Airport
includes only public-use airports with state or federally approved airport
layout plans and military airports with military service-approved military
layout plans;</para><para>(2) Airport hazard means any
structure or tree or use of land that
penetrates any approach, operation, transition, or turning zone;</para>
<para>(3) Airport hazard area means any area of land or water upon
which an airport hazard might be established if not prevented as provided
in the act, but such area shall not extend in any direction a distance in
excess of the limits provided for approach, operation, transition,
and turning zones;</para>
<para>(4) Airport
layout plan means a scaled drawing of existing and proposed land, buildings,
and facilities necessary for the operation and development of an airport prepared
in accordance with state rules and regulations and federal regulations and
guidelines;</para><para>(5) Approach zone means a zone that extends from the end of each
operation zone and is centered along the extended runway centerlines. Approach
zone dimensions are as follows:</para><para>(a) For an existing or proposed instrument
runway:</para><para>(i) An approach zone extends ten miles from the operation zone,
measured along the extended runway centerline. The approach zone is one thousand
feet wide at the end of the zone nearest the runway and expands uniformly
to sixteen thousand eight hundred forty feet wide at the farthest end of the
zone; and</para><para>(ii) The height limit of an approach zone begins at the elevation
of the runway end for which it is the approach and rises one foot vertically
for every fifty feet horizontally, except that the height limit shall not
exceed one hundred fifty feet above the nearest existing or proposed runway
end elevation within three miles of the end of the operation zone at that
runway end. At three miles from such operation zone, the height limit resumes
sloping one foot vertically for every fifty feet horizontally and continues
to the ten-mile limit; and</para><para>(b) For an existing or proposed visual runway:</para>
<para>(i) An approach
zone extends from the operation zone to the limits of the turning zone, measured
along the extended runway centerline. The approach zone is five hundred feet
wide at the end of the zone nearest the runway and expands uniformly so that
at a point on the extended runway centerline three miles from the operation
zone, the approach zone is three thousand seven hundred feet wide; and</para>
<para>(ii) The height
limit of an approach zone begins at the elevation of the runway end for which
it is the approach and rises one foot vertically for every forty feet horizontally,
except that the height limit shall not exceed one hundred fifty feet above
the nearest existing or proposed runway end elevation within three miles of
the end of the operation zone at that runway end;</para><para>(6) Electric facility
means an overhead electrical line, including poles or other supporting structures,
owned or operated by an electric supplier as defined in section 70-1001.01,
for the transmission or distribution of electrical power to the electric supplier's
customers;</para><para>(7) Existing runway means an instrument runway or a visual runway
that is paved or made of turf that has been constructed or is under construction;</para>
<para>(8) Instrument
runway means an existing runway with precision or nonprecision instrument
approaches as developed and published by the Federal Aviation Administration
or an existing or proposed runway with future precision or nonprecision instrument
approaches reflected on the airport layout plan. After September 6, 2013,
an airport shall not designate an existing or proposed runway as an instrument
runway if the runway was not previously designated as such without the approval
of the airport's governing body after a public hearing on such designation;</para>
<para>(9) Operation
zone means a zone that is longitudinally centered on each existing or proposed
runway. Operation zone dimensions are as follows:</para><para>(a) For existing and proposed
paved runways, the operation zone extends two hundred feet beyond the ends
of each runway. For existing and proposed turf runways, the operation zone
begins and ends at the same points as the runway begins and ends;</para>
<para>(b) For existing
and proposed instrument runways, the operation zone is one thousand feet wide,
with five hundred feet on either side of the runway centerline. For all other
existing and proposed runways, the operation zone is five hundred feet wide,
with two hundred fifty feet on either side of the runway centerline; and</para>
<para>(c) The height
limit of the operation zone is the same as the height of the runway centerline
elevation on an existing or proposed runway or the surface of the ground,
whichever is higher;</para><para>(10) Person
means any individual, firm, partnership, limited liability company, corporation,
company, association, joint-stock association, or body politic and includes
any trustee, receiver, assignee, or other similar representative thereof;</para>
<para>(11) Political
subdivision means any municipality, city, village, or county;</para>
<para>(12) Proposed
runway means an instrument runway or a visual runway that has not been constructed
and is not under construction but that is depicted on the airport layout plan
that has been conditionally or unconditionally approved by, or has been submitted
for approval to, the Federal Aviation Administration;</para><para>(13) Runway means a defined
area at an airport that is prepared for the landing and takeoff of aircraft
along its length;</para><para>(14) Structure
means any object constructed or installed by man, including, but without limitation,
buildings, towers, smokestacks, and overhead transmission or distribution lines;</para>
<para>(15) Transition
zone means a zone that extends outward at a right angle to the runway centerline
and upward at a rate of one foot vertically for every seven feet horizontally.
The height limit of a transition zone begins at the height limit of the adjacent
approach zone or operation zone and ends at a height of one hundred fifty
feet above the highest elevation on the existing or proposed runway;</para>
<para>(16) Tree means any object
of natural growth;</para>
<para>(17) Turning
zone's outer limit means the area located at a distance of three miles as
a radius from the corners of the operation zone of each runway and connecting
adjacent arcs with tangent lines, excluding any area within the approach zone,
operation zone, or transition zone. The height limit of the turning zone is
one hundred fifty feet above the highest elevation on the existing or proposed
runway; and</para><para>(18) Visual runway means a runway intended solely for the operation
of aircraft using visual approach procedures, with no straight-in instrument
approach procedure and no instrument designation indicated on an airport layout
plan approved by the Federal Aviation Administration, a military service-approved
military layout plan, or any planning documents submitted to the Federal Aviation
Administration by a competent authority.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 233, &#167; 1, p. 682; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB140, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>