
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-108</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Division; cooperate with federal government, political subdivisions, and others engaged in aeronautics; hearings; reports; contents.</catchline><para id="id00">The division shall cooperate with and assist the federal government, the political subdivisions of this state, and others engaged in aeronautics or the promotion of aeronautics and seek to coordinate the aeronautical activities of these bodies. To this end, the division is empowered to confer with or to hold joint hearings with any federal aeronautical agency in connection with any matter arising under the State Aeronautics Act, or relating to the sound development of aeronautics, and to avail itself of the cooperation, services, records, and facilities of such federal agencies, as fully as may be practicable, in the administration and enforcement of the act. The division shall reciprocate by furnishing to the federal agencies its cooperation, services, records, and facilities, insofar as may be practicable. The division shall report to the appropriate federal agency all accidents in aeronautics in this state of which it is informed and preserve, protect, and prevent the removal of the component parts of any aircraft involved in an accident being investigated by it until a federal agency institutes an investigation. The division shall report to the appropriate federal agency all refusals to register federal licenses, certificates, or permits and all revocations of certificates of registration, and the reasons therefor, and all penalties, of which it has knowledge, imposed upon airmen for violations of the laws of this state relating to aeronautics or for violations of the rules, regulations, or orders of the division.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 5, &#167; 6(2), p. 83; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>