<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>3-102</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Purpose of act.</catchline><para id="id00">The purpose of the State Aeronautics Act is to further the public interest and aeronautical progress by (1) providing for the protection and promotion of safety in aeronautics, (2) cooperating in effecting a uniformity of the laws relating to the development and regulation of aeronautics in the several states, (3) revising existing statutes relative to the development and regulation of aeronautics so as to grant such powers to and impose such duties upon the division in order that the state may properly perform its functions relative to aeronautics and effectively exercise its jurisdiction over persons and property within such jurisdiction, may assist in the promotion of a statewide system of airports, may cooperate with and assist the political subdivisions of this state and others engaged in aeronautics, and may encourage and develop aeronautics, (4) establishing uniform regulations, consistent with federal regulations and those of other states, in order that those engaged in aeronautics of every character may so engage with the least possible restriction, consistent with the safety and the rights of others, and (5) providing for cooperation with the federal authorities in the development of a national system of civil aviation and for coordination of the aeronautical activities of those authorities and the authorities of this state by assisting in accomplishing the purposes of federal legislation and eliminating costly and unnecessary duplication of functions properly in the province of federal agencies.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 5, &#167; 2, p. 79; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>A county should not be able to thwart the strong interest of the state in the promotion of aviation through the medium of its zoning authority. Seward County Board of Commissioners v. City of Seward, 196 Neb. 266, 242 N.W.2d 849 (1976).</para><para>Statute creating Department of Aeronautics was enacted for the promotion of safety and for cooperating in effecting uniformity of legislation in the several states consistent with federal regulations. In re Estate of Kinsey, 152 Neb. 95, 40 N.W.2d 526 (1949).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>