
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-124</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Division; acceptance of gifts of money, authorized; terms and conditions.</catchline><para id="id00">The division is authorized to accept federal and other money, either public or private, for and on behalf of this state, any municipality, or any person owning a privately owned public use airport, for the acquisition, construction, improvement, maintenance, and operation of airports and other air navigation facilities, whether such work is to be done by the state, by such municipalities, or by any person owning a privately owned public use airport, or jointly, aided by grants of aid from the United States, upon such terms and conditions as are or may be prescribed by the laws of the United States and any regulations thereunder. The division may act as agent of any municipality of this state or any person owning a privately owned public use airport, upon the request of such municipality or person, in accepting such money in its behalf for airports or other air navigation facility purposes, and in contracting for the acquisition, construction, improvement, maintenance, or operation of airports or other air navigation facilities, financed either in whole or in part by federal money, and such person or the governing body of any such municipality is authorized to designate the division as its agent for such purposes and to enter into an agreement with the division prescribing the terms and conditions of such agency in accordance with federal laws, rules, and regulations and with the State Aeronautics Act. Such money as is paid over by the United States Government shall be retained by the state or paid over to the municipalities or persons under such terms and conditions as may be imposed by the United States Government in making such grants.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 5, &#167; 7(2), p. 87; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 609, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 22. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>