<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-709"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-709</statuteno><catchline>Funds; deposit; withdrawals; security; contracts authorized.</catchline><para>All income, revenue, receipts, profits, and money of a joint authority, from whatever source derived, shall be paid to the treasurer of the joint authority who shall not commingle such money with any other money under his or her control. Such money shall be deposited in a separate bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution account or accounts. Such money shall be withdrawn only by check, draft, or order signed by the treasurer on requisition of the chairperson of the joint authority or of such other person or persons as the joint authority may authorize to make such requisitions, approved by the board. Notwithstanding the provisions of this section, such joint authority may contract with the holders of any of its bonds as to collection, custody, securing, investment, and payment of any money of the joint authority or any money held in trust or otherwise for the payment of bonds or in any way to secure bonds. The joint authority may carry out any such contract notwithstanding that such contract may be inconsistent with the previous provisions of this section. All banks, capital stock financial institutions, qualifying mutual financial institutions, and trust companies are hereby authorized to give security for such deposits of money of joint authorities pursuant to the Public Funds Deposit Security Act. Section 77-2366 shall apply to deposits in capital stock financial institutions. Section 77-2365.01 shall apply to deposits in qualifying mutual financial institutions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 24, &#167; 9, p. 211; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 33, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Public Funds Deposit Security Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2386.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>