<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id00" statutenumber="3-201"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>3-201</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para id="id00">For the purpose of the Revised Airports Act, unless specifically otherwise provided in the act, the definitions of words, terms, and phrases appearing in the State Aeronautics Act are hereby adopted. The following words, terms, and phrases shall in the Revised Airports Act have the meanings given in this section, unless otherwise specifically defined, or unless another intention clearly appears, or the context otherwise requires: (1) Municipality means any county, city, or village of this state or any city airport authority established pursuant to the Cities Airport Authorities Act and (2) airport purposes means and includes airport, restricted landing area, and other air navigation facility purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 156; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 9, &#167; 13, p. 125; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 5, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 55. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Cities Airport Authorities Act,</emphasis> see section 3-514.</para><para><emphasis>For definitions in State Aeronautics Act,</emphasis> see section 3-101.</para><para><emphasis>State Aeronautics Act,</emphasis> see section 3-154.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Municipal airport authorities are authorized to acquire property by condemnation for establishing airports. Seward County Board of Commissioners v. City of Seward, 196 Neb. 266, 242 N.W.2d 849 (1976).</para><para>Municipalities were empowered to acquire, establish, construct, improve, operate, and regulate municipal airports. City of Ord v. Biemond, 175 Neb. 333, 122 N.W.2d 6 (1963).</para><para>Constitutionality of Revised Airports Act raised but not decided. Brasier v. Cribbett, 166 Neb. 145, 88 N.W.2d 235 (1958).</para><para>Under former law municipality was defined as village, city, or county. Spencer v. Village of Wallace, 153 Neb. 536, 45 N.W.2d 473 (1951).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>