<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Aeronautics" statutenumber="3-706"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>3-706</statuteno><catchline>Joint authority; property; control; convey; transfer; title; acquire.</catchline><para>(1) Any political subdivision participating in the creation of a joint authority may, by resolution or resolutions, convey or transfer to it in accordance with the provisions of the agreement, any existing airport or any other property of such political subdivision for use in connection with a project, including real and personal property owned or leased by such political subdivision and used or useful in connection therewith. The title to any such property shall pass to the joint authority. Any conveyance of an existing airport shall be subject to any leases or agreements duly and validly made by the political subdivision affecting such airports or the property so conveyed, but any such lease or agreement which is inconsistent with the ability of the joint authority to issue negotiable bonds may be renegotiated by the authority.</para><para>(2) Any county, city, or village participating in the creation of a joint authority may acquire by purchase or condemnation real property in its name for the project or for the widening of existing roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways, or for new roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways to a project, or partly for such purposes, by purchase or condemnation in the manner provided in sections 76-704 to 76-724. Such county, city, or village may also close any roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways as may be necessary or convenient to facilitate the construction or operation of a project.</para><para>(3) Contracts may be entered into between any political subdivision and a joint authority, or between other public bodies of the State of Nebraska and such political subdivision or joint authority, or between each and any of them, providing for the conveyance of property to such political subdivision or joint authority for use in connection with a project, and for the closing of streets, roads, parkways, avenues, or highways. The amounts, terms, and conditions of payment, if any, shall be prescribed by such political subdivision or joint authority in connection with such conveyances. Such contracts may also contain covenants by such political subdivision or such public body as to the road, street, parkway, avenue, or highway improvements to be made by such political subdivision or such public body. The governing body of any political subdivision may authorize such contracts between such political subdivision and the joint authority by resolution, and no other authorization on the part of such political subdivision for such contracts shall be necessary. All obligations of any county, city, or village for the payment of money to a joint authority incurred in carrying out the provisions of the Joint Airport Authorities Act shall be included in and provided for by each annual or biennial budget of any county, city, or village thereafter made until fully discharged. In the case of other public bodies of the state, such contracts shall be authorized as provided by law.</para><para>(4) A joint authority operating under the provisions of the Joint Airport Authorities Act may acquire real property for a project in its own name at the cost and expense of the joint authority by purchase or condemnation pursuant to the provisions of sections 76-704 to 76-724 and subdivision (4) of section 3-707. The joint authority shall have the use and occupancy of such real property for so long as its corporate existence shall continue.</para><para>(5) If a joint authority shall have the use and occupancy of any real property which it shall determine is no longer required for a project the joint authority shall have power to sell, lease, or otherwise dispose thereof. Such joint authority shall retain the proceeds of sale, rentals, or other money derived from the disposition thereof for its corporate purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 24, &#167; 6, p. 205; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 22, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1116, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>