<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id142">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aeronautics" id="id144" statutenumber="3-320"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>3-320</statuteno><catchline id="id147">Zoning regulations;
board of adjustment; members;
terms; powers.</catchline><para>(1) All
airport zoning regulations adopted under the
Airport Zoning Act shall provide for a board of adjustment to
have and exercise the following powers:</para>
<para>(a) To hear and decide appeals from any order,
requirement, decision, or
determination made by the administrative agency in the enforcement of the
airport zoning regulations;</para>
<para>(b) To hear and decide any
special exceptions to the terms of the airport zoning regulations upon which
such board may be required to pass under such regulations; and</para>
<para>(c) To hear and decide petitions
for variances from
the strict application of airport zoning regulations.</para>
<para>(2) A board
of adjustment shall consist of five regular members, each to be appointed
for a term of three years by the political subdivision or joint airport zoning
board adopting the regulations. Any member thereof may be removed by the appointing
authority for cause, upon written charges and after a public hearing. The
concurring vote of four members of the board shall be necessary to reverse
any order, requirement, decision, or determination of the administrative agency
or to decide in favor of the applicant on any matter upon which the board
is required to pass under the airport zoning regulations or to effect any
variation in such regulations.</para><para>(3) The board of adjustment may, consistent
with the Airport Zoning Act, reverse or affirm wholly or partly or modify
the order, requirement, decision, or determination appealed from and may make
such order, requirement, decision, or determination as it deems right and
proper under the circumstances.</para><para>(4) A board of adjustment, board of zoning
appeals, or similar zoning appeals board that exists on September 6, 2013,
may be designated as and shall exercise the power of the board of adjustment
for airport zoning regulations as required by this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 233, &#167; 10(1), p. 688; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB140, &#167; 16.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>