
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aliens" id="id24" statutenumber="4-111"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>4-111</statuteno><catchline>Public benefits; verification of lawful presence; attestation required; professional or commercial license; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Verification of lawful presence in the United States pursuant to section 4-108 requires that the applicant for public benefits attest in a format prescribed by the Department of Administrative Services that:</para><para>(a) He or she is a United States citizen; or</para><para>(b) He or she is a qualified alien under the federal Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2009, and is lawfully present in the United States.</para><para>(2) A state agency or political subdivision of the State of Nebraska may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations or procedures for the electronic filing of the attestation required under subsection (1) of this section if such attestation is substantially similar to the format prescribed by the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(3)(a) The Legislature finds that it is in the best interest of the State of Nebraska to make full use of the skills and talents in the state by ensuring that a person who is work-authorized is able to obtain a professional or commercial license and practice his or her profession.</para><para>(b) For purposes of a professional or commercial license, the Legislature finds that a person not described in subdivision (1)(a) or (1)(b) of this section who submits (i) an unexpired employment authorization document issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security, Form I-766, and (ii) documentation issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security, the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services, or any other federal agency, such as one of the types of Form I-797 used by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services, demonstrating that such person is described in section 202(c)(2)(B)(i) through (x) of the federal REAL ID Act of 2005, Public Law 109-13, has demonstrated lawful presence pursuant to section 4-108 and is eligible to obtain such license. Such license shall be valid only for the period of time during which such person's employment authorization document is valid. Nothing in this subsection shall affect the requirements to obtain a professional or commercial license that are unrelated to the lawful presence requirements demonstrated pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(c) Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to grant eligibility for any public benefits other than obtaining a professional or commercial license.</para><para>(d) Any person who has complied with the requirements of this subsection shall have his or her employment authorization document verified through the Systematic Alien Verification for Entitlements Program operated by the United States Department of Homeland Security or an equivalent program designated by the United States Department of Homeland Security.</para><para>(e) The Legislature enacts this subsection pursuant to the authority provided in 8 U.S.C. 1621(d), as such section existed on January 1, 2016.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB403, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB947, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>For the purposes of state or local public benefits eligibility, "lawfully present" means the alien classifications
under 8 U.S.C. 1621(a)(1), (2), or (3). E.M. v. Nebraska Dept. of Health &amp; Human Servs., 306 Neb. 1, 944 N.W.2d 252 (2020).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>