<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id861"><amendatorysection chaptername="Aliens" statutenumber="4-211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>4-211</statuteno><catchline>Businesses and nonprofit organizations; attestation required; Attorney General; duty; Secretary of State; powers.</catchline><para>(1) All businesses and nonprofit organizations operating within the State of Nebraska shall attest that they are cognizant of and in compliance with the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act.</para><para>(2) The attestation required by this section shall be filed as follows:</para><para>(a) For a domestic or foreign limited liability company, the attestation shall be included in the biennial report in each odd-numbered year under section 21-125;</para><para>(b) For a domestic or foreign corporation subject to the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act, the attestation shall be included in the biennial report in each even-numbered year under section 21-301 or 21-304;</para><para>(c) For a domestic or foreign nonprofit corporation, the attestation shall be included in the biennial report in each odd-numbered year under section 21-19,172;</para><para>(d) For a domestic or foreign limited liability partnership, the attestation shall be included in the annual report under section 67-456;</para><para>(e) For banking, insurance, and building and loan association corporations paying fees and making reports to the Director of Insurance or the Director of Banking and Finance, the attestation shall be included on a report filed with the Director of Insurance or the Director of Banking and Finance. Each director shall determine the frequency with which such reports must be filed but shall not require a report to be filed more frequently than on an annual basis; and</para><para>(f) For any other business or nonprofit organization not described in subdivisions (2)(a) through (e) of this section, the attestation shall be included on the annual or biennial report submitted to the Secretary of State as required by the organic law of the business or nonprofit organization.</para><para>(3) The Attorney General shall develop the attestation required by this section in consultation with the Secretary of State.</para><para>(4) The Secretary of State may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para><para>(5) An unincorporated entity that is of a type that is not created by filing a public organic document with the Secretary of State is exempt from this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB644, &#167; 11. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>