
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id37">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Aliens" id="id39"  statutenumber="4-114"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>4-114</statuteno><catchline>Public employer and public contractor;
register with and use federal immigration verification system; Department
of Labor; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Federal
immigration verification system means the electronic verification of the work
authorization program of the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility
Act of 1996, 8 U.S.C. 1324a, known as the E-Verify Program, or an equivalent
federal program designated by the United States Department of Homeland Security
or other federal agency authorized to verify the work eligibility status of
a newly hired employee pursuant to the Immigration Reform and Control Act
of 1986;</para><para>(b) Public contractor means any contractor or his or her subcontractor
who is awarded a contract by a public employer for the physical performance
of services within the State of Nebraska; and</para><para>(c) Public employer means
any agency or political subdivision of the State of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(2) Every public
employer and public contractor shall register with and use a federal immigration
verification system to determine the work eligibility status of new employees
physically performing services within the State of Nebraska. Every contract
between a public employer and public contractor shall contain a provision
requiring the public contractor to use a federal immigration verification
system to determine the work eligibility status of new employees physically
performing services within the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) For two years after
October 1, 2009, the Department of Labor shall make available to all private
employers information regarding the federal immigration verification system
and encouraging the use of the federal immigration verification system. The
department shall report to the Legislature no later than December 1, 2011,
on the use of a federal immigration verification system by Nebraska employers.</para>
<para>(4) This section
does not apply to contracts awarded by a public employer prior to October
1, 2009.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB403, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>