<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Aliens" id="id5" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="4-108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>4-108</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Public benefits;
state agency or political subdivision; verification of lawful presence; employee;
participation in retirement system; restriction.</catchline><para>(1)
Notwithstanding any other provisions of law, unless exempted from verification
under section 4-110 or pursuant to federal law, no state agency or political
subdivision of the State of Nebraska shall provide public benefits to a person
not lawfully present in the United States.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in section 4-110 or if exempted by
federal law, every agency or political subdivision of the State of Nebraska
shall verify the lawful presence in the United States of any person who has
applied for public benefits administered by an agency or a political subdivision
of the State of Nebraska. This section shall be enforced without regard to
race, religion, gender, ethnicity, or national origin.</para>
<para>(3) On and after October 1, 2009, no employee of a state agency
or political subdivision of the State of Nebraska shall be authorized to participate
in any retirement system, including, but not limited to, the systems provided
for in the Class V School Employees
Retirement Act, the County Employees Retirement Act, the Judges
Retirement Act, the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act, the School Employees
Retirement Act, and the State Employees Retirement Act, unless the employee
(a) is a United States citizen or (b) is a qualified alien under the federal
Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq., as such act existed
on January 1, 2009, and is lawfully present in the United States.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB403, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Class V School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-978.01.</para><para><emphasis>County Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 23-2331.</para><para><emphasis>Judges Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 24-701.01.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 81-2014.01.</para><para><emphasis>School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-901.</para><para><emphasis>State Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1331.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>