<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id591"><amendatorysection chaptername="Aliens" statutenumber="4-206"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>4-206</statuteno><catchline>Transmittal of information; restrictions; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Every person within the State of Nebraska who is an agent of a foreign principal from an adversary nation or a foreign terrorist organization and who is required to register under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act and who transmits or causes to be transmitted in the United States mail, through digital communication, or by any means or instrumentality of interstate or foreign commerce any informational materials for, or in the interests of, such foreign principal in the form of prints or in any other form that is reasonably adapted to being, that such person believes will be, or that such person intends to be, disseminated or circulated among two or more persons shall, not later than forty-eight hours after the beginning of the transmittal thereof, file with the Attorney General two copies thereof.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person within the State of Nebraska who is an agent of a foreign principal from an adversary nation or a foreign terrorist organization and required to register under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act to transmit or cause to be transmitted in the United States mail, through digital communication, or by any means or instrumentality of interstate or foreign commerce any informational materials for, or in the interests of, such foreign principal without placing in such informational materials a conspicuous statement that the materials are distributed by the agent on behalf of such foreign principal, and that additional information is on file with the Attorney General. The Attorney General may by rule and regulation define what constitutes a conspicuous statement for the purposes of this section.</para><para>(3) The copies of informational materials required by this section to be filed with the Attorney General shall be available for public inspection under such rules and regulations as the Attorney General may adopt and promulgate.</para><para>(4) It shall be unlawful for any person within the State of Nebraska who is an agent of a foreign principal from an adversary nation or a foreign terrorist organization required to register under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act to transmit, convey, or otherwise furnish to any agency or official of the state, including any agency or official of a political subdivision of the state, for or in the interests of such foreign principal, any political propaganda, or to request from any such agency or official for, or in the interests of, such foreign principal, any information or advice with respect to any matter pertaining to the political or public interests, policies, or relations of an adversary nation, a foreign terrorist organization, or a political party from an adversary nation or a foreign terrorist organization, or pertaining to the foreign or domestic policies of the United States or the State of Nebraska, unless the propaganda or the request is prefaced or accompanied by a true and accurate statement to the effect that such person is registered as an agent of such foreign principal under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act.</para><para>(5) Whenever any agent of a foreign principal from an adversary nation or a foreign terrorist organization required to register under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act appears before any committee of the Legislature or a local government to testify for, or in the interests of, such foreign principal, such agent shall, at the time of such appearance, furnish the committee with a copy of such agent's most recent registration statement filed with the Attorney General for inclusion in the records of the committee as part of such agent's testimony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB644, &#167; 6. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>