<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id905"><amendatorysection chaptername="Aliens" statutenumber="4-115"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>4-115</statuteno><catchline>Critical infrastructure; contract with foreign principal; restrictions, when.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Company means a for-profit sole proprietorship, organization, association, corporation, partnership, joint venture, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, or limited liability company, including a wholly owned subsidiary, majority owned subsidiary, parent company, or affiliate of those entities or business associations that exists to make a profit;</para><para>(b) Critical infrastructure means the 911 system, a communication infrastructure system, a cybersecurity system, a high voltage electric grid, a hazardous waste treatment system, or a water treatment facility;</para><para>(c) Cybersecurity means the measures taken to protect a computer, computer network, computer system, or other technology infrastructure against unauthorized use or access;</para><para>(d) Foreign adversary means those countries listed in 15 C.F.R. 791.4, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2026;</para><para>(e) Foreign principal means:</para><para>(i) The government or any official of the government of a foreign adversary;</para><para>(ii) A political party of a foreign adversary or a member of such political party or any subdivision of such political party;</para><para>(iii)(A) A partnership, an association, a corporation, an organization, or any other combination of persons organized under the laws of or having its principal place of business in a foreign adversary;</para><para>(B) A subsidiary of an entity described in subdivision (1)(e)(iii)(A) of this section; or</para><para>(C) An entity owned or controlled wholly or in part by any person, entity, or collection of persons or entities described in subdivision (1)(e)(iii)(A) or (B) of this section;</para><para>(iv) Any person who is domiciled in a foreign adversary and is not a citizen or lawful permanent resident of the United States; and</para><para>(v) Any person, entity, or collection of persons or entities described in subdivisions (1)(e)(i) through (iv) of this section having a controlling interest in a partnership, association, corporation, organization, trust, or any other legal entity or subsidiary formed for the purpose of owning real property; and</para><para>(f) Governmental entity means any agency, department, board, commission, or political subdivision of the state that owns, operates, manages, or provides oversight for critical infrastructure.</para><para>(2)(a) A company or other entity constructing, repairing, operating, or otherwise having significant access to critical infrastructure shall not knowingly enter into a contract or other agreement relating to critical infrastructure in this state with a foreign principal if the contract or other agreement would allow the foreign principal to directly or remotely access or control critical infrastructure in this state.</para><para>(b) A governmental entity shall not knowingly enter into a contract or other agreement relating to critical infrastructure in this state with a company that is a foreign principal if the contract or other agreement would allow the foreign principal to directly or remotely access or control critical infrastructure in this state.</para><para>(c) Notwithstanding subdivisions (2)(a) and (b) of this section, a company or other entity may enter into a contract or agreement relating to critical infrastructure with a foreign principal if all of the following apply:</para><para>(i) There is no other reasonable option for addressing the need relevant to state critical infrastructure; and</para><para>(ii) Not entering into such contract or agreement would pose a greater threat to the state than the threat associated with entering into the contract.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1096, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>