<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id766"><amendatorysection chaptername="Aliens" statutenumber="4-208"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>4-208</statuteno><catchline>Attorney General; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Attorney General shall retain in permanent form one copy of each registration statement furnished under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act, and such statement shall be a public record and open to public examination and inspection at such reasonable hours, under such rules and regulations as the Attorney General may adopt and promulgate.</para><para>(2) The Attorney General shall, upon receipt, promptly transmit one copy of any registration statement filed, and one copy of every amendment or supplement to such statement filed, to the United States Secretary of State for such comment and use as the secretary may determine to be appropriate from the point of view of the foreign relations of the United States. Failure of the Attorney General to transmit such copy shall not be a bar to prosecution under the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act.</para><para>(3) The Attorney General may furnish information obtained by the Attorney General in the administration of the act to state and federal agencies and to committees of the Legislature. The Attorney General may furnish such information as may be appropriate in light of the purposes of the act. This includes, but is not limited to, the names of registrants under the act, copies of registration statements, or parts thereof, and other documents or information filed under the act.</para><para>(4) The Attorney General shall report to the Legislature every six months concerning administration of the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act, including registrations filed pursuant to the act, and the nature, sources, and content of political propaganda disseminated and distributed.</para><para>(5) The Attorney General shall post a monthly report on the portal described in section 4-212 concerning administration of the Foreign Adversary and Terrorist Agent Registration Act, including registrations filed pursuant to the act, and the nature, sources, and content of political propaganda disseminated and distributed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB644, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>