<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" id="id14" statutenumber="50-505"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>50-505</statuteno><catchline>Water Funding Task Force; created;
members; qualifications; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Water Funding Task Force is created. The task force
shall consist of the members of the Nebraska Natural Resources Commission
and eleven additional members to be appointed by the Governor. The Director
of Natural Resources or his or her designee, the chairperson of the Natural
Resources Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, and five additional
members of the Legislature appointed by the Executive Board of the Legislative
Council shall be nonvoting, ex officio members of the task force. In appointing
members to the task force, the Governor:</para>
<para>(a) Shall seek
to create a broad-based task force with knowledge of and experience with and
representative of Nebraska's water use and economy;</para><para>(b) Shall give equal recognition
to the importance of both water quantity and water quality;</para>
<para>(c) Shall appoint
one member from each of the following categories: Public power; public power
and irrigation districts; irrigation districts; a metropolitan utilities district;
municipalities; agriculture; wildlife conservation; livestock producers; agribusiness;
manufacturing; and outdoor recreation users; and</para><para>(d) May solicit and accept
nominations for appointments to the task force from recognized water interest
groups in Nebraska.</para><para>(2) The members of the task force appointed by the Governor shall
represent diverse geographic regions of the state, including urban and rural
areas. Such members shall be appointed within thirty days after June 5, 2013.
Members shall begin serving immediately following notice of appointment. Members
shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in carrying
out their duties as members as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB517, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>