<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id6" statutenumber="50-406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>50-406</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Legislative Council;
committees; public hearings; oaths;
subpoenas; books and records; examination;
litigation; appeal.</catchline><para>In the discharge
of any duty imposed by
the Legislative Council, by statute, or by a resolution of the Legislature,
the council, any committee thereof, and any standing or special committee
created by statute or resolution of the Legislature may hold public hearings
and may administer oaths, issue subpoenas when the committee has received prior approval by a majority
vote of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council to issue subpoenas
in connection with the specific inquiry or investigation in question, compel the attendance of witnesses and the production of any papers, books, accounts,
documents, and testimony, and cause
the depositions of witnesses to be taken in the manner
prescribed by law for taking depositions in civil actions in the district
court. The council or the committee
may require any state agency, political subdivision, or person to provide
information relevant to the committee's work, and the state agency, political
subdivision, or person shall provide the information requested within thirty
days after the request except as provided for in a subpoena. The statute or
resolution creating a committee may prescribe limitations on the authority
granted by this section.</para>
<para>Litigation
to compel or quash compliance with authority exercised pursuant to this section
shall be advanced on the court docket and heard and decided by the court as
quickly as possible. Either party may appeal to the Court of Appeals within
ten days after a decision is rendered.</para><para>The district court of Lancaster County has
jurisdiction over all litigation arising under this section. In all such litigation
the executive board shall provide for legal representation for the council
or committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 118, &#167; 4, p. 422; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 50-504; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 50-406; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 168, &#167; 3, p. 445; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 875; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB613, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>