<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="50-401.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>50-401.01</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Legislative Council;
executive board; members; selection; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1)
The Legislative Council shall have an executive board, to be known as the
Executive Board of the Legislative Council, which shall consist of a chairperson,
a vice-chairperson, and six members of the Legislature, to be chosen by the
Legislature at the commencement of each regular session of the Legislature
when the speaker is chosen, and the Speaker of the Legislature. The Legislature
at large shall elect two of its members from legislative districts Nos. 1, 17, 30, 32 to 38, 40 to 44, 47, and
48, two from legislative districts Nos. 2, 3, 15, 16, 19, 21 to 29, 45, and 46, and
two from legislative districts Nos. 4 to 14, 18, 20, 31, 39, and 49. The Chairperson
of the Committee on Appropriations shall serve as a nonvoting ex officio member
of the executive board whenever the board is considering fiscal administration.</para>
<para>(2) The executive board shall:</para>
<para>(a) Supervise all services and service personnel of the Legislature
and may employ and fix compensation and other terms of employment for such
personnel as may be needed to carry out the intent and activities of the Legislature
or of the board, unless otherwise directed by the Legislature, including the
adoption of policies by the executive board which permit (i) the purchasing
of an annuity for an employee who retires or (ii) the crediting of amounts
to an employee's deferred compensation account under section 84-1504. The
payments to or on behalf of an employee may be staggered to comply with other
law; and</para>
<para>(b) Appoint persons to fill the positions of Legislative Fiscal
Analyst, Director of Research, Revisor of Statutes, and Legislative Auditor.
The persons appointed to these positions shall have training and experience
as determined by the executive board and shall serve at the pleasure of the
executive board. The Legislative Performance Audit Committee shall recommend
the person to be appointed Legislative Auditor. Their respective salaries
shall be set by the executive board.</para>
<para>(3) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the executive
board may contract to obtain legal, auditing, accounting, actuarial, or other
professional services or advice for or on behalf of the executive board, the
Legislative Council, the Legislature, or any member of the Legislature. The
providers of such services or advice shall meet or exceed the minimum professional
standards or requirements established or specified by their respective professional
organizations or licensing entities or by federal law. Such contracts, the
deliberations of the executive board with respect to such contracts, and the
work product resulting from such contracts shall not be subject to review
or approval by any other entity of state government.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 118, &#167; 1, p. 421; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 60, &#167; 1, p. 261; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 50-501; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 118, &#167; 1, p. 414; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 50-401; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 168, &#167; 1(2), p. 445; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 169, &#167; 1, p. 655; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 310, &#167; 1, p. 872; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 595, &#167; 1, p. 2026; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1129, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 485, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 898, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 579, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1243, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 314, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 510, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 956, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB711, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>