<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-114"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>50-114</statuteno><catchline>Clerk; duties; official records of the Legislature; audio and video recordings; restrictions on use.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be the duty of the Clerk of the Legislature to attend the sessions of the Legislature, to call the roll, to read the journals, bills, memorials, resolutions, petitions, and all other papers or documents necessary to be read in the Legislature, to keep a correct journal of the proceedings in the Legislature, and to do and perform such other duties as may be imposed upon the clerk by the Legislature or by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>(2) The records of floor debate and committee hearings as prepared and permanently maintained by the Clerk of the Legislature are the official records of the Legislature.</para><para>(3) Any government website offering access to audio and video recordings of the proceedings of the Legislature or of a committee or division of the Legislature shall require notification to any website user, using appropriate technology, that such recordings shall not be used, reproduced, or redistributed without express permission by the Legislative Council and in accordance with the policies developed by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council pursuant to section 50-117.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1867, &#167; 4, p. 85; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3755; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3148; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 50-114; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 101, &#167; 1, p. 418; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 50-114; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 50-114; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 328, &#167; 8, p. 871; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB254, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>May 27, 2023</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Entries found in legislative journals prevail over evidence furnished by enrolled bill. Webster v. City of Hastings, 59 Neb. 563, 81 N.W. 510 (1900).</para><para>Enrolled bill and journals of houses are the official records relative to enactment of law and are the only competent evidence. State v. Abbott, 59 Neb. 106, 80 N.W. 499 (1899).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>