<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id927"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-801"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-801</statuteno><catchline>Water resources; legislative findings and declarations.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds and declares as follows:</para><para>(1) The future vibrancy of the people, communities, and businesses of Nebraska depends on reliable sources of water;</para><para>(2) While it is in the state's best interest to retain control over its water supplies, much of the state's water resources are currently underutilized;</para><para>(3) Well-planned flood control is critical to the future of the people, communities, and businesses of Nebraska;</para><para>(4) The state's water resources provide economic benefit to the people, communities, and businesses of Nebraska by helping to attract visitors from other states and boost local economies;</para><para>(5) Nebraska has tremendous water resources across the state, including, but not limited to, the Ogallala Aquifer, Lake McConaughy, the Platte River, the Republican River, and the Missouri River. The state's lakes and rivers help Nebraskans enjoy the water resources in our state and make Nebraska an even more attractive place to live and raise a family;</para><para>(6) In light of the disruption from the COVID-19 coronavirus pandemic and the trend toward a remote workforce around the country, people around the country are rethinking where they want to work, live, and raise a family. As people consider where to live, access to sustainable water resources and outdoor recreational opportunities will be important considerations in making Nebraska a competitive choice for the future;</para><para>(7) Studies should be conducted focusing on securing Nebraska's future water supply and strengthening Nebraska's flood control infrastructure, while also considering economic and recreational opportunities, including opportunities from increased tourism, in finding innovative solutions and winning opportunities for the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(8) Any such studies must not deter ongoing economic activity or fail to protect current investment in the areas under study; and</para><para>(9) An investment in a one-time series of studies that take advantage of previous studies while including innovative approaches and new technologies is best positioned to find solutions for all Nebraskans, especially Nebraskans living, working, and investing in the areas under study.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB406, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>