<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id22"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>50-117</statuteno><catchline>Digital Internet archive of closed-captioned video coverage of the Legislature; policies and procedures; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislative Council, through the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, shall develop and maintain a publicly accessible, digital Internet archive of closed-captioned video coverage of the Legislature, including floor debate and public committee hearings indexed by legislative bill or resolution number or by date, beginning with the coverage of the One Hundred Ninth Legislature, First Session, in January 2025 or as soon as live, closed-captioned video coverage of the Legislature is available for use, whichever is sooner, as provided in section 79-1316. Closed-captioned video coverage shall include closed captioning in both English and Spanish.</para><para>(2) Applicable historical video coverage of the Legislature shall be collected and added to the digital archive as available. Applicable historical video coverage shall only consist of video coverage of the Legislature captured by the Nebraska Educational Telecommunications Commission and closed-captioned prior to January 1, 2025.</para><para>(3) Such archive is intended solely for educational and informational purposes and to enhance access for the public, in keeping with the Legislature's commitment to transparency in state government.</para><para>(4) Audio and video recordings of the proceedings of the Legislature or of a committee or division of the Legislature are not official records of such proceedings and shall not be admissible in any proceeding as evidence of legislative history, action, or intent.</para><para>(5) The Executive Board of the Legislative Council shall develop policies and procedures surrounding the creation and ongoing usage of the publicly accessible, indexed, digital Internet archive of closed-captioned video coverage of the Legislature developed pursuant to this section. Such policies shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) The usage of archived video recordings for purposes other than legislative purposes;</para><para>(b) A determination regarding which committee hearings and committee briefings shall be recorded and added to the digital archive;</para><para>(c) Parameters surrounding long-term storage of archived video recordings; and</para><para>(d) Management of costs in relation to supporting public accessibility of archived video recordings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB254, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>