<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id6" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="50-501"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-501</statuteno><catchline>Natural Resources Committee of the
Legislature; development of statewide strategic plan for biotechnology; contents;
Biotechnology Development Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature recognizes the importance of biotechnology and the
role that biotechnology plays in the economic well-being of the State of Nebraska.
The Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature shall be responsible for
the development of a statewide strategic plan for biotechnology in Nebraska.
The plan shall include a baseline review and assessment of the potential in
the biotechnology economy in Nebraska and a strategic plan for the state's
efforts in creating wealth and jobs in the biotechnology economy. The plan
shall address strategies for developing the biotechnology economy and shall
include, but not be limited to, research, testing, agricultural feedstock
and chemicals, drugs and other pharmaceuticals, medical materials, medical
laboratories, and advanced biofuels. The plan shall estimate the wealth and
the number of jobs that may be generated from expanding the biotechnology
economy.</para>
<para>(2) The Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature, in consultation
with the Executive Board of the Legislature, shall commission a nonprofit
corporation to provide research, analysis, and recommendations to the committee
for the development of the plan. The nonprofit corporation shall be incorporated
pursuant to the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, shall be organized exclusively
for nonprofit purposes within the meaning of section 501(c)(6) of the Internal
Revenue Code as defined in section 49-801.01, shall be engaged in activities
to facilitate and promote the growth of life sciences within Nebraska, shall
be dedicated to the development and growth of the biotechnology economy, and
shall agree to remit one hundred thousand dollars to the State Treasurer for
credit to the Biotechnology Development Cash Fund for the research required
by this section. The nonprofit corporation shall retain such consultation
services as required for assistance in providing research, analysis, and recommendations.
The nonprofit corporation shall present its research, analysis, and recommendations
to the committee by September 30, 2010.</para>
<para>(3) The Natural Resources Committee shall prepare and present to the
Legislature a statewide strategic plan for biotechnology during the One Hundred
Second Legislature, First Session, for consideration by the Legislature. The
committee shall prepare annual updates to the plan for consideration by the
Legislature.</para>
<para>(4) The Biotechnology Development Cash Fund is created. The Natural
Resources Committee shall use money in the fund to commission the nonprofit
corporation and provide access to resources necessary for developing the plan.
The fund may receive gifts, bequests, grants, or other contributions or donations
from public or private entities. Within five days after the State Treasurer
receives one hundred thousand dollars from the nonprofit corporation for credit
to the fund, the State Treasurer shall transfer one hundred thousand dollars
from the General Fund to the Biotechnology Development Cash Fund. It is the
intent of the Legislature to appropriate two hundred thousand dollars to the
fund for fiscal year 2009-10. Any money in the fund available for investment
shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska
Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Biotechnology means the technological application that uses biological
systems, living organisms, or derivatives of biological systems or living
organisms to make or modify products or processes for specific use; and</para>
<para>(b) Biotechnology economy means economic activity derived from scientific
and research activity focused on understanding mechanisms and processes at
the genetic and molecular levels and the application of the mechanisms and
processes to industrial processes.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB246, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB911, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>