<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id7"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-450"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-450</statuteno><catchline>Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center Special Oversight Committee of the Legislature; members; staff; powers and duties; termination.</catchline><para>(1) The Executive Board of the Legislative Council shall appoint a special committee of the Legislature to be known as the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center Special Oversight Committee of the Legislature. The committee shall consist of no more than eleven members of the Legislature appointed by the executive board. Members shall include the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature, two other members of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature, one member of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature, two members of the Education Committee of the Legislature, the chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature, one other member of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature, and one member of the Legislature from each legislative district in which a youth rehabilitation and treatment center is located. The Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center Special Oversight Committee shall elect a chairperson and vice-chairperson from the membership of the committee. The executive board may provide the committee with a legal counsel, committee clerk, and other staff as required by the committee from existing legislative staff. The committee may hold hearings and request and receive progress reports from the Department of Health and Human Services regarding the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers.</para><para>(2) The Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center Special Oversight Committee of the Legislature may study the quality of care and related issues at the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers. The committee shall provide oversight of the administration and operations, including funding, capacity, and staffing practices at the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers. The committee shall provide oversight for planning at the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers. The committee shall utilize existing studies, reports, and legislation developed to address the conditions existing at the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers. The committee shall not be limited to such studies, reports, or legislation. The committee shall issue a report with its findings and recommendations to the Legislature on or before December 15, 2020.</para><para>(3) The Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center Special Oversight Committee of the Legislature shall terminate on December 31, 2020.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1144, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>