<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id306"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-435"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>50-435</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Economic Development Task Force; created; members; meetings; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds and declares that economic development is vitally important to the well-being of the State of Nebraska, and that the Legislature and the state would benefit from a more coordinated approach to legislation addressing economic development.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska Economic Development Task Force is created. The task force shall collaborate with the Department of Economic Development and the Department of Labor to gather input on issues pertaining to economic development and discuss proactive approaches on economic development. The task force shall monitor analysis and policy development in all aspects of economic development in Nebraska. The task force shall also discuss long-range strategic plans to improve economic development within the state.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska Economic Development Task Force shall be composed of three members of the Legislature appointed by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, one from each congressional district, and the following seven members: The chairperson of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, the chairperson of the Banking, Commerce and Insurance Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, the chairperson of the Business and Labor Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, the chairperson of the Education Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, the chairperson of the Revenue Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, the chairperson of the Legislature's Planning Committee or his or her designee, and the chairperson of the Urban Affairs Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee. The task force members shall choose a chairperson and vice-chairperson from among the task force members.</para><para>(4)(a) The Nebraska Economic Development Task Force shall meet on or before June 15, 2017, and on or before each June 15 thereafter.</para><para>(b) Following the meeting required by subdivision (4)(a) of this section, the task force shall meet not less than once every three months, but shall not be required to meet while the Legislature is in session.</para><para>(c) Meetings of the task force shall be called by the chairperson.</para><para>(d) The task force may ask other persons or entities to attend its meetings or present information at such meetings.</para><para>(e) The task force shall annually identify economic development priorities and electronically submit a report to the Legislature on or before December 31, 2017, and on or before each December 31 thereafter.</para><para>(5) This section shall terminate on January 1, 2021.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB641, &#167; 5. </para><terminationdate>January 1, 2021</terminationdate></source></law>
</legaldoc>