<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-417.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-417.04</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officers retirement plans survey; purpose; report; actuarial survey.</catchline><para>(1) The retirement system shall conduct a survey of the retirement plans currently in place for law enforcement officers throughout Nebraska. The retirement system shall conduct the survey and issue a report to the committee no later than October 1, 2007.</para><para>(2) At the time that the report is provided to the committee, information which supports the report shall be provided to any firm employed to conduct an actuarial survey from the information gathered by the retirement system upon the firm's request. The information provided shall not include any personal information such as the name or social security number of law enforcement officers.</para><para>(3) The survey shall include, but not be limited to, the following information:</para><para>(a) What types of retirement plans are in place for law enforcement officers; and</para><para>(b) Any other information which the retirement system or the committee deems necessary.</para><para>(4) The retirement system shall create, in consultation with the committee, a method to receive the materials required for the survey. The method shall utilize a unique identifier for each law enforcement officer, each political subdivision, and the state agency responding.</para><para>(5) The purpose of the survey is to conduct a review of the many retirement plans throughout Nebraska for law enforcement officers and to assist an actuarial firm in determining the cost to implement a defined benefit retirement plan with benefits capped at various levels between sixty and eighty percent of pay with costs separately determined for cities of the first class, cities of the second class, villages, counties, and the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc>