<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-702"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>50-702</statuteno><catchline>Legislative Mental Health Care Capacity Strategic Planning Committee; established; members; independent consultant; recommendations; termination.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislative Mental Health Care Capacity Strategic Planning Committee is established. The committee shall consist of the following members: (a) The chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, (b) the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, (c) the chairperson of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee, and (d) four senators selected by the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council. The committee shall select a chairperson and vice-chairperson from among its members.</para><para>(2)(a) No later than November 1, 2023, the Legislative Mental Health Care Capacity Strategic Planning Committee shall contract with an independent consultant with expertise in inpatient mental health care delivery. The contract shall be awarded based on competitive bids and be subject to the approval of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council upon a recommendation of a majority of the committee. The consultant shall assist the committee in determining the necessary capacity for inpatient mental health care beds for both state-operated and privately owned facilities based on best practices in mental health care. The consultant shall provide recommendations to achieve the necessary capacity if the current state inpatient mental health bed capacity is insufficient.</para><para>(b) On or before November 1, 2024, the consultant shall provide a written report of its findings and recommendations to the Legislative Mental Health Care Capacity Strategic Planning Committee.</para><para>(3) This section terminates on November 1, 2025.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB921, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB254, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>