<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-125</statuteno><catchline>Legislature; special session; how convened; notice.</catchline><para>Whenever ten or more members of the Legislature shall lodge with the Secretary of State a positive statement in writing, over their signatures respectively, setting forth the purpose or purposes for which said Legislature is convened, requesting that the Legislature meet in special session, personally delivered or transmitted by either registered or certified mail, return card requested, the Secretary of State shall forthwith certify to each of the other members of the Legislature, transmitted by either registered or certified mail, return card requested, the fact that ten or more members have lodged such statements with him and the object or objects of calling such session. If within ten days thereafter an additional number of the members of the Legislature, sufficient to make two-thirds or more, shall lodge statements in like manner as aforementioned with the Secretary of State, requesting that the Legislature meet in special session, the Secretary of State shall forthwith certify to the Governor the fact that two-thirds or more of said members have lodged said statements with him and the object or objects of calling such session. Thereupon the Governor shall, by proclamation, stating therein the purpose or purposes for which it is called, convene the Legislature to meet in special session within five days after receipt of said certificate from the Secretary of State. The Legislature shall enter upon no business except that for which it was called together.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 117, &#167; 2, p. 419; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 50-118; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 50-125; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 242, &#167; 42, p. 854; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 430, &#167; 1, p. 1452. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 