<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-417.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-417.05</statuteno><catchline>Political subdivisions and state; provide information; confidentiality.</catchline><para>Each political subdivision and the state shall provide the retirement system with such information as the retirement system deems necessary and appropriate to conduct the review required under section 50-417.04. The material to be obtained by the retirement system may include, but not be limited to, the following concerning law enforcement officers employed by the political subdivision or the state:</para><para>(1) Names;</para><para>(2) Dates of birth;</para><para>(3) Dates of hire;</para><para>(4) Taxable earnings for the prior fiscal year;</para><para>(5) Years of service;</para><para>(6) Gender;</para><para>(7) Whether or not the law enforcement officer is enrolled in a retirement plan;</para><para>(8) The type of plan the law enforcement officer is enrolled in, the required employee contribution percentage, and the employer contribution percentage, along with an indication if it is a fixed percentage or a variable contribution rate. If the law enforcement officer is enrolled in a defined contribution plan, the political subdivision or state shall also disclose the account balance attributable to employer contributions and employee contributions, excluding any balance due to rollovers from another qualified plan or attributable to voluntary employee contributions; and </para><para>(9) Any other information that the retirement system or the committee deems important to the conduct of the survey.</para><para>Any material received by the retirement system shall be considered confidential and shall not be disclosed to a third party except as provided in subsection (2) of section 50-417.04.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 15. </para></source></law></legaldoc>