<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id485"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1904"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1904</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System Act, the following definitions apply:</para><para>(1) Administrator means a person charged with administration of (a) a program or an office of the department or (b) a private agency;</para><para>(2) Department means the Department of Correctional Services;</para><para>(3) Director means the Director of Correctional Services;</para><para>(4) Inspector General means the Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System appointed under section 50-1905;</para><para>(5) Malfeasance means a wrongful act that the actor has no legal right to do or any wrongful conduct that affects, interrupts, or interferes with performance of an official duty;</para><para>(6) Management means supervision of subordinate employees;</para><para>(7) Misfeasance means the improper performance of some act that a person may lawfully do;</para><para>(8) Obstruction means hindering an investigation, preventing an investigation from progressing, stopping or delaying the progress of an investigation, or making the progress of an investigation difficult or slow;</para><para>(9) Office means the office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System and includes the Inspector General and other employees of the office;</para><para>(10) Private agency means an entity that contracts with the department or contracts to provide services to another entity that contracts with the department; and</para><para>(11) Record means any recording in written, audio, electronic, or computer storage form, including, but not limited to, a draft, memorandum, note, report, computer printout, notation, message, medical record, mental health record, case file, clinical record, financial record, and administrative record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2021), &#167; 47-903; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 48. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB150, section 56, with LB298, section 48, to reflect all amendments.</note> <note>Changes made by LB150 became operative September 3, 2025. Changes made by LB298 became effective June 5, 2025.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>