<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1153"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1153</statuteno><catchline>Legislative districts; division; population figures and maps; basis; numbers; boundaries; established by maps; Clerk of Legislature; Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The State of Nebraska is hereby divided into forty-nine legislative districts. Each district shall be entitled to one member in the Legislature. The Legislature adopts the official population figures and maps from the 2020 Census Redistricting (Public Law 94-171) TIGER/Line Shapefiles published by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census.</para><para>(2) The numbers and boundaries of the legislative districts are designated and established by maps identified and labeled as maps LEG21-39006, LEG21-39006-1, LEG21-39006-2, LEG21-39006-2A, LEG21-39006-3, LEG21-39006-4, LEG21-39006-5, LEG21-39006-6, LEG21-39006-7, LEG21-39006-8, LEG21-39006-9, LEG21-39006-10, LEG21-39006-11, LEG21-39006-12, LEG21-39006-13, LEG21-39006-14, LEG21-39006-15, LEG21-39006-15A, LEG21-39006-16, LEG21-39006-16A, LEG21-39006-17, LEG21-39006-18, LEG21-39006-19, LEG21-39006-19A, LEG21-39006-20, LEG21-39006-21, LEG21-39006-22, LEG21-39006-22A, LEG21-39006-23, LEG21-39006-24, LEG21-39006-25, LEG21-39006-26, LEG21-39006-27, LEG21-39006-28, LEG21-39006-29, LEG21-39006-30, LEG21-39006-30A, LEG21-39006-31, LEG21-39006-32, LEG21-39006-32A, LEG21-39006-33, LEG21-39006-33A, LEG21-39006-34, LEG21-39006-34A, LEG21-39006-35, LEG21-39006-36, LEG21-39006-37, LEG21-39006-38, LEG21-39006-38A, LEG21-39006-39, LEG21-39006-40, LEG21-39006-40A, LEG21-39006-40B, LEG21-39006-41, LEG21-39006-41A, LEG21-39006-41B, LEG21-39006-42, LEG21-39006-42A, LEG21-39006-43, LEG21-39006-44, LEG21-39006-44A, LEG21-39006-45, LEG21-39006-46, LEG21-39006-47, LEG21-39006-48, and LEG21-39006-49, filed with the Clerk of the Legislature, and incorporated by reference as part of Laws 2021, LB3, One Hundred Seventh Legislature, First Special Session.</para><para>(3)(a) The Clerk of the Legislature shall transfer possession of the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section to the Secretary of State on October 1, 2021.</para><para>(b) When questions of interpretation of legislative district boundaries arise, the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section in possession of the Secretary of State shall serve as the indication of the legislative intent in drawing the legislative district boundaries.</para><para>(c) Each election commissioner or county clerk shall obtain copies of the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section for the election commissioner's or clerk's county from the Secretary of State.</para><para>(d) The Secretary of State shall also have available for viewing on his or her website the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section identifying the boundaries for the legislative districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-201; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 50-1101; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB703, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>
