<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1140"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1140</statuteno><catchline>District No. 39, description.</catchline><para>District No. 39 shall contain those parts of Douglas, Washington, and Sarpy counties beginning at the intersection of the Douglas, Washington, and Dodge County lines, west along the Douglas-Dodge County line to North 264th Street, south on North 264th Street to U.S. Highway 275, southeast then south on U.S. Highway 275 to 240th Street, south on 240th Street to West Center Road, east on West Center Road to South 204th Street, south on South 204th Street to F Street, east on F Street to South 192nd Street, south on South 192nd Street to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, east along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to South 180th Street, south on South 180th Street and continuing south along a north-south line extending south from South 180th Street to the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way, east along the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way to South 144th Street, north on South 144th Street to Josephine Street, east on Josephine Street to South 139th Avenue, south on South 139th Avenue to Frederick Avenue, east on Frederick Avenue to South 137th Avenue, northeast on South 137th Avenue to South 136th Street, south on South 136th Street to Edna Street, east on Edna Street to South 132nd Avenue, north on South 132nd Avenue to Gertrude Street, east on Gertrude Street to South 132nd Street, north on South 132nd Street to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, west along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to South 161st Avenue, follow South 161st Avenue north to Z Street, west on Z Street to Washington Street, west on Washington Street to South 166th Avenue, north on South 166th Avenue to Y Street, east on Y Street to South 166th Street, north on South 166th Street to S Street, northeast on S Street to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from South 165th Street, north along such line to South 165th Street, north on South 165th Street to Ohern Street, west then northwest on Ohern Street to Riggs Street, west on Riggs Street to South 167th Street, north on South 167th Street to Holmes Street, east on Holmes Street to South 167th Street, north on South 167th Street to Rolling Ridge Road, west on Rolling Ridge Road to South 168th Street, north on South 168th Street to the intersection of an east-west line extending west from the intersection of South 163rd Street and Harney Street, east along such line to South 163rd Street, north on South 163rd Street to Lamp Street, east on Lamp Street to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from South 160th Street, north along such line to Capitol Avenue, east on Capitol Avenue to South 160th Street, north on South 160th Street to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Davenport Street, east along such line to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from South 157th Street, north along such line to West Dodge Road, west on West Dodge Road to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from North 168th Street, north along such line to North 168th Street, north on North 168th Street to Ida Street, east on Ida Street to North 156th Street, north on North 156th Street to State Street, east on State Street to North 132nd Street, north on North 132nd Street to the Douglas-Washington County line, west along the Douglas-Washington County line to County Road 33, north on County Road 33 to County Road 38, west on County Road 38 to County Road 29, north on County Road 29 to County Road P30, west then north on County Road P30 to U.S. Highway 30, northeast on U.S. Highway 30 to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from County Road 30, west along such line to County Road 30, west on County Road 30 and continuing west along east-west lines extending west from County Road 30 to the Washington-Dodge County line, and southeast then south along the Washington-Dodge County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 40; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-240; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 40. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 