<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1208" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1208</statuteno><catchline>Performance audit; committee; duties; section; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The committee shall, by majority vote, adopt requests for performance audit. The committee chairperson shall notify each requester of any action taken on his or her request.</para><para>(2) Before the section begins a performance audit, it shall notify in writing the agency director, the program director, when relevant, and the Governor that a performance audit will be conducted.</para><para>(3) Following notification, the section shall arrange an entrance conference to provide the agency with further information about the audit process. The agency director shall inform the agency staff, in writing, of the performance audit and shall instruct agency staff to cooperate fully with the section.</para><para>(4) After the entrance conference, the section shall conduct the research necessary to draft a scope statement for consideration by the committee. The scope statement shall identify the specific issues to be addressed in the audit. The committee shall, by majority vote, adopt, reject, or amend and adopt the scope statement prepared by the section.</para><para>(5) Once the committee has adopted a scope statement, the section shall develop an audit plan. The audit plan shall include a description of the research and audit methodologies to be employed and a projected deadline for completion of the section's report. The audit plan shall be submitted to the committee, and a majority vote shall be required for its approval.</para><para>(6) If the performance audit reveals a need to modify the scope statement or audit plan, the Legislative Auditor may request that the committee make revisions. A majority vote shall be required to revise the scope statement or audit plan. The agency shall be notified in writing of any revision to the scope statement or audit plan.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 988, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 607, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 956, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>