<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id940"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1705"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1705</statuteno><catchline>Director of Legislative Oversight; appointment; term; removal; vacancy; qualifications; salary; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Director of Legislative Oversight shall be appointed by the Legislature, with the vote of two-thirds of the members required for approval of such appointment, from nominations submitted by the Legislative Oversight Committee. The director shall serve for a term of six years, unless removed by a two-thirds vote of the members of the Legislature or, if the Legislature is not in session, by a two-thirds vote of the members of the Legislative Council. If the office of Director of Legislative Oversight becomes vacant for any reason, the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council shall appoint an acting director until a successor Director of Legislative Oversight is appointed. The director shall be selected without regard to political affiliation and on the basis of integrity, capability for strong leadership, commitment to government oversight, and demonstrated ability in accounting, auditing, financial analysis, law, management analysis, public administration, investigation, or criminal justice administration or other closely related fields. No person may serve as director within two years after the last day on which such person served as a member of the Legislature or while such person is a candidate for or holds any other state office. The director shall receive such salary as is set by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>(2) The Director of Legislative Oversight shall:</para><para>(a) Develop key performance indicators, with the approval of the Legislative Oversight Committee, for both short-term and long-term legislative oversight of state agencies and programs;</para><para>(b) Make recommendations to the Legislative Oversight Committee and the Executive Board of the Legislative Council regarding the duties, responsibilities, and activities of the division and division staff;</para><para>(c) Ensure that all assessments, investigations, audits, inspections, and other reviews are conducted by the division without regard to special or partisan interest and in accordance with relevant standards or guidelines; and</para><para>(d) Carry out the director's duties under the Legislative Performance Audit Act, the Office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare Act, and the Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 21. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Legislative Performance Audit Act,</emphasis> see section 50-1201.</para><para><emphasis>Office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare Act,</emphasis> see section 50-1801.</para><para><emphasis>Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System Act,</emphasis> see section 50-1901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>