<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1110</statuteno><catchline>District No. 9, description.</catchline><para>District No. 9 shall contain that part of Douglas County beginning at the intersection of North 24th Street and Cuming Street, south on North 24th Street to South 24th Street, south on South 24th Street to St. Mary's Avenue, west on St. Mary's Avenue to South 24th Street, south on South 24th Street to Leavenworth Street, west on Leavenworth Street to Interstate Highway 480, south on Interstate Highway 480 to Ed Creighton Avenue, west on Ed Creighton Avenue to Hanscom Boulevard, follow Hanscom Boulevard south to Vinton Street, west on Vinton Street to South 32nd Avenue, north on South 32nd Avenue to Spring Street, west on Spring Street to South 34th Street, north on South 34th Street to Frederick Street, west on Frederick Street to South 35th Street, north on South 35th Street to Oak Street, west on Oak Street and continuing west along an east-west line extending west from Oak Street to Field Club Trail, north on Field Club Trail to Wright Street, west on Wright Street to South 39th Street, follow South 39th Street north to Martha Street, west on Martha Street to South 39th Street, north on South 39th Street to Frances Street, west on Frances Street to South 48th Street, north on South 48th Street to Poppleton Avenue, west on Poppleton Avenue to South 55th Street, north on South 55th Street to Poppleton Avenue, west on Poppleton Avenue to South 56th Street, south on South 56th Street to William Street, west on William Street to South 60th Street, north on South 60th Street to William Street, west on William Street to South 63rd Street, north on South 63rd Street to Pacific Street, west on Pacific Street to South 67th Street, north on South 67th Street to Leavenworth Street, west on Leavenworth Street to South 67th Street, north on South 67th Street to Howard Street, west on Howard Street to South 68th Street, north on South 68th Street to Dodge Street, east on Dodge Street to North 46th Street, north on North 46th Street to California Street, east on California Street to North Saddle Creek Road, north on North Saddle Creek Road to Cuming Street, east on Cuming Street to North 40th Street, north on North 40th Street to Nicholas Street, east on Nicholas Street to Hawthorne Avenue, east on Hawthorne Avenue to North 34th Street, south on North 34th Street to Lincoln Boulevard, east on Lincoln Boulevard to North 33rd Street, south on North 33rd Street to Cuming Street, and east on Cuming Street to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-210; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 