<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1130"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1130</statuteno><catchline>District No. 29, description.</catchline><para>District No. 29 shall contain that part of Lancaster County beginning at the intersection of South 27th Street and Rokeby Road, east on Rokeby Road to South 40th Street, north on South 40th Street to the southern boundary of 9H-4 Precinct, follow such boundary east to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Tucson Drive, west along such line to San Mateo Lane, north on San Mateo Lane to Birch Creek Drive, east then south on Birch Creek Drive to Union Hill Road, east on Union Hill Road to South 48th Street, north on South 48th Street to Beaver Creek Lane, north on Beaver Creek Lane to Pine Lake Road, east on Pine Lake Road to South 56th Street, north on South 56th Street to Elkcrest Drive, west on Elkcrest Drive to South 54th Street, south on South 54th Street to Woodland Avenue, west on Woodland Avenue to South 53rd Street, north on South 53rd Street to Claire Avenue, west on Claire Avenue to South 52nd Street, north on South 52nd Street to Pioneers Boulevard, west on Pioneers Boulevard to South 52nd Street, north on South 52nd Street to Prescott Avenue, east on Prescott Avenue to South 54th Street, north on South 54th Street to Calvert Street, east on Calvert Street to South 56th Street, north on South 56th Street to South Street, west on South Street to South 27th Street, south on South 27th Street to Sheridan Boulevard, southeast on Sheridan Boulevard to Van Dorn Street, east on Van Dorn Street to the off-street bike path, southwest along the off-street bike path to State Highway 2, west on State Highway 2 to South 27th Street, and south on South 27th Street to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-230; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 30. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 