<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id472"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1915"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1915</statuteno><catchline>Report; director; accept, reject, or request modification; when final; written response; corrected report; appended material.</catchline><para>(1) Within fifteen business days after a report is presented to the director under section 50-1914, the director may determine whether to accept, reject, or request modification of the recommendations contained in the report. Any response shall be in writing and may include corrections of factual errors. The Inspector General, with input from the Director of Legislative Oversight, may consider any request for modifications but is not obligated to accept such request. Such report shall become final (a) upon the decision of the director to accept or reject the recommendations in the report, (b) within fifteen business days after the director requests modifications or after the Inspector General incorporates such modifications, whichever occurs earlier, or (c) fifteen days after the report is presented to the director if no response is made. If the Inspector General does not accept a requested modification, the recommendation for which such modification was requested shall be considered to be rejected by the director.</para><para>(2) Within fifteen business days after the report is presented to the director, the report shall be presented to the private agency or other provider of correctional services that is the subject of the report and to persons involved in the implementation of the recommendations in the report. Within fifteen business days after receipt of the report, the private agency or other provider may submit a written response to the office to correct any factual errors in the report. The Inspector General, with input from the Director of Legislative Oversight, shall consider all materials submitted under this subsection to determine whether a corrected report shall be issued. If the Inspector General determines that a corrected report is necessary, the corrected report shall be issued within fifteen business days after receipt of the written response.</para><para>(3) If the Inspector General does not issue a corrected report pursuant to subsection (2) of this section or if the corrected report does not address all issues raised in the written response, the private agency or other provider may request that its written response, or portions of the response, be appended to the report or corrected report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 15; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2021), &#167; 47-915; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 59. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>