<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id377"><amendatorysection statutenumber="50-1516" chaptername="Legislature"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1516</statuteno><catchline>Election contest; grounds.</catchline><para>(1) The election of a person to represent a legislative district as a member of the Legislature may be contested for any or all of the following grounds:</para><para>(a) For misconduct, fraud, or corruption on the part of an election commissioner, a county clerk, an inspector, a judge or clerk of election, a member of a counting or canvassing board, or an employee of the election commissioner or county clerk sufficient to change the result;</para><para>(b) If the respondent member has given or offered to any voter or an election commissioner, a county clerk, an inspector, a judge or clerk of election, a member of a counting or canvassing board, or an employee of the election commissioner or county clerk any bribe or reward in money, property, or thing of value for the purpose of procuring his or her election;</para><para>(c) If illegal votes have been received or legal votes rejected at the polls sufficient to change the results;</para><para>(d) For any error of any board of canvassers in counting the votes or in declaring the result of the election if the error would change the result;</para><para>(e) If the respondent member is in default as a collector and custodian of public money or property; or</para><para>(f) For any other cause which shows that another person was legally elected.</para><para>(2) When the misconduct is on the part of an election commissioner, a county clerk, an inspector, a judge or clerk of election, a member of a counting or canvassing board, or an employee of the election commissioner or county clerk, it shall be insufficient to set aside the election unless the vote of the county or precinct would change the result as to that office.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB744, &#167; 23. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>