<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id312"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id212" statutenumber="50-1814"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1814</statuteno><catchline>Inspector General's report of investigation; contents; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) The Inspector General's report of an investigation shall be in writing and may contain recommendations for systemic reform. A report of an investigation shall be presented to the Director of Legislative Oversight and the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee. The Inspector General shall present the report of an investigation to the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director within three business days after the report is presented to the Director of Legislative Oversight and the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee.</para><para>(2) Any person receiving a report under this section shall not further distribute the report or any confidential information contained in the report beyond the entity that is the subject of the report. The Inspector General, upon notifying the Director of Legislative Oversight and the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director, may distribute the report, to the extent that it is relevant to a child's welfare, to the guardian ad litem and attorneys in the juvenile court in which a case is pending involving the child or family who is the subject of the report. The report shall not be distributed beyond the parties except through the appropriate court procedures to the judge.</para><para>(3) A report that identifies misconduct, misfeasance, malfeasance, or violation of statute, rules, or regulations by an employee of the department, the juvenile services division, the commission, a private agency, a licensed child care facility, or another provider that is relevant to providing appropriate supervision of an employee may be shared with the employer of such employee. The employer shall not further distribute the report or any confidential information contained in the report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB207, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2024, &#167; 43-4327; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 37. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>