<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id445"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1912"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1912</statuteno><catchline>Reports of investigations; distribution; redact confidential information; powers of office; disclosure of confidential information; summarized final report; release.</catchline><para>(1) Reports of investigations conducted by the office shall not be distributed beyond the entity that is the subject of the report without the consent of the Inspector General.</para><para>(2) The office shall redact confidential information before distributing a report of an investigation.</para><para>(3) The office may disclose confidential information to the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee at the chairperson's request. The office may also disclose confidential information to the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee, the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, and the chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature when such disclosure is, in the judgment of the Director of Legislative Oversight, appropriate to keep the Legislature informed of important events, issues, and developments in the Nebraska correctional system.</para><para>(4) The office may also disclose such confidential information to the Legislative Oversight Committee when such disclosure is, in the judgment of the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee, appropriate to keep the Legislature informed of important events, issues, and developments in the Nebraska correctional system.</para><para>(5)(a) A summarized final report based on an investigation may be publicly released in order to bring awareness to systemic issues.</para><para>(b) Such report shall be released only:</para><para>(i) After a disclosure is made to the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee pursuant to subsection (3) of this section; and</para><para>(ii) If a determination is made by the Inspector General with the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee that doing so would be in the best interest of the public.</para><para>(c) If there is disagreement about whether releasing the report would be in the best interest of the public, the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council shall make the final decision.</para><para>(d) The Legislative Oversight Committee shall be notified prior to a report of an investigation being publicly released under this section.</para><para>(6) Records and documents, regardless of physical form, that are obtained or produced by the office in the course of an investigation are not public records for purposes of sections 84-712 to 84-712.09. Reports of investigations conducted by the office are not public records for purposes of sections 84-712 to 84-712.09.</para><para>(7) The office may withhold the identity of sources of information to protect from retaliation any person who files a complaint or provides information in good faith pursuant to the Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB539, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2021), &#167; 47-912; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 56. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>