<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id719"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id208" statutenumber="50-1813"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1813</statuteno><catchline>Department; commission; juvenile services division; provide access to information; manner; objections.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall provide the Director of Legislative Oversight and the office with access to records, reports, and documents maintained by the department in connection with administration of the Nebraska child welfare system.</para><para>(2) The commission shall provide the office with access to records, reports, and documents maintained in connection with administration of juvenile justice services.</para><para>(3) The juvenile services division, as directed by the juvenile court or the Office of Probation Administration, shall provide the office with access to records, reports, and documents maintained by the juvenile services division in connection with a specific case under investigation.</para><para>(4) Information shall be provided in the most efficient and timely way, in a manner that is least burdensome to the department, commission, or juvenile services division, and in a manner which maintains the confidentiality of the information. This may include providing information through secure electronic access to case files and secure access to information maintained electronically in databases and case management systems. The office, by and through the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, may enter into information-sharing agreements with the department, the commission, or the juvenile services division to assist in the implementation of and compliance with the Office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare Act.</para><para>(5)(a) The department, commission, or juvenile services division may object to the production or disclosure of records, reports, and documents in writing on the grounds that such records, reports, and documents are legally privileged, identifying the specific grounds for such objection. Following such objection, the office and the department, commission, or juvenile services division may negotiate terms of production or disclosure pursuant to this section.</para><para>(b) In the event that satisfactory terms of production or disclosure cannot be reached between the office and the department, commission, or juvenile services division, the office may request the issuance of a subpoena pursuant to section 50-1810.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB954, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 43-4326; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 36. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>