<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1126"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1126</statuteno><catchline>District No. 25, description.</catchline><para>District No. 25 shall contain that part of Lancaster County beginning at the intersection of North 27th Street and the Lancaster-Saunders County line, east then south along the Lancaster-Saunders County line to the Lancaster-Cass County line, south along the Lancaster-Cass County line to the Lancaster-Otoe County line, south along the Lancaster-Otoe County line to Yankee Hill Road, west on Yankee Hill Road to South 91st Street, south on South 91st Street to Yankee Hill Road, west on Yankee Hill Road to South 70th Street, south on South 70th Street to Rokeby Road, west on Rokeby Road and continuing west along an east-west line extending west from Rokeby Road to South 40th Street, north on South 40th Street to the southern boundary of 9H-4 Precinct, follow such boundary east to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Tucson Drive, west along such line to San Mateo Lane, north on San Mateo Lane to Birch Creek Drive, east then south on Birch Creek Drive to Union Hill Road, east on Union Hill Road to South 48th Street, north on South 48th Street to Beaver Creek Lane, north on Beaver Creek Lane to Pine Lake Road, east on Pine Lake Road to South 56th Street, north on South 56th Street to Elkcrest Drive, west on Elkcrest Drive to South 54th Street, south on South 54th Street to Woodland Avenue, west on Woodland Avenue to South 53rd Street, north on South 53rd Street to Claire Avenue, west on Claire Avenue to South 52nd Street, north on South 52nd Street to Pioneers Boulevard, west on Pioneers Boulevard to South 52nd Street, north on South 52nd Street to Prescott Avenue, east on Prescott Avenue to South 54th Street, north on South 54th Street to Calvert Street, east on Calvert Street to South 56th Street, north on South 56th Street to A Street, east on A Street to South 70th Street, north on South 70th Street to O Street, east on O Street to the eastern boundary of 12B-8 Precinct, follow such boundary north to the southern boundary of 12A-8 Precinct, follow such boundary east then north to David Murdock Trail, west on David Murdock Trail to the eastern boundary of 12C-6 Precinct, follow such boundary north to the eastern boundary of 12E Precinct, follow such boundary north then west to the eastern boundary of 12F Precinct, follow such boundary north, west, south, then west to North 27th Street, and north on North 27th Street to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-226; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 26. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 