<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1122</statuteno><catchline>District No. 21, description.</catchline><para>District No. 21 shall contain that part of Saunders County not included in legislative district 23 and that part of Lancaster County beginning at the intersection of the Lancaster-Seward County line and West Van Dorn Street, east on West Van Dorn Street to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from Southwest 33rd Street, north along such line to Southwest 33rd Street, north then northwest on Southwest 33rd Street to Timber Ridge Road, north on Timber Ridge Road to West A Street, east on West A Street to the eastern boundary of Garfield 2 Precinct, follow such boundary north to the southern boundary of 1F-2 Precinct, follow such boundary east to Oak Creek, east along Oak Creek to Interstate Highway 180, south on Interstate Highway 180 to Salt Creek, northeast along Salt Creek to North 14th Street, north on North 14th Street to Superior Street, east on Superior Street to Bel Ridge Drive, north on Bel Ridge Drive and continuing north along a north-south line extending north from Bel Ridge Drive to Hartland Road, east on Hartland Road to North 17th Street, follow North 17th Street north to Prairie Lane, east on Prairie Lane to North 20th Street, south on North 20th Street to Boston Drive, east on Boston Drive to Valley Forge Road, north on Valley Forge Road to Philadelphia Drive, east on Philadelphia Drive to North 25th Street, north on North 25th Street to Folkways Boulevard, east on Folkways Boulevard to North 27th Street, north on North 27th Street to the Lancaster-Saunders County line, west along the Lancaster-Saunders County line to the Lancaster-Seward County line, and south along the Lancaster-Seward County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 22; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-222; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 22. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 