<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1128"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1128</statuteno><catchline>District No. 27, description.</catchline><para>District No. 27 shall contain that part of Lancaster County beginning at the intersection of West Van Dorn Street and a north-south line extending south from Southwest 33rd Street, north along such line to Southwest 33rd Street, north then northwest on Southwest 33rd Street to Timber Ridge Road, north on Timber Ridge Road to West A Street, east on West A Street to the eastern boundary of Garfield 2 Precinct, follow such boundary north to the southern boundary of 1F-2 Precinct, follow such boundary east to Oak Creek, east along Oak Creek to Interstate Highway 180, south on Interstate Highway 180 to North 9th Street, south on North 9th Street to O Street, east on O Street to South 12th Street, south on South 12th Street to South Street, east on South Street to South 27th Street, south on South 27th Street to Sheridan Boulevard, southeast on Sheridan Boulevard to Van Dorn Street, east on Van Dorn Street to the off-street bike path, southwest along the off-street bike path to State Highway 2, west on State Highway 2 to South 27th Street, south on South 27th Street to Pine Lake Road, west on Pine Lake Road to Helen Witt Drive, southeast then south on Helen Witt Drive to the southern boundary of 5E-6 Precinct, follow such boundary west to South 14th Street, north on South 14th Street to the southern boundary of 5E-4 Precinct, follow such boundary west, northeast, then west to the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way, follow the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way north to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Pioneers Boulevard, west along such line to Pioneers Boulevard, west on Pioneers Boulevard to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, north along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to the western boundary of 5E-1 Precinct, follow such boundary north then west to the southern boundary of Garfield 2(1) Precinct, follow such boundary west to West Van Dorn Street, and west on West Van Dorn Street to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 28; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-228; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 28. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 