<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id575"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id135" statutenumber="50-1805"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1805</statuteno><catchline>Office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare; created; purpose; Inspector General; appointment; term; certification; employees; removal.</catchline><para>(1) The office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare is created within the Division of Legislative Oversight for the purpose of conducting investigations, audits, inspections, and other oversight of the Nebraska child welfare system for the Legislature. The Inspector General shall be appointed by the Director of Legislative Oversight with approval from the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee, and the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) The Inspector General shall be appointed for a term of five years and may be reappointed. The Inspector General shall be selected without regard to political affiliation and on the basis of integrity, capability for strong leadership, and demonstrated ability in accounting, auditing, financial analysis, law, management analysis, public administration, investigation, or criminal justice administration or other closely related fields. No former or current executive or manager of the department may be appointed Inspector General within five years after such former or current executive's or manager's period of service with the department. Not later than two years after the date of appointment, the Inspector General shall obtain certification as a Certified Inspector General by the Association of Inspectors General, its successor, or another nationally recognized organization that provides and sponsors educational programs and establishes professional qualifications, certifications, and licensing for inspectors general. During the Inspector General's employment, the Inspector General shall not be actively involved in partisan affairs.</para><para>(3) The Inspector General shall employ such investigators and support staff as the Inspector General deems necessary to carry out the duties of the office within the amount available by appropriation through the Division of Legislative Oversight for the office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare. The Inspector General shall be subject to the control and supervision of the Director of Legislative Oversight, except that removal of the Inspector General shall require approval of the chairperson of the Legislative Oversight Committee. The Inspector General may also be removed by a two-thirds majority vote of the Legislative Oversight Committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 43-4317; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 28. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>