<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1132</statuteno><catchline>District No. 31, description.</catchline><para>District No. 31 shall contain that part of Douglas County beginning at the intersection of the Douglas-Sarpy County line and South 138th Street, north on South 138th Street to Q Street, east on Q Street to South 120th Street, north on South 120th Street to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, west along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to South 132nd Street, north on South 132nd Street to West Center Road, west on West Center Road to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, northwest along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to Pacific Street, east on Pacific Street to South 156th Street, north on South 156th Street to West Dodge Road, west on West Dodge Road to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from South 157th Street, south along such line to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Davenport Street, west along such line to South 160th Street, south on South 160th Street to Capitol Avenue, west on Capitol Avenue to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from South 160th Street, south along such line to Lamp Street, west on Lamp Street to South 163rd Street, south on South 163rd Street to Harney Street, west along an east-west line extending west from the intersection of South 163rd Street and Harney Street to South 168th Street, south on South 168th Street to Rolling Ridge Road, east on Rolling Ridge Road to South 167th Street, south on South 167th Street to Holmes Street, west on Holmes Street to South 167th Street, south on South 167th Street to Riggs Street, east on Riggs Street to Ohern Street, southeast then east on Ohern Street to South 165th Street, south on South 165th Street and continuing south along a north-south line extending south from South 165th Street to S Street, southwest on S Street to South 166th Street, south on South 166th Street to Y Street, west on Y Street to South 166th Avenue, south on South 166th Avenue to Washington Street, east on Washington Street to Z Street, east on Z Street to South 161st Avenue, follow South 161st Avenue south to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, and east along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 32; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-232; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 32. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 