<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="50-1211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1211</statuteno><catchline>Committee; review materials; reports;
public hearing; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The committee shall review
the office's report, the agency's
response, the Legislative Auditor's summary of the agency's response, and
the Legislative Fiscal Analyst's opinion prescribed in section 50-1210. The
committee may amend and shall adopt or reject each recommendation in the report
and indicate whether each recommendation can be implemented by the agency
within its current appropriation. The adopted recommendations shall be incorporated
into a committee report, which shall be approved by majority vote.</para>
<para>(2) The committee report shall include, but not be limited to, the office's report, the agency's written response
to the report, the Legislative Auditor's summary of the agency response, the
committee's recommendations, and any opinions of the Legislative Fiscal Analyst
regarding whether the committee's recommendations can be implemented by the
agency within its current appropriation.</para>
<para>(3) The committee may decide, by majority vote, to defer adoption of
a committee report pending a public hearing. If the committee elects to schedule
a public hearing, it shall release, for review by interested persons prior
to the hearing, the office's report, the agency's
response, the Legislative Auditor's summary of the agency's response, and
any opinions of the Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The public hearing shall be
held not less than ten nor more than twenty business days following release
of the materials.</para>
<para>(4) When the committee elects to schedule a hearing, a summary of the
testimony received at the hearing shall be attached to the committee report
as an addendum. A transcript of the testimony received at the hearing shall
be on file with the committee and available for public inspection. Unless
the committee votes to delay release of the committee report, the report shall
be released within forty business days after the public hearing.</para>
<para>(5) Once the committee has approved its report, the committee shall,
by majority vote, cause the committee report to be released to all members
of the Legislature and to the public. The report submitted to the members
of the Legislature shall be submitted electronically. The committee may, by
majority vote, release the committee report or portions thereof prior to public
release of the report.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 988, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 607, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 956, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB39, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>