<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1105</statuteno><catchline>District No. 4, description.</catchline><para>District No. 4 shall contain that part of Douglas County beginning at the intersection of West Center Road and the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, northwest along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to Pacific Street, east on Pacific Street to South 156th Street, north on South 156th Street to North 156th Street, north on North 156th Street to West Maple Road, east on West Maple Road to North 132nd Street, south on North 132nd Street to Blondo Street, east on Blondo Street to North 123rd Street, south on North 123rd Street to Decatur Street, west on Decatur Street to North 126th Street, south on North 126th Street to Charles Street, east on Charles Street to Rose Lane, follow Rose Lane south to North 122nd Street, south on North 122nd Street to Burt Street, west on Burt Street to Burt Plaza, west on Burt Plaza to North 124th Court, north on North 124th Court to Burt Court, west on Burt Court to Rose Lane, southwest on Rose Lane to Burt Street, west on Burt Street to the western boundary of Precinct 6-30, follow such boundary south to West Dodge Road, east on West Dodge Road to South 114th Street, south on South 114th Street to Hickory Road, southwest on Hickory Road to Crawford Road, northwest on Crawford Road to Skylark Drive, west on Skylark Drive to South 120th Street, south on South 120th Street to Shirley Street, west on Shirley Street to South 126th Street, south on South 126th Street to Marinda Street, west on Marinda Street to Royal Wood Drive, south on Royal Wood Drive to West Center Road, and west on West Center Road to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-205; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 