<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id965"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1601"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1601</statuteno><catchline>Infrastructure Review Task Force; created; transportation infrastructure; duties; members; reports.</catchline><para>(1) The Infrastructure Review Task Force is created.</para><para>(2) The task force shall:</para><para>(a) Review and analyze Nebraska's transportation infrastructure network;</para><para>(b) Examine and consider Nebraska's historic transportation infrastructure development efforts and expected future transportation infrastructure needs;</para><para>(c) Utilize information and research available from the annual report on the needs of the state highway system prepared by the Department of Transportation and any other information or resources available to the department;</para><para>(d) Examine the status and condition of Nebraska's transportation infrastructure with consideration given to highway safety concerns and make recommendations as to how Nebraska might maintain and ensure safe transportation infrastructure now and in the future;</para><para>(e) Consider transportation through the lens of its economic impact on Nebraska; and</para><para>(f) Research any federal funding that may be available to Nebraska and make recommendations as to how Nebraska might obtain and use such funds.</para><para>(3)(a) The task force consists of the following members:</para><para>(i) The Governor;</para><para>(ii) A designee of the Governor;</para><para>(iii) The chairperson of the Revenue Committee of the Legislature;</para><para>(iv) The chairperson of the Transportation and Telecommunications Committee of the Legislature;</para><para>(v) The Speaker of the Legislature;</para><para>(vi) The Director-State Engineer;</para><para>(vii) The Tax Commissioner; and</para><para>(viii) Three members of the Legislature appointed by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>(b) Members of the task force who are not members of the Legislature shall be nonvoting, ex officio members.</para><para>(4) The chairperson of the task force shall be the chairperson of the Revenue Committee of the Legislature. Any staff support needed for the task force shall be fulfilled by the staff of the Revenue Committee of the Legislature.</para><para>(5) The members of the task force shall serve on the task force without compensation.</para><para>(6) On or before December 1 of each year, the task force shall submit a report containing the results of its work study and its recommendations, if any, together with drafts of legislation necessary to carry out its recommendations. The reports shall be submitted electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB558, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>