<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1112</statuteno><catchline>District No. 11, description.</catchline><para>District No. 11 shall contain that part of Douglas County beginning at the intersection of the Grace Street Outfall and the Nebraska-Iowa state line, north along the Nebraska-Iowa state line to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Cornish Boulevard, west along such line to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, north along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to Ames Avenue, west on Ames Avenue to North 20th Street, north on North 20th Street to Florence Boulevard, northwest on Florence Boulevard to Ogden Street, west on Ogden Street to North 24th Street, north on North 24th Street to Kansas Avenue, west on Kansas Avenue to North 30th Street, south on North 30th Street to Laurel Avenue, west on Laurel Avenue to North 42nd Street, south on North 42nd Street to Sorenson Parkway, west on Sorenson Parkway to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from North 48th Street, south along such line to Redman Avenue, east on Redman Avenue to North 47th Avenue, south on North 47th Avenue to Jaynes Street, west on Jaynes Street to North 48th Street, south on North 48th Street to Fort Street, east on Fort Street to North 48th Street, south on North 48th Street to Ames Avenue, west on Ames Avenue to North 52nd Street, south on North 52nd Street to Pratt Street, east on Pratt Street to North 45th Street, south on North 45th Street to Grant Street, west on Grant Street to North 45th Street, south on North 45th Street to Seward Street, east on Seward Street to North 45th Street, south on North 45th Street to Hamilton Street, east on Hamilton Street to North 42nd Street, south on North 42nd Street to Lafayette Avenue, east on Lafayette Avenue to North 40th Street, south on North 40th Street to Nicholas Street, east on Nicholas Street to Hawthorne Avenue, east on Hawthorne Avenue to North 34th Street, south on North 34th Street to Lincoln Boulevard, east on Lincoln Boulevard to North 33rd Street, south on North 33rd Street to Cuming Street, east on Cuming Street to North 15th Street, north on North 15th Street to Nicholas Street, east on Nicholas Street to North 11th Street, north on North 11th Street to Seward Street, east on Seward Street to North 6th Street, south on North 6th Street to Abbott Drive, east on Abbott Drive to the Grace Street Outfall, and southeast along the Grace Street Outfall to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-212; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 