<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1209"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1209</statuteno><catchline>Tax incentive performance audits; schedule; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Tax incentive performance audits shall be conducted by the office pursuant to this section on the following tax incentive programs:</para><para>(a) The Angel Investment Tax Credit Act;</para><para>(b) The Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act;</para><para>(c) The Nebraska Advantage Act;</para><para>(d) The Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act;</para><para>(e) The Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act;</para><para>(f) The Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act;</para><para>(g) The Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act;</para><para>(h) The New Markets Job Growth Investment Act; and</para><para>(i) Any other tax incentive program created by the Legislature for the purpose of recruitment or retention of businesses in Nebraska. In determining whether a future tax incentive program is enacted for the purpose of recruitment or retention of businesses, the office shall consider legislative intent, including legislative statements of purpose and goals, and may also consider whether the tax incentive program is promoted as a business incentive by the Department of Economic Development or other relevant state agency.</para><para>(2) The office shall develop a schedule for conducting tax incentive performance audits and shall update the schedule annually. The schedule shall ensure that each tax incentive program is reviewed at least once every three years.</para><para>(3) Each tax incentive performance audit conducted by the office pursuant to this section shall include the following:</para><para>(a) An analysis of whether the tax incentive program is meeting the following goals:</para><para>(i) Strengthening the state's economy overall by attracting new business to the state, expanding existing businesses, increasing employment, creating high-quality jobs, and increasing business investment;</para><para>(ii) Revitalizing rural and other distressed areas of the state;</para><para>(iii) Diversifying the state's economy and positioning Nebraska for the future by stimulating entrepreneurial, high-tech, and renewable energy firms; and</para><para>(iv) Any other program-specific goals found in the statutes for the tax incentive program being evaluated;</para><para>(b) An analysis of the economic and fiscal impacts of the tax incentive program. The analysis may take into account the following considerations in addition to other relevant factors:</para><para>(i) The extent to which the tax incentive changes business behavior;</para><para>(ii) The results of the tax incentive for the economy of Nebraska as a whole. This consideration includes both direct and indirect impacts generally and any effects on other Nebraska businesses; and</para><para>(iii) A comparison to the results of other economic development strategies with similar goals, other policies, or other incentives;</para><para>(c) An assessment of whether adequate protections are in place to ensure the fiscal impact of the tax incentive does not increase substantially beyond the state's expectations in future years;</para><para>(d) An assessment of the fiscal impact of the tax incentive on the budgets of local governments, if applicable; and</para><para>(e) Recommendations for any changes to statutes or rules and regulations that would allow the tax incentive program to be more easily evaluated in the future, including changes to data collection, reporting, sharing of information, and clarification of goals.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 988, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 607, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB39, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB538, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Angel Investment Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6301.</para><para><emphasis>Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5701.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,187.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2901.</para><para><emphasis>New Markets Job Growth Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 77-1101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>