<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1124</statuteno><catchline>District No. 23, description.</catchline><para>District No. 23 shall contain the county of Butler, that part of Colfax County beginning at the intersection of the Butler, Platte, and Colfax County lines, north along the Platte-Colfax County line to County Road G, east on County Road G to County Road 7, north on County Road 7 to County Road M, east on County Road M and continuing east along east-west lines extending east from County Road M to the Dodge-Colfax County line, south along the Dodge-Colfax County line to the Colfax-Butler County line, and west along the Colfax-Butler County line to the point of beginning, that part of Saunders County beginning at the intersection of the Butler-Saunders County line and County Road F, east on County Road F and continuing east along east-west lines extending from County Road F to the Saunders-Sarpy County line, north along the Saunders-Sarpy County line to the Saunders-Douglas County line, northwest along the Saunders-Douglas County line to the Saunders-Dodge County line, west along the Saunders-Dodge County line to the Saunders-Butler County line, and south along the Saunders-Butler County line to the point of beginning, that part of Sarpy County beginning at the intersection of the Sarpy-Saunders County line and U.S. Highway 6, northeast then north on U.S. Highway 6 to Capehart Road, west on Capehart Road to South 234th Street, north on South 234th Street to Schram Road, east on Schram Road to South 234th Street, north on South 234th Street to West Angus Road, northeast on West Angus Road to South 232nd Street, follow South 232nd Street north to Lincoln Road, east on Lincoln Road to U.S. Highway 6, northeast on U.S. Highway 6 to South 204th Street, north on South 204th Street to Giles Road, east on Giles Road to the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way, east along the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from South 180th Street, north along such line to South 180th Street, north on South 180th Street to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, west along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the Saunders-Sarpy County line, and south along the Saunders-Sarpy County line to the point of beginning, and that part of Douglas County beginning at the intersection of the Douglas-Sarpy County line and South 192nd Street, north on South 192nd Street to F Street, west on F Street to South 204th Street, north on South 204th Street to West Center Road, west on West Center Road to 240th Street, north on 240th Street to U.S. Highway 275, north then northwest on U.S. Highway 275 to North 264th Street, north on North 264th Street to the Douglas-Dodge County line, west along the Douglas-Dodge County line to the Douglas-Saunders County line, southeast along the Douglas-Saunders County line to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, and east along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-224; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 24. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 