<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1153"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1153</statuteno><catchline>Legislative
districts; division; population
figures and maps; basis;
numbers; boundaries; established by maps; Clerk of Legislature; Secretary
of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The State of Nebraska is hereby divided
into forty-nine legislative districts. Each district shall be entitled to
one member in the Legislature. The Legislature adopts the official population
figures and maps from the 2010 Census Redistricting (Public Law
94-171) TIGER/Line Shapefiles published by the
United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census.</para>
<para>(2) The numbers and boundaries
of the legislative districts are designated and established by maps identified
and labeled as maps LEG11-1, LEG11-1A, LEG11-43002E-2, LEG11-43002E-2A, LEG11-2B,
LEG11-3, LEG11-4, LEG11-5, LEG11-6, LEG11-7, LEG11-8, LEG11-9, LEG11-10, LEG11-11,
LEG11-12, LEG11-13, LEG11-14, LEG11-15, LEG11-16, LEG11-17, LEG11-18, LEG11-19,
LEG11-20, LEG11-21, LEG11-21A, LEG11-22, LEG11-23, LEG11-24, LEG11-25, LEG11-25A,
LEG11-26, LEG11-27, LEG11-28, LEG11-29, LEG11-30, LEG11-30A, LEG11-31, LEG11-32,
LEG11-32A, LEG11-33, LEG11-34, LEG11-34A, LEG11-35, LEG11-36, LEG11-37, LEG11-37A,
LEG11-38, LEG11-38A, LEG11-39, LEG11-40, LEG11-41, LEG11-42, LEG11-43002E-43,
LEG11-44, LEG11-45, LEG11-46, LEG11-43002E-47, LEG11-48, and LEG11-43002E-49,
filed with the Clerk of the Legislature, and incorporated by reference as
part of Laws 2011, LB703.</para><para>(3)(a)
The Clerk of the Legislature shall transfer possession of the maps referred
to in subsection (2) of this section to the Secretary of State on May 27,
2011.</para><para>(b)
When questions of interpretation of legislative district boundaries arise,
the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section in possession of the
Secretary of State shall serve as the indication of the legislative intent
in drawing the legislative district boundaries.</para><para>(c) Each election commissioner or
county clerk shall obtain copies of the maps referred to in subsection (2)
of this section for the election commissioner's or clerk's county from the
Secretary of State.</para><para>(d)
The Secretary of State shall also have available for viewing on his or her
web site the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section identifying
the boundaries for the legislative districts.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-201; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 50-1101; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB703, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>