<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1131"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1131</statuteno><catchline>District No. 30, description.</catchline><para>District No. 30 shall contain the county of Gage and that part of Lancaster County beginning at the intersection of the Lancaster, Gage, and Saline County lines, east along the Lancaster-Gage County line to the Lancaster-Otoe County line, north along the Lancaster-Otoe County line to Yankee Hill Road, west on Yankee Hill Road to South 91st Street, south on South 91st Street to Yankee Hill Road, west on Yankee Hill Road to South 70th Street, south on South 70th Street to Rokeby Road, west on Rokeby Road and continuing west along an east-west line extending west from Rokeby Road to Rokeby Road, west on Rokeby Road to South 27th Street, north on South 27th Street to Pine Lake Road, west on Pine Lake Road to Helen Witt Drive, southeast then south on Helen Witt Drive to the southern boundary of 5E-6 Precinct, follow such boundary west to South 14th Street, north on South 14th Street to the southern boundary of 5E-4 Precinct, follow such boundary west, northeast, then west to the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way, follow the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way north to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Pioneers Boulevard, west along such line to Pioneers Boulevard, west on Pioneers Boulevard to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, north along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to the western boundary of 5E-1 Precinct, follow such boundary north then west to the southern boundary of Garfield 2(1) Precinct, follow such boundary west to West Van Dorn Street, west on West Van Dorn Street to the Lancaster-Seward County line, south then west along the Lancaster-Seward County line to the Lancaster-Saline County line, and south along the Lancaster-Saline County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-231; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 31. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 