<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1147"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1147</statuteno><catchline>District No. 46, description.</catchline><para>District No. 46 shall contain that part of Lancaster County beginning at the intersection of O Street and North 35th Street, north on North 35th Street to Apple Street, east on Apple Street to North 38th Street, north on North 38th Street to Dudley Street, east on Dudley Street to North 40th Street, north on North 40th Street to Holdrege Street, east on Holdrege Street to North 48th Street, north on North 48th Street to Leighton Avenue, west then northwest on Leighton Avenue to North 44th Street, north on North 44th Street to Adams Street, east on Adams Street to North 48th Street, north on North 48th Street to David Murdock Trail, east on David Murdock Trail to the eastern boundary of 12C-6 Precinct, follow such boundary north to the eastern boundary of 12-E Precinct, follow such boundary north then west to the eastern boundary of 12-F Precinct, follow such boundary north, west, south, then west to North 27th Street, north on North 27th Street to Folkways Boulevard, west on Folkways Boulevard to North 25th Street, south on North 25th Street to Philadelphia Drive, west on Philadelphia Drive to Valley Forge Road, south on Valley Forge Road to Boston Drive, west on Boston Drive to North 20th Street, north on North 20th Street to Prairie Lane, west on Prairie Lane to North 17th Street, follow North 17th Street south to Hartland Road, west on Hartland Road to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from Bel Ridge Drive, south along such line to Bel Ridge Drive, south on Bel Ridge Drive to Superior Street, west on Superior Street to North 14th Street, south on North 14th Street to Salt Creek, southwest along Salt Creek to Interstate Highway 180, south on Interstate Highway 180 to North 9th Street, south on North 9th Street to O Street, and east on O Street to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 47; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-247; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 47. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 