<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1146"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1146</statuteno><catchline>District No. 45, description.</catchline><para>District No. 45 shall contain that part of Sarpy County beginning at the intersection of the Nebraska-Iowa state line and the Douglas-Sarpy County line, west along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, southeast along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to Childs Road, west on Childs Road to South 25th Street, north on South 25th Street to Linda Street, west on Linda Street to Cedar Island Road, south on Cedar Island Road to Childs Road, west on Childs Road to the western boundary of Bellevue 4-4 Precinct, follow such boundary north to Bonnie Street, west on Bonnie Street to South 30th Street, south on South 30th Street to Evelyn Street, west on Evelyn Street to South 32nd Street, north on South 32nd Street to Chandler Road West, west on Chandler Road West to South 36th Street, south on South 36th Street to Suburban Drive, west on Suburban Drive to South 39th Avenue, north on South 39th Avenue to South 40th Street, northwest on South 40th Street to Southern Hills Drive, southwest on Southern Hills Drive to South 42nd Street, north on South 42nd Street to Margo Street, west on Margo Street to Bernadette Avenue, west on Bernadette Avenue to South 48th Street, south on South 48th Street to Cornhusker Road, east on Cornhusker Road to South 36th Street, south on South 36th Street to Bline Avenue, east on Bline Avenue to Golden Boulevard, east on Golden Boulevard to South 31st Street, south on South 31st Street to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Sierra Street, east along such line to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from 28th Street, south along such line to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Dacey Drive, east along such line to South 25th Street, south on South 25th Street to Capehart Road, east on Capehart Road to U.S. Highway 75, south on U.S. Highway 75 to the Sarpy-Cass County line, east along the Sarpy-Cass County line to the Nebraska-Iowa state line, and north along the Nebraska-Iowa state line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 46; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-246; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 46. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 