<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="50-1213"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1213</statuteno><catchline>Office; access to information
and records; prohibited acts; penalty; proceedings; not reviewable by court;
committee or office employee; privilege;
working papers; not public records.</catchline><para>(1) The office shall
have access to any and all information and records, confidential or otherwise,
of any agency, in whatever form they may be, unless the office is
denied such access by federal law or explicitly named and denied such access
by state law. If such a law exists, the agency shall provide the committee
with a written explanation of its inability to produce such information and
records and, after reasonable accommodations are made, shall grant the office access to all information and records
or portions thereof that can legally be reviewed. Accommodations that may
be negotiated between the agency and the committee include, but are not limited
to, a requirement that specified information or records be reviewed on agency
premises and a requirement that specified working papers be securely stored
on agency premises.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in this section, any confidential information
or confidential records shared with the office shall remain confidential
and shall not be shared by an employee of the office with
any person who is not an employee of the office, including any member
of the committee. If necessary for the conduct of the performance audit, the office may discuss or share confidential information
with the chairperson of the committee. If a dispute arises between the office and the agency as to the accuracy of
a performance audit or preaudit inquiry involving confidential information
or confidential records, the Speaker of the Legislature, as a member of the
committee, will be allowed access to the confidential information or confidential
records for the purpose of assessing the accuracy of the performance audit
or preaudit inquiry.</para>
<para>(3) Except as provided in subdivision (10)(c) of section 77-27,119,
if the speaker or chairperson knowingly divulges or makes known, in any manner
not permitted by law, confidential information or confidential records, he
or she shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor. Except as provided in subsection
(11) of section 77-2711 and subdivision (10)(c) of section 77-27,119, if any
employee or former employee of the office knowingly divulges
or makes known, in any manner not permitted by law, confidential information
or confidential records, he or she shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor
and, in the case of an employee, shall be dismissed.</para>
<para>(4) No proceeding of the committee or opinion or expression of any member
of the committee or office employee acting at
the direction of the committee shall be reviewable in any court. No member
of the committee or office employee acting at
the direction of the committee shall be required to testify or produce evidence
in any judicial or administrative proceeding concerning matters relating to
the work of the office except in a proceeding
brought to enforce the Legislative Performance Audit Act.</para>
<para>(5) Pursuant to sections 84-712 and 84-712.01 and subdivision (5) of
section 84-712.05, the working papers obtained or produced by the committee
or office shall not be considered
public records. The committee may make the working papers available for purposes
of an external quality control review as required by generally accepted government
auditing standards. However, any reports made from such external quality control
review shall not make public any information which would be considered confidential
when in the possession of the office.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 988, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 607, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 588, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB39, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>