<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="50-1210"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1210</statuteno><catchline>Report of findings and recommendations;
distribution; confidentiality; agency response.</catchline><para>(1) Upon
completion of a performance audit, the office shall prepare a report
of its findings and recommendations for action. The Legislative Auditor shall
provide the office's report concurrently
to the committee, agency director, and Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The report
submitted to the committee and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted
electronically. The committee may, by majority vote, release the office's report or portions thereof to other
individuals, with the stipulation that the released material shall be kept
confidential.</para>
<para>(2) When the Legislative Auditor provides the report to the Legislative
Fiscal Analyst, the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall issue an opinion to the
committee indicating whether the office's recommendations can
be implemented by the agency within its current appropriation.</para>
<para>(3) When the Legislative Auditor provides the report to the agency,
the agency shall have twenty business days from the date of receipt of the
report to provide a written response. Any written response received from the
agency shall be attached to the committee report. The agency shall not release
any part of the report to any person outside the agency, except that an agency
may discuss the report with the Governor. The Governor shall not release any
part of the report.</para>
<para>(4) Following receipt of any written response from the agency, the Legislative
Auditor shall prepare a brief written summary of the response, including a
description of any significant disagreements the agency has with the office's report or recommendations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 988, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 607, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 956, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB39, &#167; 8.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>