<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1104</statuteno><catchline>District No. 3, description.</catchline><para>District No. 3 shall contain that part of Sarpy County beginning at the intersection of the Sarpy-Cass County line and the western boundary of La Platte I Precinct, follow such boundary north to Platteview Road, west on Platteview Road to South 84th Street, south on South 84th Street to Platteview Road, west on Platteview Road to South 216th Street, north on South 216th Street to U.S. Highway 6, north on U.S. Highway 6 to Capehart Road, west on Capehart Road to South 234th Street, north on South 234th Street to Schram Road, east on Schram Road to South 234th Street, north on South 234th Street to West Angus Road, northeast on West Angus Road to South 232nd Street, follow South 232nd Street north to Lincoln Road, east on Lincoln Road to U.S. Highway 6, northeast on U.S. Highway 6 to South 204th Street, north on South 204th Street to Giles Road, east on Giles Road to the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way, east along the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad right-of-way to South 144th Street, north on South 144th Street to Josephine Street, east on Josephine Street to South 139th Avenue, south on South 139th Avenue to Frederick Avenue, east on Frederick Avenue to South 137th Avenue, northeast on South 137th Avenue to South 136th Street, south on South 136th Street to Edna Street, east on Edna Street to South 132nd Avenue, north on South 132nd Avenue to Gertrude Street, east on Gertrude Street to South 132nd Street, north on South 132nd Street to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, east along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the intersection of a north-south line extending north from South 120th Street, south along such line to South 120th Street, south on South 120th Street and continuing south along a north-south line extending south from South 120th Street to State Highway 370, east on State Highway 370 to South 60th Street, north on South 60th Street and continuing north along a north-south line extending north from South 60th Street to West Papillion Creek, east along West Papillion Creek to South 36th Street, south on South 36th Street to Bline Avenue, east on Bline Avenue to Golden Boulevard, east on Golden Boulevard to South 31st Street, south on South 31st Street to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Sierra Street, east along such line to the intersection of a north-south line extending south from 28th Street, south along such line to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from Dacey Drive, east along such line to South 25th Street, south on South 25th Street to Capehart Road, east on Capehart Road to U.S. Highway 75, south on U.S. Highway 75 to the Sarpy-Cass County line, and west along the Sarpy-Cass County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 406, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-204; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 614, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 