<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1119.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1119.01</statuteno><catchline>District No. 18, description.</catchline><para>District No. 18 shall contain those parts of Douglas and Washington counties beginning at the intersection of the Douglas-Washington County line and the Nebraska-Iowa state line, north along the Nebraska-Iowa state line to Serenity Lane, west on Serenity Lane to County Road 35, south on County Road 35 to County Road P14, west on County Road P14 to County Road P31, south on County Road P31 to County Road P16, follow County Road P16 west to County Road 16, follow County Road 16 west to U.S. Highway 75, south on U.S. Highway 75 to South Creek, west then southwest along South Creek to State Highway 91, west on State Highway 91 to County Road 23, south on County Road 23 to the intersection of an east-west line extending east from County Road 30, east along such line to U.S. Highway 30, southwest on U.S. Highway 30 to County Road P30, south then east on County Road P30 to County Road 29, south on County Road 29 to County Road 38, east on County Road 38 to County Road 33, south on County Road 33 to the Douglas-Washington County line, east along the Douglas-Washington County line to North 132nd Street, south on North 132nd Street to State Street, west on State Street to North 156th Street, south on North 156th Street to Ida Street, west on Ida Street to North 168th Street, south on North 168th Street and continuing south along a north-south line extending south from North 168th Street to West Dodge Road, east on West Dodge Road to North 156th Street, north on North 156th Street to West Maple Road, east on West Maple Road to North 114th Avenue, north on North 114th Avenue to Manderson Street, northeast on Manderson Street to Old Maple Road, east on Old Maple Road to North 108th Street, north on North 108th Street to the intersection of an east-west line extending west from Hilltop Road, west along such line to North 112th Street, north on North 112th Street to Fowler Avenue, northwest on Fowler Avenue to North 113th Street, follow North 113th Street north to Camden Avenue, west on Camden Avenue to North 114th Street, north on North 114th Street to Crown Point Avenue, east on Crown Point Avenue to North 108th Street, north on North 108th Street to Military Road, west on Military Road to North 114th Street, north on North 114th Street to State Street, east on State Street to Blair High Road, north on Blair High Road to North 108th Street, east then north on North 108th Street to Rainwood Road, east on Rainwood Road to North 96th Street, north on North 96th Street to State Highway 36, east on State Highway 36 to North 72nd Street, north on North 72nd Street to Northern Hills Drive, east on Northern Hills Drive to Calhoun Frontage Road, northwest then east on Calhoun Frontage Road to Calhoun Road, north on Calhoun Road to the Douglas-Washington County line, and east along the Douglas-Washington County line to the point of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 852, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 