<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id979"><amendatorysection chaptername="Legislature" statutenumber="50-1704"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1704</statuteno><catchline>Division of Legislative Oversight; established; powers and duties; division staff; confidential information and confidential records; sharing; restrictions; grounds for dismissal.</catchline><para>(1) The Division of Legislative Oversight is established within the Legislative Council. The division shall be responsible for conducting assessments, investigations, audits, inspections, and other reviews of Nebraska state government to ensure the Legislature is able to carry out its responsibilities to secure needed information to legislate and appropriate. The Director of Legislative Oversight shall be responsible for hiring, firing, and supervising division staff.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Division of Legislative Oversight shall have access to confidential information and confidential records necessary to carry out its responsibilities.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided by law, any confidential information or confidential records shared with the Division of Legislative Oversight shall remain confidential and shall not be shared by an employee of the division with any person who is not an employee of the division, including any member of the Legislative Oversight Committee.</para><para>(4) The Division of Legislative Oversight and the office of Public Counsel may share confidential information as necessary to carry out the responsibilities of such division and office. Such sharing of confidential information shall include, but not be limited to, the sharing of confidential information when necessary to refer complaints between such division and office and to assist in investigations and the resolution of complaints. The Division of Legislative Oversight and the office of Public Counsel, at the discretion of the Director of Legislative Oversight and the Public Counsel, may coordinate to work jointly on complaints and investigations in circumstances of overlapping jurisdiction.</para><para>(5) If any employee of the Division of Legislative Oversight knowingly divulges or makes known, in any manner not permitted by law, confidential information or confidential records, it shall be grounds for dismissal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 20. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>