<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id715"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Legislature" id="id163" statutenumber="50-1808"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>50-1808</statuteno><catchline>Office; access to information and personnel; cooperation with office; when required.</catchline><para>(1) The office shall have access to all information and personnel necessary to perform the duties of the office and to carry out the Office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare Act.</para><para>(2) All employees of the department, the juvenile services division as directed by the juvenile court or the Office of Probation Administration, or the commission, all foster parents, and all owners, operators, managers, supervisors, and employees of private agencies, licensed child care facilities, juvenile detention facilities, staff secure juvenile facilities, and other providers of child welfare services or juvenile justice services shall cooperate with the office. Cooperation includes, but is not limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) Provision of full access to and production of records and information. Providing access to and producing records and information for the office is not a violation of confidentiality provisions under any law, statute, rule, or regulation if done in good faith for purposes of the Office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare Act;</para><para>(b) Fair and honest disclosure of records and information reasonably requested by the office pursuant to the act;</para><para>(c) Encouraging employees to fully comply with reasonable requests of the office pursuant to the act;</para><para>(d) Prohibition of retaliation by owners, operators, or managers against employees for providing records or information or filing or otherwise making a complaint to the office;</para><para>(e) Not requiring employees to gain supervisory approval prior to filing a complaint with or providing records or information to the office;</para><para>(f) Not requiring employees to report filing a complaint with or providing records or information to the office; and</para><para>(g) Not requiring employees to request that counsel for the employer be present while being questioned in the course of an investigation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB954, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 43-4321; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB298, &#167; 31. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>