<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Counties" statutenumber="22-187"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>22-187</statuteno><catchline>Thurston.</catchline><para>The county of Thurston is bounded as follows: Commencing at a point where the west boundary of the Omaha Indian reservation intersects the south line of section thirty-four, township twenty-five, north, range five, east of the sixth principal meridian; thence east to the northeast corner of township twenty-four, north, range seven, east; thence south to the south line of the Omaha Indian reservation as originally surveyed; thence east along said line to the line between sections thirty-two and thirty-three, township twenty-four, north, range ten, east; thence north to the northwest corner of section twenty-one, township twenty-four, north, range ten, east; thence east to the eastern boundary line of the State of Nebraska as established by the Iowa-Nebraska Boundary Compact of 1943; thence in a northwesterly direction along said boundary line to its intersection with the north line of the Winnebago Indian reservation, in township twenty-seven, north, range ten, east; thence west along the north line of said reservation to an intersection with the line between sections thirty-three and thirty-four, township twenty-seven, north, range six, east; thence south to the southwest corner of section thirty-four, township twenty-seven, north, range six, east; thence west to the west boundary of said Winnebago Indian reservation; and thence south along the west line of the Winnebago and Omaha Indian reservations to the place of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1889, c. 3, &#167; 1, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 902; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 231, &#167; 11, p. 828; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 804; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 25-191; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 22-187; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 65, &#167; 7, p. 214. </para></source></law></legaldoc>