<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Counties" statutenumber="22-407"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>22-407</statuteno><catchline>Consolidated counties; statutory references; rights and liabilities; books and records; money; congressional and legislative districts.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the effective date of the consolidation agreement for the consolidation of counties, the counties involved in the consolidation agreement shall be treated under the name or names and upon the terms and conditions set forth in the consolidation agreement. Except as provided in subsections (6) through (8) of this section, statutory references to the names of the counties as they existed prior to the consolidation agreement shall be deemed to reference the name or names of the consolidated county or counties as set forth in the consolidation agreement.</para><para>(2) All rights, privileges, and franchises of each of the several counties, all real and personal property, all rights-of-way, all other interests, and all debts due on whatever account, as well as other things in action, belonging to each of such counties shall be deemed as transferred to and vested in the consolidated county or counties without further act or deed. All records, books, and documents shall be transferred to and vested in the consolidated county if only one county is formed, or if two or more counties are formed, all books, records, and documents shall be transferred pursuant to the consolidation agreement.</para><para>(3) The title to real property, either by deed or otherwise, under the laws of this state vested in any of the counties, shall not be deemed to revert or be in any way impaired by reason of this consolidation, but the rights of creditors and all liens upon the property of any of the counties shall be preserved unimpaired. All prior indebtedness of each county shall remain a charge on the taxable property within the territory of each county as it existed prior to consolidation. A special tax levy shall be assessed on the taxable property within the prior county's boundaries to retire all prior indebtedness for that area.</para><para>(4) If there are two or more consolidated counties formed, all money on hand and accounts receivable shall be divided between the consolidated counties pursuant to the consolidation agreement.</para><para>(5) Suits may be brought and maintained against such consolidated county or counties in any of the courts of this state in the same manner as against any other county. Pursuant to the consolidation agreement, any action or proceeding pending by or against any of the counties consolidated may be prosecuted to judgment and the consolidated county or counties may be substituted in its place.</para><para>(6) The boundaries for townships, school districts, and election districts for offices other than the consolidated offices shall continue as prior to consolidation unless and until changed in accordance with law.</para><para>(7) Until changed by law, the same district courts shall continue, though it may result in the consolidated county or counties being a part of two or more districts. All such courts shall, however, be held at the place designated as the county seat of the consolidated county or counties, and each such court and the judge thereof shall continue to have and exercise the same jurisdiction as the court or judge had exercised before such consolidation. If two or more judges have jurisdiction in any consolidated county or counties, they or a majority of them shall exercise the power to appoint officers and fill vacancies as is vested in judges of district courts of other counties.</para><para>(8) For the purpose of representation in Congress and in the Legislature, the existing boundaries for congressional and legislative districts shall continue until changed in accordance with law. Such consolidated county or counties shall in all respects, except as provided in sections 22-401 to 22-407, be subject to all the obligations and liabilities imposed and shall possess all the rights, powers, and privileges vested by law in other counties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 34, &#167; 7, p. 220; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 25-407; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 22-407; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 44, &#167; 5, p. 158; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 91; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 22. </para></source></law></legaldoc>