<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Counties" statutenumber="22-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>22-402</statuteno><catchline>Consolidation agreement; contents; advisory committee.</catchline><para>(1) The county boards of any two or more adjoining counties may enter into a consolidation agreement for the consolidation of such counties or for the consolidation of one or more county or township offices except the office of county commissioner or county supervisor. The county boards of any two or more adjoining counties may enter into a consolidation agreement for the joint performance of any common function or service. A consolidation agreement shall not be considered an interlocal cooperation agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act.</para><para>(2) The consolidation agreement shall include (a) the names of the several counties which propose to consolidate, (b) the name or names under which the counties would consolidate which shall distinguish it from the name of any other county in Nebraska other than the consolidating counties, (c) the manner of financing and allocating all costs associated with the agreement, (d) the property, real and personal, belonging to each county and the fair value thereof in current money of the United States, (e) the indebtedness, bonded and otherwise, of each county and the repayment of the indebtedness after consolidation, (f) the proposed name and location of the county seat of the consolidated county, (g) if the counties have different forms of county organization and government, the proposed form of county organization and government of the consolidated county or counties, and (h) any other terms of the agreement.</para><para>(3) If the consolidation agreement provides for the joint performance of any common function or service or the consolidation of one or more county or township offices, the agreement shall also include (a) a description of the function or service which will be performed jointly or the office which will be consolidated, (b) the duration of the agreement, (c) the method for establishing and allocating salaries of holders of consolidated offices, (d) the method for adopting budgets and appropriating money for the joint function, service, or office, (e) the allocation of assets and liabilities pursuant to the agreement, (f) the procedure for amendment of the agreement, (g) the method of withdrawing from the agreement in accordance with section 22-416 and the distribution of assets upon withdrawal, and (h) the method of dissolving the agreement and the distribution of assets or liabilities upon dissolution.</para><para>(4) Each county board may appoint an advisory committee composed of three persons to assist the board in the preparation of such agreement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 34, &#167; 2, p. 217; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 25-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 22-402; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 44, &#167; 2, p. 155; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 22. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>