<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Counties" statutenumber="22-405"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>22-405</statuteno><catchline>Consolidation; election; laws applicable; ballot; form; majority required; when effective; effect on election to remove county seat.</catchline><para>(1) When the publication of the consolidation agreement in each of the counties is completed, each county board shall submit the question of whether to consolidate as proposed in the consolidation agreement to the registered voters at the next general election or at a special election held on the same day in each of the counties which are parties to the agreement.</para><para>(2) For the consolidation of counties, the question shall be submitted to the voters in substantially the following form:</para><para>"Shall (name of county in which ballot will be voted) consolidate with (name of other county or counties) according to the consolidation agreement previously adopted in such counties? Yes No".</para><para>(3) For the consolidation of one or more county or township offices, the question shall be submitted to the voters in substantially the following form:</para><para>"Shall (name of county in which ballot will be voted) enter the consolidation agreement with (name of other county or counties) for the consolidation of the office of (name of office) according to the consolidation agreement previously adopted in such counties? Yes No".</para><para>(4) For the joint performance of any common function or service, the question shall be submitted to the voters in substantially the following form:</para><para>"Shall (name of county in which ballot will be voted) enter the consolidation agreement with (name of other county or counties) for the joint performance of (name of function or service) according to the consolidation agreement previously adopted in such counties? Yes No".</para><para>(5) The election shall be conducted in accordance with the Election Act. The election commissioner or county clerk shall certify the results to each county board involved in the agreement. If a majority of the voters of each county voting on the question submitted vote in favor of the consolidation agreement for the consolidation of counties or for the consolidation of one or more county or township offices, the consolidation agreement shall become effective on the first Thursday after the first Tuesday in January following the next general election in which one or more consolidated county or township officers are first elected, and the terms of the incumbents in the offices involved in the agreement shall be deemed to end on that date. If a majority of the voters of each county voting on the question submitted vote in favor of the consolidation agreement for the joint performance of any common function or service, the consolidation agreement becomes effective on the date specified in the consolidation agreement.</para><para>(6) The submission of the question of consolidation of counties shall not bar submission of the question of the removal of the county seat under sections 22-301 to 22-303, it being the intention that either proposition may be submitted without reference to submission of the other proposition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 34, &#167; 5, p. 218; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 25-405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 22-405; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 44, &#167; 3, p. 156; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 92, &#167; 2, p. 399; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 25. </para></source></law></legaldoc>