<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Counties" statutenumber="22-135"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>22-135</statuteno><catchline>Garden.</catchline><para>The county of Garden is bounded as follows: Commencing at the southeast corner of section thirty-one, township fifteen, north, range forty-one west of the sixth principal meridian; thence north on section lines to the northeast corner of section six, township sixteen north, range forty-one, west; thence east on the fourth standard parallel to the southeast corner of township seventeen north, range forty-one, west; thence north along the range line between ranges forty and forty-one to the northeast corner of township twenty, north, range forty-one, west; thence west along the fifth standard parallel to the southeast corner of section thirty-three, township twenty-one north, range forty-one, west; thence north on section lines to the northeast corner of section four, township twenty-three, north, range forty-one, west, on south boundary of Sheridan County; thence west on said boundary line to the northwest corner of section four in township twenty-three, north, range forty-six, west; thence south to the township line between townships twenty and twenty-one, north, range forty-six, west; thence east on said township line to the northwest corner of section four, in township twenty, north, range forty-six, west; thence south to township line between townships sixteen and seventeen, north; thence east to the northwest corner of section four, township sixteen, north, range forty-six, west; thence south to the township line between the townships fourteen and fifteen, north; thence east on said township line to the place of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Formed from Deuel County pursuant to Laws 1879, &#167; 10, p. 355, by vote of electors Nov. 2, 1909; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 848; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 231, &#167; 4, p. 824; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 750; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 155, &#167; 2, p. 394; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 25-137; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 22-135.</para></source><annotation><para>Boundary line between Garden and Grant Counties established. State ex rel. Reed v. Garden County, 103 Neb. 142, 170 N.W. 835 (1919), rehearing denied 130 Neb. 145, 171 N.W. 299 (1919).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>