<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Counties" statutenumber="22-127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>22-127</statuteno><catchline>Dodge.</catchline><para>The county of Dodge is bounded as follows: Commencing at the intersection of the line dividing ranges four and five, east, with the south bank of the Platte River; thence easterly along the south bank of the Platte River to the fourth standard parallel; thence east along said parallel to the southeast corner of section thirty-one, township seventeen, north, range ten, east; thence north on section lines, three miles to the northeast corner of section nineteen, township seventeen, north, of range ten, east; thence west on section lines two miles to southwest corner of section thirteen, township seventeen, range nine, east; thence north on section lines, one mile to northwest corner of section thirteen, last aforesaid; thence west on section line one mile to southwest corner of section eleven, township seventeen, north, range nine, east; thence north on section lines one mile to northwest corner of said section eleven, last aforesaid; thence west on section lines one mile to the southwest corner of section three, township seventeen, range nine, east; thence north on section lines one mile to the northwest corner of said section three; thence west on section line one mile to northwest corner of section four, township seventeen, range nine, east; thence north on section line one mile to northeast corner of section thirty-two, township eighteen, range nine, east; thence west one-half mile on section line to northwest corner of the northeast quarter of section thirty-two, township eighteen, range nine, east; thence north on half section line two miles to the southeast corner of the southwest quarter of section seventeen, township eighteen, range nine, east; thence west on section line one-half mile to southwest corner of section seventeen, township eighteen, range nine, east; thence north on section lines fifteen miles to northeast corner of section six, township twenty, range nine, east; thence west along the fifth standard parallel to the northwest corner of township twenty, north of range five, east; thence south by the line dividing ranges four and five, east, to the place of beginning.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 12, &#167; 17, p. 215; </para><para>Laws 1875, &#167; 1, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 840; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 742; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 25-129; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 22-127.</para></source><annotation><para>Boundary line is not the river, but imaginary line in the river. Dodge County v. Saunders County, 70 Neb. 442, 97 N.W. 617 (1903).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>