<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id00" statutenumber="84-618"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>84-618</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Treasury Management Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Treasury Management Cash Fund is created. A pro rata share of the budget appropriated for the treasury management functions of the State Treasurer and for the administration of the achieving a better life experience program as provided in sections 77-1401 to 77-1409 shall be charged to the income of each fund held in invested cash, and such charges shall be transferred to the Treasury Management Cash Fund. The allocation of charges may be made by any method determined to be reasonably related to actual costs incurred by the State Treasurer in carrying out the treasury management functions under section 84-602 and in carrying out the achieving a better life experience program as provided in sections 77-1401 to 77-1409. Approval of the agencies, boards, and commissions administering these funds shall not be required.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of this section to have funds held in invested cash be charged a pro rata share of such expenses when this is not prohibited by statute or the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) The Treasury Management Cash Fund shall be used for the treasury management functions of the State Treasurer and for the administration of the achieving a better life experience program as provided in sections 77-1401 to 77-1409. To the extent permitted by section 529A as defined in section 77-1401, the fund may receive gifts for administration, operation, and maintenance of a program established under sections 77-1403 to 77-1409.</para><para>(4) Transfers may be made from the Treasury Management Cash Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Treasury Management Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 424, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB591, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>May 28, 2015</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>