<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-931"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>84-931</statuteno><catchline>Convenor or facilitator; contract authorized; state employee; disqualification; members of negotiated rulemaking committee; expenses; per diem; grants or gifts.</catchline><para>(1) An agency may employ or enter into a contract for the services of an organization or individual to serve as a convenor or facilitator for a negotiated rulemaking committee or may use the services of a state employee to act as a convenor or facilitator for a committee.</para><para>(2) An agency shall determine whether a person under consideration as a convenor or facilitator of a negotiated rulemaking committee has any financial or other interest that would preclude the person from serving in an impartial and independent manner. A person disqualified under this criterion shall be dropped from further consideration.</para><para>(3) Members of a negotiated rulemaking committee shall be responsible for their own expenses of participation. However, an agency may reimburse a committee member for expenses incurred in serving on the committee as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 and a reasonable per diem rate of compensation if:</para><para>(a) The committee member certifies a lack of adequate financial resources to participate in the committee; and</para><para>(b) The agency determines that the committee member's participation in the committee is necessary to ensure an adequate representation of the interests of the members.</para><para>(4) An agency may accept grants or gifts from any source to fund the negotiated rulemaking process if:</para><para>(a) Information on the name of the person giving the grant or gift and the amount of the grant or gift is available to the public;</para><para>(b) The grant or gift is given to and accepted by the agency without placing any condition on the membership of a negotiated rulemaking committee or the outcome of the negotiated rulemaking process; and</para><para>(c) There is consensus among the members of the negotiated rulemaking committee that the acceptance of the grant or gift will not diminish the integrity of the negotiated rulemaking process.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 133. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>