<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id00" statutenumber="84-906.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>84-906.03</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>It shall be the duty of the Secretary of State:</para><para>(1) To establish and cause to be compiled, indexed by subject, and published a codification system for all rules and regulations filed to be designated the Nebraska Administrative Code;</para><para>(2) To cause the Nebraska Administrative Code to be computerized to facilitate agencies in revision of their rules and regulations and provide research capabilities;</para><para>(3) To post a current copy of existing rules and regulations as accepted by the Secretary of State as filed on the website of the Secretary of State; to distribute a current copy of any existing rules and regulations as accepted by the Secretary of State as filed to all interested persons on request at a price fixed to cover costs of printing, handling, and mailing; and to distribute, on a regular basis, copies of any or all modifications or amendments to agency rules and regulations as accepted by the Secretary of State as filed to all interested persons on request at a price fixed to cover costs of printing, handling, and mailing; and</para><para>(4) To remit fees collected pursuant to this section to the State Treasurer for credit to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 134, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 267, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 712, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 130, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 784, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 992, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB867, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 36. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>