<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-206</statuteno><catchline>Deputy attorney general; bond or insurance; powers and duties; compensation.</catchline><para>The Attorney General shall appoint a deputy attorney general, who shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201. A copy of the appointment shall be deposited in the office of the Secretary of State. The deputy may do and perform, in the absence of the Attorney General, all the acts and duties that may be authorized and required to be performed by the Attorney General. The Attorney General shall be responsible for all acts of such deputy. The deputy shall receive a salary of such amount as shall be fixed by the Attorney General, to be paid on a monthly basis by warrant of the Director of Administrative Services on the State Treasurer. The salary of the deputy attorney general and each full-time assistant attorney general shall be not less than twenty thousand dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1887, c. 84, &#167; 1, p. 629; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5542; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 205, &#167; 6, p. 907; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 107, &#167; 2, p. 379; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4839; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 84-206; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 228, &#167; 1, p. 775; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 84-206; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 346, &#167; 4, p. 1092; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 338, &#167; 8, p. 1119; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 355, &#167; 1, p. 1132; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 347, &#167; 1, p. 1066; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 220, &#167; 1, p. 759; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 451, &#167; 1, p. 1503; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 535, &#167; 1, p. 1680; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 246, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 48. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For bonding provisions,</emphasis> see Chapter 11.</para><para><emphasis>For other provisions as to deputy state officers,</emphasis> see Chapter 84, article 8.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Attorney General has power to designate an assistant attorney general to appear in his stead in trial of a criminal cause, and it is not necessary that the assistant be a bonded deputy under above section. Carlsen v. State, 127 Neb. 11, 254 N.W. 744 (1934).</para><para>Assistant attorney general has no power to make and sign information in his own name, and information so signed is a nullity. Lower v. State, 106 Neb. 666, 184 N.W. 174 (1921).</para><para>Prohibition against creation of new executive department does not prevent the appointment of deputy. In re Appropriations for Deputies, Etc., 25 Neb. 662, 41 N.W. 643 (1889).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>