<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id606"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-947"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>84-947</statuteno><catchline>Individual with criminal conviction; submit preliminary application; occupational board; duties; determination; appeal; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The fundamental right of an individual to pursue an occupation includes the right of an individual with a criminal history to obtain an occupational license, government certification, or state recognition of the individual's personal qualifications.</para><para>(2)(a) An individual who has a criminal conviction may submit to the appropriate occupational board a preliminary application for an occupational license, government certification, or state recognition of the individual's personal qualifications for a determination as to whether the individual's criminal conviction would disqualify the individual from obtaining the occupational license, government certification, or state recognition of the individual's personal qualifications from that occupational board. The preliminary application may be submitted at any time, including prior to obtaining required education or paying any fee, other than the fee for the preliminary application under subsection (7) of this section.</para><para>(b) The individual may include with the preliminary application additional information about the individual's current circumstances, including the time since the offense, completion of the criminal sentence, other evidence of rehabilitation, testimonials, employment history, and employment aspirations.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of a preliminary application under subsection (2) of this section and a fee if required under subsection (7) of this section, the appropriate occupational board shall make a determination of whether the individual's criminal conviction would disqualify the individual from obtaining an occupational license, government certification, or state recognition of the individual's personal qualifications from that occupational board.</para><para>(4) The occupational board shall issue its determination in writing within ninety days after receiving a preliminary application under subsection (2) of this section. The determination shall include findings of fact and conclusions of law. If the occupational board determines that the individual's criminal conviction would disqualify the individual, the occupational board may advise the individual of any action the individual may take to remedy the disqualification. If the occupational board finds that the individual has been convicted of a subsequent criminal conviction, the occupational board may rescind a determination upon finding that the subsequent criminal conviction would be disqualifying under subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(5) The individual may appeal the determination of the occupational board. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(6) An individual shall not file another preliminary application under this section with the same occupational board within two years after the final decision on the previous preliminary application, except that if the individual has taken action to remedy the disqualification as advised by the occupational board, the individual may file another preliminary application under this section with the same occupational board six months after the final decision on the previous preliminary application.</para><para>(7) An occupational board may charge a fee not to exceed one hundred dollars for each preliminary application filed pursuant to this section. The fee is intended to offset the administrative costs incurred under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB299, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>