<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-912.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-912.02</statuteno><catchline>Petition for intervention; hearing officer or designee; grant petition; conditions; powers and duties; order.</catchline><para>(1) A hearing officer or designee shall grant a petition for intervention if:</para><para>(a) The petition is submitted in writing to the hearing officer or designee, with copies mailed to all parties named in the hearing officer's notice of the hearing, at least five days before the hearing;</para><para>(b) The petition states facts demonstrating that the petitioner's legal rights, duties, privileges, immunities, or other legal interests may be substantially affected by the proceeding or that the petitioner qualifies as an intervenor under any provision of law; and</para><para>(c) The hearing officer or designee determines that the interests of justice and the orderly and prompt conduct of the proceedings will not be impaired by allowing the intervention.</para><para>(2) The hearing officer or designee may grant a petition for intervention at any time upon determining that the intervention sought is in the interests of justice and will not impair the orderly and prompt conduct of the proceedings.</para><para>(3) If a petitioner qualifies for intervention, the hearing officer or designee may impose conditions upon the intervenor's participation in the proceedings, either at the time that intervention is granted or at any subsequent time. Conditions may include:</para><para>(a) Limiting the intervenor's participation to designated issues in which the intervenor has a particular interest demonstrated by the petition;</para><para>(b) Limiting the intervenor's use of discovery, cross-examination, and other procedures so as to promote the orderly and prompt conduct of the proceedings; and</para><para>(c) Requiring two or more intervenors to combine their presentation of evidence and argument, cross-examination, discovery, and other participation in the proceedings.</para><para>(4) The hearing officer or designee, at least twenty-four hours before the hearing, shall issue an order granting or denying each pending petition for intervention, specifying any conditions and briefly stating the reasons for the order. The hearing officer or designee may modify the order at any time, stating the reasons for the modification. The hearing officer or designee shall promptly give notice of an order granting, denying, or modifying intervention to the petitioner for intervention and to all parties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 28. </para></source></law></legaldoc>