<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-926"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-926</statuteno><catchline>Negotiated rulemaking committee established; agency; duties; Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If an agency decides to establish a negotiated rulemaking committee, the agency shall:</para><para>(a) Give notice to the Secretary of State; and</para><para>(b) Publish the notice in a newspaper having general circulation in the state and, as appropriate, in other newspapers and publications.</para><para>(2) The notice shall include:</para><para>(a) An announcement that the agency intends to establish a negotiated rulemaking committee to negotiate and develop a proposed rule;</para><para>(b) A description of the subject and scope of the rule to be developed and the issues to be considered;</para><para>(c) A list of interests likely to be significantly affected by the proposed rule;</para><para>(d) A list of the persons proposed to represent the affected interests and the agency;</para><para>(e) A proposed schedule for completing the work of the committee; and</para><para>(f) An explanation of how a person may apply for or nominate another person for membership on the committee.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State shall establish and maintain a list of subscribers who wish to receive notice of an agency's intent to establish a negotiated rulemaking committee and shall provide such notice to such subscribers at a cost to be assessed against each subscriber. The Secretary of State shall collect payments and make disbursements of such funds as may be necessary to carry out the notification required by this subsection.</para><para>(4) The agency shall provide a period of at least thirty days for the submission of comments upon and applications for membership on a negotiated rulemaking committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>