<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-168"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-168</statuteno><catchline>Acceptance of cession or retrocession of federal jurisdiction; conditions; filing; memorandum of understanding.</catchline><para>(1) By appropriate executive order, the Governor may accept on behalf of the state full or partial cession or retrocession of federal jurisdiction, including criminal, civil, or juvenile, over any lands, except Indian lands, in federal enclaves within the state where such cession or retrocession has been offered by appropriate federal authority.</para><para>(2) To be accepted by the Governor, such offer must:</para><para>(a) Clearly state the subject matter of the offer, including specifically identifying whether it includes matters of criminal, civil, or juvenile jurisdiction and the scope of any concurrent jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) Provide a metes and bounds description of the boundaries; and</para><para>(c) Indicate whether the offer includes future contiguous expansions of land acquired for military purposes.</para><para>(3) An executive order accepting a cession or retrocession of jurisdiction shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State and in the office of the register of deeds of the county in which the affected real estate is located. Upon filing, the Governor shall cause a certified copy of the executive order and any documents filed under this subsection to be sent to the appropriate federal authority.</para><para>(4) If an area of concurrent jurisdiction between the state and the federal government is established pursuant to this section, any state agency or political subdivision may enter into a memorandum of understanding with any federal agency for coordination and designation of responsibilities relating to such concurrent jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 545, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1195, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>