<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="84-612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-612</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Cash Reserve Fund;
created; transfers; receipt of federal funds.</catchline><para>(1)
There is hereby created within the state treasury a fund known as the Cash
Reserve Fund which shall be under the direction of the State Treasurer. The
fund shall only be used pursuant to this section.</para>
<para>(2) The State Treasurer shall transfer funds from the Cash
Reserve Fund to the General Fund upon certification by the Director of Administrative
Services that the current cash balance in the General Fund is inadequate to
meet current obligations. Such certification shall include the dollar amount
to be transferred. Any transfers made pursuant to this subsection shall be
reversed upon notification by the Director of Administrative Services that
sufficient funds are available.</para>
<para>(3) In addition to receiving transfers from other funds, the
Cash Reserve Fund shall receive federal funds received by the State of Nebraska
for undesignated general government purposes, federal revenue sharing, or
general fiscal relief of the state.</para>
<para>(4) On July 7, 2009, the State Treasurer shall transfer five
million dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Roads Operations Cash Fund.
The Department of Roads shall use such funds to provide the required state
match for federal funding made available to the state through congressional
earmarks.</para>

<para>(5) The State Treasurer shall
transfer a total of sixty-eight million dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund
to the General Fund on or before June 30, 2013, on such dates and in such
amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of
the Department of Administrative Services.</para>




<para>(6) The State Treasurer shall
transfer ten million dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the General Fund
on or before June 30, 2013, on such date as directed by the budget administrator
of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para>
<para>(7) The State Treasurer, at
the direction of the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department
of Administrative Services, shall transfer not to exceed forty-three million
fifteen thousand four hundred fifty-nine dollars in total from the Cash Reserve
Fund to the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund between July 1, 2013, and June
30, 2017.</para>
<para>(8) The State
Treasurer shall transfer fourteen million five hundred thousand dollars from
the Cash Reserve Fund to the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund on or before
June 30, 2015, on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the
budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para>
<para>(9) The State
Treasurer shall transfer fifty million five hundred thousand dollars from
the Cash Reserve Fund to the General Fund on or before December 31, 2014,
on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division
of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 59, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 713, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 501, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 739, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 870, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1091, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 310, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 857, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 783, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 38, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1045, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1290, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 401, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 63, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 988, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1134, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 881, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1214, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 541, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 798, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1090, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 427, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1256, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB323, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB846, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1094, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1165, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB456, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB2, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB317, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB379, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB200, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB130, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1016, &#167; 3.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB130, section 2, with LB1016, section 3, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB1016 became effective March 29, 2014. Changes made by LB130 became effective July 18, 2014.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>