<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection statutenumber="84-901.03" chaptername="State Officers" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>84-901.03</statuteno><catchline>Agency; guidance document; issuance; availability; notice; request to revise or repeal; response; agency publish index.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the issuance of a guidance document, an agency shall make such document available at one public location and on the agency’s web site. The agency shall also publish on its web site an index summarizing the subject matter of all currently applicable rules and regulations and guidance documents. Such agency shall provide the index electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature by December 31 of each year.</para><para>(2) An agency shall ensure that the first page of each guidance document includes the following notice: This guidance document is advisory in nature but is binding on an agency until amended by such agency. A guidance document does not include internal procedural documents that only affect the internal operations of the agency and does not impose additional requirements or penalties on regulated parties or include confidential information or rules and regulations made in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. If you believe that this guidance document imposes additional requirements or penalties on regulated parties, you may request a review of the document.</para><para>(3) A person may request in writing that an agency revise or repeal a guidance document or convert a guidance document into a rule or regulation. No later than sixty calendar days after the agency receives such a request, the agency shall advise the requestor in writing of its decision to (a) revise or repeal the guidance document, (b) initiate a proceeding to consider a revision or repeal of a guidance document, (c) initiate the rulemaking or regulationmaking process to convert the guidance document into a rule or regulation, or (d) deny the request and state the reason for the denial.</para><para>(4) All decisions made by an agency under this section shall be made available at one public location and on the agency’s web site.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB867, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB209, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>