<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-913"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-913</statuteno><catchline>Contested cases; notice of hearing; record; transcript.</catchline><para>In any contested case all parties shall be afforded an opportunity for hearing after reasonable notice. The notice shall state the time, place, and issues involved, but if, by reason of the nature of the proceeding, the issues cannot be fully stated in advance of the hearing or if subsequent amendment of the issues is necessary, they shall be fully stated as soon as practicable. Opportunity shall be afforded all parties to present evidence and argument with respect thereto. The agency shall prepare an official record, which shall include testimony and exhibits, in each contested case, but it shall not be necessary to transcribe shorthand notes unless requested for purpose of rehearing, in which event the transcript and record shall be furnished by the agency upon request and tender of the cost of preparation. Informal disposition may also be made of any contested case by stipulation, agreed settlement, consent order, or default. Each agency shall adopt appropriate rules and regulations for notice and hearing in contested cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 456, &#167; 6, p. 1512; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 838, &#167; 1, p. 3162; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 253, &#167; 15.</para></source><annotation><para>Where the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission failed to provide the appellant with notice as required under this section and the commission's own regulations, the appellant was denied due process, and as a result of such denial, the commission's decision with regard to the appellant's liquor license did not conform to the law. Lariat Club v. Nebraska Liquor Control Comm., 267 Neb. 179, 673 N.W.2d 29 (2004).</para><para>Administrative bodies have only that authority specifically conferred upon them by statute or by construction necessary to achieve the purpose of the relevant act, and as such, the Department of Revenue is not statutorily authorized to grant motions for summary judgment. Southeast Rur. Vol. Fire Dept. v. Neb. Dept. of Rev., 251 Neb. 852, 560 N.W.2d 436 (1997).</para><para>On objection to application for liquor license, where hearing is required, the matter becomes a contested case under section 84-901(3), and notice to applicant of the issues is necessary. J K &amp; J, Inc. v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 194 Neb. 413, 231 N.W.2d 694 (1975).</para><para>The procedural rules to be applied are those in effect at time of hearing or proceeding, not those in effect when the act or violation is charged to have taken place. Durousseau v. Nebraska State Racing Commission, 194 Neb. 288, 231 N.W.2d 566 (1975).</para><para>Department of Banking required to establish procedural rules providing for notice and hearing. First Fed. Sav. &amp; Loan Assn. v. Department of Banking, 187 Neb. 562, 192 N.W.2d 736 (1971).</para><para>In contested case, common carriers are entitled to present argument. Ready Mix, Inc. v. Nebraska Railroads, 181 Neb. 697, 150 N.W.2d 275 (1967).</para><para>In hearing before the Liquor Control Commission where no notice of hearing is required, this section would not be applicable. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, 181 Neb. 277, 147 N.W.2d 803 (1967).</para><para>Notice of hearing in a contested case is required to state the issues involved. County of Lancaster v. State Board of Equalization &amp; Assessment, 180 Neb. 497, 143 N.W.2d 885 (1966); County of Brown v. State Board of Equalization &amp; Assessment, 180 Neb. 487, 143 N.W.2d 896 (1966); County of Blaine v. State Board of Equalization &amp; Assessment, 180 Neb. 471, 143 N.W.2d 880 (1966).</para><para>In contested case before administrative board, notice and hearing are required. School Dist. No. 8 v. State Board of Education, 176 Neb. 722, 127 N.W.2d 458 (1964).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>