<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id8">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id10" statutenumber="84-907"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-907</statuteno><catchline id="id13">Rule or regulation;
adoption; amendment; repeal; hearing; notice; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) No
rule or regulation shall be adopted, amended, or repealed by any agency except
after public hearing on the question of adopting, amending, or repealing such
rule or regulation. Notice of such hearing shall be given at least thirty
days prior thereto to the Secretary of State and by publication in a newspaper
having general circulation in the state. All such hearings shall be open to
the public.</para>
<para>(2) The public hearing on a rule or regulation
that is required to be adopted, amended, or repealed based upon a legislative
bill shall be held within twelve months after the effective or operative date
of the legislative bill. If there is more than one applicable effective or
operative date, the twelve-month period shall be calculated using the latest
date. In addition to the requirements of section 84-906.01, draft
copies or working copies of all rules and regulations to be adopted, amended,
or repealed by any agency shall be available to the public in the office of
the Secretary of State at the time of giving notice. The notice shall include: (a) A declaration of availability of such draft
or work copies for public examination; (b) a short explanation of
the purpose of the proposed rule or regulation or the reason for the amendment
or repeal of the rule or regulation; and (c) a description, including
an estimated quantification, of the fiscal impact on state agencies, political
subdivisions, and persons being regulated or an explanation of where the description
of the fiscal impact may be inspected and obtained. No person may challenge
the validity of any rule or regulation, the adoption, amendment, or repeal
of any rule or regulation, or any determination of the applicability of any
rule or regulation on the basis of the explanation or description provided
pursuant to subdivisions (b) and
(c) of this subsection.</para>
<para>(3) Any agency adopting, amending,
or repealing a rule or regulation may make written application to the Governor
who may, upon receipt of a written showing of good cause, waive the notice
of public hearing. </para>
<para>For purposes
of this subsection, good cause shall
include, but not be limited to, a showing by the agency that:</para>
<para>(a) Compliance with the requirements of this section would result in extreme hardship
on the citizens of this state;</para>
<para>(b) An emergency exists which must be remedied immediately;
or</para>
<para>(c) A timely filing or publication of notice of a public hearing or the public hearing was
prevented by some unforeseeable event beyond the immediate control of the
agency and that the parties affected have not and will not suffer material
injury as a result of the agency's action.</para>
<para>(4) Whenever
public notice is waived, the agency shall, so far as practicable, give notice
to the public of the proposed rule or regulation change and of the rule or
regulation as finally adopted or changed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 359, &#167; 1, p. 1138; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 462, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 585, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 846, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 992, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 253, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 487, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 373, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB617, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>This section is in pari materia with section 84-901. City of Scottsbluff v. United Telephone Co. of the West, 171 Neb. 229, 106 N.W.2d 12 (1960).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
