<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-127</statuteno><catchline>Governor; disability; examination; conference; members; findings; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever it appears that the Governor is unable to discharge the duties of the office, the person next in line of succession to the office of Governor or the person who is dean of the College of Medicine of the University of Nebraska may call a conference consisting of the person who is dean of the College of Medicine of the University of Nebraska, the person who is chairperson of the Department of Psychiatry at the University of Nebraska Medical Center, and the dean of an accredited college of medicine located in the State of Nebraska to be selected by the other two members of the conference. The three members of the conference shall examine the Governor. After the examination, or if upon attempting to examine the Governor the members of the conference are unable to examine him or her because of circumstances beyond their control, they shall conduct a secret ballot and, by unanimous vote, may find that the Governor is temporarily unable to discharge the duties of the office.</para><para>(2) The finding of or failure to find a disability shall be made public, and in case the Governor is found to be unable to discharge the duties of the office, the person next in line of succession to the office of Governor shall be notified. After receiving the notification, the powers, duties, and emoluments of the office of Governor shall, under Article IV, section 16, of the Constitution of Nebraska, devolve upon the person next in line of succession to the office of Governor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 452, &#167; 1, p. 1379; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 832, &#167; 1, p. 3155; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 112, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>