
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-710"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-710</statuteno><catchline>Fees, proceeds, and money due state; payment to State Treasurer; duty of state officers and department heads; exceptions.</catchline><para>It shall be unlawful for any executive department, state institution, board, or officer acting under or by virtue of any statute or authority of the state, including the State Racing and Gaming Commission, to receive any fees, proceeds from the sale of any public property, or any money belonging to the state or due for any service rendered by virtue of state authority without paying the same into the state treasury within three business days of the receipt thereof when the aggregate amount is five hundred dollars or more and within seven days of the receipt thereof when the aggregate amount is less than five hundred dollars. The State Treasurer may, upon a written request from an executive department, state institution, board, or officer stating that the applicable time period cannot be met, grant additional time to remit the funds to the state treasury. Funds received by an executive department, state institution, board, or officer for a good or service which may or may not be delivered contingent upon a selection process shall not be subject to this section until the selection period is over.</para><para>The provisions of this section and section 84-711 shall not apply to money received as proceeds of any fair, exposition, or exhibition held by any state board or society or of membership contributions to or receipts from miscellaneous sales by the Nebraska State Historical Society.</para><para>Such money so paid into the treasury shall be withdrawn therefrom or paid out only upon proper voucher and warrant.</para><para>The head of any institution receiving, from any source, funds to be held in trust and expended for the benefit of any inmate thereof shall not be required to pay such trust funds into the state treasury as provided in this section but shall, at the end of each month, file with the Director of Administrative Services a detailed and attested statement of all such money received and expended by him or her.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 132, &#167; 1, p. 442; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5593; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4900; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 84-710; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 84-710; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 453, &#167; 1, p. 1381; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 418, &#167; 3, p. 1280; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 933, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 61, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB561, &#167; 49. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>