<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-913.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-913.04</statuteno><catchline>Proceedings; limitation on participation.</catchline><para>(1) A person who has served as investigator, prosecutor, or advocate in a contested case or in its prehearing stage may not serve as hearing officer or assist or advise a hearing officer in the same proceeding except as provided in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) A person who is subject to the authority, direction, or discretion of one who has served as investigator, prosecutor, or advocate in a contested case or in its prehearing stage may not serve as hearing officer or assist or advise a hearing officer in the same proceeding except as provided in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3) If all parties consent, a person who has served as, or who is subject to the authority, direction, or discretion of one who has served as, investigator, prosecutor, or advocate in a contested case or in its prehearing stage may assist a hearing officer in the preparation of orders.</para><para>(4) A person who has participated in a determination of probable cause or other equivalent preliminary determination in a contested case may serve as hearing officer or assist or advise a hearing officer in the same proceeding.</para><para>(5) A person may serve as hearing officer at successive stages of the same contested case.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 32.</para></source><annotation><para>The Legislature specifically barred only prosecutors, investigators, and advocates from participating as hearing officers in administrative hearings. City of Lincoln v. Central Platte NRD, 263 Neb. 141, 638 N.W.2d 839 (2002).</para><para>In this section, the Legislature has barred only prosecutors, investigators, and advocates from participating as hearing officers, or assisting hearing officers, in administrative hearings. Saunders Cty. v. Metropolitan Utilities Dist.-A, 11 Neb. App. 138, 645 N.W.2d 805 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>