<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id5" statutenumber="84-617"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>84-617</statuteno><catchline id="id8">State Treasurer Administrative Fund; created; use; investment; fee schedule.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the State Treasurer Administrative Fund. Funds received by the State Treasurer pursuant to his or her administrative duties shall be credited to the fund. Such funds shall include:</para><para>(a) Payments for returned check charges or for electronic payments not accepted;</para><para>(b) Payments for wire transfers initiated by the State Treasurer at the request of state agencies;</para><para>(c) Payments for copies of cashed state warrants;</para><para>(d) Payments for copies, including microfilm, computer disk, or magnetic tape, of listings relating to outstanding state warrants;</para><para>(e) Payments for copies, including microfilm, computer disk, or magnetic tape, of listings of owners of unclaimed property held by the State Treasurer pursuant to the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act; and</para><para>(f) Payments under the Interior Design Voluntary Registration Act.</para><para>(2) Money in the fund received pursuant to subdivisions (1)(a) through (d) of this section shall be credited to the General Fund quarterly. Money in the State Treasurer Administrative Fund received pursuant to subdivisions (1)(e) and (f) of this section shall be credited to the Unclaimed Property Cash Fund. The State Treasurer may retain such amount as he or she deems appropriate in the State Treasurer Administrative Fund for purposes of making change for cash payments. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) The State Treasurer may establish a fee schedule for any of the services listed in subdivisions (1)(a) through (e) of this section. The fees shall approximate the cost of providing the service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 50, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 132; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 354, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB619, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB16, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interior Design Voluntary Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 71-6101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act,</emphasis> see section 69-1329.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>