<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-913.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-913.01</statuteno><catchline>Hearing officer; prehearing conference; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The hearing officer designated to conduct the hearing may determine, subject to the agency's rules and regulations, whether a prehearing conference will be conducted. If the conference is conducted:</para><para>(a) The hearing officer shall promptly notify the agency of the determination that a prehearing conference will be conducted. The agency may assign another hearing officer for the prehearing conference; and</para><para>(b) The hearing officer for the prehearing conference shall set the time and place of the conference and give reasonable written notice to all parties and to all persons who have filed written petitions to intervene in the matter. The agency shall give notice to other persons entitled to notice.</para><para>(2) The notice shall include:</para><para>(a) The names and mailing addresses of all parties and other persons to whom notice is being given by the hearing officer;</para><para>(b) The name, official title, mailing address, and telephone number of any counsel or employee who has been designated to appear for the agency;</para><para>(c) The official file or other reference number, the name of the proceeding, and a general description of the subject matter;</para><para>(d) A statement of the time, place, and nature of the prehearing conference;</para><para>(e) A statement of the legal authority and jurisdiction under which the prehearing conference and the hearing are to be held;</para><para>(f) The name, official title, mailing address, and telephone number of the hearing officer for the prehearing conference; and</para><para>(g) A statement that a party who fails to attend or participate in a prehearing conference, hearing, or other stage of a contested case or who fails to make a good faith effort to comply with a prehearing order may be held in default under the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>The notice may include any other matters that the hearing officer considers desirable to expedite the proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 29. </para></source></law></legaldoc>