<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id5" statutenumber="84-907.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-907.04</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Proposed rule
or regulation; explanatory statement; contents; use; agency; written report; contents.</catchline>
<para>(1) At the time an agency finalizes a proposed rule or regulation
and prior to submission to the Secretary of State, Attorney General, and Governor,
the agency shall attach to the proposed rule or regulation a concise explanatory
statement containing:</para>
<para>(a) Its reasons for adopting the rule or regulation;</para>
<para>(b) An indication of any change between the text of the proposed
rule or regulation contained or referenced in the published notice and the
text of the rule or regulation to be adopted, with the reasons for any change;
and</para>
<para>(c) When procedural rules differ from the model rules, the
agency's reasons why relevant portions of the model rules were impracticable
under the circumstances.</para>
<para>(2) Only the reasons contained in the concise explanatory
statement may be used by an agency as justifications for the adoption of the
rule or regulation in any proceeding in which its validity is at issue.</para>
<para>(3) The agency
shall also attach to the proposed rule or regulation a written report that
includes a summary of the testimony offered at the public hearing and that
lists any specific issues or questions that were presented by individuals
or representatives of organizations at the hearing or in written testimony
submitted as part of the public hearing process. The report shall also include
a response from the agency proposing the regulatory change to the questions
and issues that were presented by individuals or representatives of organizations
at the hearing or in written testimony submitted as part of the public hearing
process. The written report shall also be submitted to the Executive Board
of the Legislative Council. The chairperson of the executive board or committee
staff member of the executive board shall refer each written report received
pursuant to this subsection for review (a) to the chairperson of the standing
committee of the Legislature which has subject matter jurisdiction over the
issue involved in the rule or regulation or which has traditionally handled
the issue and (b) if practicable, to the member of the Legislature who was
the primary sponsor of a legislative bill that granted the agency the rulemaking
authority if the member is still serving or, if the legislative bill was amended
to include the rulemaking authority, to the member of the Legislature who
was the primary sponsor of the amendment that granted rulemaking authority
if the member is still serving.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB719, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>