<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id24">
<sectno id="id25">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" id="id26" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="84-602.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>84-602.02</statuteno><catchline>Web site; contents.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) Not
later than January 1, 2010, the web site established, developed, and maintained
by the State Treasurer pursuant to subdivision (9) of section 84-602 shall
provide such information as will document the sources of all tax receipts
and the expenditure of state funds by all agencies, boards, commissions, and
departments of the state.</para>
<para>(b) The State
Treasurer shall, in appropriate detail, cause to be published on the web site:</para>
<para>(i) The identity,
principal location, and amount of funds received or expended by the State
of Nebraska and all of its agencies, boards, commissions, and departments;</para>
<para>(ii) The
funding or expending agency, board, commission, or department;</para>
<para>(iii) The
budget program source;</para><para>(iv) The amount, date, purpose, and recipient of all disbursed funds;
and</para><para>(v) Such other relevant information as will further the intent of
enhancing the transparency of state government financial operations to its
citizens and taxpayers. The web site shall include data for fiscal year 2008-09
and each fiscal year thereafter.</para><para>(2) Beginning July 1, 2010, the data shall
be available on the web site no later than thirty days after the end of the
preceding fiscal year. All agencies, boards, commissions, and departments
of the state shall provide to the State Treasurer, at such times and in such
form as designated by the State Treasurer, such information as is necessary
to accomplish the purposes of the Taxpayer Transparency Act. Nothing in this
subsection requires the disclosure of information which is considered confidential
under state or federal law or is not a public record under section 84-712.05.</para>
<para>(3)(a) For
purposes of this section, expenditure of state funds means all expenditures
of appropriated or nonappropriated funds by an agency, board, commission,
or department of the state from the state treasury in forms including, but
not limited to:</para><para>(i) Grants;</para><para>(ii) Contracts;</para><para>(iii) Subcontracts;</para><para>(iv) State aid to political
subdivisions; and</para><para>(v) Tax refunds or credits that may be disclosed pursuant to the
Nebraska Advantage Act, the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit
Act, the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act, or the Nebraska
Advantage Rural Development Act.</para><para>(b) Expenditure of state funds does not
include the transfer of funds between two agencies, boards, commissions, or
departments of the state or payments of state or federal assistance to an
individual.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB16, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5701.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,187.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>