<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id13" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="84-612"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id15">84-612</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Cash Reserve Fund;
created; transfers; receipt of federal funds.</catchline><para>(1) There is
hereby created within the state treasury a fund known as the Cash Reserve
Fund which shall be under the direction of the State Treasurer. The fund shall
only be used pursuant to this section.</para>
<para>(2) The State Treasurer shall transfer funds from the Cash Reserve Fund
to the General Fund upon certification by the Director of Administrative Services
that the current cash balance in the General Fund is inadequate to meet current
obligations. Such certification shall include the dollar amount to be transferred.
Any transfers made pursuant to this subsection shall be reversed upon notification
by the Director of Administrative Services that sufficient funds are available.</para>
<para>(3) The State Treasurer, at the direction of the budget administrator
of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services, shall
transfer such amounts not to exceed seven million seven hundred fifty-three
thousand two hundred sixty-three dollars in total from the Cash Reserve Fund
to the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund between July 1, 2003, and June 30,
2007.</para>
<para>(4) The State Treasurer, at the direction of the budget administrator,
shall transfer an amount equal to the total amount transferred pursuant to
subsection (3) of this section from the General Fund to the Cash Reserve Fund
on or before June 30, 2008.</para>
<para>(5) In addition to receiving transfers from other funds, the Cash Reserve
Fund shall receive federal funds received by the State of Nebraska for undesignated
general government purposes, federal revenue sharing, or general fiscal relief
of the state.</para>
<para>(6) On June 15, 2009, the State Treasurer shall transfer four million
nine hundred ninety thousand five hundred five dollars from the Cash Reserve
Fund to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(7) On or before June 16, 2009, the State Treasurer, at the direction
of the budget administrator, shall transfer fifty million dollars from the
Cash Reserve Fund to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(8) The State Treasurer, at the direction of the budget administrator,
shall transfer such amounts, as certified by the Director of Administrative
Services, for employee health insurance claims and expenses, not to exceed
twelve million dollars in total from the Cash Reserve Fund to the State Employees
Insurance Fund between May 1, 2007, and June 30, 2011.</para>
<para>(9) On July 9, 2007, the State Treasurer shall transfer five million
dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Job Training Cash Fund. The State
Treasurer shall transfer from the Job Training Cash Fund to the Cash Reserve
Fund such amounts as directed in section 81-1201.21.</para>
<para>(10) On July 7, 2008, the State Treasurer shall transfer five million
dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Job Training Cash Fund. The State
Treasurer shall transfer from the Job Training Cash Fund to the Cash Reserve
Fund such amounts as directed in section 81-1201.21.</para>
<para>(11) On or before June 30, 2009, the State Treasurer shall transfer
nine million five hundred ninety thousand dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund
to the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund.</para>
<para>(12) The State Treasurer, at the direction of the budget administrator,
shall transfer an amount equal to the total amount transferred pursuant to
subsection (8) of this section from the appropriate health insurance accounts
of the State Employees Insurance Fund in such amounts as certified by the
Director of Administrative Services to the Cash Reserve Fund on or before
June 30, 2011.</para>
<para>(13) On July 7, 2009, the State Treasurer shall transfer five million
dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Roads Operations Cash Fund. The
Department of Roads shall use such funds to provide the required state match
for federal funding made available to the state through congressional earmarks.</para>
<para>(14) Within five days after the budget division of the Department of
Administrative Services notifies the State Treasurer that matching fund requirements
under section 82-331 have been met, the State Treasurer shall transfer one
million dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation
Endowment Fund.</para>
<para>(15) On or before June 15, 2010, the State Treasurer, at the direction
of the budget administrator, shall transfer one hundred five million dollars
from the Cash Reserve Fund to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(16) On or before June 15, 2011, the State Treasurer, at the direction
of the budget administrator, shall transfer one hundred fifty-one million
dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(17) On June 15, 2009, the State Treasurer shall transfer seven million
five hundred thousand dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Governor's
Emergency Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(18) On July 7, 2009, the State Treasurer shall transfer one million
dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the State Visitors Promotion Cash Fund.
The Department of Economic Development shall use such funds to provide funding
for the promotion and support of the hosting of a Special Olympics national
event by a city of the primary class.</para>
<para>(19) On or before June
30, 2011, the State Treasurer, at the direction of the budget administrator,
shall transfer three million dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the General
Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 59, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 713, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 501, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 739, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 870, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1091, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 310, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 857, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 783, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 38, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1045, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1290, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 401, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 63, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 988, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1134, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1219, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 881, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1214, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 541, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 798, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1090, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 427, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1256, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB323, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB846, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1094, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1165, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB456, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB2, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB317, &#167;  1.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>