<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id10" statutenumber="84-602"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>84-602</statuteno><catchline id="id13">State Treasurer;
duties.</catchline><para>It shall be the duty of the State Treasurer:</para>
<para>(1) To receive and keep all money of the state not expressly required
to be received and kept by some other person;</para>
<para>(2) To disburse the public money upon warrants drawn upon the state
treasury according to law and not otherwise;</para>
<para>(3) To keep a just, true, and comprehensive account of all money received
and disbursed;</para>
<para>(4) To keep a just account with each fund, and each head of appropriation
made by law, and the warrants drawn against them;</para>
<para>(5) To render a full statement to the Department of Administrative Services
of all money received by him or her from whatever source, and if on account
of revenue, for what year; of all penalties and interest on delinquent taxes
reported or accounted for to him or her, and of all disbursements of public
funds; with a list, in numerical order, of all warrants redeemed, the name
of the payee, amount, interest, and total amount allowed thereon, and with
the amount of the balance of the several funds unexpended; which statement
shall be made on the first day of December, March, June, and September, and
more often if required;</para>
<para>(6) To report electronically to
the Legislature as soon as practicable, but within ten days after the commencement
of each regular session, a detailed statement of the condition of the treasury
and its operations for the preceding fiscal year;</para>
<para>(7) To give information electronically to
the Legislature, whenever required, upon any subject connected with the treasury
or touching any duty of his or her office;</para>
<para>(8) To account for, and pay over, all money received by him or her as
such treasurer, to his or her successor in office, and deliver all books,
vouchers, and effects of office to him or her; and such successor shall receipt
therefor. In accounting for and paying over such money the treasurer shall
not be held liable on account of any loss occasioned by any investment, when
such investment shall have been made pursuant to the direction of the state
investment officer; and</para>
<para>(9) To develop and maintain a single, searchable web site with information
on state tax receipts and expenditures which is accessible by the public at
no cost to access as provided in section 84-602.02. The web site shall be
hosted on a server owned and operated by the State of Nebraska or approved
by the Chief Information Officer. The naming convention for the web site shall
identify the web site as a state government web site. The web site shall not
include the treasurer's name, the treasurer's image, the treasurer's seal,
or a welcome message.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 4, &#167; 18, p. 24; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5577; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4881; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 84-602; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 84-602; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 617, &#167; 1, p. 2069; </para><para>Laws 1970, Spec. Sess., c. 3, &#167; 1, p. 67; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB16, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 224.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><annotation><para>State Treasurer was necessary party to declaratory judgment action testing constitutionality of statute. Haynes v. Anderson, 163 Neb. 50, 77 N.W.2d 674 (1956).</para><para>State Treasurer is required to keep a warrant register for registration of unpaid warrants and warrants should be paid in order of their presentation. State v. Omaha National Bank, 66 Neb. 857, 93 N.W. 319 (1903).</para><para>Appropriation, authorizing State Treasurer to reimburse sinking fund from General Fund, is command to make proper entries on books, and issuance of warrant to him therefor is void. State v. Omaha Nat. Bank, 59 Neb. 483, 81 N.W. 319 (1899).</para><para>Turning over certificates of deposits from state depositories is sufficient, without physical transfer of money to successor. In re State Treasurer's Settlement, 51 Neb. 116, 70 N.W. 532 (1897).</para><para>Requirement to account to successor for all money received can be satisfied only by delivery of actual cash. State v. Hill, 47 Neb. 456, 66 N.W. 541 (1896).</para><para>Action on bond for money unaccounted for must be brought in county of capital. State v. Hill, 38 Neb. 698, 57 N.W. 548 (1894).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>