<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id00" statutenumber="84-906.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>84-906.04</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Secretary of State; maintain docket for pending proceedings; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The Secretary of State shall maintain a current public rulemaking or regulationmaking docket for each pending rulemaking or regulationmaking proceeding. A rulemaking or regulationmaking proceeding is pending from the time it is commenced by publication of a notice of proposed rule or regulation making to the time it is terminated by publication of a notice of termination or the rule or regulation becoming effective.</para><para>(2) For each rulemaking or regulationmaking proceeding, the docket shall indicate:</para><para>(a) The subject matter of the proposed rule or regulation;</para><para>(b) The time, date, and location of the public hearing regarding the proposed rule or regulation;</para><para>(c) The name and address of agency personnel with whom people may communicate regarding the proposed rule or regulation;</para><para>(d) Where written comments on the proposed rule or regulation may be inspected;</para><para>(e) The time during which written comments may be made;</para><para>(f) Where the description of the fiscal impact may be inspected and obtained;</para><para>(g) The current status of the proposed rule or regulation and any agency determinations with respect thereto;</para><para>(h) Any known timetable for agency decisions or other action in the proceeding;</para><para>(i) The date of the rule's or regulation's adoption;</para><para>(j) The date of the rule's or regulation's filing, indexing, and publication; and</para><para>(k) The operative date of the rule or regulation if such date is later than the effective date prescribed in sections 84-906 and 84-911.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 446, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB867, &#167; 10. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>