<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1202</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For
purposes of the Records Management Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) State agency means any department,
division, office, commission, court, board, or elected, appointed, or constitutional
officer, except individual members of the Legislature, or any other unit or
body, however designated, of the executive, judicial, and legislative branches
of state government;</para>
<para>(2) Agency head means the chief or principal official or representative
in any state or local agency or the
presiding judge of any court, by whatever title known. When an agency consists
of a single official, the agency and the agency head are one and the same;</para>
<para>(3) Local agency means an agency of any
county, city, village, township, district, authority, or other public corporation
or political entity, whether existing under charter or general law, including
any entity created pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act or the Joint
Public Agency Act. Local political subdivision does not include a city of
the metropolitan class or a district or other unit which by law is considered
an integral part of state government;</para>
<para>(4) Record means any book,
document, paper, photograph, microfilm, sound recording, magnetic storage
medium, optical storage medium, or other material regardless of physical form
or characteristics created or received pursuant to law, charter, or ordinance
or in connection with any other activity relating to or having an effect upon
the transaction of public business;</para>
<para>(5) State record means a record
which normally is maintained within the custody or control of a state agency
or any other record which is designated or treated as a state record according
to general law;</para>
<para>(6) Local record means a record
of a local political subdivision or of any agency thereof unless designated
or treated as a state record under general law;</para>
<para>(7) Essential record means
a state or local record which is within one or the other of the following
categories and which shall be preserved pursuant to the Records Management
Act:</para>
<para>(a) Category A. Records containing information necessary to the operations
of government under all conditions, including a period of emergency created
by a disaster; or</para>
<para>(b) Category B. Records not within Category A but which contain information
necessary to protect the rights and interests of persons or to establish or
affirm the powers and duties of state or local governments in the resumption
of operations after a disaster;</para>
<para>(8) Preservation duplicate
means a copy of an essential record which is used for the purpose of preserving
the record pursuant to the act;</para>
<para>(9) Disaster means any occurrence
of fire, flood, storm, earthquake, explosion, epidemic, riot, sabotage, or
other conditions of extreme peril resulting in substantial injury or damage
to persons or property within this state, whether such occurrence is caused
by an act of nature or of humans, including an enemy of the United States;</para>
<para>(10) Administrator means the
State Records Administrator;</para>
<para>(11) Board means the State
Records Board;</para>
<para>(12) Electronic access means electronically collecting,
sharing, disseminating, and providing access to (a) public records or (b) electronic information and services;</para>
<para>(13) Electronic information
and services means any data, information, or service that is created, generated,
collected, maintained, or distributed in electronic form by a state agency
or local agency through transactions with individuals, businesses, and other
entities by means of electronic access;</para><para>(14) Portal means the
state's centralized electronic information system by which public
records or electronic information
and services are provided using electronic access;</para>
<para>(15) Public records includes
all records and documents, regardless of physical form, of or belonging to
this state or any agency, branch, department, board, bureau, commission, council,
subunit, or committee of this state except when any other statute expressly
provides that particular information or records shall not be made public.
Data which is a public record in its original form shall remain a public record
when maintained in computer files; and</para>
<para>(16) Network manager means
an individual, a private entity, a state agency, or any other governmental
subdivision responsible for providing
the infrastructure and services needed to implement and operate the portal
and for directing and supervising the day-to-day operations and
expansion of the portal.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 455, &#167; 2, p. 1385; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 841, &#167; 1, p. 3167; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 559, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 747, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 25, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 81, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 590, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>