
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1412"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1412</statuteno><catchline>Meetings of public body; rights of public; public body; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to the Open Meetings Act, the public has the right to attend and the right to speak at meetings of public bodies, and all or any part of a meeting of a public body, except for closed sessions called pursuant to section 84-1410, may be videotaped, televised, photographed, broadcast, or recorded by any person in attendance by means of a tape recorder, a camera, video equipment, or any other means of pictorial or sonic reproduction or in writing. Except for closed sessions called pursuant to section 84-1410, a public body shall allow members of the public an opportunity to speak at each meeting.</para><para>(2) It shall not be a violation of subsection (1) of this section for any public body to make and enforce reasonable rules and regulations regarding the conduct of persons attending, speaking at, videotaping, televising, photographing, broadcasting, or recording its meetings, including meetings held by virtual conferencing.</para><para>(3) No public body shall require members of the public to identify themselves as a condition for admission to the meeting nor shall such body require that the name of any member of the public be placed on the agenda prior to such meeting in order to speak about items on the agenda. The body shall require any member of the public desiring to address the body to identify himself or herself, including an address and the name of any organization represented by such person unless the address requirement is waived to protect the security of the individual.</para><para>(4) No public body shall, for the purpose of circumventing the Open Meetings Act, hold a meeting in a place known by the body to be too small to accommodate the anticipated audience.</para><para>(5) No public body shall be deemed in violation of this section if it holds its meeting in its traditional meeting place which is located in this state.</para><para>(6) No public body shall be deemed in violation of this section if it holds a meeting outside of this state if, but only if:</para><para>(a) A member entity of the public body is located outside of this state and the meeting is in that member's jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) All out-of-state locations identified in the notice are located within public buildings used by members of the entity or at a place which will accommodate the anticipated audience;</para><para>(c) Reasonable arrangements are made to accommodate the public's right to attend, hear, and speak at the meeting, including making virtual conferencing available at an instate location to members, the public, or the press, if requested twenty-four hours in advance;</para><para>(d) No more than twenty-five percent of the public body's meetings in a calendar year are held out-of-state;</para><para>(e) Out-of-state meetings are not used to circumvent any of the public government purposes established in the Open Meetings Act; and</para><para>(f) The public body publishes notice of the out-of-state meeting at least twenty-one days before the date of the meeting in a legal newspaper of statewide circulation.</para><para>(7) Each public body shall, upon request, make a reasonable effort to accommodate the public's right to hear the discussion and testimony presented at a meeting.</para><para>(8) Public bodies shall make available at the meeting or the instate location for virtual conferencing as required by subdivision (6)(c) of this section, for examination and copying by members of the public, at least one copy of all reproducible written material to be discussed at an open meeting, either in paper or electronic form. Public bodies shall make available at least one current copy of the Open Meetings Act posted in the meeting room at a location accessible to members of the public. At the beginning of the meeting, the public shall be informed about the location of the posted information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 325, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 43, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 117, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 324, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1073; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 250, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 898, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB962, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB83, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB43, &#167; 21. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source><annotation><para>To preserve an objection that a public body failed to make documents available at a public meeting as required by subsection (8) of this section, a person who attends a public meeting must not only object to the violation, but must make that objection to the public body or to a member of the public body. Stoetzel &amp; Sons v. City of Hastings, 265 Neb. 637, 658 N.W.2d 636 (2003).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>