<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id118">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id120" statutenumber="84-1505"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1505</statuteno><catchline id="id123">Deferred compensation;
treatment; investment; payment
for civil damages; conditions.</catchline><para>(1)
All compensation deferred under the plan, all property and rights purchased
with the deferred compensation, and all investment income attributable to
the deferred compensation, property, or rights shall be held in trust for
the exclusive benefit of participants and their beneficiaries by the State
of Nebraska until such time as payments shall be paid under the terms of the
deferred compensation plan. All such assets held in trust shall be invested
by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion
Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) The State Treasurer shall be the custodian of the funds
and securities of the deferred compensation plan and may deposit the funds
and securities in any financial institution approved by the Nebraska Investment
Council. All disbursements therefrom shall be paid by him or her only upon
vouchers duly authorized by the retirement board. The State Treasurer shall
furnish annually to the retirement board a sworn statement of the amount of
the funds in his or her custody belonging to the deferred compensation plan,
which statement shall be as of the calendar year ending December 31 of each
year.</para>
<para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (4) of
this section, all compensation deferred under the plan, all property
and rights purchased with the deferred compensation, and all investment income
attributable to the deferred compensation, property, or rights shall not be
subject to garnishment, attachment, levy, the operation of bankruptcy or insolvency
laws, or any other process of law whatsoever and shall not be assignable.</para>
<para>(4) If a participant
in the deferred compensation plan is convicted of or pleads no contest to
a felony that is defined as assault, sexual assault, kidnapping, child abuse,
false imprisonment, or theft by embezzlement and is found liable for civil
damages as a result of such felony, following distribution of the participant's
compensation deferred under the plan, property and rights purchased with the
deferred compensation, or investment income attributable to the deferred compensation,
property, or rights from the plan, the court may order the payment of such
compensation, property and rights, or investment income for such civil damages,
except that the compensation, property and rights, or investment income to
the extent reasonably necessary for the support of the participant or any
of his or her beneficiaries shall be exempt from such payment. Any order for
payment of compensation, property and rights, or investment income shall not
be stayed on the filing of any appeal of the conviction. If the conviction
is reversed on final judgment, all compensation, property and rights, or investment
income paid as civil damages shall be forfeited and returned to the participant.
The changes made to this section by Laws 2012, LB916, shall apply to persons
convicted of or who have pled no contest to such a felony and who have been
found liable for civil damages as a result of such felony prior to, on, or
after April 7, 2012.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 428, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1974, &#167; 84-1329.02; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 460, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 44.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>