<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id58">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id60" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="84-1309.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1309.02</statuteno><catchline id="id63">Cash balance
benefit; election; effect; administrative services agreements; authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that, in order to
improve the competitiveness of the retirement plan for state employees, a
cash balance benefit shall be added to the State Employees Retirement Act
on and after January 1, 2003. Each member who is employed and participating
in the retirement system prior to January 1, 2003, may either elect to continue
participation in the defined contribution benefit as provided in the act prior
to January 1, 2003, or elect to participate in the cash balance benefit as
set forth in this section. An active member shall make a one-time election beginning
September 1, 2012, through October 31, 2012, in order to participate in the
cash balance benefit. If no such election is made, the member shall be treated
as though he or she elected to continue participating in the defined contribution
benefit as provided in the act prior to January 1, 2003. Members who elect
to participate in the cash balance benefit beginning September 1, 2012, through
October 31, 2012, shall commence participation in the cash balance benefit
on January 2, 2013. Any member who made the election prior to April 7, 2012,
does not have to make another election of the cash balance benefit beginning
September 1, 2012, through October 31, 2012.</para>
<para>(2) For a member employed and participating in the retirement
system beginning on and after January 1, 2003, or a member employed and participating
in the retirement system on January 1, 2003, who, prior to April 7, 2012, or beginning September 1, 2012, through October
31, 2012, elects to convert his or her employee and employer accounts
to the cash balance benefit:</para>
<para>(a) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(b) of section 84-1321.01,
the employee cash balance account within
the State Employees Retirement Fund shall, at any time, be equal
to the following:</para>
<para>(i) The initial employee account balance, if any, transferred
from the defined contribution plan account described in section 84-1310; plus</para>
<para>(ii) Employee contribution credits deposited in accordance
with section 84-1308; plus</para>
<para>(iii) Interest credits credited in accordance with subdivision
(18) of section 84-1301; plus</para>
<para>(iv) Dividend amounts credited in accordance with subdivision
(4)(c) of section 84-1319; and</para>
<para>(b) The employer cash balance account shall, at any time,
be equal to the following:</para>
<para>(i) The initial employer account balance, if any, transferred
from the defined contribution plan account described in section 84-1311; plus</para>
<para>(ii) Employer contribution credits deposited in accordance
with section 84-1309; plus</para>
<para>(iii) Interest credits credited in accordance with subdivision
(18) of section 84-1301; plus</para>
<para>(iv) Dividend amounts credited in accordance with subdivision
(4)(c) of section 84-1319.</para>
<para>(3) In order to carry out the provisions of this section,
the board may enter into administrative services agreements for accounting
or record-keeping services. No agreement shall be entered into unless the
board determines that it will result in administrative economy and will be
in the best interests of the state and its participating employees. The board
may develop a schedule for the allocation of the administrative services agreements
costs for accounting or record-keeping services and may assess the costs so
that each member pays a reasonable fee as determined by the board.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 366, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 35.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>