<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1204</statuteno><catchline>State Records Board; established; members; duties; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The State Records Board is hereby established. The board shall:</para><para>(a) Advise and assist the administrator in the performance of his or her duties under the Records Management Act;</para><para>(b) Provide electronic access to public records or electronic information and services through the portal;</para><para>(c) Develop and maintain the portal for providing electronic access to public records or electronic information and services;</para><para>(d) Provide appropriate oversight of a network manager;</para><para>(e) Approve reasonable fees for electronic access to public records or electronic information and services pursuant to sections 84-1205.02 and 84-1205.03;</para><para>(f) Have the authority to enter into or renegotiate agreements regarding the management of the portal in order to provide individuals, businesses, and other entities with electronic access to public records or electronic information and services;</para><para>(g) Explore ways and means of reducing the costs of agencies to manage record retention, expanding the amount and type of public records or electronic information and services provided through the portal, and, when appropriate, implement changes necessary to effect such purposes;</para><para>(h) Explore new technologies as a means of improving access to public records or electronic information and services by individuals, businesses, and other entities and, if appropriate, implement the new technologies;</para><para>(i) Explore options of expanding the portal and its services to individuals, businesses, and other entities;</para><para>(j) Have the authority to grant funds to a state or local agency for the development of programs and technology to improve electronic access to public records or electronic information and services consistent with the act; and</para><para>(k) Perform such other functions and duties as the act requires.</para><para>(2) In addition to the administrator, the board shall consist of:</para><para>(a) The Governor or his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The Attorney General or his or her designee;</para><para>(c) The Auditor of Public Accounts or his or her designee;</para><para>(d) The State Treasurer or his or her designee;</para><para>(e) The Director of Administrative Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(f) Three representatives appointed by the Governor to be broadly representative of banking, insurance, and law groups; and</para><para>(g) Three representatives appointed by the Governor to be broadly representative of libraries, the general public, and professional members of the Nebraska news media.</para><para>(3) The administrator shall be chairperson of the board. Upon call by the administrator, the board shall convene periodically in accordance with its rules and regulations or upon call by the administrator.</para><para>(4) Six members of the board shall constitute a quorum, and the affirmative vote of six members shall be necessary for any action to be taken by the board. No vacancy in the membership of the board shall impair the right of a quorum to exercise all the rights and perform all the duties of the board.</para><para>(5) The representatives appointed by the Governor shall serve staggered three-year terms as the Governor designates and may be appointed for one additional term. Members of the board shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 455, &#167; 4, p. 1387; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 841, &#167; 3, p. 3170; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 559, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 18, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 590, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 257, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB880, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 134. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>