<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id586">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id588" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="84-1307"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1307</statuteno><catchline id="id591">Retirement
system; membership; requirements; composition; exercise of option to join;
effect; new employee; participation in another governmental plan; how treated;
separate employment; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The membership
of the retirement system shall be composed of all persons who are or were
employed by the State of Nebraska and who maintain an account balance with
the retirement system.</para>
<para>(2) The following employees of the State of Nebraska are
authorized to participate in the retirement system: (a) All permanent full-time
employees shall begin participation in the retirement system upon employment;
and (b) all permanent part-time employees who have attained the age of eighteen years may exercise the option to begin
participation in the retirement system. An employee who exercises the option
to begin participation in the retirement system pursuant to this section shall
remain in the retirement system until his or her termination of employment
or retirement, regardless of any change of status as a permanent or temporary
employee.</para>
<para>(3) On and after July 1, 2010, no employee shall be authorized
to participate in the retirement system provided for in the State Employees
Retirement Act unless the employee (a) is a United States citizen or (b) is
a qualified alien under the federal Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C.
1101 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2009, and is lawfully present
in the United States.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section, (a) permanent full-time
employees includes employees of the Legislature or Legislative Council who
work one-half or more of the regularly scheduled hours during each pay period
of the legislative session and (b) permanent part-time employees includes
employees of the Legislature or Legislative Council who work less than one-half
of the regularly scheduled hours during each pay period of the legislative
session.</para>
<para>(5)(a) Within the first one
hundred eighty days of employment, a full-time employee may apply to the board
for vesting credit for years of participation in another Nebraska governmental
plan, as defined by section 414(d) of the Internal Revenue Code. During the
years of participation in the other Nebraska governmental plan, the employee
must have been a full-time employee, as defined in the Nebraska governmental
plan in which the credit was earned. The board may adopt and promulgate rules
and regulations governing the assessment and granting of vesting credit.</para>
<para>(b) If the contributory
retirement plan or contract let pursuant to section 48-609 is terminated,
employees of the Department of Labor who are active participants in such contributory
retirement plan or contract on the date of termination of such plan or contract
shall be granted vesting credit for their years of participation in such plan
or contract.</para><para>(6) Any employee who qualifies
for membership in the retirement system pursuant to this section may not be
disqualified for membership in the retirement system solely because such employee
also maintains separate employment which qualifies the employee for membership
in another public retirement system, nor may membership in this retirement
system disqualify such an employee from membership in another public employment
system solely by reason of separate employment which qualifies such employee
for membership in this retirement system.</para>
<para>(7) State agencies shall ensure that employees authorized
to participate in the retirement system pursuant to this section shall enroll
and make required contributions to the retirement system immediately upon
becoming an employee. Information necessary to determine membership in the
retirement system shall be provided by the employer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 532, &#167; 7, p. 1670; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 842, &#167; 1, p. 3177; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 492, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 219, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 325, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 834, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 501, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1192, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 366, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1147, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 45.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>