<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1205"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1205</statuteno><catchline>Board; network manager; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The board may employ or contract with a network manager. A network manager may be an individual, a private entity, a state agency, or another governmental subdivision. The board shall prepare criteria and specifications for the network manager in consultation with the Department of Administrative Services. Such criteria shall include procedures for submission of proposals by an individual, a private entity, a state agency, or another governmental subdivision. Selection of the network manager shall comply with all applicable procedures of the department. The board may negotiate and enter into a contract with the selected network manager which provides the duties, responsibilities, and compensation of the network manager.</para><para>(2) The network manager shall provide the infrastructure and services needed to implement and operate the portal and shall direct and supervise the day-to-day operations and expansion of the portal. The network manager shall (a) attend meetings of the board, (b) keep a record of all portal operations, which shall be the property of the board, (c) maintain and be the custodian of all financial and operational records, and (d) annually update and revise the business plan for the portal in consultation with and under the direction of the board.</para><para>(3) The board shall finance the operation and maintenance of the portal from revenue generated pursuant to sections 60-483 and 84-1205.02.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 590, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 37. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>