<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id00" statutenumber="84-1613"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1613</statuteno><catchline id="id00">State Employees Insurance Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para id="id00">The State Employees Insurance Fund is established. The fund shall be administered by the personnel division of the Department of Administrative Services. All funds appropriated to pay the state's share of the cost of the coverages provided by sections 84-1601 to 84-1615 and all payroll deductions made under sections 84-1601 to 84-1615 shall be credited to the fund. The division shall make premium payments to the carrier, carriers, or combinations of carriers selected under section 84-1603 from this fund. The division may also use the fund to make incentive payments to state employees pursuant to section 44-1413.</para><para id="id00">Any funds in the State Employees Insurance Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para id="id00">On or before October 1, 2001, the State Treasurer shall transfer one million five hundred thousand dollars from the excess state share of life insurance history money of the State Employees Insurance Fund to the Workers' Compensation Claims Revolving Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 516, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 273, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 44-1630; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 303, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 133; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1252, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 541, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1119, &#167; 26. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>