<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id611" statutenumber="84-1501"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1501</statuteno><catchline id="id614">Public Employees Retirement Board; created; members; qualifications; appointment; terms; vacancy; expenses; removal.</catchline><para>(1) The Public Employees Retirement Board is hereby established.</para><para>(2)(a) The board shall consist of eight appointed members as described in this subsection and the state investment officer as a nonvoting, ex officio member. Six of the appointed members shall be active or retired participants in the retirement systems administered by the board, and two of the appointed members (i) shall not be employees of the State of Nebraska or any of its political subdivisions and (ii) shall have at least ten years of experience in the management of a public or private organization or have at least five years of experience in the field of actuarial analysis or the administration of an employee benefit plan.</para><para>(b) The six appointed members who are participants in the systems shall be as follows:</para><para>(i) Two of the appointed members shall be participants in the School Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska and shall include one administrator and one teacher;</para><para>(ii) One of the appointed members shall be a participant in the Nebraska Judges Retirement System as provided in the Judges Retirement Act;</para><para>(iii) One of the appointed members shall be a participant in the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement System;</para><para>(iv) One of the appointed members shall be a participant in the Retirement System for Nebraska Counties; and</para><para>(v) One of the appointed members shall be a participant in the State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(c) Appointments to the board shall be made by the Governor and shall be subject to the approval of the Legislature. All appointed members shall be citizens of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(3)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, all members shall serve for terms of five years or until a successor has been appointed and qualified. The terms shall begin on January 1 of the appropriate year.</para><para>(b) To ensure an experienced and knowledgeable board, the terms of the appointed members shall be staggered as follows:</para><para>(i) One of the two members described in subdivisions (2)(a)(i) and (ii) of this section shall be appointed to serve for a five-year term which begins in 2017;</para><para>(ii) One of the two members described in subdivisions (2)(a)(i) and (ii) of this section shall be appointed to serve for a five-year term which begins in 2018;</para><para>(iii) The participant in the School Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska who is a teacher shall be appointed for a five-year term which begins in 2019;</para><para>(iv) The participant in the School Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska who is an administrator and the participant in the State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska shall be appointed for a five-year term which begins in 2020;</para><para>(v) The participant in the Retirement System for Nebraska Counties and the participant in the Nebraska Judges Retirement System shall be appointed to serve for a five-year term which begins in 2021; and</para><para>(vi) The participant in the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement System shall be appointed to serve for a three-year term which begins in 2020, and his or her successor shall be appointed to serve for a five-year term which begins in 2023.</para><para>(4) In the event of a vacancy in office, the Governor shall appoint a person to serve the unexpired portion of the term subject to the approval of the Legislature.</para><para>(5) The appointed members of the board may be removed by the Governor for cause after notice and an opportunity to be heard.</para><para>(6) The members of the board shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 250, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 36, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 216; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 59, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 418, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 46. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Judges Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 24-701.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>