<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id120" statutenumber="84-1505"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1505</statuteno><catchline id="id123">Deferred compensation; treatment; investment.</catchline><para>(1) All compensation deferred under the plan, all property and rights purchased with the deferred compensation, and all investment income attributable to the deferred compensation, property, or rights shall be held in trust for the exclusive benefit of participants and their beneficiaries by the State of Nebraska until such time as payments shall be paid under the terms of the deferred compensation plan. All such assets held in trust shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) The State Treasurer shall be the custodian of the funds and securities of the deferred compensation plan and may deposit the funds and securities in any financial institution approved by the Nebraska Investment Council. All disbursements therefrom shall be paid by him or her only upon vouchers duly authorized by the retirement board. The State Treasurer shall furnish annually to the retirement board a sworn statement of the amount of the funds in his or her custody belonging to the deferred compensation plan, which statement shall be as of the calendar year ending December 31 of each year.</para><para>(3) All compensation deferred under the plan, all property and rights purchased with the deferred compensation, and all investment income attributable to the deferred compensation, property, or rights shall not be subject to garnishment, attachment, levy, the operation of bankruptcy or insolvency laws, or any other process of law whatsoever and shall not be assignable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 428, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1974, &#167; 84-1329.02; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 460, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB40, &#167; 17. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>