<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id650">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id652" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="84-1321"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1321</statuteno><catchline id="id655">Employees;
termination of employment; benefits; when; how computed; vesting; deferment
of benefits; certain required
minimum distributions; election authorized.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as provided in section 42-1107, upon termination of employment before
becoming eligible for retirement under section 84-1317, a member may, upon
application to the board, receive:</para>
<para>(a) If not vested, a termination benefit equal to the amount
in his or her employee account or member cash balance account as of the date
of final account value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the lump-sum
or first annuity payment made at any time after termination but no later than
April 1 of the year following the year in which the member attains the age
of seventy and one-half years;
or</para>
<para>(b) If vested, a termination benefit equal to (i) the amount
of his or her member cash balance account as of the date of final account
value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the lump-sum or first annuity
payment made at any time after termination but no later than April 1 of the
year following the year in which the member attains the age of seventy and
one-half years or (ii)(A) the amount in his or her employee account as of
the date of final account value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the
lump-sum or first annuity payment made at any time after termination but no
later than April 1 of the year following the year in which the member attains
the age of seventy and one-half years plus (B) the amount of his or her employer
account as of the date of final account value payable in a lump sum or an
annuity with the lump-sum or first annuity payment made at any time after
termination but no later than April 1 of the year following the year in which
the member attains the age of seventy and one-half years.</para>
<para>The member cash balance account or employer and employee
accounts of a terminating member shall be retained by the board, and the termination
benefit shall be deferred until a valid application for benefits has been
received.</para>
<para>(2) At the option of the terminating member, any lump sum
of the vested portion of the employer account or member cash balance account
or any annuity provided under subsection (1) of this section shall commence
as of the first of the month at any time after such member has terminated
his or her employment with the state or may be deferred, except that no benefit
shall be deferred later than April 1 of the year following the year in which
the employee has both attained at least seventy and one-half years of age
and has terminated his or her employment with the state. Such election by the terminating
member shall be made at any time prior to the commencement of the lump-sum
or annuity payments.</para>
<para>(3) Members of the retirement system shall be vested after
a total of three years of participation in the system as a member pursuant
to section 84-1307, including vesting credit. If an employee retires pursuant
to section 84-1317, such an employee shall be fully vested in the retirement
system.</para>
<para>(4) A participant
or beneficiary who would have been required to receive required minimum distributions
for 2009 but for the enactment of section 401(a)(9)(H) of the Internal Revenue
Code, and who would have satisfied that requirement by receiving distributions
that are either equal to the 2009 required minimum distributions or one or
more payments in a series of substantially equal distributions, including
the 2009 required minimum distribution, made at least annually and expected
to last for the life or life expectancy of the participant, the joint lives
or joint life expectancy of the participant and the participant's designated
beneficiary, or for a period of at least ten years, shall receive those distributions
for 2009 unless the participant or beneficiary chooses not to receive such
distributions. Participants and beneficiaries shall be given the opportunity
to elect to stop receiving the distributions.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 532, &#167; 21, p. 1675; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 498, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 56, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 604, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 219, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 751, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 325, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 308, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 60, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 417, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1306, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1273, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 366, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 41.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>