<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1214.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1214.01</statuteno><catchline>State Archives; authority; duties.</catchline>
<para>The State Archives of the Nebraska State Historical Society has the
authority to acquire, in total or in part, any document, record, or material
which has been submitted to the board for disposition or transfer when such
material is determined to be of archival or historical significance by the
State Archivist or the board. The head of any state or local agency shall certify in writing
to the society the transfer of the custody of such material to the State Archives.
No state or local agency
shall dispose of, in any other manner except by transfer to the State Archives,
that material which has been appraised as archival or historical without the
written consent of the State Archivist and the administrator. If such material
is determined to be in jeopardy of destruction or deterioration and such material
is not necessary to the conduct of daily business in the state or local agency of origin, it shall be
the prerogative of the State Archivist to petition the administrator and the state or local agency of origin
for the right to transfer such material into the safekeeping of the State
Archives. It shall be the responsibility of the administrator to hear arguments
for or against such petition and to determine the results of such petition.
The State Archivist shall prepare invoices and receipts in triplicate for
materials acquired under this section, shall retain one copy, and shall deliver
one copy to the administrator and one copy to the state or local agency head from whom the records
are obtained.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 841, &#167; 11, p. 3175; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 18, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>