<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1201"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1201</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent.</catchline><para>The
Legislature declares that:</para>
<para>(1) Programs for the systematic and centrally correlated management
of state and local records will promote efficiency and economy in the day-to-day
record-keeping activities of state and local agencies and
will facilitate and expedite governmental operations;</para>
<para>(2) Records containing information essential to the operations of government,
and to the protection of the rights and interests of persons, must be safeguarded
against the destructive effects of all forms of disaster and must be available
as needed. It is necessary
to adopt special provisions for the selection and preservation of essential
state and local records, thereby insuring the protection and availability
of such information;</para>
<para>(3) The increasing availability and use of computers is creating a growing
demand for electronic access to public records, and state and local agencies should use new technology
to enhance public access to public records and
to reduce costs in maintaining, preserving, or retaining public records;</para>
<para>(4) There must be public accountability in the process of collecting,
sharing, disseminating, and accessing public records;</para>
<para>(5) The Legislature has oversight responsibility for the process of
collecting, sharing, disseminating, and providing access, including electronic
access, to public records and establishing fees for disseminating and providing
access;</para>
<para>(6) Several state agencies, individually and collectively, are providing
electronic access to public records through various means, including the portal;</para>
<para>(7) New technology has
allowed state agencies to offer electronic information and services through
various means, including the portal;</para><para>(8) As technology becomes available, state and local
agencies should continue to explore providing electronic information and services
to individuals, businesses, and other entities; and</para><para>(9) There is a need for a uniform policy regarding
the management, operation, and oversight of systems providing electronic access
to public records or electronic
information and services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 455, &#167; 1, p. 1385; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 590, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB880, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB719, section 7, with LB880, section 1, to reflect all amendments.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>