<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1226"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1226</statuteno><catchline>Records Management Micrographics Services Revolving Fund; created; credits; expenditures; rental.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created a fund to be known as the Records Management Micrographics Services Revolving Fund. All charges received by the Secretary of State under sections 84-1209 and 84-1225 and legislative appropriations shall be credited to such fund. Whenever any micrographics equipment of any state agency, except the University of Nebraska or the state colleges, shall become surplus property and shall be sold pursuant to section 81-161.04, the proceeds from the sale of such equipment shall be deposited in the state treasury and shall be credited by the State Treasurer to the Records Management Micrographics Services Revolving Fund. Expenditures shall be made from such fund to finance the micropublishing services and the computer output microfilm services by the Secretary of State or his or her authorized agent in accordance with appropriations made by the Legislature, to receive and expend funds pursuant to section 84-1225 for the provision of source document microfilming and for procuring and replacing micrographic equipment provided to state agencies, and to receive and expend funds pursuant to section 84-1209 for the providing of records storage services for state agencies.</para><para>(2) By agreement between any state agency and the State Records Administrator, any state agency may be billed one full year's rental for equipment at the beginning of each fiscal year. The State Records Administrator may coordinate with the Director of Administrative Services to set up a separate subaccount within the fund for the purpose of accounting for micrographic equipment procurement and replacement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 520, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 559, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 29. </para></source></law></legaldoc>