<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1325"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1325</statuteno><catchline>Employees; military service; credit; payments.</catchline><para>(1) Any employee who, while an employee, entered into and served in the armed forces of the United States and who within ninety days after honorable discharge or honorable separation from active duty again became an employee shall be credited, for the purposes of the provisions of section 84-1317, with all the time actually served in the armed forces as if such person had been an employee throughout such service in the armed forces pursuant to the terms and conditions of subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) Under such rules and regulations as the retirement board adopts and promulgates, any employee who is reemployed on or after December 12, 1994, pursuant to 38 U.S.C. 4301 et seq., may pay to the retirement system an amount equal to the sum of all deductions which would have been made from the employee's compensation during such period of military service. Payment shall be made within the period required by law, not to exceed five years. To the extent that payment is made, (a) the employee shall be treated as not having incurred a break in service by reason of his or her period of military service, (b) the period of military service shall be credited for the purposes of determining the nonforfeitability of the member's accrued benefits and the accrual of benefits under the plan, and (c) the employer shall allocate the amount of employer contributions to the member's employer account in the same manner and to the same extent the allocation occurs for other employees during the period of service. For purposes of member and employer contributions under this subsection, the member's compensation during the period of military service shall be the rate the member would have received but for the military service or, if not reasonably determinable, the average rate the member received during the twelve-month period immediately preceding military service.</para><para>(3) The employer shall pick up the member contributions made through irrevocable payroll deduction authorizations pursuant to this section, and the contributions so picked up shall be treated as employer contributions in the same manner as contributions picked up under subsection (1) of section 84-1308.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 532, &#167; 25, p. 1676; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 37. </para></source></law></legaldoc>