<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id230">
<sectno id="id231" opdate="July 1, 2009">Sec. 19.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id232" statutenumber="84-1512"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id234">84-1512</statuteno><catchline id="id235">Board; access
to records; director; duties; employer education program.</catchline><para>(1) The Public Employees Retirement Board, for purposes of administering
the various retirement systems under its jurisdiction, shall receive from
the Department of Administrative Services and other employers such information
as is necessary for the efficient and accurate administration of the systems
and shall consult with the Department of Administrative Services and other
employers as to the form in which the information is to be presented and received
by the board. The information in the records shall be provided by the employers
in an accurate and verifiable form, as specified by the director of the Nebraska
Public Employees Retirement Systems. The director shall, from time to time,
carry out testing procedures to verify the accuracy of such information. The
director shall have access to records maintained by the Department of Administrative
Services on the Nebraska employees information system data base for the purpose
of obtaining any information which may be necessary to verify the accuracy
of information and administer the systems and the holder of the records shall
comply with a request by the director for access by providing such facts and
information to the director in a timely manner.</para>
<para>(2) The director shall develop and implement an employer
education program using principles generally accepted by public employee retirement
systems so that all employers have the knowledge and information necessary
to prepare and file reports as the board requires.</para>
<para>(3) The information
obtained by the board pursuant to this section shall not be considered public
records subject to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09, except that the following
information shall be considered public records: The member's name, the retirement
system in which the member is a participant, the date the member's participation
in the retirement system commenced, and the date the member's participation
in the retirement system ended, if applicable.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1192, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 503, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>