<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id625">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id627" statutenumber="84-1503">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1503</statuteno><catchline id="id630">Board; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) It shall be the duty of the Public Employees Retirement
Board:</para>
<para>(a) To administer the retirement systems provided for in
the County Employees Retirement Act, the Judges Retirement Act, the Nebraska
State Patrol Retirement Act, the School Employees Retirement Act, and the
State Employees Retirement Act. The agency for the administration of the retirement
systems and under the direction of the board shall be known and may be cited
as the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems;</para>
<para>(b) To appoint a director to administer the systems under
the direction of the board. The appointment shall be subject to the approval
of the Governor and a majority of the Legislature. The director shall be qualified
by training and have at least five years of experience in the administration
of a qualified public or private employee retirement plan. The director shall
not be a member of the board. The salary of the director shall be set by the
board. The director shall serve without term and may be removed by the board;</para>
<para>(c) To provide for an equitable allocation of expenses among
the retirement systems administered by the board, and all expenses shall be
provided from the investment income earned by the various retirement funds
unless alternative sources of funds to pay expenses are specified by law;</para>
<para>(d) To administer the deferred compensation program authorized
in section 84-1504;</para>
<para>(e) To hire an attorney, admitted to the Nebraska State Bar
Association, to advise the board in the administration of the retirement systems
listed in subdivision (a) of this subsection;</para>
<para>(f) To hire an internal auditor to perform the duties described
in section 84-1503.04 who meets the minimum standards as described in section
84-304.03;</para>
<para>(g) To adopt and implement procedures for reporting information
by employers, as well as testing and monitoring procedures in order to verify
the accuracy of such information. The information necessary to determine membership
shall be provided by the employer. The board shall adopt and promulgate rules
and regulations and prescribe such forms necessary to carry out this subdivision.
Nothing in this subdivision shall be construed to require the board to conduct
onsite audits of political subdivisions for compliance with statutes, rules,
and regulations governing the retirement systems listed in subdivision (1)(a)
of this section regarding membership and contributions; and</para>
<para>(h) To prescribe and furnish forms for the public retirement
system plan reports required to be filed pursuant to sections 2-3228, 12-101,
14-567, 14-1805.01, 14-2111, 15-1017, 16-1017, 16-1037, 19-3501, 23-1118,
23-3526, 71-1631.02, and 79-987.</para>
<para>(2) In administering the retirement systems listed in subdivision
(1)(a) of this section, it shall be the duty of the board:</para>
<para>(a) To determine, based on information provided by the employer,
the prior service annuity, if any, for each person who is an employee of the
county on the date of adoption of the retirement system;</para>
<para>(b) To determine the eligibility of an individual to be a
member of the retirement system and other questions of fact in the event of
a dispute between an individual and the individual's employer;</para>
<para>(c) To adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the
management of the board;</para>
<para>(d) To keep a complete record of all proceedings taken at
any meeting of the board;</para>
<para>(e) To obtain, by a competitive, formal, and sealed bidding
process through the materiel division of the Department of Administrative
Services, actuarial services on behalf of the State of Nebraska as may be
necessary in the administration and development of the retirement systems.
Any contract for actuarial services shall contain a provision allowing the
actuary, without prior approval of the board, to perform actuarial studies
of the systems as requested by entities other than the board, if notice, which
does not identify the entity or substance of the request, is given to the
board, all costs are paid by the requesting entity, results are provided to
the board, the Nebraska Retirement
Systems Committee of the Legislature, and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst upon
being made public, and such actuarial studies do not interfere with the actuary's
ongoing responsibility to the board. The term of the contract shall be for
up to three years. A competitive, formal, and sealed bidding process shall
be completed at least once every
three years, unless the board determines that such a process would not be
cost effective under the circumstances and that the actuarial services performed
have been satisfactory, in which case the contract may also contain an option
for renewal without a competitive, formal, and sealed bidding process for
up to three additional years. An actuary under contract for the State of Nebraska
shall be a member of the American Academy of Actuaries;</para>
<para>(f) To direct the State Treasurer to transfer funds, as an
expense of the retirement systems, to the Legislative Council Retirement Study
Fund. Such transfer shall occur beginning on or after July 1, 2005, and at
intervals of not less than five years and not more than fifteen years and
shall be in such amounts as the Legislature shall direct;</para>
<para>(g) To adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry
out the provisions of each retirement system described in subdivision (1)(a)
of this section, which shall include, but not be limited to, the crediting
of military service, direct rollover distributions, and the acceptance of
rollovers;</para>
<para>(h) To obtain, by a competitive, formal, and sealed bidding
process through the materiel division of the Department of Administrative
Services, auditing services for a separate compliance audit of the retirement
systems to be completed by December 31, 2012, and from time to time
thereafter at the request of the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature, to be
completed not more than every four years but not less than every ten years.
The compliance audit shall be in addition to the annual audit conducted by
the Auditor of Public Accounts. The compliance audit shall include, but not
be limited to, an examination of records, files, and other documents and an
evaluation of all policies and procedures to determine compliance with all
state and federal laws. A copy of the compliance audit shall be given to the
Governor, the board, and the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and shall
be presented to the committee at a public hearing;</para>
<para>(i) To adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the
adjustment of contributions or benefits, which shall include, but not be limited
to: (i) The procedures for refunding contributions, adjusting future contributions
or benefit payments, and requiring additional contributions or repayment of
benefits; (ii) the process for a member, member's beneficiary, employee, or
employer to dispute an adjustment to contributions or benefits; and (iii)
notice provided to all affected persons. All notices shall be sent prior to
an adjustment and shall describe the process for disputing an adjustment to
contributions or benefits; and</para>
<para>(j) To administer all retirement system plans in a manner
which will maintain each plan's status as a qualified plan pursuant to the
Internal Revenue Code. The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
necessary or appropriate to maintain such status including, but not limited
to, rules or regulations which restrict discretionary or optional contributions
to a plan or which limit distributions from a plan.</para>
<para>(3) By March 31 of each year, the board
shall prepare a written plan of action and shall present such plan to the
Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of
the Legislature at a public hearing. The plan shall include, but
not be limited to, the board's funding policy, the administrative costs and
other fees associated with each fund and plan overseen by the board, member
education and informational programs, the director's duties and limitations,
an organizational structure of the office of the Nebraska Public Employees
Retirement Systems, and the internal control structure of such office to ensure
compliance with state and federal laws.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 216, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 498, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 416, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 70, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 751, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 549, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1170, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 672, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1306, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 502, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 78; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 849, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1192, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 808, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 503, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 51.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB474, section 14, with LB509, section 51, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB509 became operative July 1, 2011. Changes made by LB474 became effective August 27, 2011.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 23-2331.</para><para><emphasis>Judges Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 24-701.01.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 81-2014.01.</para><para><emphasis>School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-901.</para><para><emphasis>State Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1331.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
