<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id714">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id716" statutenumber="84-1511.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1511.01</statuteno><catchline id="id719">Board; retirement
education and financial planning program; for whom; required information;
funding; attendance; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The Public Employees
Retirement Board shall establish a comprehensive retirement education and
financial planning program for all members of the State Employees Retirement
System of the State of Nebraska and for all members of the Retirement System
for Nebraska Counties, who are under age fifty and not eligible to attend
the preretirement planning program established in section 84-1511. The program
may be provided to members in a single-day format, or may be provided in equivalent
partial-day segments.</para>
<para>(2) The retirement education and financial planning program
shall include discussion on the retirement system, financial planning, and
budgeting as well as any other planning information valuable to employees
before they reach age fifty.</para>
<para>(3) The employer shall provide each eligible employee leave
with pay to attend a retirement education and financial planning program twice
prior to age fifty. For purposes of this subsection, leave with pay means
time off paid by the employer and shall not mean vacation, sick, personal,
or compensatory time. Leave with pay shall be provided to each eligible employee
in order that the employee may attend the full retirement education and financial
planning program, whether it is provided in a single-day program or in the
equivalent partial-day segments. An employee may choose to attend a full program
more than twice, but leave to attend any additional single-day programs or
equivalent segments shall be at the expense of the employee and shall be at
the discretion of the employer. An employee may not attend a full program
more than once per fiscal year.</para>
<para>(4) Funding to cover the expense of the retirement education
and financial planning program shall be charged proportionately to the State
Employees Retirement Fund and the County Employees Retirement Fund.</para>
<para>(5) A nominal registration fee may be
charged each person attending a retirement education and financial planning
program to cover the costs for meals or meeting rooms or other expenses incurred
for the program.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 254, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 369, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 45.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>