<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1206</statuteno><catchline>Administrator; duties; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) With due regard for the functions of the state and local agencies concerned, and with
such guidance and assistance from the board as may be required, the administrator
shall:</para>
<para>(a) Establish standards, procedures, and techniques for the effective
management of public records;</para>
<para>(b) Make continuing surveys of paperwork, microfilm, and electronic storage operations,
and recommend improvements in current records management practices, including, but not limited to, the economical use of and cost reductions in space,
equipment, and supplies employed in creating, maintaining, storing, preserving,
and servicing records;</para>
<para>(c) Establish standards for the preparation of schedules providing for
the retention of records of continuing value and
for the prompt and orderly disposal of records no longer possessing sufficient
administrative, legal, historical, or fiscal value to warrant their further
retention; and</para>
<para>(d) Obtain from the state
or local agencies concerned such reports and other data as are
required for the proper administration of the records management program, including organizational
charts of agencies concerned.</para>
<para>(2) The administrator shall establish standards for designating essential
records, shall assist state
and local agencies in identifying essential records, and shall
guide such agencies in the establishment
of programs for the preservation of essential records.</para>
<para>(3) The administrator may advise and assist members of the Legislature
and other officials in the maintenance and disposition of their personal or
political papers of public interest and may provide such other services as
are available to state and local agencies, within the limitation of available
funds.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 455, &#167; 6, p. 1388; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 841, &#167; 4, p. 3171; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 641, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 747, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB880, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>