<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id191"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1515"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1515</statuteno><catchline>Member of any Nebraska state public retirement system; written solicitations; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this section, no person or entity shall include any name, logo, symbol, or similar name, logo, or symbol of any of the following in a written solicitation for any financial product or service directed to a member of any Nebraska state public retirement system without the consent of the Public Employees Retirement Board:</para><para>(i) The Public Employees Retirement Board;</para><para>(ii) The Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems;</para><para>(iii) The School Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(iv) Any retirement system for a Class V school;</para><para>(v) The Retirement System for Nebraska Counties;</para><para>(vi) The State Employees Retirement System;</para><para>(vii) The Nebraska Judges Retirement System; or</para><para>(viii) The Nebraska State Patrol Retirement System.</para><para>(b) Any written solicitation for any financial product or service directed to a member of any Nebraska state public retirement system shall clearly and conspicuously state that the person or entity is not sponsored by or affiliated with the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, or any retirement system specified in subdivisions (1)(a)(iii) through (viii) of this section. Any such statement shall be in close proximity to and in larger font size than the first use and any prominent uses of the name, logo, or symbol in the written solicitation, including on an envelope or through an envelope window containing the written solicitation.</para><para>(2) No person or entity shall use the name of the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, any retirement system specified in subdivisions (1)(a)(iii) through (viii) of this section, or any name similar to the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, or any retirement system specified in subdivisions (1)(a)(iii) through (viii) of this section, in any written solicitation for any financial product or service directed to any member of any Nebraska state public retirement system if such use could cause a reasonable person to be confused, mistaken, or deceived initially or otherwise as to any of the following:</para><para>(a) Any sponsorship, affiliation, connection, or association with the person who or entity that initiated or sent the written solicitation and the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, or any retirement system specified in subdivisions (1)(a)(iii) through (viii) of this section;</para><para>(b) Any approval or endorsement of the person who or entity that initiated or sent the written solicitation by the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, or any retirement system specified in subdivisions (1)(a)(iii) through (viii) of this section; or</para><para>(c) Any approval or endorsement of any product or service provided or offered by the person who or entity that initiated or sent the written solicitation by the Public Employees Retirement Board, the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems, or any retirement system specified in subdivisions (1)(a)(iii) through (viii) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB295, &#167; 26. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>