<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1503.02" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1503.02</statuteno><catchline>Board; duties and responsibilities.</catchline><para>(1) The appointed members of the Public Employees Retirement Board shall have the responsibility for the administration of the retirement systems pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of section 84-1503, shall be deemed fiduciaries with respect to the administration of the retirement systems, and shall be held to the standard of conduct of a fiduciary specified in subsection (2) of this section. The nonvoting, ex officio member of the board shall not be deemed a fiduciary.</para><para>(2) As fiduciaries, the appointed members of the board shall discharge their duties with respect to the retirement systems solely in the interests of the members and beneficiaries of the retirement systems for the exclusive purposes of providing benefits to members and members' beneficiaries and defraying reasonable expenses incurred within the limitations and according to the powers, duties, and purposes prescribed by law at the time such duties are discharged. The appointed members of the board shall not have a duty in their official capacity to seek the enhancement of plan benefits through the legislative process if such benefits are not already contained within the plan documents. The appointed members of the board shall act with the care, skill, prudence, and diligence under the circumstances then prevailing that a prudent person acting in like capacity and familiar with such matters would use in the conduct of an enterprise of a like character and with like aims.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 18.</para></source></law></legaldoc>