<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id5" statutenumber="84-1413"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">84-1413</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Meetings; minutes;
roll call vote; secret ballot; when.</catchline><para>(1) Each public
body shall keep minutes of all meetings showing the time, place, members present
and absent, and the substance of all matters discussed.</para>
<para>(2) Any action taken on any question or motion duly moved
and seconded shall be by roll call vote of the public body in open session,
and the record shall state how each member voted or if the member was absent
or not voting. The requirements of a roll call or viva voce vote shall be
satisfied by a municipality,
a county, a learning community, a joint entity created pursuant to the Interlocal
Cooperation Act, a joint public agency created pursuant to the Joint Public
Agency Act, or an agency formed under the Municipal Cooperative Financing
Act which utilizes an electronic voting device which allows the
yeas and nays of each member of such city council, village board, county board, or governing body to be readily
seen by the public.</para>
<para>(3) The vote to elect leadership within a public body may
be taken by secret ballot, but the total number of votes for each candidate
shall be recorded in the minutes.</para>
<para>(4) The minutes of all meetings and evidence and documentation
received or disclosed in open session shall be public records and open to
public inspection during normal business hours.</para>
<para>(5) Minutes shall be written and available for inspection
within ten working days or prior to the next convened meeting, whichever occurs
earlier, except that cities of the second class and villages may have an additional
ten working days if the employee responsible for writing the minutes is absent
due to a serious illness or emergency.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 325, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 609, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 86, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 663, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 501, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB361, &#167;  3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Municipal Cooperative Financing Act,</emphasis> see section 18-2401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>If a person present at a meeting observes and fails to object to an alleged public meetings laws violation in the form of a failure to conduct rollcall votes before taking actions on questions or motions pending, that person waives his or her right to object at a later date. Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 264 Neb. 944, 653 N.W.2d 240 (2002).</para><para>Subsection (2) of this section does not require the record to state that the vote was by roll call, but requires only that the record show if and how each member voted. Neither does the statute set a time limit for recording the results of a vote, after which no corrections of the record can be made. If no intervening rights of third persons have arisen, a board of county commissioners has power to correct the record of the proceedings had at a previous meeting so as to make them speak the truth, particularly where the correction supplies some omitted fact or action and is done not to contradict or change the original record but to have the record show that a certain action was taken or thing done, which the original record fails to show. State ex rel. Schuler v. Dunbar, 214 Neb. 85, 333 N.W.2d 652 (1983).</para><para>Failure by a public governing body, as defined under section 84-1409, R.R.S.1943, to take and record a roll call vote on an action, as required by section 84-1413(2), R.S.Supp.,1980, grants any citizen the right to sue for the purpose of having the action declared void. In this case such failure could not be later corrected by a nunc pro tunc order because there was no showing that a roll call vote on the disputed action was actually taken, and even if it was the record showed it was not recorded until over a year later. Sections 23-1301, R.R.S.1943, and 23-1302, R.R.S.1943, make it the duty of the county clerk to record proceedings of the board of county commissioners. State ex rel. Schuler v. Dunbar, 208 Neb. 69, 302 N.W.2d 674 (1981).</para>
<para>There is no requirement that a public body make a record of where notice was published or posted. Wolf v. Grubbs, 17 Neb. App. 292, 759 N.W.2d 499 (2009).</para>
</annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>