<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id461">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id463" statutenumber="84-1323"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1323</statuteno><catchline id="id466">Employees;
death before retirement; death benefit; amount; direct transfer to retirement plan; death while performing
qualified military service; additional death benefit.</catchline>
<para>(1) In
the event of the death before his or her retirement date of any employee who
is a member of the system, the death benefit shall be equal to (a) for participants in the defined contribution
benefit, the total of the employee account and the employer account and (b) for participants in the cash balance benefit,
the benefit provided in section 84-1309.02. The death benefit shall be paid
to the member's beneficiary, to an alternate payee pursuant to a qualified
domestic relations order as provided in section 42-1107, or to the member's
estate if there are no designated beneficiaries. If the beneficiary is not
the member's surviving spouse, the death benefit shall be paid as a lump-sum
payment or payments, except that the entire account must be distributed by
the fifth anniversary of the member's death. If the sole primary beneficiary
is the member's surviving spouse, the surviving spouse may elect to receive
an annuity calculated as if the member retired and selected a one-hundred-percent
joint and survivor annuity effective on the annuity purchase date. If the
surviving spouse does not elect the annuity option within one hundred eighty
days after the death of the member, the surviving spouse shall receive a lump-sum
payment or payments, except that the entire account must be distributed by
the fifth anniversary of the member's death.</para>
<para>(2) A lump-sum
death benefit paid to the member's beneficiary, other than the member's estate,
that is an eligible distribution may be distributed in the form of a direct
transfer to a retirement plan eligible to receive such transfer under the
provisions of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(3) For any member whose death occurs on
or after January 1, 2007, while performing qualified military service as defined
in section 414(u) of the Internal Revenue Code, the member's beneficiary shall
be entitled to any additional death benefit that would have been provided,
other than the accrual of any benefit relating to the period of qualified
military service. The additional death benefit shall be determined as if the
member had returned to employment with the State of Nebraska and such employment
had terminated on the date of the member's death.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 532, &#167; 23, p. 1676; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 498, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 751, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1306, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1273, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 41.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>