<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id373">
<sectno id="id374" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 27.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id375" statutenumber="84-1323.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id377">84-1323.01</statuteno><catchline id="id378">Employee;
retirement; disability; medical examination.</catchline><para>(1)
Any member who is an employee, disregarding the length of service, may be
retired as a result of disability either upon the member's own application
or upon the application of the member's employer or any person acting in the
member's behalf. Before any member may be so retired, a medical examination
shall be made at the expense of the retirement system, which examination shall
be conducted by a disinterested physician legally authorized to practice medicine
under the laws of the state in which he or she practices, such physician to
be selected by the retirement board, and the physician shall certify to the
board that the member suffers from an inability to engage in a substantially
gainful activity by reason of any medically determinable physical or mental
impairment which began while
the member was a participant in the plan and which can be expected
to result in death or to be of long-continued and indefinite duration and
should be retired. The application for disability retirement shall be made
within one year of termination of employment.</para>
<para>(2) The retirement board may require any disability beneficiary
who has not attained the age of fifty-five to undergo a medical examination
at the expense of the board once each year. If any disability beneficiary
refuses to undergo such an examination, the disability retirement benefit
may be discontinued by the board.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 498, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 417, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167;  27.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>