<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id599">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id601" statutenumber="84-1321.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1321.01</statuteno><catchline id="id604">Termination
of employment; account forfeited; when; State Employer Retirement Expense
Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>(1) For a member who
has terminated employment and is not vested, the balance of the member's employer
account or employer cash balance account shall be forfeited. The forfeited
account shall be credited to the State Employees Retirement Fund and shall
first be used to meet the expense charges incurred by the retirement board
in connection with administering the retirement system, which charges shall
be credited to the State Employees Defined Contribution Retirement Expense
Fund, if the member participated in the defined contribution option, or to
the State Employees Cash Balance Retirement Expense Fund, if the member participated
in the cash balance option, and the remainder, if any, shall then be used
to reduce the state contribution which would otherwise be required to fund
future service retirement benefits or to restore employer accounts or employer
cash balance accounts. No forfeited amounts shall be applied to increase the
benefits any member would otherwise receive under the State Employees Retirement
Act.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If a member ceases
to be an employee due to the termination of his or her employment by the state
and a grievance or other appeal of the termination is filed, transactions
involving forfeiture of his or her employer account or employer cash balance
account and, except as provided
in subdivision (b) of this subsection, transactions for payment of benefits
under sections 84-1317 and 84-1321 shall be suspended pending
the final outcome of the grievance or other appeal.</para>
<para>(b) If a member elects
to receive benefits payable under sections 84-1317 and 84-1321 after a grievance
or appeal is filed, the member may receive an amount up to the balance of
his or her employee account or member cash balance account or twenty-five
thousand dollars payable from the employee account or member cash balance
account, whichever is less.</para><para>(3) The State
Employer Retirement Expense Fund is created. The fund shall be administered
by the Public Employees Retirement Board. The fund shall be established and
maintained separate from any funds held in trust for the benefit of members
under the retirement system. The fund shall be used to meet expenses of the
State Employees Retirement System of the State of Nebraska whether such expenses
are incurred in administering the member's employer account or in administering
the member's employer cash balance account when the funds available in the
State Employees Defined Contribution Retirement Expense Fund or State Employees
Cash Balance Retirement Expense Fund make such use reasonably necessary.</para>
<para>(4) The director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement
Systems shall certify to the Accounting Administrator of the Department of
Administrative Services when accumulated employer account forfeiture funds
are available to reduce the state contribution which would otherwise be required
to fund future service retirement benefits or to restore employer accounts
or employer cash balance accounts referred to in subsection (1) of this section.
Following such certification, the Accounting Administrator shall transfer
the amount reduced from the state contribution from the Imprest Payroll Distributive
Fund to the State Employer Retirement Expense Fund. Expenses incurred as a
result of the state depositing amounts into the State Employer Retirement
Expense Fund shall be deducted prior to any additional expenses being allocated.
Any remaining amount shall be allocated in accordance with subsection (3)
of this section. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested
by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion
Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1200, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 48.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>