<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id435">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Officers" id="id437" statutenumber="84-1311.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1311.03</statuteno><catchline id="id440">Defined
contribution benefit; employer account; investment options; procedures; administration.</catchline>
<para>(1) Each member employed and participating in the retirement
system prior to January 1, 2003, who has elected not to participate in the
cash balance benefit, shall be allowed to allocate all contributions to his
or her employer account to various investment options. Such investment options
shall be the same as the investment options of the employee account as provided
in subsection (1) of section 84-1310.01. If a member fails to select an option
or combination of options, all of his or her funds in the employer account
shall be placed in the balanced account option described in subdivision (1)(d)
of section 84-1310.01. Each member shall be given a detailed current description
of each investment option prior to making or revising his or her allocation.</para>
<para>(2) Each member of the retirement system may allocate contributions
to his or her employer account to the investment options in percentage increments
as set by the board in any proportion, including full allocation to any one
option. A member under subdivision (1)(a) of section 84-1323
or his or her beneficiary may transfer any portion of his or her funds among
the options. The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for
changes of a member's allocation of contributions to his or her accounts after
his or her most recent allocation and for transfers from one investment account
to another.</para>
<para>(3) The board shall develop a schedule for the allocation
of administrative costs of maintaining the various investment options and
shall assess the costs so that each member pays a reasonable fee as determined
by the board.</para>
<para>(4) In order to carry out the provisions of this section,
the board may enter into administrative services agreements for accounting
or record-keeping services. No agreement shall be entered into unless the
board determines that it will result in administrative economy and will be
in the best interests of the state and its participating employees.</para>
<para>(5) The state, the board, the state investment officer, the
members of the Nebraska Investment Council, or the agency shall not be liable
for any investment results resulting from the member's exercise of control
over the assets in the employer account.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 687, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1200, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 503, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1147, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 37.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>