<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Officers" statutenumber="84-1601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>84-1601</statuteno><catchline>Program; established; coverage; employees of the Nebraska State Patrol; optional coverage.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby established a program of group life and health insurance for all permanent employees of this state who work one-half or more of the regularly scheduled hours during each pay period, excluding employees of the University of Nebraska, the state colleges, and the community colleges. Such program shall be known as the Nebraska State Insurance Program and shall replace any current program of such insurance in effect in any agency and funded in whole or in part by state contributions.</para><para>(2) Temporary employees of the state who have a work assignment of at least six months' duration and who work at least twenty hours per week may purchase health insurance through the Nebraska State Insurance Program. The state shall pay the same proportion of the insurance premium for temporary employees as is established through the collective bargaining process for permanent employees. For purposes of this subsection, temporary employees means individuals (a) employed in the Temporary Employee Pool as described in subdivision (6) of section 81-1307 and (b) hired directly by state agencies. In no event shall a temporary employee mean an individual hired through a private employment agency.</para><para>(3) For purposes of sections 84-1601 to 84-1615, health insurance may be construed to include coverage for disability and dental health care services.</para><para>(4) Any commissioned employee of the Nebraska State Patrol who on or after July 17, 1986, has reached fifty-one years of age or becomes medically disabled and who will not receive benefits from the federal social security program shall be afforded the opportunity to remain enrolled in the state employees group health insurance program until age sixty-five. Employees electing this option shall be responsible for the entire premium cost, including the state's share, the employee's share, and an administrative fee consistent with that allowed by federal guidelines for continuation of health insurance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 516, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 789, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 244, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 970, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 115, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 705, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 74, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 491, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 44-1620; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 303, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1162, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 113, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 47. </para></source><annotation><para>Public employee benefits to be realized at retirement are not mere gratuities but are deferred compensation. Omer v. Tagg, 235 Neb. 527, 455 N.W.2d 815 (1990).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>