<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id28">
<sectno id="id29" opdate="May 30, 2009">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id30" statutenumber="24-301.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id32">24-301.02</statuteno><catchline id="id33">District court
judicial districts; described; number of judges.</catchline><para>The
State of Nebraska shall be divided into the following twelve district court
judicial districts:</para>
<para>District No. 1 shall contain the counties of Clay, Nuckolls,
Saline, Jefferson, Gage, Thayer, Johnson, Pawnee, Nemaha, Fillmore, and Richardson;</para>
<para>District No. 2 shall contain the counties of Sarpy, Cass,
and Otoe;</para>
<para>District No. 3 shall contain the county of Lancaster;</para>
<para>District No. 4 shall contain the county of Douglas;</para>
<para>District No. 5 shall contain the counties of Merrick, Platte,
Colfax, Boone, Nance, Hamilton, Polk, York, Butler, Seward, and Saunders;</para>
<para>District No. 6 shall contain the counties of Dixon, Dakota,
Cedar, Burt, Thurston, Dodge, and Washington;</para>
<para>District No. 7 shall contain the counties of Knox, Cuming,
Antelope, Pierce, Wayne, Madison, and Stanton;</para>
<para>District No. 8 shall contain the counties of Cherry, Keya
Paha, Brown, Rock, Blaine, Loup, Custer, Boyd, Holt, Garfield, Wheeler, Valley,
Greeley, Sherman, and Howard;</para>
<para>District No. 9 shall contain the counties of Buffalo and Hall;</para>
<para>District No. 10 shall contain the counties of Adams, Phelps,
Kearney, Harlan, Franklin, and Webster;</para>
<para>District No. 11 shall contain the counties of Hooker, Thomas,
Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Keith, Perkins, Lincoln, Dawson, Chase, Hayes, Frontier,
Gosper, Dundy, Hitchcock, Red Willow, and Furnas; and</para>
<para>District No. 12 shall contain the counties of Sioux, Dawes,
Box Butte, Sheridan, Scotts Bluff, Morrill, Garden, Banner, Kimball, Cheyenne,
Grant, and Deuel.</para>
<para>In the fourth district there shall be sixteen judges of the
district court. In the third district,
until June 30, 2011, there shall be seven judges of the district
court and, beginning July 1,
2011, there shall be eight judges of the district court. In the
second, fifth, ninth, eleventh, and twelfth districts there shall be four
judges of the district court. In the first and sixth districts there shall
be three judges of the district court. In the seventh, eighth, and tenth districts
there shall be two judges of the district court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 5, &#167; 1, p. 70; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 203, &#167; 1, p. 623; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 217; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 12, &#167; 1, p. 64; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 3, &#167; 1, p. 55; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 114, &#167; 1, p. 278; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 146, &#167; 1, p. 620; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 199; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 119, &#167; 1, p. 283; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 5-103; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 5-105; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 11, &#167; 1, p. 99; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 24, &#167; 1, p. 125; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 23, &#167; 1, p. 186; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 24, &#167; 1, p. 189; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 229; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1301, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 1, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 618, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 121, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 287, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 516, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-105; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 181, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1059, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 306, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 19, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 189, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 404, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 92, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1207, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB377, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional provisions,</emphasis> see Article V, sections 10 and 11, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Rights of newly appointed judges under merit plan of judicial selection governed by applicable laws in effect at time of appointment and qualification. Garrotto v. McManus, 185 Neb. 644, 177 N.W.2d 570 (1970).</para><para>Omission of county in amendatory act providing for judicial districts did not exclude county from the operation of the laws or judicial authority of the state. State ex rel. Reed v. Grimes, 98 Neb. 762, 154 N.W 544 (1915).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>