<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-707.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-707.01</statuteno><catchline>Surviving spouse; benefits; applicable, when.</catchline><para>(1) This section only applies to a judge who first served as a judge on or after July 1, 2004, and to a future member who elects to make contributions and receive benefits as provided in section 24-703.03.</para><para>(2) In the event of the death of a judge subsequent to retirement, his or her surviving spouse, if any, shall be entitled to receive, if the surviving spouse was born not more than five years subsequent to the birth of the deceased judge, a monthly benefit payable for life equal to fifty percent of the monthly benefit the retired judge was entitled to receive under the normal form of payment. Such benefit to the surviving spouse shall be provided without actuarial reduction or other assessment to the retired judge in determining his or her benefits. The entire cost of such a benefit shall be assumed by the fund. This benefit value may be applied on an actuarially equivalent basis to any joint and survivor benefit elected by a retiring judge with the surviving spouse as named beneficiary.</para><para>(3) In the event that the spouse of a retiring judge was born more than five years subsequent to the birth of the judge, such benefit to the judge described under subsection (2) of this section shall be reduced by the actuarial cost of providing a benefit to the surviving spouse equal to fifty percent of the benefit the retired judge was entitled to receive. The reduction to the retired judge's benefit shall be limited to that portion of the actuarial cost that exceeds the actuarial cost if the spouse was born five years subsequent to the judge. In the event of the death of a retired judge as described by this subsection, his or her surviving spouse shall receive a monthly benefit payable for life equal to fifty percent of the monthly benefit received by the deceased judge.</para><para>(4) This section shall not prevent a retiring judge from contracting to provide a larger percentage of benefit for a surviving spouse under other applicable statutes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>