<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id18">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id20" statutenumber="24-507"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-507</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Clerk magistrates;
appointment; serve as clerk of court;
assist clerk of district court; agreement; contents; ex officio clerk of the
district court; when.</catchline><para>(1) There shall
be appointed a clerk magistrate to serve each county. Clerk magistrates shall
be appointed by the county judge, or judges if the district has more than
one county judge, and shall serve at the pleasure of the county judge or judges,
subject to personnel rules adopted by the Supreme Court.</para>
<para>(2) The clerk magistrate shall be the clerk of the county
court and if appointed as clerk magistrate for more than one county shall
be the clerk of the county court for each county.</para>
<para>(3) In counties
when the district court clerk or staff is temporarily unavailable, the clerk
magistrate as clerk of the county court shall, under the direction of the
district court judge and in cooperation and agreement with the Supreme Court,
State Court Administrator, and clerk of the district court, assist the clerk
of the district court in the provision of district court services which would
otherwise require the presence of district court staff. Any agreement entered
into under this subsection must be signed and stipulated to by the State Court
Administrator, the county board, and the clerk of the district court after
obtaining input from the clerk of the county court, a district court judge,
a county court judge, and the county attorney. Any agreement entered into
under this subsection may include, but is not limited to, financial considerations
and scheduling.</para><para>(4) When an agreement has been reached pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)
of section 32-524 or subsection (3) of section 32-524 for a clerk magistrate
as clerk of the county court to be ex officio clerk of the district court,
the clerk magistrate shall perform the duties required by law of the clerk
of the district court under the direction of the district court judge for
the county and the State Court Administrator.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 529, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB669, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
