<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-201.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-201.02</statuteno><catchline>Supreme Court judicial districts; described.</catchline><para>Based on the 2000 Census of Population by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, the State of Nebraska is hereby divided into six Supreme Court judicial districts. Each district shall be entitled to one Supreme Court judge. The limits and designations of the six districts shall be as follows:</para><para>District No. 1. The counties of Lancaster, Cass, and Otoe;</para><para>District No. 2. That part of Douglas County not included in Supreme Court judicial district 4;</para><para>District No. 3. The counties of Boyd, Knox, Cedar, Dixon, Dakota, Holt, Antelope, Pierce, Wayne, Thurston, Garfield, Wheeler, Boone, Madison, Stanton, Cuming, Burt, Greeley, Howard, Nance, Merrick, Platte, Colfax, Dodge, and Washington;</para><para>District No. 4. Sarpy County and that part of Douglas County beginning at the intersection of the Douglas-Sarpy County line and South 180th Street, north on South 180th Street to West Center Road, east on West Center Road to Interstate Highway 680, north on Interstate Highway 680 to Pacific Street, east on Pacific Street to Turner Boulevard, southeast then northeast on Turner Boulevard to Pacific Street, east on Pacific Street and continuing east along east-west lines extending east from Pacific Street to South 20th Street, south on South 20th Street to Pierce Street, east on Pierce Street and continuing east along an east-west line extending east from Pierce Street to South 16th Street, north on South 16th Street to the intersection of an east-west line extending west from Pacific Street, east along such line to Pacific Street, east on Pacific Street to South 11th Street, north on South 11th Street to Mason Street, east on Mason Street to South 10th Street, north on South 10th Street to the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way, east along the Union Pacific Railroad right-of-way to the Nebraska-Iowa state line, south along the Nebraska-Iowa state line to the Douglas-Sarpy County line, and west along the Douglas-Sarpy County line to the point of beginning;</para><para>District No. 5. The counties of Phelps, Harlan, Kearney, Franklin, Hall, Adams, Webster, Nuckolls, Thayer, Clay, Hamilton, Polk, Butler, Saunders, York, Seward, Fillmore, Saline, Jefferson, Gage, Johnson, Nemaha, Pawnee, and Richardson; and</para><para>District No. 6. The counties of Valley, Sherman, Buffalo, Furnas, Gosper, Dawson, Custer, Loup, Blaine, Rock, Brown, Keya Paha, Cherry, Thomas, Logan, Lincoln, Frontier, Red Willow, Hitchcock, Hayes, McPherson, Hooker, Grant, Arthur, Keith, Perkins, Chase, Dundy, Deuel, Garden, Sheridan, Cheyenne, Morrill, Box Butte, Dawes, Sioux, Scotts Bluff, Banner, and Kimball.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 545, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 552, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-109; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 616, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 853, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional provisions,</emphasis> see Article V, section 5, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>