<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id61" statutenumber="24-708"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>24-708</statuteno><catchline id="id64">Retirement of judge; when; deferment of payment; board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in section 24-721, a judge may retire upon reaching the age of sixty-five years and upon making application to the board. Upon retiring each such judge shall receive retirement annuities as provided in section 24-710.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 24-721, a judge may retire upon reaching the age of fifty-five years and elect to receive a reduced monthly retirement income in lieu of a deferred vested annuity. The judge may request that the reduced monthly retirement income commence at any date, beginning on the first day of the month following the actual retirement date and ending on the normal retirement date. The amount of the reduced monthly retirement income shall be calculated based on the length of creditable service and average compensation at the actual retirement date. When a judge has elected to receive a reduced monthly retirement income to commence at the age of sixty-four years, the monthly payments shall be reduced by three percent. When a judge has elected to receive a reduced monthly retirement income to commence at the age of sixty-three years, the monthly payments shall be reduced by six percent. When a judge has elected to receive a reduced monthly retirement income to commence at the age of sixty-two years, the monthly payments shall be reduced by nine percent. When a judge has elected to receive a reduced monthly retirement income to commence prior to the age of sixty-two years, the monthly payments shall be further reduced to an amount that is actuarially equivalent to the amount payable at the age of sixty-two years.</para><para>(3) Payment of any benefit provided under the Judges Retirement Act shall not be deferred later than the required beginning date.</para><para>(4) The effective date of retirement payments shall be the first day of the month following (a) the date a member qualifies for retirement as provided in this section or (b) the date upon which a member's request for retirement is received on an application form provided by the retirement system, whichever is later. An application may be filed no more than one hundred twenty days in advance of qualifying for retirement.</para><para>(5) The board shall make reasonable efforts to locate the member or the member's beneficiary and distribute benefits by the required beginning date. If the board is unable to make such a distribution, the benefit shall be distributed pursuant to the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act and no amounts may be applied to increase the benefits any member would otherwise receive under the Judges Retirement Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 83, &#167; 8, p. 248; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 78, &#167; 2, p. 317; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 79, &#167; 3, p. 322; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 115, &#167; 3, p. 444; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 353, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 750, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 296, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 506, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 320, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1147, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1054, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 25, 2020</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act,</emphasis> see section 69-1329.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>