<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id154">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id156" statutenumber="24-701"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>24-701</statuteno><catchline id="id159">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Judges Retirement Act, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Fund means the Nebraska Retirement Fund for Judges;</para>
<para>(2) Judge means and includes (a) all duly elected or appointed
Chief Justices or judges of the Supreme Court and judges of the district courts
of Nebraska who serve in such capacity on and after January 3, 1957, (b)(i)
all duly appointed judges of the Nebraska Workmen's Compensation Court who
served in such capacity on and after September 20, 1957, and prior to July
17, 1986, and (ii) judges of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court who
serve in such capacity on and after July 17, 1986, (c) judges of separate
juvenile courts, (d) judges of the county courts of the respective counties
who serve in such capacity on and after January 5, 1961, (e) judges of the
county court and clerk magistrates who were associate county judges and members
of the fund at the time of their appointment as clerk magistrates, (f) judges
of municipal courts established by Chapter 26, article 1, who served in such
capacity on and after October 23, 1967, and prior to July 1, 1985, and (g)
judges of the Court of Appeals;</para>
<para>(3) Prior service means all the periods of time any person
has served as a (a) judge of the Supreme Court or judge of the district court
prior to January 3, 1957, (b) judge of the county court prior to January 5,
1961, (c) judge of the Nebraska Workmen's Compensation Court prior to September
20, 1957, (d) judge of the separate juvenile court, or (e) judge of the municipal
court prior to October 23, 1967;</para>
<para>(4)(a) Current service means the period of service (i) any
judge of the Supreme Court or judge of the district court serves in such capacity
from and after January 3, 1957, (ii)(A) any judge of the Nebraska Workmen's
Compensation Court served in such capacity from and after September 20, 1957,
and prior to July 17, 1986, and (B) any judge of the Nebraska Workers' Compensation
Court serves in such capacity on and after July 17, 1986, (iii) any county
judge serves in such capacity from and after January 5, 1961, (iv) any judge
of a separate juvenile court serves in such capacity, (v) any judge of the
municipal court served in such capacity subsequent to October 23, 1967, and
prior to July 1, 1985, (vi) any judge of the county court or associate county
judge serves in such capacity subsequent to January 4, 1973, (vii) any clerk
magistrate, who was an associate county judge and a member of the fund at
the time of appointment as a clerk magistrate, serves in such capacity from
and after July 1, 1986, and (viii) any judge of the Court of Appeals serves
in such capacity on or after September 6, 1991.</para>
<para>(b) Current service shall not be deemed to be interrupted
by (i) temporary or seasonal suspension of service that does not terminate
the employee's employment, (ii) leave of absence authorized by the employer
for a period not exceeding twelve months, (iii) leave of absence because of
disability, or (iv) military service, when properly authorized by the board.
Current service does not include any period of disability for which disability
retirement benefits are received under section 24-709;</para>
<para>(5) Military service means active service of (a) any judge
of the Supreme Court or judge of the district court in any of the armed forces
of the United States during a war or national emergency prior or subsequent
to September 18, 1955, if such service commenced while such judge was holding
the office of judge, (b) any judge of the Nebraska Workmen's Compensation
Court or the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court in any of the armed forces
of the United States during a war or national emergency prior or subsequent
to September 20, 1957, if such service commenced while such judge was holding
the office of judge, (c) any judge of the municipal court in any of the armed
forces of the United States during a war or national emergency prior or subsequent
to October 23, 1967, and prior to July 1, 1985, if such service commenced
while such judge was holding the office of judge, (d) any judge of the county
court or associate county judge in any of the armed forces of the United States
during a war or national emergency prior or subsequent to January 4, 1973,
if such service commenced while such judge was holding the office of judge,
(e) any clerk magistrate, who was an associate county judge and a member of
the fund at the time of appointment as a clerk magistrate, in any of the armed
forces of the United States during a war or national emergency on or after
July 1, 1986, if such service commenced while such clerk magistrate was holding
the office of clerk magistrate, and (f) any judge of the Court of Appeals
in any of the armed forces of the United States during a war or national emergency
on or after September 6, 1991, if such service commenced while such judge
was holding the office of judge. The board shall have the power to determine
when a national emergency exists or has existed for the purpose of applying
this definition and provision;</para>
<para>(6) Creditable service means the total number of years served
as a judge, including prior service, military service, and current service,
computed to the nearest one-twelfth year. For current service prior to the
time that the member has contributed the required percentage of salary until
the maximum benefit as limited by section 24-710 has been earned, creditable
service does not include current service for which member contributions are
not made or are withdrawn and not repaid;</para>
<para>(7)(a) Compensation means the statutory salary of a judge
or the salary being received by such judge pursuant to law. Compensation does
not include compensation for unused sick leave or unused vacation leave converted
to cash payments, insurance premiums converted into cash payments, reimbursement
for expenses incurred, fringe benefits, per diems, or bonuses for services
not actually rendered, including, but not limited to, early retirement inducements,
cash awards, and severance pay, except for retroactive salary payments paid
pursuant to court order, arbitration, or litigation and grievance settlements.
Compensation includes overtime pay, member retirement contributions, and amounts
contributed by the member to plans under sections 125 and 457 of the Internal
Revenue Code as defined in section 49-801.01 or any other section of the code
which defers or excludes such amounts from income.</para>
<para>(b) Compensation in excess of the limitations set forth in
section 401(a)(17) of the Internal Revenue Code as defined in section 49-801.01
shall be disregarded. For an employee who was a member of the retirement system
before the first plan year beginning after December 31, 1995, the limitation
on compensation shall not be less than the amount which was allowed to be
taken into account under the retirement system as in effect on July 1, 1993;</para>
<para>(8) Beneficiary means a person so designated by a judge in
the last designation of beneficiary on file with the board or, if no designated
person survives or if no designation is on file, the estate of such judge;</para>
<para>(9) Normal form annuity means a series of equal monthly payments
payable at the end of each calendar month during the life of a retired judge
as provided in sections 24-707 and 24-710, except as provided in section 42-1107.
The first payment shall include all amounts accrued since the effective date
of the award of the annuity. The last payment shall be at the end of the calendar
month in which such judge dies. If at the time of death the amount of annuity
payments such judge has received is less than contributions to the fund made
by such judge, plus regular interest, the difference shall be paid to the
beneficiary or estate;</para>
<para>(10) Board means the Public Employees Retirement Board;</para>
<para>(11) Member means a judge eligible to participate in the
retirement system established under the Judges Retirement Act;</para>
<para>(12) Original member means a judge who first served as a
judge prior to December 25, 1969, who does not elect to become a future member
pursuant to subsection (8) of section 24-703 or section 24-710.01, and who
was retired on or before December 31, 1992;</para>
<para>(13) Future member means a judge who first served as a judge
on or after December 25, 1969, or means a judge who first served as a judge
prior to December 25, 1969, who elects to become a future member on or before
June 30, 1970, as provided in subsection (8) of section 24-703 or section
24-710.01;</para>
<para>(14) Final average compensation means the average monthly
compensation for the three twelve-month periods of service as a judge in which
compensation was the greatest or, in the event of a judge serving less than
three twelve-month periods, the average monthly compensation for such judge's
period of service;</para>
<para>(15) Regular interest means interest fixed at a rate equal
to the daily treasury yield curve for one-year treasury securities, as published
by the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, that applies on July
1 of each year, which may be credited monthly, quarterly, semiannually, or
annually as the board may direct;</para>
<para>(16) Normal retirement date means the first day of the month
following attainment of age sixty-five;</para>
<para>(17) Actuarial equivalence means the equality in value of
the aggregate amounts expected to be received under different forms of payment.
The determinations are to be based on the 1994 Group Annuity Mortality Table
reflecting sex-distinct factors blended using seventy-five percent of the
male table and twenty-five percent of the female table. An interest rate of
eight percent per annum shall be reflected in making these determinations;</para>
<para>(18) Current benefit means the initial benefit increased
by all adjustments made pursuant to the Judges Retirement Act;</para>
<para>(19) Initial benefit means the retirement benefit calculated
at the time of retirement;</para>
<para>(20) Plan year means the twelve-month period beginning on
July 1 and ending on June 30 of the following year;</para>
<para>(21) Retirement
application means the form approved and provided by the retirement system
for acceptance of a member's request for either regular or disability retirement;</para>
<para>(22) Retirement
date means (a) the first day of the month following the date upon which a
member's request for retirement is received on a retirement application if
the member is eligible for retirement and has terminated employment or (b)
the first day of the month following termination of employment if the member
is eligible for retirement and has filed an application but has not yet terminated
employment;</para><para>(23) Retirement
system or system means the Nebraska Judges Retirement System as provided in
the Judges Retirement Act;</para>
<para>(24) Surviving spouse means
(a) the spouse married to the member on the date of the member's death or
(b) the spouse or former spouse of the member if survivorship rights are provided
under a qualified domestic relations order filed with the board pursuant to
the Spousal Pension Rights Act. The spouse or former spouse shall supersede
the spouse married to the member on the date of the member's death as provided
under a qualified domestic relations order. If the benefits payable to the
spouse or former spouse under the qualified domestic relations order are less
than the value of benefits entitled to the surviving spouse, the spouse married
to the member on the date of the member's death shall be the surviving spouse
for the balance of the benefits; and</para>
<para>(25) Termination of employment
occurs on the date on which the State Court Administrator's office determines
that the judge's employer-employee relationship with the State of Nebraska
is dissolved. The State Court Administrator's office shall notify the board
of the date on which such a termination has occurred. Termination of employment
does not include ceasing employment as a judge if the judge returns to regular
employment as a judge or is employed on a regular basis by another agency
of the State of Nebraska and there are less than one hundred twenty days between
the date when the judge's employer-employee relationship ceased and the date
when the employer-employee relationship recommences. It is the responsibility
of the employer that is involved in the termination of employment to notify
the board of such change in employment and provide the board with such information
as the board deems necessary. If the board determines that termination of
employment has not occurred and a retirement benefit has been paid to a member
of the retirement system pursuant to section 24-710, the board shall require
the member who has received such benefit to repay the benefit to the retirement
system.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 83, &#167; 1, p. 244; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 78, &#167; 1, p. 315; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 79, &#167; 1, p. 318; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 409; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 189, &#167; 13, p. 687; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 115, &#167; 1, p. 440; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 178, &#167; 1, p. 759; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 120; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 226, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 905, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 223, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 750, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 92, &#167; 1;</para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 9; </para> <para>Laws 1986, LB 351, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 529, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 506, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 682, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 700, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1273, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 674, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1192, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB6, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 10.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Spousal Pension Rights Act,</emphasis> see section 42-1101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Judges Retirement Act did not become operative until after terms of all incumbent judges had expired. Wilson v. Marsh, 162 Neb. 237, 75 N.W.2d 723 (1956).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>