<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-201.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>24-201.02</statuteno><catchline>Supreme Court judicial districts; numbers; boundaries; established by maps; Clerk of Legislature; Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Based on the 2020 Census of Population by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, the State of Nebraska is hereby divided into six Supreme Court judicial districts. Each district shall be entitled to one Supreme Court judge.</para><para>(2) The numbers and boundaries of the districts are designated and established by maps identified and labeled as maps SUP21-39001, SUP21-39001-1, SUP21-39001-2, SUP21-39001-3, SUP21-39001-3A, SUP21-39001-4, SUP21-39001-5, and SUP21-39001-6, filed with the Clerk of the Legislature, and incorporated by reference as part of Laws 2021, LB6, One Hundred Seventh Legislature, First Special Session.</para><para>(3)(a) The Clerk of the Legislature shall transfer possession of the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section to the Secretary of State on October 1, 2021.</para><para>(b) When questions of interpretation of district boundaries arise, the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section in possession of the Secretary of State shall serve as the indication of the legislative intent in drawing the district boundaries.</para><para>(c) Each election commissioner or county clerk shall obtain copies of the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section for the election commissioner's or clerk's county from the Secretary of State.</para><para>(d) The Secretary of State shall also have available for viewing on his or her website the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section identifying the boundaries for the districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 545, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 552, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 5-109; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 616, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 853, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB699, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, First Spec. Sess., LB6, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional provisions,</emphasis> see Article V, section 5, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>