<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-209" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-209</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Nebraska Reports; Nebraska Appellate Reports; Nebraska Advance Sheets; Decisions of the Nebraska Court of Appeals; disposition; price; Supreme Court Reports Cash Fund; created.</catchline><para>(1) Unless otherwise directed by the Supreme Court, one copy in print format of the Nebraska Reports and one copy in print format of the Nebraska Appellate Reports shall be furnished by the Supreme Court to each judge of the Supreme Court, Court of Appeals, Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, and district, separate juvenile, and county courts, to each county law library, and to each state library, and two copies of such reports shall be furnished to the Legislative Council. The State Court Administrator shall be furnished as many additional copies in print format as he or she deems necessary for the operation of the Court of Appeals and the Supreme Court.</para><para>(2) Unless otherwise directed by the Supreme Court, one copy in print format of the opinions of the Nebraska Supreme Court in pamphlet form, known as the Nebraska Advance Sheets, and one copy in print format of the opinions of the Nebraska Court of Appeals in pamphlet form, known as the Decisions of the Nebraska Court of Appeals, shall be furnished to each judge of the Supreme Court, Court of Appeals, Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, and district, separate juvenile, and county courts, as many copies as may be requested by the members of the Legislature shall be furnished to the Clerk of the Legislature, and the State Court Administrator shall be furnished as many copies as he or she deems necessary for the operation of the Court of Appeals and the Supreme Court.</para><para>(3) The balance of the Nebraska Reports, Nebraska Appellate Reports, Nebraska Advance Sheets, and Decisions of the Nebraska Court of Appeals shall be sold as called for at such price and in such format as shall be prescribed by the Supreme Court. The money received from such sales shall be paid into the Supreme Court Reports Cash Fund which is hereby created.</para><para>(4) Upon request from any office or entity entitled to free copies of the Nebraska Reports, the Nebraska Appellate Reports, the Nebraska Advance Sheets, or the Decisions of the Nebraska Court of Appeals, the court may stop sending the publications to such office or entity until the request is withdrawn.</para><para>(5) If it is determined by the Supreme Court, pursuant to subsection (2) of section 24-212, that publication of the opinions of the Supreme Court and the Court of Appeals shall be in electronic format, as an alternative to or in addition to print format, the distribution or sale of such print or electronic opinions for purposes of this section shall be directed by the Supreme Court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 20, p. 86; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 24, &#167; 2, p. 330; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 41, &#167; 1, p. 179; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1147; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 213, &#167; 1, p. 752; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1076; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 129, &#167; 1, p. 322; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 27-209; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 59, &#167; 1, p. 236; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 27-209; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 24-209; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 185, &#167; 3, p. 611; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 210, &#167; 1, p. 742; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 101, &#167; 1, p. 332; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 243, &#167; 1, p. 724; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 303, &#167; 1, p. 897; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 129, &#167; 1, p. 496; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 10, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1284, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 9, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 377, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 271, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 848, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 498, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 750, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1059, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 271, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB301, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>In absence of copyright, printer could publish and sell copies of Supreme Court Reports, even though plates belonged to state. State v. State Journal Co., 77 Neb. 752, 110 N.W. 763 (1906), affirming 75 Neb. 275, 106 N.W. 434 (1905).</para><para>Supreme Court Reports belong to office and not to judge personally. Clifford v. Hall County, 60 Neb. 506, 83 N.W. 661 (1900).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>