<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id56">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id58" statutenumber="24-710.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>24-710.02</statuteno><catchline id="id61">Retirement
benefits; exemption from legal process; exception; payment for civil damages; conditions.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2)
of this section, all annuities or benefits which any person shall
be entitled to receive under the Judges Retirement Act shall not be subject
to garnishment, attachment, levy, the operation of bankruptcy or insolvency
laws, or any other process of law whatsoever and shall not be assignable except
to the extent that such annuities or benefits are subject to a qualified domestic
relations order under the Spousal Pension Rights Act. The payment of any annuities or benefits subject to such
order shall take priority over any payment made pursuant to subsection (2)
of this section.</para>
<para>(2) If a member
of the retirement system is convicted of or pleads no contest to a felony
that is defined as assault, sexual assault, kidnapping, child abuse, false
imprisonment, or theft by embezzlement and is found liable for civil damages
as a result of such felony, following distribution of the member's annuities
or benefits from the retirement system, the court may order the payment of
the member's annuities or benefits under the retirement system for such civil
damages, except that the annuities or benefits to the extent reasonably necessary
for the support of the member or any of his or her beneficiaries shall be
exempt from such payment. Any order for payment of annuities or benefits shall
not be stayed on the filing of any appeal of the conviction. If the conviction
is reversed on final judgment, all annuities or benefits paid as civil damages
shall be forfeited and returned to the member. The changes made to this section
by Laws 2012, LB916, shall apply to persons convicted of or who have pled
no contest to such a felony and who have been found liable for civil damages
as a result of such felony prior to, on, or after April 7, 2012.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 506, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1273, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 16.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Spousal Pension Rights Act,</emphasis> see section 42-1101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>