<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-301.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-301.01</statuteno><catchline>District judge; judge of separate juvenile court; salary.</catchline><para>As soon as the same may be legally paid under the Constitution of Nebraska, each judge of the district court and each judge of a separate juvenile court shall be paid a salary of thirty-nine thousand five hundred dollars per annum. On January 8, 1981, the salary shall be increased to an amount equal to six percent over the base salary. For the purposes of this section base salary shall mean the amount derived by increasing thirty-nine thousand five hundred dollars by six percent. On January 6, 1983, and thereafter the salary paid shall be an amount equal to ninety-two and one-half percent of the salary set for the Chief Justice and judges of the Supreme Court. Such salary shall be payable in equal installments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 251; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 345, &#167; 3, p. 1090; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 58, &#167; 2, p. 191; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 77, &#167; 2, p. 232; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 93, &#167; 2, p. 406; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 127, &#167; 2, p. 480; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 110, &#167; 1, p. 434; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 116, &#167; 1, p. 446; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 136, &#167; 2, p. 422; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 174, &#167; 2, p. 755; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1293, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 923, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 76, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 672, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 398, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 111, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Section,</emphasis> interpretation, see section 24-201.03.</para><para><emphasis>Supreme Court judges,</emphasis> salary, see section 24-201.01.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Salary increase for district judges under this section became effective upon appointment of new district judges. Garrotto v. McManus, 185 Neb. 644, 177 N.W.2d 570 (1970).</para><para>Salary of district judge could not be decreased during term by deductions for retirement fund. Wilson v. Marsh, 162 Neb. 237, 75 N.W.2d 723 (1956).</para><para>Legislature of 1945 had once before fixed salary of district judges. State ex rel. Johnson v. Marsh, 149 Neb. 1, 29 N.W.2d 799 (1947).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>