<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-803" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>24-803</statuteno><catchline>Judicial nominating commission; members; term; appointments by Governor; elections by lawyers.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, as the term of a member of a judicial nominating commission initially appointed or selected expires, the term of office of each successor member shall be for a period of four years. The Governor shall appoint all successor members of each nominating commission who are judges of the Supreme Court and citizen members or alternate citizen members. The Governor shall appoint two alternate citizen members, not of the same political party, to each nominating commission. The term of office of an alternate citizen member of a commission shall be for a period of four years except that the initial appointments shall terminate on December 31, 1999. The lawyers residing in the judicial district or area of the state served by a judicial nominating commission shall select all successor and alternate lawyer members of such commission in the manner prescribed in section 24-806. The term of office of an alternate lawyer member of a commission shall be for a period of four years. No member of any nominating commission, including the Supreme Court member of any such commission, shall serve more than a total of eight consecutive years as a member of the commission, and if such member has served for more than six years as a member of the commission, he or she shall not be eligible for reelection or reappointment. Alternate lawyer and citizen members shall be selected to fill vacancies in their order of election or appointment.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section and Article V, section 21, of the Constitution of Nebraska, a member of a judicial nominating commission shall be deemed to have served on such commission if he or she was a member of the commission at the time of the publication of the notice required by subsection (1) of section 24-810.</para><para>(3) Members of the judicial nominating commissions for the office of judge of the district court shall also serve as members of the judicial nominating commissions for the office of judge of the county court for counties located within the district court judicial districts served, except that members of the judicial nominating commissions for district judge and county judge in districts 1, 2, 3, 4, and 10 shall be appointed or selected separately to serve on such commissions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 124, &#167; 3, p. 472; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 110, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 251, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1059, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 189, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 303, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB339, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>