<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-719"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-719</statuteno><catchline>Commission; meetings; quorum; annual report.</catchline><para>(1) Meetings of the Commission on Judicial Qualifications shall be held at least annually at Lincoln, Nebraska, or at such other place or places within the State of Nebraska and at such time as the commission may determine. A majority of the members of the commission shall constitute a quorum. No action of the commission shall be valid unless concurred in by a majority of its members. The date of the annual meeting of the commission shall be fixed by resolution of the commission and special meetings of the commission may be called at any time by the chairperson or vice-chairperson of the commission or by the Supreme Court or at the written request of any two members of the commission.</para><para>(2) To the extent permitted by the Constitution of Nebraska, the commission shall prepare and make available to the public an annual report outlining the activities of the commission in the previous year. The report shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) The total number of meetings held by the commission;</para><para>(b) The total number of complaints filed with the commission;</para><para>(c) The total number of complaints dismissed by the commission;</para><para>(d) The total number of public reprimands issued by the commission;</para><para>(e) The total number of formal complaints filed by the commission; and</para><para>(f) The costs incurred by the commission which shall include:</para><para>(i) Expenses paid to commission members pursuant to section 24-718;</para><para>(ii) Expenses paid to special masters appointed by the commission; and</para><para>(iii) Expenses paid to special investigators hired by the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 141, &#167; 5, p. 431; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 475, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 754, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>