<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-503</statuteno><catchline>County judge districts; created; number of judges; membership.</catchline><para>For the purpose of serving the county courts in each county, twelve county judge districts are hereby created:</para><para>District No. 1 shall contain the counties of Saline, Jefferson, Gage, Thayer, Johnson, Pawnee, Nemaha, and Richardson;</para><para>District No. 2 shall contain the counties of Sarpy, Cass, and Otoe;</para><para>District No. 3 shall contain the county of Lancaster;</para><para>District No. 4 shall contain the county of Douglas;</para><para>District No. 5 shall contain the counties of Merrick, Platte, Colfax, Boone, Nance, Hamilton, Polk, York, Butler, Seward, and Saunders;</para><para>District No. 6 shall contain the counties of Dixon, Dakota, Cedar, Burt, Thurston, Dodge, and Washington;</para><para>District No. 7 shall contain the counties of Knox, Cuming, Antelope, Pierce, Wayne, Madison, and Stanton;</para><para>District No. 8 shall contain the counties of Cherry, Keya Paha, Brown, Rock, Blaine, Loup, Custer, Boyd, Holt, Garfield, Wheeler, Valley, Greeley, Sherman, and Howard;</para><para>District No. 9 shall contain the counties of Buffalo and Hall;</para><para>District No. 10 shall contain the counties of Fillmore, Adams, Clay, Phelps, Kearney, Harlan, Franklin, Webster, and Nuckolls;</para><para>District No. 11 shall contain the counties of Hooker, Thomas, Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Keith, Perkins, Lincoln, Dawson, Chase, Hayes, Frontier, Gosper, Dundy, Hitchcock, Red Willow, and Furnas; and</para><para>District No. 12 shall contain the counties of Sioux, Dawes, Box Butte, Sheridan, Scotts Bluff, Morrill, Garden, Banner, Kimball, Cheyenne, Grant, and Deuel.</para><para>District 4 shall have twelve county judges. Districts 3 and 5 shall have six county judges. Districts 11 and 12 shall have five county judges. Districts 2, 6, and 9 shall have four county judges. Districts 1, 7, 8, and 10 shall have three county judges.</para><para>Judge of the county court shall include any person appointed to the office of county judge or municipal judge prior to July 1, 1985, pursuant to Article V, section 21, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>Any person serving as a municipal judge in district 3 or 4 immediately prior to July 1, 1985, shall be a judge of the county court and shall be empowered to hear only those cases as provided in section 24-517 which the presiding judge of the county court for such district, with the concurrence of the Supreme Court, shall direct.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 785, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 618, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 287, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 516, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 509, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 181, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1059, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 404, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB377, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>