<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-204.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-204.01</statuteno><catchline>Original jurisdiction; issue of constitutionality of acts of Legislature; attorney fees; costs; payment.</catchline><para>When an original action is instituted in the Supreme Court by or against the state, or any office, department, or officer thereof, involving the constitutionality of any act of the Legislature no matter when such act was passed, attorney fees and costs may be allowed if any of the following conditions set forth in subdivision (1), (2), or (3) of this section are found to exist:</para><para>(1)(a) The action challenges the constitutionality of an act which the Attorney General has previously ruled constitutional or unconstitutional or as to which he has made no ruling, or (b) the action supports the constitutionality of an act which the Attorney General has previously ruled unconstitutional;</para><para>(2) The action is pending or commenced while the Legislature is in session; or</para><para>(3) The action is brought by a real party in interest and raises a justiciable issue or issues.</para><para>No such payment shall be made until approval thereof shall have been given by the Legislature by resolution adopted by a majority vote of its members.</para><para>The Supreme Court, upon finding that the conditions set forth in this section exist, shall allow reasonable attorney fees and costs in such amounts and for such parties as the court shall determine. Such fees and costs shall be taxed to the Attorney General and paid out of such appropriation as the Legislature shall make for that purpose.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 135, &#167; 1, p. 420. </para></source></law></legaldoc>