<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id00" statutenumber="24-212"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>24-212</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Preparation and publication of decisions of the Supreme Court and Court of Appeals; annotations.</catchline><para>(1) The Reporter of Decisions shall prepare the opinions designated for permanent publication from the Supreme Court and Court of Appeals for publication in the Nebraska Appellate Courts Online Library as soon as feasible. Such opinions should show the name of the judge writing the opinion, the names of the judges concurring therein, and the names of the judges, if any, dissenting from the opinion.</para><para>(2) At such times as the Revisor of Statutes may request, the Reporter shall also edit and arrange for publication or electronic release in the statutes of Nebraska, annotations of the decisions of the Supreme Court of Nebraska and the decisions of the Court of Appeals designated for permanent publication and transmit them to the Revisor of Statutes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 19, p. 85; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 24, &#167; 1, p. 329; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1146; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1075; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 84, &#167; 1, p. 334; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 27-212; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 24-212; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 328, &#167; 1, p. 868; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 377, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 848, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1244, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 271, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB301, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB799, &#167; 4. </para></source><annotation><para>Reporter should cooperate in letting printing contract with other state agencies authorized to act. Traphagen v. Lindsay, 95 Neb. 823, 146 N.W. 1026 (1914).</para><para>It is the duty of reporter to publish at lowest reasonable cost. In re Brown, 15 Neb. 688, 50 N.W. 273 (1884).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>