<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id6" statutenumber="24-313"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">24-313</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Inferior tribunal;
powers over.</catchline><para>The district court may by rule compel
an inferior court or board to allow an appeal or to make or amend records
according to law either by correcting an evident mistake or supplying an evident
omission. This section shall not apply if the Administrative Procedure
Act otherwise provides.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 28, p. 88; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1172; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1095; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 27-313; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 24-313; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 182, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>District court may by order compel an inferior court or tribunal to amend record to correct an evident mistake. Liljehorn v. Fyfe, 178 Neb. 532, 134 N.W.2d 230 (1965).</para><para>District court may, by order, direct transcript to be returned to county judge for proper certification. Goetz Brewing Co. v. Waln, 92 Neb. 614, 139 N.W. 230 (1912), Ann. Cas. 1914A 336 (1912).</para><para>District court may not compel excise board to reconvene and hear evidence excluded. In re Thompsen, 84 Neb. 67, 120 N.W. 952 (1909).</para><para>Question of power to require supplemental transcript on criminal appeal raised but not decided. Thomsen v. State, 82 Neb. 634, 118 N.W. 330 (1908).</para><para>District court may compel excise board to furnish certified transcript in appeal, in liquor license contest. State ex rel. Thomas v. Board of Fire &amp; Police Comrs. of Omaha, 76 Neb. 741, 108 N.W. 122 (1906).</para><para>District court may, by rule, compel county judge to write true history of case. New Home Sewing-Machine Co. v. Thornburg, 56 Neb. 636, 77 N.W. 86 (1898).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>