<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id651"><amendatorysection statutenumber="24-232" chaptername="Courts"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>24-232</statuteno><catchline>Eviction proceedings; annual report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) On or before January 15, 2022, and July 15, 2022, and on or before each January 15 and July 15 thereafter, the Supreme Court shall electronically submit a report to the Clerk of the Legislature that includes, for the preceding six months the following information pertaining to eviction proceedings, broken down by county:</para><para>(a) The number of eviction proceedings initiated;</para><para>(b) The number of tenants represented by counsel;</para><para>(c) The number of landlords represented by counsel;</para><para>(d) The number of orders granting restitution of the premises entered by default; and</para><para>(e) The number of orders granting restitution of the premises entered, broken down by the specific statutory authority under which possession was sought.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Eviction proceeding means an action involving a claim for forcible entry and detainer involving a residential tenancy under sections 25-21,219 to 25-21,235, the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act, or the Mobile Home Landlord and Tenant Act;</para><para>(b) Landlord includes a landlord as defined in section 76-1410 and a landlord as defined in section 76-1462;</para><para>(c) Residential tenancy means a tenancy subject to the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act or the Mobile Home Landlord and Tenant Act or any other tenancy involving a dwelling unit as defined in section 76-1410;</para><para>(d) Tenant means a tenant or former tenant of a residential tenancy; and</para><para>(e) When reference in this section is made to a definition found in both the Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act and the Mobile Home Landlord and Tenant Act, the definition relevant to the type of tenant at issue applies for purposes of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB320, &#167; 14. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Mobile Home Landlord and Tenant Act,</emphasis> see section 76-1450.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act,</emphasis> see section 76-1401.</para>
    </crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>