<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" id="id42" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="24-230"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>24-230</statuteno><catchline>Judicial hearing officer; appointment
by Supreme Court; powers; qualifications; rights of parties.</catchline><para>(1) The Supreme Court
may appoint judicial hearing officers as needed to serve on a full-time or
part-time basis for county courts sitting as juvenile courts and for separate
juvenile courts. A judicial hearing officer is entitled to receive a salary
as established by the Supreme Court.</para>
<para>(2) In accordance
with the rules of the Supreme Court, a judicial hearing officer may preside
in, hear, and determine any case or proceeding initiated under the Nebraska
Juvenile Code.</para><para>(3) To be qualified for appointment as a judicial hearing officer,
a person shall be an attorney in good standing admitted to the practice of
law in the State of Nebraska and shall meet any other requirements imposed
by the Supreme Court. A judicial hearing officer shall be sworn or affirmed
to faithfully hear and examine the cause and to make a just and true report
according to the best of his or her understanding. The oath or affirmation
may be administered by any judge of the State of Nebraska. A judicial hearing
officer may be removed at any time by the Supreme Court.</para>
<para>(4) In any and
all cases referred to a judicial hearing officer by a county court sitting
as a juvenile court or a separate juvenile court, the parties shall have the
right to take exceptions to the findings and recommendations made by the hearing
officer and to have a further hearing before such court for final disposition.
The court upon receipt of the findings, recommendations, and exceptions shall
review the judicial hearing officer's report and may accept or reject all
or any part of the report and enter judgment based on the court's own determination.</para>
<para>(5) The Supreme
Court shall promulgate rules for all other qualifications of judicial hearing
officers; for the extent of authority which may be assigned and the procedure
for assignment of authority by a county court sitting as a juvenile court
or a separate juvenile court; for practice and procedure before such judicial
hearing officers; and for the training of judicial hearing officers, including
rules for training sessions and continuing education requirements.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB669, &#167; 6.</para><operativedate>August 27, 2011</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>