<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id100" statutenumber="24-703.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>24-703.01</statuteno><catchline>Participation in retirement system; requirements.</catchline><para>No judge shall be authorized to participate in the retirement system provided for in the Judges Retirement Act unless the judge is a United States citizen or is lawfully present in the United States. The court and the judge shall maintain at least one of the following documents, which shall be unexpired if applicable to the particular document or which has an expiration date that has been extended by the United States Department of Homeland Security or the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services so that such document is still valid, to demonstrate United States citizenship or lawful presence in the United States as of the judge's date of hire and produce any such document so maintained upon request of the board or the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems:</para><para>(1) A state-issued driver's license;</para><para>(2) A state-issued identification card;</para><para>(3) A state-issued motor vehicle learner's permit;</para><para>(4) A certified copy of a birth certificate or delayed birth certificate issued in any state, territory, or possession of the United States;</para><para>(5) A Consular Report of Birth Abroad issued by the United States Department of State;</para><para>(6) A United States passport;</para><para>(7) A foreign passport with a United States visa;</para><para>(8) A United States Certificate of Naturalization;</para><para>(9) A United States Certificate of Citizenship;</para><para>(10) A tribal certificate of Native American blood or similar document;</para><para>(11) A United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Employment Authorization Document, Form I-766;</para><para>(12) A United States Citizenship and Immigration Services Permanent Resident Card, Form I-551; or</para><para>(13) Any other document issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security or the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services granting employment authorization in the United States and approved by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB198, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB295, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>