<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id561"><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="24-710.15"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>24-710.15</statuteno><catchline>Judges who became members on and after July 1, 2015; cost-of-living adjustment.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning July 1, 2015, for judges who become members on and after July 1, 2015, if the annual valuation made by the actuary, as approved by the board, indicates that the system is fully funded and has sufficient actuarial surplus to provide for a supplemental lump-sum cost-of-living adjustment, the board may, in its discretion, elect to pay a maximum one and one-half percent supplemental lump-sum cost-of-living adjustment to each retired member or beneficiary based on the retired member's or beneficiary's total monthly benefit through June 30 of the year for which the supplemental lump-sum cost-of-living adjustment is being calculated. The supplemental lump-sum cost-of-living payment shall be paid within sixty days after the board's decision. In no event shall the board declare a supplemental lump-sum cost-of-living adjustment if such adjustment would cause the plan to be less than fully funded.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, fully funded means the unfunded actuarial accrued liability, based on the lesser of the actuarial value and the market value, under the entry age actuarial cost method is less than zero on the most recent actuarial valuation date.</para><para>(3) Any decision or determination by the board to declare or not declare a cost-of-living adjustment or as to whether the annual valuation indicates a sufficient actuarial surplus to provide for a cost-of-living adjustment shall be made in the sole, absolute, and final discretion of the board and shall not be subject to challenge by any member or beneficiary. In no event shall the Legislature be constrained or limited in amending the system notwithstanding the effect of any such change upon the actuarial surplus of the system and the ability of the board to declare future cost-of-living adjustments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB468, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>