<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id13" statutenumber="24-517"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>24-517</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Jurisdiction.</catchline><para>Each county court shall have the following jurisdiction:</para><para>(1) Exclusive original jurisdiction of all matters relating to decedents' estates, including the probate of wills and the construction thereof, except as provided in subsection (c) of section 30-2464 and section 30-2486;</para><para>(2) Exclusive original jurisdiction in all matters relating to the guardianship of a person, except if a separate juvenile court already has jurisdiction over a child in need of a guardian, concurrent original jurisdiction with the separate juvenile court in such guardianship;</para><para>(3) Exclusive original jurisdiction of all matters relating to conservatorship of any person, including (a) original jurisdiction to consent to and authorize a voluntary selection, partition, and setoff of a ward's interest in real estate owned in common with others and to exercise any right of the ward in connection therewith which the ward could exercise if competent and (b) original jurisdiction to license the sale of such real estate for cash or on such terms of credit as shall seem best calculated to produce the highest price subject only to the requirements set forth in section 30-3201;</para><para>(4) Concurrent jurisdiction with the district court to involuntarily partition a ward's interest in real estate owned in common with others;</para><para>(5) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in all civil actions of any type when the amount in controversy is forty-five thousand dollars or less through June 30, 2005, and as set by the Supreme Court pursuant to subdivision (b) of this subdivision on and after July 1, 2005.</para><para>(a) When the pleadings or discovery proceedings in a civil action indicate that the amount in controversy is greater than the jurisdictional amount of subdivision (5) of this section, the county court shall, upon the request of any party, certify the proceedings to the district court as provided in section 25-2706. An award of the county court which is greater than the jurisdictional amount of subdivision (5) of this section is not void or unenforceable because it is greater than such amount, however, if an award of the county court is greater than the jurisdictional amount, the county court shall tax as additional costs the difference between the filing fee in district court and the filing fee in county court.</para><para>(b) The Supreme Court shall adjust the jurisdictional amount for the county court every fifth year commencing July 1, 2005. The adjusted jurisdictional amount shall be equal to the then current jurisdictional amount adjusted by the average percentage change in the unadjusted Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Federal Bureau of Labor Statistics for the five-year period preceding the adjustment date. The jurisdictional amount shall be rounded to the nearest one-thousand-dollar amount;</para><para>(6) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in any criminal matter classified as a misdemeanor or for any infraction. The district court shall have concurrent original jurisdiction in any criminal matter classified as a misdemeanor that arises from the same incident as a charged felony;</para><para>(7) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in domestic relations matters as defined in section 25-2740 and with the district court and separate juvenile court in paternity or custody determinations as provided in section 25-2740;</para><para>(8) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in matters arising under the Nebraska Uniform Trust Code;</para><para>(9) Exclusive original jurisdiction in any action based on violation of a city or village ordinance, except with respect to violations committed by persons under eighteen years of age;</para><para>(10) The jurisdiction of a juvenile court as provided in the Nebraska Juvenile Code when sitting as a juvenile court in counties which have not established separate juvenile courts;</para><para>(11) Exclusive original jurisdiction in matters of adoption, except if a separate juvenile court already has jurisdiction over the child to be adopted, concurrent original jurisdiction with the separate juvenile court;</para><para>(12) Exclusive original jurisdiction in matters arising under the Nebraska Uniform Custodial Trust Act;</para><para>(13) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in any matter relating to a power of attorney and the action or inaction of any agent acting under a power of attorney;</para><para>(14) Exclusive original jurisdiction in any action arising under sections 30-3401 to 30-3432;</para><para>(15) Exclusive original jurisdiction in matters arising under the Nebraska Uniform Transfers to Minors Act;</para><para>(16) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in matters arising under the Uniform Principal and Income Act;</para><para>(17) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in matters arising under the Uniform Testamentary Additions to Trusts Act (1991) except as otherwise provided in subdivision (1) of this section;</para><para>(18) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court to determine contribution rights under section 68-919;</para><para>(19) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the district court in matters arising under the Uniform Community Property Disposition at Death Act except for all matters relating to decedents' estates for which the county court has exclusive original jurisdiction under subdivision (1) of this section; and</para><para>(20) All other jurisdiction heretofore provided and not specifically repealed by Laws 1972, Legislative Bill 1032, and such other jurisdiction as hereafter provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 226, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 96, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 373, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 137, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 529, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1229, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 422, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1296, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 229, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1041, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 269, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 361, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB280, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB314, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB83, &#167; 16. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> see section 43-2,129.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Custodial Trust Act,</emphasis> see section 30-3501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Transfers to Minors Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Trust Code,</emphasis> see section 30-3801.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Community Property Disposition at Death Act,</emphasis> see section 30-4701.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Principal and Income Act,</emphasis> see section 30-3116.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Testamentary Additions to Trusts Act (1991),</emphasis> see section 30-3601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Jurisdiction</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Jurisdiction</emphasis></para><para>Although county courts lack general equity jurisdiction, they may apply equitable principles to matters that are within their exclusive jurisdiction, and subsection (3) of this section empowers county courts to apply equitable principles in matters related to a conservatorship of a person. In re Guardianship & Conservatorship of Maronica B., 314 Neb. 597, 992 N.W.2d 457 (2023).</para>
        
        <para>The purpose of subdivision (11) of this section is to vest jurisdiction over adoption proceedings⁚including paternity determinations⁚with the county court or the separate juvenile court. Peterson v. Jacobitz, 309 Neb. 486, 961 N.W.2d 258 (2021).</para><para>A county court has jurisdiction to construe a power of attorney or review an agent's conduct and grant appropriate relief. In re Estate of Adelung, 306 Neb. 646, 947 N.W.2d 269 (2020).</para><para>County courts have not been given authority to decide motions to transfer to juvenile court in cases in which they lack jurisdiction to try the case. State v. A.D., 305 Neb. 154, 939 N.W.2d 484 (2020).</para><para>The county courts have the power to construe wills. Brinkman v. Brinkman, 302 Neb. 315, 923 N.W.2d 380 (2019).</para><para>Despite the Legislature's grant of exclusive jurisdiction over adoption matters to county or juvenile courts under subsection (11) of this section, the privilege of the writ of habeas corpus is part of Nebraska's organic law. Thus, district courts have general, overlapping jurisdiction over an adoption challenge when a parent claims his or her child is being illegally detained for an adoption in a habeas proceeding. Jesse B. v. Tylee H., 293 Neb. 973, 883 N.W.2d 1 (2016).</para><para>The Legislature cannot limit or take away the broad and general jurisdiction of the district courts, as conferred by the Nebraska Constitution. But it can give county courts concurrent original jurisdiction over the same subject matter. Jesse B. v. Tylee H., 293 Neb. 973, 883 N.W.2d 1 (2016).</para><para>The concurrent, original jurisdiction conferred on a county court under subdivision (7) of this section is more expansive than the jurisdiction conferred by section 25-2740(3) on a county court sitting as a juvenile court or a separate juvenile court. The jurisdiction conferred by section 25-2740(3) is neither exclusive nor original, because the conditions of section 43-2,113 must first be satisfied. Those conditions require a district court to transfer the case to juvenile court and the juvenile court to consent to the transfer. Molczyk v. Molczyk, 285 Neb. 96, 825 N.W.2d 435 (2013).</para><para>In common-law and equity actions relating to decedents' estates, the county courts have concurrent original jurisdiction with the district courts. When the jurisdiction of the county court and the district court is concurrent, the basic principles of judicial administration require that the court which first acquires jurisdiction should retain it to the exclusion of the other court. Washington v. Conley, 273 Neb. 908, 734 N.W.2d 306 (2007).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the county court has exclusive original jurisdiction of all proceedings regarding a decedent's estate. Mischke v. Mischke, 253 Neb. 439, 571 N.W.2d 248 (1997).</para><para>This section does not divest a county court of its subject matter jurisdiction to modify its own void judgments. State v. LeGrand, 249 Neb. 1, 541 N.W.2d 380 (1995).</para><para>Subsection (4) of this section does not vest equity jurisdiction in the county courts. Iodence v. Potmesil, 239 Neb. 387, 476 N.W.2d 554 (1991).</para><para>This section clearly grants county courts jurisdiction over actions involving speeding violations. State v. Jones, 209 Neb. 296, 307 N.W.2d 126 (1981).</para><para>County courts have exclusive original jurisdiction of all matters related to decedents' estates, including the probate of wills and the construction thereof, and all other jurisdiction heretofore provided and not specifically repealed by Laws 1972, L.B. 1032, and such other jurisdiction as thereafter provided by law. County courts, in exercising exclusive original jurisdiction over estates, may apply equitable principles to matters within probate jurisdiction. In re Estate of Layton, 207 Neb. 646, 300 N.W.2d 802 (1981).</para><para>Notwithstanding this section, the district court retains jurisdiction in injunction actions brought to enforce zoning ordinances. Village of Springfield v. Hevelone, 195 Neb. 37, 236 N.W.2d 811 (1975).</para><para>Subdivision (11) of this section vests exclusive original jurisdiction over adoption proceedings in the county courts. Peterson v. Jacobitz, 29 Neb. App. 486, 955 N.W.2d 329 (2021).</para><para>Subdivision (1) of this section gives county courts exclusive original jurisdiction of all matters relating to decedents' estates. In re Estate of Stretesky, 29 Neb. App. 338, 955 N.W.2d 1 (2021).</para><para>Subsection (1) of this section confers upon the county court exclusive original jurisdiction of all matters relating to the decedents' estates, including the probate of wills and the construction thereof, except as provided in sections 30-2464(c) and 30-2486. Lenners v. St. Paul Fire &amp; Marine Ins. Co., 18 Neb. App. 772, 793 N.W.2d 357 (2010).</para><para>This section, combined with sections 25-2740 and 43-247, vests juvenile courts and county courts sitting as juvenile courts with jurisdiction over a custody modification proceeding if the court already has jurisdiction over the juvenile under a separate provision of section 43-247. In re Interest of Ethan M., 18 Neb. App. 63, 774 N.W.2d 766 (2009).</para><para>Jurisdiction over confirmation of arbitration awards is conferred upon the district court, and the county court has no such jurisdiction. MBNA America Bank v. Hansen, 16 Neb. App. 536, 745 N.W.2d 609 (2008).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>A parent can challenge the legality of an adoption by objecting to the proceeding in county court. But seeking a writ of habeas corpus is an equally available remedy for a parent's claim that his or her child is being illegally detained for an adoption. Jesse B. v. Tylee H., 293 Neb. 973, 883 N.W.2d 1 (2016).</para><para>When a district court has exercised jurisdiction over a habeas proceeding to challenge the legality of an adoption before an adoption proceeding is filed in county court, the doctrine of jurisdictional priority requires the district court to retain jurisdiction over the matter to the exclusion of the county court until it determines whether the child is being legally detained for an adoption. Jesse B. v. Tylee H., 293 Neb. 973, 883 N.W.2d 1 (2016).</para><para> Although county courts lack general equity jurisdiction, they may apply equitable principles to matters that are within their exclusive jurisdiction. Thus, when a county court has exclusive jurisdiction over a guardianship case, it can recognize a petitioner's in loco parentis status in determining the petitioner's standing to seek visitation or custody. But it cannot confer permanent in loco parentis status on a petitioner in advance of a custody dispute because the doctrine is transitory. In re Guardianship of Brydon P., 286 Neb. 661, 838 N.W.2d 262 (2013). </para><para>The certification of a civil proceeding, in which the amount in controversy exceeds the statutory limit, is now mandatory only upon the request of a party. Hunt v. Trackwell, 262 Neb. 688, 635 N.W.2d 106 (2001).</para><para>When a claim presented in the manner described in section 30-2486 and within the time limit described in section 30-2485 is disallowed by the personal representative, the dissatisfied claimant may, within 60 days of the mailing of notice of the disallowance, commence a proceeding against the personal representative in the district court insofar as the claim relates to matters within the district court's chancery or common-law jurisdiction. Holdrege Co-op Assn. v. Wilson, 236 Neb. 541, 463 N.W.2d 312 (1990).</para><para>One suing a parent under the family purpose doctrine for damages caused by a member of the family, who was killed in an accident, need not first file a claim in the estate of the decedent. Marcus v. Everett, 195 Neb. 518, 239 N.W.2d 487 (1976).</para><para>In the exercise of its jurisdiction over a custody modification proceeding, a county court sitting as a juvenile court cannot permanently modify child custody through the mere adoption of a case plan pursuant to section 43-285(2). In re Interest of Ethan M., 18 Neb. App. 63, 774 N.W.2d 766 (2009).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>