<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id149" statutenumber="24-1302"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>24-1302</statuteno><catchline id="id152">Problem solving court; establish; Supreme Court; rules; funding, legislative intent; Supreme Court Administrator; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, problem solving court means a drug, veterans, mental health, driving under the influence, reentry, young adult, or other problem solving court.</para><para>(2) A district, county, or juvenile court may establish a problem solving court, subject to the Supreme Court's rules. A problem solving court shall function within the existing structure of the court system. The goals of a problem solving court shall be consistent with any relevant standards adopted by the United States Department of Justice and the National Association of Drug Court Professionals, as such standards existed on January 1, 2023.</para><para>(3) An individual may participate in a problem solving court as a condition of probation, as a sentence imposed by a court, or as otherwise provided by the Supreme Court's rules.</para><para>(4) Problem solving courts shall be subject to rules which shall be promulgated by the Supreme Court for procedures to be implemented in the administration of such courts.</para><para>(5) It is the intent of the Legislature that funds be appropriated separately to the Supreme Court such that each judicial district may operate at least one drug, veterans, mental health, driving under the influence, reentry, and young adult problem solving court. The State Court Administrator shall ensure that each judicial district has at least one of such courts by January 1, 2024.</para><para>(6) The State Court Administrator shall track and evaluate outcomes of problem solving courts. On or before June 1, 2024, and on or before each June 1 thereafter, the State Court Administrator shall electronically submit a report to the Legislature regarding the impact of problem solving courts on recidivism rates in the state. The report shall also include rates of return to court and program completion. The report shall identify judicial districts that are underserved by problem solving courts and what services or funding are needed to properly serve such districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 454, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB919, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB50, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 2, 2023</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>