<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts" statutenumber="24-1104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-1104</statuteno><catchline>Decisions; form; when published.</catchline><para>(1) Decisions of the Court of Appeals shall be in the form of an order which may be accompanied by a memorandum opinion. The memorandum opinion shall not be published unless publication is ordered by the Court of Appeals. All memorandum opinions shall be filed with the Clerk of the Supreme Court, shall be public records, and shall be made available to the public in such manner as may be determined by the Court of Appeals.</para><para>(2) In determining whether to publish a memorandum opinion, the Court of Appeals may take into consideration one or more of the following factors:</para><para>(a) Whether the decision enunciates a new rule of law;</para><para>(b) Whether the decision applies an established rule of law to a factual situation significantly different from that in published opinions;</para><para>(c) Whether the decision resolves or identifies a conflict between prior Court of Appeals decisions;</para><para>(d) Whether the decision will contribute to legal literature by collecting case law or reciting legislative history; and</para><para>(e) Whether the decision involves a case of substantial and continuing public interest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 360, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 462, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1296, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 68, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>This section envisions that decisions of the Court of Appeals be published only in limited circumstances. Metro Renovation v. State, 249 Neb. 337, 543 N.W.2d 715 (1996).</para><para>An opinion of a single judge of the Court of Appeals is not an opinion of the Court of Appeals; thus, this section does not provide the Supreme Court with jurisdiction to order its publication, nor does authority exist for publication absent such an order. State v. Chambers, 242 Neb. 124, 493 N.W.2d 328 (1992).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>