<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts" id="id34" statutenumber="24-1007"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>24-1007</statuteno><catchline id="id37">State Court Administrator;
compile judicial workload statistics;
how; juveniles in Nebraska's
justice system; annual report; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The State Court Administrator
shall compile uniform and accurate statistics which will assist in the evaluation
of judicial workloads. The judicial workload statistics shall be based on
caseload numbers weighted by category of case. The judicial workload statistics
shall be compiled annually for each district, county, and separate juvenile
court judicial district in the state.</para>
<para>(2) The State
Court Administrator shall develop and provide an annual report to the Legislature
and the Governor on juveniles in Nebraska's justice system. The report to
the Legislature shall be provided electronically. For purposes of this section,
juvenile has the same meaning as in section 43-245. The report shall include,
but not be limited to, geographic and demographic information on the following:</para>
<para>(a) Juveniles
prosecuted in juvenile court under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of
section 43-247, including the total number of filings and adjudications;</para>
<para>(b) Juveniles
prosecuted in adult criminal court for felonies, misdemeanors, and traffic
offenses. The information shall include juveniles sentenced to terms in adult
jails and prisons and juveniles placed on adult probation;</para>
<para>(c) The number
of motions to transfer and the number of cases transferred to adult court
from juvenile court and from adult criminal court to juvenile court;</para>
<para>(d) Juveniles
placed on juvenile probation, the number of juveniles on probation in out-of-home
care, the number of juveniles completing probation, the number of motions
to revoke probation and probation revocations, and the average length of time
on probation;</para><para>(e) Juveniles with and without access to counsel in juvenile and
adult court, both appointed and retained; and</para><para>(f) Rates of recidivism.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 189, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>