<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Fire Companies And Firefighters" statutenumber="35-517" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>35-517</statuteno><catchline id="id00">District; boundaries; county board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The county board shall set the boundaries of all rural or suburban fire protection districts in the county so that all areas within the county which are not within the incorporated areas of cities and villages are included within a rural or suburban fire protection district.</para><para>(2) By July 1 of the year following the dissolution of any rural or suburban fire protection district, the county board shall set the boundaries of all remaining rural and suburban fire protection districts so that all areas within the county which are not within the incorporated areas of cities and villages are included within a rural or suburban fire protection district.</para><para>(3) Any county may set the boundaries of all rural and suburban fire protection districts which have the greatest portion of their valuation in such county so that the highest levy of a rural or suburban fire protection district is no more than two times the average levy of all rural and suburban fire protection districts which have the greatest portion of their valuation in such county based on the property tax request or levy and associated valuation for the current fiscal year. For purposes of this subsection, each county shall examine the property tax request or levy of each rural or suburban fire protection district in the county for all purposes except bonded indebtedness for the current fiscal year and lease-purchase contracts in existence on July 1, 1998, as compared to the valuation for the tax year against which the levy was imposed. If one or more fire protection districts do not meet the standard required by this subsection for the current year, boundaries may be relocated to place more valuation in the high levy districts and less in the low levy districts so that the standard is met. If any district is to be eliminated by the county to meet the standard, the property tax request or levy for the current fiscal year will be assumed to be transferred to the other districts which are to be in the territory of the eliminated district in proportion to the valuation transferred to such districts for purposes of compliance with the standard, the district shall be deemed to be dissolved, and the obligations and assets of the district shall be disposed of as provided in section 35-521. For purposes of this subsection, the average levy of all rural and suburban fire protection districts means the total taxes levied by all rural and suburban fire protection districts in a county which have the greatest portion of their valuation in such county divided by the total taxable valuation of all such districts.</para><para>(4) Before May 1 of the year in which any change in boundaries allowed or required under this section is to be effective, the county board shall forthwith designate a time and place for a hearing before the county board of such county and shall give due notice thereof in the manner prescribed by section 35-514. The hearing shall be prior to June 1. At the time and place so fixed the county board shall meet and all persons interested shall have opportunity to be heard. Thereupon, the county board shall consider the general rural fire protection policy for the county as a whole and shall determine the boundaries of the district or districts, whether as existing prior to such determination or otherwise, and shall make a written order of such determination which shall be filed in the office of the county clerk by July 1 of the year in which any change in boundaries under this section is to be effective. If all rural and suburban fire protection districts in a county which have the greatest portion of their valuation in such county agree to a change in boundaries and submit a proposal to change boundaries to the county board prior to the hearing, the county shall adopt the proposal unless it finds that the proposal is not consistent with the fire protection policy in the county as a whole or does not result in levies which comply with the standard described in this section. Thereafter, such reorganized district or districts shall be deemed to be organized and operating under sections 35-501 to 35-517. Nothing herein contained shall impair, affect, or discharge any previously existing contract, obligation, lien, or charge of the district or districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 98, &#167; 17, p. 270; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 589, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1120, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB325, &#167; 6. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>