<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Fire Companies and Firefighters" id="id19" statutenumber="35-901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id21">35-901</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Volunteer departments;
trust fund; established; use; public funds; restrictions; express authorization
required; when; section, how construed; expenditures of public funds; procedure;
gambling money; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section,
volunteer department shall mean volunteer fire department or volunteer first-aid,
rescue, or emergency squad or volunteer fire company serving any city, village,
county, township, or rural or suburban fire protection district.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, each volunteer
department may establish a volunteer department trust fund. All general donations
or contributions, bequests, or annuities made to the volunteer department
and all money raised by or for the volunteer department shall be deposited
in the trust fund. The trust fund shall be under the control of the volunteer
department, and the volunteer department may make expenditures from the trust
fund as it deems necessary. The treasurer of the volunteer department shall
be the custodian of the trust fund.</para>
<para>(3) The trust fund shall not be considered public funds or funds of
any city, village, county, township, or rural or suburban fire protection
district for any purpose, including the Nebraska Budget Act, nor shall any
city, village, county, township, or rural or suburban fire protection district
incur any liability solely by reason of any expenditure from such fund except
liability for property when any city, village, county, township, or rural
or suburban fire protection district receives title to property acquired with
money from such fund.</para>
<para>(4)(a) If the total amount of expenditures and receipts in the trust
fund exceeds one hundred thousand dollars in any twelve-month period, the
volunteer department shall inform any city, village, county, township, or
rural or suburban fire protection district receiving service from the department
and such entity may examine or cause to be examined all books, accounts, vouchers,
records, and expenditures with regard to the trust fund.</para>
<para>(b) Funds, fees, or charges solicited, collected, or received by a volunteer
department that are (i) in consequence of the performance of fire or rescue
services by the volunteer department at a given place and time, (ii) accomplished
through the use by the volunteer department of equipment owned by the taxing
authority supporting such department and provided to the volunteer department
for that purpose, and (iii) paid by or on behalf of the recipient of those
services shall not be deposited in a trust fund authorized by this section.
Such funds are public funds of the taxing authority supporting the volunteer
department and are deemed to have been collected by the volunteer department
as the agent of the taxing authority and are held by the department on its
behalf. If such funds are in the possession of a volunteer department, the
taxing authority shall cause all the books, accounts, records, vouchers, expenditures,
and statements regarding such funds to be examined and independently audited
at the expense of the taxing authority by a qualified professional auditor
or the Auditor of Public Accounts for the immediately preceding five years.</para>
<para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed or deemed to permit a
violation of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act.</para>
<para>(6) All expenditures of public funds as defined in the Nebraska Budget
Act for support of a volunteer department or its purposes shall be submitted
as claims, approved by the taxing authority supporting such department or
its purposes, and published as required by law. All such claims shall be properly
itemized for proposed expenditure or reimbursement for costs already incurred
and paid except as may be otherwise permitted pursuant to section 35-106.</para>
<para>(7) All money raised pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska
Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, and the Nebraska
Small Lottery and Raffle Act shall be subject to such acts with respect to
the deposit and expenditure of such money.</para>
<para>(8) No volunteer department shall solicit, charge, or collect any funds,
fees, or charges as described in subdivision (4)(b) of this section without
the express authorization of the taxing authority supporting the department
by vote of a majority of the members of the governing body of such taxing
authority. Such authorization shall not extend beyond a twelve-month period
but may be renewed at the discretion of the taxing authority in the same manner
in which it was initially granted. Upon collection or receipt, such funds,
fees, or charges shall be remitted to the designated officer of the taxing
authority for deposit to the account of the taxing authority.</para>
<para>(9) Funds, fees, or charges as described
in subdivision (4)(b) of this section which are in the possession of the taxing
authority shall be expended by such taxing authority solely (a) for the support
of the emergency response activities of the volunteer department which gave
rise to those funds, fees, or charges, (b) for charges directly related to
the collection of those funds, fees, or charges, or (c) for the support of a service
award benefit program adopted and conducted pursuant to the Volunteer Emergency
Responders Recruitment and Retention Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 516, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1096, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB522, &#167;  1.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Budget Act,</emphasis> see section 13-501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para><para><emphasis>Volunteer Emergency Responders Recruitment and Retention Act,</emphasis> see section 35-1301.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>