<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Fire Companies And Firefighters" statutenumber="35-509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>35-509</statuteno><catchline>District; budget; tax to support; limitation; how levied; county treasurer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The board of directors shall have the power and duty to determine a general fire protection and rescue policy for the district and shall annually fix the amount of money for the proposed budget statement as may be deemed sufficient and necessary in carrying out such contemplated program for the ensuing fiscal year, including the amount of principal and interest upon the indebtedness of the district for the ensuing year.</para><para>(2)(a) For any rural or suburban fire protection district that has levy authority pursuant to subsection (10) of section 77-3442, after the adoption of the budget statement, the president and secretary of the district shall certify the amount of tax to be levied which the district requires for the adopted budget statement for the ensuing year to the proper county clerk or county clerks on or before September 30 of each year. The county board shall levy a tax not to exceed ten and one-half cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such district for the maintenance of the fire protection district for the fiscal year, plus such levy as is authorized to be made under subdivision (13)(a) of section 35-508, all such levies being subject to subsection (10) of section 77-3442. The tax shall be collected as other taxes are collected in the county, deposited with the county treasurer, and placed to the credit of the rural or suburban fire protection district so authorizing the same on or before the fifteenth day of each month or more frequently as provided in section 77-1759 or be remitted to the county treasurer of the county in which the greatest portion of the valuation of the district is located as is provided for by subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(b) For any rural or suburban fire protection district that does not have levy authority pursuant to subsection (10) of section 77-3442, after the adoption of the budget statement, the president and secretary of the district shall request the amount of tax to be levied which the district requires for the adopted budget statement for the ensuing year to the proper county clerk or county clerks on or before August 1 of each year pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-3443. The county board shall levy a tax not to exceed ten and one-half cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such district for the maintenance of the fire protection district for the fiscal year, plus such levy as is authorized to be made under subdivision (13)(b) of section 35-508, all such levies being subject to section 77-3443. The tax shall be collected as other taxes are collected in the county, deposited with the county treasurer, and placed to the credit of the rural or suburban fire protection district so authorizing the same on or before the fifteenth day of each month or more frequently as provided in section 77-1759 or be remitted to the county treasurer of the county in which the greatest portion of the valuation of the district is located as is provided for by subsection (3) of this section. For purposes of section 77-3443, the county board of the county in which the greatest portion of the valuation of the district is located shall approve the levy.</para><para>(3) All such taxes collected or received for the district by the treasurer of any other county than the one in which the greatest portion of the valuation of the district is located shall be remitted to the treasurer of the county in which the greatest portion of the valuation of the district is located at least quarterly. All such taxes collected or received shall be placed to the credit of such district in the treasury of the county in which the greatest portion of the valuation of the district is located.</para><para>(4) In no case shall the amount of tax levy exceed the amount of funds to be received from taxation according to the adopted budget statement of the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1939, c. 38, &#167; 5, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 35-605; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 35-405; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 128, &#167; 1, p. 368; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 98, &#167; 9, p. 266; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 383; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 287, &#167; 54, p. 962; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 127, &#167; 1, p. 360; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 128, &#167; 4, p. 365; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 34, p. 693; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 849, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 375, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 150; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 918, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1120, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB325, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB63, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB644, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>