<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fire Companies And Firefighters" statutenumber="35-502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>35-502</statuteno><catchline>District; organization; conversion from rural to suburban fire protection district; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) In order to provide for the protection of lives and property in rural and suburban areas against loss or damage by fire, more than fifty percent of the registered voters residing in the following are hereby authorized and empowered to initiate the formation of rural or suburban fire protection districts under the conditions specified in this section:</para><para>(a)(i) Any territory in the State of Nebraska equivalent in area to one township or more which is situated outside the corporate limits of any city or village; or</para><para>(ii) Any area of less than one township which is surrounded by rural or suburban fire protection districts; or</para><para>(b) Any area situated in the State of Nebraska outside the corporate limits of any city or village in which there are at least two hundred homes and which has a taxable valuation of at least two million eight hundred sixty thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) Such districts shall be organized in the manner provided by sections 35-501 to 35-517. If the district is organized in an area set forth in subdivision (1)(a) of this section, it shall be a rural fire protection district and references in such sections to rural fire protection districts shall refer to such a district. If the district is organized in an area set forth in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, it shall be a suburban fire protection district and references in such sections to a suburban fire protection district shall refer to such a district. Unless the context indicates otherwise, district, when used in such sections, shall refer to either a rural or suburban fire protection district, as the case may be.</para><para>(3) Any rural fire protection district which has been duly organized under Chapter 35, which has within its boundaries at least two hundred homes, and which has a taxable valuation of at least two million eight hundred sixty thousand dollars is hereby authorized and empowered to convert to a suburban fire protection district in the manner provided by section 35-519.</para><para>(4) Beginning July 1, 1998, no new rural or suburban fire protection district shall be formed except by merger or reorganization of two or more existing rural or suburban fire protection districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1939, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 192; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 35-601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 35-401; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 98, &#167; 2, p. 262; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 128, &#167; 2, p. 363; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 144, &#167; 1, p. 554; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 849, &#167; 1; <para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 148; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 918, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 129; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1120, &#167; 8. </para></source><annotation><para>Organization of rural fire protection district may be collaterally attacked when defects complained of are jurisdictional. Kelle v. Crab Orchard Rural Fire Protection Dist., 164 Neb. 593, 83 N.W.2d 51 (1957).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>