<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Fire Companies And Firefighters" statutenumber="35-506" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>35-506</statuteno><catchline>District; vote on organization; officers; terms; compensation.</catchline><para>(1) After formation of a district by merger or reorganization under section 35-517, at the time and place fixed by the county board for public hearing as provided in section 35-514, the registered voters who are residing within the boundaries of the district shall have the opportunity to decide by majority vote of those present whether the organization of the district shall be completed. Permanent organization shall be effected by the election of a board of directors consisting of five residents of the district. Such directors shall at the first regular meeting after their election select from the board a president, a vice president, and a secretary-treasurer who shall serve as the officers of the board of directors for one year. The board shall reorganize itself annually. The elected member of the board of directors receiving the highest number of votes in the election shall preside over the first regular meeting until the officers of such board have been selected. The three members receiving the highest number of votes shall serve for a term of four years and the other two members for a term of two years; and this provision shall apply to directors elected at the organizational meeting of the district.</para><para>(2) The board shall reorganize itself annually. Election of directors of existing districts shall be held by the registered voters present at the regular annual meeting provided for in section 35-507 which is held in the calendar year during which the terms of directors are scheduled to expire. As the terms of these members expire, their successors shall be elected for four years and hold office until their successors have been elected. If the district contains more than one township, each township may be represented on the board of directors unless there are more than five townships within the district, and in such event there shall be only five directors on the board and no township shall have more than one member elected to such board of directors. In case of a vacancy on account of resignation, death, malfeasance, or nonfeasance of a member, the remaining members of the board shall fill the vacancy for the unexpired term. The person appointed to fill the vacancy shall be from the same area as the person whose office is vacated, if possible, otherwise from the district at large.</para><para>(3) The members of the board of directors of a rural or suburban fire protection district may receive up to fifty dollars for each meeting of the board, but not to exceed twelve meetings in any calendar year, and reimbursement for any actual expenses necessarily incurred as a direct result of their responsibilities and duties as members of the board engaged upon the business of the district. When it is necessary for any member of the board of directors to travel on business of the district and to attend meetings of the district, he or she shall be allowed mileage at the rate provided in section 81-1176 for each mile actually and necessarily traveled.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1939, c. 38, &#167; 4, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 35-604; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 35-404; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 98, &#167; 6, p. 264; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 208, &#167; 1, p. 567; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 283, &#167; 1, p. 1051; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 257, &#167; 36, p. 950; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 756, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1120, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB63, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>