<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Fire Companies and Firefighters" statutenumber="35-518"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>35-518</statuteno><catchline>District; contract for protection with counties of adjoining state; terms; damages.</catchline><para>Any rural or suburban fire protection district may enter into contracts on an annual or other basis with any rural fire protection district of an adjoining county or counties of another state having a general fire protection program or firefighting equipment under the control of the fire protection district for the fire protection services or fire protection cooperation. All such contracts shall be upon terms suitable to all concerned. The terms and conditions upon and in compliance with which each district is to cooperate in furnishing, maintaining, and operating fire equipment for outside aid, mutual aid, or making payment for such service shall be expressly stipulated. The secretary-treasurer of the fire protection district is authorized to pay over money to the treasurer or other proper officer of the fire protection district in an adjoining state authorized to receive the same in accordance with the terms of the contract and upon the order of the board of directors. Any fire protection district, department, company, or firefighters answering any fire alarm or performing fire prevention services or rescue, resuscitation, first-aid, inspection, or any other official work outside its state and within a rural or suburban fire protection district organized under the provisions of Chapter 35, article 5, shall be considered an agent of the rural or suburban fire protection district located in the State of Nebraska, and acting solely and alone in a governmental capacity, and such rural or suburban fire protection district located in another state shall not be liable in damages for any act of commission, omission, or negligence while answering or returning from any fire, or reported fire, or doing or performing any fire prevention work or rescue, resuscitation, first-aid, inspection, or other official work.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 128, &#167; 13, p. 372; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 102. </para></source></law></legaldoc>