<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Fire Companies And Firefighters" statutenumber="35-1313"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>35-1313</statuteno><catchline>Service award benefits; payment upon military service, disability, or death.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Service award benefits may be paid to a participant as provided in subsection (1) of section 35-1312 notwithstanding that such participant has not been an active emergency responder, active rescue squad member, or active volunteer firefighter for the specified years of service if in the years of service in which such participant did not qualify such failure was due (i) to a period during a year of service in the armed forces of the United States upon active duty or (ii) to an injury or disability incurred by the participant and directly related to the participant's duties or activities as a volunteer member of the volunteer department.</para><para>(b) Upon the completion of the specified years of service pursuant to this subsection, the participant shall have a nonforfeitable interest in the annual accounts of all years of service in which such participant is listed on the certification list. Such interest is equivalent to a proportionate equal share with all other participants listed on the certification list for a year of service in (i) the principal amount of all contributions deposited into the annual account for such year of service and (ii) all income derived therefrom.</para><para>(2) Service award benefits shall be paid to a participant as provided in subsection (1) of section 35-1312 notwithstanding that such participant had not been an active emergency responder, active rescue squad member, or active volunteer firefighter for the specified years of service if such participant suffered a permanent disability resulting from an injury incurred by the participant and directly related to the participant's duties or activities as a volunteer member of the volunteer department which disqualified the participant from further service as a volunteer. At the time such disability is confirmed and certified to the governing body of the city, village, or rural or suburban fire protection district conducting the service award benefit program, the participant shall have a nonforfeitable interest in the annual accounts of all years of service in which such participant is listed on the certification list. Such interest is equivalent to a proportionate equal share with all other participants listed on the certification list for a year of service in (a) the principal amount of all contributions deposited into the annual account for such year of service and (b) all income derived therefrom.</para><para>(3) Service award benefits shall be paid to the beneficiary of a participant notwithstanding that such participant has not been an active emergency responder, active rescue squad member, or active volunteer firefighter for the specified years of service if such participant dies in the course of his or her active service as a volunteer member of a volunteer department or dies as the result of injuries incurred by the participant directly related to his or her duties or activities as a volunteer member of a volunteer department. At the time of the participant's death, the beneficiary of the participant shall have a nonforfeitable interest in the annual accounts of all years of service in which the participant is listed on the certification list. Such interest is equivalent to a proportionate equal share with all other participants listed on the certification list for a year of service in (a) the principal amount of all contributions deposited into the annual account for such year of service and (b) all income derived therefrom.</para><para>(4) Service award benefits shall be paid to the beneficiary of a participant upon the death of a participant notwithstanding that such participant had not reached the age of sixty-five if such participant would have been entitled to receive service award benefits at age sixty-five pursuant to subsection (1) of section 35-1312 or subsection (1) or (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 849, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 808, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>