<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Culture And History" statutenumber="82-101" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>82-101</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska State Historical Society; state agency; Director of the Nebraska State Historical Society; appointment; board of trustees; membership in society; purpose; acceptance of gifts; operation of historical sites and museums.</catchline><para>The Nebraska State Historical Society, operated in the public interest since 1878, is hereby declared to be and does hereby consent to be a state agency on and after July 16, 1994. The society shall hold, in trust for the people of the State of Nebraska, all of the society's present and future collections of property. The Governor shall appoint the Director of the Nebraska State Historical Society subject to approval by the Legislature. The Director of the Nebraska State Historical Society shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor. The agency shall be under the direction of such director. A board of trustees, who shall be elected in part by the members of the society and in part appointed by the Governor as provided in section 82-101.01, shall advise the director and perform other duties specified in statute. Membership in the society shall be open to all persons interested in the accomplishment of the purposes of the society. In addition to all other objects and purposes provided by law, the object of the society shall be to promote historical knowledge and research, awaken public interest, and popularize historical study throughout the state in a nonpolitical manner. The society's headquarters and museum in Lincoln shall be used by the society for the preservation, care, research, and exhibition of and research into documents, books, newspapers, weapons, tools, pictures, relics, scientific specimens, farm and factory products, and all other collections pertaining to the history of the world, particularly to that of Nebraska and the West. The society shall have the power to accept gifts and to own, control, and dispose of property, real and personal. It shall, either alone or in cooperation with other agencies, operate historical sites and museums as agreed to with appropriate state agencies or as directed by the Governor and the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1883, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 340; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 146, &#167; 1, p. 458; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7166; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6817; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 82-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 82-101; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 438, &#167; 1, p. 1356; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1236, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1169, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>