<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Culture And History" id="id00" statutenumber="82-129"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>82-129</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Nebraska State Historical Society; transfer property to Willa Cather Foundation.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) In 1978, the Nebraska State Historical Society acquired, without cost to the state, clear title in the name of the State of Nebraska to the real and personal property as described in section 82-130 of the Willa Cather Pioneer Memorial and Educational Foundation, now known as the Willa Cather Foundation, except the foundation's trust account and investments which are retained by the foundation. The Nebraska State Historical Society may enter into agreements with the foundation for the operation of the Willa Cather Center and for the real property owned by the State of Nebraska, but the society shall be responsible for the general administration and continued maintenance of such property and may accept gifts, grants, and bequests for such purposes.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska State Historical Society may enter into an agreement with the Willa Cather Foundation to transfer clear title of any properties described in section 82-130 from the State of Nebraska to the Willa Cather Foundation at no cost to either the society or foundation other than any property transfer transactional costs to be shared equally by the parties.</para><para>(3) In order to carry out any agreements made according to subsection (2) of this section, the Nebraska State Historical Society may dispose of these real properties using the vacant building and excess land process under sections 72-811 to 72-818.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 567, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB379, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>