<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Culture and History" statutenumber="82-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>82-503</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Archaeological Resources Preservation Act:</para><para>(1) Archaeological resource means any material object of past human life or activities that is of archaeological interest. Such objects include, but are not limited to, pottery, basketry, bottles, weapons, tools, structures or portions of structures, dwellings, rock paintings, rock carvings, intaglios, graves, human skeletal materials, or any portion or piece of any of such items. Nonfossilized and fossilized paleontological specimens, or any portion or piece thereof, shall not be considered archaeological resources unless found in an archaeological context. No object shall be treated as an archaeological resource under this subdivision unless such object is determined to be at least fifty years of age;</para><para>(2) Archaeological site means a place or location where archaeological resources are found;</para><para>(3) Master archaeological site file means the records inventory of all known Nebraska archaeological sites maintained by the Nebraska State Historical Society;</para><para>(4) National Register of Historic Places means the register of districts, sites, buildings, structures, and objects significant in American history, architecture, archaeology, engineering, and culture, maintained by the Secretary of the Interior under the authority of the federal Historic Sites, Buildings, and Antiquities Act, 16 U.S.C. 462(b), and the National Historic Preservation Act, 16 U.S.C. 470a(a)(1)(A);</para><para>(5) State agency means any division, department, board, bureau, commission, or agency of the State of Nebraska; and</para><para>(6) Undertaking means a project, activity, or program funded in whole or in part under the jurisdiction of a state agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 211, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>