<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Culture And History" id="id83" statutenumber="82-331"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>82-331</statuteno><catchline id="id86">Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby established in the state treasury a trust fund to be known as the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund. The fund shall consist of funds appropriated or transferred by the Legislature, and only the earnings of the fund may be used as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) On August 1, 1998, the State Treasurer shall transfer five million dollars from the General Fund to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, it is the intent of the Legislature that the State Treasurer shall transfer (a) an amount not to exceed one million dollars from the General Fund to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund on December 31, 2013, (b) an amount not to exceed five hundred thousand dollars from the General Fund to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund on December 31, 2014, (c) an amount not to exceed seven hundred fifty thousand dollars from the General Fund to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund on December 31 of 2015 and 2016, and (d) an amount not to exceed five hundred thousand dollars from the General Fund to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund annually on December 31 beginning in 2019 and continuing through December 31, 2028.</para><para>(4) Prior to the transfer of funds from any state account into the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund, the Nebraska Arts Council shall provide documentation to the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services that qualified endowments have generated a dollar-for-dollar match of new money, up to the amount of state funds authorized by the Legislature to be transferred to the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund. For purposes of this section, new money means a contribution to a qualified endowment generated after July 1, 2011. Contributions not fully matched by state funds shall be carried forward to succeeding years and remain available to provide a dollar-for-dollar match for state funds. For an endowment to be a qualified endowment (a) the endowment must meet the standards set by the Nebraska Arts Council or Nebraska Humanities Council, (b) the endowment must be intended for long-term stabilization of the organization, and (c) the funds of the endowment must be endowed and only the earnings thereon expended. The budget division of the Department of Administrative Services shall notify the State Treasurer to execute a transfer of state funds up to the amount specified by the Legislature, but only to the extent that the Nebraska Arts Council has provided documentation of a dollar-for-dollar match. State funds not transferred shall be carried forward to the succeeding year and be added to the funds authorized for a dollar-for-dollar match during that year.</para><para>(5) The Legislature shall not appropriate or transfer money from the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund for any purpose other than the purposes stated in sections 82-330 to 82-333, except that the Legislature may appropriate or transfer money from the fund upon a finding that the purposes of such sections are not being accomplished by the fund.</para><para>(6) Any money in the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(7) All investment earnings from the Nebraska Cultural Preservation Endowment Fund shall be credited to the Nebraska Arts and Humanities Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 799, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1165, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB316, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1063, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB969, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 55. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>