<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id356"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Culture and History" statutenumber="82-703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>82-703</statuteno><catchline>Willa Cather National Statuary Hall Selection Committee; created; members; duties; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The Willa Cather National Statuary Hall Selection Committee is created. The committee shall consist of members of the Nebraska Hall of Fame Commission created pursuant to section 72-724.</para><para>(2) Upon approval by the Joint Committee on the Library of Congress and pursuant to the agreement described in section 82-702, the Willa Cather National Statuary Hall Selection Committee shall:</para><para>(a) Select a sculptor to create a statue of Willa Cather to be placed in the National Statuary Hall and review and approve the plans for the statue; and</para><para>(b) Identify a method to obtain necessary funding to pay for all of the following. All funds shall be privately donated and separately managed. No state funds shall be expended for such purposes:</para><para>(i) The sculptor for designing and carving or casting the statue;</para><para>(ii) The design and fabrication of the pedestal;</para><para>(iii) The transportation of the statue and pedestal to the United States Capitol;</para><para>(iv) The removal and transportation of the replaced statue;</para><para>(v) The temporary placement of the new statue in the Rotunda of the United States Capitol for the unveiling ceremony;</para><para>(vi) The unveiling ceremony; and</para><para>(vii) Any other expenses that the committee determines are necessary to incur.</para><para>(3) The committee has the authority to receive and disburse gifts.</para><para>(4) The committee shall execute the requirements of this section no later than June 30, 2023.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB807, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>