<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Culture And History" statutenumber="82-118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>82-118</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska State Historical Society; statewide historic survey; acceptance of federal act.</catchline><para>The State of Nebraska hereby assents to the provisions of an Act of Congress entitled An Act to establish a program for the preservation of additional historic properties throughout the Nation, and for other purposes, approved October 15, 1966, Public Law 89-665, 89th Congress, as amended as of January 1, 1993. The Nebraska State Historical Society shall perform all such acts as may be necessary on behalf of the State of Nebraska to conduct, coordinate, and carry out the purposes and objectives of such Act of Congress, as amended as of January 1, 1993, for and within the State of Nebraska. The society shall carry out a comprehensive statewide historic survey in accordance with criteria established by the Secretary of the Interior for the preservation, acquisition, and development of such property as provided in the Act of Congress, as amended as of January 1, 1993, and may transfer funds made available to the state to other state agencies, local governments, other public bodies, private organizations, and individuals for the acquisition of title or interests in and for the development of any district, site, building, structure, or object that is significant in American history, architecture, archeology, and culture, or property used in connection therewith, and for its development in order to assure the preservation for public benefit of any such historic properties in compliance with such Act of Congress, as amended as of January 1, 1993, and with rules and regulations promulgated by the Secretary of the Interior for the administration of such Act of Congress, as amended as of January 1, 1993. For these purposes the society may inspect the projects and examine the records of those projects eligible for grants and establish such rules and regulations relating thereto as may be necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 596, &#167; 1, p. 2032; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 628, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 407, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 682, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>