<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-111"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>17-111</statuteno><catchline>Mayor; ordinances; veto power; passage
over veto.</catchline><para>The mayor shall have power to veto or sign any
ordinance passed by the city council and
to approve or veto any order, bylaw, resolution, award of or vote to enter
into any contract, or the allowance of any claim. If the mayor approves the
ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution, contract, or claim, he or she shall sign
it, and it shall become effective. If the mayor vetoes the ordinance, order,
bylaw, resolution, contract, or any item or items of appropriations or claims,
he or she shall return it to the city council stating that the measure is
vetoed. The mayor may issue the veto at the meeting at which the measure passed
or within seven calendar days after the meeting. If the mayor issues the veto
after the meeting, the mayor shall notify the city clerk of the veto in writing.
The clerk shall notify the city council in writing of the mayor's veto. Any ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution, award of or
vote to enter into any contract, or the allowance of any claim vetoed
by the mayor may be passed over his or
her veto by a vote of two-thirds of the members of the council.
If the mayor neglects or refuses to sign any ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution, award of or vote to enter into
any contract, or the allowance of any claim, but fails to veto the measure
within the time required by this section, the measure shall
become effective without his or her signature. The mayor may veto any item or items
of any appropriation bill or any claims bill, and approve the remainder thereof,
and the item or items vetoed may be passed by the council over the veto as
in other cases.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 11, p. 195; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5003; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4172; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-111; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-111; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB803, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>Mayor's approval may be condition precedent to the validity of the ordinance by its terms, and failure of such approval during mayor's incumbency renders ordinance void. Rooney v. City of South Sioux City, 111 Neb. 1, 195 N.W. 474 (1923).</para><para>Where an ordinance or resolution is passed either with or without the mayor's concurrence, he, being the executive officer, is obliged to execute the duties therein contained irrespective of his sanction or disapproval thereof. State ex rel. Fuller v. Martin, 27 Neb. 441, 43 N.W. 244 (1889).</para><para>The duty of the mayor is to guard and protect the rights of the city. Greenwood v. Cobbey, 26 Neb. 449, 42 N.W. 413 (1889).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>