<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-530" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-530</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Waterworks; franchises; terms.</catchline><para id="id00">Cities of the second class and villages shall have power to make contracts with and authorize any person, company, or corporation to erect and maintain a system of waterworks and water supply, and to give such contractors the exclusive privilege for a term not exceeding twenty-five years to lay down in the streets and alleys of such city or village water mains and supply pipes, and to furnish water to such city or village, and the residents of such cities or villages, under such regulations as to price, supply, and rent of water meters, as the city council or village board of trustees may from time to time prescribe by ordinance for the protection of the city or village. The right to supervise and control such person, company, or corporation shall not be waived or set aside.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 23, &#167; 8, XV, p. 176; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 20, &#167; 1, XV, p. 167; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 12, &#167; 1, XV, p. 295; </para><para>Laws 1893, c. 8, &#167; 1, p. 133; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 250; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 30, &#167; 1, p. 256; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 126; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5119; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 103, &#167; 1, p. 271; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 46, &#167; 2, p. 131; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 48, &#167; 1, p. 137; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 52, &#167; 1, p. 150; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4292; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 41, &#167; 1, p. 157; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-441; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 141; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-441; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-530; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 156. </para></source><annotation><para>An ordinance, contracting for supply of water and payment therefor with private water company, is valid even though not preceded by an appropriation to meet such water rentals. City of North Platte v. North Platte Water-Works Co., 56 Neb. 403, 76 N.W. 906 (1898).</para><para>City of second class is authorized to contract with third persons to erect and maintain a system of waterworks to supply water. North Platte Water-Works Company v. City of North Platte, 50 Neb. 853, 70 N.W. 393 (1897).</para><para>An agreement to rent more hydrants than the assessed valuation of property in a municipality will justify does not affect the validity of contract to erect and maintain a waterworks system. State ex rel. Tarr v. City of Crete, 32 Neb. 568, 49 N.W. 272 (1891).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>