<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Second Class and Villages" statutenumber="17-958"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-958</statuteno><catchline>Cold storage plants; bonds; approval of electors; interest; redemption.</catchline><para>The question of issuing bonds for any purpose contemplated by sections 17-956 to 17-960 shall be submitted to the electors at any election held for that purpose after not less than thirty days' notice has been given by publication in some legal newspaper published in and of general circulation in such municipality or, if no legal newspaper is published therein, by publication in some legal newspaper published in the county in which such city or village is located. If there is no legal newspaper published in the county wherein such city or village is located, the publication shall be in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the county. Such bonds may be issued only when a majority of the electors voting on the question favor their issuance. They shall bear interest, payable annually or semiannually, and shall be payable any time the municipality may determine at the time of their issuance but in not more than twenty years after their issuance. The aggregate amount of bonds that may be issued for the construction or purchase of a cold storage or refrigeration plant shall not exceed five percent of the taxable valuation of all the property in such city or village subject to taxation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 24, &#167; 3, p. 118; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-803; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-958; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 58, p. 308; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 534, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 64. </para></source></law></legaldoc>