<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-555" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-555</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Streets and sidewalks; removal of obstructions; trees; declaration of nuisance; procedure; special assessment.</catchline><para>(1) Cities of the second class or villages may remove all obstructions from sidewalks, curbstones, gutters, and crosswalks at the expense of the person placing them there or at the expense of the city or village and require and regulate the planting and protection of shade trees in and along the streets and the trimming and removing of such trees.</para><para>(2) Cities of the second class or villages may by ordinance declare it to be a nuisance for a property owner to permit, allow, or maintain any dead or diseased trees within the right-of-way of streets within the corporate limits or within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of the city or village. Notice to abate and remove such nuisance and notice of the right to a hearing and the manner in which it may be requested shall be given to each owner or owner's duly authorized agent and to the occupant, if any. The city or village shall establish the method of notice by ordinance. If notice is given by first-class mail, such mail shall be conspicuously marked as to its importance. Within five days after receipt of such notice, the owner or occupant of the lot or piece of ground may request a hearing with the city or village to appeal the decision to abate or remove the nuisance by filing a written appeal with the office of the city clerk or village clerk. A hearing on the appeal shall be held within fourteen days after the filing of the appeal and shall be conducted by an elected or appointed officer as designated in the ordinance. The hearing officer shall render a decision on the appeal within five business days after the conclusion of the hearing. If the appeal fails, the city or village may have the work done to abate and remove the dead or diseased trees. If the owner or occupant of the lot or piece of ground does not request a hearing with the city or village within five days after receipt of such notice or fails to comply with the order to abate and remove the nuisance, the city or village may have such work done. The city or village may levy and assess all or any portion of the costs and expenses of the work upon the lot or piece of ground so benefited as a special assessment.</para><para>(3) Cities of the second class or villages may regulate the building of bulkheads, cellar and basement ways, stairways, railways, windows, doorways, awnings, lampposts, awning posts, all other structures projecting upon or over and adjoining, and all other excavations through and under the sidewalks in the city or village.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 69, XXIV, p. 215; </para><para>Laws 1881, c. 23, &#167; 8, XXIV, p. 183; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 20, &#167; 1, XXIV, p. 174; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 12, &#167; 1, XXIV, p. 303; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5129; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4304; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-453; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-555; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 695, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB266, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB703, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 179. </para></source><annotation><para>City could not authorize use of part of street for private garage purposes. Michelsen v. Dwyer, 158 Neb. 427, 63 N.W.2d 513 (1954).</para><para>Where rubbish mixed with ice and snow had been permitted to accumulate and remain on public street, the question of the negligence of the village in failing to remove such obstruction is one for the jury. Pinches v. Village of Dickens, 127 Neb. 239, 254 N.W. 877 (1934).</para><para>City of second class has authority by ordinance to regulate and prevent use of sidewalks and streets and to remove obstructions therefrom, but such body cannot act arbitrarily and deny one citizen privileges which it grants to another. City of Pierce v. Schramm, 116 Neb. 263, 216 N.W. 809 (1927).</para><para>Where village permitted one party to occupy part of public street in operation of gasoline pump, it could not arbitrarily deny similar privilege to another party. Kenney v. Village of Dorchester, 101 Neb. 425, 163 N.W. 762 (1917).</para><para>City ordinance granting franchise to telephone company is not exclusive unless so indicated in ordinance. City of Plattsmouth v. Nebraska Tel. Co., 80 Neb. 460, 114 N.W. 588 (1908).</para><para>Abutting property owner is entitled to damages for destruction of trees planted along street in front of his property. Bronson v. Albion Telephone Co., 67 Neb. 111, 93 N.W. 201 (1903).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>