<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-607"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>17-607</statuteno><catchline>Treasurer; depositories; qualification; bond; exemption of treasurer from liability; conflict of interest.</catchline><para>(1) The treasurer of a city of the second class or village shall deposit, and at all times keep on deposit, for safekeeping, in banks, capital stock financial institutions, or qualifying mutual financial institutions of approved and responsible standing, all money collected, received, or held by him or her as city treasurer or village treasurer. Such deposits shall be subject to all regulations imposed by law or adopted by the city council or village board of trustees for the receiving and holding thereof. The fact that a stockholder, director, or other officer of such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution is also serving as mayor, as a member of the city council, as a member of the village board of trustees, as a member of a board of public works, or as any other officer of such municipality shall not disqualify such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution from acting as a depository for such municipal funds. Section 77-2366 shall apply to deposits in capital stock financial institutions. Section 77-2365.01 shall apply to deposits in qualifying mutual financial institutions.</para><para>(2) The city council or village board of trustees shall require from all banks, capital stock financial institutions, or qualifying mutual financial institutions (a) a bond in such penal sum as may be the maximum amount on deposit at any time less the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or, in lieu thereof, (b) security given as provided in the Public Funds Deposit Security Act, to secure the payment of all such deposits and accretions. The city council or village board of trustees shall approve such bond or giving of security. The city treasurer or village treasurer shall not be liable for any loss of any money sustained by reason of the failure of any such depository so designated and approved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 65, p. 209; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5149; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 304, &#167; 1, p. 961; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4324; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 168; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 45, &#167; 1, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-515; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 124; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 140, &#167; 2, p. 515; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 31, &#167; 1, p. 155; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-515; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 27, &#167; 2(1), p. 121; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-607; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 54, &#167; 3, p. 264; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 33, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 757, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1274, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 175, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 206. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Public Funds Deposit Security Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2386.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A municipal treasurer is required to deposit its funds in a bank selected by the village board. Village of Hampton v. Gausman, 136 Neb. 550, 286 N.W. 757 (1939).</para><para>Where village treasurer deposits funds in bank duly designated by board as its depository and, after insolvency of such bank, sureties confess their liability and to recoup part of their loss sold bonds pledged with them by bank, such sureties are not entitled to a preferred claim against assets of such bank for balance of their loss. Shumway v. Department of Banking, 131 Neb. 246, 267 N.W. 469 (1936).</para><para>A village treasurer is not authorized to deposit village funds in a bank not designated by board of trustees as a depository. Village of Overton v. Nagel, 128 Neb. 264, 258 N.W. 461 (1935); State ex rel. Sorensen v. Bank of Otoe, 125 Neb. 414, 250 N.W. 547 (1933); State ex rel. Sorensen v. Bank of Otoe, 125 Neb. 383, 250 N.W. 254 (1933).</para><para>Deposit of funds in duly designated depository by city treasurer, where he received them for the specific purpose of investing them in securities designated by ordinance, does not make such funds trust funds. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Fidelity State Bank, 127 Neb. 529, 255 N.W. 781 (1934).</para><para>Where a bank, not designated as a depository by village board, accepts village funds from its treasurer, with knowledge of their character, such bank holds such funds as trustee, and on bank's insolvency, the village is entitled to a preferred claim therefor. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Plateau State Bank, 126 Neb. 407, 253 N.W. 433 (1934).</para><para>Designation of bank as a depository does not relieve treasurer and his bondsmen from liability for funds of municipality lost in bank failure, where treasurer was officer, director, and stockholder of the bank and knew bank was unsafe. City of Cozad v. Thompson, 126 Neb. 79, 252 N.W. 606 (1934).</para><para>Treasurer is liable on his official bond for loss of funds deposited by him in a bank not duly designated as a depository. City of South Sioux City v. Mullins, 125 Neb. 410, 250 N.W. 549 (1933).</para><para>City treasurer is bound to deposit city money in bank which has made application and been accepted as city depository by the city council. Luikart v. City of Aurora, 125 Neb. 263, 249 N.W. 590 (1933).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>