<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Second Class and Villages" statutenumber="17-937"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-937</statuteno><catchline>Existing cemetery association; trustees; oath; bond; vacancy; how filled.</catchline><para>Each of the trustees of such cemetery association shall thereupon forthwith qualify by subscribing to an oath in the office of the city clerk or village clerk, as the case may be, substantially as follows: That he will faithfully, impartially, and honestly perform his duties as such trustee; <emphasis type="italic">Provided further,</emphasis> that whenever the trustees of any cemetery association organized under sections 17-926 to 17-939, shall receive the gift of any property, real or personal, in trust, for the perpetual care of said cemetery, or anything connected therewith, said trustees shall, upon the enactment of bylaws by the association to that effect, require the treasurer of said association to give a bond to said association in a sum equal to the amount of said trust fund and other personal property, conditioned for the faithful administration of said trust and for the care of said funds and property. Said bonds shall be approved by the mayor of the city and by the chairman of the board of trustees of the village and shall remain on file with and in the custody of the city clerk or the village clerk, as the case may be, of such city or village. The premium on the bond of the treasurer shall be paid from available cemetery funds credited to or in the hands of said cemetery association. In the event of a vacancy occurring among the members of the board of trustees of such cemetery association, such vacancy shall be filled in the like manner as the original member of said board of trustees was elected in accordance with the provisions of section 12-501. Such trustee elected as aforesaid to fill such vacancy shall subscribe to the oath as hereinbefore provided. Such appointment to fill such vacancy shall continue until the successor of such trustee shall be duly elected and qualified.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 46, &#167; 8, p. 199; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-548; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-937.</para></source></law></legaldoc>