<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-613" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>17-613</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Ordinances; style; publication; proof.</catchline><para id="id00">The style of all ordinances of a city of the second class or village shall be: Be it ordained by the mayor and city council of the city of ......, or the chairperson and board of trustees of the village of ....... . All ordinances of a general nature shall, before they take effect, be published, within fifteen days after they are passed, (1) in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in such city or village or (2) by publishing the same in book, pamphlet, or electronic form. In case of riot, infectious or contagious diseases, or other impending danger, failure of public utility, or any other emergency requiring its immediate operation, such ordinance shall take effect upon the proclamation of the mayor or chairperson of the village board of trustees, posted in at least three of the most public places in the city or village. Such emergency ordinance shall recite the emergency, be passed by a three-fourths vote of the city council or village board of trustees, and be entered of record on the minutes of the city or village. The passage, approval, and publication of all ordinances shall be sufficiently proved by a certificate under seal of the city or village from the city clerk or village clerk, showing that such ordinance was passed and approved and when and in what legal newspaper the ordinance was published. When ordinances are printed in book, pamphlet, or electronic form, purporting to be published by authority of the village board of trustees or city council, the ordinance need not be otherwise published, and such book, pamphlet, or electronic form shall be received as evidence of the passage and legal publication of such ordinances as of the dates mentioned in such book, pamphlet, or electronic form in all courts without further proof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 59, p. 207; </para><para>Laws 1881, c. 23, &#167; 7, p. 171; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5153; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4328; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-519; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-613; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 137; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 462; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 282, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 212; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB159, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For other provisions applicable to ordinances,</emphasis> see sections 18-131, 18-132, 18-1724, and 19-3701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Generally, ordinances do not go into effect until published. City of Milford v. Schmidt, 175 Neb. 12, 120 N.W.2d 262 (1963).</para><para>Ordinances of a general nature are required to be published. Chicago, St. P., M. &amp; O. Ry. Co. v. City of Randolph, 163 Neb. 687, 81 N.W.2d 159 (1957).</para><para>Paving ordinance was properly published. Freeman v. City of Neligh, 155 Neb. 651, 53 N.W.2d 67 (1952).</para><para>Where an ordinance was printed in pamphlet form by the village, it was regularly published, and a village cannot question its validity on the ground that it was not validly adopted. Village of Deshler v. Southern Nebraska Power Co., 133 Neb. 778, 277 N.W. 77 (1938).</para><para>There is no requirement that the newspaper be printed within the city and, where there is no paper printed in the city, if an ordinance is published in a newspaper printed elsewhere and circulated generally in the city to local subscribers, the publication is sufficient. Hadlock v. Tucker, 93 Neb. 510, 141 N.W. 192 (1913).</para><para>Certificate of village clerk, attached to an ordinance, attested by official seal, stating when passed and approved, and when and in what paper published, is sufficient. Bailey v. State, 30 Neb. 855, 47 N.W. 208 (1890).</para><para>Ordinance calling election became effective when publication was complete. Central Electric &amp; Gas Co. v. City of Stromsburg, 289 F.2d 217 (8th Cir. 1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>