<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-922" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>17-922</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Sewers; assessments; interest; exempt property; cost; how paid.</catchline><para id="id00">No city council or village board of trustees shall cause to be assessed for any of the improvements authorized pursuant to section 17-913, property by law not assessable, or property not included within the district defined in the preliminary resolution, and shall not assess property not benefited. The cost of sewers at the intersection of streets and alleys and opposite property belonging to the United States Government, or other property not assessable, may be included with the cost of the rest of the work and may be assessed on the property within the district, if benefited by the improvement to such extent, or may be paid from unappropriated money in the general fund. The cost of the improvements shall draw interest from the date of acceptance thereof by the city council or village board of trustees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 189, &#167; 10, p. 431; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4346; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-537; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-922; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 53, p. 305; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 257. </para></source><annotation><para>In absence of a jurisdictional defect in proceedings, where property owner had opportunity but failed to present his objections to the municipal body making assessments for local improvements, he cannot thereafter attack collaterally the levy so made. Weilage v. City of Crete, 110 Neb. 544, 194 N.W. 437 (1923).</para><para>In levying special assessments for construction of sewers, they should be confined to abutting property only. Hurd v. Sanitary Sewer District No. 1 of Harvard, 109 Neb. 384, 191 N.W. 438 (1922).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>