<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-108.02" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-108.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Officers and employees; merger of offices or employment; salaries.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) All officers and employees of a city of the second class shall receive such compensation as the mayor and city council may fix at the time of their appointment or employment subject to the limitations set forth in this section.</para><para id="id00">(2) The city council may at its discretion by ordinance combine and merge any elective or appointive office or employment or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments, except mayor and city council member, with any other elective or appointive office or employment so that one or more of such offices or employments or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments may be held by the same officer or employee at the same time.</para><para id="id00">(3) The city manager in a city of the second class under the city manager plan of government as provided in Chapter 19, article 6, may in his or her discretion combine and merge any elective or appointive office or employment or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments, except mayor and city council member, with any other elective or appointive office or employment so that one or more of such offices or employments or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments may be held by the same officer or employee at the same time.</para><para id="id00">(4) The offices or employments merged and combined under subsection (2) or (3) of this section shall always be construed to be separate, and the effect of the combination or merger shall be limited to a consolidation of official duties only. The salary or compensation of the officer or employee holding the merged and combined offices or employments or offices and employments shall not be in excess of the maximum amount provided by law for the salary or compensation of the office, offices, employment, or employments so merged and combined.</para><para id="id00">(5) For purposes of this section, volunteer firefighters and ambulance drivers shall not be considered officers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 7, p. 195; </para><para>Laws 1881, c. 23, &#167; 2, p. 168; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 133; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5000; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 46, &#167; 1, p. 130; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4169; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-108; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 36, &#167; 3, p. 149; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-108; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 30, &#167; 2, p. 140; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-108; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 25, &#167; 1, p. 135; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 31, &#167; 1(3), p. 140; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1145, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 368, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 682, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 756, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 931, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 12, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 492; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>