<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-612" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>17-612</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Elective officers, salary; increase during term of office prohibited; exception.</catchline><para id="id00">The salary of any elective officer in a city of the second class or village shall not be increased or diminished during the term for which he or she has been elected except when there has been a combination and merger of offices as provided by sections 17-108.02 and 17-209.02, and except that when there are officers elected to the city council or a board or commission having more than one member and the terms of one or more members commence and end at different times, the compensation of all members of such city council, board, or commission may be increased or diminished at the beginning of the full term of any member thereof. No person who resigned or vacated any office shall be eligible for the same office during the time for which he or she was elected if during the same time the salary was increased.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 75, p. 220; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5152; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4327; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-518; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-612; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 25, &#167; 3, p. 136; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 89, &#167; 3, p. 452; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 942, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 211. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>City attorney who resigns cannot be rehired by council to perform same duties under the designation of "special counsel" at an increase in pay. Darnell v. City of Broken Bow, 139 Neb. 844, 299 N.W. 274 (1941).</para><para>When, at time of election of city officers, no ordinance had fixed their salaries, this section does not prevent the city council and mayor from fixing such salaries thereafter by ordinance. Wheelock v. McDowell, 20 Neb. 160, 29 N.W. 291 (1886); State ex rel. Wagner v. McDowell, 19 Neb. 442, 27 N.W. 433 (1886).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>