<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-305</statuteno><catchline>Reorganization; existing ordinances; effect; modification.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the expiration of one year after the date of the declaration of the Secretary of State under section 17-301, the city shall be, as of that date, incorporated as a city of the second class. All ordinances, bylaws, acts, regulations, obligations, rules, and proclamations existing and in force in or with respect to any such city at the time of the declaration of the Secretary of State under section 17-301 shall be and remain in full force and effect for a period of one year and may be enacted, altered, or amended during such period in a manner consistent with the statutes governing cities of the first class, except that any such acts, alterations, or amendments shall not be effective beyond the date upon which the city is incorporated as a city of the second class.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (1) of this section, a city shall amend, repeal, or modify all ordinances, bylaws, acts, regulations, obligations, rules, and proclamations which are existing and in force in or with respect to such city at the time of the declaration of the Secretary of State under section 17-301 and which are inconsistent with the statutes governing cities of the second class in a manner which is in conformance and consistent with the statutes governing cities of the second class to take effect upon the effective date of the city's incorporation as a city of the second class.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 112, &#167; 5, p. 454; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-166; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-305; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1119, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 8. </para></source><annotation><para>Upon decrease in population of first-class city below five thousand inhabitants, the ordinances, rules, and regulations remain in effect. State ex rel. Cashman v. Carmean, 138 Neb. 819, 295 N.W. 801 (1941).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>