<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-611" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-611</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Officer; extra compensation prohibited.</catchline><para id="id00">No officer shall receive any pay or perquisites from a city of the second class or village other than his or her salary. Neither the city council nor village board of trustees shall pay or appropriate any money or other valuable thing to any person not an officer for the performance of any act, service, or duty, the doing or performance of which shall come within the proper scope of the duties of any officer of such municipality.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 68, p. 210; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5151; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4326; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-517; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-611; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 38, &#167; 3, p. 208; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 62, &#167; 2, p. 280; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 283, &#167; 3, p. 831; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 494, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 549, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 370, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 210. </para></source><annotation><para>Payments made by village under void contract may be recovered. Heese v. Wenke, 161 Neb. 311, 73 N.W.2d 223 (1955).</para><para>Under former law, interest of members of council in other contracts did not invalidate ordinance. Freeman v. City of Neligh, 155 Neb. 651, 53 N.W.2d 67 (1952).</para><para>An officer who has made a contract with a city or village for salary, additional to that provided by law, cannot recover in quantum meruit. Neisius v. Henry, 142 Neb. 29, 5 N.W.2d 291 (1942).</para><para>Where, under this section, the making of a contract is prohibited, a recovery quantum meruit cannot be had. Village of Bellevue v. Sterba, 140 Neb. 744, 1 N.W.2d 820 (1942).</para><para>Where a city attorney resigns, but still acts as legal advisor to the city and is allowed compensation at the rate provided by ordinance for salary of city attorney, he remains de facto city attorney and cannot enter into legal contract with city for collection of taxes. Darnell v. City of Broken Bow, 139 Neb. 844, 299 N.W. 274 (1941).</para><para>City, having a regular salaried attorney, is not for that reason prevented from employing a special attorney when the city attorney is absent, ill, or disqualified. Meeske v. Baumann, 122 Neb. 786, 241 N.W. 550 (1932), 83 A.L.R. 131 (1932).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>