<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-606"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-606</statuteno><catchline>Treasurer; duties; failure to file account; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The treasurer of each city of the second class or village shall be the custodian of all money belonging to the city or village. He or she shall keep a separate account of each fund or appropriation and the debts and credits belonging thereto. He or she shall give every person paying money into the treasury a receipt for such money, specifying the date of payment and on what account paid. He or she shall also file copies of such receipts with his or her monthly reports, and he or she shall, at the end of every month, and as often as may be required, render an account to the city council or village board of trustees, under oath, showing the state of the treasury at the date of such account and the balance of money in the treasury. He or she shall also accompany such accounts with a statement of all receipts and disbursements, together with all warrants redeemed and paid by him or her, which warrants, with any and all vouchers held by him or her, shall be filed with his or her account in the clerk's office. If the city treasurer or village treasurer fails to render his or her account within twenty days after the end of the month, or by a later date established by the city council or village board of trustees, the mayor of a city of the second class or the chairperson of the village board of trustees with the advice and consent of the trustees may use this failure as cause to remove the city treasurer or village treasurer from office.</para><para>(2) The city treasurer or village treasurer shall keep a record of all outstanding bonds against the city or village, showing the number and amount of each bond, for and to whom the bonds were issued, and the date upon which any bond is purchased, paid, or canceled. He or she shall accompany the annual statement submitted pursuant to section 19-1101 with a description of the bonds issued and sold in that year and the terms of sale, with every item of expense thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 64, p. 209; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5148; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4323; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-514; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-606; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 528, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB112, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 205. </para></source><annotation><para>Duties of city treasurer were clerical and not such as to preclude participation in proceedings for bond election. Inslee v. City of Bridgeport, 153 Neb. 559, 45 N.W.2d 590 (1951).</para><para>Designation of depository and the furnishing of depository bond does not relieve treasurer from duty of exercising reasonable prudence in protection of funds of the municipality. Village of Hampton v. Gausman, 136 Neb. 550, 286 N.W. 757 (1939).</para><para>City treasurer, as custodian of city funds, is required to account monthly to the council, which requirement implies the power of the city to contract and to pay for an audit of his accounts. Campbell Co. v. City of Harvard, 123 Neb. 539, 243 N.W. 653 (1932).</para><para>Power to remove city treasurer for any reason cannot be exercised until specific charges are preferred against such treasurer, notice is given him thereof, and he has had an opportunity to be heard. State ex rel. Ballmer v. Strever, 93 Neb. 762, 141 N.W. 820 (1913).</para><para>Money paid to village treasurer for liquor license as required by municipal ordinance is received by such treasurer in his official capacity and his bondsmen are liable if he fails to account therefor. Hrabak v. Village of Dodge, 62 Neb. 591, 87 N.W. 358 (1901).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>