<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-424"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-424</statuteno><catchline>Additions; plat; failure to execute and record; power of county clerk; costs; collection.</catchline><para>Whenever the original owners or proprietors of any subdivision of land as contemplated in sections 17-415 and 17-416, have sold or conveyed any part thereof or invested the public with any rights therein, and have failed and neglected to execute and file for record a plat as provided in said sections, the county clerk shall notify some or all of such owners and proprietors by mail or otherwise, and demand an execution of said plat as provided. If such owners or proprietors, whether notified or not, fail and neglect to execute and file for record said plat, for thirty days after the issuance of such notice, the clerk shall cause the plat of such subdivision to be made, and also any surveying necessary therefor. Such plat shall be signed and acknowledged by the clerk, who shall certify that he executed it by reason of the failure of the owners or proprietors named to do so, and filed for record. When so filed for record, it shall have the same effect for all purposes as if executed, acknowledged and recorded by the owners or proprietors themselves. A correct statement of the costs and expenses of such plat, surveying and recording, verified by oath, shall be by the clerk laid before the first session of the county board, who shall allow the same and order the same to be paid out of the county treasury, and shall at the same time assess the said amount, pro rata, upon all several subdivisions of said tract, lot or parcel so subdivided. Such assessment shall be collected with and in like manner as the general taxes, and shall go to the county general fund; or the board may direct suit to be brought in the name of the county, before any court having jurisdiction, to recover of the original owners or proprietors, or either of them, the cost and expense of procuring and recording such plat.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 113, p. 235; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5101; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4274; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-423; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-424.</para></source></law></legaldoc>