<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-926" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-926</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Cemetery; acquisition; condemnation; procedure.</catchline><para id="id00">Any city of the second class or village through its mayor and city council or village board of trustees may, by eminent domain, condemn, purchase, hold, and pay for land not exceeding one hundred sixty acres outside the corporate limits of any city of the second class or village for the purpose of the burial of the dead. The mayor and city council or chairperson and village board of trustees are also empowered and authorized to receive by gift or devise real estate for cemetery purposes. In the event any city of the second class or village through its mayor and city council or chairperson and village board of trustees desires to purchase any cemetery belonging to any corporation, partnership, limited liability company, association, or individual, which cemetery has already been properly surveyed and platted, and is used for cemetery purposes, then the mayor and city council or chairperson and village board of trustees are hereby authorized and empowered to purchase the cemetery. In the event the owner or owners of such cemetery desired to be purchased by any city of the second class or village will not or cannot sell and convey such cemetery to the city or village or in the event the owner or owners of such cemetery cannot agree upon the price to be paid for the cemetery, the mayor and city council or the village board of trustees shall by resolution declare the necessity for the acquisition of such cemetery by exercise of the power of eminent domain. The adoption of the resolution shall be deemed conclusive evidence of such necessity. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 46, &#167; 1, p. 195; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-541; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-926; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 60, p. 474; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 70, &#167; 3, p. 273; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 265. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>