<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-906" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-906</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Power plant; construction; eminent domain; procedure.</catchline><para id="id00">Any city of the second class or village is hereby authorized and empowered to erect a power plant, electric or other light works outside the corporate limits of such city or village and to acquire real estate required for such power plant, electric or other light works. Such city or village in establishing and erecting such power plant, electric or other light works shall have the right to purchase or take private property for the purpose of erecting such power plant, electric or other light works and constructing, running, and extending its transmission line. In all cases such city or village shall pay to such person or persons whose property shall be taken or injured thereby such compensation therefor as may be agreed upon or as shall be allowed by lawful condemnation proceedings. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724, except as to property specifically excluded by section 76-703 and as to which sections 19-701 to 19-707 are applicable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 192, &#167; 1, p. 711; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4394; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-906; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 59, p. 474; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 242. </para></source><annotation><para>Power is conferred upon municipality to erect electric or other light works outside the corporate limits of the municipality, and to raise funds therefor. Interstate Power Co. v. City of Ainsworth, 125 Neb. 419, 250 N.W. 649 (1933).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>