<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" id="id78" statutenumber="17-405.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>17-405.01</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Annexation; powers; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section and section 17-407, the mayor and city council of any city of the second class or the chairperson and members of the village board of trustees may by ordinance, except as provided in sections 13-1111 to 13-1118, at any time, include within the corporate limits of such city or village any contiguous or adjacent lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways as are urban or suburban in character, and in such direction as may be deemed proper. Such grant of power shall not be construed as conferring power to extend the limits of any city of the second class or village over any agricultural lands which are rural in character.</para><para>(2) The mayor and city council of any city of the second class or the chairperson and members of the village board of trustees may, by ordinance, annex any lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways which constitute a redevelopment project area so designated by the city or village or its community redevelopment authority in accordance with the provisions of the Community Development Law when such annexation is for the purpose of implementing a lawfully adopted redevelopment plan containing a provision dividing ad valorem taxes as provided in subsection (1) of section 18-2147 and which will involve the construction or development of an agricultural processing facility, notwithstanding that such lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways are not contiguous or adjacent or are not urban or suburban in character. Such annexation shall comply with all other provisions of law relating to annexation generally for cities of the second class and villages. The city or village shall not, in consequence of the annexation under this subsection of any noncontiguous land, exercise the authority granted to it by law to extend its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction beyond its corporate boundaries for purposes of planning, zoning, or subdivision development without the agreement of any other city, village, or county currently exercising zoning jurisdiction over the area surrounding the annexed redevelopment project area. The annexation of any noncontiguous land undertaken pursuant to this subsection shall not result in any change in the service area of any electric utility without the express agreement of the electric utility serving the annexed noncontiguous area at the time of annexation, except that at such time following the annexation of the noncontiguous area as the city or village lawfully annexes sufficient intervening territory so as to directly connect the noncontiguous area to the main body of the city or village, such noncontiguous area shall, solely for the purposes of section 70-1008, be treated as if it had been annexed by the city or village on the date upon which the connecting intervening territory had been formally annexed. For purposes of this subsection, agricultural processing facility means a plant or establishment where value is added to agricultural commodities through processing, fabrication, or other means and where eighty percent or more of the direct sales from the facility are to other than the ultimate consumer of the processed commodities. A facility shall not qualify as an agricultural processing facility unless its construction or development involves the investment of more than one million dollars derived from nongovernmental sources.</para><para>(3) The mayor and two-thirds of the city council of any city of the second class or the chairperson and two-thirds of the members of the village board of trustees may, by ordinance, annex any lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways when such annexation is for the purpose of relocating part or all of such city or village due to catastrophic flooding, notwithstanding that such lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways are not contiguous or adjacent or are not urban or suburban in character. Such annexation shall comply with all other provisions of law relating to annexation generally for cities of the second class and villages. The city or village shall not, in consequence of the annexation under this subsection of any noncontiguous land, exercise the authority granted to it by law to extend its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction beyond its corporate boundaries for purposes of planning, zoning, or subdivision development without the agreement of any other city, village, or county currently exercising zoning jurisdiction over the area surrounding the annexed area. The annexation of any noncontiguous land undertaken pursuant to this subsection shall not result in any change in the service area of any electric utility without the express agreement of the electric utility serving the annexed noncontiguous area at the time of annexation, except that at such time following the annexation of the noncontiguous area as the city or village lawfully annexes sufficient intervening territory so as to directly connect the noncontiguous area to the main body of the city or village, such noncontiguous area shall, solely for the purposes of section 70-1008, be treated as if it had been annexed by the city or village on the date upon which the connecting intervening territory had been formally annexed. If, within five years following an annexation undertaken pursuant to this subsection, part or all of the city or village has not been relocated to the annexed area, the city or village shall initiate detachment of such annexed area pursuant to subsection (2) of section 18-3316. For purposes of this subsection, catastrophic flooding means a flooding event that (a) results in total property damage within the city or village which exceeds forty-five percent of the total assessed value of the improvements within the city or village and (b) is declared to be a major disaster by the President of the United States or the Governor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 74, &#167; 1, p. 240; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 875, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB495, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 110; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB874, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 171; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB131, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community Development Law,</emphasis> see section 18-2101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Contiguity or adjacency requires the connecting point between the land sought to be annexed and the corporate boundary to be substantially adjacent. County of Sarpy v. City of Gretna, 273 Neb. 92, 727 N.W.2d 690 (2007).</para><para>Neither the shape of the annexed tract nor the purpose for the annexation determines whether an annexation is lawful. County of Sarpy v. City of Gretna, 273 Neb. 92, 727 N.W.2d 690 (2007).</para><para>Agricultural lands which are urban or suburban in character are subject to annexation hereunder and there is no provision which prevents consideration thereof at a special meeting. Holden v. City of Tecumseh, 188 Neb. 117, 195 N.W.2d 225 (1972).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>