<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" id="id00" statutenumber="17-311"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-311</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Village; increase in population; reorganization as city of the second class.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Except as provided in section 17-312, whenever any village increases in population until it has a population of more than eight hundred inhabitants but less than five thousand inhabitants, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the village board of trustees shall certify such fact to the Secretary of State who, upon the filing of such a certificate, shall by proclamation declare such village to have become a city of the second class. After such proclamation, such city shall be governed by the laws of this state applicable to cities of the second class. The government of such city shall continue as organized at the date of such proclamation until the reorganization as a city of the second class.</para><para id="id00">(2) If any village becomes a city of the second class, the village board of trustees shall call a special election for the purpose of electing the mayor and city council members to be held not more than eight months after the proclamation is issued. At the initial election of the mayor and city council members, the names of the candidates receiving the greatest number of votes at the primary election if one is held shall be placed on the general election ballot. One-half or the bare majority of the candidates for city council in each precinct or ward or at-large candidates, as the case may be, receiving the greatest number of votes at the general election, shall be elected to terms of the longest duration, and those receiving the next greatest number of votes shall be elected to the remaining term or terms. The members of the village board of trustees shall hold office only until the newly elected mayor and city council members assume office.</para><para id="id00">(3) All ordinances, bylaws, acts, rules, regulations, obligations, and proclamations existing and in force in or with respect to any village at the time of its incorporation as a city of the second class shall remain in full force and effect after such incorporation as a city of the second class until repealed or modified by such city within one year after the date of the filing of the certificate pursuant to subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 1119, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 796, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 495; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 103. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>