<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" id="id15" statutenumber="17-208"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>17-208</statuteno><catchline id="id18">Appointive officers; term of office; police officer; removal, demotion, or suspension; procedure; board of health; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The village board of trustees may appoint a village clerk, treasurer, attorney, engineer, overseer of the streets, and chief of police and other such officers as shall be required by ordinance or otherwise required by law.</para><para>(2)(a) The village chief of police or any other police officer may appeal to the village board of trustees his or her removal, demotion, or suspension with or without pay. After a hearing, the village board of trustees may uphold, reverse, or modify the action.</para><para>(b) The village board of trustees shall by ordinance adopt rules and regulations governing the removal, demotion, or suspension with or without pay of any police officer, including the village chief of police. The ordinance shall include a procedure for such removal, demotion, or suspension with or without pay of any police officer, including the village chief of police, upon the written accusation of the village chief of police, the chairperson of the village board of trustees, or any citizen or taxpayer. The village board of trustees shall establish by ordinance procedures for acting upon such written accusation, including: (i) Provisions for giving notice and a copy of the written accusation to the police officer; (ii) the police officer's right to have an attorney or representative retained by the police officer present with him or her at all hearings or proceedings regarding the written accusation; (iii) the right of the police officer or his or her attorney or representative retained by the police officer to be heard and present evidence; and (iv) the right of the police officer as well as the individual imposing the action or their respective attorneys or representatives to record all hearings or proceedings regarding the written accusation. The ordinance shall also include a procedure for making application for an appeal, specifications on the period of time within which such application shall be made, and provisions on the manner in which the appeals hearing shall be conducted. Both the police officer and the individual imposing the action or their respective attorneys or representatives shall have the right at the hearing to be heard and to present evidence to the village board of trustees for its consideration. Not later than thirty days following the adjournment of the meeting at which the hearing was held, the village board of trustees shall vote to uphold, reverse, or modify the action. The failure of the village board of trustees to act within thirty days or the failure of a majority of the elected board members to vote to reverse or modify the action shall be construed as a vote to uphold the action. The decision of the village board of trustees shall be based upon its determination that, under the facts and evidence presented at the hearing, the action was necessary for the proper management and the effective operation of the police department in the performance of its duties under the statutes of the State of Nebraska. Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent the preemptory suspension or immediate removal from duty of an officer by the appropriate authority, pending the hearing authorized by this section, in cases of gross misconduct, neglect of duty, or disobedience of orders.</para><para>(c) This subsection does not apply to a police officer during his or her probationary period.</para><para>(3) The village board of trustees shall also appoint a board of health consisting of three members: The chairperson of the village board of trustees, who shall be chairperson, and two other members. One member shall be a physician or health care provider, if one can be found who is willing to serve. Such physician or health care provider, if appointed, shall be the medical advisor to the board of health. If the village board of trustees has appointed a chief of police, the chief of police may be appointed to the board of health and serve as secretary and quarantine officer. A majority of the board of health shall constitute a quorum and shall enact rules and regulations, which shall have the force and effect of law, to safeguard the health of the people of such village and prevent nuisances and unsanitary conditions. The board of health shall enforce such rules and regulations and provide fines and punishments for violations.</para><para>(4) The village clerk, treasurer, attorney, engineer, overseer of the streets, members of the board of health, and other appointed officers, except regular police officers, shall hold office for one year unless removed by the chairperson of the village board of trustees with the advice and consent of the village board of trustees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 47, p. 204; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 18, &#167; 1, p. 158; </para><para>Laws 1895, c. 15, &#167; 1, p. 110; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 20, &#167; 1, p. 137; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5058; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 165, &#167; 1, p. 369; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4230; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-208; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-208; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 346, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1162, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB158, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB308, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 70. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Village marshal is appointive officer, and is not an employee within the meaning of the Workmen's Compensation Act. Suverkrubbe v. Village of Fort Calhoun, 127 Neb. 472, 256 N.W. 47 (1934).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>