
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-207" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-207</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of trustees; powers; restrictions.</catchline><para>The village board of trustees shall have power to pass ordinances: (1) To prevent and remove nuisances within the village or within its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction; (2) to restrain and prohibit gambling; (3) to provide for licensing and regulating theatrical and other amusements within the village; (4) to prevent the introduction and spread of contagious diseases; (5) to establish and regulate markets; (6) to erect and repair bridges; (7) to erect, repair, and regulate wharves; (8) to regulate the landing of watercraft; (9) to provide for the inspection of building materials to be used or offered for sale in the village; (10) to govern the planting and protection of shade trees in the streets and the building of structures projecting upon or over and adjoining, and all excavations through and under, the sidewalks of the village; (11) to maintain the peace, good government, and welfare of the village and its trade and commerce; and (12) to enforce all ordinances by inflicting penalties upon inhabitants or other persons, for the violation of such ordinances, not exceeding five hundred dollars for any one offense, recoverable with costs. Nothing in this section shall be construed to apply to bingo, lotteries, lotteries by the sale of pickle cards, or raffles conducted in accordance with the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, or the State Lottery Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 46, p. 203; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 15, &#167; 1, p. 123; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5057; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4229; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-207; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-207; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 190; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 128, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB266, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 68. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>It is the duty of a municipality to regulate the building of stairways projecting upon, over, or adjoining sidewalks, and it is liable for negligence in performing such duty. Pinches v. Village of Dickens, 127 Neb. 239, 254 N.W. 877 (1934).</para><para>Village is liable for services of one superintending the repair and alteration of well or waterworks where the improvement was completed and all other bills therefor paid by village, without question. Launt v. Village of Oakdale, 88 Neb. 320, 129 N.W. 258 (1911).</para><para>Villages as well as cities of second class have full power to license, regulate, and prohibit billiard and pool hall within their limits. Cole v. Village of Culbertson, 86 Neb. 160, 125 N.W. 287 (1910).</para><para>Village board may grant liquor license at a special meeting after legal notice. Vogel v. Rawley, 85 Neb. 600, 123 N.W. 1037 (1909).</para><para>Municipality has no power by ordinance to prohibit the keeping of card tables or power to make it unlawful to permit card playing. In re Sapp, 79 Neb. 781, 113 N.W. 261 (1907).</para><para>The running of a bowling alley in connection with a saloon or hotel was declared, under former act, to be a criminal offense. Koepke v. State, 68 Neb. 152, 93 N.W. 1129 (1903).</para><para>Village boards have power by ordinance to license and regulate billiard and pool rooms and an ordinance whose main object is to license and regulate the same, is not wholly void because of imposing an occupation tax not clearly expressed in title. Morgan v. State, 64 Neb. 369, 90 N.W. 108 (1902).</para><para>Village is subject to liability for defective sidewalk. City of Wahoo v. Reeder, 27 Neb. 770, 43 N.W. 1145 (1889); Village of Orleans v. Perry, 24 Neb. 831, 40 N.W. 417 (1888); Village of Ponca v. Crawford, 23 Neb. 662, 37 N.W. 609 (1888).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>