<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-715" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>17-715</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Claims; allowance; payment.</catchline><para id="id00">Upon the allowance of claims by the city council of a city of the second class or village board of trustees, the order for their payment shall specify the particular fund or appropriation out of which they are payable as specified in the adopted budget statement; and no order or warrant shall be drawn in excess of eighty-five percent of the current levy for the purpose for which it is drawn, unless there shall be sufficient money in the treasury at the credit of the proper fund for its payment. In the event there exists at the time such warrant is drawn, obligated funds from the federal government or the State of Nebraska, or both from the federal government and the State of Nebraska, for the general purpose or purposes of such warrant, then such warrant may be drawn in excess of eighty-five percent of the current levy for the purpose for which it is drawn to the additional extent of one hundred percent of such obligated federal or state funds. No claim shall be audited or allowed unless an order or warrant for the payment thereof may legally be drawn.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 81, p. 223; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 18, &#167; 1, p. 160; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5193; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4383; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-581; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-715; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 23, p. 686; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 693, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 226. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Where warrant is drawn in excess of eighty-five per cent of the current levy, unless sufficient money is in the treasury to credit of the proper fund for the payment thereof, the warrant is void and the payment thereof may be enjoined. Ballard v. Cerney, 83 Neb. 606, 120 N.W. 151 (1909).</para><para>Where warrant was issued by reason of fraudulent representations of payee's agent, mandamus will not force city treasurer to pay the same in third person's hands. State ex rel. First Nat. Bank of York v. Cook, 43 Neb. 318, 61 N.W. 693 (1895).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>