<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Second Class and Villages" statutenumber="17-312"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-312</statuteno><catchline>Village; retention of village government; petition; election.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any village attains a population exceeding eight hundred inhabitants and one-fourth of the legal voters but not less than one hundred registered voters of the village petition the board of trustees of such village, the board of trustees shall cause to be published for at least thirty days a notice stating that the question of retaining a village form of government will be submitted at the next regularly scheduled election or at a special election announced in such notice. Thereupon there shall be submitted by the board of trustees at such election the question of retaining a village form of government. Such election shall be conducted in the manner provided for cities of the second class. The form of the ballot at such election shall be For retention of village government and Against retention of village government. If the majority of the votes cast are for retention of village government, then such village shall remain a village and be governed under the provisions of the law relating to villages unless at some future election such village adopts a city government in the manner provided for the adoption of a village government.</para><para>(2) If the question is submitted at a special election, such election shall be held not later than October 15 of an odd-numbered year. If the question is rejected, city officials shall be elected at the next regularly scheduled election.</para><para>(3) If the question is submitted at a regularly scheduled election, no village trustees shall be elected at such election, but trustees whose terms are to expire following such election shall hold office until either their successors or city officials take office as follows:</para><para>(a) If the question is rejected, the village board shall call a special election, to be held not more than eight months after the election at which the question was rejected, for the purpose of electing city officials under the provisions of law relating to cities of the second class. The terms of office for such officials shall be established pursuant to section 17-311. The members of the board of trustees shall hold office only until the newly elected city officials assume office; and</para><para>(b) If the question is approved, the village board shall call a special election, to be held not more than eight months after the election at which the question was approved, for the purpose of electing successors to those members of the village board who held office beyond the normal expiration of their terms. Such special election shall be conducted under the provisions of law relating to villages. Persons so elected shall take office as soon after the completion of the canvass of the votes as is practicable, and their terms of office shall be as if the holdovers had not occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 190; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5007; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4249; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-301; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-307; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 91, &#167; 2, p. 455; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 62, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 661, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 796, &#167; 1; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1990, &#167; 17-307; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 496. </para></source></law></legaldoc>