<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-541"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-541</statuteno><catchline>Waterworks; water commissioner; appointment; term; bond or insurance; removal; public works commissioner, when.</catchline><para>As soon as a system of waterworks or mains or portion or extension of any system of waterworks or water supply has been established by a city of the second class or village, the mayor of such city or the chairperson of the village board of trustees shall nominate and, by and with the advice and consent of the city council or village board of trustees, shall appoint any competent person who shall be known as the water commissioner of such city or village and whose term of office shall be for one fiscal year or until his or her successor is appointed and qualified. Annually at the first regular meeting of the city council or village board of trustees in December, the water commissioner shall be appointed as provided in this section. The water commissioner may at any time, for sufficient cause, be removed by a two-thirds vote of the city council or village board of trustees. Any vacancy occurring in the office of water commissioner by death, resignation, removal from office, or removal from the city or village may be filled in the manner provided in this section for the appointment of such commissioner.</para><para>The water commissioner shall, before he or she enters upon the discharge of his or her duties, execute a bond or provide evidence of equivalent insurance to such city or village in a sum to be fixed by the mayor and city council or the village board of trustees, but not less than five thousand dollars, conditioned upon the faithful discharge of his or her duties, and such bond shall be signed by two or more good and sufficient sureties, to be approved by the mayor and city council or village board of trustees or executed by a corporate surety.</para><para>The water commissioner, subject to the supervision of the mayor and city council or village board of trustees, shall have the general management and control of the system of waterworks or mains or portion or extension of any system of waterworks or water supply in the city or village. In a city of the second class or village where no board of public works exists, and such city or village has other public utilities than its waterworks system, the mayor and city council or the village board of trustees shall by ordinance designate the water commissioner as public works commissioner with authority to manage not only the system of waterworks but also other public utilities, and all of the provisions of this section applying to the water commissioner shall apply to the public works commissioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 23, &#167; 8, XV, p. 180; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 20, &#167; 1, XV, p. 170; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 12, &#167; 1, XV, p. 299; </para><para>Laws 1893, c. 8, &#167; 1, p. 136; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 252; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 30, &#167; 1, p. 259; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 129; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5119; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 103, &#167; 1, p. 273; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 48, &#167; 1, p. 139; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 52, &#167; 1, p. 153; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 46, &#167; 2, p. 134; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4292; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 41, &#167; 1, p. 160; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-441; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 144; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 158; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-441; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-541; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 51, &#167; 1, p. 193; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 484, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB347, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 167. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>