<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-511" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>17-511</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Streets; improvement by ordinance; objections; time of filing; special assessment.</catchline><para>Whenever the governing body of a city of the second class or village deems it necessary to make the improvements in section 17-509 which are to be funded by a levy of special assessment on the property specially benefited, such governing body shall by ordinance create an improvement district and, after the passage, approval, and publication of such ordinance, shall publish notice of the creation of any such district for six days in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city or village if such legal newspaper is a daily newspaper or for two consecutive weeks if such legal newspaper is a weekly newspaper. If the owners of the record title representing more than fifty percent of the front footage of the property directly abutting on the street or alley to be improved file with the city clerk or village clerk within twenty days after the first publication of such notice written objections to the creation of such district, such improvement shall not be made as provided in such ordinance, but such ordinance shall be repealed. If objections are not filed against the district in the time and manner prescribed in this section, the governing body shall immediately cause such work to be done or such improvement to be made, shall contract for the work or improvement, and shall levy special assessments on the lots and parcels of land abutting on or adjacent to such street or alley specially benefited in such district in proportion to such benefits to pay the cost of such improvement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 42, &#167; 1, p. 177; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-432; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 136, &#167; 20, p. 530; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-432; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-511; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 176, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 196, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 129. </para></source><annotation><para>Separate and distinct method for initiating paving project is provided by this section. Elliott v. City of Auburn, 172 Neb. 1, 108 N.W.2d 328 (1961).</para><para>Requirements of this section compared with similar requirements applicable to first-class cities. Danielson v. City of Bellevue, 167 Neb. 809, 95 N.W.2d 57 (1959).</para><para>Property abutting on "T" intersection was liable for special assessments. Chicago &amp; N. W. Ry. Co. v. City of Seward, 166 Neb. 662, 90 N.W.2d 282 (1958).</para><para>Cost of paving intersections should be assessed upon all the taxable property of city. Chicago &amp; N. W. Ry. Co. v. City of Seward, 166 Neb. 123, 88 N.W.2d 175 (1958).</para><para>Creation of paving district must be ordered by ordinance. Chicago, St. P., M. &amp; O. Ry. Co. v. City of Randolph, 163 Neb. 687, 81 N.W.2d 159 (1957).</para><para>Constitutionality upheld against claim of failure of lawful classification and violation of due process. Freeman v. City of Neligh, 155 Neb. 651, 53 N.W.2d 67 (1952).</para><para>Where paving district is created by ordinance without petition, majority of resident owners of directly abutting property may file objections and prevent such paving. Manners v. City of Wahoo, 153 Neb. 437, 45 N.W.2d 113 (1950).</para><para>In case of objection by one joint tenant in which the other joint tenant has not joined, rebuttable presumption arises that the one objecting represents the entire property. Bonner v. City of Imperial, 149 Neb. 721, 32 N.W.2d 267 (1948).</para><para>An ordinance specifying a street or part of street to be paved, sufficiently describes a paving district and such street or part of street and abutting property therein constitute the paving district. Chittenden v. Kibler, 100 Neb. 756, 161 N.W. 272 (1917).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>