
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-514" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-514</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Streets; improvement; assessments; certification to county treasurer.</catchline><para id="id00">All assessments under sections 17-509 to 17-512 shall be a lien on the property on which levied from the date of levy and shall be certified by direction of the city council or village board of trustees to the city treasurer or village treasurer for collection. Except as provided in section 18-1216, such assessment shall be due and payable to such treasurer until the first day of November thereafter, or until the delivery of the tax list for such year to the county treasurer of the county in which such city or village is situated, at and after which time such assessment shall be due and payable to such county treasurer. The city council or village board of trustees of such city or village shall, within the time provided by law, cause such assessments, or portion thereof then remaining unpaid, to be certified to the county clerk for entry upon the proper tax lists. If the city treasurer or village treasurer collects any assessment or portion of such assessment so certified while such assessment shall be payable to the county treasurer, the city treasurer or village treasurer shall certify the assessment or portion of such assessment to the county treasurer at once, and the county treasurer shall correct the record to show such payment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 191; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 139; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5110; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 92, &#167; 1, p. 232; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 102, &#167; 1, p. 268; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 145; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4283; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 135, &#167; 1, p. 331; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 42, &#167; 1, p. 178; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-432; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 136, &#167; 20, p. 531; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-432; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-514; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 962, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 132. </para></source><annotation><para>Special assessments are a lien from date of levy. Belza v. Village of Emerson, 159 Neb. 651, 68 N.W.2d 272 (1955).</para><para>Special assessments on real property are a lien inferior to lien of general taxes, and where property is sold at a tax foreclosure to satisfy lien of general taxes, title passes to a purchaser by such sale, free and clear of all special assessment liens. Polenz v. City of Ravenna, 145 Neb. 845, 18 N.W.2d 510 (1945).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>