<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Second Class and Villages" statutenumber="17-905"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-905</statuteno><catchline>Utilities; acquisition; revenue bonds; issuance; when authorized.</catchline><para>Supplemental to any existing law on the subject and in lieu of the issuance of general obligation bonds, or the levying of taxes upon property, as by law provided, any city of the second class or any village may construct, purchase or otherwise acquire a waterworks plant or a water system, or a gas plant or a gas system, including a natural or bottled gas plant, gas distribution system or gas pipe lines, either within or without the corporate limits of the city or village, and real and personal property needed or useful in connection therewith, and pay the cost thereof by pledging and hypothecating the revenue and earnings of any waterworks plant or water system, or gas plant or gas system, including a natural or bottled gas plant, gas distribution system or gas pipelines, owned or to be owned by the city or village. In the exercise of the authority herein granted, the city or village may issue and sell revenue bonds or debentures and enter into such contracts in connection therewith as may be proper and necessary. Such revenue bonds or debentures shall be a lien only upon the revenue and earnings of the waterworks plant or water system, gas plant or gas system, including a natural or bottled gas plant, gas distribution system or gas pipe lines, owned or to be owned by the city or village. No such city or village shall pledge or hypothecate the revenue and earnings of any waterworks plant or water system, or gas plant or gas system, including a natural or bottled gas plant, gas distribution system or gas pipelines, nor issue revenue bonds or debentures, as herein authorized, until the proposition relating thereto has been submitted in the usual manner to the qualified voters of such city or village at a general or special election, and approved by a majority of the electors voting on the proposition submitted; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> such proposition shall be submitted, whenever requested, within thirty days after a sufficient petition signed by the qualified voters of such city or village equal in number to twenty percent of the vote cast at the last general municipal election held therein is filed with the city clerk or village clerk, as the case is. Three weeks' notice of the submission of the proposition shall be given by publication in some legal newspaper published in or of general circulation in such city or village, or, if no legal newspaper is published therein, then by posting in five or more public places therein. The requirement herein for a vote of the electors, however, shall not apply when such city or village seeks to pledge or hypothecate such revenue or earnings, or issue revenue bonds or debentures solely for the maintenance, extension or enlargement of any waterworks plant or water system, or any gas plant or any gas system, including a natural or bottled gas plant, gas distribution system or gas pipelines, owned by such city or village.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 22, &#167; 2, p. 113; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-596; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-905.</para></source><annotation><para>Issuance of revenue bonds is authorized. Talbott v. City of Lyons, 171 Neb. 186, 105 N.W.2d 918 (1960).</para><para>Power to acquire gas distribution system by eminent domain was not conferred. Village of Walthill v. Iowa Electric Light &amp; Power Co., 125 F.Supp. 859 (D. Neb. 1954).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>