<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" id="id6" statutenumber="17-301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>17-301</statuteno><catchline id="id9">City of the first class; reorganization as city of the second class; procedure; mayor, city council, and Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies to cities of the first class whose population is less than five thousand inhabitants but more than eight hundred inhabitants as determined by the federal decennial census conducted in the year 2010 or any subsequent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census.</para><para>(2)(a) If a city of the first class has a population of less than five thousand inhabitants but not less than four thousand inhabitants, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the mayor of the city shall certify such fact to the Secretary of State. If the mayor and city council determine that it is in the best interests of such city to become a city of the second class, the mayor and city council shall adopt an ordinance to that effect and shall notify the Secretary of State and notice and a copy of such ordinance shall accompany the certification. If the Secretary of State receives such notification, he or she shall declare such city to be a city of the second class. If the mayor and city council determine that it is in the best interests of such city to remain a city of the first class, they shall submit to the Secretary of State, within nine years after the certification is required to be submitted pursuant to this subdivision, an explanation of the city's plan to increase the city's population.</para><para>(b) If a city of the first class has a population of less than five thousand inhabitants but not less than four thousand inhabitants, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census immediately following the census or revised certified count referred to in subdivision (a) of this subsection, the mayor of the city shall certify such fact to the Secretary of State. If the mayor and city council determine that it is in the best interests of such city to become a city of the second class, the mayor and city council shall adopt an ordinance to that effect and shall notify the Secretary of State and notice and a copy of such ordinance shall accompany the certification. If the Secretary of State receives such notification, he or she shall declare such city to be a city of the second class.</para><para>(c) If a city of the first class has a population of less than five thousand inhabitants but not less than four thousand inhabitants, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census immediately following the census or revised certified count referred to in subdivision (b) of this subsection, the mayor of the city shall certify such fact to the Secretary of State. After receipt of such certification, the Secretary of State shall declare such city to be a city of the second class.</para><para>(3) If a city of the first class has a population of less than four thousand inhabitants but more than eight hundred inhabitants, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census, the mayor of the city shall certify such fact to the Secretary of State. After receipt of such certification, the Secretary of State shall declare such city to be a city of the second class.</para><para>(4) Beginning on the date upon which a city becomes a city of the second class pursuant to section 17-305, such city shall be governed by the laws of this state applicable to cities of the second class.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 112, &#167; 1, p. 452; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 17-162; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-301; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1119, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB919, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 95.</para></source><annotation><para>When it is definitely shown that a first-class city has decreased in population to less than five thousand inhabitants, the mayor of the city has a mandatory duty to certify such fact to the Governor. State ex rel. Cashman v. Carmean, 138 Neb. 819, 295 N.W. 801 (1941).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>