<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>17-110</statuteno><catchline>Mayor; general duties and powers.</catchline><para>(1) The mayor shall preside at all meetings of the city council of a city of the second class. The mayor may vote on any matter that requires either a majority vote of the city council or a majority vote of all the elected members of the city council if (a) the mayor's vote is required due to the city council members being equally divided or (b) a majority of the city council members or majority vote of all the elected members cannot be reached due to absence, vacancy, or abstention of one or more city council members. For purposes of such vote, the mayor is deemed to be a member of the city council.</para><para>(2) The mayor shall have superintendence and control of all the officers and affairs of the city and shall take care that the ordinances of the city and all laws governing cities of the second class are complied with.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 10, p. 195; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5002; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4171; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-110; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-110; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 55, &#167; 3, p. 266; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 172, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 662, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB113, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB531, &#167; 8. </para></source><annotation><para>The mayor has no power to suspend the operation of an ordinance which contains no provision in itself empowering him so to do. Pulver v. State, 83 Neb. 446, 119 N.W. 780 (1909).</para><para>The mayor and council have power to compromise and settle claims against the city. State ex rel. Fuller v. Martin, 27 Neb. 441, 43 N.W. 244 (1889).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>