<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-121" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>17-121</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Health and sanitation; rules and regulations; board of health; members; powers.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A city of the second class shall have the power to make regulations to prevent the introduction and spread of contagious, infectious, or malignant diseases into the city, to make quarantine laws for that purpose, and to enforce such regulations.</para><para id="id00">(2) In cities of the second class with a commission plan of government as provided in the Municipal Commission Plan of Government Act and cities of the second class with a city manager plan of government as provided in the City Manager Plan of Government Act, a board of health shall be created consisting of five members: The mayor, who shall be chairperson, and four other members. One member shall be a physician or health care provider, if one can be found who is willing to serve. Such physician or health care provider, if appointed, shall be the board's medical advisor. If the city manager has appointed a chief of police, the chief of police shall serve on the board as secretary and quarantine officer.</para><para id="id00">(3) In all other cities of the second class, a board of health shall be created consisting of four members: The mayor, who shall be chairperson, the president of the city council, and two other members. One member shall be a physician or health care provider, if one can be found who is willing to serve. Such physician or health care provider, if appointed, shall be the board's medical advisor. If the mayor has appointed a chief of police, the chief of police shall serve on the board as secretary and quarantine officer.</para><para id="id00">(4) A majority of the board of health shall constitute a quorum and shall enact rules and regulations, which shall have the force and effect of law, to safeguard the health of the people of such city, may enforce them, and may provide fines and punishments for the violation of such rules and regulations. The board of health shall have power to and shall make all necessary rules and regulations relating to matters of sanitation of such city, including the removal of dead animals, the sanitary condition of the streets, alleys, vacant grounds, stockyards, wells, cisterns, privies, waterclosets, cesspools, and all buildings and places not specified where filth, nuisances, or offensive matter is kept or is liable to or does accumulate. The board of health may regulate, suppress, and prevent the occurrence of nuisances and enforce all laws of the state and ordinances of the city relating to nuisances or to matters of sanitation of such city. The board of health shall also have control of hospitals, dispensaries, places for treatment of sick, and related matters under such restrictions and provisions as may be provided by ordinance of such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 39, II, p. 201; </para><para>Laws 1881, c. 24, &#167; 1, p. 194; </para><para>Laws 1895, c. 14, &#167; 1, II, p. 109; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5015; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 44, &#167; 1, p. 128; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4184; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-123; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-121; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 190, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 119, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1019, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1162, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>City Manager Plan of Government Act,</emphasis> see section 19-601.</para><para><emphasis>Municipal Commission Plan of Government Act,</emphasis> see section 19-401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>City of second class may enjoin nuisance maintained outside corporate limits. City of Lyons v. Betts, 184 Neb. 746, 171 N.W.2d 792 (1969).</para><para>Where a nuisance is admitted to exist, members of the board of health have the legal discretion to determine the manner of abating the same. State ex rel. Glatfelter v. Hart, 106 Neb. 61, 182 N.W. 567 (1921).</para><para>The Legislature has not conferred upon the board of health power to adopt a regulation making it criminal to maintain a slaughterhouse outside of the city. State v. Temple, 99 Neb. 505, 156 N.W. 1063 (1916).</para><para>Neither city nor officers of its board of health are liable for damages sustained by reason of their acts committed in the exercise of police power, but a city may be liable for its neglect of an undelegable duty. Sheets v. City of McCook, 95 Neb. 139, 145 N.W. 252 (1914).</para><para>The powers and jurisdiction of cities of second class and townships are entirely separate, distinct, and unlike in all respects. Chilton v. Town of Gratton, 82 F. 873 (Cir. Ct., D. Neb. 1897).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>