<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-202" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>17-202</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of trustees; election; terms.</catchline><para id="id00">The corporate powers and duties of every village shall be vested in a board of trustees which shall consist of three or five members. At the first statewide general election held after the incorporation of a village with five members, two trustees shall be elected to serve two years and three trustees shall be elected to serve four years. At the first statewide general election held after the incorporation of a village with three members, two trustees shall be elected to serve four years and one trustee shall be elected to serve two years. At the first statewide general election held after changing the number of trustees from five to three, one trustee shall be elected to serve two years and two trustees shall be elected to serve four years. The two trustees receiving the highest and second highest number of votes or tied for the highest number of votes shall serve the four-year terms, and the trustee receiving the next highest number of votes shall serve the two-year term. Thereafter the board members shall be elected as provided in the Election Act. The terms shall begin on the first regular meeting of the board in December following the statewide general election. The changes made to this section by Laws 1994, LB 76, and Laws 1995, LB 194, shall not change the staggering of the terms of the board members in villages established prior to January 1, 1995.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 41, p. 202; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 78; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5052; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4224; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 17-202; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 120; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 17-202; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 257, &#167; 9, p. 936; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 493; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 194, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB289, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Board of trustees,</emphasis> election, see section 32-532.</para><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para><para><emphasis>Vacancies,</emphasis> see sections 32-568 and 32-569.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>