
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-209.02" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-209.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Officers and employees; combine or merge office, employment, or duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The village board of trustees may, by ordinance, combine or merge any elective or appointive village office or village employment or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments, except that the office of village trustee shall not be combined or merged with any other village office or village employment except as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(b) The village offices or village employments combined or merged shall always be construed to be separate and the effect of the combination or merger shall be limited to a consolidation of official duties only.</para><para>(2)(a) The office of village trustee shall not be combined or merged with any other village office or village employment, except that a member of the village board of trustees may receive compensation to perform seasonal or emergency work upon approval by the village board of trustees.</para><para>(b) No member of the village board of trustees shall receive compensation from the village in excess of the maximum amount provided by law.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, volunteer firefighters and volunteer rescue squad personnel shall not be considered village officers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 25, &#167; 2, p. 135; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1945, &#167; 17-209.01; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 106; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 368, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 682, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 548, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 756, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB405, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>