<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Second Class And Villages" statutenumber="17-1002" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>17-1002</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Designation of jurisdiction; suburban development; subdivision; platting; consent required; review; when required.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (5) of this section, any city of the second class or village may designate by ordinance the portion of the territory located within its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction outside of any other organized city or village within which the designating city or village will exercise the powers and duties granted by this section and section 17-1003 or section 19-2402.</para><para>(2) No owner of any real property located within the area designated by a city or village pursuant to subsection (1) or (5) of this section may subdivide, plat, or lay out such real property in building lots, streets, or other portions of the same intended to be dedicated for public use or for the use of the purchasers or owners of lots fronting thereon or adjacent thereto without first having obtained the approval of the city council or village board of trustees or its agent designated pursuant to section 19-916 and, when applicable, having complied with sections 39-1311 to 39-1311.05. The fact that such real property is located in a different county or counties than some or all portions of the municipality shall not be construed as affecting the necessity of obtaining the approval of the city council or village board of trustees or its designated agent.</para><para>(3) No plat of such real property shall be recorded or have any force or effect unless approved by the city council or village board of trustees or its designated agent.</para><para>(4) Except as provided in subsection (6) of this section, in counties that have adopted a comprehensive development plan which meets the requirements of section 23-114.02 and are enforcing subdivision regulations, the county planning commission shall be provided with all available materials on any proposed subdivision plat, contemplating public streets or improvements, which is filed with a city of the second class or village in that county, when such proposed plat lies partially or totally within the portion of the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of that city or village where the powers and duties granted by this section and section 17-1003 or section 19-2402 are being exercised by that municipality in such county. The commission shall be given four weeks to officially comment on the appropriateness of the design and improvements proposed in the plat. The review period for the commission shall run concurrently with subdivision review activities of the municipality after the commission receives all available material for a proposed subdivision plat.</para><para>(5) If a city of the second class or village receives approval for the cession and transfer of additional extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction under section 13-327, such city or village may designate by ordinance the portion of the territory located within its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction and outside of any other organized city or village within which the designating city or village will exercise the powers and duties granted by this section and section 17-1003 or section 19-2402 and shall include territory ceded under section 13-327 within such designation.</para><para>(6) In counties having a population in excess of one hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census but less than two hundred fifty thousand inhabitants that have adopted a comprehensive development plan which meets the requirements of section 23-114.02 and are enforcing subdivision regulations, the county planning department and public works department shall be provided with all available materials on any proposed subdivision plat, contemplating public streets or improvements, which is filed with a city of the second class or village in that county, when such proposed plat lies partially or totally within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction being exercised by that city of the second class or village in such county. The county may officially comment on the appropriateness of the design and improvements proposed in the plat.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 37, &#167; 2, p. 204; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 70, &#167; 4, p. 233; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 75, &#167; 5, p. 244; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 186, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 71, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 208, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 222, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB864, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB877, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB74, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB133, &#167; 307. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>