<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id396"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-834"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>81-834</statuteno><catchline>Critical procurements; review; report; confidential; unauthorized public disclosure, penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Administrative Services shall conduct a review of critical procurements purchased or supplied through a state supply chain or state vendor supply chain and produce a report, which shall be electronically submitted using a secure method to the Governor by November 1, 2024.</para><para>(2) The report shall:</para><para>(a) Summarize the critical procurements produced in or by a foreign adversary, a state-owned enterprise of a foreign adversary, a company domiciled within a foreign adversary, or a company owned by a company domiciled within a foreign adversary;</para><para>(b) Summarize the critical procurements manufactured in countries or by companies at risk of disruption in the event of a Pacific conflict;</para><para>(c) Summarize the critical procurements sourced from any country or company which utilizes Pacific supply chain processes at risk of disruption in the event of a Pacific conflict;</para><para>(d) Assess the difficulty in identifying potential alternative sourcing, if relevant; and</para><para>(e) Assess the level of risk to the State of Nebraska associated with such a disruption in sourcing for each procurement that is threatened in the event of a Pacific conflict.</para><para>(3) The Department of Administrative Services may contract with a private consultant to assist with the review and report required under this section, and such contract need not be competitively bid.</para><para>(4) Information contained in the report required under this section is confidential. Unauthorized public disclosure of such confidential information is a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1300, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>