<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,133.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,133.01</statuteno><catchline>Other officials and contestants; license required; fees; revocation of license.</catchline><para>The State Athletic Commissioner may grant licenses to qualified physicians, managers, matchmakers, and professional mixed martial arts, professional boxing, or professional sparring match or exhibition judges upon an application and payment of an annual fee set by the commissioner in rule and regulation. Such fee for matchmakers shall be not less than ten dollars and not more than one hundred dollars. Such fee for physicians, managers, and professional mixed martial arts, professional boxing, or professional sparring match or exhibition judges shall be not less than ten dollars and not more than twenty dollars. The commissioner may also grant licenses to qualified timekeepers, contestants, and seconds upon an application and payment of an annual fee set by the commissioner in rule and regulation. Such fee shall be not less than ten dollars and not more than twenty dollars. The application shall include the applicant's social security number. No person shall serve as physician, manager, matchmaker, or judge at any professional mixed martial arts, professional boxing, or professional sparring match or exhibition who is not licensed as such. No person shall serve as timekeeper or contestant at any professional mixed martial arts or professional boxing match who is not licensed as such. The commissioner shall have summary authority to stop any match at which any person is serving in violation of the provisions of this section. Any license granted under the provisions of this section may be revoked for cause.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 501, &#167; 1, p. 1604; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 849, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 980, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 223; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 482, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB471, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB869, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB291, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>May 27, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>