<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,239.05">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,239.05</statuteno><catchline>Indemnification of state officials
and employees; when; Attorney General; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1)
The State of Nebraska shall indemnify its officials and employees and its
past officials and employees for money damages and reasonable costs incurred
as a result of an act or omission occurring in the course and scope of employment
of such official or employee after May 22, 1981. Such official's or employee's
right to indemnification shall include the payments of awards, settlements,
and associated costs, including appeal bonds and reasonable costs associated
with a required appearance before any tribunal.</para>
<para>(2) Subsection (1) of this section shall not apply in case of malfeasance
in office or willful or wanton neglect of duty. This section shall not be
interpreted as an expansion of any state official's or employee's personal
liability.</para>
<para>(3) The Attorney General shall notify the Risk Manager when an official
or employee is being represented by the Attorney General or has engaged competent
counsel approved by the Attorney General. The reasonable costs of litigation,
including appeal bonds, or the reasonable costs of any appearance before any
tribunal shall be paid by the Risk Manager from the State Self-Insured Indemnification
Fund.</para>
<para>(4) The Attorney General shall file copies of all awards and settlements
and any final court approval with the Risk Manager and shall request that
the Risk Manager make the required payments, if funds are available, from
the State Self-Insured Indemnification Fund, except that any portion of an
award or settlement which is for punitive damages may only be paid with the
approval of the Legislature. The official or employee may file a claim under
the State Miscellaneous Claims Act if payment is not made.</para>
<para>(5) The Risk Manager shall report electronically all
claims and judgments paid from the State Self-Insured Indemnification Fund
to the Clerk of the Legislature annually. The report shall include the name
of the claimant, the amount claimed and paid, and a brief description of the
claim, including any agency, program, and activity under which the claim arose.
Any member of the Legislature may receive an electronic copy of the
report by making a request to the Risk Manager.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 273, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1208, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 77, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB256, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 176.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Miscellaneous Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,294.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>