<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,133"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,133</statuteno><catchline>Referees; license; duties; fee.</catchline><para>The State Athletic Commissioner is authorized to grant licenses to competent referees, upon an application and the payment of a fee set by the commissioner in rule and regulation. Such fee shall be not less than ten dollars and not more than forty dollars per annum. The commissioner may revoke any license so granted for such cause as may be deemed sufficient. At every professional boxing, professional mixed martial arts, professional kickboxing, professional bare-knuckle boxing, amateur mixed martial arts, or professional sparring match or exhibition, there shall be in attendance a duly licensed referee, who shall direct and control the match. The referee shall stop the match whenever he or she deems it advisable, (1) because of the physical condition of the contestants or one of them, (2) when one of the contestants is clearly outclassed by his or her opponent, or (3) for any other sufficient reason. The referee shall, at the termination of every professional boxing, professional mixed martial arts, professional kickboxing, professional bare-knuckle boxing, amateur mixed martial arts, or professional sparring match or exhibition, indicate a winner. The fees of the referee and other licensed officials may be fixed by the commissioner and shall be paid by the licensed organization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 382, &#167; 6, p. 1328; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 849, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 482, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB471, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB869, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB291, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB70, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>