<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id615"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-6,127"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-6,127</statuteno><catchline>Health Information Technology Board; created; members; expenses; quorum.</catchline><para>(1) The Health Information Technology Board is created. The board shall have seventeen members. Except for members designated in subdivision (2)(o) of this section, the members shall be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the members of the Legislature. The members may begin to serve immediately following appointment and prior to approval by the Legislature. The members shall be appointed by February 1, 2021, and the board shall begin meeting on or before April 1, 2021.</para><para>(2) Members designated under subdivisions (b), (c), (d), (e), (g), (h), and (i) of this subsection shall hold a credential under the Uniform Credentialing Act. Except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section, the board shall consist of:</para><para>(a) One individual who has experience in operating the prescription drug monitoring program created under section 71-2454;</para><para>(b) Two physicians, one of whom shall be a family practice physician, who are in active practice and in good standing with the Department of Health and Human Services appointed from a list of physicians provided by a statewide organization representing physicians;</para><para>(c) One pharmacist who is in active practice and in good standing with the department appointed from a list of pharmacists provided by a statewide organization representing pharmacists;</para><para>(d) One alcohol and drug counselor providing services for a state-licensed alcohol and drug abuse addiction treatment program;</para><para>(e) One health care provider who is board-certified in pain management;</para><para>(f) One hospital administrator appointed from a list of hospital administrators provided by a statewide organization representing hospital administrators;</para><para>(g) One dentist who is in active practice and in good standing with the department appointed from a list of dentists provided by a statewide organization representing dentists;</para><para>(h) One nurse practitioner who is in active practice and in good standing with the department authorized to prescribe medication appointed from a list of nurse practitioners authorized to prescribe medication provided by a statewide organization representing such nurse practitioners;</para><para>(i) One veterinarian who is in active practice and in good standing with the department appointed from a list of veterinarians provided by a statewide organization representing veterinarians;</para><para>(j) One representative of the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(k) One representative of a delegate as defined in section 71-2454;</para><para>(l) One health care payor as defined in section 25-21,247 or an employee of a health care payor;</para><para>(m) One credentialed health information management professional appointed from a list of such professionals provided by a statewide organization representing such professionals;</para><para>(n) One representative of the statewide health information exchange described in section 71-2455; and</para><para>(o) The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and the chairperson of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature, both of whom are nonvoting, ex officio members.</para><para>(3) Except for members designated in subdivisions (2)(a) and (o) of this section:</para><para>(a) A minimum of three members shall be appointed from each congressional district;</para><para>(b) Each member shall be appointed for a five-year term beginning on April 1, 2021, and may serve for any number of such terms;</para><para>(c) Any member appointed prior to April 1, 2021, shall begin to serve immediately upon appointment and continue serving for the term beginning on April 1, 2021; and</para><para>(d) Any vacancy in membership, other than by expiration of a term, shall be filled within ninety days by the Governor by appointment for the vacant position as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) If, after appointment, the classification of a member's credential changes or a member's credential classification is terminated and if such credential was a qualification for appointment, the member shall be permitted to continue to serve as a member of the board until the expiration of the term for which appointed unless the member loses the credential due to disciplinary action.</para><para>(5) The members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in serving on the board as provided in section 71-2455.</para><para>(6) A simple majority of members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of all business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1183, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>