<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-642"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-642</statuteno><catchline>Cancer registry; legislative intent; information released.</catchline><para>It is the intent of the Legislature to require the establishment and maintenance of a cancer registry for the State of Nebraska. This responsibility is delegated to the Department of Health and Human Services along with the authority to exercise the necessary powers to implement sections 81-642 to 81-650. To insure an accurate and continuing source of data concerning cancer, all hospitals within the state shall make available to the department upon its request, at least once a year, information contained in the medical records of patients who have cancer within such time following its diagnosis as the department shall require. Any medical doctor, osteopathic physician, or dentist within the state shall make such information available to the department upon request by the department. This cancer registry should provide a central data bank of accurate, precise, and current information which medical authorities state will assist in the research for the prevention, cure, and control of cancer. The information contained in the cancer registry may be used as a source of data for scientific and medical research. Any information released from the cancer registry shall be disclosed as Class I, Class II, Class III, or Class IV data as provided in sections 81-663 to 81-675.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 212, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 342, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 113; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 848; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 739.</para></source></law></legaldoc>