
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-118.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-118.01</statuteno><catchline>Electronic payment; acceptance; conditions; central bank digital currency; acceptance prohibited.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any state official or state agency may accept credit cards, charge cards, or debit cards, whether presented in person or electronically, or electronic funds transfers as a method of cash payment of any tax, levy, excise, duty, custom, toll, interest, penalty, fine, license, fee, or assessment of whatever kind or nature, whether general or special, as provided by section 77-1702.</para><para>(b) A state official or state agency shall not accept a central bank digital currency as a method of cash payment of any tax, levy, excise, duty, custom, toll, interest, penalty, fine, license, fee, or assessment of whatever kind or nature.</para><para>(2) The total amount of such taxes, levies, excises, duties, customs, tolls, interest, penalties, fines, licenses, fees, or assessments of whatever kind or nature, whether general or special, paid for by credit card, charge card, debit card, or electronic funds transfer shall be collected by the state official or state agency.</para><para>(3) Any state official or state agency operating a facility in a proprietary capacity may choose to accept credit cards, charge cards, or debit cards, whether presented in person or electronically, or electronic funds transfers as a means of cash payment, and may adjust the price for services to reflect the handling and payment costs.</para><para>(4) The state official or state agency shall obtain, for each transaction, authorization for use of any credit card, charge card, or debit card used pursuant to this section from the financial institution, vending service company, credit card or charge card company, or third-party merchant bank providing such service.</para><para>(5) The types of credit cards, charge cards, or debit cards accepted and the payment services provided for any state official or state agency shall be determined by the State Treasurer and the Director of Administrative Services with the advice of the committee convened pursuant to subsection (5) of section 13-609. The State Treasurer and the director shall contract with one or more credit card, charge card, or debit card companies or third-party merchant banks for services on behalf of the state and those counties, cities, and political subdivisions that choose to participate in the state contract for such services. Any negotiated discount, processing, or transaction fee imposed by a credit card, charge card, or debit card company or third-party merchant bank shall be considered, for purposes of this section, as an administrative expense.</para><para>(6) A state official or state agency obtaining, for each transaction, authorization for use of any credit card or charge card used pursuant to this section may, but is not required to, impose a surcharge or convenience fee upon the person making a payment by credit card or charge card so as to wholly or partially offset the amount of any discount or administrative fees charged to the state agency, but the surcharge or convenience fee shall not exceed the surcharge or convenience fee imposed by the credit card or charge card companies or third-party merchant banks which have contracted under subsection (5) of this section. The surcharge or convenience fee shall be applied only when allowed by the operating rules and regulations of the credit card or charge card involved or when authorized in writing by the credit card or charge card company involved. When a person elects to make a payment to a state agency by credit card or charge card and such a surcharge or convenience fee is imposed, the payment of such surcharge or convenience fee shall be deemed voluntary by such person and shall be in no case refundable. If a payment is made electronically by credit card, charge card, debit card, or electronic funds transfer as part of a system for providing or retrieving information electronically, the state official or state agency shall be authorized but not required to impose an additional surcharge or convenience fee upon the person making a payment.</para><para>(7) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Central bank digital currency means a digital medium of exchange, token, or monetary unit of account issued by the United States Federal Reserve System or any analogous federal agency that is made directly available to the consumer by such federal entities. Central bank digital currency includes a digital medium of exchange, token, or monetary unit of account so issued that is processed or validated directly by such federal entities; and</para><para>(b) Electronic funds transfer means the movement of funds by nonpaper means, usually through a payment system, including, but not limited to, an automated clearinghouse or the Federal Reserve's Fedwire system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 612, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 70, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 994, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 97. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>