<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id801"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,282" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,282</statuteno><catchline>Adulteration of food; prohibited; adulteration, defined; deceptive trade practice.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall adulterate any food or manufacture, produce, import, distribute, promote, display for sale, offer for sale, attempt to sell, or sell any adulterated food.</para><para>(2) Food shall be deemed to be adulterated if:</para><para>(a) It bears or contains any substance which may render it injurious to health, considering the quantity of such substance in or on the food;</para><para>(b) It consists in whole or in part of any diseased, contaminated, filthy, putrid, or decomposed substance or is otherwise unsafe for use as food;</para><para>(c) It has been manufactured, processed, packaged, stored, or held under insanitary conditions where it may have become unsafe for use as food;</para><para>(d) It is the product of a diseased animal or one that has died by any means other than slaughter;</para><para>(e) It is a cultivated-protein food product;</para><para>(f) Its container is so constructed as to render the food unsafe or otherwise injurious to health; or</para><para>(g) Any valuable constituent of the food has been wholly or partially omitted or abstracted.</para><para>(3)(a) Any violation of this section that is committed in the course of business, vocation, or occupation shall, additionally and separately, constitute a deceptive trade practice.</para><para>(b) This section shall not be construed to affect the liability for any action that violates the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 487, &#167; 32; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 81-216.28; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 358, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB246, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act,</emphasis> see section 87-306.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>