<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-638"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>81-638</statuteno><catchline>Cancer and smoking disease research; appropriation; distribution; contracts; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to subsection (4) of this section, the Legislature shall appropriate for each year from the Health and Human Services Cash Fund to the department an amount derived from one cent of the cigarette tax imposed by section 77-2602, less any amount appropriated from the fund specifically to the University of Nebraska Eppley Institute for Research in Cancer and Allied Diseases. The department shall, after deducting expenses incurred in the administration of such funds, distribute such funds exclusively for grants and contracts for research of cancer and smoking diseases, for funding the cancer registry prescribed in sections 81-642 to 81-650, and for associated expenses due to the establishment and maintenance of such cancer registry. Not more than two hundred thousand dollars shall be appropriated for funding the cancer registry and associated expenses. The University of Nebraska may receive such grants and contracts, and other postsecondary institutions having colleges of medicine located in the State of Nebraska may receive such contracts.</para><para>(2) Subject to subsection (4) of this section, the Legislature shall appropriate for each year from the Health and Human Services Cash Fund to the department for cancer research an amount derived from two cents of the cigarette tax imposed by section 77-2602 to be used exclusively for grants and contracts for research on cancer and smoking diseases. No amount shall be appropriated or used pursuant to this subsection for the operation and associated expenses of the cancer registry. Not more than one-half of the funds appropriated pursuant to this subsection shall be distributed to the University of Nebraska Medical Center for research in cancer and allied diseases and the University of Nebraska Eppley Institute for Research in Cancer and Allied Diseases. The remaining funds available pursuant to this subsection shall be distributed for contracts with other postsecondary educational institutions having colleges of medicine located in Nebraska which have cancer research programs for the purpose of conducting research in cancer and allied diseases.</para><para>(3) Any contract between the department and another postsecondary educational institution for cancer research under subsection (2) of this section shall provide that:</para><para>(a) Any money appropriated for such contract shall only be used for cancer research and shall not be used to support any other program in the institution;</para><para>(b) Full and detailed reporting of the expenditure of all funds under the contract is required. The report shall include, but not be limited to, separate accounting for personal services, equipment purchases or leases, and supplies. Such reports shall be made available electronically to the Legislature; and</para><para>(c) No money appropriated for such contract shall be spent for travel, building construction, or any other purpose not directly related to the research that is the subject of the contract.</para><para>(4) The State Treasurer shall transfer seven million dollars from the Health and Human Services Cash Fund to the General Fund on or before June 30, 2018, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. It is the intent of the Legislature that the transfer to the General Fund in this subsection be from funds credited to the Cancer Research subfund of the Health and Human Services Cash Fund which were in excess of appropriations established in subsections (1) and (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 506, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 192, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 925, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 595, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 847; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 736; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 167; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 48. </para><effectivedate>May 16, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>