<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id67">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id69" statutenumber="81-8,210"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id71">81-8,210</statuteno><catchline id="id72">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the State Tort Claims Act:</para>
<para>(1) State agency includes all departments, agencies, boards,
bureaus, and commissions of the State of Nebraska and corporations the primary
function of which is to act as, and while acting as, instrumentalities or
agencies of the State of Nebraska but shall not include corporations that
are essentially private corporations or entities created pursuant to the Interlocal
Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act. State agency does not include
any contractor with the State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(2) State Claims Board means the board created by section
81-8,220;</para>
<para>(3) Employee of the state means any one or more officers or
employees of the state or any state agency and shall include duly appointed
members of boards or commissions when they are acting in their official capacity.
State employee does not include any employee of an entity created pursuant
to the Interlocal Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act or any contractor
with the State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(4) Tort claim means any claim against the State of Nebraska
for money only on account of damage to or loss of property or on account of
personal injury or death caused by the negligent or wrongful act or omission
of any employee of the state, while acting within the scope of his or her
office or employment, under circumstances in which the state, if a private
person, would be liable to the claimant for such damage, loss, injury, or
death but does not include any claim accruing before January 1, 1970, any claim against an employee
of the state for money only on account of damage to or loss of property or
on account of personal injury or death caused by the negligent or wrongful
act or omission of the employee while acting within the scope of his or her
employment occurring on or after August 25, 1989, and any claim allowed under the Nebraska Claims for Wrongful
Conviction and Imprisonment Act;</para>
<para>(5) Award means any amount determined by the Risk Manager
or State Claims Board to be payable to a claimant under section 81-8,211 or
the amount of any compromise or settlement under section 81-8,218; and</para>
<para>(6) Risk Manager means the Risk Manager appointed under section
81-8,239.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 756, &#167; 2, p. 2845; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 541, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 81, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB821, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB260, &#167;  10.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Claims for Wrongful Conviction and Imprisonment Act,</emphasis> see section 29-4601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, for purposes of filing a claim against a mental health board or its members, the boards of mental health in Nebraska are state agencies within the meaning of the State Tort Claims Act. Zimmerman v. Douglas Cty. Hosp., 252 Neb. 583, 563 N.W.2d 349 (1997).</para><para>A claim for remuneration for services rendered pursuant to a contract is not a "tort claim" as defined in this section. Plaintiff's claim was therefore not subject to the exclusive jurisdiction of the tort claims board. L. J. Vontz Constr. Co. v. State, 230 Neb. 377, 432 N.W.2d 7 (1988).</para><para>The State Tort Claims Act provides for liability of the state the same as a private person under like circumstances. Cortes v. State, 191 Neb. 795, 218 N.W.2d 214 (1974).</para><para>Claims for injunctive relief need not be brought under the Tort Claims Act. Czarnick v. Loup River P.P. Dist., 190 Neb. 521, 209 N.W.2d 595 (1973).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>