<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,300"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,300</statuteno><catchline>Risk Manager; State Claims Board;
claims; filing; investigation; duties; review by Legislature; payment.</catchline>
<para>(1) After
investigation, the Risk Manager or State Claims Board shall either approve,
approve with conditions or limitations, or disapprove of each claim or request
and append to the claim or request a concise statement of the facts brought
out in such investigation upon which its approval or disapproval is based.
If any claim is approved in an amount of more than five thousand dollars,
the approval of the board is required. Such claim or request, together with
the original papers supporting it and the appended statement, shall be filed
with the Risk Manager in the manner prescribed by the State Claims Board.
The Risk Manager shall promptly notify each claimant of the decision by the
Risk Manager or State Claims Board on his or her claim by regular mail. The
notification shall include (a) the decision of the Risk
Manager or State Claims Board, (b) a statement that a claimant
dissatisfied with the decision of the Risk Manager may have his or her claim
reviewed by the board or a statement that a claimant dissatisfied with the
decision of the board may have his or her claim reviewed by the Legislature
upon application, (c) the procedure for making
an application for review, and (d) the time limit for making
such application.</para>
<para>(2) If the
claimant is dissatisfied with the decision of the Risk Manager, he or she
may file an application for review by the board. If the claimant is dissatisfied
with the decision of the board, he or she may file an application for review
by the Legislature. The application for review shall be filed with the Risk
Manager in the manner prescribed by the board. The application for review
shall be filed within sixty days after the date of the decision which is being
reviewed.</para>
<para>(3) Each
claim which has been approved or for which an application for review with
the Legislature has been filed and each request referred to in section 81-8,297
shall be delivered electronically by
the Risk Manager to the chairperson of the Business and Labor Committee of
the Legislature at the next regular session of the Legislature convening after
the date of the decision of the board. The Risk Manager may direct the payment
by the state agency involved of any claim not in excess of five thousand dollars
if such payment is agreed to by the head of the agency involved. The State
Claims Board may direct payment by the state agency involved of any claim
not in excess of fifty thousand dollars if such payment is agreed to by the
head of the agency involved and the agency has sufficient funds to pay the
claim. If claims approved by the Risk Manager or State Claims Board arise
out of the same facts and circumstances, they shall be aggregated. If the
Risk Manager or State Claims Board does not direct the payment of a claim
as set forth in this section or the claim exceeds the dollar limitations set
forth in this section, the claim shall be reviewed by the Legislature and
an appropriation made therefor if appropriate. The Risk Manager shall report electronically all claims
and judgments paid under the State Miscellaneous Claims Act to the Clerk of
the Legislature and the chairperson of the Business
and Labor Committee of the Legislature. The report shall include the name
of the claimant, a statement of the amount claimed and paid, and a brief description
of the claim including the agency and program or activity under which the
claim arose. Any member of the Legislature may receive an
electronic copy of the report by making a request to the Risk
Manager.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 129, &#167; 5, p. 433; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-861; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 438, &#167; 1, p. 1474; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 427, &#167; 3, p. 1336; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 588, &#167; 3, p. 2001; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1967, &#167; 81-861; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 756, &#167; 31, p. 2854; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 565, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 273, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1028, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 81-8,239; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB821, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 178.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>