<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id13"  statutenumber="81-885.16" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.16</statuteno><catchline>Real Property Appraiser Act; applicability; broker's price opinion or comparative market analysis; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The Real Property Appraiser Act shall not apply to a person licensed under the Nebraska Real Estate License Act who, in the ordinary course of his or her business, gives a broker's price opinion or comparative market analysis, except that such opinion or analysis shall not be referred to as an appraisal.</para><para>(2) No compensation, fee, or other consideration shall be charged for a broker's price opinion or comparative market analysis other than a real estate commission or brokerage fee charged or paid for brokerage services rendered in connection with the sale of the real estate involved unless the opinion or analysis is in writing, is signed by the preparer, includes the date on which it was prepared, and contains or has attached thereto the following disclosure in bold fourteen-point type: This opinion or analysis is not an appraisal. It is intended only for the benefit of the addressee for the purpose of assisting buyers or sellers or prospective buyers or sellers in deciding the listing, offering, or sale price of the real property, for lending purposes in a transaction other than a federally related transaction, or for real property tax appeal purposes. This opinion or analysis is not governed by the Real Property Appraiser Act.</para><para>(3) A broker's price opinion or comparative market analysis prepared for an existing or potential lienholder originating, extending, renewing, or modifying a loan in a transaction other than a federally related transaction may not be used as the sole basis to determine the value of the real estate for the purpose of originating a loan secured by such real estate, and the person giving the opinion or analysis must be engaged directly by the lienholder or its agent. Such person shall have no duty to inquire as to any other basis used to determine such value.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB375, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Real Property Appraiser Act,</emphasis> see section 76-2201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>