<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 1, 2009">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-188.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-188.04</statuteno><catchline>University Building Renewal Assessment
Fund; capital improvement project; depreciation charges.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of this section, capital improvement project means (a) construction
of a new facility, structure, or building, (b) construction of additions to
an existing facility, structure, or building, (c) renovation of an existing
facility, structure, or building if the total project cost of such renovation
represents not less than fifteen percent of the value of the existing facility,
structure, or building as determined by the Department of Administrative Services,
(d) purchase of an existing facility, structure, or building, and (e) acquisition
of a facility, structure, or building through means of conveyance other than
sale and purchase.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning with the fiscal year that commences subsequent to the
calendar year in which has occurred substantial completion of a capital improvement
project by the University of Nebraska as defined in subdivisions (1)(a) through
(1)(c) of this section or acquisition of a capital improvement project by
the University of Nebraska as defined in subdivisions (1)(d) and (1)(e) of
this section, the department shall assess a capital improvement depreciation
charge to the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and shall assess
such charge for each fiscal year thereafter,
except that no depreciation charges shall be assessed or paid pursuant to
this section for the period beginning July 1, 2009, and ending June 30, 2011.</para>
<para>(3) The annual depreciation charge for a capital improvement project
as defined in subdivisions (1)(a) through (1)(c) of this section shall be
computed as one percent of the total project cost of the capital improvement
project. The annual depreciation charge for a capital improvement project
as defined in subdivision (1)(d) of this section shall be computed as one
percent of the greater of the purchase price or the value, as determined by
the department, of the capital improvement project at the time of acquisition.
The annual depreciation charge for a capital improvement project as defined
in subdivision (1)(e) of this section shall be computed as one percent of
the value, as determined by the department, of the capital improvement project
at the time of acquisition. The department may assess the charge annually
or in monthly, quarterly, or semiannual installments.</para>
<para>(4) Depreciation charges shall not be assessed pursuant to this section
for capital improvement projects relating to facilities, structures, or buildings
from which revenue is derived and pledged for the retirement of revenue bonds
issued under sections 85-403 to 85-411.</para>
<para>(5) Payment of depreciation charges assessed pursuant to this section
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the University Building
Renewal Assessment Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 410, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB318, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>