<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-549"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-549</statuteno><catchline>Transportation of gas; operation of pipeline facilities; records; reports; inspection; State Fire Marshal; duties; confidential information.</catchline><para>(1) Each person who engages in the transportation of gas or who owns or operates pipeline facilities shall establish and maintain such records, make such reports, and provide such information as the State Fire Marshal may reasonably require to enable him or her to determine whether such person has acted or is acting in compliance with the Nebraska Natural Gas Pipeline Safety Act of 1969 and the standards established under the act. Each such person shall, upon request of an officer, employee, or agent authorized by the State Fire Marshal, permit such officer, employee, or agent to inspect books, papers, records, and documents relevant to determining whether such person has acted or is acting in compliance with the act and the standards established pursuant to the act. For purposes of enforcement, officers, employees, or agents authorized by the State Fire Marshal, upon presenting appropriate credentials to the individual in charge, are authorized (a) to enter upon, at reasonable times, pipeline facilities and (b) to inspect, at reasonable times and within reasonable limits and in a reasonable manner, such facilities. Each such inspection shall be commenced and completed with reasonable promptness.</para><para>(2) In the course of the exercise of his or her duties and responsibilities under the act, the State Fire Marshal shall wherever practicable employ a practice of spot checking and issuance of certificates of compliance, with respect to persons subject to the act, to limit costs of enforcement of the safety standards established pursuant to section 81-543.</para><para>(3) All information reported to or otherwise obtained by the State Fire Marshal or his or her representative pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, which information contains or relates to a trade secret as referred to in 18 U.S.C. 1905 or otherwise constitutes a trade secret under law, shall be considered confidential for the purpose of such laws, except that such information may be disclosed to other officers or employees concerned with carrying out the act or when relevant in any proceeding under the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 763, &#167; 8, p. 2889; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 858, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>