<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-202</statuteno><catchline>Department of Agriculture; State Veterinarian; office created; appointment; salary; qualifications; exercise of powers.</catchline><para>Within the Department of Agriculture there shall be the position of State Veterinarian appointed by and subordinate only to the Director of Agriculture. The powers and duties of the department provided by law for the protection of the health of livestock as defined in section 54-2921 shall be exercised and discharged through the department under the direction of the State Veterinarian. The State Veterinarian shall hold office at the will of the director. The State Veterinarian shall receive such salary as fixed by the director and approved by the Governor. The State Veterinarian shall have authority to employ assistants and fix their compensation, subject to the approval of the director. The State Veterinarian shall be a graduate of a college of veterinary medicine accredited by the American Veterinary Medical Association, shall be licensed and accredited as a veterinarian, and shall have demonstrated administrative ability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 149, &#167; 4, p. 572; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 81-107; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-202; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 419, &#167; 2, p. 1282; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 334, &#167; 9, p. 958; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 267, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB344, &#167; 79. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For livestock,</emphasis> general provisions, see Chapter 54.</para><para><emphasis>For pathogenic microorganisms,</emphasis> see sections 71-1801 to 71-1805.</para><para><emphasis>Veterinary Medicine and Surgery Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-3301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>