<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-521"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-521</statuteno><catchline>Fire insurance companies; reports to State Fire Marshal required; copies mailed to fire department of certain cities.</catchline><para>Every fire insurance company authorized to transact business in this state is required to report to the State Fire Marshal, through the secretary or other officer of the company designated by the board of directors for that purpose, all fire losses on property insured in any such company, giving the date of fire, the amount of probable loss, the character of property destroyed or damaged, and the supposed cause of the fire, together with the amount of insurance carried by such company. Such report shall be mailed to the State Fire Marshal within thirty days after notice of loss is received by such company. Each company is also required to report the amount of loss adjusted on each fire to the State Fire Marshal within thirty days after adjustment is made. Such report shall be in addition to any, and not in lieu of any, report or reports such companies may be required to make by any law of this state to the Director of Insurance; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that in the case of a fire of suspicious origin a preliminary report shall be made immediately through some officer of the insurance company showing the name of the assured, the date of fire, location, occupancy, and such facts and circumstances as shall come to his knowledge, tending to establish the cause or origin of the fire; <emphasis type="italic">and provided further,</emphasis> that copies of the reports required by this section concerning any city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class shall be mailed by the insurance company concerned to the fire department of such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 183, &#167; 20, p. 487; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-5520; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-521; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 550, &#167; 1, p. 1799. </para></source></law></legaldoc>