<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-520.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-520.05</statuteno><catchline>Land-management burning; application
for permit; plan; contents; fire chief; duties.</catchline><para>(1) A landowner,
tenant, or other landowner's agent of the land where land-management burning is proposed shall file
an application for a permit and a plan for conducting such burning. The plan
shall include:</para>
<para>(a) The name of the landowner of the land on which land-management burning is to occur;</para>
<para>(b) The name of the person who will supervise the land-management burning if such person is different
than the landowner;</para>
<para>(c) The land-management objective to be accomplished;</para>
<para>(d) A map showing the areas to be burned, including natural and manmade
firebreaks;</para>
<para>(e) Procedures to be used to confine the fire in boundary areas without
preexisting firebreaks;</para>
<para>(f) A list of equipment that will be on hand;</para>
<para>(g) The types and conditions of the vegetative matter to be burned on
the land and in adjacent areas;</para>
<para>(h) Identification of roads and habitations that may be affected by
smoke;</para>
<para>(i) A description of weather conditions believed to be required to safely
and successfully conduct the land-management burning, including
wind speed and direction, temperature, and relative humidity; and</para>
<para>(j) Such other information as may be prescribed by the fire chief of
a local fire department.</para>
<para>(2) The fire chief of a local fire department shall evaluate each plan
to determine its compliance with subsection (1) of this section. If a plan
fails to comply with all provisions of such subsection, a permit for land-management burning shall
not be issued.</para>
<para>(3) The fire chief of a local fire department shall issue a permit
for land-management burning if
(a) the plan complies with subsection (1) of this section and (b) the fire
chief determines
that land-management burning conducted
in accordance with the plan would be conducted with due regard for the safety
of people and property outside the burning areas. No permit shall be valid
for more than thirty days.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 408, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB248, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>