<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-161.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-161.04</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Materiel division; surplus property; sale; procedure; proceeds of sale, how credited.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever any using agency has any personal property for which it no longer has any need or use, it shall notify the materiel division in writing setting forth a description of the property and the approximate length of time that the property has been in the possession of the using agency. The materiel division shall appraise the property and notify all other using agencies of the state that the materiel division has the property for sale and that the property can be bought at the appraised price. No property will be sold until first offered to using agencies as provided by this section unless the property is unusable. If the materiel division fails to receive an offer from any using agency, it may sell or dispose of the property by any method which is most advantageous to the State of Nebraska, including auction, sealed bid, private or public sale, or trade-in for other property, with priorities given to the other political subdivisions. All sales shall be made in the name of the State of Nebraska. The materiel division shall charge an administrative fee for the disposition of surplus property. Such administrative fee shall be a percentage of the amount of the sale of the surplus property. In the event surplus property is determined to have no market value, the materiel administrator may waive the administrative fee.</para><para id="id00">(2) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the proceeds of the sales shall be deposited with the State Treasurer and credited to the General Fund unless the using agency certifies to the materiel division that the property was purchased in part or in total from either cash accounts or federal funds or from a percentage of such accounts or funds, in which case the proceeds of the sale to that extent shall be credited to the cash or federal account in the percentage used in originally purchasing the property. The cost of selling surplus property shall be deducted from the proceeds of the surplus property sold. The proceeds received from the sale of passenger-carrying motor vehicles originally purchased with money from the General Fund, other than passenger-carrying motor vehicles used by the Nebraska State Patrol, less selling costs, shall be deposited in the state treasury and credited by the State Treasurer to the Transportation Services Bureau Revolving Fund. The proceeds received from the sale of passenger-carrying motor vehicles used by the Nebraska State Patrol, less selling costs, shall be deposited in the state treasury and credited by the State Treasurer to the Nebraska State Patrol Vehicle Replacement Cash Fund. The proceeds received from the sale of micrographic equipment, other than that of the University of Nebraska and state colleges, less selling costs, shall be deposited in the state treasury and credited by the State Treasurer to the Records Management Micrographics Services Revolving Fund. The proceeds received from the sale of aircraft, less selling costs, shall be deposited in the state treasury and credited by the State Treasurer to the Aeronautics Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 215, &#167; 9, p. 706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-153; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 310, &#167; 1(2), p. 943; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 1071; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-153.01; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 508, &#167; 13, p. 1621; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 781, &#167; 1, p. 2958; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1452, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 447, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 559, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 590, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 381, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 274. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>