<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-550"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-550</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Natural Gas Pipeline Safety
Cash Fund; created; use; investment; assessments.</catchline><para>(1) The
Nebraska Natural Gas Pipeline Safety Cash Fund is created. The fund shall
consist of money received from assessments pursuant to this section which
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. Transfers may be made from the fund to
the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature through June 30, 2010. The Nebraska Natural Gas Pipeline Safety Cash Fund shall be used for purposes
of administering the Nebraska Natural Gas Pipeline Safety Act of 1969. The
fund shall be administered by the State Fire Marshal. Any money in the fund
available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) To defray the cost of administering the Nebraska Natural Gas Pipeline
Safety Act of 1969, the State Fire Marshal shall on March 1 of each year make
an assessment against persons having pipeline facilities in this state subject
to the act, which assessment shall be paid within thirty days thereafter.</para>
<para>(3) The assessment against each such person shall be based on the number
of meters such person has in service for the retail sale of gas in this state
at the end of the calendar year next preceding such assessment. The amount
of such assessment shall be set by the State Fire Marshal in an amount not
to exceed twenty cents multiplied by the number of such meters for each such
person.</para>
<para>(4) It shall be the duty of the State Fire Marshal to make timely application
each year to the United States Government for the maximum funds to which this
state may be entitled from the United States Government for the administration
of the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 763, &#167; 9, p. 2890; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 410, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 383, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 858, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 66.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>