<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id398">
<sectno id="id399" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 30.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id400" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-6,120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-6,120</statuteno><catchline>Transportation services; restrictions
on providers; criminal history record information check required; fingerprinting;
costs; release of results; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No individual who has been convicted
of a felony or of any crime involving moral turpitude, or who has been charged
with or indicted for a felony or crime involving moral turpitude and there
has been no final resolution of the prosecution of the crime, shall provide
transportation services under contract with the Department of Health and Human
Services, whether as an employee or as a volunteer, for vulnerable adults
as defined in section 28-371 or for persons under nineteen years of age.</para>
<para>(2) In order
to assure compliance with subsection (1) of this section, any individual who
will be providing such transportation services to such vulnerable adults or
persons under nineteen years of age and any individual who is providing such
services on August 30, 2009, shall be subject to a national criminal history
record information check by the Department of Health and Human Services through
the Nebraska State Patrol.</para><para>(3) In addition to the national criminal history record information
check required in subsection (2) of this section, all individuals employed
to provide transportation services under contract with the Department of Health
and Human Services to vulnerable adults or persons under nineteen years of
age shall submit to a national criminal history record information check every
two years during the period of such employment.</para><para>(4) Individuals shall
submit two full sets of fingerprints to the Nebraska State Patrol to be submitted
to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for the national criminal history record
information check required under this section. The individual shall pay the
actual cost of fingerprinting and the national criminal history record information
check.</para><para>(5)(a) Individuals shall authorize release of the results and contents
of a national criminal history record information check under this section
to the employer and the Department of Health and Human Services as provided
in this section.</para><para>(b) The Nebraska State Patrol shall not release the contents of
a national criminal history record information check under this section to
the employer or the individual but shall only indicate in writing to the employer
and the individual whether the individual has a criminal record.</para>
<para>(c) The Nebraska
State Patrol shall release the results and the contents of a national criminal
history record information check under this section in writing to the department
in accordance with applicable federal law.</para><para>(6) The Department of Health and Human
Services may develop and implement policies that provide for administrative
exceptions to the prohibition in subsection (1) of this section, including,
but not limited to, situations in which relatives of the vulnerable adult
or person under nineteen years of age provide transportation services for
such vulnerable adult or person under nineteen years of age or situations
in which the circumstances of the crime or the elapsed time since the commission
of the crime do not warrant the prohibition. Any decision made by the department
regarding an administrative exception under this section is discretionary
and is not appealable.</para><para>(7) An individual who does not comply with this section is guilty
of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 30.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>