<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id5" statutenumber="81-132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-132</statuteno><catchline id="id8">State budget; departmental budget estimates; duty to submit; contents; proposed changes; filing.</catchline><para>(1) All departments, offices, institutions, and expending agencies of the state government requesting appropriations for the next biennium shall file in the office of the Director of Administrative Services the budget forms furnished them by the director under the provisions of sections 81-1113 and 81-1113.01. Such budget forms shall be filed on or before September 15 of each even-numbered year. The forms shall show their total estimated requirements for the next biennium for each unit of their organization and activity classified as to object of expenditure. With such forms, each department, office, institution, and expending agency shall file a report showing all money received by such department, office, institution, or expending agency together with the estimated receipts for the next biennium. Such estimates shall be accompanied by a statement in writing giving facts and explanations of reasons for each item of increased appropriation requested. The report submitted by the Department of Health and Human Services shall include, but not be limited to, the key goals, benchmarks, and progress reports required pursuant to sections 81-3133 to 81-3133.03.</para><para>(2) Any department, office, institution, or expending agency proposing changes to its appropriation for the biennium in progress shall file in the office of the Director of Administrative Services the budget forms for requesting such changes furnished by the director under the provisions of sections 81-1113 and 81-1113.01. Such forms shall be filed on or before October 24 of each odd-numbered year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 210, &#167; 8, p. 748; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7275; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-308; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-132; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 526, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 12, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB949, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1092, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>