<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-201.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-201.04</statuteno><catchline>Office services; billings and charges; Management Services Expense Revolving Fund; created; receipts; disbursements; investment.</catchline><para>In conjunction with providing services authorized pursuant to section 81-201.03, the Department of Agriculture shall develop a system of equitable billings and charges for such services. Such system of charges shall reflect, as nearly as may be practical, the actual share of costs incurred on behalf of or for such services to any board, commission, or political subdivision of the state or any other agency of the state or federal government. Any board, commission, or political subdivision of the state or any other agency of the state or federal government which uses such services shall pay for the services out of appropriated or available funds.</para><para>There is hereby created the Management Services Expense Revolving Fund. All gifts, grants, and fees or charges collected for such services from any source, including federal, state, public, or private sources, and any appropriation by the Legislature for such purpose shall be credited to such fund. Expenditures shall be made from the fund for the payment of expenses. Such payments shall be made by the Director of Agriculture. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 579, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 358, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 97. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>