<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.55"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.55</statuteno><catchline>Immunity from liability for activities; covered by Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act; licenses, not required; emergency management worker; powers, duties, immunities, privileges.</catchline><para>(1) All functions provided for in the Emergency Management Act and all other activities relating to emergency management are hereby declared to be governmental functions. The United States, the state, any political subdivision thereof, any other agencies of the United States, the state, or a political subdivision thereof, and, except in cases of willful misconduct, gross negligence, or bad faith, any emergency management worker complying with or reasonably attempting to comply with the provisions of the act, any emergency management act of Congress, or any order, rule, or regulation promulgated pursuant to the act or any emergency management act of Congress or acting pursuant to any ordinance relating to black-out or other precautionary measures enacted by any political subdivision of the state shall not be liable for the death of or injury to persons or for damage to property as a result of any such activity. This section shall not affect the right of any person to receive benefits to which he or she would otherwise be entitled under the Emergency Management Act, under the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act, or under any pension law or the right of any person to receive any benefits or compensation under any act of Congress.</para><para>(2) Any requirement for a license to practice any professional, mechanical, or other skill shall not apply to any authorized emergency management worker who in the course of performing duties as such practices such professional, mechanical, or other skill during a civil defense emergency or declared state of emergency.</para><para>(3) Any emergency management worker performing emergency management services at any place in this state pursuant to agreements, compacts, or arrangements for mutual aid and assistance to which the state or a political subdivision thereof is a party shall possess the same powers, duties, immunities, and privileges he or she would ordinarily possess if performing such duties in the state, province, or political subdivision thereof in which normally employed or rendering services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 315, &#167; 9, p. 1080; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 517, &#167; 1, p. 1633; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-829.21; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 612, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 35. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1,110.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>In order for the district court to have subject matter jurisdiction under the disaster and civil defense statutes, the plaintiff must allege facts which show either (1) that the political subdivision's actions were not undertaken when complying with or reasonably attempting to comply with the provisions relating to civil defense set forth in this section or an order, rule, or regulation promulgated thereunder and therefore the general immunity does not apply, or (2) that the political subdivision's actions constituted willful misconduct, gross negligence, or bad faith so as to fall within an exception to the general immunity. Lawry v. County of Sarpy, 254 Neb. 193, 575 N.W.2d 605 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>