<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-885.55"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.55</statuteno><catchline>Errors and omissions insurance; commission; duties; certificate of coverage; required; when; group plan unavailable at a reasonable premium; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Every licensee under the Nebraska Real Estate License Act, except an inactive broker or salesperson, shall have errors and omissions insurance to cover all activities contemplated under the act. The commission shall make the errors and omissions insurance available to all licensees by contracting with an insurer for a group policy after competitive bidding. Any group policy obtained by the commission shall be available to all licensees with no right on the part of the insurer to cancel any licensee. Licensees may obtain errors and omissions insurance independently if the coverage complies with the minimum requirements established by the commission.</para><para>(2) The commission shall determine the terms and conditions of coverage required under this section, including the minimum limits of coverage, the permissible deductible, and permissible exemptions. Each licensee shall be notified of the required terms and conditions at least thirty days prior to the annual license renewal date. A certificate of coverage showing compliance with the required terms and conditions shall be filed with the commission by the annual license renewal date by each licensee who does not participate in the group program administered by the commission.</para><para>(3) If the commission is unable to obtain errors and omissions insurance coverage to insure all licensees who choose to participate in the group program at a reasonable premium not to exceed five hundred dollars, the errors and omissions insurance requirement of this section shall not apply during the year for which coverage cannot be obtained.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 118, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 863, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 845, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>