<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,134"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,134</statuteno><catchline>Boxing, mixed martial arts, kickboxing, bare-knuckle boxing, or sparring matches; rules governing.</catchline><para>(1) Any professional boxing match, professional mixed martial arts match, professional kickboxing match, professional bare-knuckle boxing match, or amateur mixed martial arts match conducted in this state which is labeled or promoted as a championship match shall have regional or national significance and the approval of a nationally recognized professional boxing, mixed martial arts, kickboxing, or bare-knuckle boxing association.</para><para>(2) Professional boxing, professional kickboxing, professional bare-knuckle boxing, or professional sparring matches or exhibitions shall not exceed ten rounds in length, except in a championship match, which shall not exceed fifteen rounds. No round shall be longer than three minutes. At least one minute shall intervene between rounds. Except for professional kickboxing or professional bare-knuckle boxing matches, the contestants shall wear during the contest gloves weighing at least eight ounces each.</para><para>(3) Professional mixed martial arts matches or exhibitions shall not exceed three rounds in length, except in a championship match, which shall not exceed five rounds in length. No round shall be longer than five minutes. At least one minute shall intervene between rounds.</para><para>(4) No professional boxing contestant, professional mixed martial arts contestant, professional kickboxing contestant, professional bare-knuckle boxing contestant, or amateur mixed martial arts contestant shall be allowed to participate or take part in any contest in this state unless a duly licensed physician shall certify in writing that such contestant has taken a physical examination the day of the contest and is physically fit to engage in the proposed contest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 382, &#167; 7, p. 1328; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 849, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB471, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB869, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB70, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>