<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,196"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,196</statuteno><catchline>Licensure applicants; examination; eligibility; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Applications for licensure as a professional landscape architect shall be on forms prescribed and furnished by the State Board of Landscape Architects.</para><para>(2) Applicants who hold a landscape architecture degree accredited by the Landscape Architectural Accreditation Board or its equivalent as determined by the board may sit for the Landscape Architect Registration Examination as administered by the Council of Landscape Architectural Registration Boards.</para><para>(3) The following shall be considered as the minimum evidence satisfactory to the State Board of Landscape Architects that an applicant is eligible for initial licensure, upon application, as a professional landscape architect:</para><para>(a) Submission of an application accompanied by the fee established by the board, in accordance with subsection (1) of section 81-8,194;</para><para>(b) Submission of a council record maintained by the Council of Landscape Architectural Registration Boards;</para><para>(c) Graduation from a program accredited by the Landscape Architectural Accreditation Board or its equivalent as determined by the State Board of Landscape Architects;</para><para>(d) Passage of an examination on technical and professional subjects as prescribed by the board or its equivalent as determined by the board;</para><para>(e) A record of three years or more of diversified post-degree experience directly related to landscape architecture under the direct supervision of a professional landscape architect or equivalent experience as determined by the board; and</para><para>(f) One or more written professional references which shall be submitted by the applicant to the board.</para><para>(4) An individual holding a license to practice landscape architecture issued by a proper authority of any jurisdiction recognized by the board, based on credentials that do not conflict with subsection (3) of this section and other provisions of the Professional Landscape Architects Act, may, upon application, be licensed as a professional landscape architect after demonstration of good reputation and character.</para><para>(5) An individual who has been licensed to practice landscape architecture for fifteen years or more in one or more jurisdictions recognized by the board and who has practiced landscape architecture in compliance with the licensing laws in the jurisdiction where his or her landscape architecture practice has occurred since initial licensure may, upon application, be licensed as a professional landscape architect after demonstration of good reputation and character.</para><para>(6) The board may accept the verified information contained in a valid council record issued by the Council of Landscape Architectural Registration Boards in lieu of the same information that is required on the form prescribed by the board.</para><para>(7) Examination materials shall not be considered public records.</para><para>(8) The board may adopt the examinations and grading procedures of the Council of Landscape Architectural Registration Boards. The board may also adopt guidelines published from time to time by the council.</para><para>(9) Licensure shall be effective upon issuance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 565, &#167; 13, p. 1863; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 224; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1140, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB30, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>