
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id250">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id252" statutenumber="81-8,240"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,240</statuteno><catchline id="id255">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>As used in sections 81-8,240 to 81-8,254, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Administrative agency shall mean any department, board,
commission, or other governmental unit, any official, any employee of the
State of Nebraska acting or purporting to act by reason of connection with
the State of Nebraska, any corporation, partnership, business, firm, governmental
entity, or person who is providing health and human services to individuals or service delivery, service coordination,
or case management under contract with the State of Nebraska and
who is subject to the jurisdiction of the office of Public Counsel as required
by section 73-401, any regional behavioral health authority, any community-based
behavioral health services provider that contracts with a regional behavioral
health authority, and any county or municipal correctional or jail facility
and employee thereof acting or purporting to act by reason of connection with
the county or municipal correctional or jail facility; but shall not include
(a) any court, (b) any member or employee of the Legislature or the Legislative
Council, (c) the Governor or his or her personal staff, (d) any political
subdivision or entity thereof except a county or municipal correctional or
jail facility or a regional behavioral health authority, (e) any instrumentality
formed pursuant to an interstate compact and answerable to more than one state,
or (f) any entity of the federal government; and</para>
<para>(2) Administrative act shall include every action, rule,
regulation, order, omission, decision, recommendation, practice, or procedure
of an administrative agency.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 762, &#167; 1, p. 2879; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 121; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB467, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 41.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>