<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id468"><sectno id="id469" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 37.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id470" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-657"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id472">81-657</statuteno><catchline id="id473">Brain injury registry; physician, psychologist, hospital, and rehabilitation center; report required; contents.</catchline><para>(1) If a person with brain or head injury is treated in this state in the office of a physician or psychologist licensed to practice in this state but is not admitted to a hospital within this state, the treating physician or psychologist shall provide a report of such injury to the department within thirty days after such treatment and identification of the person sustaining such injury.</para><para>(2) If a person with brain or head injury is admitted to or treated at a hospital or a rehabilitation center located within a hospital in this state, such hospital or rehabilitation center shall provide a report of such injury to the department within thirty days after the discharge of such person from the hospital or rehabilitation center.</para><para>(3) A report provided under this section shall contain the following information about the person who has sustained the brain or head injury, if known:</para><para>(a) Name;</para><para>(b) Date of birth;</para><para>(c) Gender;</para><para>(d) Residence;</para><para>(e) Date of the injury;</para><para>(f) Final diagnosis or classification of the injury according to the International Classification of Disease, Clinical Modification Coding System of the World Health Organization, as adopted by the department;</para><para>(g) Cause of the injury and, if practicable, whether the injury resulted from an accident involving the use of alcohol;</para><para>(h) Place or site of occurrence of the injury;</para><para>(i) Identification of the reporting source;</para><para>(j) Disposition upon discharge;</para><para>(k) Payor source; and</para><para>(l) Any additional information the department deems necessary and appropriate to carry out the purposes of the Brain Injury Registry Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 308, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 163; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 152, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1178, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1312; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 37.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2008</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc>
