<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id6" statutenumber="81-829.42"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.42</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Governor's Emergency
Program; established.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature recognizes
that, while appropriations are adequate to meet the normal needs, the necessity
exists for anticipating and making advance provision to care for the unusual
and extraordinary burdens imposed on the state and its political subdivisions
by disasters, emergencies, or civil defense emergencies. To meet such situations,
it is the intention of the Legislature to confer emergency powers on the Governor,
acting through the Adjutant General and the Nebraska Emergency Management
Agency, and to vest him or her with adequate power and authority within the
limitation of available funds appropriated to the Governor's Emergency Program
to meet any disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency.</para>
<para>(2) There is hereby established the Governor's Emergency Program.
Funds appropriated to the program shall be expended, upon direction of the
Governor, for any state of emergency. The state of emergency proclamation
shall set forth the emergency and shall state that it requires the expenditure
of public funds to furnish immediate aid and relief. The Adjutant General
shall administer the funds appropriated to the program.</para>
<para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature that the first recourse
shall be to funds regularly appropriated to state and local agencies. If the
Governor finds that the demands placed upon these funds are unreasonably great,
he or she may make funds available from the Governor's Emergency Program.
Expenditures may be made upon the direction of the Governor for any or all
emergency management functions or to meet the intent of the state emergency
operations plans as outlined in section 81-829.41. Expenditures may also be
made to state and federal agencies to meet the matching requirement of any
applicable assistance programs.</para>
<para>(4) Assistance shall be provided from the funds appropriated
to the Governor's Emergency Program to political subdivisions of this state
which have suffered from a disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency
to such an extent as to impose a severe financial burden exceeding the ordinary
capacity of the subdivision affected. Applications for aid under this section
shall be made to the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency on such forms as
shall be prescribed and furnished by the agency. The forms shall require the
furnishing of sufficient information to determine eligibility for aid and
the extent of the financial burden incurred. The agency may call upon other
agencies of the state in evaluating such applications. The Adjutant General
shall review each application for aid under this section and recommend its
approval or disapproval, in whole or in part, to the Governor. If the Governor
approves, he or she shall determine and certify to the Adjutant General the
amount of aid to be furnished. The Adjutant General shall thereupon issue
his or her voucher to the Director of Administrative Services who shall issue
his or her warrants therefor to the applicant.</para>
<para>(5) When a state of emergency has been proclaimed by the Governor,
the Adjutant General, upon order of the Governor, shall have authority to
expend funds for purposes including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The purposes of the Emergency Management Act, including
emergency management functions and the responsibilities of the Governor as
outlined in the act;</para>
<para>(b) Employing for the duration of the state of emergency additional
personnel and contracting or otherwise procuring all necessary appliances,
supplies, and equipment;</para>
<para>(c) Performing services for and furnishing materials and supplies
to state government agencies and local governments with respect to performance
of any duties enjoined by law upon such agencies and local governments which
they are unable to perform because of extreme climatic phenomena and receiving
reimbursement in whole or in part from such agencies and local governments
able to pay therefor under such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon
by the Adjutant General and any such agency or local government;</para>
<para>(d) Performing services for and furnishing materials to any
individual in connection with alleviating hardship and distress growing out
of extreme climatic phenomena and receiving reimbursement in whole or in part
from such individual under such terms as may be agreed upon by the Adjutant
General and such individual;</para>
<para>(e) Opening up, repairing, and restoring roads and highways;</para>
<para>(f) Repairing and restoring bridges;</para>
<para>(g) Furnishing transportation for supplies to alleviate suffering
and distress;</para>
<para>(h) Restoring means of communication;</para>
<para>(i) Furnishing medical services and supplies to prevent the
spread of disease and epidemics;</para>
<para>(j) Quelling riots and civil disturbances;</para>
<para>(k) Training individuals or governmental agencies for the
purpose of perfecting the performance of emergency management duties as provided
in the Nebraska emergency operations plans;</para>
<para>(l) Procurement and storage of special emergency supplies
or equipment, determined by the Adjutant General to be required to provide
rapid response by state government to assist local governments in impending
or actual disasters, emergencies, or civil defense emergencies;</para>
<para>(m) Clearing or removing debris and wreckage which may threaten
public health or safety from publicly owned or privately owned land or water;
and</para>
<para>(n) Such other measures as are customarily necessary to furnish
adequate relief in cases of disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency.</para>
<para>(6) If aerial fire suppression or hazardous material response
is immediately required, the Adjutant General may make expenditures of up
to twenty-five thousand dollars
per event without a state of emergency proclamation issued by the Governor.</para>
<para>(7) The Governor may receive such voluntary contributions
as may be made from any nonfederal source to aid in carrying out the purposes
of this section and shall credit the same to the Governor's Emergency Cash
Fund.</para>
<para>(8) All obligations and expenses incurred by the Governor
in the exercise of the powers and duties vested in the Governor by this section
shall be paid by the State Treasurer out of available funds appropriated to
the Governor's Emergency Program, and the Director of Administrative Services
shall draw his or her warrants upon the State Treasurer for the payment of
such sum, or so much thereof as may be required, upon receipt by him or her
of proper vouchers duly approved by the Adjutant General.</para>
<para>(9) This section shall be liberally construed in order to
accomplish the purposes of the Emergency Management Act and to permit the
Governor to adequately cope with any disaster, emergency, or civil defense
emergency which may arise, and the powers vested in the Governor by this section
shall be construed as being in addition to all other powers presently vested
in him or her and not in derogation of any existing powers.</para>
<para>(10) Such funds as may be made available by the government
of the United States for the purpose of alleviating distress from disasters,
emergencies, and civil defense emergencies may be accepted by the State Treasurer
and shall be credited to a separate and distinct fund unless otherwise specifically
provided in the act of Congress making such funds available or as otherwise
allowed and provided by state law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 612, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 107; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 403, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB766, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB390, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>