<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.50"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.50</statuteno><catchline>Local emergency; declared; principal executive officer of a local government; effect; interjurisdictional emergency management organization.</catchline><para>(1) A local emergency may be declared only by the principal executive officer of a local government who finds that conditions defined as a disaster or an emergency exist or by a person who by resolution has been authorized and designated by the governing board of a local government to determine that an emergency within the scope of his or her authorization exists. A copy of the resolution shall be filed with the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency to be effective. The proclamation shall continue in effect until the principal executive officer finds that the disaster or emergency has been dealt with to the extent that those conditions no longer exist. The local governing body by resolution may terminate a local state of emergency proclamation at any time, and upon such termination the principal executive officer shall terminate the proclamation. Any order or proclamation declaring, continuing, or terminating a local emergency shall be given prompt and general publicity and shall be filed promptly with the clerk of the local government and the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency.</para><para>(2) The effect of a declaration of a local emergency shall be to activate the response and recovery aspects of any and all applicable city, village, county, or interjurisdictional emergency operations plans and to authorize the furnishing of aid and assistance under such plans.</para><para>(3) No interjurisdictional emergency management organization or official thereof may declare a local emergency unless expressly authorized by the agreement pursuant to which the organization functions, but an interjurisdictional emergency management organization shall provide aid and services in accordance with the agreement and emergency operations plan pursuant to which it functions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 30. </para></source></law></legaldoc>