<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 1, 2009">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-188.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-188.02</statuteno><catchline>State Building Renewal Assessment
Fund; capital improvement project; depreciation charges.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of this section, capital improvement project means (a) construction
of a new facility, structure, or building, (b) construction of additions to
an existing facility, structure, or building, (c) renovation of an existing
facility, structure, or building if the total project cost of such renovation
represents not less than fifteen percent of the value of the existing facility,
structure, or building as determined by the Department of Administrative Services,
(d) purchase of an existing facility, structure, or building, and (e) acquisition
of a facility, structure, or building through means of conveyance other than
sale and purchase.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning with the fiscal year that commences subsequent to the
calendar year in which has occurred substantial completion of a capital improvement
project as defined in subdivisions (1)(a) through (1)(c) of this section or
acquisition of a capital improvement project as defined in subdivisions (1)(d)
and (1)(e) of this section, the department shall assess a capital improvement
depreciation charge to the agency maintaining ownership or control of the
related facility, structure, or building and shall assess such charge for
each fiscal year thereafter,
except that no depreciation charges shall be assessed or paid pursuant to
this section for the period beginning July 1, 2009, and ending June 30, 2011.</para>
<para>(3) The annual depreciation charge for a capital improvement project
as defined in subdivisions (1)(a) through (1)(c) of this section shall be
computed as one percent of the total project cost of the capital improvement
project. The annual depreciation charge for a capital improvement project
as defined in subdivision (1)(d) of this section shall be computed as one
percent of the greater of the purchase price or the value, as determined by
the department, of the capital improvement project at the time of acquisition.
The annual depreciation charge for a capital improvement project as defined
in subdivision (1)(e) of this section shall be computed as one percent of
the value, as determined by the department, of the capital improvement project
at the time of acquisition. The department may assess the charge annually
or in monthly, quarterly, or semiannual installments.</para>
<para>(4) Depreciation charges shall not be assessed pursuant to this section
for capital improvement projects relating to facilities, structures, or buildings
owned, leased, or operated by the: (i) University of Nebraska; (ii) Nebraska
state colleges; (iii) Department of Aeronautics; (iv) Department of Roads;
(v) Game and Parks Commission; or (vi) Board of Educational Lands and Funds
or to other buildings or grounds owned, leased, or operated by the State of
Nebraska which are specifically exempted by the Department of Administrative
Services because the assessment of such depreciation charges would result
in the ineligibility for federal funding or would result in hardship on an
agency, board, or commission due to other exceptional or unusual circumstances.
Depreciation charges shall not be assessed pursuant to this section for capital
improvement projects relating to facilities, structures, or buildings of which
the department is custodian pursuant to section 81-1108.17 and for which charges
are assessed pursuant to subdivision (4)(b) of such section.</para>
<para>(5) Payment of depreciation charges assessed pursuant to this section
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Building
Renewal Assessment Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 666, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 410, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB318, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>