<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id6" statutenumber="81-829.40"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.40</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Governor; powers
and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Governor shall be responsible
for meeting the dangers to the state and people presented by disasters, emergencies,
and civil defense emergencies, and in the event of disaster, emergency, or
civil defense emergency beyond local control, he or she may assume direct
operational control over all or any part of the emergency management functions
within this state. He or she shall have general direction and control of emergency
management and the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency and shall be responsible
for carrying out the provisions of the Emergency Management Act.</para>
<para>(2) In order to effect the policy and purposes of the act,
the Governor may issue proclamations and make, amend, and rescind the necessary
orders, rules, and regulations to carry out the act.</para>
<para>(3) A state of emergency proclamation shall be issued by the
Governor if he or she finds that a disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency
has occurred or that the occurrence or threat thereof is imminent. All proclamations
issued under this subsection shall indicate the nature of the disaster, emergency,
or civil defense emergency, the area or areas threatened, and the conditions
which have brought about the state of emergency. All proclamations shall be
disseminated promptly by means calculated to bring the contents to the attention
of the general public and shall be promptly filed with the Nebraska Emergency
Management Agency, the Secretary of State, and the clerks of the local governments
in the area to which it applies. The proclamation shall continue in effect
until the Governor finds that the threat or danger has passed or the disaster,
emergency, or civil defense emergency has been dealt with to the extent that
those conditions no longer exist and terminates the proclamation by letter
of notice to such agency, the Secretary of State, and the clerks of the local
governments in the area to which it applies. The Legislature by resolution
may terminate a state of emergency proclamation at any time, whereupon the
Governor shall terminate the proclamation by letter of notice to such agency,
the Secretary of State, and the clerks of the local governments in the area
to which it applies.</para>
<para>(4) A state of emergency proclamation shall activate state,
city, village, county, and interjurisdictional emergency management organizations
and emergency operations plans applicable to the local government or area
in question and shall be the authority for the deployment and use of any forces
to which the plan or plans apply and for use or distribution of any supplies,
equipment, materials, and facilities assembled, stockpiled, or arranged to
be made available pursuant to the act or any other provision of law relating
to disasters, emergencies, or civil defense emergencies.</para>
<para>(5) During the continuance of any state of emergency, the Governor shall be commander
in chief of the organized and unorganized militia and of all other forces
available for emergency management duty. To the greatest extent practicable,
the Governor shall delegate or assign command authority by prior arrangement
embodied in appropriate proclamations, orders, rules, and regulations, but
nothing shall restrict his or her authority to do so by orders issued at the
time of the disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency.</para>
<para>(6) In addition to any other powers conferred upon the Governor
by law, he or she may:</para>
<para>(a) Suspend the provisions of any regulatory statute prescribing
the procedures for conduct of state business or the orders, rules, or regulations
of any state agency if strict compliance with the provisions of any statute,
order, rule, or regulation would in any way prevent, hinder, or delay necessary
action in coping with the disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency;</para>
<para>(b) Utilize all available resources of the state government
and of each political subdivision of the state as are reasonably necessary
to cope with the disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency;</para>
<para>(c) Transfer the direction, personnel, or functions of state
departments and agencies or units thereof for the purpose of performing or
facilitating emergency management;</para>
<para>(d) Subject to any applicable requirements for compensation
under section 81-829.57, commandeer or utilize any private property if he
or she finds this necessary to cope with the disaster, emergency, or civil
defense emergency;</para>
<para>(e) Direct and compel the evacuation of all or part of the
population from any stricken or threatened area within the state if he or
she deems this action necessary for the preservation of life or other emergency
management;</para>
<para>(f) Prescribe routes, modes of transportation, and destinations
in connection with evacuation;</para>
<para>(g) Control ingress and egress to and from a disaster area,
the movement of persons within the area, and the occupancy of premises in
the area;</para>
<para>(h) Suspend or limit the sale, dispensing, or transportation
of alcoholic beverages, explosives,
and combustibles; and</para>
<para>(i) Make provisions for the availability and use of temporary
emergency housing.</para>
<para>(7) In the event of a civil defense emergency, the Governor shall assume direct operational
control over all or any part of the emergency management functions within
this state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 315, &#167; 4(1), p. 1076; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-829.09; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB390, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>