<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,231" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,231</statuteno><catchline>Standards for licensure of elevator mechanics; State Fire Marshal; duties.</catchline><para>The State Fire Marshal shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing standards for licensure of elevator mechanics. An applicant for an elevator mechanic license shall demonstrate the following qualifications before being granted an elevator mechanic license:</para><para>(1) Not less than three years' work experience in the conveyance industry, in construction, maintenance, and service or repair, as verified by current and previous employers;</para><para>(2) One of the following:</para><para>(a) Satisfactory completion of a written examination administered by the committee on the most recent referenced codes and standards;</para><para>(b) Acceptable proof that the applicant has worked as a conveyance constructor, maintenance, or repair person. Such person shall have worked as an elevator mechanic without the direct and immediate supervision of a licensed elevator contractor and have passed a written examination approved by the State Fire Marshal. This employment shall not be less than three years immediately prior to the effective date of the license;</para><para>(c) Certificates of completion and successfully passing an elevator mechanic examination of a nationally recognized training program for the conveyance industry as provided by the National Elevator Industry Educational Program or its equivalent; or</para><para>(d) Certificates of completion of an apprenticeship program for elevator mechanics, having standards substantially equal to those of the Conveyance Safety Act and registered with the Bureau of Apprenticeship and Training of the United States Department of Labor or a state apprenticeship council; and</para><para>(3) Any additional qualifications adopted and promulgated in rule and regulation by the State Fire Marshal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 22; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-2522; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 67. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>