<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,196"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,196</statuteno><catchline>Applicant for registration; requirements.</catchline><para>Each applicant for registration as a professional landscape architect shall complete an application which includes his or her social security number and shall have the following requirements:</para><para>(1) Graduation from a course of study in landscape architecture of four years or more in a school or college satisfactory to the board. In addition, the applicant shall also submit a specific record of four years or more of practical experience in landscape architecture which is of a grade and character satisfactory to the board. In lieu of graduation from a four-year landscape architecture course in school or college, and the additional requirement for practical experience, there may be substituted evidence of at least eight years of practical experience which in the opinion of the board has prepared the applicant for examination and registration;</para><para>(2) Successful passing of a written, oral, or written and oral examination in landscape architecture which is designed to determine the proficiency and qualifications to engage in the practice of professional landscape architecture. No applicant shall be entitled to take this examination until the applicant's education, training or experience, or both training and experience, have met the requirements of the board;</para><para>(3) Be at least twenty-one years of age; and</para><para>(4) Be of good character.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 565, &#167; 13, p. 1863; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 224. </para></source></law></legaldoc>