<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id856"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-6,128"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-6,128</statuteno><catchline>Health Information Technology Board; duties; meetings; annual report.</catchline><para>(1) The Health Information Technology Board shall:</para><para>(a) Establish criteria for data collection and disbursement by the statewide health information exchange described in section 71-2455 and the prescription drug monitoring program created under section 71-2454 to improve the quality of information provided to clinicians. Such data shall not include proprietary or confidential financial information maintained by a health care provider or health care entity;</para><para>(b) Establish the framework and standards necessary to ensure the secure and seamless exchange of health information in real-time between health care providers and health care entities through the statewide health information exchange;</para><para>(c) Evaluate and ensure that the statewide health information exchange is meeting technological standards for reporting of data for the prescription drug monitoring program, including the data to be collected and reported and the frequency of data collection and disbursement;</para><para>(d) Provide the governance oversight necessary to ensure that any health information in the statewide health information exchange and the prescription drug monitoring program may be accessed, used, or disclosed only in accordance with the privacy and security protections set forth in the federal Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, Public Law 104-191, and regulations promulgated thereunder. All protected health information is privileged, is not a public record, and may be withheld from the public pursuant to section 84-712.05; and</para><para>(e) Provide recommendations to the statewide health information exchange on any other matters referred to the board.</para><para>(2) The board, upon the recommendation of the department, shall adopt rules and regulations necessary to carry out the Population Health Information Act. Notwithstanding section 71-2455, the department shall draft, promulgate, and enforce such rules and regulations.</para><para>(3) The authority of the board to direct the use or release of data under this section or section 71-2454 shall apply only to requests submitted to the board after September 1, 2021.</para><para>(4) The board may hold meetings by telecommunication or electronic communication subject to the Open Meetings Act. Any official action or vote of the members of the board shall be preserved in the records of the board.</para><para>(5) By November 15, 2021, and November 15 of each year thereafter, the board shall develop and submit an annual report to the Governor and the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature regarding considerations undertaken, decisions made, accomplishments, and other relevant information. The report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1183, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB411, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB967, &#167; 13. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>