<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-520.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>81-520.01</statuteno><catchline>Statewide open burning ban; waiver;
permit; fee.</catchline><para>(1) There shall be a statewide open burning
ban on all bonfires, outdoor rubbish fires, and fires for the purpose of clearing
land.</para>
<para>(2) The fire chief of a local fire department may waive an open burning
ban under subsection (1) of this section for an area under the
local fire department's jurisdiction by issuing an open burning
permit to a person requesting permission to conduct open burning. The permit
issued by the fire chief to a person desiring to conduct open burning
shall be in writing, signed by the fire chief, and on a form prescribed by the State Fire
Marshal. The State Fire Marshal shall provide local fire departments with
such forms.</para>
<para>(3) The fire chief of a local fire department may waive the open burning
ban in the local fire department's jurisdiction
when conditions are acceptable to the chief. Anyone intending to burn in such jurisdiction when
the open burning ban has been waived shall notify the fire chief of
his or her intention to burn prior
to starting the burn.</para>
<para>(4) The fire chief of a local fire department may adopt standards listing the conditions
acceptable for issuing a permit to conduct open burning under subsection (2)
of this section.</para>
<para>(5) The local fire department may charge a fee, not to exceed ten dollars,
for each such permit issued. This fee shall be remitted to the governing body
for inclusion in the general funds allocated to the fire department. Such
funds shall not reduce the tax requirements for the fire department. No such
fee shall be collected from any state or political subdivision to which such
a permit is issued to conduct open burning under subsection (2) of this section
in the course of such state's or political subdivision's official duties.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 810, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 790, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 408, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB248, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>A permit issued under this section is a license and does not create any contractual liability between the person obtaining the permit and the fire district that issues it. Syracuse Rur. Fire Dist. v. Pletan, 254 Neb. 393, 577 N.W.2d 527 (1998).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
