<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,174"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,174</statuteno><catchline>Beekeeping; inspection certificate; fees; State Apiary Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>Upon issuing a certificate to a beekeeper after an inspection as provided in section 81-2,173, the department shall collect a certificate fee as set forth in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Nebraska Apiary Act not to exceed the following amounts: Two hundred dollars for the inspection of two hundred fifty colonies or less; two hundred fifty dollars for the inspection of two hundred fifty-one through five hundred colonies; three hundred fifty dollars for the inspection of five hundred one through one thousand colonies; and four hundred fifty dollars for the inspection of more than one thousand colonies. The certification fee shall be paid prior to the issuance of certificates by the department. All fees and any gifts, grants, or donations from any source shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Apiary Cash Fund which is hereby created. The fund shall be used to defray the expenses of administering the Nebraska Apiary Act. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 9, &#167; 10, p. 81; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-2710; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-2,174; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 8, &#167; 49, p. 118; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 722, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1001, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1071, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 835, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>