<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,129"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,129</statuteno><catchline>State Athletic Commissioner; jurisdiction;
activities covered.</catchline><para>The State Athletic Commissioner shall
have sole direction, management, control, and jurisdiction over all professional
mixed martial arts, professional wrestling, professional boxing, and professional sparring matches and exhibitions and all amateur
mixed martial arts matches and
exhibitions to be held within the state, except such as are conducted by universities,
colleges, high schools, the military, and recognized amateur associations
for contestants under sixteen years of age. No professional boxers, professional mixed martial
arts contestants, or professional wrestlers,
or amateur mixed
martial arts contestants who have attained the age of sixteen, shall participate
in a match or exhibition for a prize or purse, or at which an admission fee
is charged, either directly or indirectly, in the form of dues or otherwise,
in this state except by a club, association, organization, or person licensed
by the commissioner, as provided in section 81-8,130, and in pursuance of
a license granted by the commissioner for such match or exhibition under section 81-8,130.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 382, &#167; 2, p. 1327; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 849, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB471, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB869, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Fight contests, which include kickboxing, mixed martial arts, and submission wrestling, do not qualify as professional wrestling or boxing matches or exhibitions as those terms are used in the statute. The State Athletic Commissioner has jurisdiction over professional wrestling and boxing and has no authority to issue a license for fight contests. Mason v. City of Lincoln, 266 Neb. 399, 665 N.W.2d 600 (2003).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>