<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-885.14"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.14</statuteno><catchline>Fees; license; renewal; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) To pay the expense of the maintenance and operation of the office of the commission and the enforcement of the Nebraska Real Estate License Act, the commission shall, at the time an application is submitted, collect from an applicant for each broker's or salesperson's examination a fee to be established by the commission of not more than two hundred fifty dollars and an application fee of not more than two hundred fifty dollars. The commission shall also collect a reexamination fee to be established by the commission of not more than two hundred fifty dollars for each reexamination. The commission may direct an applicant to pay the examination or reexamination fee to a third party who has contracted with the commission to administer the examination. Prior to the issuance of an original license, each applicant who has passed the examination required by section 81-885.13 or who has received a license under section 81-885.17 shall pay a license fee to be established by the commission. The license fee established by the commission shall not exceed the following amounts: For a broker's license, not more than two hundred fifty dollars; and for a salesperson's license, not more than two hundred dollars.</para><para>(2) Any applicant who is an active duty member of the armed forces of the United States or the spouse of such servicemember shall be exempt from payment of the license fee described in subsection (1) of this section if (a) such servicemember is assigned to a permanent duty station in Nebraska and (b)(i) the applicant is already duly licensed in another regulatory jurisdiction or (ii) the applicant was previously licensed in Nebraska within three years prior to becoming a resident of the State of Nebraska after such duty assignment.</para><para>(3) After the original issuance of a license, a renewal application and a renewal fee to be established by the commission of not more than five hundred dollars for each broker, and not more than four hundred dollars for each salesperson, shall be due and payable on or before November 30 of each renewal year. A broker or salesperson who: (a) Is required to submit evidence of completion of continuing education pursuant to section 81-885.51 on or before November 30, 2011, shall renew his or her license on or before such date for two years; (b) is not required to submit evidence of completion of continuing education until November 30, 2012, shall renew his or her license on or before November 30, 2011, for one year and shall renew his or her license on or before November 30, 2012, for two years; or (c) receives his or her original license on or after January 1, 2011, shall renew his or her license on or before the immediately following November 30 for two years. Each subsequent renewal under subdivisions (a), (b), and (c) of this subsection shall be for a two-year period and shall be due on or before November 30 of each renewal year. Failure to remit renewal fees when due shall automatically cancel such license on December 31 of the renewal year, but otherwise the license shall remain in full force and effect continuously from the date of issuance unless suspended or revoked by the commission for just cause. Any licensee who fails to file an application for the renewal of any license and pay the renewal fee as provided in this section may file a late renewal application and shall pay, in addition to the renewal fee, an amount to be established by the commission of not more than twenty-five dollars for each month or fraction thereof beginning with the first day of December if such late application is filed before July 1 of the ensuing year.</para><para>(4) Any check presented to the commission as a fee for either an original or renewal license or for examination for license which is returned to the State Treasurer unpaid or any electronic payment presented to the commission as a fee for either an original or renewal license or for examination for license that is not accepted against the commission shall be cause for revocation or denial of license.</para><para>(5) An inactive broker or salesperson may renew his or her license by submitting an application before December 1 prior to the ensuing year. Such broker or salesperson shall submit the renewal fee together with the completed renewal application on which he or she has noted his or her present inactive status. Any broker or salesperson whose license has been renewed on such inactive status shall not be permitted to engage in the real estate business until such time as he or she fulfills the requirements for active status. Any license which has been inactive for a continuous period of more than three years shall be reinstated only if the licensee has met the examination requirement of an original applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 68, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 899, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 361, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 936, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 182, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 350, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 118, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 204, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB11, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB23, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB12, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>