<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-5,167"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,167</statuteno><catchline id="id00">State boiler inspector; deputy inspectors; qualifications; bond or insurance.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The State Fire Marshal shall employ a state boiler inspector who shall work under the direct supervision of the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee. The state boiler inspector shall:</para><para id="id00">(a) Be a practical boilermaker, technical engineer, operating engineer, or boiler inspector;</para><para id="id00">(b) Hold an "AI" or "IS" Commission from the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors;</para><para id="id00">(c) Be qualified by not less than ten years' experience in the construction, installation, repair, inspection, or operation of boilers, steam generators, and superheaters;</para><para id="id00">(d) Have a knowledge of the operation and use of boilers, steam generators, and superheaters for the generating of steam for power, heating, or other purposes; and</para><para id="id00">(e) Neither directly nor indirectly be interested in the manufacture, ownership, or agency of boilers, steam generators, and superheaters.</para><para id="id00">(2) The State Fire Marshal may hire deputy inspectors as necessary to carry out the Boiler Inspection Act. Deputy inspectors shall hold an "IS" Commission from the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors or acquire the same within twelve months of hire. Such deputy inspectors shall otherwise be subject to and governed by the same rules and regulations applicable to and governing the acts and conduct of the state boiler inspector.</para><para id="id00">(3) Before entering upon his or her duties under the Boiler Inspection Act, the state boiler inspector and each deputy inspector shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 112, &#167; 1, p. 392; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-701; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 48-701; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 462, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 395, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 66, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB264, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2018, &#167; 48-721; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB37, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>