<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id48">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id50" statutenumber="81-181"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-181</statuteno><catchline id="id53">Agency; proposed
building renewal projects report; submitted, when; contents; allocation of
funds; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Not later than September 15 of each even-numbered year, each agency shall submit
to the Governor, in the form prescribed by him or her, a report of its proposed
building renewal projects for the next biennium. Such
report shall contain the information specified in section 81-177 and shall
constitute a request for the allocation of funds from the Building Renewal
Allocation Fund. Such report shall also constitute, as applicable, a request
for the allocation of funds from the State Building Renewal Assessment Fund,
University Building Renewal Assessment Fund, or State College Building Renewal
Assessment Fund. The Governor shall, with the advice of the task force, allocate
from such funds the sum necessary for the accomplishment of projects approved
by him or her. Allocations from the Building Renewal Allocation Fund shall
be made in a manner that assures accomplishment of Class I projects first,
followed by accomplishment of Class II projects, and then accomplishment of
Class III projects, unless doing so in a particular case would violate sound
building renewal policies and practices. The amount of such allocation shall
not be transferred to the agency but shall remain within, as applicable, the
Building Renewal Allocation Fund, State Building Renewal Assessment Fund,
University Building Renewal Assessment Fund, or State College Building Renewal
Assessment Fund subject to the control of the Governor until disbursed consistent
with the provisions of the Deferred Building Renewal Act.</para>
<para>(2) The University of Nebraska and the state colleges may
include in their reports under subsection (1) of this section their proposed
building renovation projects that have received approval of the Coordinating
Commission for Postsecondary Education, if required pursuant to section 85-1414,
for the coming biennium as authorized by
section 81-188.03 or 81-188.05, as applicable, which shall constitute requests
for allocation of funds for such proposed projects from the University Building
Renewal Assessment Fund or the State College Building Renewal Assessment Fund,
as applicable. The Governor, with the advice of the task force, shall allocate
from the University Building Renewal Assessment Fund or the State College
Building Renewal Assessment Fund, as applicable, the sum necessary for the
accomplishment of the renovation projects approved by him or her. Such allocations
shall not be transferred to the University of Nebraska or the state college
or colleges making the request but shall remain in the University Building
Renewal Assessment Fund or the State College Building Renewal Assessment Fund,
as applicable, subject to the control of the Governor until disbursed pursuant
to the Deferred Building Renewal Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 309, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 369, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>