<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,239.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,239.03</statuteno><catchline>Risk Manager; present budget request; contents; deficiency appropriation; procedure; investment.</catchline><para>The Risk Manager shall present a budget request as provided in subdivision (1) of section 81-1113 for the Risk Management Program which shall separately state the amount requested for the Tort Claims Fund, State Insurance Fund, State Self-Insured Property Fund, State Self-Insured Indemnification Fund, and Workers' Compensation Claims Revolving Fund, and such budget shall be based on the projected needs for such funds. If the Risk Manager does not assess state agencies for any of the funds listed in this section, the amount of expenditures paid from the fund on behalf of any non-general-fund agency shall be separately stated and paid into the funds from an appropriation to such non-general-fund agency. If the amount of money in any of such funds is not sufficient to pay any awards or judgments authorized by sections 48-192 to 48-1,109 or the State Tort Claims Act, the Risk Manager shall immediately advise the Legislature and request an emergency appropriation to satisfy such awards and judgments. Any money in such funds available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the State Insurance Fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 273, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1211, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB256, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1092, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 33. </para><effectivedate>August 21, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>State Tort Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,235.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>