<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,159"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,159</statuteno><catchline>Contractor certificate; required; application; fee; examination; renewal; responsible managing employee.</catchline><para>(1) Any water-based fire protection system contractor who installs, repairs, alters, adds to, maintains, or inspects water-based fire protection systems in this state shall first obtain a contractor certificate.</para><para>(2) A water-based fire protection system contractor may apply to the State Fire Marshal for a contractor certificate. The application shall be made on a form prescribed by the State Fire Marshal and shall include a certificate fee of up to one hundred dollars. Each applicant must designate a responsible managing employee on the application, and this individual's name shall appear on the certificate with that of the water-based fire protection system contractor upon issuance. Proof of insurance required by section 81-5,160 shall also accompany the application.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of a complete application, proof of insurance, and certificate fee, the State Fire Marshal shall schedule a time for an examination of the responsible managing employee to demonstrate that he or she is familiar with the procedures and rules of the State Fire Marshal relating to water-based fire protection systems. If the responsible managing employee passes the examination, the State Fire Marshal shall issue the certificate to the water-based fire protection system contractor within thirty days.</para><para>(4) A certificate shall expire on September 30 of the year following issuance. An application for renewal shall be filed at least thirty days prior to expiration and shall be accompanied by a renewal fee of up to one hundred dollars and a sworn affidavit that the responsible managing employee is currently employed by the water-based fire protection system contractor. A water-based fire protection system contractor who fails to apply for renewal within the time stated in this subsection must make a new application for a certificate.</para><para>(5) A responsible managing employee may only act as such for one water-based fire protection system contractor at a time. When a responsible managing employee terminates his or her association with a water-based fire protection system contractor, the water-based fire protection system contractor shall notify the State Fire Marshal within thirty days after termination. The responsible managing employee shall not be designated as the responsible managing employee for more than two water-based fire protection system contractors in any twelve-month period. The State Fire Marshal shall revoke the certificate of a water-based fire protection system contractor whose responsible managing employee has terminated his or her association with the water-based fire protection system contractor unless an application designating a new responsible managing employee is filed within six months after termination or prior to expiration of the current certificate, whichever is earlier.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 636, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>