<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id55">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id57" statutenumber="81-188.05">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>81-188.05</statuteno><catchline id="id60">State College
Building Renewal Assessment Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The State College Building Renewal Assessment Fund is created.
The fund shall be under the control of the Governor for allocation to building
renewal projects and building renovation projects of the Nebraska state colleges.
No amounts accruing to the State College Building Renewal Assessment Fund
shall be transferred to any other fund and no amounts accruing to the fund
shall be expended in any manner for purposes other than as provided in this
section or as appropriated by the Legislature to meet the cost of administering
the Deferred Building Renewal Act.</para>
<para>(2) Revenue credited to the fund shall include amounts as
provided by the Legislature and such other revenue as may be incident
to administration of the fund.</para>
<para>(3) Amounts appropriated from the fund shall be expended to
conduct renewal work as defined in section 81-173, to conduct renovation work,
and to complete other improvements incident to such renewal or renovation
work as deemed necessary or appropriate by the task force. Expenditures from
the fund for capital improvements shall be limited to exclude expenditures
for capital improvement projects relating to facilities, structures, or buildings
from which revenue is derived and pledged for the retirement of revenue bonds
issued under sections 85-403 to 85-411.</para>
<para>(4) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be
invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(5) For purposes of this section, renovation work means work
to replace the interior or exterior systems of an existing building to accommodate
changes in use of building space or changes in programmatic need for building
space.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 410, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB380, &#167; 3.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>