<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,287"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,287</statuteno><catchline>Regulatory authority; enforcement; issue stop-sale, stop-use, removal orders; procedure.</catchline><para>If a regulatory authority finds that food is being manufactured, processed, distributed, offered for sale, or sold in violation of the adulteration, misbranding, deceptive packaging, or false advertising provisions of sections 81-2,282 to 81-2,285 or any other requirement of the Nebraska Pure Food Act which affects such food, such regulatory authority may issue and enforce a written or printed stop-sale, stop-use, or removal order to the person in charge of such food if the issuance of such an order is necessary for the protection of the public health, safety, or welfare. No food subject to any such order shall be used, sold, or moved without permission from the regulatory authority. Such an order shall specifically describe the nature of the violation found and the precise actions needed to be taken to bring the food into compliance with the applicable provisions of the act. Such order shall clearly advise the person in charge of the food that he or she may request an immediate hearing before the director or his or her designee on the matter. No such order may direct the involuntary and immediate disposal or destruction of any food until the person in charge of such food has been afforded an opportunity to be heard on the matter and an opportunity to appeal any order of the director or his or her designee from such a hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. The regulatory authority may issue a stop-sale, stop-use, or removal order against articles of food that are perishable, even if the practical result of such an order is to bring about the involuntary disposal of such food, when, in the opinion of the person issuing the order, no alternative course of action would sufficiently protect the public health, safety, or welfare under the circumstances.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 487, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 165; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1990, &#167; 81-216.33; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 358, &#167; 56. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>