<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id46">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id48" statutenumber="81-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-125</statuteno><catchline id="id51">State budget;
submission to Legislature by Governor; when; contents.</catchline><para>The
Governor shall on or before January 15 of each odd-numbered year present to
the Legislature a complete budget for all the activities of the state receiving
appropriations or requesting appropriations, except that the Governor during
his or her first year in office shall present such budget to the Legislature
on or before February 1. Such budget shall be a tentative work program for
the coming biennium, shall contain a full and itemized report of the expenditures
from appropriations made by the previous Legislature and the items which the
Governor deems worthy of consideration for the coming biennium, for the respective
departments, offices, and institutions, and for all other purposes, and shall
contain the estimated revenue from taxation, the estimated revenue from sources
other than taxation, an estimate of the amount required to be raised by taxation
and the sales and income tax rates necessary to raise such amount, the revenue
foregone by operation of laws in effect at the time of such report granting
tax expenditures and reduced tax liabilities as identified in the report required
by section 77-5731, and recommendations as to deficiency funding requirements
pursuant to section 81-126. The summary of the tax expenditure report prepared
pursuant to subsection
(1) of section 77-385 and a summary of the report required by
section 77-5731 shall be included with or appended to the budget presented
to the Legislature. The Governor may make recommendations whether to continue
or eliminate, in whole or in part, each tax expenditure and incentive program
or to limit the duration of particular tax expenditures and incentives to
a fixed number of years and shall include his or her reasoning for each recommendation,
if any. The recommendations shall be transmitted to the Revenue Committee
of the Legislature at the same time the Governor submits a budget as required
in this section. The budget as transmitted to the Legislature shall show the
estimated requirements for each activity of the state as prepared by the Department
of Administrative Services and the final recommendation of the Governor. The
budget shall comprise the complete report to the Legislature of all appropriations
made for the current biennium and expenditures therefrom by all agencies receiving
appropriations, and the report of expenditures contained in the budget shall
be in lieu of all other biennial or other financial reports required by statute
to the Legislature by expending agencies of appropriations and expenditures
for their own activities except the biennial report of the State Treasurer
and Director of Administrative Services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 210, &#167; 1, p. 745; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7268; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-301; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-125; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 577, &#167; 1, p. 1907; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 526, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 169, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 82, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB629, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB989, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional provisions:</emphasis></para><para>Budget bill, see Article IV, section 7, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>