<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id513"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,207"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,207</statuteno><catchline>Complaint; enforcement; procedures.</catchline><para>A complaint against any person involving any matter coming within the jurisdiction of the board shall be in writing and shall be filed with the board. The complaint, at the discretion of the board, shall be heard within a reasonable time in accordance with the rules and regulations and may be heard through the use of a hearing officer. The accused shall have the right to appear personally with or without counsel, to cross-examine adverse witnesses, and to produce evidence and witnesses in his or her defense. The board shall set the time and place of the hearing and shall cause a copy of the complaint, together with a notice of the time and place fixed for the hearing, to be sent by registered mail to the accused, at his or her last-known mailing address known to the board, at least thirty days before the hearing. If after the hearing the board finds the accused has violated the Professional Landscape Architects Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, it may issue any order or take any action described in section 81-8,208. If the board finds no violation, it shall enter an order dismissing the complaint. If the order revokes, suspends, or cancels a license, the board shall notify the licensee and the Secretary of State in writing. The board may reissue a license that has been revoked. An application for the reissuance of a license shall be made in such a manner as the board directs and shall be accompanied by a fee established by the board, in accordance with subsection (1) of section 81-8,194.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB30, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>