
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,215"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,215</statuteno><catchline>Applicability of act.</catchline><para>(1) The Conveyance Safety Act applies to the construction, operation, inspection, testing, maintenance, alteration, and repair of conveyances. Conveyances include the following equipment, associated parts, and hoistways which are not exempted under section 81-5,216:</para><para>(a) Hoisting and lowering mechanisms equipped with a car which moves between two or more landings. This equipment includes elevators;</para><para>(b) Power driven stairways and walkways for carrying persons between landings. This equipment includes:</para><para>(i) Escalators; and</para><para>(ii) Moving sidewalks; and</para><para>(c) Hoisting and lowering mechanisms equipped with a car, which serves two or more landings and is restricted to the carrying of material by its limited size or limited access to the car. This equipment includes:</para><para>(i) Dumbwaiters;</para><para>(ii) Material lifts and dumbwaiters with automatic transfer devices; and</para><para>(iii) Conveyors and related equipment within the scope of American Society of Mechanical Engineers B20.1.</para><para>(2) The act applies to the construction, operation, inspection, maintenance, alteration, and repair of automatic guided transit vehicles on guideways with an exclusive right-of-way. This equipment includes automated people movers.</para><para>(3) The act applies to conveyances in private residences located in counties that have a population of more than one hundred thousand inhabitants at the time of installation. Such conveyances are subject to inspection at installation but are not subject to periodic inspections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB265, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-2507; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 51. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>