<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,117</statuteno><catchline>Land surveying; eligibility for licensure; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall be eligible for a license unless:</para><para>(a) He or she has successfully passed an examination, designed to determine his or her proficiency and qualification to engage in the professional practice of land surveying. No applicant shall be entitled to take such examination until he or she shows the necessary practical experience in land surveying work; and</para><para>(b) He or she (i) has not less than six years of surveying experience of which five years must be as defined in subdivision (2) of section 81-8,109, and three of such five years must have been in a responsible position as a subordinate to a professional land surveyor, or (ii) has graduated, after a course of not less than four years in surveying, engineering, or other approved curriculum, with proportionate credit for lesser time, from a school or college approved by the examining board as of satisfactory standing and has an additional two years of practice in a responsible position.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, responsible position means a position that requires initiative, skill, and independent judgment and does not include the position of chainman, rodman, instrument person, ordinary drafter, or other position performing routine work.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 383, &#167; 10, p. 1334; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 764, &#167; 3, p. 2894; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 442, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 478, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 874, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB303, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB102, &#167; 33. </para><operativedate>September 1, 2024</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Registered surveyors are professionals for purposes of professional negligence. Bixenmann v. Dickinson Land Surveyors, 294 Neb. 407, 882 N.W.2d 910 (2016).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>