<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,184"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,184</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Professional Landscape
Architects Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Professional landscape architect means a
person who, by
reason of his or her knowledge
acquired by professional education or practical experience, or both, is qualified
to engage in the practice of professional landscape
architecture as provided in the
act;</para>
<para>(2) Practice of professional landscape
architecture means the performance of professional
services such as consultations, investigations, reconnaissance, research,
planning, design, or responsible supervision in connection with projects involving
the arranging of land and the elements thereon for public and private use
and enjoyment, including the alignment of roadways and the location of buildings,
service areas, parking areas, walkways, steps, ramps, pools, and other structures,
and the grading of the land, surface and subsoil drainage, erosion control,
planting, reforestation, and the preservation of the natural landscape and
aesthetic values, in accordance with accepted professional standards of public
health, welfare, and
safety. Practice
of professional landscape architecture includes the location and
arrangement of such tangible objects and features as are incidental and necessary
to the purposes outlined in this subdivision but does not include the design of structures or
facilities with separate and self-contained purposes for habitation or industry, the design of public streets
and highways, utilities, storm and sanitary sewers, and sewage treatment facilities which are ordinarily included in the practice
of engineering or architecture,
or the making of land surveys or final land plats for
official approval or recording. Nothing contained in the act shall preclude a duly licensed professional landscape architect
from performing any of the services defined
as practice of professional landscape architecture in this subdivision
in connection with the settings, approaches, or
environment for buildings, structures, or
facilities. Nothing contained in the
act shall be construed as authorizing a professional landscape architect to engage in
the practice of architecture, engineering, or land surveying. Nothing in the act shall prohibit any person, firm, or
corporation or their officers, agents, or employees from preparing planting plans for plant materials
in connection with the sale of nursery stock, plants, trees, shrubs, flowers,
sod, or other plant material, outdoor decorative ornaments, seed, fertilizer,
chemicals, gardening tools and equipment, and related items of merchandise
or the propagation, planting, or
growth of any indoor or outdoor plants; and</para>
<para>(3) Board means the State Board of Landscape
Architects created by the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 565, &#167; 1, p. 1860; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 98, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1140, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>