<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,272.24"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,272.24</statuteno><catchline>Time/temperature control for safety food; date marking; sale, consumption, or discard requirements.</catchline><para>In addition to the provisions of sections 3-501.17 and 3-501.18 of the Food Code which apply to food held at a temperature of forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) or below, food held in refrigeration between forty-five degrees Fahrenheit (seven degrees Celsius) and forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) shall meet the following requirements:</para><para>(1) Except when packaging food using a reduced oxygen packaging method as specified in section 3-502.12 of the Food Code and except as specified in section 3-501.17 of the Food Code, refrigerated, ready-to-eat, time/temperature control for safety food prepared and held in a food establishment for more than twenty-four hours shall be clearly marked to indicate the date of preparation. The food shall be sold, consumed on the premises, or discarded within four calendar days or less;</para><para>(2) Except as specified in section 3-501.17 of the Food Code, refrigerated, ready-to-eat, time/temperature control for safety food prepared and packaged by a food processing plant and held refrigerated at such food establishment, shall be clearly marked, at the time the original container is opened in a food establishment, to indicate the date the food container was opened. The food shall be sold, consumed on the premises, or discarded within four calendar days or less; and</para><para>(3) A food specified under this section shall be discarded if such food:</para><para>(a) Exceeds the temperature and time combinations specified in subdivision (1) of this section, except time that the food is frozen;</para><para>(b) Is in a container or package that does not bear a date or day;</para><para>(c) Is appropriately marked with a date or day that exceeds the temperature and time combination as specified in subdivision (1) of this section; or</para><para>(d) Is prepared in a food establishment and dispensed through a vending machine with an automatic shut-off control if it exceeds the temperature and time combination as specified in subdivision (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 199, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 474, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 250, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB74, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB798, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>