<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id12" statutenumber="81-132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-132</statuteno><catchline id="id15">State budget;
departmental budget estimates; duty to submit; contents.</catchline><para>All departments, offices, and institutions of the state government
requesting appropriations shall file in the office of the Director of Administrative
Services the budget forms furnished them by the director under the provisions
of sections 81-1113 and 81-1113.01. The budget forms required by this section
shall be filed on or before September 15 of each even-numbered year, except
that in 2002, the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department
of Administrative Services may extend the filing deadline for budget forms
to a date no later than October 15, 2002. The forms shall show their total
estimated requirements for the next biennium for each unit of their organization
and activity classified as to object of expenditure. With such forms, each
department, office, institution, and expending agency shall file a report
showing all money received by such department, office, institution, or expending
agency together with the estimated receipts for the coming biennium. Such
estimates shall be accompanied by a statement in writing giving facts and
explanations of reasons for each item of increased appropriation requested. The report submitted by the Department
of Health and Human Services shall include, but not be limited to, the key
goals, benchmarks, and progress reports required pursuant to section 81-3133.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 210, &#167; 8, p. 748; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7275; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-308; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-132; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 526, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 12, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB949, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>April 10, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>