<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-646"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-646</statuteno><catchline>Cancer registry; hospital; health practitioner; provide data; contents.</catchline><para>(1) On the request of the department or its authorized representative, each medical doctor, osteopathic physician, or dentist within the state shall produce and make available to the department or its authorized representative, in a manner prescribed by the department, data which the department determines is necessary and appropriate from each medical record of cancer under the doctor's, osteopathic physician's, or dentist's custody or control.</para><para>(2) Each hospital within the state shall make available to the department or its authorized representative on presentation of proper identification of the department's representative, a list of names of cancer patients, corresponding medical records numbers, and medical records which document the diagnosis and treatment of cancer on the premises of the hospital, office, or clinic during normal working hours, for the purpose of recording specific data about a patient's cancer.</para><para>(3) Each hospital that initially diagnoses cancer made reportable by the department for more than fifty patients during a calendar year shall, for the next calendar year, at the request of the department or its authorized representative, produce and make available, in a manner prescribed by the department, data which the department determines is necessary and appropriate from each medical record of cancer under the control of the hospital. Any hospital with fewer than fifty initial diagnoses of cancer may report in the same manner.</para><para>(4) The data produced pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall include, but not be limited to, the:</para><para>(a) Patient's name, address, and available social security number;</para><para>(b) Patient's hospital accession number;</para><para>(c) Patient's birthdate, race, and sex;</para><para>(d) Date of diagnosis;</para><para>(e) Primary site of cancer;</para><para>(f) Stage of the disease, including in situ, localized, regional, distant, or metastasis;</para><para>(g) Basis of staging, including clinical diagnostic, surgical evaluative, postsurgical treatment pathological, or retreatment; and</para><para>(h) Diagnostic confirmation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 212, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 925, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 342, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 88. </para></source></law></legaldoc>