<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-502.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>81-502.03</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Fire Safety Appeals Board; disagreement; hearing; notice; decision; written report prior to order; exception; applicability of section.</catchline><para>(1) In case of disagreement concerning the propriety of any action taken or proposed to be taken by the State Fire Marshal or the application of any statute, rule, or regulation under the jurisdiction of the office with respect to any establishment or installation, the State Fire Marshal may, and upon application of any party in interest, shall provide for a hearing before the Nebraska Fire Safety Appeals Board in the county of the establishment or installation which is the subject of the disagreement. At least ten days' written notice shall be given to the governing body responsible for the establishment or installation involved and to any public official having jurisdiction. The board shall make a decision based upon the evidence brought forth in the hearing and issue its order accordingly. Prior to ordering any political or governmental subdivision of the State of Nebraska to make any modification in the design or construction of any public building or any modification in the location, installation, or operation of any existing equipment in any public building or to replace such equipment, the State Fire Marshal, his or her first assistant, or one of his or her deputies shall personally appear at a regular meeting of the governing board of such subdivision and present a written report stating the condition of such building or equipment and the reason why such building should be modified or such equipment should be modified or replaced, and a copy of such report shall be attached to the order. Nothing in this section shall prevent the State Fire Marshal from ordering necessary repairs, and nothing in sections 81-502.01 to 81-502.03 shall prevent the State Fire Marshal, when actual and immediate danger to life exists, from ordering and requiring the occupants to vacate a building or structure subject to his or her jurisdiction.</para><para>(2) This section shall not apply to any decision, determination, or other action taken or made by the State Fire Marshal or the Underground Excavation Safety Committee under the One-Call Notification System Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 570, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 485, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 893, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB683, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>