<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,135"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,135</statuteno><catchline>Licensee; reports; contents; gross receipts tax; amounts.</catchline><para>Every licensee conducting or holding any professional mixed martial arts, amateur mixed martial arts, professional boxing, professional kickboxing, or professional bare-knuckle boxing match shall furnish to the State Athletic Commissioner a written report showing the articles of agreement between the contestants, the number of tickets sold for each contest, the amount of the gross receipts thereof, the gross receipts from sale of any television rights, and such other matters as the commissioner shall prescribe. Within such time the licensee shall pay to the commissioner a tax of five percent of the total gross receipts of any professional mixed martial arts, professional boxing, professional kickboxing, or professional bare-knuckle boxing match or exhibition, exclusive of state and federal taxes, except the gross receipts from sale of television rights, and five percent of such rights, and five percent of the total gross receipts of any amateur mixed martial arts match or exhibition, exclusive of state and federal taxes, except that if such match or exhibition is conducted as an incidental feature in any event or entertainment of a different character, such portion of the total receipts shall be paid to the state as the commissioner may determine, or as may be fixed by rule adopted under section 81-8,139.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 382, &#167; 8, p. 1329; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 434, &#167; 1, p. 1349; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 520, &#167; 1, p. 1638; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 778, &#167; 4, p. 2951; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 849, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB471, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB869, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB291, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB70, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>