<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id392"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,311"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,311</statuteno><catchline>Semiquincentennial Commission; members; vacancy; termination.</catchline><para>(1) The Semiquincentennial Commission is created. The commission shall be housed within the Nebraska State Historical Society for administrative and budgetary purposes.</para><para>(2) The commission shall consist of seventeen members.</para><para>(3) The Legislature intends for the commission to include members from all regions of the state, representing all major interests and a diverse array of industries.</para><para>(4) The commission shall include the following members:</para><para>(a) The Director of the Nebraska State Historical Society or the designee of the director, who shall serve as the chairperson;</para><para>(b) The Director of Economic Development or the designee of such person;</para><para>(c) The Commissioner of Education or the designee of such person; and</para><para>(d) The President of the University of Nebraska or the designee of such person;</para><para>(5) The commission shall include at least one member from each of the following subdivisions to be appointed by the Governor before September 1, 2021:</para><para>(a) A Native American from a federally recognized Indian tribe, as of January 1, 2021, residing within the State of Nebraska. Such member shall be appointed from a list of five nominees submitted by the Commission on Indian Affairs;</para><para>(b) An African American who is a legal resident of the State of Nebraska. Such member shall be appointed from a list of five nominees submitted by the Commission on African American Affairs;</para><para>(c) A Latino-American who is a legal resident of the State of Nebraska. Such member shall be appointed from a list of five nominees submitted by the Commission on Latino-Americans;</para><para>(d) A curator or director of a private cultural institution as defined in section 58-807.01 or a professional historian;</para><para>(e) A member of the Nebraska Tourism Commission;</para><para>(f) A representative from the Nebraska Humanities Council;</para><para>(g) A legal resident of the first congressional district;</para><para>(h) A legal resident of the second congressional district; and</para><para>(i) A legal resident of the third congressional district.</para><para>(6) The same individual shall not fulfill the requirements of more than one subdivision of subsections (4) and (5) of this section.</para><para>(7) No more than eight of the members shall be affiliated with the same political party.</para><para>(8) Any vacancy on the commission of an appointed member occurring after the initial appointment of members shall be filled by the Governor by appointment.</para><para>(9) The commission shall terminate on June 30, 2027.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB275, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>