<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-523"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-523</statuteno><catchline>State Fire Marshal; office; support and maintenance; tax on fire insurance companies; rate; credit.</catchline><para>(1) For the purpose of maintaining the office of the State Fire Marshal and such other fire prevention activities as the Governor may direct, every foreign and alien insurance company including nonresident attorneys for subscribers to reciprocal insurance exchanges shall, on or before March 1, pay a tax to the Director of Insurance of three-fourths of one percent of the gross direct writing premiums and assessments received by each of such companies during the preceding calendar year for fire insurance business done in this state.</para><para>(2) For the purpose set forth in subsection (1) of this section, every domestic insurance company including resident attorneys for subscribers to reciprocal insurance exchanges shall, on or before March 1, pay a tax to the Director of Insurance of three-eighths of one percent of the gross direct writing premiums and assessments received by each of such companies during the preceding calendar year for fire insurance business done in this state.</para><para>(3) The term fire insurance business, as used in subsections (1), (2), and (4) of this section, shall include, but not be limited to, premiums of policies on fire risks on automobiles, whether written under floater form or otherwise.</para><para>(4) Return premiums on fire insurance business, subject to the fire insurance tax, in accordance with subsections (1) and (2) of this section, may be deducted from the gross direct writing premiums for the purpose of the tax calculations provided for by subsections (1) and (2) of this section. In the case of mutual companies and assessment associations, the dividends paid or credited to policyholders or members in this state shall be construed to be return premiums.</para><para>(5) Any tax collected pursuant to subsections (1) and (2) of this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund.</para><para>(6) An insurance company described in this section shall receive a credit on the tax imposed under this section as provided in the Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act and the Relocation Incentive Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 183, &#167; 22, p. 488; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-5522; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 82, &#167; 1, p. 330; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 81-5522; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-523; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 281, &#167; 1, p. 977; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 332, &#167; 1, p. 1091; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 376, &#167; 1, p. 1316; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 212, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 408, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 345; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1023, &#167; 17. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Relocation Incentive Act,</emphasis> see section 77-3107.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under former statute, fund created under its provisions could be paid out on proper warrants without legislative appropriation. State ex rel. Ridgell v. Hall, 99 Neb. 89, 155 N.W. 228 (1915), affirmed on rehearing 99 Neb. 95, 156 N.W. 16 (1916).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>