<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,235" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,235</statuteno><catchline>Continuing education; extension; when granted; approved providers; records.</catchline><para>(1) The renewal of elevator mechanic licenses granted under the Conveyance Safety Act shall be conditioned upon the submission of a certificate of completion of a course designed to ensure the continuing education on new and existing rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the State Fire Marshal. Such course shall consist of not less than eight hours of instruction that shall be attended and completed within one year immediately preceding any license renewal. The individual holding the elevator mechanic license shall pay the cost of such course.</para><para>(2) The courses shall be taught by instructors through continuing education providers that may include association seminars and labor training programs. The committee shall make recommendations to the State Fire Marshal about approval of continuing education providers.</para><para>(3) An elevator mechanic licensee who is unable to complete the continuing education course required under this section prior to the expiration of the license due to a temporary disability may apply for an extension from the state elevator inspector. The extension shall be on a form provided by the state elevator inspector which shall be signed by the applicant and accompanied by a certified statement from a competent physician attesting to such temporary disability. Upon the termination of such temporary disability, the elevator mechanic licensee shall submit to the state elevator inspector a certified statement from the same physician, if practicable, attesting to the termination of such temporary disability. At such time an extension sticker, valid for ninety days, shall be issued to the licensed elevator mechanic and affixed to the license. Such extension shall be renewable for periods of ninety days upon a showing that the disability continues.</para><para>(4) Approved continuing education providers shall keep uniform records, for a period of ten years, of attendance of elevator mechanic licensees following a format approved by the state elevator inspector, and such records shall be available for inspection by the state elevator inspector upon request. Approved continuing education providers are responsible for the security of all attendance records and certificates of completion. Falsifying or knowingly allowing another to falsify such attendance records or certificates of completion shall constitute grounds for suspension or revocation of the approval required under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-2526; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 71. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>