<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-2,162.27"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,162.27</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Fertilizers and Soil Conditioners Administrative Fund; created; use; transfers; investment.</catchline><para>(1) All money received under the Nebraska Commercial Fertilizer and Soil Conditioner Act and the Agricultural Liming Materials Act shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Fertilizers and Soil Conditioners Administrative Fund, which fund is hereby created. Money so received shall be used by the department for defraying the expenses of administering the Nebraska Commercial Fertilizer and Soil Conditioner Act and the Agricultural Liming Materials Act. The fund may also be used to defray costs incurred by the department directly related to administrative and budgetary support of the Healthy Soils Task Force pursuant to sections 2-401 to 2-404, except that no more than ten thousand dollars may be expended by the department from the fund for such purpose. Until January 1, 2020, the fund may also be used to defray all reasonable and necessary costs related to the implementation of the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act. The Department of Agriculture shall document all costs incurred for such purpose. The budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services may transfer a like amount from the Nebraska Hemp Program Fund to the Fertilizers and Soil Conditioners Administrative Fund no later than October 1, 2022. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer two hundred seventy-five thousand dollars from the Fertilizers and Soil Conditioners Administrative Fund to the General Fund on or before June 30, 2019, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(2) Any unexpended balance in the Fertilizers and Soil Conditioners Administrative Fund at the close of any biennium shall, when reappropriated, be available for the uses and purposes of the fund for the succeeding biennium. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 333, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 157, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB93, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB243, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 23. </para><note>Changes made by LB243 became effective April 18, 2019. Changes made by LB657 became operative May 31, 2019.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Agricultural Liming Materials Act,</emphasis> see section 2-4301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Hemp Farming Act,</emphasis> see section 2-501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>