<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.48"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.48</statuteno><catchline>Emergency management aid and assistance; mutual aid arrangements; interjurisdictional emergency management agreement.</catchline><para>(1) The director or coordinator of each city, village, county, or interjurisdictional emergency management organization shall, in collaboration with other public and private entities within this state, develop or cause to be developed mutual aid arrangements for reciprocal emergency management aid and assistance in case of disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency too great to be dealt with unassisted. Such arrangements shall be consistent with the state emergency operations plan, and in time of emergency it shall be the duty of each city, village, county, or interjurisdictional emergency management organization to render assistance in accordance with the provisions of such mutual aid arrangements.</para><para>(2) The director or coordinator of each city, village, county, or interjurisdictional emergency management organization may, subject to the approval of the Governor, enter into mutual aid arrangements with emergency management agencies or organizations in other states for reciprocal emergency management aid and assistance in case of disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency too great to be dealt with unassisted.</para><para>(3) It shall be a sufficient reason for the Governor to require an interjurisdictional emergency management agreement or arrangement pursuant to section 81-829.47 if the area and local governments involved have available equipment, supplies, and forces necessary to provide mutual aid on a regional basis and that the local governments have not already made adequate provision for mutual aid, but in requiring the making of an interjurisdictional emergency management arrangement to accomplish the purposes of this section, the Governor need not require establishment and maintenance of an interjurisdictional emergency management organization or arrangement for any other disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 315, &#167; 8(1), p. 1080; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-829.19; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 28. </para></source></law></legaldoc>