<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id584"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,307"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,307</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska-Ireland Commission; members; purpose; Nebraska-Ireland Fund; created; use; investment; report.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby established the Nebraska-Ireland Commission.</para><para>(2) The commission shall consist of the following members:</para><para>(a) The Director of the Department of Agriculture or the director's designee;</para><para>(b) The Director of the Department of Economic Development or the director's designee;</para><para>(c) A representative of a Nebraska postsecondary educational institution to be appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(d) Two representatives from a Nebraska business association such as a trade organization, economic development organization, or chamber of commerce appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(e) A representative of a Nebraska nonprofit organization offering child and family services and community programs and interested in enhancing relationships between Nebraska and Ireland, including furthering trade, appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(f) A member of the public who is interested in enhancing relationships between Nebraska and Ireland, including furthering trade, appointed by the Governor; and</para><para>(g) Three members of the Nebraska Legislature, one from each of the Congressional districts, who shall serve as nonvoting, ex officio members appointed by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council.</para><para>(3) Each member shall serve for a term of two years and may be reappointed without limit. If a position becomes vacant, such position must be filled for the duration of the term in the same manner as the original appointment.</para><para>(4) Members shall serve on the commission without compensation but may be compensated for expenses incurred in the performance of official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 if funds are available.</para><para>(5) The commission shall elect a chairperson and vice-chairperson from among its members. The commission shall hold meetings at least once each quarter at the call of the chairperson. The committee may conduct its meetings by virtual conferencing as defined in section 84-1409. A majority of the members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of the business of the commission.</para><para>(6) The purpose of the Nebraska-Ireland Commission shall be to advance, promote, and encourage business and other mutually beneficial activities between Nebraska and Ireland, including:</para><para>(a) Bilateral trade and investment;</para><para>(b) Joint action on policy issues of mutual interest;</para><para>(c) Business and academic exchanges;</para><para>(d) Mutual economic support between Nebraska and Ireland;</para><para>(e) Mutual investment in the infrastructure of Nebraska and Ireland; and</para><para>(f) Other issues as determined by the commission.</para><para>(7) For administrative and budgetary purposes, the commission shall be housed within the Department of Economic Development. Additional support to facilitate the work of the commission may be requested from appropriate federal and state agencies and other stakeholders as appropriate.</para><para>(8) The Nebraska-Ireland Fund is hereby established. The Department of Economic Development shall administer the fund. The purpose of the fund is to defray the administrative expenses of the commission and to support the commission's efforts to carry out its purposes. The fund shall consist of transfers authorized by the Legislature, funds raised by or on behalf of the commission, funds from the federal government, gifts, grants, and funds from other sources. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Investment earnings from investment money in the fund shall be credited to the fund.</para><para>(9) On or before December 1, 2027, and on or before December 31 of each year thereafter, the commission shall submit an annual report to the Governor and the Legislature containing the commission's findings, results, and recommendations. The report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1087, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>