<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,162.05" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,162.05</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Commercial fertilizer; label affixed to package; contents; common name; custom-blended products; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Any packaged commercial fertilizer distributed in this state, except custom-blended products, shall have placed on or affixed to the package a label stating clearly and conspicuously:</para><para>(a) The net weight or measure of the product;</para><para>(b) The name and principal address of the manufacturer or distributor;</para><para>(c) The name of the product, including any term, design, trademark, or chemical designation used in connection with the product;</para><para>(d) The guaranteed analysis showing the minimum percentage of plant nutrients claimed in the following order and form:</para><para>Total Nitrogen.....percent</para><para>Ammoniacal Nitrogen</para><para>(Specialty products only).....percent</para><para>Nitrate Nitrogen</para><para>(Specialty products only).....percent</para><para>Water Insoluble Nitrogen</para><para>(Specialty products only).....percent</para><para>Available Phosphate (P2O5).....percent</para><para>Soluble Potash (K2O).....percent</para><para>Unacidulated mineral phosphatic materials and basic slag shall be guaranteed as to both total available phosphate and the degree of fineness. Plant nutrients, other than nitrogen, phosphorus, and potassium, shall be guaranteed when present in significant quantities as determined by the director, which guarantees shall be expressed in elemental form. The director may also request that the sources of such nutrients be included on the label. Other beneficial substances, determinable by chemical methods, may be guaranteed only by permission of the director by and with the advice of the University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources;</para><para>(e) The sources from which the nitrogen, available phosphate (P2O5), and potash (K2O) are derived; and</para><para>(f) The grade stated in whole numbers in the same terms, order, and percentages as in the guaranteed analysis, except as follows:</para><para>(i) Specialty products may be guaranteed in fractional units of less than one percent of the total nitrogen, available phosphate, and soluble potash; and</para><para>(ii) The director may allow types of fertilizer materials, bone meal, or manures to be guaranteed in fractional units.</para><para>(2) If distributed in bulk, a written or printed statement of the information required by subdivisions (a), (b), (c), and (d) of subsection (1) of this section shall accompany delivery and be supplied to the purchaser.</para><para>(3) Whenever a commercial fertilizer is so comprised as to be recognized by a name commonly understood by ordinary individuals, such name shall be prominently and conspicuously displayed on the label.</para><para>(4) Custom-blended products shall bear a tag or invoice stating the name and principal address of the manufacturer, the name and address of the purchaser, and the net weight or measure and the composition of the product by weight or percentage of ingredients used. A duplicate copy of such information shall be kept by the manufacturer for use by the department for sampling and inspection purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 334, &#167; 5, p. 1040; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 333, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 692, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 889, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 366, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB93, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>"Product" under sections 81-2,162.01 to 81-2,162.07, R.R.S.1943, means the product which is sold in the normal course of business to the ultimate consumer, and consists of the finished product. "Manufacture" means manufacture of the finished product. "Distributes" means distribution of the finished product, and not a mere ingredient. PPG Industries Canada LTD v. Kreuscher, 204 Neb. 220, 281 N.W.2d 762 (1979).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>