<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id399" statutenumber="81-885.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.01</statuteno><catchline id="id402">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Real Estate License Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Associate broker means a person who has a broker's license and who is employed by another broker to participate in any activity described in subdivision (2) of this section;</para><para>(2) Broker means any person who, for any form of compensation or consideration or with the intent or expectation of receiving the same from another, negotiates or attempts to negotiate the listing, sale, purchase, exchange, rent, lease, or option for any real estate or improvements thereon, or assists in procuring prospects or holds himself or herself out as a referral agent for the purpose of securing prospects for the listing, sale, purchase, exchange, renting, leasing, or optioning of any real estate or collects rents or attempts to collect rents, gives a broker's price opinion or comparative market analysis, or holds himself or herself out as engaged in any of the foregoing. Broker also includes any person: (a) Employed, by or on behalf of the owner or owners of lots or other parcels of real estate, for any form of compensation or consideration to sell such real estate or any part thereof in lots or parcels or make other disposition thereof; (b) who auctions, offers, attempts, or agrees to auction real estate; or (c) who buys or offers to buy or sell or otherwise deals in options to buy real estate;</para><para>(3) Broker's price opinion means an analysis, opinion, or conclusion prepared by a person licensed under the Nebraska Real Estate License Act in the ordinary course of his or her business relating to the price of specified interests in or aspects of identified real estate or identified real property for the purpose of (a) listing, purchase, or sale, (b) originating, extending, renewing, or modifying a loan in a transaction other than a federally related transaction, or (c) real property tax appeals;</para><para>(4) Commission means the State Real Estate Commission;</para><para>(5) Comparative market analysis means an analysis, opinion, or conclusion prepared by a person licensed under the act in the ordinary course of his or her business relating to the price of specified interests in or aspects of identified real estate or identified real property by comparison to other real property currently or recently in the marketplace for the purpose of (a) listing, purchase, or sale, (b) originating, extending, renewing, or modifying a loan in a transaction other than a federally related transaction, or (c) real property tax appeals;</para><para>(6) Designated broker means an individual holding a broker's license who has full authority to conduct the real estate activities of a real estate business. In a sole proprietorship, the owner, or broker identified by the owner, shall be the designated broker. In the event the owner identifies the designated broker, the owner shall file a statement with the commission subordinating to the designated broker full authority to conduct the real estate activities of the sole proprietorship. In a partnership, limited liability company, or corporation, the partners, limited liability company members, or board of directors shall identify the designated broker for its real estate business by filing a statement with the commission subordinating to the designated broker full authority to conduct the real estate activities of the partnership, limited liability company, or corporation. The designated broker shall also be responsible for supervising the real estate activities of any associate brokers or salespersons;</para><para>(7) Distance education means courses in which instruction does not take place in a traditional classroom setting, but rather through other media by which instructor and student are separated by distance and sometimes by time;</para><para>(8) Federal financial institution regulatory agency means (a) the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, (b) the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, (c) the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, (d) the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, (e) the National Credit Union Administration, or (f) the successors of any of those agencies;</para><para>(9) Federally related transaction means a real-estate-related transaction that (a) requires the services of an appraiser and (b) is engaged in, contracted for, or regulated by a federal financial institution regulatory agency;</para><para>(10) Inactive broker means an associate broker whose license has been returned to the commission by the licensee's broker, a broker who has requested the commission to place the license on inactive status, a new licensee who has failed to designate an employing broker or have the license issued as an individual broker, or a broker whose license has been placed on inactive status under statute, rule, or regulation;</para><para>(11) Inactive salesperson means a salesperson whose license has been returned to the commission by the licensee's broker, a salesperson who has requested the commission to place the license on inactive status, a new licensee who has failed to designate an employing broker, or a salesperson whose license has been placed on inactive status under statute, rule, or regulation;</para><para>(12) Person means and includes individuals, corporations, partnerships, and limited liability companies, except that when referring to a person licensed under the act, it means an individual;</para><para>(13) Purchaser means a person who acquires or attempts to acquire or succeeds to an interest in land;</para><para>(14) Real estate means and includes condominiums and leaseholds, as well as any other interest or estate in land, whether corporeal, incorporeal, freehold, or nonfreehold, and whether the real estate is situated in this state or elsewhere;</para><para>(15) Regulatory jurisdiction means a state, district, or territory of the United States, a province of Canada or a foreign country, or a political subdivision of a foreign country, which has implemented and administers laws regulating the activities of a broker;</para><para>(16)(a) Right-to-list home sale agreement means an agreement:</para><para>(i) By the owner of residential real estate to provide another person with the exclusive right to list such residential real estate for sale at a future date in exchange for monetary consideration or an equivalent to monetary consideration; and</para><para>(ii)(A) That states that the agreement runs with the land or otherwise purports to bind future owners of such residential real estate; or</para><para>(B) That purports to be a lien, encumbrance, or other real property security interest; and</para><para>(b) Right-to-list home sale agreement does not include any lien, encumbrance, or other real property security interest expressly authorized under the laws of this state, including any:</para><para>(i) Home warranty or similar product that covers the cost of maintenance of a major home system or appliance for a fixed period;</para><para>(ii) Insurance contract;</para><para>(iii) Option or right of refusal to purchase the residential real estate;</para><para>(iv) Contract for deed or purchase;</para><para>(v) Declaration created in the formation of a common-interest community or an amendment to such declaration;</para><para>(vi) Maintenance or repair agreement entered by a homeowners' association in a common-interest community;</para><para>(vii) Mortgage or trust deed loan or a commitment to make or receive a mortgage or trust deed loan;</para><para>(viii) Security agreement under the Uniform Commercial Code relating to the sale or rental of any personal property or fixture;</para><para>(ix) Water, sewer, electrical, telephone, cable, or other regulated utility service provider; or</para><para>(x) Right granted by the Nebraska Construction Lien Act;</para><para>(17) Salesperson means any person, other than an associate broker, who is employed by a broker to participate in any activity described in subdivision (2) of this section;</para><para>(18) Subdivider means any person who causes land to be subdivided into a subdivision for himself, herself, or others or who undertakes to develop a subdivision but does not include a public agency or officer authorized by law to create subdivisions;</para><para>(19) Subdivision or subdivided land means any real estate offered for sale and which has been registered under the Interstate Land Sales Full Disclosure Act, 15 U.S.C. 1701 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 1973, or real estate located out of this state which is divided or proposed to be divided into twenty-five or more lots, parcels, or units;</para><para>(20) Team means two or more persons licensed by the commission who (a) work under the supervision of the same broker, (b) work together on real estate transactions to provide real estate brokerage services, (c) represent themselves to the public as being part of a team, and (d) are designated by a team name; and</para><para>(21) Team leader means any person licensed by the commission and appointed or recognized by his or her broker as the leader for his or her team.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 68, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 68, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 182, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 350, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 118, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 529; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 618, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 863, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB26, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB931, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB375, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB678, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB258, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1073, &#167; 30. </para><operativedate>April 16, 2024</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Construction Lien Act,</emphasis> see section 52-125.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A person who solicits the sale of another's property in exchange for an option to purchase the property from the owners to resell to the buyers for a higher price is acting as a broker under this section. Choice Homes v. Donner, 311 Neb. 835, 976 N.W.2d 187 (2022).</para><para>Unless otherwise specified in a written agency agreement pursuant to section 76-2422(6), the fiduciary duties owed by a real estate broker derive only from the performance of limited activities defined in subdivision (2) of this section. Professional Mgmt. Midwest v. Lund Co., 284 Neb. 777, 826 N.W.2d 225 (2012).</para><para>When a client engages a real estate broker to perform any of the activities defined in subdivision (2) of this section, the resulting agency relationship is called a brokerage relationship. Professional Mgmt. Midwest v. Lund Co., 284 Neb. 777, 826 N.W.2d 225 (2012).</para><para>One of the enumerated activities covered by section 76-2422(6) is the exchange of property, based on the plain language of subdivision (2) of this section. McCully, Inc. v. Baccaro Ranch, 279 Neb. 443, 778 N.W.2d 115 (2010).</para><para>Pursuant to the Nebraska Real Estate License Act, any person collecting a fee or commission on the sale of real estate must be a licensed real estate broker or salesperson unless they meet one of the exceptions provided in the act. In re Estate of Ronan, 277 Neb. 516, 763 N.W.2d 704 (2009).</para><para>"Business brokers" are real estate brokers, as defined by this section, if the attempted sale or lease involves the transfer of any interest in real estate. Ford v. American Medical International, 228 Neb. 226, 422 N.W.2d 67 (1988).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>