<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,177"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,177</statuteno><catchline>Special inspector commission; requirements; inspection under provision of a city ordinance; inspection under the act not required; when; insurance coverage required.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The State Fire Marshal may issue a special inspector commission to an inspector in the employ of a company if the inspector has previously passed the examination prescribed by the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors and the company is an insurance company authorized to insure boilers in this state against loss from explosion or is an authorized inspection agency.</para><para>(b) Each special inspector employed by an insurance company or authorized inspection agency who has been issued a special inspector commission under this section shall submit to the state boiler inspector complete data of each boiler required to be inspected by the Boiler Inspection Act which is insured or inspected by such insurance company or authorized inspection agency on forms approved by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(c) Insurance companies shall notify the State Fire Marshal of new, canceled, or suspended risks relating to insured boilers. Insurance companies shall notify the State Fire Marshal of all boilers which the company insures, or any boiler for which insurance has been canceled, not renewed, or suspended within thirty days after such action. Authorized inspection agencies shall notify the State Fire Marshal of any new or canceled agreements relating to the inspection of boilers or pressure vessels within thirty days after such action.</para><para>(d) Insurance companies and authorized inspection agencies shall immediately notify the State Fire Marshal of defective boilers. If a special inspector employed by an insurance company, upon the first inspection of new risk, finds that the boiler or any of the appurtenances are in such condition that the inspector's company refuses insurance, the company shall immediately submit a report of the defects to the state boiler inspector.</para><para>(2) The inspection required by the act shall not be required if (a) an annual inspection is made under a city ordinance which meets the standards set forth in the act, (b) a certificate of inspection of the boiler is filed with the State Fire Marshal with a certificate fee, and (c) the inspector for the city making such inspection is required by such ordinance to either hold a commission from the National Board of Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspectors commensurate with the type of inspections performed by the inspector for the city or acquire the commission within twelve months after appointment.</para><para>(3) The State Fire Marshal may, by rule and regulation, provide for the issuance of a special inspector commission to an inspector in the employ of a company using or operating an unfired pressure vessel subject to the act for the limited purpose of inspecting unfired pressure vessels used or operated by such company.</para><para>(4) All inspections made by a special inspector shall be performed in accordance with the act, and a complete report of such inspection shall be filed with the State Fire Marshal in the time, manner, and form prescribed by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(5) The state boiler inspector may, at his or her discretion, inspect any boiler to which a special inspector commission applies.</para><para>(6) The State Fire Marshal may, for cause, suspend or revoke any special inspector commission.</para><para>(7) No authorized inspection agency shall perform inspections of boilers in the State of Nebraska unless the authorized inspection agency has insurance coverage for professional errors and omissions and comprehensive and general liability under a policy or policies written by an insurance company authorized to do business in this state in effect at the time of such inspection. Such insurance policy or policies shall be in an amount not less than the minimum amount as established by the State Fire Marshal. Such minimum amount shall be established with due regard to the protection of the general public and the availability of insurance coverage, but such minimum insurance coverage shall not be less than one million dollars for professional errors and omissions and one million dollars for comprehensive and general liability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 112, &#167; 6(2), p. 394; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-712; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 176, &#167; 1, p. 584; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 959, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 48-712; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 462, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 438, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 395, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB226, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-731; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>