
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments"  statutenumber="81-2,272.01" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,272.01</statuteno><catchline>Time/temperature control for safety food; temperature; equipment.</catchline><para>(1) Except during preparation, cooking, or cooling or when time is used as the public health control as specified under the Nebraska Pure Food Act and except as specified under subsection (2) of this section, time/temperature control for safety food shall be maintained:</para><para>(a) At one hundred thirty-five degrees Fahrenheit (fifty-seven degrees Celsius) or above, except that roasts cooked to a temperature and for a time specified in the Nebraska Pure Food Act or reheated as specified in the act may be held at a temperature of one hundred thirty degrees Fahrenheit (fifty-four degrees Celsius) or above; or</para><para>(b) At:</para><para>(i) Forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) or less; or</para><para>(ii) Forty-five degrees Fahrenheit (seven degrees Celsius) or between forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) and forty-five degrees Fahrenheit (seven degrees Celsius) in existing refrigeration equipment that is not capable of maintaining the food at forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) or less if:</para><para>(A) The equipment is in place and in use in the food establishment; and</para><para>(B) Refrigeration equipment that is not capable of meeting a cold holding temperature of forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) that is in use on March 8, 2012, shall, upon replacement of the equipment or at a change of ownership of the food establishment, be replaced with equipment that is capable of maintaining foods at forty-one degrees Fahrenheit (five degrees Celsius) or below.</para><para>(2) Eggs that have not been treated to destroy all viable Salmonellae shall be stored in refrigerated equipment that maintains an ambient air temperature of forty-five degrees Fahrenheit (seven degrees Celsius) or less.</para><para>(3) Time/temperature control for safety food in a homogenous liquid form may be maintained outside of the temperature control requirements, as specified under subsection (1) of this section, while contained within specially designed equipment that complies with the design and construction requirements as specified in the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB771, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB798, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>