<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-885.28"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.28</statuteno><catchline>Refusal of witness to attend or testify; proceedings in district court.</catchline><para>(1) If any witness so subpoenaed shall refuse to attend the taking of a deposition or the hearing, or if attending shall refuse to testify, the commission may apply to the district court of the county in which the deposition is to be taken or in which the hearing is to be held for an order compelling the attendance of the witness, the giving of testimony, and the production of books, papers, and documents.</para><para>(2) The application shall be by petition, setting forth:</para><para>(a) That due notice has been given of the time and place of attendance of the witness or the production of the books, papers, and documents;</para><para>(b) That the witness has been subpoenaed in the manner prescribed by section 81-885.27; and</para><para>(c) That the witness has failed and refused to attend or produce the papers required by subpoena before the commission, or officer taking the deposition in the cause or proceeding named in the subpoena, or has refused to answer questions propounded to him or her in the course of the hearing or deposition.</para><para>(3) The court, upon petition of the commission, shall enter an order directing the witness to appear before the court at a time and place to be fixed by the court in such order, the time to be not more than ten days from the date of the order, and then and there show cause why he or she has not attended, testified, or produced the books, papers, or documents before the commission. A certified copy of the order shall be served upon the witness.</para><para>(4) If at the show-cause hearing, it shall appear to the court that the subpoena was regularly issued by the director of the commission, the court shall thereupon enter an order that the witness appear before the commission or the officer taking the deposition at the time and place fixed in the order and testify or produce the required books, papers, or documents, and upon failure to obey such order the witness shall be dealt with as for contempt of court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 68, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 182, &#167; 22. </para></source></law></legaldoc>