<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,173" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,173</statuteno><catchline>State Fire Marshal; adopt rules and regulations; adopt schedule of fees; incorporation of codes.</catchline><para>The State Fire Marshal may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the purpose of effectuating the Boiler Inspection Act, including rules and regulations for the methods of testing equipment, the construction and installation of new boilers, and a schedule of inspection and certificate fees for boilers required to be inspected by the act. Such rules and regulations may incorporate by reference any portion of (1) the Boiler and Pressure Vessel Code of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, as amended, (2) the National Board Inspection Code, as amended, (3) the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Code for Controls and Safety Devices for Automatically Fired Boilers, as amended, concerning controls and safety devices for automatically fired boilers, (4) the American Petroleum Institute Pressure Vessel Inspection Code API-510, and (5) the National Fire Protection Association pamphlet 85, Boiler and Combustion Systems Hazards Code, including codes referenced in such code. A copy of all rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the Boiler Inspection Act, including copies of all codes incorporated by reference, shall be kept on file in the office of the State Fire Marshal and shall be known as the Boiler Safety Code.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 112, &#167; 4(1), p. 393; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 48-707; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 48-707; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 462, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 438, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 66, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-727; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>