<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id172"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,314"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,314</statuteno><catchline>Semiquincentennial Commission Fund; created; use; investment; termination.</catchline><para>(1) The Semiquincentennial Commission Fund is created. Such fund shall consist of money appropriated by the Legislature and gifts, grants, or donations from any source, including federal, state, public, and private sources.</para><para>(2) The Semiquincentennial Commission Fund shall be utilized for the purpose of administering the Semiquincentennial Commission and executing commemorative activities and implementing educational activities, events, and celebrations related to the Semiquincentennial of the United States.</para><para>(3) Money received by the Semiquincentennial Commission shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Semiquincentennial Commission Fund. Any money in the Semiquincentennial Commission Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(4)(a) The State Treasurer shall transfer the unobligated balance in the Semiquincentennial Commission Fund to the Historical Society Fund on June 1, 2027.</para><para>(b) The Semiquincentennial Commission Fund terminates on June 30, 2027, and the State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the fund on such date to the Historical Society Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB275, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>May 22, 2021</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>