<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,184"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,184</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Professional Landscape Architects Act:</para><para>(1) Board means the State Board of Landscape Architects;</para><para>(2) Coordinating professional means a design professional who coordinates, as appropriate, the work of all design professionals involved in a project;</para><para>(3) Design professional means a professional landscape architect, a licensed architect, or a professional engineer;</para><para>(4) License means an authorization granted by the board to practice landscape architecture;</para><para>(5) Practice of landscape architecture means the application of the principles of mathematical, physical, biological, and social sciences in consultation, evaluation, planning, design, including, but not limited to, the preparation, review and filing of plans, drawings, specifications, and other contract documents, and administration of contracts relative to projects principally directed at the functional and aesthetic use and preservation of land in the performance of professional services. These professional services include, but are not limited to:</para><para>(a) Investigation, selection, and allocation of land and natural resources for appropriate uses;</para><para>(b) Development of feasibility and site selection studies to govern the planning, design, and management of the land;</para><para>(c) Preparation, review, and analysis of land-use master, site, and comprehensive development plans and preliminary subdivision plans;</para><para>(d) Determining the location and siting of improvements, including buildings, site features, access, and environs for the improvements;</para><para>(e) Collaboration with architects, professional engineers, and registered land surveyors in the design of streets, highways, bridges, buildings, and structures with respect to the functional and aesthetic requirements of the area in which such facilities are to be placed;</para><para>(f) Preservation and management of natural, cultural, historic, and aesthetic resources;</para><para>(g) Design of: Sites, landforms, water features, and water bodies; site grading; surface and subsurface drainage and management; sediment and erosion control; noninhabitable structures; park and recreation areas; site vehicular circulation systems, greenways, and streetscapes; equestrian, bicycle, and pedestrian circulation systems; and site lighting, irrigation, plantings, and related construction details and specifications; and</para><para>(h) Location and arrangement of such tangible objects and features as are incidental and necessary to the purposes outlined in this section. Practice of landscape architecture does not include the design of structures or facilities with separate and self-contained purposes for habitation or industry, or the design of streets and highways, utilities, storm and sanitary sewers, and water and sewage treatment facilities, such as are exclusive to the practice of engineering, architecture, or land surveying; and</para><para>(6) Professional landscape architect or licensee means a person who is licensed by the board to practice landscape architecture.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 565, &#167; 1, p. 1860; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 98, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1140, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB30, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>