<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id435"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,121.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,121.02</statuteno><catchline>Land surveying; organizational practice; certificate of authorization; application; fee; renewal.</catchline><para>(1) An individual licensed under the Land Surveyors Regulation Act may practice or offer to practice the profession of land surveying through an organization if the criteria for organizational practice established by the board are met and the organization has been issued a certificate of authorization by the board.</para><para>(2) An organization applying for a certificate of authorization shall designate at least one professional land surveyor as the person in responsible charge of any practice of land surveying by the organization. One who renders only occasional professional services for an organization may not be designated as being in responsible charge of the professional activities of an organization under this section.</para><para>(3) To obtain a certificate of authorization, an application shall be filed with the board. The application shall contain the name and license number of each individual designated as in responsible charge and licensed to practice land surveying in Nebraska.</para><para>(4) Applications for a certificate of authorization shall be made on a form prescribed and furnished by the board.</para><para>(5) The certificate of authorization fee for organizations shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed three hundred dollars for the initial application.</para><para>(6) An organization shall notify the board of any changes in the status of any individual designated as in responsible charge within thirty days after the effective date of the change.</para><para>(7) An organization is not relieved of responsibility for the conduct or acts of its agents, employees, officers, or partners by reason of its compliance with this section. An individual practicing land surveying is not relieved of responsibility for services performed by reason of employment or any other relationship with an organization holding a certificate of authorization.</para><para>(8) The Secretary of State shall not issue a certificate of authority to do business in the state to an applicant or issue a registration of name in the state to an organization which intends to engage in the practice of land surveying unless the board has issued the applicant a certificate of authorization or a letter indicating the eligibility of the applicant to receive a certificate or to register the name.</para><para>(9) The Secretary of State shall not register any trade name or service mark which includes the words land surveyor or land surveying, or any modification or derivative of such words, in an applicant's firm name or logotype unless the board has issued the applicant a certificate of authorization or a letter indicating the eligibility of the applicant to register the trade name or service mark.</para><para>(10) An organization may engage in the practice of land surveying for itself without obtaining a certificate of authorization.</para><para>(11) A certificate of authorization shall expire on a date established by the board and become invalid after that date unless renewed. The board shall notify every organization holding a certificate of authorization under the act of the date of the expiration of the certificate of authorization and the amount of the fee required for renewal. The notice shall be provided at least one month in advance of the date of the expiration to the organization at the last-known address on file with the board. Only valid certificates may be renewed prior to expiration. Renewal fees shall not exceed two hundred dollars per year.</para><para>(12) The board may issue a new certificate of authorization to replace any lost, destroyed, or mutilated certificate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB102, &#167; 31. </para><operativedate>September 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>