<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.58"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.58</statuteno><catchline>Emergency management; supplies and services from federal government; funds; disposition.</catchline><para>Whenever the federal government or any agency or officer thereof offers to the state or, through the state, to any political subdivision thereof services, equipment, supplies, materials, or funds by way of gift, grant, or loan for purposes of disaster response and emergency management, the state, acting through the Governor, or such political subdivision, acting with the consent of the Governor and through its principal executive officer or governing body, may accept such offer. Upon such acceptance the Governor of the state or principal executive officer or governing body of such political subdivision may authorize any officer of the state or such political subdivision to receive such services, equipment, supplies, materials, or funds on behalf of the state or such political subdivision, subject to the terms of the offer and the rules and regulations, if any, of the agency making the offer. All such funds received on behalf of the state shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to a separate and distinct fund unless otherwise specifically provided in the act of Congress making such funds available, or as otherwise allowed and provided by state law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 315, &#167; 10(3), p. 1081; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 342, &#167; 2, p. 973; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-829.24; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 403, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc>