
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,236"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,236</statuteno><catchline>Director; contract and cooperate
with federal government; expenditure of funds.</catchline><para>The Director
of Agriculture may contract and cooperate with the Animal and Plant Health
Inspection Service of the United States Department of Agriculture in the management
and control of (1) coyotes, bobcats, foxes, and other predatory animals listed
in section 23-358 in this state that are injurious to livestock, poultry,
and game animals and the public health, (2) black-tailed
prairie dogs and other injurious commensal and field rodents,
and (3) nuisance birds or other nuisance wildlife in accordance with organized
and systematic plans of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of
the United States Department of Agriculture for the management and control
of such animals. Supervision of the program shall be by the local representative
of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of the United States Department
of Agriculture. Expenditure of funds appropriated by the Legislature may not
be made without the approval in writing by the director. The director in cooperation
with the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of the United States Department
of Agriculture may enter into agreements with other governmental agencies
and with counties, associations, corporations, or individuals when such cooperation
is deemed to be necessary to promote the management and control of such predatory
animals, black-tailed prairie
dogs and other injurious commensal and field rodents, nuisance
birds, or other nuisance wildlife.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 96, &#167; 1, p. 413; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 124, &#167; 2, p. 399; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-609; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 102, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB473, &#167; 11.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County animal damage control program,</emphasis> see sections 23-358 to 23-361.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>