<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-406</statuteno><catchline>Contractor, Business, and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Contractor, Business, and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Department of Labor and shall consist of fees collected by the department pursuant to the Farm Labor Contractors Act, the Contractor Registration Act, the Health Care Staffing Agency Registration Act, and the Professional Employer Organization Registration Act, the annual administrative and operational support fee described in section 48-648, and such sums as are appropriated to the fund by the Legislature.</para><para>(2) The fund shall be used for:</para><para>(a) Enforcing and administering:</para><para>(i) The Employment Security Law;</para><para>(ii) The Farm Labor Contractors Act;</para><para>(iii) The Contractor Registration Act;</para><para>(iv) The Employee Classification Act;</para><para>(v) The Health Care Staffing Agency Registration Act;</para><para>(vi) The Professional Employer Organization Registration Act;</para><para>(vii) The Non-English-Speaking Workers Protection Act;</para><para>(viii) The Wage and Hour Act;</para><para>(ix) The Nebraska Wage Payment and Collection Act;</para><para>(x) The Nebraska Healthy Families and Workplaces Act;</para><para>(xi) The child labor provisions found in sections 48-302 to 48-313;</para><para>(xii) The veterans preference provisions found in sections 48-225 to 48-231 and section 48-238;</para><para>(xiii) The military employment provisions found in sections 55-160 to 55-166; and</para><para>(xiv) The onsite safety and health consultation program provided to private sector employers under 29 C.F.R. part 1908;</para><para>(b) Any other purposes related to the proper administration of programs under the Department of Labor, as determined by the Commissioner of Labor; and</para><para>(c) Workforce development grants to be used in accordance with subsection (2) of section 81-407. No transfer from the Contractor, Business, and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund shall be made to the Workforce Development Program Cash Fund for this purpose except on written authorization by the Governor at the request of the Commissioner of Labor.</para><para>(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB270, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB847, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB921, &#167; 20. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB847, section 23, with LB921, section 20, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB847 became effective July 18, 2026. Changes made by LB921 became operative July 18, 2026.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Contractor Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2101.</para><para><emphasis>Employee Classification Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2901.</para><para><emphasis>Employment Security Law,</emphasis> see section 48-601.</para><para><emphasis>Farm Labor Contractors Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1701.</para><para><emphasis>Health Care Staffing Agency Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 48-4101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Healthy Families and Workplaces Act,</emphasis> see section 48-3801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Wage Payment and Collection Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1228.</para><para><emphasis>Non-English-Speaking Workers Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2207.</para><para><emphasis>Professional Employer Organization Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Wage and Hour Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1209.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>