<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,239.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,239.02</statuteno><catchline>State Insurance Fund; State Self-Insured Property Fund; State Self-Insured Indemnification Fund; State Self-Insured Liability Fund; created; purposes; report; attorney's fees.</catchline><para>The following separate permanent revolving funds are established in the state treasury for use under the Risk Management Program according to the purposes for which each fund is established:</para><para>(1) The State Insurance Fund is hereby created for the purpose of purchasing insurance to cover property, fidelity, and liability risks of the state and workers' compensation claims against the state and other risks to which the state or its agencies, officials, or employees are exposed and for paying related expenses, including the costs of administering the Risk Management Program. The fund may receive deposits from assessments against state agencies to provide insurance coverage as directed by the Risk Manager. The Risk Manager may retain in the fund sufficient money to pay for any deductibles, self-insured retentions, or copayments as may be required by such insurance policies and Risk Management Program expenses;</para><para>(2) The State Self-Insured Property Fund is hereby created for the purpose of replacing, repairing, or rebuilding state property which has incurred damage or is suffering other loss not fully covered by insurance and for paying related expenses. The fund may receive deposits from assessments against state agencies to provide property coverage as directed by the Risk Manager. The Risk Manager may assess state agencies to provide self-insured property coverage;</para><para>(3) The State Self-Insured Indemnification Fund is hereby created for the purpose of paying indemnification claims under section 81-8,239.05. Indemnification claims shall include payments for awards, settlements, and associated costs, including appeal bonds and reasonable costs and attorney's fees associated with a required appearance by agency legal counsel or other legal counsel hired, with prior approval of the Attorney General, to represent the agency, official, or employee before any tribunal. The fund may receive deposits from assessments against state agencies to pay for the costs associated with providing and supporting indemnification claims. The creation of this fund shall not be interpreted as expanding the liability exposure of the state or its agencies, officials, or employees; and</para><para>(4)(a) The State Self-Insured Liability Fund is hereby created for the purpose of paying compensable liability and fidelity claims against the state or its agencies, officials, or employees which are not fully covered by insurance and for which there is insufficient agency funding and for which a legislative appropriation is made under section 81-8,239.11.</para><para>(b) The fund may be used to pay claims against the state or its agencies, officials, or employees for which there is a specific provision of law for the resolution of such claims but which are not otherwise payable from the State Insurance Fund, State Self-Insured Property Fund, State Self-Insured Indemnification Fund, Workers' Compensation Claims Revolving Fund, or Tort Claims Fund. Such claims shall include payments for awards, settlements, and associated costs, including appeal bonds and reasonable costs and attorney's fees associated with a required appearance by agency legal counsel or other legal counsel hired, with prior approval of the Attorney General, to represent the agency, official, or employee before any tribunal.</para><para>(c) A claim for reasonable costs and attorney's fees described in subdivision (b) of this subsection shall be paid from the State Self-Insured Liability Fund if such claim results from the inability of the Attorney General to represent an agency, official, or employee due to a conflict of interest. A conflict of interest shall not be deemed to exist when the Attorney General is a party to such claim or represents a party to such claim.</para><para>(d) The creation of this fund shall not be interpreted as expanding the liability exposure of the state or its agencies, officials, or employees.</para><para>(e) The Risk Manager shall report electronically all claims and judgments paid from the State Self-Insured Liability Fund to the Clerk of the Legislature annually. The report shall include the name of the claimant, the amount claimed and paid, and a brief description of the claim, including any agency, program, and activity under which the claim arose. Any member of the Legislature may receive an electronic copy of the report by making a request to the Risk Manager.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 273, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 144; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1208, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 77, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1211, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1248, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 3, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 485, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB256, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 175; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB418, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB922, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>