<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id5" statutenumber="81-132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-132</statuteno><catchline id="id8">State budget; departmental
budget estimates; duty to submit; contents.</catchline><para>All
departments, offices, and institutions of the state government requesting
appropriations shall file in the office of the Director of Administrative
Services the budget forms furnished them by the director under the provisions
of sections 81-1113 and 81-1113.01. The budget forms required by this section
shall be filed on or before September 15 of each even-numbered year. The
forms shall show their total estimated requirements for the next biennium
for each unit of their organization and activity classified as to object of
expenditure. With such forms, each department, office, institution, and expending
agency shall file a report showing all money received by such department,
office, institution, or expending agency together with the estimated receipts
for the coming biennium. Such estimates shall be accompanied by a statement
in writing giving facts and explanations of reasons for each item of increased
appropriation requested. The report submitted by the Department of Health
and Human Services shall include, but not be limited to, the key goals, benchmarks,
and progress reports required pursuant to sections 81-3133 to 81-3133.03.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 210, &#167; 8, p. 748; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7275; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-308; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-132; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 526, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 12, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB949, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>April 3, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>