<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,118"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,118</statuteno><catchline>Land surveying; application and registration fees; examination fee; failure to pay fees, effect.</catchline><para>To pay the expense of the operation and enforcement of the Land Surveyors Regulation Act, the examining board shall establish application and registration fees. Total application and registration fees shall not exceed two hundred dollars and shall be in addition to the examination fee which shall be set to recover the costs of the examination and its administration. The board may direct applicants to pay the examination fee directly to a third party who has contracted to administer the examination. At the time the application for registration is submitted the board shall collect from the applicant a nonrefundable application fee. If the applicant successfully qualifies by examination, he or she shall be registered until April 1 of the immediately following odd-numbered year upon payment of a registration fee as set forth in the rules or regulations. After the issuance of a certificate of registration, a biennial fee of not less than five nor more than one hundred fifty dollars, as the examining board shall direct, shall be due and payable on or before January 1 of each odd-numbered year. Failure to remit biennial fees when due shall automatically cancel the registration effective the immediately following April 1, but otherwise the registration shall remain in full force and effect continuously from the date of issuance, unless suspended or revoked by the examining board for just cause. A registration which has been canceled for failure to pay the biennial fee when due may be reinstated within one year, but the biennial fee shall be increased ten percent for each month or fraction of a month that payment is delayed. Nothing in this section shall prevent the examining board from suspending or revoking any registration for just cause.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 383, &#167; 11, p. 1335; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 442, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 564, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 621, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 874, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB252, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB138, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>