<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,230" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,230</statuteno><catchline>Elevator mechanic license; elevator contractor license; application; form; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Any person wishing to engage in the work of an elevator mechanic shall apply for and obtain an elevator mechanic license from the State Fire Marshal. The application shall be on a form provided by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(2) Any person wishing to engage in the business of an elevator contractor shall apply for and obtain an elevator contractor license from the State Fire Marshal. The application shall be on a form provided by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(3) Each application shall contain:</para><para>(a) If an individual, the name, residence and business address, and social security number of the applicant;</para><para>(b) If a partnership, the name, residence and business address, and social security number of each partner;</para><para>(c) If a domestic corporation, the name and business address of the corporation and the name, residence address, and social security number of the principal officer of the corporation; and if a corporation other than a domestic corporation, the name and address of an agent located locally who is authorized to accept service of process and official notices;</para><para>(d) The number of years the applicant has engaged in the business of installing, inspecting, maintaining, or servicing conveyances;</para><para>(e) The approximate number of individuals to be employed by the applicant and, if applicable, satisfactory evidence that the employees are or will be covered by workers' compensation insurance;</para><para>(f) Satisfactory evidence that the applicant is or will be covered by general liability, personal injury, and property damage insurance;</para><para>(g) Permission for the State Fire Marshal to access the criminal history record information of individuals, partners, or officers maintained by the Federal Bureau of Investigation through the Nebraska State Patrol;</para><para>(h) A description of all accidents causing personal injury or property damage in excess of one thousand dollars involving conveyances installed, inspected, maintained, or serviced by the applicant; and</para><para>(i) Such other information as the State Fire Marshal may by rule and regulation require.</para><para>(4) Social security numbers on applications shall not be made public or be considered a part of a public record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-2521; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 66. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>