<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-406</statuteno><catchline>Contractor and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Contractor and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Department of Labor and shall consist of fees collected by the department pursuant to the Farm Labor Contractors Act, the Contractor Registration Act, and the Professional Employer Organization Registration Act and such sums as are appropriated to the fund by the Legislature. The fund shall be used for enforcing and administering the Farm Labor Contractors Act, the Contractor Registration Act, the Employee Classification Act, and the Professional Employer Organization Registration Act. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Money in the Contractor and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund may be transferred to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer one million seven hundred thousand dollars from the Contractor and Professional Employer Organization Registration Cash Fund to the General Fund on or before June 15, 2018, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB270, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 47. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Contractor Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2101.</para><para><emphasis>Employee Classification Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2901.</para><para><emphasis>Farm Labor Contractors Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1701.</para>><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Professional Employer Organization Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>