<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,139.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,139.01</statuteno><catchline>Athletic Advisory Committee;
created; members; qualifications; expenses; duties; appeal.</catchline><para>(1)
An advisory committee is hereby created which shall be known as the Athletic
Advisory Committee. The Governor shall appoint five persons
to the committee. The members shall be selected on their experience, training,
and interest in mixed martial arts, professional boxing,
and professional wrestling.
One member shall be or shall have been active in mixed martial arts, one member shall be or shall have been
active in professional wrestling, one member shall be or shall have been active
in professional boxing, one member shall be a medical doctor with ringside
experience, and one member shall be an at-large member. The members shall
serve at the pleasure of the Governor, and the commissioner may recommend
individuals to serve on the advisory committee. The members shall receive
no salaries but shall receive reimbursement for their expenses as provided
in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The committee shall meet and be located within
the Charitable Gaming Division of the Department of Revenue. The committee
may exercise and perform its powers and duties at any location in the state.
The committee shall review the rules and regulations drawn up by the commissioner
pursuant to section 81-8,139 and shall make recommendations and give advice
regarding any proposed or adopted rules and regulations.</para>
<para>(2) The Athletic Advisory Committee shall serve as an appeals board
which shall hear and determine all cases of parties who contest any of the
State Athletic Commissioner's decisions. The procedure for such appeal shall
be designated in the commissioner's rules and regulations, and the decision
of the committee shall be by a majority vote of the committee. Any party who
wishes to appeal from the committee's decision may appeal the decision, and
the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 849, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 170; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 397, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1033, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB471, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB869, &#167; 11.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>