<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id489" statutenumber="81-505.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>81-505.01</statuteno><catchline id="id492">State Fire Marshal; establish and assess fees; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) The State Fire Marshal shall establish and assess fees not to exceed the actual costs for the performance of services by the State Fire Marshal or by qualified local fire prevention personnel to whom the State Fire Marshal has delegated authority to perform such services. Prior to establishing or altering such fees, the State Fire Marshal shall hold a public hearing on the question of the adoption of or change in fees. Notice of such hearing shall be given at least thirty days prior thereto (a) by publication in a newspaper having general circulation in the state and (b) by notifying in writing the head of any agency or department having jurisdiction over facilities that would be subject to the fees. Fees for services performed by the State Fire Marshal shall be paid to the State Fire Marshal and shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Fire Marshal Cash Fund. Fees for services performed by local fire prevention personnel shall be paid directly to the office of the local fire prevention personnel.</para><para>(2) The fee for inspection for fire safety of any premises or facility pursuant to section 81-502 or 81-503.01 shall be not less than twenty-five nor more than one hundred fifty dollars and shall be paid by the licensee or applicant for a license. The fee for inspection for fire safety of the same premises or facility made within twelve months after the last prior inspection shall be not less than twenty-five nor more than one hundred fifty dollars and shall be paid by the licensee or applicant for a license. The fees for inspection for fire safety of foster family homes as defined in section 71-1901 may be paid by the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(3) The fee for providing investigation reports to insurance companies shall not exceed three dollars for each report provided. The State Fire Marshal may charge an amount not to exceed the actual cost of preparation for any other approved information release.</para><para>(4)(a) The State Fire Marshal shall charge a fee for reviewing plans, blueprints, and shop drawings to determine compliance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 81-503.01 or 81-5,147. The State Fire Marshal shall establish such fee in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated to be effective on January 1, 2022. Such fee shall meet the costs of administering the plan review requirement found in sections 81-503.01 and 81-5,147 but shall not exceed five hundred dollars. The fee schedule as it existed prior to August 28, 2021, shall be used through December 31, 2021.</para><para>(b) The fees established pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection shall not be assessed or collected by any political subdivision to which the State Fire Marshal has delegated the authority to conduct such review and which reviews plans, blueprints, or shop drawings to determine compliance with such political subdivision's own fire safety regulations. Nothing in this subdivision shall be construed to prohibit such political subdivision from assessing or collecting a fee set by its governing board for such review.</para><para>(c) An additional fee equal to fifty percent of the fee charged pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be assessed for reviewing plans, blueprints, and shop drawings to determine compliance with the accessibility standards and specifications adopted pursuant to section 81-5,147, except that the additional fee assessed pursuant to this subdivision shall not exceed two hundred fifty dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 498, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 471, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 893, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 930, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 251, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 377, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 839; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 216; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB195, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB37, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>