<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.57"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.57</statuteno><catchline>Persons within the state; conduct; personal services; compensation for property; claim; file.</catchline><para>(1) Each person within this state shall conduct himself or herself and keep and manage his or her affairs and property in ways that will reasonably assist and will not unreasonably detract from the ability of the state and the public successfully to meet disasters, emergencies, or civil defense emergencies. This obligation shall include appropriate personal service and use or restriction on the use of property in time of disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency. The Emergency Management Act shall not be construed to increase or decrease these obligations, but the act recognizes their existence under the Constitution of Nebraska and statutes of this state and the common law. Compensation for services or for the taking or use of property shall be only to the extent that obligations recognized in this subsection are exceeded in a particular case and then only to the extent that the claimant may not be deemed to have volunteered his or her services or property without compensation.</para><para>(2) No personal services may be compensated by the state or any subdivision or agency thereof, except pursuant to statute or local law, resolution, or ordinance.</para><para>(3) Compensation for property shall be made only if the property was commandeered or otherwise used in coping with a disaster, emergency, or civil defense emergency and its use or destruction was ordered by the Governor or a member of the emergency management forces of this state to whom the Governor has duly delegated such authority.</para><para>(4) Any person claiming compensation for the use, damage, loss, or destruction of property under the act shall file a claim therefor with the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency in the form and manner the agency provides.</para><para>(5) Unless the amount of compensation on account of property damaged, lost, or destroyed is agreed upon between the claimant and the agency, the amount of compensation shall be calculated in the same manner as compensation due for a taking of property pursuant to the condemnation laws of this state.</para><para>(6) Nothing in this section shall apply to or authorize compensation for the destruction or damaging of standing timber or other property in order to provide a fire break or to the release of waters or the breach of impoundments in order to reduce pressure or other danger from actual or threatened flood.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 37. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For eminent domain procedures,</emphasis> see section 76-701 et seq.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>