<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,148"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,148</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement of standards and specifications; responsibility; failure to comply; effect.</catchline><para>The responsibility for enforcement of the standards and specifications adopted pursuant to section 81-5,147 for (1) buildings and facilities which are newly constructed for first occupancy, (2) alterations of existing buildings and facilities used by the public, and (3) new constructed covered multifamily dwellings as defined in section 20-319 shall lie with the State Fire Marshal or the appropriate officials of the governing bodies of the state government and its political subdivisions responsible for the review and approval of the building plans. Enforcement responsibility includes an appeal process conducted by the enforcing authority for the appeal of any enforcement action or proposed enforcement action. With respect to the enforcement of section 81-5,147 as described in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section, when plans are being reviewed for both building code and fire code regulations, the officials responsible for building code review shall be responsible for enforcement of section 81-5,147. With respect to the enforcement of section 81-5,147 as described in subdivision (3) of this section, when plans are being reviewed for both building code and fire code regulations, the officials in a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class shall be responsible for enforcement of section 81-5,147. Officials in a city of the second class or village shall not be responsible for enforcement of section 81-5,147 as described in subdivision (3) of this section if such officials have submitted to the State Fire Marshal a written statement declaring their intent not to assume responsibility for such enforcement. When plans are being reviewed solely for fire code regulations or when the officials responsible for building code review have submitted such a written statement, the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee shall be responsible for enforcement of section 81-5,147. No official of any governing body of the state government or its political subdivisions responsible for such enforcement shall approve or authorize an occupancy permit unless such building, facility, or dwelling complies with the standards and specifications prescribed by such section. Any unauthorized departure from the standards and specifications established by the State Fire Marshal pursuant to such section may be corrected by full compliance with such standards and specifications within one hundred eighty days after discovery of such departure. Failure to correct an unauthorized departure from such standards and specifications shall result in denial or revocation of the occupancy permit for the building, facility, or dwelling.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 430, &#167; 19, p. 1377; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 602, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 986, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 473, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 646, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 72-1119; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 377, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 161. </para></source></law></legaldoc>