<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-885.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.03</statuteno><catchline>Broker, associate broker, salesperson,
defined; license required;
cease and desist order; violation; fine; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any person
who, directly or indirectly for another, with the intention or upon the promise
of receiving any form of compensation or consideration, offers, attempts,
or agrees to perform or performs any single act described in subdivision (2)
of section 81-885.01, whether as a part of a transaction, or as an entire
transaction, shall be deemed a broker, associate broker, or salesperson within
the meaning of the Nebraska Real Estate License Act, and such action shall constitute sufficient contact with
the state for the exercise of personal jurisdiction over such person in any
action arising out of such action. Committing a single act described
in such subdivision by a person required to be licensed under the Nebraska
Real Estate License Act and not so licensed shall constitute a violation of
the act for which the commission
may impose sanctions pursuant to this section for the protection of the public
health, safety, or welfare.</para>
<para>(2) Notwithstanding any
other provision of the law to the contrary, the director may issue a cease
and desist order against any person who violates this section by performing
any action described in subsection (1) of this section without the appropriate
license. Such order shall be final ten days after issuance unless the violator
requests a hearing pursuant to section 81-885.25.</para><para>(3) If such person violates a cease
and desist order issued pursuant to this section, he or she shall be subject
to further proceedings before the commission. If, during such proceedings,
the commission makes a finding of guilt, the commission may impose a fine
not to exceed (a) one thousand dollars for each day that any action is performed
without the appropriate license following the issuance of the order or (b)
the amount of all money earned as commission by the violator, whichever is
greater. Judgments for the collection of any fine imposed under this section
may be filed in the district court of any county in this state.</para>
<para>(4) Notice and hearing
requirements under this section shall be in accordance with the Administrative
Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 68, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 182, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 863, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB691, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>