<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-885.21"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-885.21</statuteno><catchline>Broker; separate trust account; notify commission where maintained; examination by representative of commission; broker entitled to money; when.</catchline><para>(1) Each broker other than an inactive broker shall maintain in a bank, savings bank, building and loan association, or savings and loan association a separate, insured non-interest-bearing checking account in this state in his or her name or the name under which he or she does business which shall be designated a trust account in which all downpayments, earnest money deposits, or other trust funds received by him or her, his or her associate brokers, or his or her salespersons on behalf of his or her principal or any other person shall be deposited and remain until the transaction is closed or otherwise terminated unless all parties having an interest in the funds have agreed otherwise in writing.</para><para>(2) Each broker shall notify the commission of the name of the bank, savings bank, building and loan association, or savings and loan association in which the trust account is maintained and also the name of the account on forms provided therefor.</para><para>(3) Each broker shall authorize the commission to examine such trust account by a duly authorized representative of the commission. Such examination shall be made annually or at such time as the commission may direct.</para><para>(4) A broker may maintain more than one trust account in his or her name or the name under which he or she does business if the commission is advised of such account as required in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(5) In the event a branch office maintains a separate trust account, a separate bookkeeping system shall be maintained in the branch office.</para><para>(6) A broker shall not be entitled to any part of the earnest money or other money paid to him or her or the entity under which he or she does business in connection with any real estate transaction as part or all of his or her compensation or consideration until the transaction has been consummated or terminated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 68, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 354, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 361, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 238, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 118, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 863, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc>