<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,230"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,230</statuteno><catchline>Elevator mechanic license; elevator contractor license; application; form; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Any person wishing to engage in the work of an elevator mechanic shall apply for and obtain an elevator mechanic license from the State Fire Marshal. The application shall be on a form provided by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(2) Any person wishing to engage in the business of an elevator contractor shall apply for and obtain an elevator contractor license from the State Fire Marshal. The application shall be on a form provided by the State Fire Marshal.</para><para>(3) Each application for an elevator mechanic license shall contain:</para><para>(a) The name and address of the applicant;</para><para>(b) A contact email address;</para><para>(c) A contact telephone number;</para><para>(d) The number of years the applicant has engaged in the business of installing, inspecting, maintaining, or servicing conveyances;</para><para>(e) Permission for the State Fire Marshal to access the criminal history record information of individuals, partners, or officers maintained by the Federal Bureau of Investigation through the Nebraska State Patrol; and</para><para>(f) Such other information as the State Fire Marshal may by rule and regulation require.</para><para>(4) Each application for an elevator contractor license shall contain:</para><para>(a) All information required under subsection (3) of this section;</para><para>(b) The name and address of the business;</para><para>(c) The approximate number of employees to be employed by the applicant and, if applicable, satisfactory evidence that the employees are or will be covered by workers' compensation insurance;</para><para>(d) Satisfactory evidence that the applicant is or will be covered by general liability, personal injury, and property damage insurance;</para><para>(e) A description of all accidents causing personal injury or property damage in excess of one thousand dollars involving conveyances installed, inspected, maintained, or serviced by the applicant; and</para><para>(f) The name, telephone number, and Nebraska elevator mechanic license number of a licensed elevator mechanic employed by or contracted with the business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 489, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2010), &#167; 48-2521; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB301, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB415, &#167; 27. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>