<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,147.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,147.02</statuteno><catchline>Container; labeling requirements.</catchline><para>Each container of agricultural, vegetable, or flower seeds which is
sold within this state for sowing purposes shall bear thereon or have attached
thereto in a conspicuous place a plainly written or printed label or tag in
the English language giving the following information, which statement shall
not be modified or denied in the labeling or on another label attached to
the container:</para>
<para>(1) For any agricultural seeds or any mixture thereof, any vegetable
seeds or any mixture thereof, or any flower seeds or any mixture thereof for
sowing purposes that have been treated, unless each seed container bears a
label giving the following information and statements as established in the
rules and regulations:</para>
<para>(a) A word or statement indicating that the seeds have been treated;</para>
<para>(b) The commonly accepted coined, chemical (generic), or abbreviated
chemical name of any substance used in such treatment;</para>
<para>(c) If the substance used in such treatment in the amount remaining
with the seeds is harmful to humans or other vertebrate animals, an appropriate
caution statement approved by the director as adequate for the protection
of the public such as, "Do Not Use For Food Or Feed Or Oil Purposes", except
that the caution statement for mercurials and similarly toxic substances,
as established in the rules and regulations, shall be a representation of
a skull and crossbones and a statement such as, "This Seed Has Been Treated
With POISON", in red letters on a background of distinctly contrasting color;</para>
<para>(d) A description approved by the director for the protection of the
public of any process used in such treatment; and</para>
<para>(e) If the seed is treated with an inoculant, the year and month beyond
which the inoculant, if shown in the labeling, is no longer claimed to be
effective (Date of expiration);</para>
<para>(2) For agricultural seeds except for grass seed mixtures as provided
in subdivision (5) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) The commonly accepted name of the kind and variety of each agricultural
seed component, in excess of five percent of the whole, and the percentage
by weight of each in the order of its predominance, except that if the variety
of the kinds which are generally labeled as to their variety as established
in the rules and regulations is not stated, the label shall show the name
of the kind and the words, "Variety Not Stated". When more than one component
is required to be named, the word mixture, mix, mixed, or blend shall be shown
conspicuously on the label. Hybrids shall be labeled as hybrids except when
the pure seed contains less than seventy-five percent hybrid seed. If the
percentage of the hybrid seed is equal to or greater than seventy-five percent
but less than ninety-five percent, the percentage of hybrid shall be labeled
parenthetically following the variety;</para>
<para>(b) The lot number or other lot identification;</para>
<para>(c) Origin, if known. If the origin is unknown, the fact shall be stated;</para>
<para>(d) The percentage by weight of all weed seed;</para>
<para>(e) The name and rate of occurrence per pound of each kind of restricted
noxious weed seed:</para>
<para>(i) For Agrostis spp., bluegrass, timothy, orchardgrass, fescue, alsike
clover, white clover, reed canarygrass, ryegrass, foxtail millet, alfalfa,
red clover, sweetclover, lespedeza, smooth brome, crimson clover, Brassica
spp., flax, wheatgrass, and other agricultural seed of similar size and weight,
or mixtures within such group, when present singly or collectively in excess
of eighteen seeds per pound; and</para>
<para>(ii) For all other agricultural seed or agricultural seed mixtures not
included in subdivision (i) of this subdivision, when present, label as found;</para>
<para>(f) Percentage by weight of agricultural seeds which may be designated
as other crop seed other than those required to be named on the label;</para>
<para>(g) The percentage by weight of inert matter;</para>
<para>(h) For each named agricultural seed, the percentage of germination
exclusive of hard seed and the percentage of hard seed if present. Following
the percentage of germination exclusive of hard seed and the percentage of
hard seed, if present, the total germination and hard seed percentage may
be stated if desired. The calendar month and year the test was completed to
determine such percentages or an expiration date for those seeds labeled for
lawn and turf purposes shall also be stated;</para>
<para>(i) For each of the following named grasses the percentage of germination
exclusive of dormant seed, the percentage of dormant seed if present, or the
percentage of viability as indicated by a tetrazolium (TZ) test and the calendar
month and year the test was completed to determine such percentages. Following
the percentage of germination, exclusive of dormant seed and the percentage
of dormant seed, if present, the total germination and dormant seed may be
stated if desired. Also, for each of the following named grasses when extreme
dormancy is encountered, the result of a tetrazolium (TZ) test may be shown
in lieu of the percentage of germination to indicate the potential viability
of the seed:</para>
<para>
<table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="COLSPEC2" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec align="right" colname="col2" colwidth="1.04*"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Bluestem:</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Big</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Andropogon gerardii</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Little</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Schizachyrium scoparium</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Sand</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Andropogon hallii</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Yellow</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Bothriochioa ischaemum</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Dropseed, sand</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Sporobolus cryptandrus</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Buffalograss</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Buchloe dactyloides</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Grama:</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Sideoats</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Bouteloua curtipendula</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Blue</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Bouteloua gracilis</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Indiangrass</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Sorghastrum nutans</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Lovegrass, sand</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Eragrostis trichodes</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Needlegrass, green</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Stipa viridula</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Prairie sandreed</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Calamovilfa longifolia</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Ricegrass, Indian</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Oryzopsis hymenoides</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Wheatgrass, western</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Elymus smithii</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Switchgrass</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Panicum virgatum; and</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></para>
<para>(j) The name and address of the person who labeled such seed or who
sells such seed within this state;</para>
<para>(3) For agricultural, vegetable, and flower seeds that are coated:</para>
<para>(a) The percentage of pure seeds with coating material removed;</para>
<para>(b) The percentage of coating material should be shown as a separate
item in close association with the percentage of inert matter; and</para>
<para>(c) The percentage of germination should be determined on four hundred
pellets with or without seeds;</para>
<para>(4) For products which claim to be a combination of mulch, seed, and
fertilizer the word combination shall be followed by the words "Mulch - Seed
- Fertilizer". The word combination must appear on the upper thirty percent
of the principal display panel and must be the largest and most conspicuous
type on the container, equal to or larger than the product name. The words
"Mulch - Seed - Fertilizer" shall be no smaller than one-half the size of,
and in close proximity to, the word combination. Such product shall contain
a minimum of seventy percent mulch;</para>
<para>(5) For seed mixtures for lawns and turf purposes in containers of fifty
pounds or less:</para>
<para>(a) The word mixed, mixture, mix, or blend;</para>
<para>(b) Commonly accepted name, in order of its predominance of the kind
and variety, or kind of each agricultural seed present in excess of five percent
of the whole;</para>
<para>(c) Percentage by weight of pure seed of each agricultural seed named;</para>
<para>(d) For each agricultural seed named under subdivision (b) of this subdivision:</para>
<para>(i) Percentage of germination exclusive of hard seed;</para>
<para>(ii) Percentage of hard seed if present; and</para>
<para>(iii) Calendar month and year the test was completed to determine such
percentages or an expiration date;</para>
<para>(e) Percentage by weight of all weed seed;</para>
<para>(f) Percentage by weight of all agricultural seeds, which may be designated
as crop seed, other than those stated under subdivision (b) of this subdivision;</para>
<para>(g) Percentage by weight of inert matter;</para>
<para>(h) Lot number or other lot identification;</para>
<para>(i) The name and rate of occurrence of each kind of restricted noxious
weed seed per pound when present singly or collectively in excess of the numbers
shown in subdivision (2)(e)(i) of this section;</para>
<para>(j) Name and address of the person who labeled such seed or who sells
such seed within this state;</para>
<para>(k) Origin, if known. If the origin is unknown, the fact shall be stated; and</para>
<para>(l) For cool season lawn
and turf grass seed and mixtures, including kentucky bluegrass, red fescue,
chewings fescue, hard fescue, tall fescue, perennial rye grass, intermediate
rye grass, annual rye grass, colonial bentgrass, and creeping bentgrass:</para>
<para>(i) The calendar month
and year the germination test was completed to determine the percentage required
under subdivision (5)(d)(i) of this section and the germination test date
for each component or, if each component does not show a germination test
date, the oldest germination test date shall be used for the mixture; or</para>
<para>(ii) In place of the
test date, the statement "sell by (date)", which date shall not be more than
fifteen months after the date of the germination test exclusive of the month
of the germination test;</para><para>(6) For grass seed for which
claims are made regarding the beneficial presence of Acremonium species:</para>
<para>(a) The seed shall have on the analysis label or on a separate label
which is in close proximity to the analysis label the actual percentage of
viable endophyte present in each component and the month and year that a viable
endophyte test was performed to establish the percentage of endophyte present.
For mixtures, the oldest test date shall be used. The test date shall be stated
as "Endophyte Test Date". Freshly harvested seed may be labeled and shipped
based on a seed endophyte test until October 1 of the harvest year; and</para>
<para>(b) The viable endophyte test must have been conducted within the last
nine months, not including the month of the test. If the test date exceeds
nine months the seed lot must be retested and relabeled or all references
to endophyte must be removed from the label;</para>
<para>(7) For vegetable seeds in containers prepared for use in home gardens
or household plantings or vegetable seeds in preplanted containers, mats,
tapes, or other planting devices:</para>
<para>(a) The name of the kind and variety of seed;</para>
<para>(b) Lot number or other lot identification;</para>
<para>(c) The calendar month and year the seeds were tested or the year for
which the seed was packaged for sale as "Packed for (year)";</para>
<para>(d) For seeds which germinate less than the standard last established
in the rules and regulations:</para>
<para>(i) Percentage of germination exclusive of hard seed;</para>
<para>(ii) Percentage of hard seed if present;</para>
<para>(iii) The calendar month and year the test was completed to determine
such percentages; and</para>
<para>(iv) The words "Below Standard" in not less than eight-point type;</para>
<para>(e) For seeds placed in a germination medium, mat, tape, or other device
in such a way as to make it difficult to determine the quantity of seed without
removing the seeds from the medium, mat, tape, or other device, a statement
to indicate the minimum number of seeds in the container;</para>
<para>(f) The name and rate of occurrence per pound of each kind of restricted
noxious weed seed present; and</para>
<para>(g) The name and address of the person who labeled such seed or who
sells such seed within this state;</para>
<para>(8) For vegetable seeds in containers other than containers prepared
for use in home gardens or household plantings and other than preplanted containers,
mats, tapes, or other planting devices:</para>
<para>(a) The name of each kind and variety present in excess of five percent
and the percentage by weight of each in order of its predominance;</para>
<para>(b) Lot number or other lot identification;</para>
<para>(c) For each named vegetable seed:</para>
<para>(i) The percentage of germination exclusive of hard seed;</para>
<para>(ii) The percentage of hard seed if present; and</para>
<para>(iii) The calendar month and year the test was completed to determine
such percentages. Following the information prescribed in subdivisions (i)
and (ii) of this subdivision, the total germination and hard seed percentage
may be stated as such, if desired;</para>
<para>(d) The name and rate of occurrence per pound of each kind of restricted
noxious weed seed present; and</para>
<para>(e) Name and address of the person who labeled the seed or who sells
such seed within this state;</para>
<para>(9) For flower seeds in containers prepared for use in home gardens
or household plantings or flower seeds in preplanted containers, mats, tapes,
or other planting devices:</para>
<para>(a) For all kinds of flower seeds:</para>
<para>(i) The name of the kind and variety or a statement of type and performance
characteristics as established in rules and regulations. Mixtures shall be
listed on the label as mixture, mix, or mixed. Seeds described as native wildflower
seeds shall only be seeds from flowers that are indigenous to North America.
Seeds described as introduced wildflower seeds shall only be seeds from flowers
that are not indigenous to North America;</para>
<para>(ii) The calendar month and year the seed was tested or the year for
which the seed was packaged for sale as "Packed for (year)"; and</para>
<para>(iii) The name and address of the person who labeled the seed for sale
within this state;</para>
<para>(b) For seeds of those kinds for which standard testing procedures are
prescribed, such as methods published by the Association of Official Seed
Analysts or other generally recognized methods, and which germinate less than
the germination standard last established in the rules and regulations:</para>
<para>(i) Percentage of germination exclusive of hard seeds; and</para>
<para>(ii) The words "Below Standard" in not less than eight-point type; and</para>
<para>(c) For seeds placed in a germination medium, mat, tape, or other device
in such a way as to make it difficult to determine the quantity of seed without
removing the seeds from the medium, mat, tape, or device, a statement to indicate
the minimum number of seeds in the container;</para>
<para>(10) For flower seeds in containers other than packets prepared for
use in home flower gardens or household plantings and other than preplanted
containers, mats, tapes, or other planting devices:</para>
<para>(a) The name of the kind and variety or a statement of type and performance
characteristics as established in rules and regulations. Mixtures shall be
listed on the label as mixture, mixed, or mix. Seeds described as native wildflower
seeds shall only be seeds from flowers that are indigenous to North America.
Seeds described as introduced wildflower seeds shall only be seeds from flowers
that are not indigenous to North America;</para>
<para>(b) The percentage by weight of pure seed for each flower seed named;</para>
<para>(c) Lot number or other lot identification;</para>
<para>(d) Percentage by weight of all weed seed when present in flower seed;</para>
<para>(e) Name and rate of occurrence per pound of each kind of restricted
noxious weed seed, if present, listed under the heading noxious weed seeds;</para>
<para>(f) The calendar month and year that the seed was tested;</para>
<para>(g) The name and address of the person who labeled the seed or who sells
the seed within this state; and</para>
<para>(h) For those kinds of seed for which standard testing procedures are
prescribed in generally recognized official methods:</para>
<para>(i) Percentage of germination exclusive of hard seed; and</para>
<para>(ii) Percentage of hard seed if present; and</para>
<para>(11) For agricultural seeds sold on a pure live seed basis, as established
in the rules and regulations, the information required by subdivision (2)(a)
of this section, except as modified in this subdivision:</para>
<para>(a) The label need not show:</para>
<para>(i) The percentage by weight of each agricultural seed component as
required by subdivision (2)(a) of this section; or</para>
<para>(ii) The percentage by weight of inert matter as required by subdivision
(2)(g) of this section; and</para>
<para>(b) The label shall, instead of the information required by subdivision
(2)(h) of this section or subdivision (2)(i) of this section when appropriate,
show for each named agricultural seed:</para>
<para>(i) The percentage of pure live seed as established in the rules and
regulations; and</para>
<para>(ii) The calendar month and year in which the test determining the percentage
of pure live seed was completed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 759, &#167; 3, p. 2863; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1290, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 633, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 460, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 37, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 263, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB166, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>