<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-6,109"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-6,109</statuteno><catchline>Transition from prior law.</catchline><para>(1) On and after May 26, 2001, for purposes of the Parkinson's Disease Registry Act:</para><para>(a) Any rules, regulations, and orders of the Department of Health and Human Services Regulation and Licensure adopted pursuant to the former Parkinson's Disease Registry Act, as such act existed prior to February 14, 2001, and in effect on February 13, 2001, shall be revived and continue in effect until revised, amended, repealed, or nullified pursuant to law;</para><para>(b) Any contracts entered into by the department prior to February 14, 2001, and in effect on February 13, 2001, in connection with the duties and functions of the former act are recognized and may be revived upon the agreement of all contract parties. If revived, the department shall succeed to all rights and obligations under such contracts;</para><para>(c) Any cash funds, custodial funds, gifts, trusts, grants, and appropriations of funds which were available for use by the department for purposes of the former act shall continue to be available for use by the department if such funds continue to exist; and</para><para>(d) Any documents created, information compiled, or property used by the department under the former act shall continue to be available to and may be used by the department.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, former act means the Parkinson's Disease Registry Act, as such act existed prior to February 14, 2001, which act was outright repealed in Laws 2001, LB 209.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 152, &#167; 17. </para></source></law></legaldoc>