<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id735"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,279"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,279</statuteno><catchline>Mobile Food Establishment Ordinance Registry; department; powers and duties; city of the first class or city of the second class; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, city means a city of the first class or a city of the second class.</para><para>(2) The department shall establish and maintain the Mobile Food Establishment Ordinance Registry. The registry shall be made available for review by the public on the department's website. The purpose of the registry is to record in a central location the municipal ordinances used to regulate mobile food establishments.</para><para>(3) Each city shall participate in the registry. Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, each city shall provide the department with the following information for the registry:</para><para>(a) The name and address of each person responsible for regulating mobile food establishment operations;</para><para>(b) A sample copy of any form that is required to be submitted in order for the mobile food establishment to operate in the city;</para><para>(c) A complete electronic record of the ordinances used to regulate mobile food establishments; and</para><para>(d) Any other information the department deems necessary.</para><para>(4) Any city that does not regulate the operation of mobile food establishments in any way shall submit to the department for publication on the registry a written statement confirming that the city does not regulate the operation of mobile food establishments.</para><para>(5) To ensure an accurate and updated registry, each city shall:</para><para>(a) Upon a request by the department, make available to the department all information required pursuant to this section; and</para><para>(b) Beginning in 2023, by December 31 of each calendar year notify the department of any new or modified ordinance adopted within such calendar year regulating mobile food establishments.</para><para>(6) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB562, &#167; 28. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>