<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,200"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,200</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of licensure; expiration; notice; renewal.</catchline><para>Certificates of licensure shall expire on a date established by the board and shall become invalid on that date unless renewed. In 2021, a licensee whose last name begins with a letter between the letters "A" and "L" shall renew his or her certificate of licensure for one year and a licensee whose last name begins with a letter between the letters "M" and "Z" shall renew his or her certificate of licensure for two years. Each subsequent renewal shall be for a two-year period. The board shall notify every person licensed under the Professional Landscape Architects Act of the expiration date of his or her certificate of licensure and the amount of the fee, in accordance with subsection (1) of section 81-8,194, required for renewal. The notice shall be sent at least one month in advance of the date of the expiration. Valid certificates of licensure may be renewed prior to expiration upon application and payment of applicable fees. The fee to be paid on an expired certificate of licensure shall be increased by ten percent for each month or fraction of a month such payment is delayed, except that the maximum fee for a delayed renewal shall not exceed twice the amount of the original renewal fee and no renewals shall be made after one year after the expiration date, in accordance with subsection (1) of section 81-8,194. Expired licenses shall be renewed in accordance with the rules and regulations of the board. The board may require individual licensees to obtain professional development in accordance with the rules and regulations of the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 565, &#167; 17, p. 1865; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 477, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1140, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB30, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>