<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id906"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.08</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Nonprofit Security Grant Program; created; administration; grant; application; purpose; issuance; working group.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Nonprofit Security Grant Program is created. The program shall be administered by the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency.</para><para>(2) In order to receive a grant under the program, a qualified nonprofit organization shall submit an application to the agency on a form prescribed by the agency. The agency may accept an application submitted to the federal government for a federal nonprofit security grant instead of the state application prescribed by the agency.</para><para>(3) Grants may be issued to qualified nonprofit organizations to reimburse such organizations for the costs of target hardening and other safety and security projects intended to mitigate vulnerabilities identified in a vulnerability assessment completed by the qualified nonprofit organization or by a vendor with whom the qualified nonprofit organization has contracted, including projects involving:</para><para>(a) Planning;</para><para>(b) Equipment;</para><para>(c) Training; or</para><para>(d) Security personnel.</para><para>(4) The agency may prescribe requirements for vulnerability assessments and may allow other target hardening and safety and security projects to qualify for grant funding in addition to those activities described in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(5) The agency may begin issuing grants under the program on January 1, 2025.</para><para>(6) The agency shall establish a working group of stakeholders to review and evaluate applications. The working group shall make recommendations on funding decisions and shall provide such recommendations to the agency.</para><para>(7) The agency may award up to five hundred thousand dollars in grants per year. A qualified nonprofit organization shall not receive more than fifty thousand dollars in grants in any one year.</para><para>(8) A qualified nonprofit organization shall not be eligible for a grant under the program if:</para><para>(a) The qualified nonprofit organization applied for a grant under the program and received the full amount of its funding request in the previous year; or</para><para>(b) The qualified nonprofit organization received a federal nonprofit security grant within the previous five years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1300, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>