
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.56"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.56</statuteno><catchline>Interstate Civil Defense and Disaster Compact; withdrawal; recognition of credential, when; other agreements or compacts; approval.</catchline><para>(1) The State of Nebraska hereby withdraws from the Interstate Civil Defense and Disaster Compact pursuant to Article 13 of such compact.</para><para>(2) If any person holds a license, certificate, or other permit issued by any state or political subdivision thereof evidencing the meeting of qualifications for professional, mechanical, or other skills, the person may render aid involving that skill in this state to meet an emergency or disaster, and the State of Nebraska shall give due recognition to the license, certificate, or other permit.</para><para>(3) The Governor may enter into, and execute on behalf of the State of Nebraska, mutual aid agreements or emergency preparedness compacts with other states. Any such agreement or compact shall provide for reimbursement of all costs incurred by the State of Nebraska for actions taken in another state, for indemnification of the State of Nebraska and its employees against all claims, costs, or fees arising from actions taken in another state, and for termination of the agreement or assistance as necessary to meet disasters, emergencies, or other needs of the State of Nebraska. Any mutual aid agreement or emergency preparedness compact other than the Emergency Management Assistance Compact that does not meet the requirements specified in this subsection shall be submitted electronically to the Legislature for approval by the Legislature before such agreement or compact can become effective.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 494, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 43, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 172; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB847, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Emergency Management Assistance Compact,</emphasis> see section 1-124, Appendix, Nebraska Revised Statutes, Volume 2A.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>