<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-8,119.01" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,119.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">License; renewal; professional development requirements; inactive status.</catchline><para>(1) As a condition for renewal of a license issued pursuant to the Land Surveyors Regulation Act, a licensee who has previously renewed his or her license shall be required to successfully complete thirty hours of professional development within the preceding two calendar years. Any licensee who completes in excess of thirty hours of professional development within the preceding two calendar years may have the excess, not to exceed fifteen hours, applied to the requirement for the next biennium.</para><para>(2) The examining board shall not renew the license of any licensee who has failed to complete the professional development requirements pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, unless he or she can show good cause why he or she was unable to comply with such requirements. If the examining board determines that good cause was shown, the examining board shall permit the professional land surveyor to make up all outstanding required hours of professional development.</para><para>(3) A licensee may at any time prior to the termination of his or her license request to be classified as inactive. Such inactive licenses may be maintained by payment of a biennial fee of not less than five nor more than fifty dollars as determined by the examining board. Holders of inactive licenses shall not be required to complete professional development as required in subsection (1) of this section. Holders of inactive licenses shall not practice land surveying. If the examining board determines that an inactive licensee has actively practiced land surveying, the examining board may immediately revoke his or her license.</para><para>(4) A holder of an inactive license may return his or her license to an active license to practice land surveying by the applicant electing to either:</para><para>(a) Complete one and one-half the biennial requirement for professional development. Such requirement shall be satisfied as set forth in the rules or bylaws; or</para><para>(b) Take such examination as the examining board deems necessary to determine his or her qualifications. Such examination shall cover areas designed to demonstrate the applicant's proficiency in current methods of land surveying practice.</para><para>Additionally he or she shall pay the biennial fee as required in section 81-8,118.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 478, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 564, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 621, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 874, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB138, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB102, &#167; 35. </para><operativedate>September 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>