<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-2,162.27"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,162.27</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Fertilizers and Beneficial Substances Administrative Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) All money received under the Nebraska Commercial Fertilizer and Beneficial Substances Act and the Agricultural Liming Materials Act shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Fertilizers and Beneficial Substances Administrative Fund.</para><para>(2) The Fertilizers and Beneficial Substances Administrative Fund is created. Money in the fund shall be used by the department for defraying the expenses of administering the Nebraska Commercial Fertilizer and Beneficial Substances Act, the Agricultural Liming Materials Act, and any other plant health program that is administered by the department. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para><para>(3) Any unexpended balance in the Fertilizers and Beneficial Substances Administrative Fund at the close of any biennium shall, when reappropriated, be available for the uses and purposes of the fund for the succeeding biennium. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 333, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 157, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB93, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB243, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB657, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB262, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB794, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB948, &#167; 33. </para><note> The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB794, section 4, with LB948, section 33, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB794 became effective July 18, 2026. Changes made by LB948 became effective March 17, 2026.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Agricultural Liming Materials Act,</emphasis> see section 2-4301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>