<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id661" statutenumber="81-8,194"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,194</statuteno><catchline id="id664">Board; fees; disposition; State Board of Landscape Architects Cash Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall establish fees of no more than three hundred dollars for applications and initial certificates of licensure and annual renewals for services related to the Professional Landscape Architects Act based on the administration costs incurred by the board. The board shall collect, account for, and remit such fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Board of Landscape Architects Cash Fund which is hereby created. All fees are nonrefundable.</para><para>(2) Transfers may be made from the State Board of Landscape Architects Cash Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the State Board of Landscape Architects Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) Warrants for the payment of expenses and compensation as provided for in the Professional Landscape Architects Act shall be issued by the Director of Administrative Services and paid by the State Treasurer out of the State Board of Landscape Architects Cash Fund upon presentation of vouchers regularly drawn by the chairperson of the board and approved by the board. At no time shall the total amount of warrants exceed the total amount of fees collected under the act and credited to the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 565, &#167; 11, p. 1863; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 98, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 477, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB396, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1140, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB30, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>