<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id45"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-412"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-412</statuteno><catchline>Workforce retention or workforce attraction plans; grant program; application for grant; contents; award; priority.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Labor shall establish a grant program to provide additional support for the implementation of workforce retention or workforce attraction plans. Grants shall be made available to economic development organizations that assist employers experiencing a change in ownership and control as defined in subdivision (3) of section 77-6546. The total amount of grant funds awarded pursuant to this subsection shall not exceed three hundred thousand dollars. For purposes of this section, employer has the same meaning as in subdivision (6) of section 77-6546.</para><para>(2) The grants awarded pursuant to subsection (1) of this section must be made within the ten-year period immediately following the change in ownership and control as defined in subdivision (3) of section 77-6546.</para><para>(3) Prior to the award of a grant pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the economic development organization must apply to the department for a grant. Grants will only be awarded to an economic development organization if such economic development organization submits to the department a retention and relocation plan application. Such application shall include:</para><para>(a) The name of the applicant and a contact person for such application;</para><para>(b) Information regarding the applicant's qualification as an economic development organization supporting an employer experiencing a change in ownership and control as defined in subdivision (3) of section 77-6546;</para><para>(c) A narrative description of the employer's retention and relocation plan to retain within the state or relocate to the state employees during the seven years following the change in ownership and control as defined in subdivision (3) of section 77-6546;</para><para>(d) The amount of funding requested subject to the limitations of this section; and</para><para>(e) Any other information the department may require.</para><para>(4) If the funds available for grants in any year are insufficient to provide grants to all eligible applicants, the department shall prioritize awards to the retention and relocation plan of the employer with the largest average number of employees within Nebraska during the ten years prior to the employer's change in ownership and control as defined in subdivision (3) of section 77-6546.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1165, &#167; 28. </para><operativedate>April 17, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>