<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,147.09"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,147.09</statuteno><catchline>Violations; penalty; hearing; enforcement.</catchline><para>Any person violating the Nebraska Seed Law shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>It shall be the duty of the county attorney of the county in which any violation has occurred, is occurring, or is about to occur or the Attorney General when notified by the Department of Agriculture of a violation or a threatened violation to institute appropriate proceedings, either criminal or injunctive, or both, without delay. Before the director reports a violation, an opportunity shall be given to the person against whom proceedings will be brought to present such person's views to the director at a hearing held pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>If after such hearing or without such hearing, in case the defendant or his or her agent or attorney fails or refuses to appear, the director is of the opinion that the evidence warrants prosecution, he or she shall proceed as provided in this section. The county attorney or the Attorney General, as the case may be, shall institute proceedings at once against any person charged with a violation of the Nebraska Seed Law, if in the judgment of the director the information submitted warrants such action.</para><para>After judgment by the court in any case arising under such law, the director shall publish any information pertinent to the issuance of the judgment by the court in such media as he or she may designate from time to time.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 759, &#167; 10, p. 2874; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 280; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 460, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 37, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>