<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id487">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id489" statutenumber="81-505.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-505.01</statuteno><catchline id="id492">State Fire
Marshal; establish and assess fees; procedures.</catchline><para>(1)
The State Fire Marshal shall establish and assess fees not to exceed the actual
costs for the performance of services by the State Fire Marshal or by qualified
local fire prevention personnel to whom the State Fire Marshal has delegated
authority to perform such services. Prior to establishing or altering such
fees, the State Fire Marshal shall hold a public hearing on the question of
the adoption of or change in fees. Notice of such hearing shall be given at
least thirty days prior thereto (a) by publication in a newspaper having general
circulation in the state and (b) by notifying in writing the head of any agency
or department having jurisdiction over facilities that would be subject to
the fees. Fees for services performed by the State Fire Marshal shall be paid
to the State Fire Marshal and shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for
credit to the State Fire Marshal Cash Fund. Fees for services performed by
local fire prevention personnel shall be paid directly to the office of the
local fire prevention personnel.</para>
<para>(2) The fee for inspection for fire safety of any premises
or facility pursuant to section 81-502 shall be not less than twenty-five
nor more than one hundred fifty dollars and shall be paid by the licensee
or applicant for a license. The fee for inspection for fire safety of the
same premises or facility made within twelve months after the last prior inspection
shall be not less than twenty-five nor more than one hundred fifty dollars
and shall be paid by the licensee or applicant for a license. The fees for
inspection for fire safety of foster family homes as defined in section 71-1901 may be paid by the Department of Health
and Human Services.</para>
<para>(3) The fee for providing investigation reports to insurance
companies shall not exceed three dollars for each report provided. The State
Fire Marshal may charge an amount not to exceed the actual cost of preparation
for any other approved information release.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection,
the fee for reviewing plans, blueprints, and shop drawings to determine compliance
with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 81-502
shall be assessed according to the following schedule:</para>
<para>
<table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="2">
<?PubTbl tgroup rth="0.00pt" clmarg="0.00pt" crmarg="0.00pt" ctmarg="0.00pt" cbmarg="2.10pt"?>
<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.04*"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">TOTAL VALUE OF PROPOSED</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">STRUCTURE OR IMPROVEMENT</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">FEE</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$1 - $5,000</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$5.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$5,001 - $25,000</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$5.00 for the first $5,000.00 plus</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$2.00 for each additional $5,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">or fraction thereof.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$25,001 - $50,000</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$15.00 for the first $25,000.00 plus</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$2.00 for each additional $5,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">or fraction thereof.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$50,001 - $100,000</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$25.00 for the first $50,000.00 plus</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$1.00 for each additional $5,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">or fraction thereof.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$100,001 - $200,000</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$35.00 for the first $100,000.00 plus</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$1.00 for each additional $10,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">or fraction thereof.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$200,001 or more</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$50.00 for the first $200,000.00 plus</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">$1.00 for each additional $10,000.00</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">or fraction thereof, except that the</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" />
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">total fee shall not exceed $500.00.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></para>
<para>(b) The fees set out in subdivision (a) of this subsection shall not
be assessed or collected by any political subdivision to which the State Fire
Marshal has delegated the authority to conduct such review and which reviews
plans, blueprints, or shop drawings to determine compliance with such political
subdivision's own fire safety regulations. Nothing in this subdivision shall
be construed to prohibit such political subdivision from assessing or collecting
a fee set by its governing board for such review.</para>
<para>(c) An additional fee equal to fifty percent of the fee charged pursuant
to subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be assessed for reviewing plans,
blueprints, and shop drawings to determine compliance with the accessibility
standards and specifications adopted pursuant to section 81-5,147, except
that the additional fee assessed pursuant to this subdivision shall not exceed
two hundred fifty dollars.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 498, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 471, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 893, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 930, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 251, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 377, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 839; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 216; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 48.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>