<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-5,144"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-5,144</statuteno><catchline>Smoke detector; rental property; responsibility for installing, maintaining, and testing; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, the owner of every apartment house, dwelling, hotel, lodging house, dormitory, or mobile home or the owner's authorized agent shall be responsible for supplying, installing, maintaining, and testing the smoke detectors.</para><para>(2) In the case of a dwelling unit, guest room, hotel room, or mobile home which is being occupied for one month or more by the same occupant, it shall be the responsibility of such occupant to perform the tests on the smoke detector as are recommended by the manufacturer's instructions and immediately notify, in writing, the owner or authorized agent of any deficiencies. The owner of the dwelling, apartment house, lodging house, hotel, or mobile home shall provide a notice to such occupant containing instructions for the testing of the device. For purposes of this subsection, deficiencies shall not include a worn battery or other replaceable energy unit. The occupant shall be responsible for replacement of the battery or unit, except that such battery or unit shall be in operating condition at the time the occupant takes possession. The owner or authorized agent shall correct any reported deficiencies in the smoke detector and shall not be in violation of sections 81-5,132 to 81-5,146 for a deficient smoke detector when he or she has not received notice of the deficiency.</para><para>(3) This section shall apply solely to rental property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 296, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc>