<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id654" statutenumber="81-8,110.07"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-8,110.07</statuteno><catchline id="id657">Examining board; secretary; duties; Land Surveyor Examiner's Fund; created; purpose; investment.</catchline><para>The secretary of the examining board shall receive and account for all money derived from the operation of the Land Surveyors Regulation Act and shall remit it to the State Treasurer for credit to the Land Surveyor Examiner's Fund, which fund is hereby created. This fund shall be continued from year to year. When appropriated by the Legislature, this fund shall be expended only for the purposes of the Land Surveyors Regulation Act. When not reappropriated for the succeeding biennium, the money in this fund shall not revert to the General Fund. The fund shall be paid out only upon vouchers approved by the examining board and upon warrants issued by the Director of Administrative Services and countersigned by the State Treasurer. The expenditures of the examining board shall be kept within the income collected and remitted to the State Treasurer by the examining board. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Land Surveyor Examiner's Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 442, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 874, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 110; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB138, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>