<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-829.33"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-829.33</statuteno><catchline>Governor's Emergency Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Governor's Emergency Cash Fund is created. The fund shall consist of federal reimbursements received by the state for eligible state administrative costs incurred by the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency for administering federal emergency disaster declarations and revenue from all other nonfederal government sources. Except as provided in section 90-270, the fund shall be used to pay eligible costs related to state emergency disaster declarations. The fund shall be administered by the State Administrator of the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>Transfers may be made from the Governor's Emergency Cash Fund to the Cash Reserve Fund and General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer zero dollars from the Governor's Emergency Cash Fund to the Cash Reserve Fund by June 30, 2023, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 403, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1009, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 13. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>