<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,271"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,271</statuteno><catchline>Food establishment, food processing plant, or salvage operation; permit; posting; food delivery service; location; change of ownership or location; duties; movement authorized; mobile food unit or pushcart; copy of permit.</catchline><para>(1) The permit required by section 81-2,270 shall be posted in a location in the food establishment, food processing plant, or salvage operation which is conspicuous to the public. A salvage operation shall also have a copy of the permit in each vehicle. For a food delivery service, the location shall be a permanent address where the permitholder may be contacted.</para><para>(2) The permit is not transferable to any other person or location. Any permit issued lapses automatically upon a change of ownership or location except as provided in subsection (3) of this section. The permitholder shall notify the department in writing at least thirty days prior to any change in ownership, name, or address. The permitholder shall notify the department in writing before there is a change of the name or address of the person authorized to receive the notices and orders of the department. When an establishment is to be permanently closed, the permitholder shall return the permit to the department within one week after the closing.</para><para>(3) A mobile food unit, pushcart, or vending machine may be moved if the permitholder is able to provide the location of such unit, pushcart, or machine to the regulatory authority upon request and the person authorized by the permitholder to receive notices and orders of the department maintains a permanent mailing address on file with the department. A food delivery service shall upon request provide the department with information regarding the location of all conveyances it controls.</para><para>(4) Every mobile food unit or pushcart operator shall have a copy of their permit to operate available at the mobile food unit or pushcart when in operation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 358, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 199, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB771, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB134, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>