
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,162.02" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,162.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Commercial Fertilizer and Soil Conditioner Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Director means the Director of Agriculture or his or her duly authorized agent;</para><para>(2) Department means the Department of Agriculture;</para><para>(3) Commercial fertilizer means any formula or product distributed for further distribution or ultimate use as a plant nutrient, intended to promote plant growth, containing one or more plant nutrients recognized by the Association of American Plant Food Control Officials in its official publication. The term commercial fertilizer shall not be deemed to include unmanipulated animal and vegetable manures but shall be deemed to include both finished products and fertilizer ingredients capable of being used in the formulation of a finished product;</para><para>(4) Bulk means nonpackaged;</para><para>(5) Custom-blended product means any individually compounded commercial fertilizer or soil conditioner mixed, blended, offered for sale, or sold in Nebraska to a person's specifications, when such person is the ultimate consumer, if the ingredients used in such product which are subject to the registration requirements of section 81-2,162.03 have been so registered;</para><para>(6) Distribute means to offer for sale, sell, barter, or otherwise supply commercial fertilizers or soil conditioners;</para><para>(7) Fineness means the percentage of weight of the material which will pass United States standard sieves of specified sizes;</para><para>(8) Grade means the percentage of total nitrogen, available phosphate, and soluble potash;</para><para>(9) Label means a display of written, printed, or other graphic matter upon the container in which a commercial fertilizer or soil conditioner is distributed, or a statement accompanying such product;</para><para>(10) Labeling means the label and all other written, printed, or graphic matter accompanying the commercial fertilizer or soil conditioner at any time or to which reference is made on the label;</para><para>(11) Official sample means any sample of commercial fertilizer or soil conditioner taken by the director or his or her agent;</para><para>(12) Product means both commercial fertilizers and soil conditioners;</para><para>(13) Ton means a net weight of two thousand pounds avoirdupois;</para><para>(14) Percent or percentage means the percentage by weight;</para><para>(15) Person includes individual, cooperative, partnership, limited liability company, association, firm, and corporation;</para><para>(16) Sell or sale includes exchange;</para><para>(17) Soil conditioner means any formula or product distributed, except unmanipulated animal and vegetable manures, which, when added to the soil, is intended to (a) change the physical condition of the soil or (b) produce a favorable growth, yield, or quality of crops or other soil characteristics but shall not mean a commercial fertilizer, a pesticide as defined in the Pesticide Act, or an agricultural liming material as defined in the Agricultural Liming Materials Act; and</para><para>(18) Specialty product means a product for nonfarm use.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 334, &#167; 2, p. 1037; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 429, &#167; 1, p. 1434; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 333, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 91, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 692, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 889, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 366, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 525; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB93, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Agricultural Liming Materials Act,</emphasis> see section 2-4301.</para><para><emphasis>Pesticide Act,</emphasis> see section 2-2622.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>"Product" under sections 81-2,162.01 to 81-2,162.07, R.R.S.1943, means the product which is sold in the normal course of business to the ultimate consumer, and consists of the finished product. "Manufacture" means manufacture of the finished product. "Distributes" means distribution of the finished product, and not a mere ingredient. PPG Industries Canada LTD v. Kreuscher, 204 Neb. 220, 281 N.W.2d 762 (1979).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>