<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2,147.10"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2,147.10</statuteno><catchline>Sale of labeled seeds; permit required; fees; renewal; exceptions; refusal or cancellation of permit; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) No person who labels for sale in Nebraska agricultural, vegetable, or flower seeds shall sell such seeds in Nebraska unless he or she holds a valid seed permit. Application for the permit shall be made to the Department of Agriculture on forms prescribed and furnished by the department. If the applicant is an individual, the application for a permit shall include the applicant's social security number. Application forms shall be submitted to the department accompanied by an annual registration fee based on the number of pounds of agricultural, vegetable, or flower seed the applicant labeled and sold during the preceding calendar year. Registrations shall be renewed on or before January 1 of each year. If a person fails to renew the registration by January 31 of each year, such person shall also be required to pay a delinquency fee of twenty percent per month of the amount of the fee due, not to exceed one hundred percent of the annual registration fee.</para><para>The annual registration fee shall be: </para><para><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.85*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.15*"/><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Fee:</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Applicant sold:</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Twenty-five dollars</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Less than ten thousand pounds of</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">agricultural seed (other than</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">lawn and turf seed);</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Fifty dollars</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Ten thousand or more pounds of</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">agricultural seed (other than lawn</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">and turf seed) and less than two</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">hundred fifty thousand pounds of</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">any kind of seed;</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">One hundred dollars</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Two hundred fifty thousand or </entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">more pounds and less than a five</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">hundred thousand pounds of seeds;</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Two hundred fifty dollars</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Five hundred thousand or more</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">pounds and less than one</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">million pounds of seeds;</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Three hundred fifty dollars</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">One million or more pounds</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">and less than five million</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">pounds of seeds;</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Seven hundred fifty dollars</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Five million or more pounds of seeds.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para><para>(2) Subsection (1) of this section shall not apply if the agricultural, vegetable, or flower seeds being labeled and sold are of the breeder or foundation seed classes of varieties developed by publicly financed research agencies intended for the purpose of increasing the quantity of seed available.</para><para>(3) The director shall refuse to issue a permit when the application for such permit is not in compliance with the Nebraska Seed Law or any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to such law and may cancel any permit when it is subsequently found to be in violation of any provision of such law, rule, or regulation or when the director has satisfactory evidence that the person has used fraudulent or deceptive practices in an attempted evasion of the law, rule, or regulation, except that no permit shall be refused or canceled until the person shall have been given an opportunity to be heard before the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 460, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 37, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 263, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 217. </para></source></law></legaldoc>