<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id35" statutenumber="81-188.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-188.01</statuteno><catchline id="id38">State Building
Renewal Assessment Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1)
The State Building Renewal Assessment Fund is created. The fund shall be under
the control of the Governor for allocation to building renewal projects of
the various agencies and shall be administered in a manner consistent with
the administration of the Building Renewal Allocation Fund pursuant to the
Deferred Building Renewal Act. No amounts accruing to the State Building Renewal
Assessment Fund shall be expended in any manner for purposes other than as
provided in this section or as appropriated by the Legislature to meet the
cost of administering the act. Transfers may be made from the fund to the
General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(2) Revenue credited to the State Building Renewal Assessment
Fund shall include amounts derived from charges assessed pursuant to subdivision
(4)(b) of section 81-1108.17 and
such other revenue as may be incident to the administration of the fund.</para>
<para>(3) Amounts appropriated from the fund shall be expended to
conduct renewal work as defined in section 81-173 and to complete other improvements
incident to such renewal work as deemed necessary or appropriate by the task
force. From amounts accruing to the fund as the result of depreciation charges
assessed pursuant to subdivision (4)(b) of section 81-1108.17, expenditures
for capital improvements shall be limited to improvements to only those facilities
for which such charges have been assessed and remitted. From amounts accruing
to the fund as the result of depreciation charges assessed pursuant to section
81-188.02 prior to July 1,
2011, expenditures for capital improvement projects shall be limited
to exclude (a) capital improvement projects relating to facilities, structures,
or buildings owned, leased, or operated by the (i) University of Nebraska,
(ii) Nebraska state colleges, (iii) Department of Aeronautics, (iv) Department
of Roads, (v) Game and Parks Commission, or (vi) Board of Educational Lands
and Funds and (b) capital improvement projects relating to facilities, structures,
or buildings for which depreciation charges are assessed pursuant to subdivision
(4)(b) of section 81-1108.17.</para>
<para>(4) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be
invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source> <para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 8; </para> <para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 22; </para> <para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 13; </para> <para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 6; </para> <para>Laws 2003, LB 410, &#167; 4; </para> <para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 15; </para> <para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB380, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference> <para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para> <para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>