<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,124.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,124.01</statuteno><catchline>Environmental Quality Council; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The Environmental Quality Council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations consistent with principles of risk-based corrective action governing all phases of remedial action to be taken by owners, operators, and other persons in response to a release or suspected release of a regulated substance from a tank. Such rules and regulations shall include:</para><para>(a) Provisions governing remedial action to be taken by owners and operators pursuant to section 81-15,124;</para><para>(b) Provisions by which the Department of Environment and Energy may determine the cleanup levels to be achieved through soil or water remediation and the applicable limitations for air emissions at the petroleum release site or occurring by reason of such remediation; and</para><para>(c) Such other provisions necessary to carry out the Petroleum Products and Hazardous Substances Storage and Handling Act.</para><para>(2) In developing rules and regulations, the Environmental Quality Council shall take into account risk-based corrective action assessment principles which identify the risks presented to the public health and safety or the environment by each release in a manner that will protect the public health and safety and the environment using, to the extent appropriate, a tiered approach consistent with the American Society for Testing of Materials guidance for risk-based corrective action applicable to petroleum release sites.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 289, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB154, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 120. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>