<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id501"><amendatorysection statutenumber="81-15,325" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,325</statuteno><catchline>Covered battery; disposal; requirements; solid waste facility; solid waste collector; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2028, all of the following shall apply:</para><para>(a) A person may dispose of a covered battery only by delivery to a collection site or collection event operated under a battery stewardship plan approved under section 81-15,317, unless the battery is regulated as hazardous waste;</para><para>(b) No person may knowingly cause or allow the mixing of a covered battery with recyclable materials that are intended for processing and sorting at a material recovery facility;</para><para>(c) No person may knowingly cause or allow the mixing of a covered battery with municipal waste that is intended for disposal at a landfill;</para><para>(d) No person may knowingly cause or allow the disposal of a covered battery in a landfill;</para><para>(e) No person may knowingly cause or allow the mixing of a covered battery with waste that is intended for burning or incineration; and</para><para>(f) No person may knowingly cause or allow the burning or incineration of a covered battery.</para><para>(2) An owner or operator of a solid waste facility may not be found in violation of this section if the facility has posted in a conspicuous location a sign stating that covered batteries shall be managed through collection sites established by a battery stewardship organization and are not accepted for disposal.</para><para>(3) A solid waste collector may not be found in violation of this section for a covered battery placed in a disposal container by a third party.</para><para>(4) Unless the department is notified of the reason, a battery stewardship organization shall not refuse to accept covered batteries that are inadvertently received by a recycling or solid waste facility if the batteries are properly packaged.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB36, &#167; 12. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>