<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1508"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1508</statuteno><catchline>Violations of Environmental Protection Act, Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, or Livestock Waste Management Act; civil penalties; injunctions.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who violates any of the provisions of the Environmental Protection Act, the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, or the Livestock Waste Management Act, fails to perform any duty imposed by either act or any rule or regulation issued thereunder, or violates any order or determination of the director promulgated pursuant to either act and causes the death of fish or other wildlife shall, in addition to the penalties provided in sections 81-1508.01 and 81-1508.02, be liable to pay to the state an additional amount equal to the sum of money reasonably necessary to restock waters with fish or replenish such wildlife as determined by the director after consultation with the Game and Parks Commission. Such amount may be recovered by the director on behalf of the state in a civil action brought in the district court of the county in which such violation or failure to perform the duty imposed occurred.</para><para>(2) Except as provided for in subsection (3) of this section for the handling, storage, treatment, transportation, or disposal of solid or hazardous waste, in addition to the penalties provided by this section and sections 81-1508.01 and 81-1508.02, the director, whenever he or she has reason to believe that any person, firm, or corporation is violating or threatening to violate any provision of the acts, any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated thereunder, or any order of the director, may petition the district court for an injunction. It shall be the duty of each county attorney or the Attorney General to whom the director reports a violation to cause appropriate proceedings to be instituted without delay to assure compliance with the acts.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of evidence that the past or present handling, storage, treatment, transportation, or disposal of any solid waste or hazardous waste may present an imminent and substantial endangerment to the health of humans or animals or to the environment, the director may petition the district court for an injunction to immediately restrain any person who has contributed or who is contributing to the alleged acts, to stop such handling, storage, treatment, transportation, or disposal, and to take such other action as may be necessary. It shall be the duty of each county attorney or the Attorney General to whom the director reports a violation to cause appropriate proceedings to be instituted without delay to assure compliance with the Environmental Protection Act, the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, and the Livestock Waste Management Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 939, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1435, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 538, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 342, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 216, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 356, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1078, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 565, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 413, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 570, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1209, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1102, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Livestock Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2416.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A showing of pollution is not a requisite to recovery of a civil penalty under subsection (1)(c) of this section. In an action for civil penalties under subsection (1)(c) of this section, the size of the operation must be considered in determining the amount, if any, of a penalty. State ex rel. Grams v. Beach, 243 Neb. 126, 498 N.W.2d 83 (1993).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>