<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1382"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1382</statuteno><catchline>Unresolved issues; final offers; prehearing conference; Special Master; authority.</catchline><para>(1) No later than January 10, the parties in labor contract negotiations shall reduce to writing and sign all agreed-upon issues and exchange final offers on each unresolved issue. Final offers may not be amended or modified without the concurrence of the other party.</para><para>(2) No later than January 15, the parties in labor contract negotiations shall submit all unresolved issues that resulted in impasse to the Special Master. The Special Master shall conduct a prehearing conference. He or she shall have the authority to:</para><para>(a) Determine whether the issues are ready for adjudication;</para><para>(b) Accept stipulations;</para><para>(c) Schedule hearings;</para><para>(d) Prescribe rules of conduct for the hearings;</para><para>(e) Order additional mediation if necessary; and</para><para>(f) Take any other actions which may aid in the disposal of the action.</para><para>The Special Master may consult with the parties ex parte only with the concurrence of both parties.</para><para>(3) The Special Master shall choose the most reasonable final offer on each issue in dispute. In making such choice, he or she shall consider factors relevant to collective bargaining between public employers and public employees, including comparable rates of pay and conditions of employment as described in section 48-818. The Special Master shall not apply strict rules of evidence. Persons who are not attorneys may present cases to the Special Master. The Special Master shall issue his or her ruling on or before February 15.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 661, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc>