<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1203"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1203</statuteno><catchline>Job training grant; business plan;
project criteria; training
grant; partners;
training grants for rural areas or high-poverty areas; audit; report.</catchline><para>(1) A business applying for a job training grant, other than a grant provided under subsection (3) of section
81-1201.21, shall submit a business plan to the Department of
Economic Development which includes, but is not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The number of jobs to be created or the number of existing positions
that will be retrained;</para>
<para>(b) The nature of the business and the type of jobs to be created or
positions to be retrained;</para>
<para>(c) The estimated wage levels of the jobs to be created or positions
to be retrained; and</para>
<para>(d) A program schedule for the job training project.</para>
<para>(2) A business applying for a job training grant, other than a grant provided under subsection (3) of section
81-1201.21, must demonstrate that the job training project to
be conducted pursuant to the grant meets the following criteria:</para>
<para>(a) The wage level of the jobs created will meet the local prevailing
average;</para>
<para>(b) The jobs created will diversify the local economy;</para>
<para>(c) The goods or services produced by the company will be export-oriented;</para>
<para>(d) Seventy-five percent of the jobs created will be full-time jobs;
and</para>
<para>(e) The new jobs will be created within three calendar years.</para>
<para>(3) A business applying for a training
grant under subsection (3)
of section 81-1201.21 may partner with a postsecondary educational institution; a private, nonprofit
organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) of
the Internal Revenue Code; or a learning community coordinating
council or school district that
has partnered with a private, nonprofit organization. The
application shall specify the role of the partnering entity in
identifying and training potential job applicants for the applicant business.</para>
<para>(4) A business applying
for a training grant under subsection (3) of section 81-1201.21 may apply
as a business that has established a program under which residents of rural
areas or high-poverty areas are trained for employment or potential employment
by documenting:</para><para>(a)
That the business has established a program designed to fill a minimum of
four positions in rural areas and a minimum of eight positions in high-poverty
areas for such business;</para><para>(b)
A program schedule for the training project;</para><para>(c) The nature of the business and
the number of positions available or to be created;</para><para>(d) That the wage level of the positions
available or to be created will meet the local prevailing average;</para>
<para>(e) The value of the
positions available or to be created in diversifying the local economy;</para>
<para>(f) That a minimum of
seventy-five percent of the positions available or to be created will be full-time
jobs;</para><para>(g)
That the business will accept funding on behalf of trainees and will provide
a match of a minimum of twenty-five percent of the value of the grant, either
monetarily or through in-kind services, as part of the training for each trainee;</para>
<para>(h) That any new position
created will be done within three calendar years;</para><para>(i) That the number of trainees
will not exceed one hundred twenty-five percent of the number of positions
that will be available at the time of application; and</para>
<para>(j) That the goods or
services produced by the business are generally exportable in nature resulting
in additional money to the community or the state and the positions available
or to be created are not local retail positions.</para><para>(5) Each business participating
in a training grant under subsection (3) of section 81-1201.21 shall be subject
to an audit by the Department of Economic Development and shall annually report
or provide to the department the following information:</para>
<para>(a) The percentage of
trainees who have successfully completed the training;</para>
<para>(b) The percentage of
trainees that such business hired;</para><para>(c) An itemized description of such business's match
including expenditures per trainee; and</para><para>(d) A copy of the training curriculum.</para>
<para>(6) For purposes of subsections (3) through (5) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) High-poverty
area means an area consisting of one or more contiguous census tracts, as
determined by the most recent federal decennial census, which contain a percentage
of persons with incomes below the poverty line of greater than thirty percent,
and all census tracts contiguous to such tract or tracts, as determined by
the most recent federal decennial census; and </para>
<para>(b) Private, nonprofit organization means an organization
whose purpose is providing basic job and life skills training to individuals
in need of such training  in
rural or high-poverty areas.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 326, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167;  27; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB961, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>