<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,210"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,210</statuteno><catchline>State Administrator; State Emergency Response Commission; created; members; terms.</catchline><para>(1) The director of the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency shall serve as the State Administrator of the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act. The State Emergency Response Commission is created and shall be a part of the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency for administrative purposes. The membership of the commission shall include the Director of Environmental Quality or his or her designee, the Director-State Engineer or his or her designee, the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety or his or her designee, the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee, the director of the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency or his or her designee, the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee, two elected officials or employees of municipal or county government, and one citizen member to represent each of the following interest groups: Firefighters, local emergency management, public or community health, environmental protection, labor, school district, small business, agricultural business, chemical industry, highway transportation, and rail transportation. The Governor shall appoint the municipal or county government officials or employees and the citizen members with the approval of the Legislature. The appointments shall be made to represent the three congressional districts as equally as possible.</para><para>(2) The members appointed by the Governor shall be appointed for terms of four years, except that of the first citizen members appointed, three members shall serve for one-year terms, three members shall serve for two-year terms, and two members shall serve for three-year terms, as designated at the time of appointment.</para><para>(3) A vacancy on the commission shall exist in the event of the death, disability, or resignation of a member. Any member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of the term for which his or her predecessor was appointed shall be appointed by the Governor for the remainder of such term.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 760.</para></source></law></legaldoc>