<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1407"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1407</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Police Standards Advisory Council; members; qualifications; terms; appointment; removal; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Police Standards Advisory Council shall consist of seven members appointed by the Governor. Six of the members shall be full-time officers or employees of a law enforcement agency and shall include one representative chief of police or his or her designee from a city of the metropolitan or primary class, a representative chief of police or his or her designee from a city of the first class, a representative chief of police or his or her designee from a city of the second class or village, a county sheriff or his or her designee from a county having a population of forty thousand or more, a county sheriff or his or her designee from a county having a population of forty thousand or less, and a member of the Nebraska State Patrol. The seventh member shall be a member of the Jail Standards Board or a person from the public at large. The representative chief of police or his or her designee from a city of the metropolitan or primary class shall not be a regular member of the commission.</para><para>(2) The members of the council shall serve for terms of four years each. Of the members first appointed, one shall serve for a term of one year, one shall serve for a term of two years, one shall serve for a term of three years, and two shall serve for terms of four years from January 1 next succeeding their appointment. Within ninety days after July 16, 1994, the Governor shall appoint the two additional members who shall serve for terms of four years from January 1 next succeeding their appointment. A member may be reappointed at the expiration of his or her term. Any vacancy occurring otherwise than by expiration of a term shall be filled, for the remainder of the unexpired term, in the same manner as the original appointment. The council shall select one of its members as chairperson.</para><para>(3) No member of the council shall serve beyond the time when he or she holds the office or employment by reason of which he or she was initially eligible for appointment. A member may be removed from the council for cause upon notice and an opportunity to be heard at a public hearing before the Governor. After the hearing, the Governor shall file in the office of the Secretary of State a complete statement of the charges, his or her findings and disposition, together with a complete record of the proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 773, &#167; 7, p. 2927; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 971, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>