<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,217"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,217</statuteno><catchline>Local emergency planning committee; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Each local emergency planning committee shall:</para><para>(a) Establish rules governing the functioning of the committee consistent with the Open Meetings Act and sections 84-712 to 84-712.09. The rules shall include provisions for public notification of committee activities, public meetings to discuss the emergency plan required under subdivision (c) of this subsection, public comments, response to such comments by the committee, and distribution of the emergency plan;</para><para>(b) Establish procedures for receiving and processing requests from the public for information required to be provided under the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act. The procedures shall include provisions to inform members of the public of the right to bring an action under federal law to enforce the act. The procedures shall include the designation of an official to serve as coordinator for information;</para><para>(c) Complete preparation of an emergency plan in accordance with the act not later than January 1, 1998, unless a plan for the emergency planning district has previously been submitted and approved by the commission. The committee shall review and update the plan once a year beginning March 1, 1999, and each March 1 thereafter, or more frequently as changed circumstances in the community or at any facility may require;</para><para>(d) Evaluate the need for resources necessary to develop, implement, and exercise the emergency plan and make recommendations with respect to additional resources that may be required and the means for providing such additional resources; and</para><para>(e) Designate a public library in each county within its district as a depository for the emergency plan, deliver the plan to the designated library, and update the plan as necessary.</para><para>(2) Each local emergency planning committee may receive gifts, bequests, grants, or other contributions or donations from public or private sources to carry out its duties and the purposes of the act, including, but not limited to, administrative costs and reimbursement to committee members for their actual and necessary travel expenses. Any gifts, bequests, grants, or other contributions or donations received from public or private sources shall be accounted for in an annual report to the commission. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the receipt and use of any gifts, bequests, grants, or other contributions or donations from public or private sources.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 32. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>