<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id20" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-12,154"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,154</statuteno><catchline>Purpose of act.</catchline><para>The
purpose of the Business Innovation Act is to encourage and support the transfer
of Nebraska-based technology and innovation in rural and urban areas of Nebraska
in order to create high growth, high technological companies, small businesses,
and microenterprises and to enhance creation of wealth and quality jobs. The
Legislature finds that the act will:</para>
<para>(1) Provide technical assistance planning grants pursuant to section
81-12,157 to facilitate phase one applications for the federal grant program;</para>
<para>(2) Provide financial assistance pursuant to section 81-12,157 to companies
receiving phase one and phase two grants pursuant to the federal grant program;</para>
<para>(3) Provide financial assistance pursuant to section 81-12,158 to companies
or individuals creating prototypes;</para>
<para>(4) Establish a financial assistance program pursuant to section 81-12,159
for innovation in value-added agriculture;</para>
<para>(5) Establish a financial assistance program pursuant to section 81-12,160
to identify commercial products and processes;</para>
<para>(6) Provide financial assistance pursuant to section 81-12,161 to companies
using Nebraska public or private college and university researchers and facilities
for applied research projects;</para>
<para>(7) Provide support and funding pursuant to section 81-12,162 for microlending
and microenterprise entities;
and</para>
<para>(8) Provide support for
locally owned and operated Nebraska-based, high growth businesses by providing
technical resources to foster development, growth, and high wage creation.
For purposes of this subdivision, Nebraska-based, high growth business means
a corporation, partnership, limited liability company, limited partnership,
or limited liability partnership registered with the Secretary of State that
has two to fifty employees and has annual sales of no less than five hundred
thousand dollars and no more than two million five hundred thousand dollars.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB387, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1114, &#167; 2.</para><terminationdate>December 1, 2021</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>