<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id663"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,241"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,241</statuteno><catchline>Economic Recovery and Incentives Division; grants; develop coordinated plan; Qualified Census Tract Recovery Grant Program; other grant funding; purposes; preparing land parcels; permitted activities; compliance with federal law.</catchline><para>(1) A primary responsibility of the Economic Recovery and Incentives Division of the Department of Economic Development shall be to utilize federal or state funding to award grants as provided in this section. The division shall develop a coordinated plan and a grant application and scoring process to award grants under subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) The coordinated plan developed pursuant to this section shall direct and prioritize the use of grants toward the economic recovery of those communities and neighborhoods within qualified census tracts located within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan class that were disproportionately impacted by the COVID-19 public health emergency and related challenges, with an emphasis on housing needs, assistance for small businesses, job training, and business development within such communities and neighborhoods. In prioritizing the use of grants, the Economic Recovery and Incentives Division may rely on any studies produced pursuant to section 81-12,242. Not later than August 1, 2022, the division shall submit a copy of an initial coordinated plan to the Economic Recovery Special Committee of the Legislature. Not later than December 1, 2022, the division shall submit a final copy of such coordinated plan to the Economic Recovery Special Committee of the Legislature.</para><para>(3)(a) The Economic Recovery and Incentives Division shall create a Qualified Census Tract Recovery Grant Program to provide funding to public and private entities located within qualified census tracts throughout the state to respond to the negative impact of the COVID-19 public health emergency.</para><para>(b) Not to exceed ten million dollars in grants shall be distributed under the grant program to eligible grantees in qualified census tracts that are located in a city of the primary class.</para><para>(c) Not to exceed ten million dollars in grants shall be distributed under the grant program to eligible grantees in qualified census tracts that are located outside of a city of the metropolitan class or a city of the primary class.</para><para>(d) All remaining funds shall be allocated for grants distributed under the grant program to eligible grantees in qualified census tracts that are located in a city of the metropolitan class, with no less than thirty-five million dollars in such grants allocated to eligible grantees which are located south of Dodge Street and east of 72nd Street in such city and no less than fifty-five million dollars in such grants allocated to eligible grantees which are located north of Dodge Street and east of 72nd Street in such city. Any funds not applied for within such areas may be allocated for grants to eligible grantees in any qualified census tract in such city.</para><para>(4) In addition to grants under the Qualified Census Tract Recovery Grant Program, the Economic Recovery and Incentives Division shall provide grant funding for the following purposes:</para><para>(a) Not to exceed sixty million dollars in grants to a nonprofit economic development organization for the development of a business park located within or adjacent to one or more qualified census tracts located within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan class and within two miles of a major airport as defined in section 13-3303;</para><para>(b) Not to exceed thirty million dollars in grants to one or more innovation hubs located in one or more qualified census tracts and within two miles of a major airport as defined in section 13-3303 providing services and resources within qualified census tracts located within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan class;</para><para>(c) Not to exceed three million dollars in grants in fiscal year 2022-23 and not to exceed three million dollars in fiscal year 2023-24 to a nonprofit organization partnering with a city of the metropolitan class for the purpose of providing internships and crime prevention within qualified census tracts located within the boundaries of such city;</para><para>(d) Not to exceed five million dollars in grants pursuant to the purposes of the Nebraska Film Office Fund on or before June 30, 2023, for the purpose of producing a film on Chief Standing Bear, a portion of which is to be filmed in one or more qualified census tracts located within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan class;</para><para>(e) Not to exceed twenty million dollars in grants to public or private entities to prepare land parcels for affordable housing or conduct other eligible affordable housing interventions under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 including production, rehabilitation, and preservation of affordable rental housing and affordable homeownership units within qualified census tracts which are located in a city of the metropolitan class;</para><para>(f) Not to exceed twenty million dollars in grants to public or private entities to prepare land parcels for affordable housing or conduct other eligible affordable housing interventions under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 including production, rehabilitation, and preservation of affordable rental housing and affordable homeownership units within qualified census tracts which are located in a city of the primary class;</para><para>(g) Not to exceed five million dollars in grants to a county agricultural society with facilities within a city of the primary class to recoup lost revenue; and</para><para>(h) Not to exceed one million dollars in grants to a postsecondary institution located in a qualified census tract in a city of the metropolitan class to provide funding for a financial literacy program to improve economic and health outcomes for individuals residing in qualified census tracts.</para><para>(5) For purposes of subdivisions (4)(e) and (f) of this section, preparing land parcels shall include:</para><para>(a) Laying drinking water mains, lines, pipes, or channels;</para><para>(b) Rehabilitation, renovation, maintenance, or other costs to secure vacant or abandoned properties in disproportionately impacted communities;</para><para>(c) Acquiring and securing legal title of vacant or abandoned properties in disproportionately impacted communities;</para><para>(d) Removal and remediation of environmental contaminants or hazards from vacant or abandoned properties in disproportionately impacted communities when conducted in compliance with applicable environmental laws or regulations;</para><para>(e) Demolition or deconstruction of vacant or abandoned buildings in disproportionately impacted communities; and</para><para>(f) Costs associated with inspection fees and other administrative costs incurred to ensure compliance with applicable environmental laws and regulations for demolition or other remediation activities in disproportionately impacted communities.</para><para>(6) All grants made by the Economic Recovery and Incentives Division utilizing federal funds allocated to the State of Nebraska from the federal Coronavirus State Fiscal Recovery Fund under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 shall meet the eligible uses under such act and any relevant guidance on the use of such funds by the United States Department of the Treasury.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1024, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>