<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id470"><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id472" statutenumber="81-1845"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1845</statuteno><catchline id="id475">Victim and
witness assistance center; selection and establishment; Nebraska Commission
on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice; duties; funding.</catchline><para>(1) Any public or private nonprofit agency may apply to the Nebraska
Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice for selection and funding
as a victim and witness assistance center pursuant to sections 81-1843 to
81-1851.</para>
<para>(2) The commission shall consider the following factors,
together with any other factors it deems appropriate, in selecting applicants
to receive funds and be designated as a victim and witness assistance center:</para>
<para>(a) The number of volunteers that the proposed center will
utilize;</para>
<para>(b) The stated goals of the applicant;</para>
<para>(c) The potential number of people that may be served by
the proposed center and the needs of the community for such a center;</para>
<para>(d) Evidence of community support for the establishment of
the proposed center; and</para>
<para>(e) The organizational structure of the agency which will
operate the proposed center and provide services to victims and witnesses
of crimes.</para>
<para>(3) Upon evaluation of all applicants, the Nebraska Commission
on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice shall select a number of public or
private nonprofit agencies which the commission deems qualified for designation
to receive funding for the establishment and operation of such centers.</para>
<para>(4) The commission shall, upon the establishment of such
centers, conduct appraisals of their performance to determine which of the
centers shall receive continuation grants.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 477, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 270, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 38.</para><effectivedate>May 8, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>