<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments"  statutenumber="81-1213.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1213.01</statuteno><catchline>High Growth Business Development
Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The High Growth Business Development Cash Fund is created.
The fund shall be administered by the Department of Economic Development to
fund a study related to high growth business development. The fund shall consist
of money appropriated or transferred by the Legislature and gifts, grants,
or bequests from any source, including money remitted to the fund from any
other federal, state, public, and private sources. Any money in the fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
<para>(2) It is the intent
of the Legislature that fifty thousand dollars of General Funds be appropriated
to the High Growth Business Development Cash Fund for the department to contract
with the private, nonprofit organization selected pursuant to subsection (3)
of section 81-12,133 to provide research, analysis of best practices in other
states, and make recommendations on ways to support and increase venture capital
in Nebraska. A report of the findings of the research and analysis and recommendations
shall be presented to the Clerk of the Legislature no later than December
1, 2014. The report shall be submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(3) On August 1, 2014,
the State Treasurer shall transfer fifty thousand dollars from the General
Fund to the High Growth Business Development Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB1114, &#167; 4.</para></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>