<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1604</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings; strategic state energy plan; development; advisory committee; contents of plan.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(a) Comprehensive planning enables the state to address its energy needs, challenges, and opportunities and enhances the state's ability to prioritize energy-related policies, activities, and programs; and</para><para>(b) Meeting the state's need for clean, affordable, and reliable energy in the future will require a diverse energy portfolio and a strategic approach, requiring engagement of all energy stakeholders in a comprehensive planning process.</para><para>(2) The Department of Water, Energy, and Environment shall develop an integrated and comprehensive strategic state energy plan and review such plan periodically as the department deems necessary. The department may organize technical committees of individuals with expertise in energy development for purposes of developing the plan. If the department forms an advisory committee pursuant to subdivision (58) of section 81-1504 for purposes of such plan, the chairperson of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature, the chairperson of the Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature, and three members of the Legislature selected by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council shall be nonvoting, ex officio members of such advisory committee.</para><para>(3) The strategic state energy plan shall include short-term and long-term objectives that will ensure a secure, reliable, and resilient energy system for the state's residents and businesses; a cost-competitive energy supply and access to affordable energy; the promotion of sustainable economic growth, job creation, and economic development; and a means for the state's energy policy to adapt to changing circumstances.</para><para>(4) The strategic state energy plan shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) A comprehensive analysis of the state's energy profile, including all energy resources, end-use sectors, and supply and demand projections;</para><para>(b) An analysis of other state energy plans and regional energy activities which identifies opportunities for streamlining and partnerships; and</para><para>(c) An identification of goals and recommendations related to:</para><para>(i) The diversification of the state's energy portfolio in a way that balances the lowest practicable environmental cost with maximum economic benefits;</para><para>(ii) The encouragement of state and local government coordination and public-private partnerships for future economic and investment decisions;</para><para>(iii) The incorporation of new technologies and opportunities for energy diversification that will maximize Nebraska resources and support local economic development;</para><para>(iv) The interstate and intrastate promotion and marketing of the state's renewable energy resources;</para><para>(v) A consistent method of working with and marketing to energy-related businesses and developers;</para><para>(vi) The advancement of transportation technologies, alternative fuels, and infrastructure;</para><para>(vii) The development and enhancement of oil, natural gas, and electricity production and distribution;</para><para>(viii) The development of a communications process between energy utilities and the department for responding to and preparing for regulations having a statewide impact; and</para><para>(ix) The development of a mechanism to measure the plan's progress.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB469, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 154; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 449. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>