<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1201.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1201.04</statuteno><catchline>Commission; members; qualifications;
chairperson; coordination.</catchline><para>(1) The
commission shall consist of nine voting members appointed by the Governor.
The chairperson of the commission shall be one of the appointed members and
shall be chosen by the commission. Each congressional district in Nebraska
shall be represented by three members, and the Governor shall solicit nominations
for appointments to the commission from recognized economic development groups
in Nebraska. The members of the commission shall be representative, to the
extent possible, of the various geographic areas of the state and of both
the urban and rural population. The director shall serve as an ad hoc nonvoting
member of the commission. In appointing the members, the Governor shall seek
to create a broad-based commission representative of the Nebraska economy.
To achieve this objective the Governor shall appoint individuals from the
following private industry sectors:</para>
<para>(a) Production agriculture;</para>
<para>(b) At least two individuals
from manufacturing, one such individual shall represent a company with no
more than seventy-five employees;</para>
<para>(c) Transportation and logistics;</para>
<para>(d) Financial services and
insurance;</para>
<para>(e) Information technology
and communications;</para>
<para>(f) Biotechnology; and</para>
<para>(g) Community development.</para>
<para>(2) The commission
and department are encouraged to involve other essential groups in the work
of the commission, including, but not limited to, the (a) University of Nebraska,
(b) Department of Agriculture, (c) State Energy Office, (d) educational institutions,
(e) Department of Labor, and (f) Nebraska Investment Finance Authority. No
more than five voting members of the commission shall belong to the same political
party.</para>
<para>(3) The commission
shall provide programmatic policy guidance and oversight to the Nebraska Manufacturing
Extension Partnership and shall provide regular consultation to the Community
Development Block Grant Program.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 965, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB388, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB947, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1053, &#167; 26.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>