<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id42" statutenumber="81-1403">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1403</statuteno><catchline id="id45">Council; duties;
administrative fine.</catchline><para>Subject to review and approval
by the commission, the council shall:</para>
<para>(1) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for law enforcement
pre-certification, certification, continuing education, and training requirements.
Such rules and regulations may include the authority to impose a fine on any
individual, political subdivision, or agency who or which violates sections 81-1401 to 81-1414.10 or any
of such rules and regulations. The fine for each separate violation of sections 81-1401 to 81-1414.10 or of
any rule or regulation adopted
and promulgated by the council pursuant to such sections shall
not exceed either (a) a one-time maximum fine of five hundred dollars or (b)
a maximum fine of one hundred dollars per day until the individual, political
subdivision, or agency complies with such rules or regulations. All fines
collected pursuant to this subdivision shall be remitted to the State Treasurer
for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution
of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(2) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the operation
of the training center;</para>
<para>(3) Recommend to the executive director of the commission
the names of persons to be appointed to the position of director of the training
center;</para>
<para>(4) Establish requirements for satisfactory completion of
pre-certification programs, certification programs, and advanced training
programs;</para>
<para>(5) Issue certificates or diplomas attesting satisfactory
completion of pre-certification programs, certification programs, and advanced
training programs;</para>
<para>(6) Revoke or suspend such certificates or diplomas according
to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by
the council pursuant to sections
81-1401 to 81-1414.10 for reasons which shall include, but not
be limited to, (a) incompetence, (b) neglect of duty, (c) physical, mental,
or emotional incapacity, and (d) final conviction of or pleading guilty or
nolo contendere to a felony. The rules and regulations shall provide for revocation
of a certificate
without a hearing upon the certificate
holder's final conviction of or pleading guilty or nolo contendere
to a felony. For purposes of this subdivision, felony means a crime punishable
by imprisonment for a term of more than one year or a crime committed outside
of Nebraska which would be punishable by imprisonment for a term of more than
one year if committed in Nebraska. The rules and regulations shall include
a procedure for hearing appeals of any person who feels that the revocation
or suspension of his or her certificate or diploma was in error;</para>
<para>(7) Set the tuition and fees for the training center and all
officers of other training academies not employed by that training academy's
agency. The tuition and fees set for the training center pursuant to this
subdivision shall be adjusted annually pursuant to the training center budget
approved by the Legislature. All other tuition and fees shall be set in order
to cover the costs of administering sections 81-1401 to 81-1414.10. All
tuition and fees shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the
Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center Cash Fund;</para>
<para>(8) Annually certify any training academies providing a basic
course of law enforcement training which complies with the qualifications
and standards promulgated by the council and offering training that meets
or exceeds training that is offered by the training center. The council shall
set the maximum and minimum applicant enrollment figures for training academies
training non-agency officers;</para>
<para>(9) Extend the programs of the training center throughout
the state on a regional basis;</para>
<para>(10) Establish the qualifications, standards, and continuing education requirements and
provide the training required by section 81-1439; and</para>
<para>(11) Do all things necessary to carry out the purpose of the
training center, except that functional authority for budget and personnel
matters shall remain with the commission.</para>
<para>Any administrative fine imposed under this section shall constitute
a debt to the State of Nebraska which may be collected by lien foreclosure
or sued for and recovered in any proper form of action by the office of the
Attorney General in the name of the State of Nebraska in the district court
of the county where the final agency action was taken. All fines imposed by
the council shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance
with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 773, &#167; 3, p. 2926; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 929, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 673, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 666, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 971, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 994, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 115, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB390, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB817, &#167; 6.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source><annotation><para>A State Patrol trooper cannot continually engage in pattern of assaultive behavior toward his or her spouse and not be in violation of subsection (5) of this section. Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 269 Neb. 541, 694 N.W.2d 171 (2005).</para><para>A State Patrol trooper is not relieved of compliance with subsection (5) simply because he or she is "off duty." Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 269 Neb. 541, 694 N.W.2d 171 (2005).</para><para>Evidence of a State Patrol trooper's neglect of duty is enough to justify the revocation of his or her law enforcement certificate. Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 269 Neb. 541, 694 N.W.2d 171 (2005).</para><para>It is not necessary to prove both neglect of duty and emotional incapacity in order to revoke a law enforcement certificate. Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 269 Neb. 541, 694 N.W.2d 171 (2005).</para><para>The Nebraska State Patrol's code of conduct, code of ethics, and oath of office may be used as guidelines for evaluating and making determinations as to the duties and conduct expected of a State Patrol trooper and in deciding whether a law enforcement certificate should be revoked pursuant to subsection (5) of this section. Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 269 Neb. 541, 694 N.W.2d 171 (2005).</para><para>It is the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice, not the Nebraska Police Standards Advisory Council, which is charged with the promulgation, adoption, and filing with the Secretary of State of rules and regulations. Hauser v. Nebraska Police Stds. Adv. Council, 264 Neb. 605, 650 N.W.2d 760 (2002).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>