<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id47">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id49" statutenumber="81-1120.27"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id51">81-1120.27</statuteno><catchline id="id52">Telecommunications
system; uses; member of Legislature; long-distance calls; how made.</catchline>
<para>(1) The facilities of the state's telecommunications systems
are provided for the conduct of state business. In addition, the state's telecommunications
systems, cellular telephones,
electronic handheld devices, or computers may be used by state
employees and officials for emails,
text messaging, local calls, and
long-distance calls to children at home, teachers, doctors, day care centers, baby-sitters, family members, or others to inform them
of unexpected schedule changes, and for other essential personal business. Any such
use for essential personal business shall be kept to a minimum
and shall not interfere with the conduct of state business. A
state employee or official shall be responsible for payment or reimbursement
of charges, if any, that directly result from any such communication. The
Department of Administrative Services may establish procedures for reimbursement
of charges pursuant to this section.</para>
<para>(2) A member of the Legislature, while engaged in legislative
business, may make personal long-distance calls on the state telecommunications
system or by using his or her state credit card. At the end of every month
upon the member's receipt of his or her long-distance call record, the personal
long-distance calls shall be designated by the member and the member billed
for such calls. Reimbursement to the state for such personal long-distance
calls by the member shall be made within thirty days from the date of designation.</para>
<para>(3) A member of the Legislature, at his or her own sole discretion,
may designate any long-distance call as sensitive or confidential in nature.
If a long-distance call is designated as sensitive or confidential in nature,
any long-distance call record used in an audit shall contain only the date
the long-distance call was made and the cost of the call. In no case shall
the person conducting the audit have access to a long-distance call number
designated as sensitive or confidential in nature by the member without the
written consent of the member. No calls made to or by a member of the Legislature
which are sensitive or confidential in nature shall be required to be disclosed
except that such calls shall be so designated by the member, and only the
amount of the call and such designation shall be made available to a person
conducting an audit.</para>
<para>For purposes of this subsection, sensitive or confidential
in nature shall mean that either the member of the Legislature or the caller
would reasonably expect that the nature or the content of the call would not
be disclosed to another person without the consent of the member and the caller.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 572, &#167; 13, p. 1885; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-1120.13; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 427, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 722, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 579, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB626, &#167;  6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>