<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id130">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id132" statutenumber="81-1439"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1439</statuteno><catchline id="id135">Law enforcement
reserve force; commission; duties; delegation of responsibilities; continuing education requirements; reserve
force manual; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Commission
on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice shall establish minimum physical,
mental, educational, and moral qualifications for all members of any law enforcement
reserve force. The commission shall also establish training and continuing education standards and be responsible
for providing such training for all members. The commission shall delegate
its responsibilities pursuant to this section to the Nebraska Police Standards
Advisory Council.</para>
<para>(2) Individuals appointed to a law enforcement reserve force
shall receive training through or under the supervision of the Nebraska Law
Enforcement Training Center and shall achieve the minimum training standards
within one year after the date of appointment.
Such training may be provided by the training center through regional workshops,
training sessions, or similar means of instruction anywhere in the state.</para>
<para>(3) Members
of the law enforcement reserve force shall be subject to the same continuing
education requirements as all other law enforcement officers pursuant to sections
81-1401 to 81-1414.10.</para><para>(4) The
governing body establishing a law enforcement reserve force shall adopt and
publish a reserve force manual setting forth the minimum qualifications, training
standards, standard
operating procedures, and continuing
education requirements for such force and such higher qualifications,
standards, and operating procedures as may actually be used.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 782, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 971, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB817, &#167; 17.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>