<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,102.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,102.01</statuteno><catchline>Property near facility; loss of value; compensation authorized; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any owner of real property that is within a three-mile radius of the facility on the date a license for such facility is granted who believes that his or her property has declined in value as a result of construction of the facility or his or her heirs or assigns may apply for compensation as provided in this section. Any application for compensation shall be filed within five years of the date the facility first begins accepting low-level radioactive waste. Upon application by a real property owner, the county board of the county in which the facility is located shall hold a hearing to determine whether a loss of real property value has occurred. In reaching a decision, the county board shall consider the value of such property on the date a license is granted to the developer, using appraisals, valuations made by the county assessor of the county, data developed by the Property Tax Administrator, and any other relevant data, including appraisals which the county board may order. If the real property owner establishes by a preponderance of the evidence that his or her property has suffered loss which has not previously been compensated due to the construction of the facility, the developer shall provide compensation to the real property owner for the amount of the loss. Compensation shall be provided by the developer from fees assessed upon generators of low-level radioactive waste at the time such waste is delivered to the facility. Any real property owner aggrieved by a final decision of the county board shall be entitled to an appeal in the same manner as appeals are taken pursuant to section 23-135.</para><para>(2) As used in this section, real property owner shall mean the owner of record in the office of the county register of deeds on the date a license is granted to the developer as provided in section 81-15,101 or his or her heirs or assigns.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1092, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 188. </para></source></law></legaldoc>