<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1108.41"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1108.41</statuteno><catchline>State comprehensive capital facilities
plan; State Comprehensive Capital Facilities Planning Committee; program statement;
appropriation for drawings and construction; contracts; approval; report;
contents.</catchline><para>(1) The division shall cause a state comprehensive
capital facilities plan to be developed. The plan shall project the state's
facilities needs for a period of six years and shall be based on programmatic
projections and input from each state agency. To aid in the development of
the plan, the Governor shall appoint a State Comprehensive Capital Facilities
Planning Committee with representatives from various state agencies. The committee
shall develop and adopt comprehensive planning guidelines and a process of
project prioritization. The state comprehensive capital facilities plan shall
be submitted electronically to
the Committee on Building Maintenance for review before such plan shall be
submitted to the Governor and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst on or before
November 15 prior to the beginning of each biennium. The plan submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall
be submitted electronically. The plan shall be based on priorities
developed by the State Comprehensive Capital Facilities Planning Committee.
The University of Nebraska and any Nebraska state college shall not be required
to comply with or be subject to the provisions of this section since these
agencies are subject to and participate in statewide facilities planning developed
by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education pursuant to the
Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act.</para>
<para>(2) An appropriation for drawings and construction may be made only
after submission of an acceptable program statement on or before September
15 of the year previous to the initiation of such appropriation. Such program
statement shall include, but not be limited to, (a) an assessment of the compatibility
of the project with the state comprehensive capital facilities plan and the
agency or departmental comprehensive capital facilities plan, (b) the identification
of the impact of the project on the space utilization of other facilities
under the control of the agency or department, and (c) the identification
of the future impact on the agency or departmental programmatic needs, demand
for utilities in excess of current capacity, parking needs, street and road
needs, and site acquisition needs. Such program statement shall be submitted
to the division and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The program statement submitted to the Legislative Fiscal
Analyst shall be submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(3) No contract for the planning, design, or construction of a new facility
or major modification or repair of an existing facility provided for by any
state appropriation may be initiated unless an acceptable program statement
has been approved by the Governor, the agency or department has submitted
to the division a certificate from the Committee on Building Maintenance that
there is no state-owned property which is adequate or which through cost-effective
renovation, as determined by the division, could be made adequate to meet
the agency's or department's needs, and the conditions of the contracts are
approved in writing by the division, except that the provisions of this section
shall not apply to projects when the total design and construction cost of
the project is less than the limit established by the division. Such program
statements and contracts shall be reviewed by the division.</para>
<para>(4) The division shall file a written report on each program statement
and contract reviewed with the Governor and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The report submitted to the Legislative
Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically. This report
shall cover the consistency of the project with the state comprehensive capital
facilities plan and the agency or departmental comprehensive capital facilities
plan. A subsequent review and report upon completion of the planning or design
phase of the project shall indicate the compatibility of the project with
the agency or departmental comprehensive capital facilities plan, compare
the probable cost of the project with accepted cost standards for similar
construction projects, and review the relationship of the project to other
state agency or departmental capital facilities in the same complex.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 772, &#167; 4, p. 2923; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 81-1108.06; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1048, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 986, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 38, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1241, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 530, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 184.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Committee on Building Maintenance,</emphasis> see section 81-185.</para><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education,</emphasis> see Article VII, section 14, Constitution of Nebraska and section 85-1403.</para><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>These sections held not applicable to the Board of Regents which cannot delegate its constitutional powers and duties to other officers or agencies. Board of Regents v. Exon, 199 Neb. 146, 256 N.W.2d 330 (1977).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>