<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1579"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1579</statuteno><catchline>Legislative policy.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature hereby declares that it is the policy of the State of Nebraska, in furtherance of its responsibility to cooperate and coordinate with the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact Commission and to protect the health, safety, and welfare of its citizens and the environment:</para><para>(a) To provide for the availability of capacity either within or outside the state for the commercial disposal of low-level radioactive waste generated within the state at commercial low-level radioactive waste disposal facilities as designated by the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact Commission, except for waste generated as a result of defense or federal research and development activities;</para><para>(b) To recognize that low-level radioactive waste can be most safely and efficiently managed on a regional basis; and</para><para>(c) To institute and maintain a regulatory program for commercial disposal of low-level radioactive waste at such facilities.</para><para>(2) It is also the policy of the State of Nebraska that the cost of disposal of low-level radioactive waste be borne by the generators of such waste. In furtherance of such policy, the state shall not be liable for any financial subsidy of the construction and maintenance of a low-level radioactive waste disposal facility.</para><para>(3) The Legislature hereby finds that it is the policy of the state that a facility for the disposal of low-level radioactive waste shall be established at a location that best protects the health and safety of its citizens and the environment. In selecting such location, the developer shall emphasize geologic, topographic, demographic, hydrologic, and other technical factors that contribute to such protection and shall construct, operate, and maintain such facility in a manner consistent with state and federal requirements.</para><para>It is the intent of the Legislature that potential host communities be actively and voluntarily involved in the siting process. To the extent possible, consistent with the highest level of protection for the health and safety of the citizens of the state and protection of the environment, the developer shall make every effort to locate the facility where community support is evident.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 426, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1092, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact,</emphasis> see section 71-3522.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>