<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1516"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1516</statuteno><catchline>Refuse, garbage, and rubbish; disposal; conditions.</catchline><para>No person shall dispose of any refuse, garbage, or rubbish at any place except a disposal area for which a permit has been issued as provided by the Environmental Protection Act or, on and after October 1, 1993, in a facility for which a permit has been issued under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act. Nothing in either act and no act of the director shall usurp the legal right of a local governing body to develop and enforce local ordinances, codes, or rules and regulations on solid waste disposal equal to or more stringent than the provisions of the acts as necessary to protect the public health and welfare and the environment, and the provisions of the acts shall not relieve the applicant from obtaining a permit from a local governing body when required or relieve the person owning or operating a disposal area from responsibility for securing proper zoning permits or complying with all applicable local ordinances, codes, or rules and regulations not in conflict with the provisions of the acts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 939, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 152, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 89. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Garbage and solid waste disposal facilities,</emphasis> construction and operation by cities of the first and second classes and villages, see sections 19-2101 to 19-2111.</para><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Solid waste disposal areas and facilities,</emphasis> siting approval from city, village, or county, see sections 13-1701 to 13-1714.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>