<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1114"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1114</statuteno><catchline>Department of Administrative Services;
building division; powers, duties, and responsibilities.</catchline><para>The
building division shall have the following powers, duties, and responsibilities:</para>
<para>(1) Shall prepare, for submittal to the Governor and to the office of
the Legislative Fiscal Analyst, analyses of the cost of every desired land
and building acquisition, new building construction, either underway or proposed,
major repair or remodeling of new, newly acquired, or existing buildings,
and each and every structural improvement to land, utilities, roads, walks,
and parking lots, costing four hundred thousand dollars or more, but excluding
right-of-way projects of the Department of Roads. The analyses submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst
shall be submitted electronically. The Department of Administrative
Services shall adjust the dollar amount in this section every four years beginning
January 1, 2002, to account for inflationary and market changes. The adjustment
shall be based on percentage changes in a construction cost index and any
other published index relevant to operations and utilities costs, as selected
by the department;</para>
<para>(2) Shall record the relationship between the proposed capital facilities
and the individual or departmental agencies' operating programs with particular
attention to needs of immediate or future operations of the department or
agency submitting such plan;</para>
<para>(3) Shall make recommendations to the Governor, the committee of the
Legislature which shall from time to time have responsibility for preparing
recommendations for appropriations, and the individual department or agency
concerned, on the probable costs of such acquisition, construction, repair,
or remodeling. The recommendations
submitted to the committee shall be submitted electronically;
and</para>
<para>(4) Shall require the submission by each department and agency of the
state of copies of all written contracts for acquisition, construction, repair,
or remodeling, including federal contracts, before such contracts are executed
by the executive officer of the state authorized to execute such contracts,
and shall maintain copies of such contracts on file for inspection by the
Legislative Fiscal Analyst.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 14, p. 1699; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 594, &#167; 2, p. 2024; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 804, &#167; 8, p. 3036; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 410, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 185.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>