<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1108.17"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1108.17</statuteno><catchline>Department of Administrative Services;
custodian of state property; director; administrator; powers and duties; Capitol
Buildings Parking Revolving Fund; created; purpose; use.</catchline><para>(1)
The Department of Administrative Services shall be the custodian of the state
laboratory and laboratory grounds, the Governor's Mansion and grounds, and
all other buildings and lands owned or leased by the State of Nebraska except
as exempted under subsections (5) and (6) of section 81-1108.15 or as provided
in the Nebraska State Capitol Preservation and Restoration Act.</para>
<para>(2) To aid in the performance of his or her duties, the Director of
Administrative Services shall appoint an administrator. The administrator,
under the direction of the director, shall have complete control and all powers
necessary to properly maintain the state laboratory and laboratory grounds,
the Governor's Mansion and grounds, and all other buildings and lands owned
or leased by the State of Nebraska except as exempted under subsections (5)
and (6) of section 81-1108.15 or as provided in the Nebraska State Capitol
Preservation and Restoration Act.</para>
<para>(3) Except as provided in the act, the administrator, under the direction
of the director, is authorized to (a) lease space or provide facilities for
the parking of state officers' and employees' vehicles as well as bureau fleet vehicles as defined in section 81-1011, (b) lease, rent,
or permit for use as apartments, dwellings, offices, and parking areas any
or all of the property acquired for parking or for future building needs,
(c) lease state property to the federal government or political subdivisions
of the state using the system of charges in subsection (4) of this section,
and (d) lease state property to a private entity to provide services necessary
for state operations or for the convenience of state officers and employees
when the space is not needed for public use. All leases shall contain the
provision that upon notice that such property is needed for public use, the
use or occupancy of the property shall cease. All money received as rent from
any property acquired shall be remitted to the State Treasurer and credited
to the State Building Revolving Fund, except that receipts from parking charges
for employee, public, and state vehicle parking shall be credited to the Capitol
Buildings Parking Revolving Fund, which fund is hereby created, for the purposes
of providing and maintaining parking for state employees and visitors.</para>
<para>(4) The system of charges for state buildings and facilities shall include
an amount sufficient to (a) accurately reflect operating costs, including
routine maintenance and repair costs, and (b) fund building renewal projects
under the Deferred Building Renewal Act and renovation, remodeling, and repair
projects beyond the scope of the act. The proceeds received under subdivision
(a) of this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the State Building Revolving Fund. The proceeds received under subdivision
(b) of this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the State Building Renewal Assessment Fund. The administrator shall develop
a system of equitable billings and charges for parking facilities under his
or her control and used by state employees and state vehicles. The system
of charges shall include an amount sufficient to cover the operating, maintenance,
and repair costs associated with the parking facilities. The administrator,
under policies and procedures established by the Director of Administrative
Services, may expend funds from time to time credited to the Capitol Buildings
Parking Revolving Fund for the purposes of obtaining, operating, and maintaining
parking facilities for employees and visitors. All money derived from any
source other than that to be credited to the State Building Revolving Fund,
the Capitol Buildings Parking Revolving Fund, the Department of Administrative
Services Cash Fund, the State Building Renewal Assessment Fund, or other appropriate
revolving fund shall be remitted to the State Treasurer and credited to the
General Fund.</para>
<para>(5) The administrator shall see that all parts and apartments of the
buildings leased are properly ventilated and kept clean and in order.</para>
<para>(6) The administrator shall at all times have charge of and supervision
over the police, janitors, and other employees in and about the state laboratory
and laboratory grounds, the Governor's Mansion and grounds, and all other
buildings and lands owned or leased by the State of Nebraska except as exempted
under subsections (5) and (6) of section 81-1108.15 or as provided in the
Nebraska State Capitol Preservation and Restoration Act. The administrator
shall institute, in the name of the state and with the advice of the Attorney
General, civil and criminal proceedings against any person for injury or threatened
injury to any public property in the state laboratory and laboratory grounds,
the Governor's Mansion and grounds, and all other buildings and lands owned
or leased by the State of Nebraska under his or her control, or for committing
or threatening to commit a nuisance in or on the buildings or lands.</para>
<para>(7) The administrator shall keep in his or her office a complete record
containing all plans and surveys of the state laboratory and grounds, the
Governor's Mansion and grounds, and all other buildings and lands owned or
leased by the State of Nebraska and of underground construction under such
buildings and lands. This subsection shall not apply to the State Capitol
and capitol grounds.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 192, &#167; 1, p. 677; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 72-707; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 161, &#167; 1, p. 625; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 94, &#167; 1, p. 407; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 144, &#167; 1, p. 573; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 72-707; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 72-706; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 278, &#167; 1, p. 879; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 354, &#167; 2, p. 1114; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 436, &#167; 2, p. 1388; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 439, &#167; 1, p. 1394; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 23, p. 1711; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 468, &#167; 1, p. 1457; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 675, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 72-706; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1048, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 986, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 576, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 607, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 311, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 530, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 314, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB744, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB207, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB779, &#167; 14.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Deferred Building Renewal Act,</emphasis> see section 81-190.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Capitol Preservation and Restoration Act,</emphasis> see section 72-2201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>