<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1222.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1222.03</statuteno><catchline>Wild West Arena; sale or lease; conditions.</catchline><para>The Department of Economic Development may: (1) Until July 1, 1991, with the written approval of the Governor, sell the property known as the Wild West Arena in Lincoln County, Nebraska; or (2) if it is in the best interest of the state, lease such property for a term not to exceed twenty years. The lease may contain an option to purchase the property at a value to be determined by the department. Proceeds of the sale or lease shall be deposited in the appropriate fund and used for the purposes set forth for the fund.</para><para>The legal description of the Wild West Arena is: The north half of lot sixteen, of the subdivision of the Cody Land and Cattle Company lands, Lincoln County, Nebraska, lying north of the north right-of-way line of Drainage District Number 1, Lincoln County, Nebraska, subject to all easements, benefits and burdens of record, such tract of land being more particularly described as follows:</para><para>Commencing at the northeast corner of lot sixteen, Cody Land and Cattle Company Subdivision, thence running west on the north line of lot sixteen a distance of one thousand three hundred thirty and eight-tenths feet to the northwest corner of lot sixteen, thence running south on the west line of lot sixteen a distance of one thousand three hundred and twenty feet to the southwest corner of the north one-half of lot sixteen, thence running east on the south line of the north one-half of lot sixteen a distance of one thousand three hundred thirty-two feet to the southeast corner of the north one-half of lot sixteen, thence running north on the east line of lot sixteen a distance of one thousand three hundred twenty feet to the point of beginning, containing forty and thirty-four hundredths acres, more or less.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 765, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>