<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1618</statuteno><catchline>Local lighting and thermal efficiency standards; conditions; fees; waiver; procedure.</catchline><para>Any county, city, or village may adopt and enforce a lighting and thermal efficiency ordinance, resolution, code, or standard. Such ordinance, resolution, code, or standard shall be deemed equivalent to the Nebraska Energy Code if it does not result in energy consumption greater than would result from the strict application of the Nebraska Energy Code and is reasonably consistent with the intent of sections 81-1608 to 81-1626. Any building or portion thereof subject to the jurisdiction of and inspected by such county, city, or village shall be deemed to comply with sections 81-1608 to 81-1626 if it meets the standards of such ordinance, resolution, code, or standards. Such county, city, or village may by ordinance or resolution prescribe a schedule of fees sufficient to pay the costs incurred pursuant to sections 81-1608 to 81-1626.</para><para>Any county, city, or village which adopts and enforces a lighting and thermal efficiency ordinance, resolution, code, or standard may waive a specific requirement of the Nebraska Energy Code when meeting such requirement is not economically justified. The local code authority shall submit to the State Energy Office its analysis for determining that a specific requirement is not justified. The State Energy Office shall review such analysis and transmit its findings and conclusions to the local code authority within a reasonable time. The local code authority shall submit to the State Energy Office its explanation as to how the original code or any revised code addresses the issues raised by the State Energy Office. After a local code authority has submitted such explanation, the authority may proceed to enforce its ordinance, resolution, code, or standard.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 954, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 2, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 124, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 888, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>