<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1102</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 81-1101 to 81-1117.05 and 81-1121, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Gender with reference to the masculine or feminine gender shall be construed to apply to either or both genders;</para><para>(2) Executive budget means the budget proposed by the Governor to the Legislature as the basis of appropriations for the operation of and capital outlay by state government during the period covered by such budget;</para><para>(3) Approved budget means the executive or Governor's budget as modified by appropriations actions of the Legislature;</para><para>(4) Budgetary allotments means the plan of expenditures, by program, subprogram, activity, or object of expenditure under the approved budget for monthly or other applicable periods of time within each fiscal year, to which a department or agency may be held during such period of time within the fiscal year;</para><para>(5) Accrual system means the recording of revenue when earned and the recording of expenditures as soon as they result in liabilities, notwithstanding the fact that the receipt of the revenue or payment of the expenditure may take place, in whole or in part, in another accounting period;</para><para>(6) Double entry system means a system of bookkeeping which requires for every entry made to the debit side of an account or accounts an entry for a corresponding amount or amounts to the credit side of another account or accounts resulting in a self-balancing accounting system;</para><para>(7) Disbursement means payment from the state treasury;</para><para>(8) Expenditure means, when an accrual system has been established, total liability incurred by contract, purchase order, or payroll commitments or as otherwise provided by law, whether or not related disbursement has been made from the state treasury, and shall mean, until an accrual system has been established, disbursements from the state treasury;</para><para>(9) Revenue means, when an accrual system has been established, additions to assets which do not increase any liability or represent the recovery of an expenditure or disbursement or any part thereof or the cancellation of liabilities without a corresponding increase in other liabilities or a decrease in assets. Until an accrual system has been established, this term means additions to cash in the state treasury or for deposit in the state treasury only;</para><para>(10) Receipts means cash received, unless otherwise qualified;</para><para>(11) Encumbrances means charges to appropriation accounts to reflect obligations for which a part of the appropriation is reserved and which shall cease to be encumbrances when paid or when an actual liability is established in a proprietary account;</para><para>(12) Financing agreement means any bond, lease-purchase obligation, installment sales contract, or similar financial arrangement, for a period greater than one year, which is entered into by the state or any agency, board, or commission thereof, not including the University of Nebraska or state colleges, in accordance with the Constitution of Nebraska and statutes of this state, relating to capital construction, real property acquisition, and personal property acquisition;</para><para>(13) Proprietary account means those accounts designed to show actual financial position and operations such as actual assets, liabilities, surplus, revenue, and expenditures, as distinguished from budgetary accounts;</para><para>(14) Program means a major operation of the state government directed toward the achievement of a definite legal objective and which, in most instances, could be carried on independently of other major operations of the state as defined and described in the accounting and budgeting manuals on file in the office of the Director of Administrative Services;</para><para>(15) Subprogram means one or more operations of a department or agency of the state designed jointly to accomplish a major program objective as defined in the accounting and budgeting manuals on file in the office of the Director of Administrative Services;</para><para>(16) Activity means one or more operations of a department or agency of the state designed jointly to accomplish the objective of a subprogram to which it is related as defined in the accounting and budgeting manual on file in the office of the Director of Administrative Services;</para><para>(17) Budget request means the complete recitation, on forms prescribed by the budget division and in the manner prescribed by such division, of the operating and construction funds requests of a department or agency for the biennium next following the then current biennium;</para><para>(18) Department means the Department of Administrative Services; and</para><para>(19) Director means the Director of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 2, p. 1690; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 593, &#167; 1, p. 2014; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 804, &#167; 1, p. 3029; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 933, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 544, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 15, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1265, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB461, &#167; 42. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>