<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id309"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1414.13"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1414.13</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officer; reciprocity program; approval; application; council; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) A person seeking certification under subdivision (2)(c) of section 81-1414 shall, in addition to any other applicable requirements of the commission or of sections 81-1401 to 81-1414.19, submit an application to the council and complete a reciprocity program as provided in this section. The application shall be made under oath and made on a form provided by the council.</para><para>(2) The applicant shall attest to the following:</para><para>(a) That the applicant's certification as a law enforcement officer has not been revoked or suspended in another jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) That the applicant has not been convicted of or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to a:</para><para>(i) Felony violation of state or federal law;</para><para>(ii) Misdemeanor crime of domestic violence; or</para><para>(iii) Misdemeanor violation of state or federal law, if the violation has a rational connection with the officer's fitness or capacity to serve as a law enforcement officer;</para><para>(c) That the applicant has not been separated from employment or disciplined for serious misconduct or a violation of the officer's oath of office, code of ethics, or statutory duties; and</para><para>(d) Any other information deemed necessary by the council.</para><para>(3) The council shall develop or approve a reciprocity program that an applicant shall complete prior to receiving certification under this section.</para><para>(4) The council shall deny certification to an applicant under this section if the council finds that the applicant does not meet the requirements of subsection (2) of this section, has omitted information required by such subsection, has provided false or misleading information in the application, or has not completed the reciprocity program.</para><para>(5) No law enforcement agency or other state or local agency shall hire as a law enforcement officer a person whose certification is denied under this section.</para><para>(6) The council may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as necessary to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 11. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>