<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id73">
<sectno id="id74">Sec. 9.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id75" statutenumber="81-1822"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id77">81-1822</statuteno><catchline id="id78">Compensation;
situations when not awarded.</catchline><para>No compensation shall
be awarded:</para>
<para>(1) If the victim aided or abetted the offender in the commission
of the unlawful act;</para>
<para>(2) If the offender will receive economic benefit or unjust
enrichment from the compensation;</para>
<para>(3) If the victim violated a criminal law of the state, which
violation caused or contributed to his or her injuries or death;</para>
<para>(4) If the victim is injured as a result of the operation
of a motor vehicle, boat, or airplane (a) unless the vehicle was used in a
deliberate attempt to injure or kill the victim, (b) unless the operator is
charged with a violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197 or a city or village
ordinance enacted in conformance with either of such sections, or (c) unless
any chemical test of the operator's breath or blood indicates an alcohol concentration
equal to or in excess of the limits prescribed in section 60-6,196; or</para>
<para>(5) If the victim incurs an economic loss which does not exceed
ten percent of his or her net financial resources. For purposes of this subdivision,
a victim's net financial resources shall not include the present value of
future earnings and shall be determined by the committee by deducting from
the victim's total financial resources:</para>
<para>(a) One year's earnings;</para>
<para>(b) The victim's equity in his or her home, not exceeding
thirty thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(c) One motor vehicle; and</para>
<para>(d) Any other property which would be exempt from execution
under section 25-1552 or 40-101.</para>
<para>Nothing in this section shall limit payments to a victim by
an offender which are made as full or partial restitution of the victim's
actual pecuniary loss. Subdivision
(5) of this section shall not apply to distributions from the Community Trust.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 910, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 942, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 540, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 87, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 489; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 773, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB598, &#167;  9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>