<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,222"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,222</statuteno><catchline>Release notification.</catchline><para>(1) An owner or operator of a facility shall immediately provide notice as described in subsection (2) of this section if:</para><para>(a) A release of an extremely hazardous substance occurs from a facility at which a hazardous chemical is produced, used, or stored and such release requires a notification under section 103(a) of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980, as amended, 42 U.S.C. 9601 et seq.;</para><para>(b) A release of an extremely hazardous substance occurs from a facility at which a hazardous chemical is produced, used, or stored and such release is not subject to the notification requirements under section 103(a) of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980, but only if the release:</para><para>(i) Is not a federally permitted release as defined in section 101(10) of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980;</para><para>(ii) Is in an amount in excess of a quantity which the administrator has determined by regulation requires notice; and</para><para>(iii) Occurs in a manner which would require notification under section 103(a) of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980; or</para><para>(c) A release of a substance which is not an extremely hazardous substance occurs at a facility at which a hazardous chemical is produced, used, or stored and such release requires notification under section 103(a) of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980.</para><para>(2) Notice shall be given immediately after the release by the owner or operator of the facility by such means as telephone or radio or in person to the commission coordinator for information and to the community emergency coordinator for the local emergency planning committee for any area likely to be affected by the release. With respect to transportation of a substance subject to the requirements of this section or storage incident to such transportation, the notice shall be satisfied by dialing 911 or, in the absence of a 911 emergency telephone number, calling the operator.</para><para>(3) Notice required under this section shall include each of the following to the extent known at the time of the notice and so long as no delay in responding to the emergency results:</para><para>(a) The chemical name or identity of any substance involved in the release;</para><para>(b) An indication of whether the substance is an extremely hazardous substance;</para><para>(c) An estimate of the quantity of any such substance that was released into the environment;</para><para>(d) The time and duration of the release;</para><para>(e) The medium or media into which the release occurred;</para><para>(f) Any known or anticipated acute or chronic health risks associated with the emergency and, if appropriate, advice regarding medical attention necessary for exposed individuals;</para><para>(g) Proper precautions to take as a result of the release, including evacuation, unless such information is readily available to the community emergency coordinator pursuant to the emergency plan; and</para><para>(h) The name and telephone number of the person or persons to be contacted for further information.</para><para>(4) As soon as practicable after a release which requires notice and as more information becomes available, such owner or operator shall provide a written followup emergency notice or notices setting forth and updating the information required under subsection (3) of this section and including additional information with respect to:</para><para>(a) Actions taken to respond to and contain the release;</para><para>(b) Any known or anticipated acute or chronic health risks associated with the release; and</para><para>(c) If appropriate, advice regarding medical attention necessary for exposed individuals.</para><para>(5) This section does not apply to any release which results in exposure to persons solely within the site or sites on which a facility is located. The exemption provided in section 81-15,227 relating to transportation does not apply to this section.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section, facility also includes motor vehicles, rolling stock, and aircraft.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 32. </para></source></law></legaldoc>