<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id21" statutenumber="81-1125.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1125.01</statuteno><catchline id="id24">Director of
Administrative Services; reports and statements required; to whom made.</catchline>
<para>It shall be the duty of the Director of Administrative Services
to digest, prepare, and report to the Governor, the Tax Commissioner, the Clerk of the Legislature, and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst, at
least twenty days before the commencement of each regular session of the Legislature:</para>
<para>(1) The
Annual Budgetary Report showing the condition of the treasury,
and the amount of the expenditures for the last fiscal year;</para>
<para>(2) The Comprehensive Annual Financial Report showing
fully all liabilities and resources of the state; and</para>
<para>(3) Such plans as he or she may deem expedient for (a) the
support of public credit, (b) lessening the public expenses, (c) using the
public money to the best advantage, (d) promoting frugality and economy in
public offices, and generally for the better management and more perfect understanding
of the fiscal affairs of the state, and (e) securing uniformity and efficiency
in the levying and collecting of taxes, systematizing the work to be done
by officers having duties to perform under the revenue law.</para>
<para>The reports submitted to the Legislature shall
be submitted electronically. Each member of the Legislature shall receive
an electronic copy of the reports required by this section
by making a request for it to the director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 4, &#167; 3, p. 19; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5545; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4847; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 84-303; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 84-303; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 459, &#167; 24, p. 1464; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 191; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>