<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1511"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1511</statuteno><catchline>Department; inspections; search warrants.</catchline><para>Any duly authorized officer, employee, or representative of the director may at any reasonable time, with the consent of the person or persons in control of an air, land, or water contaminant source, or property where dredged or fill material is being discharged, enter and inspect any property, premise, or place on or at which such a contaminant source is located or being constructed, installed, or established, or where such dredged or fill material is being discharged, for the purpose of ascertaining the state of compliance with the Environmental Protection Act, the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, and the Livestock Waste Management Act and rules and regulations in force pursuant to the acts. A suitably restricted search warrant, upon a showing of probable cause in writing and upon oath or affirmation, may be issued by the district court as provided by law to such officer, employee, or representative of the department for the purpose of enabling him or her to make such inspection. No person shall refuse entry or access to any authorized representative of the department who requests entry for purposes of inspection and who presents appropriate credentials and warrants. No person shall obstruct, hamper, or interfere with any such inspection. Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent prompt inspection without consent or appropriate warrant in acute and compelling emergency situations when there is neither sufficient time nor opportunity to obtain a search warrant. If requested, the owner or operator of the premises shall receive a report setting forth all facts found which relate to compliance status.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 939, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1435, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 152, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1209, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB809, &#167; 8. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Inspection of grain warehouses,</emphasis> department, duties, see section 88-550.</para><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Livestock Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2416.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>