
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,243"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,243</statuteno><catchline>Economic Recovery Contingency Fund; created; use; prioritize; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Economic Recovery Contingency Fund is created. The fund shall consist of transfers by the Legislature to carry out the Economic Recovery Act. Transfers may be made from the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund to the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Investment earnings on and after July 1, 2023, shall be credited to the fund.</para><para>(2) The Department of Economic Development may review the projects listed in the coordination plan and the appendices by the Economic Recovery Special Committee of the Legislature dated January 10, 2023, and shall prioritize the use of the fund on projects listed in the coordination plan followed by the projects in the appendices.</para><para>(3) The State Treasurer shall transfer seven hundred fifty thousand dollars from the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund to the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund on or after July 1, 2024, but before December 31, 2024, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. The State Treasurer shall transfer fifteen million dollars from the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund to the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund on or after July 1, 2025, but before December 31, 2025, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(4) The State Treasurer shall transfer thirty million dollars from the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund to the Inland Port Authority Fund no later than five business days after April 17, 2024, for the purpose of creating and operating an innovation district by an inland port authority and for any other purpose authorized under the Municipal Inland Port Authority Act.</para><para>(5) The State Treasurer shall transfer any unobligated funds remaining in the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund on July 31, 2026, to the Inland Port Authority Fund.</para><para>(6) The State Treasurer shall transfer seven million dollars from the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund to the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund on or after January 1, 2026, but before June 30, 2026, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1024, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB531, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB164, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1413, &#167; 56. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB164, section 27, with LB1413, section 56, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB164 became operative April 17, 2024. Changes made by LB1413 became effective April 2, 2024.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Municipal Inland Port Authority Act,</emphasis> see section 13-3301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>