<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1521.10"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1521.10</statuteno><catchline>Hazardous waste; site review committee; membership.</catchline><para>(1) The committee shall consist of twelve members, six of whom shall be local members and six of whom shall be regional members.</para><para>(2) The six local members shall be chosen as follows:</para><para>(a) If the proposed facility will be located within the zoning jurisdiction of a municipality, the chief executive officer of the municipality shall appoint six members who reside within such zoning jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) If the proposed facility will be located in an unincorporated area which is within five miles of the zoning jurisdiction of one or more municipalities, the chief executive officer of each such municipality shall appoint a member who resides within the zoning jurisdiction of the respective municipality and the chairperson of the county board of the county in which the facility would be located shall appoint additional members who reside within five miles of the proposed facility for a total of six members; and</para><para>(c) If the proposed facility will be located in an unincorporated area which is more than five miles from the zoning jurisdiction of any municipality, the chairperson of the county board of the county in which the facility would be located shall appoint six members who reside within five miles of the proposed facility.</para><para>(3) The six regional members shall be appointed by the director to represent various interests affected by a proposed facility and shall include at least one environmental representative, one academic expert, one industry representative, one community planner, one representative of public interest groups, and one representative of the medical community. The regional members shall be appointed for two-year terms and shall serve whenever a committee is needed during that time. Alternates shall be appointed to serve in case a regional member is unable to do so or is already serving on a committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 114, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>