
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1426.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1426.01</statuteno><catchline>County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program; created; grant recipient; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1) There is created a separate and distinct budgetary program within the commission to be known as the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program. Funding shall be used to provide grants to counties to help offset jail costs.</para><para>(2) The annual General Fund appropriation to the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program shall be apportioned to the counties as grants in accordance with a formula established in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. The formula shall be based on the total number per county of individuals incarcerated in jails and the total capacity of jails.</para><para>(3) Funds provided to counties under the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program shall be used exclusively to assist counties in the event that their average daily jail population increases after August 30, 2015. In distributing funds provided under the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program, counties shall demonstrate to the commission that their average daily jail population increased, using data to pinpoint the contributing factors, as a result of the implementation of Laws 2015, LB605. The commission shall grant funds to counties which have an increase in population compared to the average daily jail population of the preceding three fiscal years. In calculating the average daily jail population, counties shall only include post-adjudication inmates who are serving sentences or inmates serving custodial sanctions due to probation violations. Counties may apply for grants one year after August 30, 2015.</para><para>(4) No funds appropriated or distributed under the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program shall be used for the construction of secure detention facilities, secure treatment facilities, secure confinement facilities, or county jails. Grants received under this section shall not be used for capital construction or the lease or acquisition of facilities. Any funds appropriated to the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program to be distributed to counties under this section shall be retained by the commission to be distributed in the form of grants in the following fiscal year.</para><para>(5) In distributing funds provided under the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program, recipients shall prioritize use of the funds for programs, services, and approaches that reduce jail populations and costs. The funds may be used to supplement existing programs, services, and approaches to reduce jail populations and costs.</para><para>(6) Any aid not distributed to counties shall be retained by the commission to be distributed on a competitive basis to counties demonstrating additional need in the funding areas identified in this section.</para><para>(7) Any county receiving grants under the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program shall submit annual information electronically to the commission as required by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. The information shall include, but not be limited to, the objective sought for the grant and estimated savings and reduction in jail inmates.</para><para>(8) The commission shall report annually to the Governor and the Legislature on the distribution and use of funds for grants appropriated under the County Justice Reinvestment Grant Program. The report shall include, but not be limited to, the information listed under subsection (7) of this section. The report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(9) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to implement this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB298, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>