<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,112</statuteno><catchline>Violation; civil penalty; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who (a) violates any licensing provision of the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal Act, any rule, regulation, or order issued pursuant to the act, or any term, condition, or limitation of any license issued pursuant to the act or (b) commits any violation for which a license may be revoked under rules or regulations issued pursuant to the act may be subject to a civil penalty, to be imposed by the department, not to exceed ten thousand dollars. If any violation is a continuing one, each day of such violation shall constitute a separate violation for the purpose of computing the applicable civil penalty. The department shall have the power to compromise, mitigate, or remit such penalties.</para><para>(2) Whenever the department proposes to subject a person to the imposition of a civil penalty under this section, the department shall notify such person in writing (a) setting forth the date, facts, and nature of each act or omission with which the person is charged, (b) specifically identifying the particular provision or provisions of the section, rule, regulation, order, or license involved in the violation, and (c) specifying each penalty which the department proposes to impose and its amount. Such written notice shall be sent by registered or certified mail by the department to the last-known address of such person. The person so notified may request a hearing, in writing, within thirty days of receipt of such notice. A hearing, if granted, shall be held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. The notice shall also advise such person that upon failure to pay the civil penalty subsequently determined by the department, if any, the penalty may be collected by civil action. Any person upon whom a civil penalty is imposed may appeal such penalty, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. On the request of the department, the Attorney General or county attorney may institute a civil action to collect a penalty imposed pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 177. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>