<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id136"><amendatorysection statutenumber="81-1522" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1522</statuteno><catchline>Water Quality and Quantity Cash Fund; created; use; investment; permits; fees; exemption.</catchline><para>(1) The Water Quality and Quantity Cash Fund is created. The department shall remit all fees collected pursuant to this section and money received by the department in the form of gifts, grants, reimbursements, or monetary transfers from any source intended to be used for the purposes of the fund to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. The fund shall be used to pay the reasonable direct and indirect costs required to develop and administer programs to regulate discharges under section 402 of the Clean Water Act, as amended, 33 U.S.C. 1342 et seq. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) Beginning July 1, 2027, each application for a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit or a pretreatment permit required by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to subsection (20) of section 81-1505 shall be accompanied by an application fee, to be determined by the department. The fee shall not be more than the amount necessary to reimburse the department for administering the applications. An application required under section 54-2428 shall be exempt from the application fee required by this section.</para><para>(3) Beginning July 1, 2027, the department shall charge an annual fee to each person who has a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit or who has a pretreatment permit required by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to subsection (20) of section 81-1505. The fee shall be an amount no more than the actual cost of services provided. A permit issued pursuant to section 54-2428 shall be exempt from the annual fee required by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB759, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>