<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id83"><amendatorysection statutenumber="81-1454" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1454</statuteno><catchline>Body-worn camera policy; contents.</catchline><para>A body-worn camera policy required by section 81-1453 shall include provisions which govern the use of body-worn cameras by peace officers and the retention and disposition of recordings created with such cameras by law enforcement agencies. Such body-worn camera policy shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(1) A requirement that training be provided to any peace officer who will use a body-worn camera and to any other employee who will come into contact with video or audio data recorded by a body-worn camera;</para><para>(2) A requirement that recordings created by body-worn cameras shall be retained for a minimum period of ninety days from the date of recording. Such recordings shall be retained for more than ninety days if required by the following circumstances:</para><para>(a) Upon notice to the law enforcement agency of a criminal or civil court proceeding in which the recording may have evidentiary value or in which the recording is otherwise involved, the recording shall be retained until final judgment has been entered in the proceeding;</para><para>(b) Upon notice to the law enforcement agency of a disciplinary proceeding against an employee of the agency in which the recording may have evidentiary value or in which the recording is otherwise involved, the recording shall be retained until a final determination has been made in such proceeding; and</para><para>(c) If the recording is part of a criminal investigation that has not resulted in an arrest or prosecution, the recording shall be retained until the investigation is officially closed or suspended; and</para><para>(3) A procedure governing the destruction of recordings after the retention period described in subdivision (2) of this section has elapsed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1000, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>