<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,120</statuteno><catchline>Farm or residential tank; heating oil storage tank; registration; when required; fee; Petroleum Products and Hazardous Substances Storage and Handling Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>Any farm or residential tank or tank used for storing heating oil as defined in subdivisions (10)(a) and (b) of section 81-15,119 shall be registered with the State Fire Marshal. The registration shall be accompanied by a one-time fee of five dollars and shall be valid until the State Fire Marshal is notified that a tank so registered has been permanently closed. Such registration shall specify the ownership of, location of, and substance stored in the tank to be registered. The State Fire Marshal shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer for credit to the Petroleum Products and Hazardous Substances Storage and Handling Fund which is hereby created as a cash fund. The fund shall also consist of any money appropriated to the fund by the state. The fund shall be administered by the Department of Environmental Quality to carry out the purposes of the Petroleum Products and Hazardous Substances Storage and Handling Act, including the provision of matching funds required by Public Law 99-499 for actions otherwise authorized by the act. Any money in such fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 217, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 816, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 119; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 461, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>