<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,102</statuteno><catchline>Disposal site; acquisition or acceptance; construction contracts; conditions; use; notice required; contract for management; management; remedial cleanup costs.</catchline><para>(1) The state shall accept or acquire, by gift, transfer, or purchase, from the licensed facility operator, title to the land and appurtenances used for the disposal of low-level radioactive waste after the expiration of both the operational life and closure period of the facility, if:</para><para>(a) Both the Department of Health and Human Services Regulation and Licensure and the Department of Environmental Quality determine that (i) the requirements for site closure, decommissioning, and decontamination adopted pursuant to rules and regulations of the Department of Health and Human Services Regulation and Licensure and the Department of Environmental Quality which are allowed under federal law have been met by the licensed facility operator and (ii) such operator is in compliance with all financial requirements; and</para><para>(b) The amendments to the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact made by Laws 1991, LB 837, section 4, codified in section 71-3521, are in effect and have been ratified by Congress.</para><para>The title to the land and appurtenances shall be transferred without cost to the state. Such transfer of title to the state does not relieve the developer, licensed facility operator, or generators of such waste from liability for their actions that occurred whether known or unknown during the design, construction, operation, and closure of the facility. Sites received by gift or transfer shall be subject to approval and acceptance by the Legislature on behalf of the state.</para><para>(2) The applicant shall notify the Governor and the Legislature before beginning any onsite geological activity, such as soil core sampling, to determine the suitability of a site in the State of Nebraska for use as a facility.</para><para>(3) Lands and appurtenances which are used for the disposal of low-level radioactive waste shall be acquired and held in fee simple absolute by the licensed facility operator so long as such ownership does not preclude licensure or operation of the facility under federal law and until title to the land and appurtenances is transferred to the state pursuant to subsection (1) of this section. Such lands and appurtenances shall be used exclusively for the disposal of low-level radioactive waste until the department determines that such exclusive use is not required to protect the public health, safety, welfare, or environment. Before such a site is leased for other use, the department shall require and assure that the radioactive waste history of the site be recorded in the permanent land records of the site. Remedial cleanup costs which become necessary during the period of custodial care shall be assessed first to the licensed facility operator, then proportionately against the generators of the radioactive waste and as set out in the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact found in section 71-3521.</para><para>(4) The state may contract for the management of a disposal site. The contractor shall be subject to licensing by the department and shall be subject to the surety and custodial care funding provisions of section 81-15,103.</para><para>(5) If and until licensing of a facility is approved, no further construction contracts shall be let or actual construction begun, other than filling the identified wetland, before the Department of Environmental Quality has conducted a six-month public education program to inform the people of the county and the people of the state of the exact characteristics of the facility to be built, which program shall be undertaken forthwith.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 426, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 72, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1201, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 218; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1174, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>