<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id61">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id63" statutenumber="81-15,152"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,152</statuteno><catchline id="id66">Council; powers
and duties.</catchline><para>The council shall have the following
powers and duties:</para>
<para>(1) The power to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to govern the application procedure and requirements for making loans under
the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Assistance Act;</para>
<para>(2) The power to adopt a system for the ranking of wastewater
treatment construction projects with known needs or for which loan applications
have been received by the department. In establishing the system the council
shall consider, among other things, the severity of pollution, public health,
water quality impact, population, financial capability, and eligibility of
the construction project for federal or state funds. This priority system
shall be reviewed annually by the council;</para>
<para>(3) The power to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to govern types of nonpoint source control system projects which will be eligible
for loans and to adopt a system for priority ranking of such projects;</para>
<para>(4) The power to adopt a system of establishing interest rates
to be charged on loans. The system shall presume that the current market interest
rate shall be charged unless a municipality or a county demonstrates a serious
financial hardship. The system may allow discounted interest rates for short-term
loans. The following factors shall be considered when making a determination
of serious financial hardship: Income level of residents; amount of debt and
debt service requirements; and level of user fees both in absolute terms and
relative to income of residents;</para>
<para>(5) The power to create an administrative fee to be assessed
on a loan for the purpose of administering the Wastewater Treatment Facilities
Construction Assistance Act. Such fee shall be based on the availability of
federal funding for such purpose and the projected administrative needs for
carrying out the purposes of the act;</para>
<para>(6) The power to determine the maximum amount of any one loan
or combination of loans for any single municipality or any single county;</para>
<para>(7) Except as limited by section 81-15,151, the power to obligate
the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund and the assets
thereof, in whole or in part, to repay with interest loans to or deposits
into the fund, including bonds, the proceeds of which are deposited into the
fund;</para>
<para>(8) The power to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to govern the application procedure and requirements, including any funding
caps and cost-share requirements, for grants pursuant to subdivision (12) of section 81-15,153;</para>
<para>(9) The power
to adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish and administer
the linked deposit program; and</para><para>(10) The power to adopt and promulgate rules
and regulations for refinancing of debt obligations of municipalities in accordance
with section 81-15,151.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 766, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 623, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 311, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1234, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB514, &#167; 6.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>