
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1230"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1230</statuteno><catchline>Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund; created; use; investment; return of grant funds; when required.</catchline><para>(1) The Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund is created. Funding for the grant program described in section 81-1229 shall come from the Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund. The Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund may include revenue from appropriations from the Legislature, grants, private contributions, and other sources. In addition, the State Treasurer shall make a one-time transfer of seven million three hundred thousand dollars on or before October 1, 2017, from the Affordable Housing Trust Fund to the Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund. Any money in the Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) The department shall administer the Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund and may seek additional private or nonstate funds to use in the grant program, including, but not limited to, contributions from the Nebraska Investment Finance Authority and other interested parties.</para><para>(3) Interest earned by the department on grant funds shall be applied to the grant program.</para><para>(4) If a nonprofit development organization fails to engage in the initial qualified activity within twenty-four months after receiving initial grant funding, the nonprofit development organization shall return the grant funds to the department for credit to the General Fund.</para><para>(5) If a nonprofit development organization fails to allocate any remaining initial grant funding on a qualified activity within twenty-four months after engaging in the initial qualified activity, the nonprofit development organization shall return such unallocated grant funds to the department for credit to the Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund.</para><para>(6) Beginning July 1, 2027, any funds held by the department in the Rural Workforce Housing Investment Fund shall be transferred to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB518, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1069, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>