<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,272"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,272</statuteno><catchline>Recreation camps; permit; application; issuance; fees; disposition.</catchline><para>Before any person shall directly or indirectly operate a recreation camp he or she shall make an application to the department and receive a valid permit for the operation of such camp. Application for such a permit shall be made at least thirty days prior to the proposed operation of the camp and shall be on forms supplied by the department upon request. The application shall be in such form and contain such information as the department may deem necessary to its determination that the recreation camp will be operated and maintained in such a manner as to protect and preserve the health and safety of the persons using the camp and shall be accompanied by an annual fee. The department may establish fees by regulation to defray the actual costs of issuing the permit, conducting inspections, and other expenses incurred by the department in carrying out this section. If a person operates or is seeking to operate more than one recreation camp, a separate application shall be made for each camp. Such a permit shall not be transferable or assignable. A permit shall expire on March 31 of the following year after its issuance, upon a change of operator of the camp, or upon revocation. If the department finds, after investigation, that the camp or the proposed operation thereof conforms, or will conform, to the minimum standards for recreation camps, a permit on a form prescribed by the department shall be issued for operation of the camp. All fees shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Environmental Safety Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 328, &#167; 2, p. 1193; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 419, &#167; 7, p. 1345; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 813, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 642; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 107; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 179; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 557; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2018), &#167; 71-3102; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>