<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,247"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,247</statuteno><catchline>Rules and regulations.</catchline><para>The council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the Private Onsite Wastewater Treatment System Contractors Certification and System Registration Act. Such rules and regulations shall provide for, but not be limited to: </para><para>(1) Certification of private onsite wastewater treatment system professionals;</para><para>(2) Establishing categories for such professionals to be certified under the act;</para><para>(3) Hardship certifications;</para><para>(4) Examination requirements for certification;</para><para>(5) Continuing education requirements for certification;</para><para>(6) A fee schedule which covers direct and indirect costs to administer the act. Such costs include (a) system registration, late fees for system registration, application for certification, examination, and renewal, late fees for renewal, hardship certifications, fees for continuing education classes offered or approved by the department, other continuing education costs, and administration, (b) development and enforcement of standards, and (c) investigation, inspection, and enforcement related to any private onsite wastewater treatment system;</para><para>(7) Requirements for the registration of private onsite wastewater treatment systems to be constructed, reconstructed, altered, modified, or inspected by professionals certified under the act; and</para><para>(8) Requiring that all private onsite wastewater treatment system siting, layout, construction, closure, reconstruction, alteration, modification, repair, inspection, or pumping be performed by certified professionals in accordance with the act, rules and regulations adopted under the act, and other rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 94, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB333, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB328, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>