<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1521.17"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1521.17</statuteno><catchline>Commercial hazardous waste management facility; notice of hearing; decision by local governing body.</catchline><para>Before the county board, city council, or board of trustees approves or disapproves a proposed commercial hazardous waste management facility, notice shall be given once at least thirty days but not more than forty days before the hearing and a second time at least ten days before the hearing. Such notice shall be given by publication of a notice in a newspaper either published in or having general circulation in the county, city, or village where the proposed facility is to be located and shall state the time and place of hearing, the name of the applicant for a permit, and the exact location of the proposed facility. In deciding whether to approve or disapprove such facility, the county board, city council, or board of trustees shall determine if such facility will be in compliance with its zoning laws or violate any local ordinances or resolutions. The local governing body shall make its decision within one hundred eighty days of receipt of a copy of the application from the director and shall notify the department and the applicant of its action. If the local governing body disapproves the application, it shall specify its reasons for disapproval. If the local governing body disapproves the application, the department may not take further action on the application unless the disapproval is reversed by court order. For purposes of appeal, the decision of the local governing body to disapprove the application shall be deemed a final order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 853, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 81-1521.02; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 114, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 152, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>