<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,218"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,218</statuteno><catchline>Facility; notifications required.</catchline><para>(1) The owner or operator of each facility in which an extremely hazardous substance exceeding threshold planning quantities is present shall notify the commission that such facility is subject to the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act within sixty days after September 13, 1997, unless notification was made prior to September 13, 1997, and shall notify the commission and the local emergency planning committee of the emergency planning district in which the facility is located that such facility is subject to the act within sixty days after an extremely hazardous substance first becomes present at such facility in excess of the threshold planning quantity established for such substance. If there is a revision of the definition of extremely hazardous substances and the facility has present a substance included in the revised definition in excess of the threshold planning quantity established for such substance, the owner or operator of the facility shall notify the commission and the committee of the district in which the facility is located within sixty days after such revision that such facility is subject to the act.</para><para>(2) The commission shall notify the director and the State Administrator of facilities subject to the act. The notification shall include:</para><para>(a) Each notification received from a facility under subsection (1) of this section; and</para><para>(b) Each facility designated by the commission under subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3) For purposes of emergency planning, the commission may designate additional facilities which are subject to the act if such designation is made after public notice and opportunity for comment. The commission shall notify the facility concerned of any designation under this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 28. </para></source></law></legaldoc>