
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id300">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id302" statutenumber="81-1379"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1379</statuteno><catchline id="id305">Negotiations;
when commenced and completed; negotiated agreements; requirements; supplementary
bargaining.</catchline><para>The Chief Negotiator and any other
employer-representative and the exclusive collective-bargaining agent shall
commence negotiations on or prior to the second Wednesday in September of
the year preceding the beginning of the contract period, except that the first
negotiations commenced by any bargaining unit may commence after such September
date in order to accommodate any unresolved representation proceedings. All
negotiations shall be completed on or before March 15 of the following year.</para>
<para>All negotiated agreements shall be in writing and signed
by the parties. The authority to enter into the agreed-upon contract shall
be vested in the following:</para>
<para>(1) For the University of Nebraska, the Board of Regents;</para>
<para>(2) For the Nebraska state colleges, the Board of Trustees
of the Nebraska State Colleges;</para>
<para>(3) For other constitutional offices, the head of such office;</para>
<para>(4) For all other agencies, the Governor; and</para>
<para>(5) For the bargaining unit, a majority of those voting on
ratification after notice of the contract terms is given and a secret ballot
vote has been taken.</para>
<para>Nothing in the State Employees Collective Bargaining Act
shall be construed to prohibit supplementary bargaining on behalf of employees
in part of a bargaining unit concerning matters uniquely affecting such employees
or cooperation and coordination of bargaining between two or more bargaining
units. Supplementary bargaining in regard to employees for whom the Governor
is the employer-representative shall be the responsibility of the Chief Negotiator
and may be assigned to his or her designated representative.</para>
<para>Any agreements entered into pursuant to this section may
be adjusted after March 15 only to reflect any order issued by the commission or
the Supreme Court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 661, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB397, &#167; 25.</para></source><annotation><para>Public employee bargaining units, created under the State Employees Collective Bargaining Act, section 81-1369 et seq., must file any petition seeking to decertify an exclusive collective bargaining agent, under the Rules of the Nebraska Commission of Industrial Relations 9(II)(C)(1) (rev. 2015), during the period preceding the commencement of the statutorily required bargaining period in this section. Nebraska Protective Servs. Unit v. State, 299 Neb. 797, 910 N.W.2d 767 (2018).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>