<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1425"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1425</statuteno><catchline>Executive director; powers; duties.</catchline><para>The executive director of the commission shall:</para><para>(1) Supervise and be responsible for the administration of the policies established by the commission;</para><para>(2) Establish a Jail Standards subdivision within the commission and establish, consolidate, or abolish any other administrative subdivision within the commission and appoint and remove for cause the heads thereof, and delegate appropriate powers and duties to them;</para><para>(3) Establish and administer projects and programs for the operation of the commission;</para><para>(4) Appoint and remove employees of the commission and delegate appropriate powers and duties to them;</para><para>(5) Make rules and regulations for the management and the administration of policies of the commission and the conduct of employees under his or her jurisdiction;</para><para>(6) Collect, develop, maintain, and analyze statistical information, records, and reports as the commission may determine relevant to its functions, including, but not limited to, the statistical information set forth in section 47-627;</para><para>(7) Prior to August 1, 2001, review and analyze all cases involving criminal homicide committed on or after April 20, 1973. The review and analysis shall examine (a) the facts, including mitigating and aggravating circumstances, (b) to the extent such can be ascertained, the race, gender, religious preference, and economic status of the defendant and of the victim, (c) the charges filed, (d) the result of the judicial proceeding in each case, and (e) the sentence imposed. Upon the completion of such review, the report of such shall be transmitted to the Governor, the Clerk of the Legislature, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. The review and analysis shall be updated as new cases of criminal homicide occur. The commission shall update such report annually to the parties named in this subdivision;</para><para>(8) Transmit monthly to the commission a report of the operations of the commission for the preceding calendar month;</para><para>(9) Execute and carry out the provisions of all contracts, leases, and agreements authorized by the commission with agencies of federal, state, or local government, corporations, or persons;</para><para>(10) Perform such additional duties as may be assigned to him or her by the commission, by the chairperson of the commission, or by law; and</para><para>(11) Exercise all powers and perform all duties necessary and proper in carrying out his or her responsibilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 774, &#167; 11, p. 2935; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 328, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1008, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 22. </para></source></law></legaldoc>