<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,224"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,224</statuteno><catchline>Tier II inventory form.</catchline><para>(1) The owner or operator of any facility which is required to prepare or have available a material safety data sheet for a hazardous chemical meeting threshold quantity requirements under regulations promulgated under Title III shall prepare and submit annually on or before March 1 beginning in 1998 a tier II inventory form on data for the preceding calendar year to:</para><para>(a) The local emergency planning committee for the emergency planning district in which the facility is located;</para><para>(b) The commission coordinator for information; and</para><para>(c) The fire department with jurisdiction over the facility.</para><para>(2) An owner or operator may meet the requirements of this section with respect to a hazardous chemical which is a mixture by doing one of the following:</para><para>(a) Providing information on the tier II inventory form on each element or compound in the mixture which is a hazardous chemical. If more than one mixture has the same element or compound, only one listing on the tier II inventory form for the element or compound at the facility is necessary; or</para><para>(b) Providing information on the tier II inventory form on the mixture itself.</para><para>(3) A hazardous chemical subject to the requirements of this section is any hazardous chemical for which a material safety data sheet or a list of chemicals is required under section 81-15,223.</para><para>(4) A tier II inventory form shall provide the following information for each hazardous chemical present at the facility:</para><para>(a) The chemical name or the common name of the chemical as provided on the material safety data sheet;</para><para>(b) An estimate in ranges of the maximum amount of the hazardous chemical present at the facility at any time during the preceding calendar year;</para><para>(c) An estimate in ranges of the average daily amount of the hazardous chemical present at the facility during the preceding calendar year;</para><para>(d) A brief description of the manner of storage of the hazardous chemical;</para><para>(e) The location at the facility of the hazardous chemical; and</para><para>(f) An indication of whether the owner elects to withhold location information of a specific hazardous chemical from disclosure to the public under section 81-15,229.</para><para>(5) Upon request by the commission, the director, a committee, or a fire department with jurisdiction over the facility, the owner or operator of a facility shall provide tier II information, as described in subsection (4) of this section, to the person making the request. Any such request shall be with respect to a specific facility.</para><para>(6) A state or local official acting in his or her official capacity may have access to tier II information by submitting a request to the commission or a committee. Upon receipt of a request for tier II information, the commission or committee shall request such information from the facility owner or operator and make such information available to the official.</para><para>(7) Any person may make request to the commission, the director, or a committee for tier II information relating to the preceding calendar year with respect to a facility. Any such request shall be in writing and shall be with respect to a specific facility.</para><para>(8) Any tier II information which the commission, the director, or a committee has in its possession shall be made available to a person making a request under this section in accordance with section 81-15,229. If the commission, director, or committee does not have the tier II information in its possession, upon a request for the information the commission, director, or committee shall request the facility owner or operator for the information with respect to a hazardous chemical which a facility has stored in an amount in excess of ten thousand pounds present at the facility at any time during the preceding calendar year and make such information available in accordance with section 81-15,229 to the person making the request.</para><para>(9) In the case of tier II information which is not in the possession of the commission, the director, or a committee and which is with respect to a hazardous chemical which a facility has stored in an amount less than ten thousand pounds present at the facility at any time during the preceding calendar year, a request from a person must include the general need for the information. The commission, director, or committee may request the facility owner or operator for the tier II information on behalf of the person making the request. Upon receipt of any information requested on behalf of such person, the commission, director, or committee shall make the information available to the person in accordance with section 81-15,229.</para><para>(10) The commission, the director, or a committee shall respond to a request for tier II information under this section no later than forty-five days after the date of receipt of the request.</para><para>(11) An owner or operator of a facility which files an inventory form under this section shall, upon request by the fire department with jurisdiction over the facility, allow the fire department to conduct an onsite inspection of the facility and shall provide to the fire department specific location information on hazardous chemicals at the facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 34. </para></source></law></legaldoc>