<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1116" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1116</statuteno><catchline>Information management services division; administrator; qualifications; pay.</catchline><para>The information management services division shall be headed by an administrator. Any person who has successfully completed a four-year program at an accredited four-year college or university and who has not less than four years total experience in information management services, of which not less than one year shall have been experience as the supervisor of an information management entity in government or private enterprise and not less than two years shall have been experience as a systems analyst or with principal responsibility for systems development or supervision, or both, may be appointed information management services administrator by the Chief Information Officer. Successful completion of training courses covering the functions, programming, operations, and systems development aspects of information management equipment may be accounted as experience in direct proportion to the number of weeks of course work completed. The rate of pay for the information management services administrator shall be fixed by the Chief Information Officer subject to availability of appropriations. The information management services administrator shall have the power to select and manage such staff and supervise the operation of such equipment as he or she may require.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 518, &#167; 16, p. 1701; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 595, &#167; 4, p. 2028; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 593, &#167; 5, p. 2019; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 804, &#167; 10, p. 3038; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 921, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>