<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id7"><amendatorysection statutenumber="81-15,159.01" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,159.01</statuteno><catchline>Department of Environmental Quality; conduct study; establish advisory committee; members; department powers; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Environmental Quality shall conduct a study to examine the status of solid waste management programs operated by the department and make recommendations to modernize and revise such programs. The study shall include, but not be limited to: (a) Whether existing state programs regarding litter and waste reduction and recycling should be amended or merged; (b) a needs assessment of the recycling and composting programs in the state, including the need for infrastructure development operating standards, market development, coordinated public education resulting in behavior change, and incentives to increase recycling and composting; (c) methods to partner with political subdivisions, private industry, and private, nonprofit organizations to most successfully address waste management issues in the state; (d) recommendations regarding existing funding sources and possible new revenue sources at the state and local level to address existing and emerging solid waste management issues; and (e) revisions to existing grant programs to address solid waste management issues in a proactive manner.</para><para>(2) The Director of Environmental Quality shall establish an advisory committee to advise the department regarding the study described in this section. The members of the advisory committee shall be appointed by the director and shall include no more than nine members. The director shall designate a chairperson of the advisory committee. The members shall receive no compensation for their services.</para><para>(3) In addition to the advisory committee, the department may hire consultants and special experts to assist in the study described in this section. After completion of the study, the department shall submit a report, including recommendations, to the Executive Board of the Legislative Council and the chairpersons of the Natural Resources Committee, the Urban Affairs Committee, and the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature no later than December 15, 2017. The report shall be submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1101, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>