
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id169"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,208"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,208</statuteno><catchline>Matching funds; eligibility; application; requirements; approval; deadlines.</catchline><para>(1) In order to be eligible to receive the matching funds allowed in the Nebraska Rural Projects Act, the applicant shall file an application with the director, on a form developed by the director, requesting an agreement.</para><para>(2) The application shall:</para><para>(a) Identify the project, including the qualified location of such project;</para><para>(b) State the estimated, projected amount of total new investment at the project, including the estimated, projected amount of applicant resources;</para><para>(c) State the E-Verify number or numbers that will be used by the applicant for employees at the qualified location as provided by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services; and</para><para>(d) Contain a nonrefundable application fee of one thousand dollars. The director shall collect all application fees and shall remit the fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Rural Projects Fund.</para><para>(3) An application must be complete to establish the date of application. An application shall be considered complete once it contains the items listed in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) Once satisfied that the application is complete and that the applicant is eligible to receive the matching funds allowed in the Nebraska Rural Projects Act, the director shall approve the application.</para><para>(5) There shall be no new applications filed under this section after June 30, 2023. Any complete application filed on or before June 30, 2023, shall be considered by the director and approved if the location and applicant qualify for approval. Agreements may be executed with regard to any complete application filed on or before June 30, 2023.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB40, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>