<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id53">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id55" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-15,151.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,151.03</statuteno><catchline>Linked deposit program; eligible
financial institution; duties; linked deposit program loans; use.</catchline>
<para>(1) The department
may establish and administer the linked deposit program, pursuant to rules
and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council, to promote loans by
eligible financial institutions for the construction, rehabilitation, and
enhancement of nonpoint source control systems for public or private owners
thereof. When an eligible financial institution has executed a linked deposit
agreement with the director, the director may deposit a portion of the Wastewater
Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund with the eligible financial institution
in low-yielding deposit accounts, certificates of deposit, or other authorized
deposits as set forth in the linked deposit agreement between the director
and the eligible financial institution. Such deposits shall not be subject
to the requirements of the Public Funds Deposit Security Act. In the linked
deposit agreement, the eligible financial institution shall make loans available
at an interest rate lower than the otherwise prevailing interest rate for
construction, rehabilitation, and enhancement of nonpoint source control systems.
Eligibility for the linked deposit program shall be determined pursuant to
rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council.</para>
<para>(2) Linked deposit
program loans may be made to public or private owners by eligible financial
institutions for the construction, rehabilitation, and enhancement of nonpoint
source control systems including:</para><para>(a) Onsite wastewater and private septic
systems;</para><para>(b) Local water protection projects, including best management practices
for nutrient controls; and</para><para>(c) Eligible nonpoint source activities under the Livestock Waste
Management Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB514, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Livestock Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2416.</para><para><emphasis>Public Funds Deposit Security Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2386.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>