<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id36"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,108</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Innovation Hub Act:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Economic Development;</para><para>(2) Director means the Director of Economic Development;</para><para>(3) Economic redevelopment area means an area in the State of Nebraska in which:</para><para>(a) The average rate of unemployment in the area during the period covered by the most recent federal decennial census or American Community Survey 5-Year Estimate by the United States Bureau of the Census is at least one hundred fifty percent of the average rate of unemployment in the state during the same period; and</para><para>(b) The average poverty rate in the area is twenty percent or more for the federal census tract in the area;</para><para>(4) iHub area means the geographical area in this state in which an iHub will operate. An iHub area shall be located within:</para><para>(a) An economic redevelopment area; or</para><para>(b) An enterprise zone designated pursuant to the Enterprise Zone Act;</para><para>(5) iHub partner means an entity described in section 81-12,111 that collaborates with an iHub for purposes of driving economic growth within an iHub area;</para><para>(6) Innovation hub or iHub means a private nonprofit corporation that is designated by the director as an iHub; and</para><para>(7) Postsecondary educational institution means a two-year or four-year college or university which is a member institution of an accrediting body recognized by the United States Department of Education.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB450, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Enterprise Zone Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2101.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>