<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,101</statuteno><catchline>License application; contents; transfer; limitation; review, when; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Each application for a license shall be in writing and shall state such information as the department may determine to be necessary to decide the technical and financial qualifications or any other qualifications of the applicant deemed reasonable and necessary to protect the public health and environment with an adequate margin of safety. The applicant shall also describe the funding arrangements such applicant will make to provide for custodial care. The department may at any time after the filing of the application and before the expiration of the license require further written statements and may make such inspections as the department may deem necessary in order to determine whether the license should be modified, suspended, or revoked. All applications and statements shall be signed by the applicant or licensee.</para><para>(2) No license issued under the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal Act shall be assigned or in any manner disposed of unless the department, after securing full information, finds that the transfer is in accordance with the act and gives its consent in writing.</para><para>(3) If any person becomes the legal or beneficial owner of more than fifty percent of any class of the issued and outstanding equity securities of an applicant or licensee at any time after the application has been made and before the expiration of the license, the department shall conduct a review which shall include, but not be limited to, the environmental compliance record and financial responsibility of such person. At the conclusion of the review, the department shall issue a report of its findings, including its conclusions regarding the adequacy of such person to fulfill the provisions of the application or license and all laws, rules, and regulations. Copies of the report shall be sent to the Governor, Legislature, and local monitoring committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 426, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 761, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1201, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>