<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,214"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,214</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Cash Fund. The fund may receive gifts, bequests, grants, fees, or other contributions or donations from public or private entities. The fund shall be used to carry out the purposes of the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act, including:</para><para>(a) The funding of specific projects as approved by the commission; and</para><para>(b) The payment of expenses incurred by the commission to administer the fund. Payment from the fund for costs of administering the fund shall not exceed fifteen percent of the total receipts of the fund during the fiscal year. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing allocations from the fund and shall publish guidelines regarding allocations from the fund. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) Entities receiving allocations from the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Cash Fund shall expend the allocation in a manner expressly approved by the commission. If allocations from the fund are used for purposes other than those approved by the commission, the commission may recover by appropriate legal means any funds spent inconsistent with the terms of the allocation. Any recovered funds shall be deposited in the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 24. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>