<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,223"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,223</statuteno><catchline>Material safety data sheet.</catchline><para>(1) The owner or operator of any facility which is required to prepare or have available a material safety data sheet for a hazardous chemical under the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970, 29 U.S.C. 651 et seq., and regulations promulgated under the act shall submit a material safety data sheet for each such chemical meeting threshold quantity requirements under regulations promulgated under Title III or shall submit a list of chemicals to:</para><para>(a) The local emergency planning committee for the emergency planning district in which the facility is located;</para><para>(b) The commission coordinator for information; and</para><para>(c) The fire department with jurisdiction over the facility.</para><para>(2) An owner or operator may meet the requirements of this section with respect to a hazardous chemical which is a mixture by doing one of the following:</para><para>(a) Submitting a material safety data sheet for, or identifying on a list, each element or compound in the mixture which is a hazardous chemical. If more than one mixture has the same element or compound, only one material safety data sheet, or one listing, of the element or compound is necessary; or</para><para>(b) Submitting a material safety data sheet for the mixture itself or identifying the mixture on a list of chemicals.</para><para>(3) Each owner or operator of a facility submitting a list of chemicals under subsection (1) of this section shall, upon request by the committee, submit the material safety data sheet for any chemical on the list to the committee.</para><para>(4) A committee, upon request by any person, shall make available a material safety data sheet to the person in accordance with section 81-15,229. If the committee does not have the requested material safety data sheet, the committee shall request the sheet from the facility owner or operator and then make the sheet available to the person in accordance with section 81-15,229.</para><para>(5) Unless provided prior to September 13, 1997, the initial material safety data sheet or list of chemicals required under this section with respect to a hazardous chemical shall be provided before the later of:</para><para>(a) January 1, 1998; or</para><para>(b) Three months after the owner or operator of a facility is required to prepare or have available a material safety data sheet for the chemical under the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970, 29 U.S.C. 651 et seq., and regulations promulgated under the act.</para><para>(6) Within three months following discovery by an owner or operator of significant new information concerning an aspect of a hazardous chemical for which a material safety data sheet was previously submitted to the committee under subsection (1) of this section, a revised sheet shall be provided to the committee.</para><para>(7) For purposes of this section, hazardous chemical does not include:</para><para>(a) Any food, food additive, color additive, drug, or cosmetic regulated by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</para><para>(b) Any substance present as a solid in any manufactured item to the extent exposure to the substance does not occur under normal conditions of use;</para><para>(c) Any substance to the extent it is used for personal, family, or household purposes or is present in the same form and concentration as a product packaged for distribution and use by the general public;</para><para>(d) Any substance to the extent it is used in a research laboratory or a hospital or other medical facility under the direct supervision of a technically qualified individual; or</para><para>(e) Any substance to the extent it is used in routine agricultural operations or is a fertilizer held for sale by a retailer to the ultimate consumer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 33. </para></source></law></legaldoc>