<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id40" statutenumber="81-12,158"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,158</statuteno><catchline>Financial assistance program to create prototype of certain products; established; funds; match required; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall establish a financial assistance program to provide financial assistance to businesses that employ no more than five hundred employees or to individuals for the purposes of creating a prototype of a product stemming from research and development at a business operating in Nebraska or a public or private college or university in Nebraska.</para><para>(2)(a) Until three months after April 20, 2022, funds shall be matched by nonstate funds equivalent in money equal to fifty percent of the funds requested; and </para><para>(b) Beginning three months after April 20, 2022, funds shall be matched by nonstate funds equivalent in money equal to:</para><para>(i) Twenty-five percent of the funds requested if the applicant's principal residence or principal place of business is located in an economic redevelopment area within a city of the metropolitan class; or</para><para>(ii) Fifty percent of the funds requested for any other applicant.</para><para>(3) Matching funds may be from any nonstate source, including private foundations, federal or local government sources, quasi-governmental entities, or commercial lending institutions, or any other funds whose source does not include funds appropriated by the Legislature.</para><para>(4) The amount the department may provide shall not exceed one hundred fifty thousand dollars per project.</para><para>(5) A business or individual applying for financial assistance under this section shall include a business plan that includes a proof-of-concept demonstration.</para><para>(6) Financial assistance under this section shall be expended within twenty-four months after the date of the awarding decision.</para><para>(7) The department may award up to six million dollars per year for financial assistance under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB387, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB449, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB598, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>April 20, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>