<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id751">
<sectno id="id752">Sec. 78.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id753" statutenumber="81-15,160"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id755">81-15,160</statuteno><catchline id="id756">Waste Reduction
and Recycling Incentive Fund; created; use; investment; grants; restrictions.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Fund is created.
The department shall deduct from the fund amounts sufficient to reimburse
itself for its costs of administration of the fund. The fund shall be administered
by the Department of Environmental Quality. The fund shall consist of proceeds
from the fees imposed pursuant to the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive
Act.</para>
<para>(2) The fund may be used for purposes which include, but
are not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) Technical and financial assistance to political subdivisions
for creation of recycling systems and for modification of present recycling
systems;</para>
<para>(b) Recycling and waste reduction projects, including public
education, planning, and technical assistance;</para>
<para>(c) Market development for recyclable materials separated
by generators, including public education, planning, and technical assistance;</para>
<para>(d) Capital assistance for establishing private and public
intermediate processing facilities for recyclable materials and facilities
using recyclable materials in new products;</para>
<para>(e) Programs which develop and implement composting of yard
waste and composting with sewage sludge;</para>
<para>(f) Technical assistance for waste reduction and waste exchange
for waste generators;</para>
<para>(g) Programs to assist communities and counties to develop
and implement household hazardous waste management programs;</para>
<para>(h) Capital assistance for establishing private and public
facilities to manufacture combustible waste products and to incinerate combustible
waste to generate and recover energy resources, except that no disbursements
shall be made under this section for scrap tire processing related to tire-derived
fuel; and</para>
<para>(i) Grants for reimbursement of costs to cities of the second
class, villages, and counties of five thousand or fewer population for the
deconstruction of abandoned buildings. Eligible deconstruction costs will
be related to the recovery and processing of recyclable or reusable material
from the abandoned buildings.</para>
<para>(3) Grants up to one million dollars annually shall be available
until June 30, 2014, for new scrap tire projects only, if acceptable scrap
tire project applications are received. Eligible categories of disbursement
under section 81-15,161 may include, but are not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) Reimbursement for the purchase of crumb rubber generated
and used in Nebraska, with disbursements not to exceed fifty percent of the
cost of the crumb rubber;</para>
<para>(b) Reimbursement for the purchase of tire-derived product
which utilizes a minimum of twenty-five percent recycled tire content, with
disbursements not to exceed twenty-five percent of the product's retail cost,
except that persons who applied for a grant between June 1, 1999, and May
31, 2001, for the purchase of tire-derived product which utilizes a minimum
of twenty-five percent recycled tire content may apply for reimbursement on
or before July 1, 2002. Reimbursement shall not exceed twenty-five percent
of the product's retail cost and may be funded in fiscal years 2001-02 and
2002-03;</para>
<para>(c) Participation in the capital costs of building, equipment,
and other capital improvement needs or startup costs for scrap tire processing
or manufacturing of tire-derived product, with disbursements not to exceed
fifty percent of such costs or five hundred thousand dollars, whichever is
less;</para>
<para>(d) Participation in the capital costs of building, equipment,
or other startup costs needed to establish collection sites or to collect
and transport scrap tires, with disbursements not to exceed fifty percent
of such costs;</para>
<para>(e) Cost-sharing for the manufacturing of tire-derived product,
with disbursements not to exceed twenty dollars per ton or two hundred fifty
thousand dollars, whichever is less, to any person annually;</para>
<para>(f) Cost-sharing for the processing of scrap tires, with
disbursements not to exceed twenty dollars per ton or two hundred fifty thousand
dollars, whichever is less, to any person annually;</para>
<para>(g) Cost-sharing for the use of scrap tires for civil engineering
applications for specified projects, with disbursements not to exceed twenty
dollars per ton or two hundred fifty thousand dollars, whichever is less,
to any person annually; and</para>
<para>(h) Disbursement to a political subdivision up to one hundred
percent of costs incurred in cleaning up scrap tire collection and disposal
sites.</para>
<para>The director shall give preference to projects which utilize
scrap tires generated and used in Nebraska.</para>
<para>(4) Priority for grants made under section 81-15,161 shall
be given to grant proposals demonstrating a formal public/private partnership
except for grants awarded from fees collected under subsection (6) of section
13-2042.</para>
<para>(5) Grants awarded from fees collected under subsection (6)
of section 13-2042 may be renewed for up to a five-year grant period. Such
applications shall include an updated integrated solid waste management plan
pursuant to section 13-2032. Annual disbursements are subject to available
funds and the grantee meeting established grant conditions. Priority for such
grants shall be given to grant proposals showing regional participation and
programs which address the first integrated solid waste management hierarchy
as stated in section 13-2018 which shall include toxicity reduction. Disbursements
for any one year shall not exceed fifty percent of the total fees collected
after rebates under subsection (6) of section 13-2042 during that year.</para>
<para>(6) Any person who stores waste tires in violation of section
13-2033, which storage is the subject of abatement or cleanup, shall be liable
to the State of Nebraska for the reimbursement of expenses of such abatement
or cleanup paid by the Department of Environmental Quality.</para>
<para>(7) The Department of Environmental Quality may receive gifts,
bequests, and any other contributions for deposit in the Waste Reduction and
Recycling Incentive Fund. Transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any
money in the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive
Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment
officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State
Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 163, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 203, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 444, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1034, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 495, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 592, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 461, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 143, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB568, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB180, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB379, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 78.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>