<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,123"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,123</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Innovation Zone Commission; created; members; meetings; quorum; expenses; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds an opportunity exists to develop high technology business between the Omaha and Lincoln business communities, the university system of the State of Nebraska, including the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the University of Nebraska at Omaha, and the University of Nebraska Medical Center, and Sarpy County, including Offutt Air Force Base. The Legislature further finds that the cities of Lincoln and Omaha are moving toward designation as a single metropolitan statistical area for census purposes, possibly by the federal decennial census. Therefor, an opportunity zone commission should be established for eastern Nebraska.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska Innovation Zone Commission is created. The commission shall consist of the following members:</para><para>(a) Three members appointed by the county board of Douglas County;</para><para>(b) Two members appointed by the county board of Sarpy County;</para><para>(c) Two members appointed by the county board of Lancaster County;</para><para>(d) Two members appointed by the county board of Cass County;</para><para>(e) One member appointed by the county board of Saunders County;</para><para>(f) One member appointed by the county board of Washington County;</para><para>(g) One member appointed by the city council of Omaha;</para><para>(h) One member appointed by the city council of Lincoln;</para><para>(i) One member representing cities of the first class within Douglas, Sarpy, Lancaster, Cass, Saunders, and Washington counties appointed by the other members of the commission;</para><para>(j) One member representing cities of the second class and villages within Douglas, Sarpy, Lancaster, Cass, Saunders, and Washington counties appointed by the other members of the commission;</para><para>(k) One member appointed by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska;</para><para>(l) One member appointed by the community college areas;</para><para>(m) One member appointed by the board of directors of the Papio-Missouri River Natural Resources District; and</para><para>(n) One member appointed by the board of directors of the Lower Platte South Natural Resources District.</para><para>(3) The chairperson and vice-chairperson of the commission shall be elected by a majority of the members of the commission at the first commission meeting and shall each serve a two-year term as chairperson and vice-chairperson, respectively. The commission shall meet at the call of the chairperson or a majority of the members. The chairperson shall call such meetings as he or she determines necessary to fulfill the duties of the commission. A quorum shall be one-half of the members. The members of the commission shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(4) The commission shall carry out the duties set forth in section 81-12,120 as they relate to eastern Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 546, &#167; 7. </para><terminationdate>December 31, 2010</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc>