<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id354"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1414.19"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1414.19</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officers; list on website, when; challenge; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) On or before July 1, 2022, the commission shall post on its public website a list of all law enforcement officers who have, on or after January 1, 2021:</para><para>(a) Voluntarily surrendered their certifications or had their certifications revoked;</para><para>(b) Been convicted of or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to a felony or a Class I misdemeanor; or</para><para>(c) Upon adjudication by the council, been found to have engaged in serious misconduct.</para><para>(2) The list provided for in this section shall be accompanied on the commission's public website by a letter that includes, for each law enforcement officer on such list:</para><para>(a) The officer's name, rank, and the law enforcement agency for which such officer works or most recently worked;</para><para>(b) A statement indicating the reason such officer's name is on the list;</para><para>(c) A description of any discipline imposed; and</para><para>(d) An affirmation, signed by the chief of police, sheriff, or the head administrator of the officer's law enforcement agency or the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety affirming the truth and accuracy of the matters stated in the letter.</para><para>(3) Beginning July 1, 2022, any time a law enforcement officer voluntarily surrenders such officer's certification, has such certification revoked, or is adjudicated by the council to have engaged in serious misconduct, the council shall notify the commission within thirty days after such surrender, revocation, or adjudication.</para><para>(4) By July 1, 2022, the council shall establish a procedure, including an opportunity for a hearing, by which a law enforcement officer may challenge the inclusion of such officer's name on the list.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>