<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,149"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,149</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Assistance Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Clean Water Act means the federal Clean Water Act, as amended, 33 U.S.C. 1251 et seq.;</para><para>(2) Construction means any of the following: Preliminary planning to determine the feasibility of wastewater treatment works or nonpoint source control systems; engineering, architectural, legal, fiscal, or economic investigations or studies; surveys, designs, plans, working drawings, specifications, procedures, or other necessary preliminary actions; erection, building, acquisition, alteration, remodeling, improvement, or extension of wastewater treatment works or nonpoint source control systems; or the inspection or supervision of any of the foregoing items;</para><para>(3) Council means the Environmental Quality Council;</para><para>(4) County means any county authorized to construct a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants pursuant to the County Industrial Sewer Construction Act;</para><para>(5) Department means the Department of Environmental Quality;</para><para>(6) Fund means the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund;</para><para>(7) Municipality means any city, town, village, district, association, or other public body created by or pursuant to state law and having jurisdiction over disposal of sewage, industrial wastes, or other wastes;</para><para>(8) Nonpoint source control systems means projects which establish the use of methods, measures, or practices to control the pollution of surface waters and ground water that occurs as pollutants are transported by water from diffuse or scattered sources. Such projects include, but are not limited to, structural and nonstructural controls and operation and maintenance procedures applied before, during, and after pollution-producing activities. Sources of nonpoint source pollution may include, but are not limited to, agricultural, forestry, and urban lands, transportation corridors, stream channels, mining and construction activities, animal feeding operations, septic tank systems, underground storage tanks, landfills, and atmospheric deposition;</para><para>(9) Operate and maintain means all necessary activities including the normal replacement of equipment or appurtenances to assure the dependable and economical function of a wastewater treatment works or nonpoint source control systems in accordance with its intended purpose; and</para><para>(10) Wastewater treatment works means the structures, equipment, and processes required to collect, transport, and treat domestic or industrial wastes and to dispose of the effluent and sludges.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 766, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 164, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 27. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County Industrial Sewer Construction Act,</emphasis> see section 23-3601.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Banking Act,</emphasis> see section 8-101.01.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>