<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id775"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-1348"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1348</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Suggestion Award Board; created; membership; expenses; rules and regulations; termination.</catchline><para id="id00">There is hereby created the Suggestion Award Board. The membership of such board shall consist of the Director of Personnel, the Director of Administrative Services, the Auditor of Public Accounts or his or her designee, and three persons, each to serve a term of three years, selected and appointed by the Governor from the bargaining units listed in section 81-1373, except that the first three appointments made after February 23, 2000, shall be for terms of one year, two years, and three years, as designated by the Governor. Of the persons selected from such bargaining units, one person shall be selected from each of such bargaining units as follows:</para><para id="id00">(1) The first term from the bargaining units listed in subdivisions (1)(a), (b), and (l) of such section;</para><para id="id00">(2) The second term from the bargaining units listed in subdivisions (1)(c), (d), and (g) of such section;</para><para id="id00">(3) The third term from the bargaining units listed in subdivisions (1)(e), (f), and (h) of such section; and</para><para id="id00">(4) The fourth term from the bargaining units listed in subdivisions (1)(i), (j), and (k) of such section.</para><para id="id00">After the fourth term, the appointments shall be made starting from subdivision (1) of this section and following the same sequence.</para><para id="id00">Whenever a vacancy occurs on the board for any reason, the Governor shall appoint an individual to fill such vacancy from the same bargaining unit in which the vacancy exists.</para><para id="id00">The members shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para id="id00">The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to aid in carrying out sections 81-1350 and 81-1351.</para><para>The Suggestion Award Board terminates on July 1, 2026. This section terminates on July 1, 2026.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 286, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 44, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 395, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB151, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB346, &#167; 52. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>