<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,192"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,192</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature to adopt the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act pursuant to Title III of the Superfund Amendments and Reauthorization Act of 1986, as amended.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds that the release of hazardous and toxic chemicals threatens the health and safety of the public and the environment. The Legislature further finds that increased public knowledge and access to information on the presence of hazardous and toxic chemicals in communities enables the public to work with facilities, communities, state and federal agencies, and governmental bodies to improve chemical safety and protect the health and safety of the public and the environment. The Legislature further finds that the community's right to know is essential in protecting the health and safety of the public and the environment. The Legislature further finds that emergency planning and notification requirements assist the state and local communities in planning for and responding to a release of extremely hazardous substances.</para><para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature that all state agencies involved in emergency release notification, reporting, planning, training, response, and preparedness will coordinate and collaborate in carrying out the purposes of the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act and may, to the extent possible, share resources and funding.</para><para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature that the reporting requirements of the Nebraska Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act are to be no more stringent than the reporting requirements of the Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act pursuant to Title III of the Superfund Amendments and Reauthorization Act of 1986, as amended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 374, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>