<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,104</statuteno><catchline>Fees or surcharges for services; special assessment; failure to pay; effect; Low-Level Radioactive Waste Cash Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall collect fees or surcharges established by the council for radiation protection services provided pursuant to the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal Act and the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact. Services for which fees or surcharges may be established include (a) issuance, amendment, and renewal of licenses for facilities, (b) inspection of licensees, (c) environmental custodial care activities to assess the radiological impact of activities conducted by licensees, (d) certification of personnel to operate the facility, (e) such other activities of department personnel which are reasonably necessary to assure that the licensed facility is being operated in accordance with the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal Act and which reasonably should be borne by the licensee, (f) the budget of the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact Commission pursuant to Article IV, section (h)(2), of the compact, (g) payment by the developer of all reasonable and necessary costs of the local monitoring committees as prescribed in subsection (5) of section 81-15,101.01 until June 30, 1989, or until a site is selected, whichever is later, and (h) payment by the developer of all reasonable and necessary costs of the local monitoring committee where the facility is located as prescribed in subsection (6) of section 81-15,101.01.</para><para>(2) In determining the amount of such fees or surcharges, the council shall set the fees or surcharges in an amount sufficient to reimburse the state for its direct and indirect costs of the services specified in subsection (1) of this section. Any costs incurred by the State of Nebraska that exceed the fees or surcharges collected pursuant to this section shall be recovered through a special assessment against those generators of low-level radioactive waste which used the facility during the previous two years. The director shall compute the amount due from each generator based on the ratio of the fees or surcharges collected from a particular generator during the two-year period to the total fees or surcharges collected from all generators during such two-year period. Any special assessment collected pursuant to this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer who shall credit it to the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Cash Fund. The council shall take into account any special arrangements between the state and a licensee, another state, or a federal agency from which the cost of the service is partially or fully recovered.</para><para>(3) When a licensee fails to pay the applicable fee or surcharge, the department may suspend or revoke the license or may issue an appropriate order.</para><para>(4) Except as provided in subsections (5) and (6) of section 81-15,101.01, any fees or surcharges collected pursuant to this section shall be deposited in the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Cash Fund, which fund is hereby created. The fund shall be administered by the department. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(5) The State Treasurer shall transfer the entire balance in the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Cash Fund, including any investment income credited to the fund, to the General Fund as soon as possible after August 15, 2005.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 426, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1092, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 761, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact,</emphasis> see section 71-3522.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>