<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,129" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,129</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in the Wastewater Treatment Operator Certification Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Certificate shall mean a certificate of competency issued by the director or his or her duly authorized representative certifying that the operator has met the requirements for the specified operator classification of the certification program;</para><para>(2) Council shall mean the Environmental Quality Council;</para><para>(3) Department shall mean the Department of Environment and Energy;</para><para>(4) Director shall mean the Director of Environment and Energy;</para><para>(5) Nationally recognized association of certification authorities shall mean an organization or organizations selected by the director which (a) serve as an information center for certification activities, (b) recommend minimum standards and guidelines for classification of wastewater treatment facilities and certification of operators, (c) facilitate reciprocity between state programs, (d) assist authorities in establishing new certification programs and updating existing ones, and (e) provide testing services;</para><para>(6) Operator shall mean any person who regularly makes recommendations or is responsible for process control decisions at a wastewater treatment facility. Operator shall not include a person whose duties are limited solely to laboratory testing or maintenance or who exercises general or indirect supervision only;</para><para>(7) Voluntarily certified operator shall mean an operator who holds a certificate of competency described in section 81-15,133; and</para><para>(8) Wastewater treatment facility shall mean the structures, equipment, and processes required to collect, transport, and treat domestic or industrial wastes and to dispose of the effluent and sludge.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 533, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 127. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>