<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id16"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1571"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1571</statuteno><catchline>Department of Water, Energy, and Environment; Director of Water, Energy, and Environment; Chief Water Officer; employees of Department of Natural Resources; transfer; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) On and after July 1, 2025, the Department of Natural Resources shall be merged into the Department of Environment and Energy, which shall be renamed as the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment, and the Director of Environment and Energy shall be renamed as the Director of Water, Energy, and Environment. The Director of Natural Resources shall be renamed the Chief Water Officer and retain authorities previously prescribed for the administration of duties of the Department of Natural Resources, except as otherwise provided by law.</para><para>(2) On and after July 1, 2025, positions of employment in the Department of Natural Resources related to the powers, duties, and functions transferred to the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment pursuant to Laws 2025, LB317, are transferred to the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment. For purposes of the transition, employees of the Department of Natural Resources shall be considered employees of the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment and shall retain their rights under the state personnel system or pertinent bargaining agreement, and their service shall be deemed continuous. This section does not grant employees any new rights or benefits not otherwise provided by law or bargaining agreement or preclude the department or the director from exercising any of the prerogatives of management set forth in section 81-1311 or as otherwise provided by law. This section is not an amendment to or substitute for the provisions of any existing bargaining agreements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>