<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id175" statutenumber="81-1430"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1430</statuteno><catchline id="id178">Task force; established; members; terms; duties; quorum; report; Department of Labor; posters.</catchline><para>(1) A task force is hereby established within the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice for the purposes of investigating and studying human trafficking, the methods for advertising human trafficking services, and the victimization of individuals coerced to participate in human trafficking.</para><para>(2) The task force shall examine the extent to which human trafficking is prevalent in this state, the scope of efforts being taken to prevent human trafficking from occurring, and the services available to victims of human trafficking in this state. The task force shall utilize information and research available from the Innocence Lost National Initiative. The task force shall research and recommend a model of rehabilitative services for victims of human trafficking that includes input from the areas of law enforcement, social services, the legal profession, the judiciary, mental health, and immigration. The task force shall also investigate the limitations upon victims who wish to come forward and seek medical attention; investigate the potential to stop human trafficking; and investigate the potential to promote recovery, to protect families and children who may be profoundly impacted by such abuse, and to save lives.</para><para>(3)(a) The Department of Labor shall work with the task force to develop or select informational posters for placement around the state. The posters shall be in English, Spanish, and any other language deemed appropriate by the task force. The posters shall include a toll-free telephone number a person may call for assistance, preferably the National Human Trafficking Resource Center Hotline (888)373-7888.</para><para>(b) Posters shall be placed in rest stops, strip clubs, and casinos. The task force shall work with local businesses and nonprofit entities associated with the prevention of human trafficking to voluntarily place additional signs in high schools, postsecondary educational institutions, gas stations, hotels, hospitals, health care clinics, urgent care centers, airports, train stations, bus stations, and other locations around the state deemed appropriate by the task force.</para><para>(4) The task force shall consist of the following members:</para><para>(a) The Attorney General or his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice;</para><para>(c) The Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety or his or her designee;</para><para>(d) The Director of Correctional Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(e) The chief of police or director of public safety of a city of two hundred thousand inhabitants or more as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census;</para><para>(f) The chief of police or director of public safety of a city of less than two hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census;</para><para>(g) A county sheriff;</para><para>(h) A county attorney;</para><para>(i) A county commissioner;</para><para>(j) A mayor or city manager;</para><para>(k) A person involved with the control or prevention of juvenile delinquency;</para><para>(l) A person involved with the control or prevention of child abuse;</para><para>(m) The Commissioner of Education or his or her designee;</para><para>(n) The director of the Commission on Latino-Americans or his or her designee; and</para><para>(o) Six members, at least three of whom shall be women, from the public at large.</para><para>(5) The Governor shall appoint the members of the task force listed in subdivisions (4)(e) through (l) and (o) of this section for terms as provided in subsection (6) of this section. The membership of the task force shall represent varying geographic areas and large and small political subdivisions. One member from the public at large shall be a professional representing child welfare, and one member of the public at large shall represent juvenile pretrial diversion programs.</para><para>(6) The members of the task force appointed by the Governor shall serve six-year terms, except that of the members first appointed, four shall serve initial two-year terms, four shall serve initial four-year terms, and six shall serve initial six-year terms from January 1 next succeeding their appointments. Thereafter, all members shall serve six-year terms. A member may be reappointed at the expiration of his or her term. Any vacancy occurring otherwise than by expiration of a term shall be filled for the balance of the unexpired term in the same manner as the original appointment.</para><para>(7) No member shall serve beyond the time when he or she holds the office, employment, or status by reason of which he or she was initially eligible for appointment. Any member of the task force appointed by the Governor may be removed from the task force for cause upon notice and an opportunity to be heard at a public hearing. One of the causes for removal shall be absence from three regularly scheduled meetings of the task force during any six-month period when the member has failed to advise the task force in advance of such meeting that he or she will be absent and stating a reason therefor.</para><para>(8) The chairperson of the task force shall be designated by the Governor to serve at the pleasure of the Governor. The chairperson shall be the chief executive officer of the task force but may delegate such of his or her duties to other members of the task force as may be authorized by the task force.</para><para>(9) Notwithstanding any provision of law, ordinance, or charter provision to the contrary, membership on the task force shall not disqualify any member from holding any other public office or employment or cause the forfeiture thereof.</para><para>(10) The members of the task force shall serve on the task force without compensation, but they shall be entitled to receive reimbursement for expenses incurred incident to such service as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(11) Eleven members of the task force shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of any business or the exercise of any power of the task force. The task force shall have the power to act by a majority of the members present at any meeting at which a quorum is in attendance.</para><para>(12) Every July 1 and December 1, the task force shall report electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature the results of its investigation and study and its recommendations, if any, together with drafts of legislation necessary to carry its recommendations into effect by filing the report with the clerk.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1145, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB255, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB461, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>