<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1307"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1307</statuteno><catchline>Director of Personnel; duties.</catchline><para>The Director of Personnel shall be responsible for the administration of the personnel division. Subject to the review powers of the State Personnel Board, the director shall be responsible for development of recommendations on personnel policy and for development of specific administrative systems and shall have the authority to adopt, promulgate, and enforce rules and regulations pertaining thereto. The director shall be responsible for specific administrative systems including, but not limited to, the following:</para><para>(1) Employment Services:</para><para>(a) General employment policies and procedures;</para><para>(b) Position classification plans;</para><para>(c) Job descriptions;</para><para>(d) Job specifications;</para><para>(e) Salary or pay plans;</para><para>(f) Staffing patterns; and</para><para>(g) Recruiting of qualified applicants for employment and the maintenance of qualified applicants for employment for all positions in state government;</para><para>(2) Personnel Records:</para><para>(a) A system of records and statistical reports containing general data on all employees, including current salary levels and such other information as may be required by the operating needs of state departments and agencies and the budget division; and</para><para>(b) Standards for the development and maintenance of personnel records to be maintained within operating departments of the state government;</para><para>(3) Personnel Management:</para><para>(a) Minimum standards for evaluation of employee efficiency and a system of regular evaluation of employee performance;</para><para>(b) Administrative guidelines governing such matters as hours of work, promotions, transfers, demotions, probation, terminations, reductions in force, salary actions, and other such matters as may not be otherwise provided for by law;</para><para>(c) Administrative policies and general procedural instructions for use by all state agencies relating to such matters as employee benefits, vacation, sick leave, holidays, insurance, sickness and accident benefits, and other employee benefits as the Legislature may from time to time prescribe; and</para><para>(d) A system of formally defined relationships between the personnel division and departments and agencies to be covered by the State Personnel System;</para><para>(4) Salary and Wage Survey: Measuring, through the use of surveys, the state's comparative level of employee compensation with the labor market;</para><para>(5) Staffing Patterns:</para><para>(a) Staffing patterns for each department and agency of state government that conform with those authorized by the budget division;</para><para>(b) Revisions to staffing patterns of all departments and agencies that have been approved by the budget division;</para><para>(c) Merit increases provided for any employee of the state that are the result of positive action by the appropriate supervisor; and</para><para>(d) The state's pay plan, as enacted by the Legislature, together with such amendments as may occur, is explained in appropriate handbooks for employees of the state;</para><para>(6) Temporary Employees:</para><para>(a) The director shall administer the Temporary Employee Pool containing applicants from which state agencies can draw when in need of a short-term labor supply; and</para><para>(b) State agencies must receive approval from the director before hiring any temporary employee; and</para><para>(7) Employee Recognition Program: The director shall administer an employee recognition program for state employees. The program shall serve as the authorized program for honoring state employees for dedicated and quality service to the government of the State of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 573, &#167; 7, p. 1891; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 802, &#167; 6, p. 3022; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1030, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 491, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 661, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 14, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 44, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 314, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1162, &#167; 83. </para></source></law></legaldoc>