<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id461"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,245"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,245</statuteno><catchline>Department of Economic Development; use of funds; restrictions; grant applications; priorities.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Economic Development shall use any funds received from the federal Coronavirus Capital Projects Fund under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 as follows:</para><para>(a) No more than thirty-five million dollars to eligible projects that are located within a congressional district which contains a city of the metropolitan class. Within a city of the metropolitan class, grants shall be given to multipurpose community facilities;</para><para>(b) No less than forty million dollars to eligible projects that are located within a congressional district which contains a city of the primary class;</para><para>(c) No less than forty million dollars to eligible projects that are located within a congressional district which does not contain a city of the metropolitan class or a city of the primary class. Grants under this subdivision shall be awarded to eligible projects in cities of the second class and villages; and</para><para>(d) No more than five million dollars of such federal funds for the administration by the department of funds received from the federal Coronavirus Capital Projects Fund under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021.</para><para>(2) Any funds received from the federal Coronavirus Capital Projects Fund under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 utilized for eligible broadband infrastructure projects shall be administered in a manner consistent with the Nebraska Broadband Bridge Act, except that the matching funds requirement in section 86-1304 shall not apply to such federal funding for broadband projects.</para><para>(3) The department shall, beginning July 1, 2022, through July 15, 2022, allow a qualified public or private entity to apply for a grant using funds received from the federal Coronavirus Capital Projects Fund under the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021. The department may open additional grant application periods as needed until all funds are allocated.</para><para>(4) Grants under subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall be restricted to eligible projects in qualified census tracts. Priority for grants under subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall be given to a city of the metropolitan class in partnership with a nonprofit organization for eligible projects for the rehabilitation or expansion of existing multipurpose community facilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1024, &#167; 13. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Broadband Bridge Act,</emphasis> see section 86-1301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>