
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1637"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1637</statuteno><catchline>Predisbursement plan; contents; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Governor shall submit electronically a predisbursement plan to the Legislature if in session or the Executive Board of the Legislative Council if the Legislature is not in session.</para><para>(2) The predisbursement plan shall generally outline the uses and beneficiaries of proposed disbursements from the fund, as well as the expected benefits to the state as a whole.</para><para>(3) The predisbursement plan shall also include a policy statement which shall indicate (a) a perception of the current and anticipated trends regarding energy availability, costs, and needs in the state, (b) assumptions regarding the impacts on energy needs of the state of current and anticipated state and federal policies and market forces affecting energy use, and (c) generally, how the types of projects to be selected will address those trends and assumptions.</para><para>(4) The Legislature may hold a public hearing within thirty days after receipt of the predisbursement plan to solicit testimony on such plan. The Legislature may, no later than fifteen days following such hearing, make recommendations to the Department of Environment and Energy concerning the plan. No disbursement of or obligation to disburse any money in the fund shall be made after July 9, 1988, until forty-five days after the predisbursement plan referring to such disbursement has been submitted to the Legislature or the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, as the case may be.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 683, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 764, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 207; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 169. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>