<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1201.11"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1201.11</statuteno><catchline>Department; lead agency; clearinghouse;
staff services; coordination; status report; duties.</catchline><para>The
department shall:</para>
<para>(1) Serve as the lead state agency in the area of economic development.
The department shall develop a program to promote coordination and cooperation
within state government and with institutions of higher education, local governments,
other political subdivisions of the state, and the private sector;</para>
<para>(2) Serve as a clearinghouse for information, data, and other materials
which may be helpful or necessary to the full development of the state's economy,
which may be relevant with regard to the possibilities of future development
in Nebraska, and which will be of use to local governments, the Governor,
other state agencies, and the Legislature in discharging their responsibilities.
The department shall develop a program to ensure cooperation between state
agencies, the University of Nebraska, and other entities with related economic
information;</para>
<para>(3) Provide staff services when, in the opinion of the director, such
services are necessary and appropriate in the areas of economic development
to cities of the first class, cities
of the second class, and villages on a contractual basis when
the terms of such contracts can be mutually accepted;</para>
<para>(4) Assist the Governor in coordinating the efforts of local governments
to develop mutual and cooperative solutions to their common problems; and</para>
<para>(5) Prepare annually a status report on the activities and impacts of
the department and its programs. The status report shall include information
detailing the status of all programs administered by the department for which
the Legislature requires reporting. The status report shall be submitted to
the Governor and the Legislature on the first working day of July of each
year. The report submitted
to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 965, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB404, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 192.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>