<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id27">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id29" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-1210.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1210.02</statuteno><catchline id="id32">Interns; grants; internships;
application; certification; department; powers
and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The intent of sections
81-1210.01 to 81-1210.03 is to provide students with
valuable internship opportunities in order to retain such students
and attract workers to Nebraska by assisting Nebraska
businesses willing to provide paid internships.</para>
<para>(2) A business may
apply to the department for a grant to assist in providing
a student an internship if:</para>
<para>(a) The business certifies that the
internship meets the definition of internship in section 81-1210.01;</para>
<para>(b) The business will pay the student at
least the federal minimum hourly wage for the internship;</para>
<para>(c) The internship
will be completed within the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(d) The internship will
be completed within a period of no more than twelve months; and</para>
<para>(e) The internship
will be for a duration sufficient to allow the student to gain significant
valuable work experience and knowledge.</para><para>(3)
The department may provide grants
for internships in the following amounts:</para>
<para>(a) If the student receiving the internship
is a Federal Pell Grant recipient at the time of grant application, the grant
may be up to the lesser of seventy-five percent of the cost of the internship
or seven thousand five hundred dollars. The business applying for the grant
shall provide the department with documentation to prove that the student
is a Federal Pell Grant recipient; and</para>
<para>(b) For all other students, the grant
may be up to the lesser of seventy-five percent of the
cost of the internship or five thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(4) A business may
apply for no more than two grants for the same student, shall not be awarded
more than five grants
at any one location in any twelve-month period, and shall not be awarded more
than ten grants
total in any twelve-month period.</para>
<para>(5) A business may
allow a student to telecommute if
the business is located more than
thirty miles from the college, university, or other institution of higher education in
which the student is enrolled and if
the college, university, or other institution of higher education is
in Nebraska.</para>
<para>(6) The department shall, to the extent possible, assure that
the distribution of grants
under sections 81-1210.01 to 81-1210.03 provides equitable access to the grants
by all geographic areas of the state.</para>
<para>(7) The department
shall, to the extent possible, assure that the grants awarded pursuant to
sections 81-1210.01 to 81-1210.03 are for internships which provide valuable
learning opportunities for students who will be seeking employment in a professional
or technical field.</para><para>(8) The
department shall not allocate more than one million five hundred thousand
dollars in any
one fiscal year from the Job Training Cash Fund or its subaccounts for purposes of this section.
The department may receive funds from public, private, or other sources for
purposes of this section.</para>
<para>(9) The department
shall develop a qualified action plan by January 1 of each even-numbered year.
The plan shall, at a minimum, set forth the department's priorities and selection
criteria for awarding grants for internships. In order to encourage students
from across Nebraska to pursue internships, the plan shall also include strategies
for affirmatively marketing internships to Nebraska students in high schools,
colleges, universities, and other institutions of higher education in Nebraska.
Such strategies shall place an emphasis on marketing to underserved student
populations as defined by the department in the plan. The department shall
submit the plan to the Governor for approval.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB386, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB476, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>