
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id96"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1461"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1461</statuteno><catchline>Incentive payments; application; eligibility; tiers.</catchline><para>(1) The council shall accept applications for retention incentive payments from individual law enforcement officers in Nebraska.</para><para>(2) To be eligible for a tier 1 retention incentive payment, a law enforcement officer must complete twelve months of full-time employment as a law enforcement officer after July 1, 2022. No law enforcement officer shall receive more than one tier 1 retention incentive payment.</para><para>(3) To be eligible for a tier 2 retention incentive payment, a law enforcement officer must complete three years of full-time employment as a law enforcement officer after July 1, 2022. No law enforcement officer shall receive more than one tier 2 retention incentive payment.</para><para>(4) To be eligible for a tier 3 retention incentive payment, a law enforcement officer must complete five years of full-time employment as a law enforcement officer after July 1, 2022. No law enforcement officer shall receive more than one tier 3 retention incentive payment.</para><para>(5) Full-time law enforcement officers employed by a law enforcement agency that employs more than seventy-five full-time law enforcement officers shall only be eligible for a tier 1 retention incentive payment, and such payment shall be seven hundred fifty dollars.</para><para>(6) For full-time law enforcement officers employed by a law enforcement agency that employs seventy-five or fewer full-time law enforcement officers:</para><para>(a) The tier 1 retention incentive payment shall be one thousand five hundred dollars;</para><para>(b) The tier 2 retention incentive payment shall be two thousand five hundred dollars; and</para><para>(c) The tier 3 retention incentive payment shall be three thousand dollars.</para><para>(7) A law enforcement officer shall not be eligible for a tier 1, tier 2, or tier 3 retention incentive payment under this section if:</para><para>(a) Such law enforcement officer's certification has ever been revoked;</para><para>(b) Such law enforcement officer has ever been convicted of a felony or Class I misdemeanor. This subdivision shall not apply if the law enforcement officer received a pardon or set aside for such conviction;</para><para>(c) Such law enforcement officer has ever been adjudicated by the council to have engaged in serious misconduct, as such term is defined in section 81-1401; or</para><para>(d) Such law enforcement officer was allowed to resign instead of being terminated from employment. This subdivision shall only apply if the law enforcement officer's certification would have been revoked had he or she not resigned.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1241, &#167; 8. </para><terminationdate>June 30, 2028</terminationdate></source></law>
</legaldoc>