<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1850" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1850</statuteno><catchline>County attorney; Board of Parole; Department of Correctional Services; county corrections agency; Department of Health and Human Services; duties; notification of victim.</catchline><para>(1) Upon request of the victim and at the time of conviction of the offender, the county attorney of the jurisdiction in which a person is convicted of a felony shall forward to the Board of Parole, the Department of Correctional Services, the county corrections agency, or the Department of Health and Human Services the name and address of any victim, as defined in section 29-119, of the convicted person. The board, the Department of Correctional Services, the county corrections agency, or the Department of Health and Human Services shall include the name in the file of the convicted person, but the name shall not be part of the public record of any parole hearings of the convicted person. Any victim, including a victim who has waived his or her right to notification at the time of conviction, may request the notification prescribed in this section, as applicable, by sending a written request to the board, the Department of Correctional Services, the county corrections agency, or the Department of Health and Human Services any time after the convicted person is incarcerated and until the convicted person is no longer under the jurisdiction of the board, the county corrections agency, or the Department of Correctional Services or, if the person is under the jurisdiction of the Department of Health and Human Services, within the three-year period after the convicted person is no longer under the jurisdiction of the board, the county corrections agency, or the Department of Correctional Services.</para><para>(2) A victim whose name appears in the file of the convicted person shall be notified by the Board of Parole:</para><para>(a) Within ninety days after conviction of an offender, of the tentative date of release and the earliest parole eligibility date of such offender;</para><para>(b) Of any parole hearings or proceedings;</para><para>(c) Of any decision of the Board of Parole;</para><para>(d) When a convicted person who is on parole is returned to custody because of parole violations; and</para><para>(e) If the convicted person has been adjudged a mentally disordered sex offender or is a convicted sex offender, when such person is released from custody or treatment.</para><para>Such notification shall be given in person, by telecommunication, or by mail.</para><para>(3) A victim whose name appears in the file of the convicted person shall be notified by the Department of Correctional Services or a county corrections agency:</para><para>(a) When a convicted person is granted a furlough or release from incarceration for twenty-four hours or longer or any transfer of the convicted person to community status;</para><para>(b) When a convicted person is released into community-based programs, including educational release and work release programs. Such notification shall occur at the beginning and termination of any such program;</para><para>(c) When a convicted person escapes or does not return from a granted furlough or release and again when the convicted person is returned into custody;</para><para>(d) When a convicted person is discharged from custody upon completion of his or her sentence. Such notice shall be given at least thirty days before discharge, when practicable;</para><para>(e) Of the (i) department's calculation of the earliest parole eligibility date of the prisoner with all potential good time or disciplinary credits considered if the sentence exceeds ninety days or (ii) county corrections agency's calculation of the earliest release date of the prisoner. The victim may request one notice of the calculation described in this subdivision. Such information shall be mailed not later than thirty days after receipt of the request;</para><para>(f) Of any reduction in the prisoner's minimum sentence; and</para><para>(g) Of the victim's right to submit a statement as provided in section 81-1848.</para><para>(4) A victim whose name appears in the file of a convicted person shall be notified by the Department of Health and Human Services:</para><para>(a) When a person convicted of an offense listed in subsection (5) of this section becomes the subject of a petition pursuant to the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act or the Sex Offender Commitment Act prior to his or her discharge from custody upon the completion of his or her sentence or within thirty days after such discharge. The county attorney who filed the petition shall notify the Department of Correctional Services of such petition. The Department of Correctional Services shall forward the names and addresses of victims appearing in the file of the convicted person to the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(b) When a person under a mental health board commitment pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection escapes from an inpatient facility providing board-ordered treatment and again when the person is returned to an inpatient facility;</para><para>(c) When a person under a mental health board commitment pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection is discharged or has a change in disposition from inpatient board-ordered treatment;</para><para>(d) When a person under a mental health board commitment pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection is granted a furlough or release for twenty-four hours or longer; and</para><para>(e) When a person under a mental health board commitment pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection is released into educational release programs or work release programs. Such notification shall occur at the beginning and termination of any such program.</para><para>(5) Subsection (4) of this section applies to persons convicted of at least one of the following offenses which is also alleged to be the recent act or threat underlying the commitment of such persons as mentally ill and dangerous or as dangerous sex offenders as defined in section 83-174.01:</para><para>(a) Murder in the first degree pursuant to section 28-303;</para><para>(b) Murder in the second degree pursuant to section 28-304;</para><para>(c) Kidnapping pursuant to section 28-313;</para><para>(d) Assault in the first degree pursuant to section 28-308;</para><para>(e) Assault in the second degree pursuant to section 28-309;</para><para>(f) Sexual assault in the first degree pursuant to section 28-319;</para><para>(g) Sexual assault in the second degree pursuant to section 28-320;</para><para>(h) Sexual assault of a child in the first degree pursuant to section 28-319.01; </para><para>(i) Sexual assault of a child in the second or third degree pursuant to section 28-320.01;</para><para>(j) Stalking pursuant to section 28-311.03; or</para><para>(k) An attempt, solicitation, or conspiracy to commit an offense listed in subdivisions (a) through (j) of this subsection.</para><para>(6) A victim whose name appears in the file of a convicted person shall be notified by the Board of Pardons:</para><para>(a) Of any pardon or commutation proceedings; and</para><para>(b) If a pardon or commutation has been granted.</para><para>(7) The Board of Parole, the Department of Correctional Services, the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Board of Pardons shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as needed to carry out this section.</para><para>(8) The victim's address and telephone number maintained by the Department of Correctional Services, the Department of Health and Human Services, the county corrections agency, or the Board of Parole pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall be exempt from disclosure under public records laws and federal freedom of information laws, as such laws existed on January 1, 2004.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 186, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 523, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 325, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 270, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 127; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 85.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-901.</para><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>