<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id30" statutenumber="81-12,148"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,148</statuteno><catchline>Entities eligible to receive assistance; matching funds; requirements; applicability of section.</catchline><para>(1) Governmental subdivisions and Nebraska nonprofit organizations are eligible to receive assistance under the Site and Building Development Act. Any entity receiving assistance under subsection (1) of section 81-12,147 shall provide, or cause to be provided, matching funds for the eligible activity in an amount determined by the Department of Economic Development, which amount shall be at least equal to one hundred percent of the amount of assistance provided by the Site and Building Development Fund. Nothing in the act shall be construed to allow individuals or businesses to receive direct loans from the fund.</para><para>(2) An applicant for a grant for development of a public-private-partnership facility under subdivision (1)(h) of section 81-12,147 shall provide the Director of Economic Development with a letter of support from the United States Strategic Command prior to approval of the application and with proof of the availability of twenty million dollars in private or other funds for the facility. No funds shall be expended or grants awarded until receipt of proof of the availability of twenty million dollars in private or other funds for the facility and certification is provided by the Director of Economic Development to the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(3) This section does not apply to any inland port authority receiving assistance under subsection (2) of section 81-12,147.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB388, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB156, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>