<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,268"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,268</statuteno><catchline>Swimming pools; inspection; records; classification; plans and specifications; fees; disposition; exception; existing rules, regulations, licenses, permits, forms of approval, suits, other proceedings; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall make at least one inspection every year of each swimming pool to determine that such swimming pool complies with the minimum sanitary and safety requirements.</para><para>(2) The owner and operator of any swimming pool shall submit such operation and analytical records as may be requested at any time by the department to determine the sanitary and safety condition of the swimming pool.</para><para>(3) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations which classify swimming pools on the basis of criteria deemed appropriate by the department. The department shall charge engineering firms, swimming pool owners, and other appropriate parties fees established by rules and regulations for the review of plans and specifications of a swimming pool, the issuance of a license or permit, the inspection of a swimming pool, and any other services rendered at a rate which defrays no more than the actual cost of the services provided. All fees shall be paid as a condition of annual renewal of licensure or of continuance of licensure. Fees collected under this subsection for the review of plans and specifications shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Engineering Plan Review Cash Fund. All other fees collected under this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Environmental Safety Cash Fund. The department shall not charge a municipal corporation an inspection fee for an inspection of a swimming pool owned by such municipal corporation.</para><para>(4) The department shall establish and collect fees for certificates of competency for swimming pool operators. All fees collected under this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Environmental Safety Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) All rules and regulations adopted prior to July 1, 2021, under sections 81-15,264 to 81-15,270, as such sections existed prior to such date, shall continue to be effective to the extent not in conflict with the changes made by Laws 2021, LB148, until amended or repealed by the department.</para><para>(6) All licenses, permits, or other forms of approval issued prior to July 1, 2021, in accordance with sections 81-15,264 to 81-15,270, as such sections existed prior to such date, shall remain valid as issued for purposes of the changes made by Laws 2021, LB148, unless revoked or otherwise terminated by law.</para><para>(7) Any suit, action, or other proceeding, judicial or administrative, which was lawfully commenced prior to July 1, 2021, under sections 81-15,264 to 81-15,270, as such sections existed prior to such date, shall be subject to the provisions of such sections as they existed prior to July 1, 2021.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 760, &#167; 5, p. 2876; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 583, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 440, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 812, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1047, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 672; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 583; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1217; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2018), &#167; 71-4305; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>