<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id5" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-1801.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1801.02</statuteno><catchline>Community Trust; authorized; powers
and duties; create separate funds; distribution committee.</catchline><para>(1) A nonprofit organization,
to be known as the Community Trust, may be created. After a tragedy, the Community
Trust shall accept contributions from the public, manage such funds, and make
distributions to help individuals, families, and communities in Nebraska who
have suffered from a tragedy of violence or natural disaster. The committee
shall oversee the Community Trust. The committee shall require at least annual
reports from the Community Trust.</para>
<para>(2) The Community
Trust shall be a qualified organization under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal
Revenue Code thereby enabling contributions to the Community Trust to be tax
deductible for the donor if the donor itemizes deductions for income tax purposes
and distributions to be tax-free to the extent allowed under applicable sections
of the Internal Revenue Code. The Community Trust shall create a separate
fund for each tragedy and shall begin accepting contributions immediately
after a tragedy. A report of distributions shall be made within two weeks
after the distribution, and contributions shall be acknowledged within two
weeks after receipt.</para><para>(3) The procedures for applications, hearings, and compensation orders
for victims shall follow the procedures in the Nebraska Crime Victim's Reparations
Act, as applicable, unless the board of directors of the Community Trust creates
an alternative procedure. In any alternative procedure, the Community Trust
shall establish a distribution committee for the tragedy within one week after
the tragedy, establish eligible recipient criteria and eligible uses of the
fund, begin initial distribution of the fund within three weeks after the
tragedy, make subsequent distributions within three months after the tragedy,
and complete all distributions within six months after the tragedy.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB598, &#167;  1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>