<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id686" statutenumber="81-1201.22"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1201.22</statuteno><catchline id="id689">Administrative
Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby
created the Administrative Cash Fund to be administered by the department.
Revenue from the following sources shall be remitted to the State Treasurer
for credit to the fund:</para>
<para>(a) Fees charged for the sale of department publications or subscription
to publications;</para>
<para>(b) Fees charged for the sale of Nebraska items promoting economic development
of the state;</para>
<para>(c) Deposits charged for the temporary use of Nebraska items promoting
economic development of the state;</para>
<para>(d) Fees charged for attendance and participation in department-sponsored
conferences, training sessions, and other special events;</para>
<para>(e) Money collected from nondepartment sources in connection with cooperative
funding of advertising, marketing, promotional, or consulting activities;
and</para>
<para>(f) Money received by the department in the form of gifts, grants, reimbursements,
or appropriations from any source intended to be used by the department for
carrying out the provisions of Chapter 81, article 12.</para>
<para>(2) Revenue from the fund may be expended for the following purposes:</para>
<para>(a) Production and distribution costs of department publications;</para>
<para>(b) Purchase of items promoting economic development of the state intended
for sale;</para>
<para>(c) Reimbursement of deposits collected for the temporary use of promotional
items;</para>
<para>(d) Payment of costs in connection with department-sponsored conferences,
training sessions, and other special events;</para>
<para>(e) Payment of costs of advertising, marketing, promotional, or consulting
activities in cooperative funding partnerships with nondepartment organizations;
and</para>
<para>(f) Payment of costs for which fund revenue has been received and which
are related to department activities in Chapter 81, article 12.</para>
<para>(3) Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction
of the Legislature. Any money in the Administrative Cash Fund available for
investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the
Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1194, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1053, &#167; 28.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>