<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id847"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,313"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,313</statuteno><catchline>Home Weatherization Clearinghouse; established; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature hereby finds and declares that Nebraska is experiencing a persistent and present crisis in regards to affordable quality housing, as evidenced by lower inventory than required to support and sustain a healthy housing market. Housing inventory and availability are critical elements in population attraction and retention, workforce development, economic development, and individual family health and economic self-sufficiency. In addition to housing inventory and the availability of homes, another factor that may hinder population attraction is the quality of homes. One measurement of housing quality is age. As such, Nebraska must streamline and maximize all existing housing, weatherization, and home improvement programs to expand access to affordable quality homes and renovate and modernize existing aging housing inventory to meet modern standards.</para><para>(2) The Home Weatherization Clearinghouse is established within the Department of Environment and Energy.</para><para>(3) The clearinghouse shall:</para><para>(a) Establish a hub for information about the availability and application processes of and eligibility for grants, loans, or other programs that fund home weatherization projects, whether administered by the department, other state or local agencies, nonprofit organizations, or the federal government; and</para><para>(b) Assist in coordination efforts by state and local agencies to optimize the execution of home weatherization projects.</para><para>(4) The Department of Environment and Energy shall utilize existing staff to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB36, &#167; 18. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>