<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id378">
<sectno id="id379">Sec. 40.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id380" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-1450"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1450</statuteno><catchline>Office of Violence Prevention; director;
administration and supervision; responsibilities; advisory council; meetings;
duties.</catchline><para>(1)
The Office of Violence Prevention and its director shall be administered and
supervised, respectively, by the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and
Criminal Justice. Among its responsibilities, the Office of Violence Prevention
and its director shall be responsible for developing, fostering, promoting,
and assessing violence prevention programs. To accomplish this mission, the
duties of the director shall include, but not be limited to, program fundraising,
program evaluation, coordination of programs, and assistance with the administration
and distribution of funds to violence prevention programs.</para>
<para>(2) The advisory
council to the Office of Violence Prevention shall meet at least quarterly.
Among its responsibilities, the advisory council shall recommend to the commission
rules and regulations regarding program fundraising, program evaluation, coordination
of programs, and the criteria used to assess and award funds to violence prevention
programs. Priority for funding shall be given to communities and organizations
seeking to implement violence prevention programs which appear to have the
greatest benefit to the state and which have, as goals, the reduction of street
and gang violence and the reduction of homicides and injuries caused by firearms.
The duties of the advisory council shall include, but not be limited to, receiving
applications for violence prevention funds, evaluating such applications,
and making recommendations to the commission regarding the merits of each
application and the amount of any funds that should be awarded. If any funds
are awarded to a violence prevention program, the advisory council shall continuously
monitor how such funds are being used by the program, conduct periodic evaluations
of such programs, assess the progress and success regarding the stated goals
of each program awarded funds, and recommend to the commission any modification,
continuation, or discontinuation of funding.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 40.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>