<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,174.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,174.01</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund is created. The fund shall be used to carry out the purposes of the Nebraska Environmental Trust Act. The fund shall include proceeds designated by the board pursuant to section 81-15,173, including grants from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund. Grants from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund to the Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund shall be no more than twice the total of any other proceeds received by the Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund for the same year. Such grants, considered in the aggregate, shall in no case exceed fifty percent of the total proceeds credited to the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund pursuant to section 9-812 for that year.</para><para>Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>Allocations received by the Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund shall not be reallocated by the board, but shall remain invested. Any interest income earned by the Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund shall be available for allocation by the board as provided in section 81-15,175.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 957, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>