<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1201.18"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1201.18</statuteno><catchline>Department; administer Community
Development Block Grant Program.</catchline><para>The department shall administer
the Community Development Block Grant Program. In addition to the performance
review requirements in section 81-1201.10, the department shall develop an
ongoing program of monitoring the impact of grants on the communities receiving
the grants. The monitoring program shall include, but not be limited to, the
following information: (1) The status of the project for which such grant
was awarded; (2) the grant amount; (3) the local government contribution;
(4) the private financial contribution; (5) the goals and objectives of the
grant; and (6) the impact of the grant relative to the goals and objectives
of the grant. The department, in consultation with the commission, shall determine community development
objectives, state priorities, and guidelines for the distribution of funds
for community development projects within the Community Development Block
Grant Program, which shall conform to the objectives as set forth in the Housing
and Community Development Act of 1974, as amended, and which shall:</para>
<para>(a) Include statistical community need factors as selected by the commission; and</para>
<para>(b) Require that grant applicants submit evidence of a community assessment
process for the project, which assessment process the commission shall
design. To the extent possible, the Community Development Block Grant funds
shall be allocated on a need and competitive basis.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 965, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 639, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB947, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>