<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1201.13"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1201.13</statuteno><catchline>Travel and Tourism Division; duties; awarding of contracts.</catchline><para>The Travel and Tourism Division shall develop a program to provide promotional services and technical assistance to local governments and industry members and to ensure the protection and development of Nebraska's attraction resources. The department shall have an advisory committee to provide regular consultation to the Travel and Tourism Division.</para><para>All advertising contracts awarded by the department concerning travel and tourism shall be based on competitive bids. Contracts shall be awarded to the lowest responsible bidder, taking into consideration the best interests of the state, the quality of performance of the services rendered, the conformity with specifications, the purposes for which required, and the time of completion, and with the consultation of the Travel and Tourism Division Advisory Committee. In determining the lowest responsible bidder, in addition to price, the following elements shall be given consideration: (1) The ability, capacity, creativity, and skill of the bidder to perform the contract required; (2) the character, integrity, reputation, judgment, experience, and efficiency of the bidder; (3) whether the bidder can perform the contract within the time specified; (4) the quality of performance of previous contracts; (5) the previous and existing compliance by the bidder with laws relating to the contract; and (6) such other information as may be secured having a bearing on the decision to award the contract. The department shall advertise for bids for the awarding of contracts concerning travel and tourism pursuant to sections 73-101 to 73-105. At least thirty working days shall elapse between the time formal bids are advertised for and the time of their opening. Contracts shall be awarded within sixty working days after the bidding has been closed. Each person submitting a bid shall, by certified mail, be notified as to whom the contract was awarded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 965, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc>