<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1108.38"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1108.38</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Capitol Commission; duties; powers.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be the duty of the Nebraska Capitol Commission to provide advice to the Office of the Nebraska Capitol Commission in carrying out this section. The office shall (a) establish policies and guidelines for the implementation of the approved Capitol Landscape Restoration Master Plan on and around the capitol grounds, (b) participate with the commission created pursuant to section 90-306 to (i) formulate a landscape restoration plan for all other state-owned property within the Nebraska State Capitol Environs District and (ii) conserve, protect, and enhance the environs and vistas of the State Capitol, and (c) review the proposed construction and repairs of buildings in and around the State Capitol and all other state-owned property located within the Nebraska State Capitol Environs District. The office, with the advice of the Nebraska Capitol Commission, may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this subsection.</para><para>(2) The commission shall hold meetings on a quarterly basis or as needed. The commission shall meet at least annually with the Nebraska State Capitol Environs Commission to discuss and coordinate projects that may impact the capitol and its environs. The meeting with the Nebraska State Capitol Environs Commission may be held in conjunction with one of the meetings of the Nebraska Capitol Commission required by this subsection.</para><para>(3) In addition to any other rights and powers conferred upon the commission, it shall monitor and advise the State Building Administrator in exercising the power of eminent domain on behalf of the state for the purpose of acquiring sites or buildings for state use. The administrator may for such purpose take, hold, and condemn for the state any and all necessary property. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-701 to 76-726.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 211, &#167; 3, p. 601; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 279, &#167; 1, p. 883; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 440, &#167; 2, p. 1397; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 469, &#167; 1, p. 1462; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 72-718; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1048, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 311, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 297, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 26. </para></source></law></legaldoc>