<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1239"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1239</statuteno><catchline>Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund; created; use; investment; subaccount; purpose; return of grant funds; when required.</catchline><para>(1) The Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund is created. Funding for the grant program described in section 81-1238 shall come from the Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund. The Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund may include revenue from appropriations from the Legislature, grants, private contributions, and other sources. Any money in the Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) The department shall establish a subaccount within the Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund that shall be used to fund affordable housing and related land parcel preparation activities under the Economic Recovery Act as described in subdivisions (4)(e) and (4)(f) of section 81-12,241.</para><para>(3) The department shall administer the Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund and may seek additional private or nonstate funds to use in the grant program, including, but not limited to, contributions from the Nebraska Investment Finance Authority and other interested parties.</para><para>(4) Interest earned by the department on grant funds shall be applied to the grant program.</para><para>(5) If a nonprofit development organization, or a recipient of subaccount funds described in subsection (2) of this section, fails to engage in a qualified activity within twenty-four months after receiving initial grant funding, the nonprofit development organization or recipient of subaccount funds shall return the grant proceeds to the department for credit to the General Fund.</para><para>(6) Beginning July 1, 2029, any funds held by the department in the Middle Income Workforce Housing Investment Fund shall be transferred to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB866, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1024, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1069, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB531, &#167; 34. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Economic Recovery Act,</emphasis> see section 81-12,238.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>