<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id236">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id238" statutenumber="81-1371"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1371</statuteno><catchline id="id241">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the State Employees Collective Bargaining
Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Chief Negotiator shall mean the Chief Negotiator of the
Division of Employee Relations of the Department of Administrative Services;</para>
<para>(2) Commission shall mean the Commission of Industrial Relations;</para>
<para>(3) Division shall mean the Division of Employee Relations
of the Department of Administrative Services;</para>
<para>(4) Employee or state employee shall mean any employee of
the State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(5) Employer or state employer shall mean the State of Nebraska
and shall not include any political subdivision thereof;</para>
<para>(6) Employer-representative shall mean (a) for negotiations
involving employees of the University of Nebraska, the Board of Regents, (b)
for negotiations involving employees of the Nebraska state colleges, the Board
of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, (c) for negotiations involving
employees of other constitutional agencies, the governing officer or body
for each such agency, and (d) for negotiations involving other state employees,
the Governor;</para>
<para>(7) Grievance shall mean a management action resulting in
an injury, injustice, or wrong involving a misinterpretation or misapplication
of applicable labor contracts if so agreed to by the appropriate parties;</para>
<para>(8) Issue shall mean broad subjects of negotiation which
are presented to the commission pursuant
to section 81-1382. All aspects of wages shall be a single issue, all aspects
of insurance shall be a single issue, and all other subjects of negotiations
classified in broad categories shall be single issues;</para>
<para>(9) Mandatory topic or topics of bargaining shall mean those
subjects of negotiation on which employers must negotiate pursuant to the
Industrial Relations Act, including terms and conditions of employment which
may otherwise be provided by law for state employees, except when specifically
prohibited by law from being a subject of bargaining; and</para>
<para>(10) Meet-and-confer rights shall mean the rights of employees
to discuss wages, hours, and other terms and conditions of employment with
the appropriate employer-representative but shall not require either party
to enter into a written agreement. Employees afforded meet-and-confer rights
shall not be entitled to utilize the impasse resolution procedures provided
in the State Employees Collective Bargaining Act or to file a petition with
the commission invoking its jurisdiction as provided in the Industrial Relations
Act for the purpose of obtaining an order or orders under section 48-818.
Meet-and-confer rights shall not apply to any bargaining unit other than a
supervisory unit.</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 661, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 14, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB397, &#167; 20.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Industrial Relations Act,</emphasis> see section 48-801.01.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
