<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id183"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1573"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1573</statuteno><catchline>References to Department of Natural Resources or Department of Environment and Energy in contracts or other documents; how construed; contracts and records; how treated.</catchline><para>On and after July 1, 2025, whenever the Department of Natural Resources or the Department of Environment and Energy is referred to or designated by any contract or other document in connection with the duties and functions of the Department of Natural Resources or the Department of Environment and Energy as such departments existed prior to July 1, 2025, such reference or designation shall apply to the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment or the Chief Water Officer, as determined by the duties and functions assigned to each in statute. All contracts entered into by the Department of Natural Resources or the Department of Environment and Energy prior to July 1, 2025, in connection with the duties and functions of the Department of Natural Resources or the Department of Environment and Energy as such departments existed prior to July 1, 2025, are hereby recognized, with the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment or the Chief Water Officer, as determined by the duties and functions assigned to each in statute, succeeding to all rights and obligations under such contracts. Any cash funds, custodial funds, gifts, trusts, grants, and appropriations of funds from prior fiscal years available to satisfy obligations incurred under such contracts shall be transferred and appropriated to such department or the Chief Water Officer for the payment of such obligations. All documents and records transferred, or copies of the same, may be authenticated or certified by such department or the Chief Water Officer for all legal purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>