<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-1121"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1121</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Warrants; preparation and issuance; funds transfer systems; payment by mistake; adjustment.</catchline><para id="id00">(1)(a) The Director of Administrative Services shall have power to develop and implement a system of warrant preparation and issuance in accordance with acceptable accounting and internal control safeguards and by use of such mechanical means as may be most economical.</para><para id="id00">(b) Warrant or state warrant shall include an order drawn by the director upon the State Treasurer, directing the latter to pay a specified amount to a specified payee by the use of a dual signature negotiable instrument as provided for in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, electronic funds transfer system, telephonic funds transfer system, electric funds transfer system, funds transfers as provided for in article 4A, Uniform Commercial Code, mechanical funds transfer system, or other funds transfer system established by the director and the State Treasurer. The warrant, when it is an order drawn by the director upon the State Treasurer directing the latter to pay a specified amount to a specified payee by the use of a dual signature negotiable instrument as provided for in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, shall affect the state's cash balance in the bank when redeemed by the State Treasurer, not when cashed by a financial institution.</para><para id="id00">(2) The director shall sign each warrant or shall cause each warrant to be signed in his or her behalf either personally, by delegation of authority, or by facsimile signature as will assure the most economical, timely, and practical means for making payments from the state treasury and which means provides the most acceptable safeguarding of public funds. The signature of the director shall signify that the payment intended by a warrant bearing such signature is proper under the appropriate laws of the state.</para><para id="id00">(3) The State Treasurer shall countersign all warrants issued by the director.</para><para id="id00">(4) The State Treasurer shall make such arrangements for facsimile signature of warrants as will assure the most economical, timely, and practical means for making payments from the state treasury.</para><para id="id00">(5) The director and the State Treasurer may establish and operate an electronic funds transfer system, telephonic funds transfer system, electric funds transfer system, funds transfers as provided for in article 4A, Uniform Commercial Code, mechanical funds transfer system, or other funds transfer system established by the director and the State Treasurer for the payment of funds from and the deposit of receipts into the state treasury. Any state agency that wishes to establish and operate such a system shall jointly establish the procedures necessary to implement such a system with the cooperation of the director and the State Treasurer. The system shall be designed to be compatible with state accounting procedures. Such a system as established by the director shall employ internal control safeguards and after meeting such safeguards shall be deemed to satisfy any signature requirements. The use of an electronic funds transfer system, telephonic funds transfer system, electric funds transfer system, funds transfers as provided for in article 4A, Uniform Commercial Code, mechanical funds transfer system, or other funds transfer system established by the director and the State Treasurer or any state agency shall not create any rights that would not have been created had an order, drawn by the director upon the State Treasurer directing the latter to pay a specified amount to a specified payee by the use of a dual signature negotiable instrument as provided for in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, been used as the payment medium.</para><para id="id00">(6) Whenever it is ascertained that by mistake or otherwise any county treasurer or other person has paid into the state treasury any sum not due the state, the director shall refund to such county treasurer or other person the amount so paid. Such refund shall be carried on the books of the state as an adjustment to income and not as an expenditure or disbursement.</para><para id="id00">(7) Whenever it is ascertained that by mistake or otherwise the State of Nebraska or any of its departments, agencies, or officers shall have caused to be made a disbursement which for any reason is refunded to the state, the amount so disbursed and refunded to the state shall be credited to the fund and account from which the disbursement was made as an adjustment of expenditures and disbursements and not as a receipt. Such credited refund shall be considered part of the original appropriation to the department or agency and to the appropriate program and may be expended therefrom without further or additional appropriation. When a refund to the state or any of its departments or agencies is related to a transaction which occurred during a prior fiscal period, the refund shall be credited to the unappropriated surplus account of the fund from which the disbursement was originally made, except that (a) medicaid refunds or rebates for (i) pharmaceuticals, (ii) third-party liability recoveries, and (iii) surveillance and utilization reviews which have occurred during a prior fiscal period shall be treated as an adjustment to expenditures in the year in which the refund or rebate is received and (b) reimbursement to the State of Nebraska from other member states operating in accordance with the Emergency Management Assistance Compact shall be credited as receipts to the Governor's Emergency Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 21, p. 1709; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 546, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 236, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 257, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>