<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1531.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1531.02</statuteno><catchline>Uranium mining; department; regulatory duties; prohibited methods; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall recommend an appropriate regulatory policy for controlling uranium mining to be presented to the council and the Legislature by January 1, 1986. The department shall evaluate all reasonable regulatory options for addressing the impacts on air, land, and water quality of uranium mining by methods other than mineral production and injection wells which are presently regulated. The department shall examine and consider regulatory programs created by other states and the federal government, their applicability to Nebraska, and their success in the states or areas where they are used and shall consider, but not be limited to, the following policy options:</para><para>(a) The development of uranium surface and shaft mining regulations;</para><para>(b) The development of regulations addressing appropriate development, mitigation, or reclamation standards for uranium mining or uranium mining-related activities;</para><para>(c) The appropriateness of developing regulations addressing ground or surface water use standards for uranium mining or uranium mining-related activities as a means of limiting the impact of uranium mining on land and water resources; and</para><para>(d) The use of any other existing state regulatory programs to control or regulate the impacts of uranium mining on land and water resources.</para><para>(2) The department shall perform the evaluation in cooperation with other state agencies which have or could have a role in regulating the impacts of uranium mining on Nebraska's people and resources or in controlling other uranium mining activities. The department shall also create a citizen advisory panel, of interested or affected parties, which shall be consulted for its input and opinion on the results of the evaluation of regulatory options.</para><para>(3) Uranium mining by any method other than mineral production and injection wells shall be prohibited until legislation is passed authorizing the department to regulate such mining activities. It is the intent of the Legislature that uranium mining shall be regulated by the department. Upon receipt of evidence that uranium mining by any method other than by mineral production and injection wells or related activities are presenting or are likely to present an imminent and substantial threat to the environment, the director shall petition the district court for an injunction to immediately restrain any person from contributing to the alleged acts or to require any person to stop such acts or to take such other action as may be necessary. It shall be the duty of each county attorney or the Attorney General to whom the director reports a violation to cause appropriate proceedings to be instituted without delay to assure compliance with this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 356, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 742, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1008, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>