<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1712"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1712</statuteno><catchline>Project; professional services required; notice; qualifications and performance data; statements; certification; procedures; Department of Administrative Services; adopt.</catchline><para>(1) Public notice shall be given by each agency, in a uniform and consistent manner, when professional services are required to be contracted for a project whose basic construction cost is estimated by the agency to be more than four hundred thousand dollars and for professional services when the estimated fee for such professional services exceeds forty thousand dollars, except in cases of public emergencies so certified by the agency head. The Department of Administrative Services shall adjust the dollar amounts in this section every four years beginning January 1, 2002, to account for inflationary and market changes. The adjustments shall be based on percentage changes in a construction cost index and any other published index relevant to operations and utilities costs, as selected by the department. The public notice shall include a general description of the project and shall indicate how interested firms can apply for consideration for such contract.</para><para>(2) Each agency shall encourage firms engaged in the lawful practice of their profession who desire to provide professional services to the agency to submit annually a statement of qualifications and performance data. The agency may request a firm to update the file statement before the anniversary date to reflect changed conditions of the firm.</para><para>(3) Any firm desiring to provide professional services to an agency must first be certified by the agency as qualified pursuant to law and the regulations of the agency. The agency shall make a finding that the firm to be employed is fully qualified to render the required service. Factors to be considered in making this finding shall include capabilities to perform, adequacy of personnel, past record and performance, and experience.</para><para>(4) The Department of Administrative Services shall, with the advice of each agency, adopt administrative procedures for the evaluation of professional services, including capabilities to perform, adequacy of personnel, past record and performance, experience, and such other factors as may be determined by the agency to be applicable to its particular requirements.</para><para>(5) The public shall not be excluded from the meetings or proceedings under this section in accordance with the Open Meetings Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 715, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 33. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>