<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-1117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1117</statuteno><catchline>Information management services administrator;
powers, duties, and responsibilities; enumerated; restrictions on agency acquisitions;
Information Management Revolving Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>(1)
As used in this section, unless the context otherwise requires, information
management includes, but is not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) Mainframe computers, minicomputers, microprocessors, word processors,
and desktop computers;</para>
<para>(b) Any peripheral device to be used with the equipment listed in subdivision
(1)(a) of this section for such purposes as data input and output, data storage,
or data communications;</para>
<para>(c) Any code or program to control the operation of the equipment or
devices listed in subdivision (1)(a) or (1)(b) of this section; and</para>
<para>(d) Employment of professional expertise for computer system design,
operations, or program development.</para>
<para>(2) Subject to review and approval by the Chief Information Officer,
the information management services administrator shall have the following
powers, duties, and responsibilities:</para>
<para>(a) He or she may review the accounting and other records and reporting
systems of all divisions within the Department of Administrative Services
and within every other department and agency of the state;</para>
<para>(b) He or she shall systematically review the potential application
of information management to any work performed outside the information management
services division or by any department or agency of the state or any subdivision
of any department or agency of the state, and if the costs of mechanizing
such work will not exceed present costs or if efficiencies may be achieved,
he or she may accept responsibility for the performance of such work. He or
she may also review computer applications being used to determine if revision
or deletion of computer applications would be beneficial. The findings of
reviews made pursuant to this subdivision shall be reported to the Governor
and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst.
The findings submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted
electronically;</para>
<para>(c) He or she may, with the approval of the Chief Information Officer,
make such revisions to internal systems for production of accounting and other
reports as may be necessary to permit economical undertaking of work to be
performed by the information management services division for any agency or
department of the state;</para>
<para>(d) He or she shall organize the information management services division
to provide system review, system design, feasibility studies, and machine
reviews;</para>
<para>(e) He or she may review the operations of information management installations
as may exist in any department or agency of the state and may cause such operations
to be merged with those of the information management services division in
the event that a cost analysis shows that economic advantage may be achieved.
He or she may permit the establishment of departmental or agency information
management operations in any department or agency of the state if his or her
analysis of feasibility shows a potential economy or a substantial convenience
for the state incident to such separate establishment. No state agency shall
hire, purchase, lease, or rent any information management item listed in subsection
(1) of this section without the written approval of the information management
services administrator. All new computer programs developed or acquired for
use with information management equipment of any state agency shall be documented
according to standards developed or approved by the information management
services administrator;</para>
<para>(f) He or she shall prepare a budget in sufficient time in advance of
the statutory date for submittal of budget requests by departments and agencies
of the state as to permit each department and agency for which services are
performed, or are to be performed during the request budget period, to be
informed of the cost of maintaining the current fiscal year's production work
for inclusion within their respective budget requests;</para>
<para>(g) He or she shall provide for a system of charges for services rendered
by the information management services division to any other department or
agency of the state when these charges are allocable to a particular project
carried on by such department or division. Such standard rate charges shall,
as nearly as may be practical, reflect the actual costs incurred in the performance
of services for such department or agency. Such system of charges shall be
annually reviewed by the Legislature's Committee on Appropriations. Rates
planned for the coming fiscal year shall be included in the instructions for
completion of budget request forms as annually prepared by the Department
of Administrative Services budget division. If rate revisions are required
during the fiscal year to reflect changes in the information management services
division's operating costs, these revisions shall be announced to state agencies
at least thirty days prior to their use in billing these agencies for service.
Miscellaneous supplies shall be billed to using agencies at actual cost. Equipment
used primarily by one agency for special applications shall be billed to that
agency at actual cost. In the event of saturation of the information management
services division with the resulting need for contractual support to be furnished
by another information management installation, agencies shall be billed at
actual cost. The charges received by the department for information management
services shall be credited to a fund hereby created which shall be known as
the Information Management Revolving Fund. Expenditures shall be made from
such fund to finance the operations of the information management services
division in accordance with appropriations made by the Legislature. Any money
in the Information Management Revolving Fund available for investment shall
be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act;</para>
<para>(h) He or she may provide information management services and technical
assistance to any subdivision of government as provided for under the Interlocal
Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act;</para>
<para>(i) He or she shall provide for the centralization of all administrative
work, including that of educational institutions, into the information management
services division;</para>
<para>(j) He or she shall provide definitions of standards and common data
elements, coordinate the collection of data, consolidate data files or data
banks, and review and approve or disapprove the establishment of separate
data banks; and</para>
<para>(k) He or she shall provide assistance as requested by the Nebraska
Information Technology Commission to support the technical panel created in
section 86-521.</para>
<para>Each member of the Legislature shall receive an
electronic copy of the report required by subdivision (2)(b) of
this section by making a request for it to the administrator.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 17, p. 1703; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 804, &#167; 11, p. 3039; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 108, p. 2413; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 472, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 560, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 118; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 506; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 921, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 188.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This section held not applicable to the Board of Regents which cannot delegate its constitutional powers and duties to other officers or agencies. Board of Regents v. Exon, 199 Neb. 146, 256 N.W.2d 330 (1977).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>