
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id12" statutenumber="81-15,148"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,148</statuteno><catchline id="id15">Legislative
findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that the construction,
rehabilitation, operation, and maintenance of modern and efficient sewer systems
and wastewater treatment works are essential to protecting and improving the
state's water quality, that protecting water quality is an issue of concern
to all citizens of the state, that in addition to protecting and improving
the state's water quality, adequate wastewater treatment works are essential
to economic growth and development, and that the amount of needed assistance
which may be provided to municipalities or counties for wastewater treatment
purposes can be increased and needed projects can be undertaken more expeditiously
through the issuance of revenue bonds and the deposit of the proceeds thereof
into the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund.</para>
<para>The Legislature finds that construction, rehabilitation, operation,
and maintenance of nonpoint source control systems are essential to water
quality protection, that such systems are financially burdensome to municipalities
and counties, and that the amount of needed assistance which may be provided
to municipalities or counties for nonpoint source control systems can be increased
and needed projects can be undertaken more expeditiously through the issuance
of revenue bonds and the deposit of the proceeds of
such bonds into the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction
Loan Fund.</para>
<para>The Legislature finds and determines that the issuance of
revenue bonds for the purpose of financing the fund serves a public purpose
by assisting municipalities or counties in providing and improving wastewater
treatment facilities and nonpoint source control systems and thereby providing
clean water to the citizens of the state, promoting the health and well-being
of the citizens, and assisting in the economic growth and development of the
state and its political subdivisions. The full faith and credit and the taxing
power of the state are not pledged to the payment of such bonds or the interest
thereon.</para>
<para>The Legislature
finds that a linked deposit program established to make low-interest loans
available for the construction, rehabilitation, and enhancement of and assistance
with nonpoint source control systems will improve the water quality of the
waters of the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 766, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 311, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB514, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>