<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-1354.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1354.05</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Personnel Division Revolving Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Personnel Division Revolving Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the personnel division of the Department of Administrative Services. The fund shall consist of (a) all funds received by the personnel division for employee recognition programs and advertising and (b) assessments charged by the Director of Personnel to state agencies, boards, and commissions for human service management services provided by the division. Such assessments shall be adequate to cover actual and necessary expenses associated with providing the services. The fund shall be used to pay for expenses incurred by the division to provide such services.</para><para>(2) State agencies, boards, and commissions shall make the personnel division assessment payments to the fund (a) in one payment no later than August 1 of each year, (b) in two equal payments the first of which shall be made no later than August 1 and the second of which shall be made no later than February 1 of each year, or (c) in four equal payments to be made no later than August 1, October 1, February 1, and April 1 of each year, at the discretion of the personnel administrator.</para><para>(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB661, &#167; 35. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>