<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,161"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,161</statuteno><catchline>Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Fund; grants; application; contents; director and council; duties; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) Allocations from the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Fund may be made as grants to a political subdivision or other entity or organization, public, private, or nonprofit, when it is found that the proposed program, project, or study appears to benefit the general public, to further the goals of waste reduction and recycling, and to be consistent with proper waste management practices. Each application for a grant under the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Act shall be filed with the department in a manner and form prescribed by the department.</para><para>(2) The council shall adopt guidelines for the determination of eligibility of public, private, and nonprofit entities, organizations, or persons to receive funds pursuant to the act and for the determination of qualification and suitability of plans submitted by such entities, organizations, and persons consistent with the act.</para><para>(3) An application for a grant shall: (a) Describe the nature and purpose of the proposed program, project, or study; (b) set forth or be accompanied by a plan for development of the proposed program, project, or study, together with engineering, economic, and financial feasibility data and information and such estimated costs of construction or implementation as may be required by the department; (c) state whether money other than that for which the application is made will be used to help in meeting program, project, or study costs and whether such money is available or has been sought for this purpose; (d) when appropriate, state that the applicant holds or can acquire title to all lands or has the necessary easements and rights-of-way for the project and related lands; (e) show that the applicant possesses all necessary authority to undertake or participate in the proposed program, project, or study; and (f) demonstrate the probable environmental and ecological consequences that may result from the proposed program or project. Upon receipt of an application the director shall evaluate and investigate all aspects of the proposed program, project, or study and the proposed schedule for the development and completion of such program, project, or study and determine the eligibility of the program, project, or study for funding. As a part of his or her investigation, the director shall consider whether the plan for development of the program, project, or study is satisfactory. If the director determines that the plan is unsatisfactory or that the application does not contain adequate information upon which to make determinations, the director shall return the application to the applicant and may make recommendations to the applicant which the director considers necessary to make the plan or the application satisfactory.</para><para>(4) The director shall within a reasonable time, not to exceed six months, after receipt of such application approve or reject grant funding for the program, project, or study. The grant shall be for a specific dollar amount of funds, and the funds shall be used only for the purpose specified in the grant. The director may set any terms for the administration of the funds as he or she deems necessary and any penalties to be imposed upon the recipient if it fails to comply with any requirements of the grant.</para><para>(5) It is the intent of the Legislature that allocations from the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Fund shall be made in an equitable manner which maximizes the benefits of the fund. When awarding grants, the director shall balance the needs of: (a) All geographic areas of the state; (b) all sizes and classes of communities; and (c) all manner and scale of programs, projects, and studies. The director shall also give consideration to eligible programs, projects, and studies which would specifically employ disabled or handicapped persons.</para><para>(6) The director may deny any application which he or she determines (a) is not in conformance with this section, (b) does not reflect reasonable costs for the type of project proposed, (c) contains inaccurate, incomplete, or misleading information in the application, or (d) would require the expenditure of funds beyond the fund's unobligated balance or for any other reason which the director determines is necessary to properly administer this section.</para><para>(7) All disbursements made under this section shall be formalized by a written agreement between the department and all recipients of the disbursement. The agreement may include, but need not be limited to, the following conditions designed to protect the fund and ensure completion of the project: (a) Mechanics of funding disbursement; (b) any bidding requirements; (c) completion timelines for any deliverables; (d) record-keeping and reporting requirements; (e) security interest and insurance requirements on equipment; (f) forfeiture and repayment of funds; and (g) other conditions necessary or desirable to carry out this section.</para><para>(8) The council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 163, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 325, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 444, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1034, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 495, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 143, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>