<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id23"><sectno id="id24" opdate="December 31, 2009">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id25" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-1108.33"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id27">81-1108.33</statuteno><catchline id="id28">State building division; Task Force for Building Renewal; reviews required; report; approval; when required.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that the state will not assume responsibility for the substandard construction, repair, or maintenance of, or for the excessive maintenance or repair costs for, real property, structures, or improvements which will be made available by gift, bequest, or devise to any state agency, board, or commission. Therefor, prior to any construction, repair, or maintenance work on such real property, structure, or improvement, the state building division and the Task Force for Building Renewal shall review the plans, specifications, other construction or repair documents, and potential maintenance requirements as a requirement for acceptance by the state of such real property, structure, or improvement.</para><para>(2)(a) Any gift of, bequest of, or devise of (i) real property, (ii) a structure, or (iii) an improvement proposed to be made available to any state agency, board, or commission shall be reviewed by the state building division and the Task Force for Building Renewal pursuant to sections 81-176, 81-1108.15, and 81-1114. Such review shall include any potential matching of state funds, any plans, specifications, and other construction or repair documents reviewed pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, and any potential maintenance requirements as a condition of acceptance. Subsequent to such review, the state building division and the task force shall submit a report to the Governor, the Committee on Building Maintenance, and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst including a summary of the review of the plans, specifications, and other construction or repair documents and potential maintenance requirements and outlining the terms and conditions of the proposed gift, bequest, or devise along with its recommendation.</para><para>(b) Any proposed gift of, bequest of, or devise of (i) real property, (ii) a structure, or (iii) an improvement in excess of ten thousand dollars shall be approved by the Governor and the Legislature prior to acceptance. If the Legislature is not in session, the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, after recommendation by the Committee on Building Maintenance, may approve such gift, bequest, or devise along with the Governor.</para><para>(c) No construction or other work related to the proposed gift, bequest, or devise shall be initiated prior to receiving the approval required by this section.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, gift of, bequest of, or devise of (a) real property, (b) a structure, or (c) an improvement shall include, but not be limited to, a donation of, gift of, bequest of, devise of, or grant of (i) real property, (ii) a structure, or (iii) an improvement from an individual, an organization, a corporation, a foundation, or a similar entity or from a nonfederal governmental agency. For purposes of this section, gift, bequest, or devise shall not include a donation, gift, bequest, devise, or grant of tangible or intangible personal property.</para><para>(4) This section shall not apply to the University of Nebraska or any Nebraska state college, since these agencies are subject to and participate in statewide facilities planning developed by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education pursuant to the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 530, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 369, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1038, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1116, &#167; 8.</para><operativedate>December 31, 2009</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Committee on Building Maintenance,</emphasis> see section 81-185.</para><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education,</emphasis> see Article VII, section 14, Constitution of Nebraska and section 85-1403.</para><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1401.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc>
