<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1426"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1426</statuteno><catchline>Public officers and agencies; information, records, reports; furnish to commission; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the standardized collection, development, and maintenance of statistical information, records, and reports, including, but not limited to, the Uniform Crime Report, and shall develop the prescribed form for the collection of data.</para><para>(2) The commission shall obtain from all public officers or agencies, the functions of which include the control, apprehension, trial, or correction of criminal offenders in this state, such information, records, and reports, including, but not limited to, the Uniform Crime Report, as the commission determines relevant to its functions.</para><para>(3) It shall be the duty of all public officers and agencies, the functions of which include the control, apprehension, trial, or correction of criminal offenders in the state, to provide such information, records, and reports, including, but not limited to, the Uniform Crime Report, as the commission determines relevant to its functions.</para><para>(4) Willful or repeated failure by any public officers and agencies, the functions of which include the control, apprehension, trial, or correction of criminal offenders in this state, to submit the prescribed information, records, or reports, including the Uniform Crime Report, prescribed in this section shall subject the agency or the administrator of the agency to a civil penalty of up to one hundred dollars per day for each day of violation. Such penalty shall be recoverable by way of a civil suit brought against such agency or individually against the administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 774, &#167; 12, p. 2936; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 722, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>