
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id12" statutenumber="81-1113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1113</statuteno><catchline id="id15">Budget division; powers; duties.</catchline><para>The budget division shall prepare the executive budget in accordance with the wishes and policies of the Governor. The budget division shall have the following duties, powers, and responsibilities:</para><para>(1) Shall prescribe the forms and procedures to be employed by all departments and agencies of the state in compiling and submitting their individual budget requests and shall set up a budget calendar which shall provide for (a) the date, not later than July 15 of each even-numbered year, for distribution of instructions, (b) the date by which time requests for appropriations by each agency shall be submitted, and (c) the period during which such public hearings as the Governor may elect shall be held for each department and agency. The budget request shall be submitted each even-numbered year no later than the date provided in subsection (1) of section 81-132, shall include the intended receipts and expenditures by programs, subprograms, and activities and such additional information as the administrator may deem appropriate for each fiscal year, including the certification described in subdivision (4) of this section, shall be made upon a biennial basis, and shall include actual receipts and actual expenditures for each fiscal year of the most recently completed biennium and the first year of the current biennium and estimates for the second year of the current biennium and each year of the next ensuing biennium;</para><para>(2) Shall prescribe the forms and procedures to be employed by all departments and agencies of the state in compiling and submitting their proposed changes to existing appropriations for the biennium in progress. The budget division shall distribute instructions and forms to all departments and agencies no later than September 15 of each odd-numbered year. Departments and agencies shall submit their proposed changes no later than the date provided in subsection (2) of section 81-132;</para><para>(3) Shall work with each governmental department and agency in developing performance standards for each program, subprogram, and activity to measure and evaluate present as well as projected levels of expenditures. The budget division shall also work with the Department of Health and Human Services to develop key goals, benchmarks, and methods of quantification of progress required pursuant to sections 81-3133 to 81-3133.03;</para><para>(4)(a) Shall develop a certification form and procedure to be included in each budget request under subdivision (1) of this section through which each department and agency shall certify, for each program or practice it administers, whether such program or practice is an evidence-based program or practice, or, if not, whether such program or practice is reasonably capable of becoming an evidence-based program or practice;</para><para>(b) For purposes of this subdivision (4):</para><para>(i) Evidence-based means that a program or practice (A) offers a high level of research on effectiveness, determined as a result of multiple rigorous evaluations, such as randomized controlled trials and evaluations that incorporate strong comparison group designs or a single large multisite randomized study and (B) to the extent practicable, has specified procedures that allow for successful replication;</para><para>(ii) Program or practice means a function or activity that is sufficiently identifiable as a discrete unit of service; and</para><para> (iii) Reasonably capable of becoming an evidence-based program or practice means the program or practice is susceptible to quantifiable benchmarks that measure service delivery, client or customer satisfaction, or efficiency;</para><para>(5) Shall, following passage of legislative appropriations, be responsible for the administration of the approved budget through budgetary allotments;</para><para>(6) Shall be responsible for a monthly budgetary report for each department and agency showing comparisons between actual expenditures and allotments, which report shall be subject to review by the director and budget administrator; and</para><para>(7) Shall be responsible for the authorization of employee positions. Such authorizations shall be based on the following:</para><para>(a) A requirement that a sufficient budget program appropriation and salary limitation exist to fully fund all authorized positions;</para><para>(b) A requirement that permanent full-time positions which have been vacant for ninety days or more be reviewed and reauthorized prior to being filled. If requested by the budget division, the personnel division of the Department of Administrative Services shall review such vacant position to determine the proper classification for the position;</para><para>(c) A requirement that authorized positions accurately reflect legislative intent contained in legislative appropriation and intent bills; and</para><para>(d) Other relevant criteria as determined by the budget administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 13, p. 1698; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 594, &#167; 1, p. 2023; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 804, &#167; 7, p. 3035; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 14, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 12, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 8, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB949, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1092, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>