<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id62">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id64" statutenumber="81-1820"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id66">81-1820</statuteno><catchline id="id67">Hearing officer;
emergency award of compensation; when; conditions; review.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to the hearing officer taking action on an application for compensation from the Victim's Compensation
Fund, the applicant may request that a hearing officer make an
emergency award of compensation to the applicant. If it appears to the hearing
officer that the claim is one for which compensation is probable and undue
hardship will result to the applicant if immediate payment is not made, the
hearing officer may make an emergency award of compensation to the applicant
pending a final decision in the case, except that:</para>
<para>(a) The amount of the emergency compensation shall not exceed
five hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(b) The amount of the emergency compensation shall be deducted
from the final compensation made to the applicant; and</para>
<para>(c) The excess amount of the emergency compensation over the
final amount shall be repaid by the applicant to the committee.</para>
<para>(2) If the hearing officer refuses to make an emergency award
of compensation to the applicant, the applicant may request an emergency hearing
before the committee which may be conducted by means of teleconference. The
committee shall forthwith specify a time and place for an emergency hearing
and shall give written notice to the applicant. If it appears to the committee
that the claim is one for which compensation is probable and undue hardship
will result to the applicant if immediate payment is not made, the committee
may make an emergency award of compensation to the applicant pending a final
decision in the case, subject to the conditions and limitations stated in
subsection (1) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 910, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 540, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB598, &#167;  8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>