<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1108.22">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1108.22</statuteno><catchline>State building division; responsibility;
office space outside the State Capitol; rental; approval; required; lease
contract; filed; administrator; duties; State Building Revolving Fund; created;
use; investment; applicability of section, when.</catchline><para>(1) The
division shall have the responsibility of providing office space in leased
and state-owned buildings in the proximity of the State Capitol and in other
locations.</para>
<para>(2) When any board, agency, commission, or department of the state government
not otherwise specifically authorized by law desires to use funds available
for the purpose of renting office space outside of the State Capitol, it shall
submit a request to the Director of Administrative Services. If the director
approves the lease, the terms and location shall be approved by the director
and the administrator in writing and the leases shall be entered into and
administered by the administrator on behalf of the board, agency, commission,
or department. A copy of all such lease contracts shall be kept on file by
the state building division and shall be open to inspection by the Legislature
and the public during normal business hours.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The administrator shall develop a system of charges to cover
basic rental, maintenance, renovations, and operation of such leased and owned
properties. The charges to state agencies, boards, commissions, or departments
of state government shall be paid from funds available for the purpose of
renting space on a regular basis and placed, as applicable, in the State Building
Revolving Fund and the State Building Renewal Assessment Fund. The administrator
shall make payments for basic rentals, renovations, and maintenance and operational
costs of all leased and owned buildings from the State Building Revolving
Fund except for expenses relating to security provided by the Nebraska State
Patrol as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para>
<para>(b) The State Building Revolving Fund is created. The fund shall be
administered by the administrator. The fund shall consist of rental charges
and other receipts collected pursuant to contractual agreements between the
state building division and other entities as authorized by law. The fund
shall only be used to support the operation of the state building division
as provided by law, except that the Legislature shall make fund transfers
each fiscal year through the budget process from the State Building Revolving
Fund to the Capitol Security Revolving Fund to help pay non-general-fund costs
associated with the operation of the state capitol security division of the
Nebraska State Patrol. Any money in the State Building Revolving Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
<para>(4) The charges for such leased and owned properties shall only be adjusted
by the administrator on July 1. Prior to any adjustment in the system of charges,
the Department of Administrative Services, on or before December 1 of the
year preceding the effective date of such adjustment, shall provide electronic notification to the Committee on
Building Maintenance, the Clerk of the Legislature, and the Legislative Fiscal
Analyst of the proposed adjustment to the system of charges.</para>
<para>(5) Commencing on April 18, 1992, all leases of real property entered
into by any state agency, board, commission, or department shall be subject
to this section. Leases held by a state agency, board, commission, or department
on such date shall be valid until the lease contract is terminated or is subject
to renewal. The division shall monitor all such leases and determine when
the lease is subject to renewal. Once the determination is made, the division
shall cancel the lease as of the renewal date and shall treat the need of
the agency, board, commission, or department as an original request for space
and subject to this section. This subsection shall not apply to (a) state-owned
facilities to be rented to state agencies or other parties by the University
of Nebraska, the Nebraska state colleges, the Department of Aeronautics, the
Department of Roads, and the Board of Educational Lands and Funds, (b) facilities
to be leased for use by the University of Nebraska, the Nebraska state colleges,
and the Board of Educational Lands and Funds, (c) facilities to be leased
for nonoffice use by the Department of Roads, or (d) facilities controlled
by the State Department of Education, which were formerly controlled by the
Nebraska School for the Visually Handicapped, to be rented to state agencies
or other parties by the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 353, &#167; 1, p. 1113; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 421, &#167; 1, p. 1347; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 72-701.08; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1048, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 359, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 576, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1241, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 530, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 181.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Committee on Building Maintenance,</emphasis> see section 81-185.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>