<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1506" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1506</statuteno><catchline>Unlawful acts.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person:</para><para>(a) To cause pollution of any air, waters, or land of the state or to place or cause to be placed any wastes in a location where they are likely to cause pollution of any air, waters, or land of the state; or</para><para>(b) To discharge or emit any wastes into any air, waters, or land of the state which reduce the quality of such air, waters, or land below the air, water, or land quality standards established therefor by the council. Any such action is hereby declared to be a public nuisance. An animal feeding operation is not a nuisance if:</para><para>(i) Reasonable techniques are employed to keep dust, noise, insects, and odor at a minimum;</para><para>(ii) It is in compliance with applicable regulations adopted by the council and zoning regulations of the local governing body having jurisdiction; and</para><para>(iii) The action is brought by or on behalf of a person whose date of lawful possession of the land claimed to be affected by an animal feeding operation is subsequent to the issuance of an appropriate permit by the department for such operation or is subsequent to the operation of the feedlot and an onsite inspection by the department is made, before or after filing of the suit, and the inspection reveals that no permit is required for such operation.</para><para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person to:</para><para>(a) Discharge any pollutant into waters of the state without obtaining a permit as required by the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System created by the Clean Water Act, as amended, 33 U.S.C. 1251 et seq., and by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 81-1505;</para><para>(b) Construct, install, modify, or operate any disposal system or part thereof or any extension or addition thereto without obtaining necessary permits from the department;</para><para>(c) Increase in volume or strength any waste in excess of permitted discharges specified under any existing permit;</para><para>(d) Construct, install, or operate any industrial, commercial, or other facility or extend, modify, or add to any such facility if the operation would cause an increase in the discharge or emission of wastes into the air, waters, or land of the state or would otherwise cause an alteration of the physical, chemical, or biological properties of any air, waters, or land of the state in a manner that is not lawfully authorized;</para><para>(e) Construct or use any new outlet for the discharge or emission of any wastes into the air, waters, or land of the state without the necessary permit; or</para><para>(f) Discharge any dredged or fill material into waters of the United States without obtaining a permit as required by section 404 of the Clean Water Act, as amended, 33 U.S.C. 1344, and by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 81-1505.</para><para>(3) It shall be unlawful for any person to:</para><para>(a) Construct or operate a solid waste management facility without first obtaining a permit required under the Environmental Protection Act or under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to the acts;</para><para>(b) Violate any term or condition of a solid waste management facility permit;</para><para>(c) Violate any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to the Environmental Protection Act or the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act; or</para><para>(d) After October 1, 1993, dispose of any solid waste at any location other than a solid waste management facility holding a current permit issued by the department pursuant to the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act.</para><para>(4) It shall be unlawful to:</para><para>(a) Construct or operate an air pollution source without first obtaining a permit required under the Environmental Protection Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to subsection (12) of section 81-1505;</para><para>(b) Violate any term or condition of an air pollution permit or any emission limit set in the permit; or</para><para>(c) Violate any emission limit or air quality standard established by the council.</para><para>(5) It shall be unlawful for any person to:</para><para>(a) Construct or operate an animal feeding operation without first obtaining a permit if required under the Livestock Waste Management Act or under the Environmental Protection Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to such acts;</para><para>(b) Violate any provision of the Livestock Waste Management Act;</para><para>(c) Violate any term or condition of an animal feeding operation permit; or</para><para>(d) Violate any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the council pursuant to the Environmental Protection Act or the Livestock Waste Management Act.</para><para>(6) Nothing in this section shall be construed to authorize the department to specify the type, design, method of installation, or type of construction of any equipment of manufacturing processes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 939, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1435, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1029, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 132, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 915, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 356, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 623, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 570, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1209, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 112. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Livestock Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 54-2416.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Even in an industrial or rural area, one cannot conduct a business in such a manner as to materially prejudice a neighbor, but before enjoining it perpetually, a court of equity will usually allow the owner to correct or eliminate the cause of the grievance. Botsch v. Leigh Land Co., 195 Neb. 509, 239 N.W.2d 481 (1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>