<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id62">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id64" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-1431"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1431</statuteno><catchline>Training regarding issues in human
trafficking; task force; duties.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that law enforcement
agencies, prosecutors, public defenders, judges, juvenile detention center
staff, and others involved in the juvenile justice system and the criminal
justice system and other relevant officials be provided mandatory training
regarding issues in human trafficking. The task force established in section
81-1430 shall work with such agencies, persons, and staff to develop a proper
curriculum for the training and to determine how the training should be provided.
The determination and accompanying legislative recommendations shall be made
by December 1, 2012. Such training shall focus on:</para>
<para>(a) State and
federal law regarding human trafficking;</para><para>(b) Methods used in identifying victims
of human trafficking who are United States citizens and foreign nationals,
including preliminary interview techniques and appropriate questioning methods;</para>
<para>(c) Methods
for prosecuting human traffickers;</para><para>(d) Methods of increasing effective collaboration
with nongovernmental organizations and other relevant social service organizations
in the course of investigating and prosecuting a human trafficking case;</para>
<para>(e) Methods
for protecting the rights of victims of human trafficking, taking into account
the need to consider human rights and the special needs of women and minor
victims;</para><para>(f) The necessity of treating victims of human trafficking as crime
victims rather than as criminals; and</para><para>(g) Methods for promoting the safety and
well-being of all victims of human trafficking.</para><para>(2) The task force shall
also seek the input and participation of appropriate nongovernmental organizations
and other relevant organizations regarding the provision, preparation, and
presentation of the training called for in this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1145, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>