<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id393"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,309"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,309</statuteno><catchline>Cleanup costs; environmental lien.</catchline><para>(1) All cleanup costs for which a person is liable to the state under section 81-15,307 shall constitute a lien in favor of the state upon any real property that is owned by such person and subject to or affected by the cleanup.</para><para>(2) An environmental lien attaches when:</para><para>(a) Cleanup costs are first incurred by the state;</para><para>(b) Such person is provided written notice by certified or registered mail of potential liability; and</para><para>(c) A lien notice is filed in compliance with this section.</para><para>(3) An environmental lien notice shall state:</para><para>(a) The name of the record owner of the real property to which the environmental lien is attached;</para><para>(b) The legal description of the real property to which the environmental lien is attached;</para><para>(c) If the real property against which the lien is attached is not the property where the cleanup occurred, the legal description of the property where the cleanup occurred;</para><para>(d) An itemized statement detailing the cleanup costs incurred by the state; and</para><para>(e) A statement that an environmental lien has attached to the described real property.</para><para>(4) The environmental lien notice shall be filed with the register of deeds in each county in Nebraska where the responsible person owns or holds an interest in real property.</para><para>(5) An environmental lien is subject to the rights of any other person whose interest is perfected before an environmental lien notice has been filed.</para><para>(6) A person shall be relieved from an environmental lien when liability for cleanup costs is satisfied.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1102, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>