<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,225"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,225</statuteno><catchline>Federal funds and cash funds; use; legislative intent; changes to sections; applicability.</catchline><para>(1) For any federal funds appropriated to the department pursuant to the Shovel-Ready Capital Recovery and Investment Act, it is the intent of the Legislature that the department divide the total appropriation for grants to capital projects eligible under the act equally for each congressional district and give priority to grant requests less than or equal to five million dollars. After eligible grantees with priority status have been awarded grant funds, remaining funds may be awarded on a statewide basis with the department considering each project based on the overall economic impact of the project to the respective community and the overall benefit to the State of Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the department make reasonable adjustments to dates and deadlines and request additional documentation pursuant to any requirements for the use of funds received pursuant to the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021.</para><para>(2) For any cash funds appropriated to the department pursuant to the Shovel-Ready Capital Recovery and Investment Act, it is the intent of the Legislature that the department divide the total appropriation for grants to capital projects eligible under the act as follows:</para><para>(a) Thirty million dollars for grants to nonprofit organizations holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code that are qualified nonprofit organizations under subdivision (5)(c) of section 81-12,221; and</para><para>(b) Remaining funds equally by each congressional district.</para><para>(3) The changes made in this section and sections 81-12,220, 81-12,221, 81-12,222, and 81-12,223 by Laws 2023, LB818, apply to all grant applications filed on or after July 1, 2023. For all applications filed prior to May 25, 2023, the provisions of the Shovel-Ready Capital Recovery and Investment Act as they existed immediately prior to such date apply.</para><para>(4) The changes made in this section and sections 81-12,220, 81-12,221, 81-12,222, and 81-12,223 by Laws 2023, LB531, apply to all grant applications filed on or after July 1, 2023. For all applications filed prior to June 7, 2023, the provisions of the Shovel-Ready Capital Recovery and Investment Act as they existed immediately prior to such date apply.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB566, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB531, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 30. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>