<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,106</statuteno><catchline>License; term; review; revocation; denial; hearing; closure of facility.</catchline><para>(1) Licenses shall provide that a facility shall not accept waste for a period longer than thirty years or until five million cubic feet of low-level radioactive waste has been received, whichever occurs sooner. Licenses shall be reviewed every five years subsequent to the date of issuance and shall be modified as necessary to assure that the facility continues to comply with the currently applicable laws, rules, and regulations. Nothing in this subsection shall preclude a license from being reviewed and modified at any time during its term.</para><para>(2) The department may issue an order temporarily or permanently closing a facility prior to its scheduled closing date if it finds there is a potential hazard to public health, safety, or the environment which justifies a temporary or permanent closure. A facility that is temporarily closed shall remain closed for as long as necessary for remedial action and throughout the period of facility cleanup and stabilization. Before authorizing the reopening of a temporarily closed facility, the department shall provide an explanation of its reasons for authorizing the reopening.</para><para>(3) Any license issued under the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal Act shall be subject to revocation for failure of the licensee to comply with the terms and conditions of the license, the applicable rules and regulations, or the provisions of the act. Any person whose license has been revoked shall be afforded an opportunity for a hearing by the department upon written application made within thirty days after service of notice of such revocation.</para><para>(4) In any proceeding for the denial of an application for a license or for revocation, suspension, or modification of a license, the department shall provide to the applicant or licensee an opportunity for a hearing on the record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 426, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 761, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc>