<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id596"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,111"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,111</statuteno><catchline>Innovation hub partners.</catchline><para>(1) An iHub shall form a collaborative relationship, through a signed statement of cooperation, with at least three iHub partners. An iHub partner may be any of the following:</para><para>(a) A postsecondary educational institution;</para><para>(b) A bank or other financial institution;</para><para>(c) A municipal economic development division or department;</para><para>(d) A nonprofit economic development corporation;</para><para>(e) A federal government entity or agency focused on economic development;</para><para>(f) An inland port authority created pursuant to the Municipal Inland Port Authority Act;</para><para>(g) A business support organization, including a workforce development or training organization, an incubator or a business accelerator, a business technical assistance provider, a chamber of commerce, or a networking organization that supports innovation;</para><para>(h) An educational consortium, including technology transfer representatives;</para><para>(i) A venture capital network, including angel investors; or</para><para>(j) A business foundation, innovation foundation, science foundation, laboratory research institution, federal laboratory, or research and development facility.</para><para>(2) The department may allow an entity not listed in subsection (1) of this section to serve as an iHub partner if the department finds that such entity is related to the goals of the iHub.</para><para>(3) An iHub's board of directors shall include a representative of each iHub partner that has signed a statement of cooperation with the iHub.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB450, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Municipal Inland Port Authority Act,</emphasis> see section 13-3301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>