
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1114.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1114.02</statuteno><catchline>Capital construction project;
state building division; review and comment.</catchline><para>Any state agency,
prior to bidding a capital construction project with a total project cost
exceeding the limit established by the Department of Administrative Services
in accordance with section 81-1114.01, shall submit proposed construction
documents to the state building division for review. The state building division
shall review the construction documents and submit comments to the budget
division, the Legislative Fiscal Analyst, and the affected agencies. The comments submitted to the Legislative
Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically. Comments shall
include identification of possible cost and design alternatives and a determination
whether the construction documents are consistent with approved program statements.
The state building division shall, by rules and regulations, establish the
elements to be included in the construction documents. Comments and reviews
of construction documents shall be completed within thirty days after such
documents are submitted to the state building division. No funds shall be
expended on actual construction until construction documents have been approved
by the state building division. A copy of the approval or disapproval shall
be forwarded to the requesting agency, the budget division, and the Legislative
Fiscal Analyst. The copy submitted
to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 819, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 187.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>