
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1010"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1010</statuteno><catchline>Chief of transportation services
bureau; duties; responsibilities; Transportation Services Bureau Revolving
Fund; created; use.</catchline><para>The chief of the transportation services
bureau shall have the following duties and responsibilities:</para>
<para>(1) To establish standards which
a state agency must meet for the full-time assignment
of state-owned vehicles;</para>
<para>(2) To create a motor pool or motor pools of bureau fleet vehicles for the use of agencies
whose travel requirements do not meet the standards
established under subdivision (1) of this section;</para>
<para>(3) To repair, maintain, and lease to state agencies state-owned vehicles and
approve the acquisition, sale, or trade of each and every state-owned vehicle
made by the materiel division of the Department of Administrative Services.
The bureau may provide for repair and maintenance pursuant to subdivision
(8) of this section;</para>
<para>(4) To consult with the various state agencies using bureau
fleet vehicles and write specifications for state-owned vehicles
to be purchased by the materiel division;</para>
<para>(5) To provide for the purchase only of state-owned vehicles used primarily for the
transportation of state employees from funds received from the sale of surplus state-owned vehicles;</para>
<para>(6) To present to the accounting division of the Department of Administrative
Services cost and maintenance records of state-owned vehicles and cost records of rented bureau fleet vehicles so
that the various state agencies which use bureau fleet vehicles may
be billed for such use. Income arising from these billings shall be deposited
to the Transportation Services Bureau Revolving Fund, which fund is hereby
created. All expenses of acquisition, operation, and maintenance of state-owned
vehicles used primarily for transportation of state employees and of rental of bureau fleet vehicles shall
be paid from such fund. Money in the Transportation Services Bureau Revolving
Fund may be transferred to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.
The Department of Administrative Services shall develop a system of time and
mileage charges for the purpose of billing the various state agencies for
their vehicle usage. The daily, weekly, or monthly charge shall cover all
fixed expenses of such vehicles, and the mileage charge shall cover the variable
costs of operation;</para>
<para>(7) To monitor the utilization of permanently assigned bureau
fleet vehicles and enforce minimum utilization standards by withdrawing
permanently assigned bureau fleet vehicles from
agencies which are not meeting the standards established under subdivision (1) of this section;</para>
<para>(8) To enter into service agreements for the repair and maintenance
of bureau fleet vehicles when
it is determined that such action
would be to the economic advantage of the state;</para>
<para>(9) To insure compliance with section 81-1021 for all state-owned vehicles; and</para>
<para>(10) To enter into rental
agreements with any third-party fleet owner in the name of the State of Nebraska
for passenger vehicles for use primarily for transportation of state employees
for transportation in their official duties from one job location to another
when it is determined that such action would be to the economic advantage
of the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 770, &#167; 3, p. 2919; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 28, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1452, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 977, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 469, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 483; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB779, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>