<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-12,191"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,191</statuteno><catchline>Report; joint hearing.</catchline><para>(1) No later than October 1 following the approval of the application, and no later than October 1 of each year thereafter until the end of the transformational period, the director shall submit electronically an annual report for the previous fiscal year to the Legislature. The report shall be on a fiscal year, accrual basis that satisfies the requirements set by the Governmental Accounting Standards Board. The director shall, on or before December 15 following the approval of the application, and on or before December 15 of each year thereafter, appear at a joint hearing of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Revenue Committee of the Legislature and present the report. Any supplemental information requested by three or more committee members shall be presented within thirty days after the request.</para><para>(2) The report shall state (a) the payment of matching funds made by the State of Nebraska, (b) the expected payments of matching funds still to be made by the State of Nebraska, and (c) the investments made in the project.</para><para>(3) The report shall provide an explanation of the audit and review processes of the Department of Economic Development in approving and rejecting the provision of matching funds and in enforcing matching funds repayment.</para><para>(4) No information shall be provided in the report or in supplemental information that is protected by state or federal confidentiality laws. The identity of private donors shall not be included in the report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 107; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 191. </para><operativedate>May 22, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>