
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id364"><amendatorysection statutenumber="81-1453" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1453</statuteno><catchline>Body-worn cameras; model policy; development and distribution; contents; law enforcement agency; duties.</catchline><para>(1) On or before December 1, 2016, the commission shall develop and distribute a model body-worn camera policy that includes the procedures and provisions required by section 81-1454. Any law enforcement agency required to adopt a policy under this section that does not develop and adopt its own policy shall adopt the model body-worn camera policy developed by the commission.</para><para>(2)(a) Any law enforcement agency which uses body-worn cameras as of July 21, 2016, shall, on or before January 1, 2017, adopt a written body-worn camera policy. Such policy shall include procedures and provisions in conformance with the minimum standards set forth in the model body-worn camera policy developed by the commission and may include any other procedures and provisions the law enforcement agency deems appropriate.</para><para>(b) Beginning January 1, 2017, any law enforcement agency which uses body-worn cameras shall, prior to commencing such use, adopt a written body-worn camera policy. Such policy shall include procedures and provisions in conformance with the minimum standards set forth in the model body-worn camera policy developed by the commission and may include any other procedures and provisions the law enforcement agency deems appropriate.</para><para>(3) The head of a law enforcement agency required to adopt a policy under this section shall provide a copy of such policy to the commission within three months of such policy's adoption.</para><para>(4) On or before January 1, 2018, and each January 1 thereafter, when any law enforcement agency required to adopt a policy under this section has made any change to its policy in the preceding year, the head of such agency shall provide an updated copy of such policy to the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1000, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>