<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1108.31"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1108.31</statuteno><catchline>State Capitol improvement district;
powers.</catchline><para>Whenever any improvement district for the opening,
widening, or otherwise improving Fifteenth Street in the city of Lincoln,
Nebraska, which connects, adjoins, and is adjacent to the State Capitol and
the University of Nebraska, is created by the Mayor and the City Council of
the city of Lincoln, Nebraska, the President of the Board of Regents of the
University of Nebraska and the State Capitol Administrator are hereby authorized
to sign petitions for the creation of an improvement district including that
portion of Fifteenth Street in Lincoln, Nebraska, leading from the State Capitol
to the university campus. This is for no other purpose than to form a plan
and program, with the gathering of data and cost for the improvement of that
portion of Fifteenth Street. Such plan shall be submitted electronically to the Legislature which shall render its approval
or rejection before any liability whatsoever for the consummation of such
plan shall be fixed or made. Neither the Board of Regents of the University
of Nebraska nor the administrator shall expend any money, nor shall the provisions
of this section be construed to authorize the expenditure of any public funds
whatsoever, except for the preliminary survey incident to the formation of
such improvement plans, until the same shall have been authorized by a specific
appropriation of the Legislature for the purpose based on the tentative plans
so formulated and submitted to the Legislature as contemplated in this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 147, &#167; 1, p. 396; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 72-801; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 72-712; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1048, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 182.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>