<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id48">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Department" id="id50" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-12,149"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,149</statuteno><catchline id="id53">Department;
allocate funds; qualified action plan; contents; powers of department.</catchline><para>(1) During each calendar year in which funds are available
from the Site and Building Development Fund for use by the Department of Economic
Development, the department shall allocate a specific amount of funds, not
less than forty percent, to nonmetropolitan areas. For purposes of this section,
nonmetropolitan areas means counties with fewer than one hundred thousand
inhabitants according to the most recent federal decennial census. In selecting
projects to receive fund assistance, the department shall develop a qualified
action plan by January 1 of each even-numbered year. The plan shall give first
priority to financially viable projects that have an agreement with a business
that will locate a site within ninety days of the signed agreement. The plan
shall set forth selection criteria to be used to determine priorities of the
fund which are appropriate to local conditions, including the community's
immediate need for site and building development, proposed increases in jobs
and investment, private dollars leveraged, level of local government support
and participation, and repayment, in part or in whole, of financial assistance
awarded by the fund. The Director of Economic Development shall
submit the plan to the Governor for approval.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall fund in order of priority as many
applications as will utilize available funds less actual administrative costs
of the department in administering the program. In administering the program
the department may contract for services or directly provide funds to other
governmental entities or instrumentalities.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB388, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB78, &#167; 14.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Enterprise Zone Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2101.01.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>