<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id830"><amendatorysection statutenumber="81-1229" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1229</statuteno><catchline>Workforce housing grant program; established; workforce housing grant; application; form; award; considerations; nonprofit organization; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall establish a workforce housing grant program to foster and support the development of workforce housing in rural communities.</para><para>(2) A nonprofit development organization may apply to the director for approval of a workforce housing grant for a workforce housing investment fund. The application shall be in a form and manner prescribed by the director. Through fiscal year 2020-21, grants shall be awarded by the director on a competitive basis until grant funds are no longer available. Grant maximums shall not exceed one million dollars to any one nonprofit development organization over a two-year period, with no more than two million dollars cumulative for any single grantee through fiscal year 2020-21. Grants shall require a minimum one-to-one in matching funds to be considered a qualified grant application. Unallocated workforce housing grant funds held by the department shall be rolled to the next program year.</para><para>(3) Grants shall be awarded based upon:</para><para>(a) A demonstrated and ongoing housing need as identified by a recent housing study;</para><para>(b) A community or region that has a low unemployment rate and is having difficulty attracting workers and filling employment positions;</para><para>(c) A community or region that exhibits a demonstrated commitment to growing its housing stock;</para><para>(d) Projects that can reasonably be ready for occupancy in a period of twenty-four months; and</para><para>(e) A demonstrated ability to grow and manage a workforce housing investment fund.</para><para>(4) A workforce housing investment fund shall be required to receive annual certification from the department.</para><para>(5) A nonprofit development organization shall:</para><para>(a) Invest or intend to invest in workforce housing eligible activities;</para><para>(b) Use any fees, interest, loan repayments, or other funds it received as a result of the administration of the grant to support qualified activities; and</para><para>(c) Have an active board of directors with expertise in development, construction, and finance that meets at least quarterly to approve all qualified investments made by the nonprofit development organization. A nonprofit development organization shall have a formal plan and proven expertise to invest unused workforce housing investment fund balances and shall have an annual audit of all financial records conducted by an independent certified public accountant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB518, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>