<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id46">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id48" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-12,160"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-12,160</statuteno><catchline>Financial assistance program to
commercialize product or process; established; purpose; funds; match required;
limitation.</catchline><para>(1)
The department shall establish a financial assistance program to provide financial
assistance to businesses operating in Nebraska that employ no more than five
hundred employees or to individuals that have a prototype of a product or
process for the purposes of commercializing such product or process. The applicant
shall submit a feasibility study stating the potential sales and profit projections
for the product or process.</para>
<para>(2) The department
shall create a program with the following provisions to support commercialization
of a product or process:</para><para>(a) Commercialization infrastructure documentation,
including market assessments and start-up strategic planning;</para>
<para>(b) Promotion,
marketing, advertising, and consulting;</para><para>(c) Management and business planning support;</para>
<para>(d) Linking
companies and entrepreneurs to mentors;</para><para>(e) Preparing companies and entrepreneurs
to acquire venture capital; and</para><para>(f) Linking companies to sources of capital.</para>
<para>(3) Funds
shall be matched by nonstate funds equal to fifty percent of the funds requested.
Matching funds may be from any nonstate source, including private foundations,
federal or local government sources, quasi-governmental entities, or commercial
lending institutions, or any other funds whose source does not include funds
appropriated by the Legislature.</para><para>(4) The department shall not provide more
than five hundred thousand dollars to any one project, and such financial
assistance shall not exceed fifty percent of the cost of the project. The
department shall not award more than two million dollars per year for financial
assistance under this section.</para><para>(5) Financial assistance provided under
this section shall be expended within twenty-four months after the date of
the awarding decision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB387, &#167; 9.</para><terminationdate>December 1, 2021</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>