<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id27" statutenumber="81-15,174"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,174</statuteno><catchline id="id30">Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund is created. The fund shall be maintained in the state accounting system as a cash fund. Except as otherwise provided in this section, the fund shall be used to carry out the purposes of the Nebraska Environmental Trust Act, including the payment of administrative costs. Money in the fund shall include proceeds credited pursuant to section 9-812 and proceeds designated by the board pursuant to section 81-15,173. Transfers may be made from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund to the Water Resources Cash Fund at the direction of the Legislature, and any money so transferred shall be expended in accordance with section 81-15,168. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 957, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 408, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 111; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB229, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 42. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Water Resources Cash Fund,</emphasis> see section 61-218.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>