<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,170"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,170</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Environmental Trust Board; created; membership; qualifications; executive director.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Environmental Trust Board is hereby created as an entity of the executive branch. The board shall consist of the Director of Environmental Quality, the Director of Natural Resources, the Director of Agriculture, the secretary of the Game and Parks Commission, the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee, and nine citizens appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature. The citizen members shall begin serving immediately following notice of nomination and prior to approval by the Legislature. The citizen members shall represent the general public and shall have demonstrated competence, experience, and interest in the environment of the state. Two of the citizen appointees shall also have experience with private financing of public-purpose projects. Three appointees shall be chosen from each of the three congressional districts. The board shall hire an executive director who shall hire and supervise other staff members as may be authorized by the board. The executive director shall serve at the pleasure of the board and be solely responsible to it. The Game and Parks Commission shall provide administrative support, including, but not limited to, payroll and accounting functions, to the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 869; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 248; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 758.</para></source></law></legaldoc>