<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id735">
<sectno id="id736">Sec. 77.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id737" statutenumber="81-15,121"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id739">81-15,121</statuteno><catchline id="id740">Tanks; permit;
when required; fees; application; Underground Storage Tank Fund; created;
investment.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not (a) maintain
or use any tank for the storage of regulated substances, (b) install any new
tank, or (c) permanently close a tank without first securing a permit from
the State Fire Marshal.</para>
<para>(2) A fee shall not be charged for a permit under subdivision
(1)(a) or (c) of this section. The fee for a permit for installation shall
be fifty dollars. The State Fire Marshal shall remit the fee to the State
Treasurer for credit to the Underground Storage Tank Fund.</para>
<para>(3) All owners of operating tanks, except those provided
for in subsection (4) of this section, shall annually register each tank.
All registration permits shall expire on December 31 of the year for which
the permit was issued. The registration fee shall be thirty dollars per tank.
The State Fire Marshal shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Underground Storage Tank Fund. Such permits shall contain the information
specified in subsection (5) of this section.</para>
<para>(4) In the case of tanks permanently abandoned on or after
January 1, 1974, an annual permit shall not be required and an initial registration
permit shall be sufficient.</para>
<para>(5) The application for a registration permit shall be provided
by and filed with the State Fire Marshal's office and shall require, but not
be limited to, the following information:</para>
<para>(a) The date the tank was placed in or taken out of operation;</para>
<para>(b) The age of the tank;</para>
<para>(c) The size, type, and location of the tank; and</para>
<para>(d) The type of substances stored in the tank and the quantity
of such substances remaining in the tank if the tank has been permanently
closed.</para>
<para>(6) The registration permit fee collected pursuant to this
section shall be deposited in the Underground Storage Tank Fund which is hereby
created as a cash fund. The fund shall also consist of any money appropriated
to the fund by the state. The fund shall be administered by the State Fire
Marshal to carry out the purposes of the Petroleum Products and Hazardous
Substances Storage and Handling Act. Transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any
money in the Underground Storage Tank Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 217, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 365, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 816, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 120; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 77.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>