<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id114" statutenumber="81-1414.07"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1414.07</statuteno><catchline>Continuing education requirements; course offerings.</catchline><para>(1)(a) In order to maintain his or her professional status and serve the law enforcement profession, the community, and the residents of Nebraska, each law enforcement officer, other than a noncertified conditional officer, shall attend continuing education courses for the number of hours required in subdivision (1)(b) of this section in the areas of criminal justice and law enforcement during each calendar year beginning on January 1 and ending on December 31. A law enforcement officer is not required to meet the continuing education requirements in the year in which he or she first becomes fully certified. A law enforcement officer may retire from service in good standing without meeting the continuing education requirements in the calendar year of the officer's retirement.</para><para>(b) The number of continuing education hours required under this subsection shall be:</para><para>(i) Until January 1, 2022, twenty hours;</para><para>(ii) Beginning January 1, 2022, and until January 1, 2023, twenty-eight hours; and</para><para>(iii) Beginning January 1, 2023, thirty-two hours.</para><para>(2) The annual continuing education required by this section shall include:</para><para>(a) Refresher courses on de-escalation, mental health, and substance abuse issues;</para><para>(b) A minimum of two hours of anti-bias and implicit bias training;</para><para>(c) Firearms;</para><para>(d) Officer wellness;</para><para>(e) Legal updates, including, but not limited to, legislative changes and First Amendment and Fourth Amendment issues;</para><para>(f) Vehicular pursuit policy review; and</para><para>(g) Any other training as determined by a law enforcement agency.</para><para>(3) Continuing education courses may be offered in the form of seminars, advanced education which may include college or university classes, conferences, instruction conducted within the law enforcement officer's law enforcement agency, or instruction conducted over the Internet. Continuing education shall be of a type which has application to and seeks to maintain and improve the skills of the law enforcement officer in carrying out his or her duties and responsibilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB817, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB924, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1241, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>April 19, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>