<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1318"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1318</statuteno><catchline>State Personnel Board; created; members; appointment; term; powers.</catchline><para>There is hereby created a State Personnel Board composed of five persons appointed by the Governor subject to confirmation by the Legislature. Not more than three of the members shall be members of the same political party. Each board member shall retain his or her position until resignation or until a successor is appointed at the expiration of the member's appointive term. Any member of the board may be removed by the Governor, upon notice and hearing as determined by the Governor, for neglect of duty or malfeasance in office, but for no other cause. New members shall be appointed for terms of five years, except that any person chosen to fill a vacancy shall be appointed only for the unexpired term of the member succeeded. State employees covered by sections 81-1301 to 81-1319 shall not be appointed to the State Personnel Board. At least three appointees to the board shall have experience in personnel administration, business or public administration, labor relations, or law. The board, by majority vote, shall designate one member to serve as chairperson. The principal office and business address of the board shall be the personnel division of the Department of Administrative Services in Lincoln, Nebraska, but the board may meet and exercise any or all of its powers at any other location.</para><para>The board may delegate to a group of three or more members any or all of the powers which it may exercise. The board shall be authorized to designate and delegate its powers under section 81-1318.01 to hearing officers to conduct grievance appeal hearings and recommend a decision to the board for final action. A vacancy in the board shall not impair the right of the remaining members to exercise all the powers of the board, and three members of the board shall at all times constitute a quorum of the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 802, &#167; 9, p. 3026; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 545, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 491, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 14, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 314, &#167; 17. </para></source></law></legaldoc>