<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1108.15"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1108.15</statuteno><catchline>State building division; functions and responsibilities; facilities planning, construction, and administration.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in the Nebraska State Capitol Preservation and Restoration Act, the division shall have the primary functions and responsibilities of statewide facilities planning, facilities construction, and facilities administration and shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para><para>(2) Facilities planning shall include the following responsibilities and duties:</para><para>(a) To maintain utilization records of all state-owned, state-occupied, and vacant facilities;</para><para>(b) To coordinate comprehensive capital facilities planning;</para><para>(c) To define and review program statements based on space utilization standards;</para><para>(d) To prepare or review planning and construction documents;</para><para>(e) To develop and maintain time-cost schedules for capital construction projects;</para><para>(f) To assist the Governor and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst in the preparation of the capital construction budget recommendations;</para><para>(g) To maintain a complete inventory of all state-owned, state-occupied, and vacant sites and structures and to review the proposals for naming such sites and structures;</para><para>(h) To determine space needs of all state agencies and establish space-allocation standards; and</para><para>(i) To cause a state comprehensive capital facilities plan to be developed.</para><para>(3) Facilities construction shall include the following powers and duties:</para><para>(a) To maintain close contact with and conduct inspections of each project so as to assure execution of time-cost schedules and efficient contract performance if such project's total design and construction cost is equal to or greater than the project cost set by subdivision (1)(a) of section 81-1108.43 as adjusted by subsection (2) of section 81-1108.43;</para><para>(b) To perform final acceptance inspections and evaluations; and</para><para>(c) To coordinate all change or modification orders and progress payment orders.</para><para>(4) Facilities administration shall include the following powers and duties:</para><para>(a) To serve as state leasing administrator or agent for all facilities to be leased for use by the state and for all state-owned facilities to be rented to state agencies or other parties subject to section 81-1108.22. The division shall remit the proceeds from any rentals of state-owned facilities to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Building Revolving Fund and the State Building Renewal Assessment Fund;</para><para>(b) To provide all maintenance, repairs, custodial duties, security, and administration for all buildings and grounds owned or leased by the State of Nebraska except as provided in subsections (5) and (6) of this section;</para><para>(c) To be responsible for adequate parking and the designation of parking stalls or spaces, including access aisles, in offstreet parking facilities for the exclusive use of handicapped or disabled or temporarily handicapped or disabled persons pursuant to section 18-1737;</para><para>(d) To ensure that all state-owned, state-occupied, and vacant facilities are maintained or utilized to their maximum capacity or to dispose of such facilities through lease, sale, or demolition;</para><para>(e) To submit electronically an annual report to the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Committee on Building Maintenance regarding the amount of property leased by the state and the availability of state-owned property for the needs of state agencies;</para><para>(f) To report monthly time-cost data on projects to the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature. The report submitted to the Clerk of the Legislature shall be submitted electronically;</para><para>(g) To administer the State Emergency Capital Construction Contingency Fund;</para><para>(h) To submit status reports to the Governor and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst after each quarter of a construction project is completed detailing change orders and expenditures to date. The report submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically. Such reports shall be required on all projects costing an amount equal to or greater than the amount set forth in subdivision (1)(a) of section 81-1108.43 as adjusted by subsection (2) of section 81-1108.43 and on such other projects as may be designated by the division; and</para><para>(i) To submit a final report on each project to the Governor and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The report submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically. Such report shall include, but not be limited to, a comparison of final costs and appropriations made for the project, change orders, and modifications and whether the construction complied with the related approved program statement. Such reports shall be required on all projects costing an amount equal to or greater than the amount set forth in subdivision (1)(a) of section 81-1108.43 as adjusted by subsection (2) of section 81-1108.43 and on such other projects as may be designated by the division.</para><para>(5) Subdivisions (4)(b), (c), and (d) of this section shall not apply to (a) state-owned facilities to be rented to state agencies or other parties by the University of Nebraska, the Nebraska state colleges, the Department of Transportation, and the Board of Educational Lands and Funds, (b) buildings and grounds owned or leased for use by the University of Nebraska, the Nebraska state colleges, and the Board of Educational Lands and Funds, (c) buildings and grounds owned, leased, or operated by the Department of Correctional Services, (d) facilities to be leased for nonoffice use by the Department of Transportation, (e) buildings or grounds owned or leased by the Game and Parks Commission if the application of such subdivisions to the buildings or grounds would result in ineligibility for or repayment of federal funding, (f) buildings or grounds of the state park system, state recreation areas, state historical parks, state wildlife management areas, or state recreational trails, or (g) other buildings or grounds owned or leased by the State of Nebraska which are specifically exempted by the division because the application of such subdivisions would result in the ineligibility for federal funding or would result in hardship on an agency, board, or commission due to other exceptional or unusual circumstances, except that nothing in this subdivision shall prohibit the assessment of building rental depreciation charges to tenants of facilities owned by the state and under the direct control and maintenance of the division.</para><para>(6) Security for all buildings and grounds owned or leased by the State of Nebraska in Lincoln, Nebraska, except the buildings and grounds described in subsection (5) of this section, shall be the responsibility of the Nebraska State Patrol. The Nebraska State Patrol shall consult with the Governor, the Chief Justice, the Executive Board of the Legislative Council, and the State Capitol Administrator regarding security policy within the State Capitol and capitol grounds.</para><para>(7) Each member of the Legislature shall receive an electronic copy of the reports required by subdivisions (4)(f), (h), and (i) of this section by making a request for them to the State Building Administrator. The information on such reports shall be submitted to the division by the agency responsible for the project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 1048, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 1006, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 32, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1241, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 530, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 299, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1216, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 666, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 809, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 180; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB978, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB320, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 285. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Capitol Preservation and Restoration Act,</emphasis> see section 72-2201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>