<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id972"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1414.18"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1414.18</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement agencies; accreditation required; Nebraska Police Improvement and Professionalism Fund; created; use; investment; grant program for accreditation costs.</catchline><para>(1)(a) On or before January 1, 2023, each law enforcement agency shall be accredited in a manner approved by the commission. A law enforcement agency shall not be accredited unless it has adopted written policies as determined by the commission and met other requirements as determined by the commission.</para><para>(b) Beginning January 1, 2023, the commission shall post on its website a list of all law enforcement agencies that are not accredited as required by this subsection. The commission shall update the list at least annually, and more frequently as the commission deems necessary.</para><para>(c) A law enforcement agency that is not accredited as required by this subsection shall be ineligible to receive loans, grants, funds, or donations administered by the commission until the commission determines that such agency has been properly accredited.</para><para>(2) The commission shall develop accreditation requirements. The commission may provide its own accreditation program and may approve accreditations provided by third-party providers.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska Police Improvement and Professionalism Fund is created. The fund shall be used to provide grants as provided in subsection (4) of this section. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund any funds transferred or appropriated to the fund by the Legislature and funds received as gifts or grants or other private or public funds obtained for the purposes set forth in this section. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(4) The commission shall develop a grant program to award grants to law enforcement agencies to pay for costs of accreditation incurred pursuant to this section. In awarding such grants, the commission shall prioritize smaller law enforcement agencies.</para><para>(5) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 17. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>