<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1505.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1505.06</statuteno><catchline>Air quality construction permit; fees; Air Quality Permit Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2005, each application for an air quality construction permit required by rules and regulations adopted pursuant to subsection (12) of section 81-1505 shall be accompanied by an application fee. If fees are required under more than one subdivision of this subsection, the application shall be accompanied by the one fee which is the highest of the applicable fees. The application fee shall be based on potential to emit, as defined in such rules and regulations, in accordance with the following schedule:</para><para>(a) Three thousand dollars for facilities that directly emit or have the potential to emit one hundred tons per year or more of any air pollutant, except hazardous air pollutants;</para><para>(b) Three thousand dollars for facilities that directly emit or have the potential to emit ten tons per year or more of any single hazardous air pollutant or twenty-five tons per year or more of any combination of hazardous air pollutants;</para><para>(c) One thousand five hundred dollars for facilities that directly emit or have the potential to emit fifty tons per year or more but less than one hundred tons per year of any air pollutant, except hazardous air pollutants;</para><para>(d) One thousand five hundred dollars for facilities that directly emit or have the potential to emit (i) two and one-half tons per year or more but less than ten tons per year of any single hazardous air pollutant or (ii) ten tons per year or more but less than twenty-five tons per year of any combination of hazardous air pollutants;</para><para>(e) Two hundred fifty dollars for facilities that directly emit or have the potential to emit less than fifty tons per year of any air pollutant, except hazardous air pollutants; and</para><para>(f) Two hundred fifty dollars for facilities that directly emit or have the potential to emit (i) less than two and one-half tons per year of any single hazardous air pollutant and (ii) less than ten tons per year of any combination of hazardous air pollutants.</para><para>(2) All application fees collected under this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Air Quality Permit Cash Fund, which fund is hereby created. The Air Quality Permit Cash Fund shall be used for purposes identified in subsection (12) of section 81-1505. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, (a) air pollutant means particulate matter with a diameter of ten microns or less, sulfur dioxide or sulfur trioxide or any combination of the two, oxides of nitrogen, volatile organic compounds, and carbon monoxide and (b) hazardous air pollutant means any pollutant defined as such in rules and regulations adopted pursuant to subsection (12) of section 81-1505.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 449, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>