
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1174"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1174</statuteno><catchline>Reimbursement for expenses; request; contents; automobile; airplane; statement required; receipts; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any state officer, state employee, or member of any commission, council, committee, or board of the state is seeking reimbursement for expenses incurred by him or her in the line of duty, he or she shall be required to present a request for payment or reimbursement to the Director of Administrative Services not later than sixty days after the final day on which expenses were incurred for which reimbursement is sought.</para><para>(2)(a) Each request for reimbursement of travel and lodging expenses shall be fully itemized, including the amount, date, place, and essential character of the expense incurred.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided by subdivision (c) of this subsection, section 50-415, or Supreme Court rule, each request for any meal expense incurred during travel status shall be paid or reimbursed pursuant to a percentage of the per diem rates of the federal General Services Administration for travel within the contiguous United States, the United States Department of Defense for travel within Alaska, Hawaii, or a United States territory or possession, and the United States Department of State for foreign travel, as determined by and in accordance with policies established by the Director of Administrative Services. Such percentage shall not exceed one hundred percent nor be less than sixty percent of the federal per diem rate. Any meal expense charged directly to and paid for by the state shall be identified on the request for reimbursement and deducted from the per diem based on the percentage established for the meal provided.</para><para>(c) A member of the Nebraska State Patrol shall be reimbursed one hundred percent of the per diem rate established in subdivision (b) of this subsection, except that a member serving on a detail in executive protection shall be reimbursed in full for actual meal expenses incurred by the member if the expenses exceed one hundred percent of the established per diem rate.</para><para>(3) When reimbursement is requested for mileage by automobile, air travel by commercial carrier, air travel in airplanes chartered by the department or agency, or air travel by personally rented airplane, the points between which such travel occurred, the times of arrival and departure, and the necessity and purpose of such travel shall be stated on such request. When reimbursement is requested for mileage by automobile, the motor vehicle license plate number, the total miles traveled, and the rate per mile being requested shall also be shown on each request.</para><para>(4) The Accounting Administrator may require less supporting detail for requests covered in this section but shall not impose reporting requirements which exceed those listed unless specifically authorized by other provisions of law. No request shall be submitted by an individual for an expense when such expense has been paid by the agency or department concerned.</para><para>(5) When reimbursement for expenses incurred in air travel by privately owned airplane is requested, the cost of operating the airplane at rates per mile as established by the Department of Administrative Services shall be shown on such request. Travel by privately owned airplane or personally rented airplane shall only be authorized when it is more economical than surface transportation or will result in a substantial savings of expense or productive time.</para><para>(6) The statement of expenses shall be duly verified and supported by receipts for all of such expenditures for which reimbursement is requested except for (a) items reimbursed through a per diem payment and (b) immaterial items identified by the director.</para><para>(7) No charge for mileage shall be allowed when such mileage accrues while using an automobile owned by the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(8) No personal maintenance expenses shall be allowed to any state officer, state employee, or member of any commission, council, committee, or board of the state when such expenses are incurred in the city or village in which the residence or primary work location of such individual is located, except that individuals required to attend official functions, conferences, or hearings within such location, not to include normal day-to-day operations of the department, agency, commission, council, committee, or board, may be paid or reimbursed in accordance with policies established by the Director of Administrative Services. The approval to attend a function, conference, or hearing shall be obtained from the director of the department, agency, commission, council, committee, or board prior to an individual's attendance at such function, conference, or hearing.</para><para>(9) Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit the furnishing of coffee, tea, and any similar beverage by the Legislature or the Legislative Council to its employees or guests.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 180, &#167; 10, p. 706; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 84-306; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 84-306; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 253, &#167; 1, p. 790; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 286, &#167; 2, p. 985; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 243, &#167; 4(2), p. 660; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 568, &#167; 1, p. 1854; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 365, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 869, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 576, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 578, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 663, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 413, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1986, &#167; 84-306.01; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 32, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 292, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB533, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 111; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB964, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>