<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id14" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-1210.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>81-1210.02</statuteno><catchline>Interns; job training grants;
internships; application; certification; grants; limitation; department; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The intent
of sections 81-1210.01 to 81-1210.03 is to connect Nebraska students pursuing
postsecondary degrees with targeted industries in order to retain such students
and attract workers to Nebraska by assisting companies willing to provide
paid internships.</para>
<para>(2) An eligible
company may apply to the department for a job training grant to assist in
the hiring of an intern if:</para><para>(a) The company certifies that the internship meets the definition
of internship in section 81-1210.01;</para><para>(b) The internship pays at least the federal
minimum wage;</para><para>(c) The intern will work a minimum of two hundred hours in a twelve-week
period but no more than one thousand hours in a fifty-week period; and</para>
<para>(d) The intern applies
for the internship prior to graduation, even though the internship may be
completed after graduation.</para><para>(3) The department may provide a job training grant of up to the
lesser of forty percent of the cost of the internship or three thousand five
hundred dollars, except that if the internship is in a distressed area, the
job training grant may be up to the lesser of sixty percent of the cost of
the internship or five thousand dollars.</para><para>(4) An eligible company may apply for no
more than two job training grants for the same intern, shall not be awarded
more than five job training grants at any one location in any twelve-month
period, and shall not be awarded more than ten job training grants total in
any twelve-month period.</para><para>(5) An eligible company may allow an intern to telecommute if the
eligible company is located more than thirty miles from the college or university
in which the intern is enrolled and if the college or university is in Nebraska.</para>
<para>(6) The department
shall, to the extent possible, assure that the distribution of job training
grants under sections 81-1210.01 to 81-1210.03 provides equitable access to
the grants by all geographic areas of the state.</para><para>(7) The department shall
not allocate more than one million five hundred thousand dollars in each of
FY2011-12 and FY2012-13 from the Job Training Cash Fund for purposes of this
section. The department may receive funds from public, private, or other sources
for purposes of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB386, &#167; 2.</para><operativedate>June 1, 2011</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>