<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id156"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1414.16"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1414.16</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officer; chokehold prohibited; carotid restraint control hold prohibited; exceptions; report required.</catchline><para>(1) Except when the use of deadly force is authorized, a law enforcement officer shall not intentionally use a chokehold on any person.</para><para>(2) A law enforcement officer shall not intentionally use a carotid restraint control hold on any person unless:</para><para>(a) Either:</para><para>(i) The officer reasonably believes that the person will otherwise cause death or serious bodily injury to any person, including a law enforcement officer or noncertified conditional officer;</para><para>(ii) The person is actively resisting arrest in a manner that poses a risk of bodily injury to the officer or any other person; or</para><para>(iii) Deadly force is otherwise authorized; and</para><para>(b) The officer has been trained on the use of such hold.</para><para>(3) Following use of a carotid restraint control hold, a law enforcement officer shall create a report of the incident that articulates in detail the events leading to and following the use of such hold.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Bodily injury has the same meaning as in section 28-109;</para><para>(b) Carotid restraint control hold means utilizing bilateral pressure to the sides of a person's neck, restricting the flow of oxygenated blood to the brain;</para><para>(c) Chokehold means intentionally applying pressure to the front of the throat and cutting off air flow for a sustained amount of time; and</para><para>(d) Serious bodily injury has the same meaning as in section 28-109.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>