<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-1118"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1118</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Materiel division; established; duties; administrator; branches; established.</catchline><para id="id00">The materiel division of the Department of Administrative Services is hereby established and shall be managed by the materiel administrator.</para><para id="id00">There are hereby established the following seven branches of the materiel division of the Department of Administrative Services which shall have the following duties, powers, and responsibilities:</para><para id="id00">(1) The office supplies bureau shall be responsible for providing office supplies, paper, and forms to using agencies;</para><para id="id00">(2) Central mail shall be responsible for all mailing operations, transportation of material, tracking shipments, and making freight claims;</para><para id="id00">(3) The print shop shall be responsible for specifications and for receiving bids and placing orders to the lowest and best commercial bidder for all printing and reproduction operations for the state. The print shop shall also be responsible for coordinating all existing printing and reproduction operations of the state;</para><para id="id00">(4) Copy services shall be responsible for the purchasing and placement of all copier requirements;</para><para id="id00">(5) The state purchasing bureau shall be responsible for all purchases by all state agencies other than the University of Nebraska. The materiel division shall administer the public notice and bidding procedures and any other areas designated by the Director of Administrative Services to carry out the lease or purchase of personal property. All purchases of and contracts for materials, supplies, or equipment and all leases of personal property shall be made in the following manner except in emergencies approved by the Governor:</para><para id="id00">(a) By a competitive formal sealed bidding process through the materiel division in all cases in which the purchases are of estimated value exceeding fifty thousand dollars;</para><para id="id00">(b) By a competitive informal bidding process through the materiel division in all cases in which the purchases are of estimated value equal to or exceeding twenty-five thousand dollars but equal to or less than fifty thousand dollars;</para><para id="id00">(c) By unrestricted open market purchases through the materiel division in all cases in which purchases are of estimated value of less than twenty-five thousand dollars;</para><para id="id00">(d) All requisitions for whatever purpose coming to the state purchasing bureau shall be in conformance with the approved budget of the requisitioning department or agency;</para><para id="id00">(e) All contracts for purchases and leases shall be bid as a single whole item. In no case shall contracts be divided or fractionated in order to produce several contracts which are of an estimated value below that required for competitive bidding; and</para><para>(f) No contract for purchase or lease shall be amended to extend the duration of the contract for a period of more than fifty percent of the initial contract term. Following the adoption of any amendment to extend the contract for a period of fifty percent or less of the initial contract term, no further extensions of the original contract shall be permitted. This subdivision (f) does not prohibit the exercise of any renewal option expressly provided in the original contract;</para><para id="id00">(6) The state recycling office shall be responsible for the administration and operation of the State Government Recycling Management Act; and</para><para id="id00">(7) State surplus property shall be responsible for the disposition of the state's surplus property and the maintenance of all inventory records.</para><para id="id00">Nothing in this section shall be construed to require that works of art must be procured through the materiel division.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 18, p. 1705; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 780, &#167; 4, p. 2955; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1054, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 359, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 447, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 381, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1241, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 314, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 626, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB151, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB320, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Government Recycling Management Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1183.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>