<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id256" statutenumber="81-1425"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1425</statuteno><catchline id="id259">Executive director; powers; duties.</catchline><para>The executive director of the commission shall:</para><para>(1) Supervise and be responsible for the administration of the policies established by the commission;</para><para>(2) Establish a Jail Standards subdivision and a Community Corrections Division within the commission and establish, consolidate, or abolish any administrative subdivision within the commission and appoint and remove for cause the heads thereof, and delegate appropriate powers and duties to them;</para><para>(3) Establish and administer projects and programs for the operation of the commission;</para><para>(4) Appoint and remove employees of the commission and delegate appropriate powers and duties to them;</para><para>(5) Make rules and regulations for the management and the administration of policies of the commission and the conduct of employees under his or her jurisdiction;</para><para>(6) Collect, develop, maintain, and analyze statistical information, records, and reports as the commission may determine relevant to its functions, including, but not limited to, the statistical information set forth in section 47-627;</para><para>(7) Transmit monthly to the commission a report of the operations of the commission for the preceding calendar month;</para><para>(8) Execute and carry out the provisions of all contracts, leases, and agreements authorized by the commission with agencies of federal, state, or local government, corporations, or persons;</para><para>(9) Perform such additional duties as may be assigned to him or her by the commission, by the chairperson of the commission, or by law;</para><para>(10) Appoint and remove for cause the director of the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center;</para><para>(11) Appoint and remove for cause the director of the Office of Violence Prevention;</para><para>(12) Subpoena witnesses and documents, files, internal investigation materials, administrative files, records, memoranda, reports, personnel records, disciplinary histories, or any materials the executive director determines to be relevant, relating to law enforcement officer certification revocation, from the Nebraska State Patrol; and</para><para>(13) Exercise all powers and perform all duties necessary and proper in carrying out his or her responsibilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 774, &#167; 11, p. 2935; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 328, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1008, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB390, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB791, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>