<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id627"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,320"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,320</statuteno><catchline>Battery stewardship organization; promotional activities.</catchline><para>A battery stewardship organization implementing a battery stewardship plan approved under section 81-15,317 shall do all of the following to promote the implementation of the plan:</para><para>(1) Develop and maintain a website;</para><para>(2) Develop and place advertisements on social media or other relevant media platforms;</para><para>(3) Develop promotional materials about the program and about the restrictions on disposing of covered batteries under section 81-15,325;</para><para>(4) Develop and distribute collection site safety training procedures to collection sites to help ensure proper management of covered batteries at collection sites;</para><para>(5) Provide consumer-focused educational materials, to each collection site used under the plan, that are accessible by customers of retailers that sell covered batteries or battery containing products;</para><para>(6) Provide safety information related to covered battery collection activities to the operator of each collection site used under the plan, including appropriate protocols to reduce risks of spills or fires, to respond to a spill or fire, and to manage a collected damaged or defective battery;</para><para>(7) Provide educational materials to the operator of each collection site used under the plan for the management of recalled batteries;</para><para>(8) Upon request by a retailer or other potential collection site, provide educational materials describing collection opportunities for covered batteries;</para><para>(9) Coordinate with other battery stewardship organizations implementing a battery stewardship plan in providing education and outreach under this section; and</para><para>(10) Conduct a survey, during the first year of implementing a battery stewardship plan and once every five years thereafter, of public awareness of the outreach efforts undertaken pursuant to this section. The battery stewardship organization shall share the results of the surveys with the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB36, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>