<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,103</statuteno><catchline>Council; financial requirements; adopt rules and regulations; remedial cleanup costs; Radiation Site Closure and Reclamation Fund; Radiation Custodial Care Fund; created; use; investment; agreement with Department of Health and Human Services.</catchline><para>(1) For licensed activities involving disposal of low-level radioactive waste, the council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations which require a licensee to provide an adequate surety or other financial arrangement sufficient to accomplish any necessary corrective action or cleanup on real or personal property caused by releases of radiation from a disposal site during the operational life and closure period of the facility and to comply with the requirements for decontamination, decommissioning, site closure, and stabilization of sites, and structures and equipment used in conjunction with such licensed activity, in the event the licensee abandons the facility or defaults for any reason in performing its operational, closure, or other requirements. Such sureties required under the license shall be compatible with applicable federal financial assurance regulations and shall be reviewed by the department at the time of license review under subsection (1) of section 81-15,106. Any arrangement which constitutes self-insurance shall not be allowed. In addition to the surety requirements, the licensee shall purchase property and third-party liability insurance and pay the necessary periodic premiums at all times in such amounts as determined by the council pursuant to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal Act.</para><para>(2) All sureties required pursuant to subsection (1) of this section which are forfeited shall be paid to the department and remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Radiation Site Closure and Reclamation Fund which is hereby created. Any money in the fund may be expended by the department as necessary to complete the requirements on which licensees have defaulted. Money in this fund shall not be used for normal operating expenses of the department. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) For licensed activities involving the disposal of low-level radioactive waste, the council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations which require a licensee, before termination of the license, to make available such funding arrangements as may be necessary to provide for custodial care.</para><para>(4)(a) Remedial cleanup costs which become necessary during the operational life and closure of the facility shall be the responsibility of the licensed facility operator either directly or through applicable surety bonds, insurance, and other financial arrangements required pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, and (b) any remaining remedial cleanup costs which become necessary during the operational life and closure of the facility and which exceed funds available under subdivision (a) of this subsection shall be assessed proportionately by waste volume against the generators, then proportionately by waste volume against the party states as provided by the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact.</para><para>(5) Remedial cleanup costs which become necessary during the period of custodial care shall be assessed (a) first, against the funds established pursuant to this section and any surety bonds, insurance, or other financial arrangements established for the facility, excluding such funds reserved for custodial care, (b) second, against the licensed facility operator, (c) third, against the generators based on proportionate waste volume, and (d) fourth, against the party states based on proportionate waste volume as provided by the Central Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact.</para><para>(6) All funds collected from licensees pursuant to subsection (3) of this section and subsection (1) of section 81-15,101 shall be paid to the department and remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Radiation Custodial Care Fund which is hereby created. All interest accrued on money deposited in the fund may be expended by the department for the continuing custodial care, maintenance, and other care of facilities from which such funds are collected as necessary for protection of the public health, safety, and environment. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(7) The department may, by contract, agreement, lease, or license with the Department of Health and Human Services, provide for the decontamination, closure, decommissioning, reclamation, surveillance, or other care of a site subject to this section as needed to carry out the purposes of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 491, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 426, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 127; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 868; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1201, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 757.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>