<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1120</statuteno><catchline>Materiel Division Revolving Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Materiel Division Revolving Fund. The fund shall be administered by the materiel division of the Department of Administrative Services. The fund shall consist of (a) fees paid for printing, copying, central supply, and mailing services provided to state agencies and local subdivisions by the division, (b) assessments charged by the materiel administrator to state agencies, boards, and commissions for purchasing services provided by the division, and (c) any money collected pursuant to subdivision (10) of section 81-153. Such assessments shall be adequate to cover actual and necessary expenses that are associated with providing the service and not otherwise covered by the money collected pursuant to subdivision (10) of section 81-153. The fund shall be used to pay for expenses incurred by the division to provide such services.</para><para>(2) State agencies, boards, and commissions shall make the materiel division assessment payments to the fund no later than August 1 of each year, or in four equal payments to be made no later than August 1, October 1, February 1, and April 1 of each year, at the discretion of the materiel administrator.</para><para>(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1194, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 119; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 424, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1037, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>