<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,159" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,159</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings and intent; state purchases; preference requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature hereby finds and declares that:</para><para>(a) Some landfills operating with or without a permit in Nebraska exhibit numerous operational and management practices which are inconsistent with proper landfill management and permit requirements, and the owners and operators of such landfills should be encouraged to cooperate and work with the Department of Environment and Energy to ensure that the air, land, and water of this state are not polluted;</para><para>(b) Some landfills in Nebraska are reaching capacity and the siting of a new location can be a financially expensive and socially disruptive process, and because of this situation all Nebraska citizens and businesses are encouraged to implement waste reduction measures that will result in a reduction of waste entering landfills by at least twenty-five percent;</para><para>(c) Recycling and waste reduction are necessary components of any well-managed waste management system and can extend the lifespan of a landfill and provide alternative waste management options; and</para><para>(d) The state can encourage recycling by the example of its own purchase and use of recycled and recyclable materials. The state can also encourage recycling and waste reduction by the creation of funding grants which support existing and future waste management systems.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature that the state, as a major consumer and an example for others, should assist resource recovery by making a concerted effort to use recyclable and recycled products and encourage other levels of government and the private sector to follow its example. When purchasing products, materials, or supplies for use by the State of Nebraska, the Department of Administrative Services, the University of Nebraska, and any other state agency making such purchases shall give preference to and purchase products, materials, and supplies which are manufactured or produced from recycled material or which can be readily reused or recycled after their normal use. Preference shall also be given to the purchase of corn-based biodegradable plastics and road deicers, depending on the availability and suitability of such products. Such preference shall not operate when it would result in the purchase of products, materials, or supplies which are of inadequate quality or substantially higher cost.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 163, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 129. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>