<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-1603"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1603</statuteno><catchline id="id00">State Energy Office; powers; enumerated.</catchline><para>The office shall have the power to do such things as are necessary to carry out sections 81-1601 to 81-1605, including but not limited to the following:</para><para>(1) To adopt rules and regulations, pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act, to carry out the purposes of sections 81-1601 to 81-1605;</para><para>(2) To make all contracts pursuant to sections 81-1601 to 81-1605 and do all things to cooperate with the federal government, and to qualify for, accept, expend, and dispense public or private funds intended for the implementation of sections 81-1601 to 81-1605;</para><para>(3) To contract for services, if such work or services cannot be satisfactorily performed by employees of the agency or by any other part of state government;</para><para>(4) To enter into such agreements as are necessary to carry out energy research and development with other states;</para><para>(5) To carry out the duties and responsibilities relating to energy as may be requested or required of the state by the federal government;</para><para>(6) To cooperate and participate with the approval of the Governor in the activities of organizations of states relating to the availability, conservation, development, and distribution of energy;</para><para>(7) To engage in such activities as will seek to insure that the State of Nebraska and its citizens receive an equitable share of energy supplies at a fair price; and</para><para>(8) To form advisory committees of citizens of Nebraska to advise the director of the energy office on programs and policies relating to energy and to assist in implementing such programs. Such committees shall be of a temporary nature and no member shall receive any compensation for serving on any such committee but, with the approval of the Governor, members shall receive reimbursement for actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The minutes of meetings of and actions taken by each committee shall be kept and a record shall be maintained of the name, address, and occupation or vocation of every individual serving on any committee. Such minutes and records shall be maintained in the State Energy Office and shall be available for public inspection during regular office hours.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 232, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 198; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB469, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>