<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id34" statutenumber="81-15,175"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,175</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Fund allocations;
board; powers and duties; grant
award to Water Resources Cash Fund; payments; legislative intent; additional
grant; additional reporting.</catchline><para>(1) The
board may make an annual allocation each fiscal year from the Nebraska Environmental
Trust Fund to the Nebraska Environmental Endowment Fund as provided in section
81-15,174.01. The board shall make annual allocations from the Nebraska Environmental
Trust Fund and may make annual allocations each fiscal year from the Nebraska
Environmental Endowment Fund for projects which conform to the environmental
categories of the board established pursuant to section 81-15,176 and to the
extent the board determines those projects to have merit. The board shall
establish a calendar annually for receiving and evaluating proposals and awarding
grants. To evaluate the economic, financial, and technical feasibility of
proposals, the board may establish subcommittees, request or contract for
assistance, or establish advisory groups. Private citizens serving on advisory
groups shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses pursuant
to sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
<para>(2) The board shall establish rating systems for ranking proposals
which meet the board's environmental categories and other criteria. The rating
systems shall include, but not be limited to, the following considerations:</para>
<para>(a) Conformance with categories established pursuant to section
81-15,176;</para>
<para>(b) Amount of funds committed from other funding sources;</para>
<para>(c) Encouragement of public-private partnerships;</para>
<para>(d) Geographic mix of projects over time;</para>
<para>(e) Cost-effectiveness and economic impact;</para>
<para>(f) Direct environmental impact;</para>
<para>(g) Environmental benefit to the general public and the long-term
nature of such public benefit;
and</para>
<para>(h) Applications
recommended by the Director of Natural Resources and submitted by the Department
of Natural Resources pursuant to subsection (7) of section 61-218 shall be
awarded fifty priority points in the ranking process for the 2011 grant application
if the Legislature has authorized annual transfers of three million three
hundred thousand dollars to the Water Resources Cash Fund for each of fiscal
years 2011-12 and 2012-13 and has stated its intent to transfer three million
three hundred thousand dollars to the Water Resources Cash Fund in fiscal
year 2013-14. Priority points shall be awarded if the proposed programs set
forth in the grant application are consistent with the purposes of reducing
consumptive uses of water, enhancing streamflows, recharging ground water,
or supporting wildlife habitat in any river basin determined to be fully appropriated
pursuant to section 46-714 or designated as overappropriated pursuant to section
46-713.</para><para>(3) A grant awarded under this section pursuant to an application
made under subsection (7) of section 61-218 shall be paid out in the following
manner:</para><para>(a) The initial three million three hundred thousand dollar installment
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Water Resources
Cash Fund no later than fifteen business days after the date that the grant
is approved by the board;</para><para>(b) The second three million three hundred thousand dollar installment
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Water Resources
Cash Fund no later than May 15, 2013; and</para><para>(c) The third three million three hundred
thousand dollar installment shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Water Resources Cash Fund no later than May 15, 2014 if the Legislature
has authorized a transfer of three million three hundred thousand dollars
from the General Fund to the Water Resources Cash Fund for fiscal year 2013-14.</para>
<para>(4) It is the
intent of the Legislature that the Department of Natural Resources apply for
an additional three-year grant from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund
that would begin in fiscal year 2014-15 and such application shall be awarded
fifty priority points in the ranking process as set forth in subdivision (2)(h)
of this section if the following criteria are met:</para><para>(a) The Natural Resources
Committee of the Legislature has examined options for water funding and has
submitted a report to the Clerk of the Legislature and the Governor by December
1, 2012, setting forth:</para><para>(i) An outline and priority listing of water management and funding
needs in Nebraska, including instream flows, residential, agricultural, recreational,
and municipal needs, interstate obligations, water quality issues, and natural
habitats preservation;</para><para>(ii) An outline of statewide funding options which create a dedicated,
sustainable funding source to meet the needs set forth in the report; and</para>
<para>(iii) Recommendations
for legislation;</para><para>(b) The projects and activities funded by the department through
grants from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund under this section have
resulted in enhanced stream flows, reduced consumptive uses of water, recharged
ground water, supported wildlife habitat, or otherwise contributed towards
conserving, enhancing, and restoring Nebraska's ground water and surface water
resources. On or before July 1, 2014, the department shall submit a report
to the Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature providing demonstrable
evidence of the benefits accrued from such projects and activities; and</para>
<para>(c) In addition
to the grant reporting requirements of the trust, on or before July 1, 2014,
the department provides to the board a report which includes documentation
that:</para><para>(i) Expenditures from the Water Resources Cash Fund made to natural
resources districts have met the matching fund requirements provided in subdivision
(5)(a) of section 61-218;</para><para>(ii) Ten percent or less of the matching fund requirements has been
provided by in-kind contributions for expenses incurred for projects enumerated
in the grant application. In-kind contributions shall not include land or
land rights; and</para><para>(iii) All other projects and activities funded by the department
through grants from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund under this section
were matched not less than forty percent of the project or activity cost by
other funding sources.</para><para>(5) The
board may establish a subcommittee to rate grant applications. If the board
uses a subcommittee, the meetings
of such subcommittee shall be subject to the Open Meetings Act. The subcommittee
shall (a) use the rating systems established by the board under subsection
(2) of this section, (b) assign a numeric value to each rating criterion,
combine these values into a total score for each application, and rank the
applications by the total scores, (c) recommend an amount of funding for each
application, which amount may be more or less than the requested amount, and
(d) submit the ranked list and recommended funding to the board for its approval
or disapproval.<?Pub Caret?></para>
<para>(6) The board may commit funds
to multiyear projects, subject to available funds and appropriations. No commitment
shall exceed three years without formal action by the board to renew the grant
or contract. Multiyear commitments may be exempt from the rating process except
for the initial application and requests to renew the commitment.</para>
<para>(7) The board shall adopt
and promulgate rules and regulations and publish guidelines governing allocations
from the fund. The board shall conduct annual reviews of existing projects
for compliance with project goals and grant requirements.</para>
<para>(8) Every five years the board
may evaluate the long-term effects of the projects it funds. The evaluation
may assess a sample of such projects. The board may hire an independent consultant
to conduct the evaluation and may report the evaluation findings to the Legislature
and the Governor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 957, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 832, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB229, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB366, &#167; 1.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB229, section 3, with LB366, section 1, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB229 became effective May 18, 2011. Changes made by LB366 became effective August 27, 2011.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>