<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1821"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1821</statuteno><catchline>Payment of compensation; application; requirements; deadlines; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (3) and (4) of this section, no order for the payment of compensation shall be entered under the Nebraska Crime Victim's Reparations Act unless:</para><para>(a) The application has been submitted to the committee within the deadline provided in subsection (2) of this section; and</para><para>(b) The personal injury or death was the result of an incident or offense which had been reported to the police within five days of its occurrence or, if the incident or offense could not reasonably have been reported within that period, within five days of the time when a report could reasonably have been made.</para><para>(2) An application shall be submitted to the committee:</para><para>(a) For a victim who was nineteen years of age or older at the time of the personal injury or death, within two years after the date of the personal injury or death;</para><para>(b) For a victim who was under nineteen years of age at the time of death, within three years after the date of death; and</para><para>(c) For a victim who was under nineteen years of age at the time of the personal injury, on or before the victim's twenty-second birthday.</para><para>(3) The committee may evaluate applications submitted beyond the deadline established in this section if the committee finds that good cause existed for missing such deadline.</para><para>(4) An application submitted by or for a victim of sexual assault, domestic assault, child abuse, or sex trafficking is not subject to the five-day reporting requirement in subsection (1) of this section if, prior to submitting the application the:</para><para>(a) Applicant or victim has reported such crime to the police;</para><para>(b) Applicant or victim has obtained a protection order related to such incident or offense; or</para><para>(c) Victim has presented for a forensic medical exam.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 910, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 540, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB372, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB157, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>