<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-1414.13"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1414.13</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officer; reciprocity program; approval; application; council; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) A person seeking certification under subdivision (2)(c) of section 81-1414 shall, in addition to any other applicable requirements of the commission or of sections 81-1401 to 81-1414.19, submit an application to the council and complete the requirements for a reciprocity program as provided in this section. The application shall be made under oath and made on a form provided by the council.</para><para>(2) The applicant shall attest to the following:</para><para>(a) That the applicant's certification as a law enforcement officer has not been revoked or suspended in another jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) That the applicant has not been convicted of or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to a:</para><para>(i) Felony violation of state or federal law;</para><para>(ii) Misdemeanor crime of domestic violence; or</para><para>(iii) Misdemeanor violation of state or federal law, if the violation has a rational connection with the officer's fitness or capacity to serve as a law enforcement officer;</para><para>(c) That the applicant has not been separated from employment or disciplined for serious misconduct or a violation of the officer's oath of office, code of ethics, or statutory duties; and</para><para>(d) Any other information deemed necessary by the council.</para><para>(3) The applicant shall:</para><para>(a) Provide proof that the applicant meets the requirements listed in section 81-1410;</para><para>(b) Pass a physical fitness test;</para><para>(c) Provide proof that the applicant was awarded a certificate or diploma attesting to satisfactory completion of a training program determined by the council to be equivalent to the curriculum in subdivision (2)(a) of section 81-1414; and</para><para>(d) Pass a reciprocity test approved by the council.</para><para>(4) The council shall deny certification to an applicant under this section if the council finds that the applicant does not meet the requirements of this section, has omitted information required by this section, or has provided false or misleading information in the application. The council shall take action on an application within forty-five days after an applicant has completed all requirements under this section.</para><para>(5) No law enforcement agency or other state or local agency shall hire as a law enforcement officer a person whose certification is denied under this section.</para><para>(6) A person seeking certification under the reciprocity process provided in this section shall not exercise law enforcement authority until all certification process requirements have been met and the applicant has been certified, except that such person may serve as a noncertified conditional officer.</para><para>(7) The reciprocity test shall be offered at least once per month if an applicant has requested and is qualified to take the test. The reciprocity test shall be offered at sites with independent proctors as approved by the council. The council may authorize satellite testing locations throughout Nebraska or in other states. The council shall develop a study guide for the test by July 1, 2022. The council shall provide such study guide to applicants.</para><para>(8) The council may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as necessary to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1241, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>