<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,183" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,183</statuteno><catchline>Remedial Action Plan Monitoring Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Remedial Action Plan Monitoring Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Department of Environment and Energy. Revenue from the following sources shall be credited to the fund:</para><para>(a) Application fees collected under the Remedial Action Plan Monitoring Act;</para><para>(b) Deposits for costs associated with administration of the act, including review, oversight, and guidance;</para><para>(c) Gifts, grants, reimbursements, or appropriations from any source intended to be used for purposes of the act; and</para><para>(d) Investment interest attributable to the fund.</para><para>(2) The fund shall be used by the department to:</para><para>(a) Review applications and provide technical review, oversight, guidance, and other activities associated with remedial action plans for land pollution or water pollution;</para><para>(b) Fund activities performed by the department to address immediate or emergency threats to human health and the environment related to property under the act; and</para><para>(c) Administer and enforce the act.</para><para>(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1349, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 449, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 139. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>