<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,184"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,184</statuteno><catchline>Remedial action plan; application for monitoring; requirements; fees; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any entity which voluntarily chooses to make application for monitoring of remedial action plans for property where land pollution or water pollution exists shall:</para><para>(a) Submit an application on a form approved by the Department of Environment and Energy;</para><para>(b) Provide the department with a nonrefundable application fee of two thousand dollars; and</para><para>(c) Execute a written agreement to provide reimbursement of all department direct and indirect costs related to technical review, oversight, guidance, and other activities associated with the remedial action plan. As part of the voluntary agreement, the department shall require the applicant to post a deposit of three thousand dollars to be used by the department to cover all costs. The department shall not commence technical review, oversight, guidance, or other activities associated with the remedial action plan until the voluntary agreement is executed and a complete remedial action plan has been submitted. If the costs of the department exceed the initial deposit, an additional amount agreed upon by the department and the applicant may be required prior to proceeding. After the mutual termination of the voluntary agreement, any balance of funds paid under this subdivision shall be refunded.</para><para>(2) The department shall review and approve or deny all applications and notify the applicant in writing. If the application is denied, the notification shall state the reason for the denial. If the department determines that an application does not contain adequate information, the department shall return the application to the applicant. The applicant has sixty days to resubmit the required information or the application will be deemed denied.</para><para>(3) Within ninety days of approval of the application and voluntary agreement, the applicant shall provide a complete remedial action plan for the proposed project that conforms to all federal and state environmental standards and substantive requirements, including:</para><para>(a) Documentation regarding the investigation of land pollution or water pollution including, when appropriate, information indicating that the applicant holds or can acquire title to all lands or has the necessary easements and rights-of-way for the project and related lands;</para><para>(b) A remedial action work plan which describes the remedial action measures to be taken to address the land or water pollution; and</para><para>(c) Project monitoring reports, appropriate engineering, scientific, and financial feasibility data, and other data and information as may be required by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1349, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 449, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB724, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 140. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>