<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id47" statutenumber="81-1205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-1205</statuteno><catchline id="id50">Job training grant or training
grant; reports required; department; duties.</catchline><para>A business which
is awarded a job training grant or a training grant shall provide annual performance
reports to the Department of Economic Development and a final performance
report upon the completion of the project. The department shall provide a status report to the Appropriations
Committee of the Legislature on July 1 of each year. The status
report shall include information on each active grant, including specific
information regarding the number of positions to be trained, whether new or
existing employees are to be trained, the length of time that the project
has been active, the amount of funding committed to the project, the amount
of funding paid out to date, and the projected completion date. The status
report shall also provide information on grants closed during the reporting
year, including the total number of employees trained, whether new or existing
employees were trained, total project expenditures, and the duration time
of the project. The status report shall also provide information summarizing
the use of community college areas to provide training services and list specific
projects where a community college area is providing all or a component of
the training services. If private or inhouse training services are used, the
status report shall provide information regarding the name of the private
or inhouse training service and the qualifications of the training service. The report submitted to the Appropriations
Committee shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 326, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB956, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB961, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB404, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB906, &#167; 20.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>