<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-15,124" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>81-15,124</statuteno><catchline>Release of regulated substance; Department of Environment and Energy; State Fire Marshal; powers and duties; remedial action plan.</catchline><para>Any reported or suspected release of a regulated substance from any tank shall be investigated consistent with principles of risk-based corrective action by the State Fire Marshal and the Department of Environment and Energy. In the event that the State Fire Marshal or the department finds an adverse effect caused by a release of a regulated substance from a tank:</para><para>(1) The State Fire Marshal shall (a) determine the immediate danger presented by the release, (b) take all steps necessary to assure immediate public safety, and (c) assist the department in determining the source of the release and taking all steps necessary to ensure that the release is halted;</para><para>(2) By order of the department, the owner or operator of the tank causing the release shall, after securing the source of the release, develop a plan for remedial action to be approved by the department. The department shall inform the owner or operator of its approval or disapproval of a plan for remedial action within one hundred twenty days after receipt of a remedial action plan which contains all required information. If after one hundred twenty days the department fails to either deny, approve, or amend the remedial action plan submitted, the proposed plan shall be deemed approved; and</para><para>(3) The approved remedial action plan shall then be carried out by the owner or operator of the tank causing the release. All expenses incurred during the remedial action shall be paid by the owner or operator subject to reimbursement pursuant to the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act.</para><para>If it is determined that the source of the release is unknown or that the owner or operator of the facility causing the release is unknown or unavailable, a remedial action plan shall be developed by or under the direction of the department. Such remedial action plan shall be developed and carried out by the department with money from the Petroleum Products and Hazardous Substances Storage and Handling Fund if funds are available. If at a later date the owner or operator of the facility which caused the release is determined, he or she shall be responsible for remedial action costs incurred on his or her behalf subject to reimbursement pursuant to the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act. Any money received from such person shall be deposited in the Petroleum Products and Hazardous Substances Storage and Handling Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 217, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 289, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 237, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 119. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1501.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>