<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2117.01" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2117.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">License or registration renewal; continuing education required; instructor and course approval; certificate of attendance.</catchline><para>(1) In order to renew a license or registration issued under the State Electrical Act, the licensee or registrant shall be required to complete twelve contact hours of continuing education by January 1 of each odd-numbered year. The continuing education courses shall be approved by the board and may consist of training programs, courses, and seminars by the State Electrical Division or public or private schools, organizations, or associations. The contact hours shall include a minimum of six contact hours studying the National Electrical Code described in section 81-2104, and the remaining contact hours may include study of electrical circuit theory, blueprint reading, transformer and motor theory, electrical circuits and devices, control systems, programmable controllers, and microcomputers or any other study of electrical-related material that is approved by the board. Any additional hours studying the National Electrical Code shall be acceptable. For purposes of this section, a contact hour means fifty minutes of classroom attendance at an approved course under a qualified instructor approved by the board.</para><para>(2) An application for approval of the instructor and course offering shall be submitted annually on a form provided by the board. The approval by the board of the application shall be valid for one calendar year from the date of approval and shall include the following information:</para><para>(a) Name of the sponsoring organization or school, if any, the address of such organization or school, and the name of the contact person;</para><para>(b) The instructor's name, address, and telephone number;</para><para>(c) The title of the course offering;</para><para>(d) A description of all materials to be distributed to the participants;</para><para>(e) The date and exact location of each presentation of the course offering;</para><para>(f) The duration and time of the offering;</para><para>(g) A detailed outline of the subject matter together with the time sequence of each segment, faculty for each segment, and teaching technique used in each segment;</para><para>(h) The procedure for measuring attendance; and</para><para>(i) A description of the faculty, including name, background, and practical or teaching experience. A complete resume may be furnished.</para><para>Any application for approval of the instructor and course offering that is rejected shall be returned to the applicant with specific reasons for such rejection and stating what is needed for approval.</para><para>(3) If a continuing education course is approved, the licensee or registrant shall retain the attendance certificate and attach it to the application for renewal of his or her license or registration at the time of renewal. The licensee or registrant shall have the responsibility for record keeping and providing proof of attendance at continuing education courses.</para><para>(4) The instructor of each course shall provide an individual certificate of attendance to each licensee or registrant who attends ninety percent or more of the classroom hours. A certificate of attendance shall not be issued to a licensee or registrant who is absent for more than ten percent of the classroom hours. The certificate shall contain the licensee's or registrant's name and license or registration number, the course title, the date and location of the course, the number of credit hours, and the signature of the instructor.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to mean that a registrant shall be denied renewal of a registration by the board based solely on a failure to complete the continuing education requirement under subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 193, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 215, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB179, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>