<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2004"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2004</statuteno><catchline>State patrol; duties in general; Nebraska State Patrol Criminal Investigation Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska State Patrol, its subordinate officers such as lieutenant colonel, majors, captains, lieutenants, sergeants, corporals, patrolmen, and other employees shall be used primarily for the enforcement of the traffic and motor vehicle laws of the State of Nebraska and the handling of traffic within the state, except:</para><para>(1) The Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety, with the approval of the Governor, may designate such personnel of the Nebraska State Patrol to qualify and act as his or her deputies or investigators to assist him or her in the enforcement of the laws of the state relating to felonies, and the superintendent shall designate and train fifteen investigators in addition to those authorized on September 2, 1973, to assist in such law enforcement;</para><para>(2) The superintendent shall designate and train ten special investigators in addition to those authorized on July 12, 1974, to assist him or her and all other law enforcement agencies in this state with enforcement of drug control legislation. As an aid to such special investigators, the superintendent shall appoint two stenographers and one laboratory technician in addition to those authorized on September 2, 1973; and</para><para>(3) The Nebraska State Patrol shall provide security for all buildings and grounds owned or leased by the State of Nebraska in Lincoln, Nebraska, except the buildings and grounds described in subsection (5) of section 81-1108.15.</para><para>There is hereby created in the state treasury a cash fund to be known as the Nebraska State Patrol Criminal Investigation Cash Fund which shall be used for the enforcement of any state law relating to felonies. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 4, p. 508; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 176, &#167; 6, p. 691; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-419; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-434; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 510, &#167; 2, p. 2089; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1456, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 13, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 77, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1978), &#167; 60-434; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 403, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 133; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 31. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>