
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id93">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id95" statutenumber="81-2004.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2004.02</statuteno><catchline id="id98">Nebraska State
Patrol Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>There
is hereby created the Nebraska State Patrol Cash Fund. Money from this fund
shall be used to defray expenses incident to the administration of the Nebraska
State Patrol. All funds received by the Nebraska State Patrol for services
rendered shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska
State Patrol Cash Fund. Such fund shall be administered by the Superintendent
of Law Enforcement and Public Safety.</para>
<para>Allowable uses of the fund shall include, but not be limited
to, defraying the cost of:</para>
<para>(1) The vehicle identification inspection program established
in sections 60-181 to 60-189;</para>
<para>(2) Investigations of odometer and motor vehicle fraud, motor
vehicle licensing violations, and motor vehicle theft; and</para>
<para>(3) Other investigative expenses when money is specifically
appropriated by the Legislature for such purposes.</para>
<para>For fiscal
year 2013-14, transfers may be made from the fund to the Nebraska Capital
Construction Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money
in the Nebraska State Patrol Cash Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 851, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 134; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 31.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>