<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id484">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id486" statutenumber="81-2016"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2016</statuteno><catchline id="id489">Retirement
system; membership; requirements; new employee; participation in another governmental
plan; how treated; separate employment; effect.</catchline><para>(1)
Every member of the Nebraska State Patrol who was employed by the State of
Nebraska as such, on September 7, 1947, and every person employed as a member
of such patrol thereafter, shall be a member of the system, except for those
members of the Nebraska State Patrol who elected pursuant to section 60-1304
to remain members of the State Employees Retirement System of the State of
Nebraska. On and after July 1, 2010, no employee shall be authorized to participate
in the retirement system provided for in the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement
Act unless the employee (a) is a United States citizen or (b) is a qualified
alien under the federal Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C. 1101 et
seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2009, and is lawfully present in the
United States.</para>
<para>(2) Within the first one hundred eighty days of
employment, a member may apply to the board for eligibility and vesting credit
for years of participation in another Nebraska governmental plan, as defined
by section 414(d) of the Internal Revenue Code. During the years of participation
in the other Nebraska governmental plan, the employee must have been a full-time
employee, as defined in the Nebraska governmental plan in which the credit
was earned.</para>
<para>(3) Any officer who qualifies for membership pursuant to
subsection (1) of this section may not be disqualified from membership in
the retirement system solely because such officer also maintains separate
employment which qualifies the officer for membership in another public retirement
system, nor may membership in this retirement system disqualify such an officer
from membership in another public retirement system solely by reason of separate
employment which qualifies such officer for membership in this retirement
system.</para>
<para>(4) Information necessary to determine membership shall be
provided by the Nebraska State Patrol.</para>
<para>(5) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
governing the assessment and granting of eligibility and vesting credit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 211, &#167; 3, p. 687; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1978), &#167; 60-443; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 501, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1192, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 470, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 31.</para><effectivedate>April 25, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>