<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-2109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2109</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Journeyman electrician license; residential journeyman electrician license; qualifications; Class B journeyman electrician license; restriction on license.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) An applicant for a journeyman electrician license shall have at least four years' experience, acceptable to the board, in the electrical trade. Registration as an apprentice electrician for those years shall, on the approval of the board, constitute evidence of such experience. The board may by rule or regulation provide for the allowance of one year of experience credit for successful completion of a two-year post-high school electrical course approved by the board.</para><para id="id00">(2) On and after July 16, 2004, an applicant for a residential journeyman electrician license shall have at least three years' experience, acceptable to the board, in the electrical trade. Registration as an apprentice electrician for those years shall, on the approval of the board, constitute evidence of such experience. The board may by rule or regulation provide for the allowance of one year of experience credit for successful completion of a two-year post-high school electrical course approved by the board. A residential journeyman electrician license shall be valid only for residential installations.</para><para id="id00">(3) A Class B journeyman electrician license shall be valid only for electrical systems of not over four hundred amperes in capacity in structures used and maintained as residential dwellings but not larger than four-family dwellings located in any municipality which has a population of less than one hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 81-580; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 193, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 914, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 62. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>