<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2103</statuteno><catchline>State Electrical Division; created; State Electrical Board; members; duties; qualifications; terms.</catchline><para>There is hereby established an independent agency to be known as the State Electrical Division which shall be under the administrative and operative control of the executive director of such division. The division shall include a seven-member State Electrical Board appointed by the Governor with the consent of the Legislature. All members of the board shall be residents of the State of Nebraska. The board shall direct the efforts of the executive director and set the policy of the division. One of such members shall be a journeyman electrician, one shall be an electrical contractor or master electrician, one shall be a certified electrical inspector, one shall be a licensed professional electrical engineer, one shall be a representative of a public power district or rural electric cooperative in the state, one shall be a representative of the municipal electric systems in the state, and one shall be a member of any of such groups. The members of the board shall be appointed for staggered terms of five years. Any vacancy occurring in the membership of the board shall be filled by the Governor for the unexpired term. Each member of the board shall serve until his or her successor is appointed and qualified. The executive director shall be the executive secretary of the board and shall be responsible for all books, records, and transcripts of proceedings of the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 833, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 81-573; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 490, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 193, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 127; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 126, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>