<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id497" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-2017"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2017</statuteno><catchline id="id500">Retirement system; contributions; payment; funding of system.</catchline><para>(1) Commencing July 1, 2010, and until July 1, 2011, each officer while in the service of the Nebraska State Patrol shall pay or have paid on his or her behalf a sum equal to sixteen percent of his or her monthly compensation. Commencing July 1, 2011, and until July 1, 2013, each officer while in the service of the Nebraska State Patrol shall pay or have paid on his or her behalf a sum equal to nineteen percent of his or her monthly compensation. Commencing July 1, 2013, each officer who commenced service prior to July 1, 2016, while in the service of the Nebraska State Patrol shall pay or have paid on his or her behalf a sum equal to sixteen percent of his or her monthly compensation. Each officer who commenced service on or after July 1, 2016, while in the service of the Nebraska State Patrol shall pay or have paid on his or her behalf a sum equal to seventeen percent of his or her monthly compensation. Such amounts shall be deducted monthly by the Director of Administrative Services who shall draw a warrant monthly in the amount of the total deductions from the compensation of members of the Nebraska State Patrol in accordance with subsection (4) of this section, and the State Treasurer shall credit the amount of such warrant to the State Patrol Retirement Fund. The director shall cause a detailed report of all monthly deductions to be made each month to the board.</para><para>(2) In addition, commencing July 1, 2010, and until July 1, 2011, there shall be assessed against the appropriation of the Nebraska State Patrol a sum equal to the amount of sixteen percent of each officer's monthly compensation which shall be credited to the State Patrol Retirement Fund. Commencing July 1, 2011, and until July 1, 2013, there shall be assessed against the appropriation of the Nebraska State Patrol a sum equal to the amount of nineteen percent of each officer's monthly compensation which shall be credited to the State Patrol Retirement Fund. Commencing July 1, 2013, for each officer who commenced service prior to July 1, 2016, there shall be assessed against the appropriation of the Nebraska State Patrol a sum equal to the amount of sixteen percent of each officer's monthly compensation which shall be credited to the State Patrol Retirement Fund. Commencing July 1, 2016, for each officer who commenced service on or after July 1, 2016, there shall be assessed against the appropriation of the Nebraska State Patrol a sum equal to the amount of seventeen percent of each officer's monthly compensation which shall be credited to the State Patrol Retirement Fund. This assessment constitutes an employer match and shall be contingent upon the officer making his or her contributions to the retirement system.</para><para>(3) For the fiscal year beginning on July 1, 2002, and each fiscal year thereafter, the actuary for the board shall perform an actuarial valuation of the system using the entry age actuarial cost method. Under this method, the actuarially required funding rate is equal to the normal cost rate, plus the contribution rate necessary to amortize the unfunded actuarial accrued liability on a level percentage of salary basis. The normal cost under this method shall be determined for each individual member on a level percentage of salary basis. The normal cost amount is then summed for all members. Beginning July 1, 2006, any existing unfunded liabilities shall be reinitialized and amortized over a thirty-year period, and during each subsequent actuarial valuation, changes in the funded actuarial accrued liability due to changes in benefits, actuarial assumptions, the asset valuation method, or actuarial gains or losses shall be measured and amortized over a thirty-year period beginning on the valuation date of such change. If the unfunded actuarial accrued liability under the entry age actuarial cost method is zero or less than zero on an actuarial valuation date, then all prior unfunded actuarial accrued liabilities shall be considered fully funded and the unfunded actuarial accrued liability shall be reinitialized and amortized over a thirty-year period as of the actuarial valuation date. If the actuarially required contribution rate exceeds the rate of all contributions required pursuant to the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act, there shall be a supplemental appropriation sufficient to pay for the differences between the actuarially required contribution rate and the rate of all contributions required pursuant to the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act. Such valuation shall be on the basis of actuarial assumptions recommended by the actuary, approved by the board, and kept on file with the board.</para><para>(4) The state shall pick up the member contributions required by this section for all compensation paid on or after January 1, 1985, and the contributions so picked up shall be treated as employer contributions pursuant to section 414(h)(2) of the Internal Revenue Code in determining federal tax treatment under the code and shall not be included as gross income of the member until such time as they are distributed or made available. The contributions, although designated as member contributions, shall be paid by the state in lieu of member contributions. The state shall pay these member contributions from the same source of funds which is used in paying earnings to the member. The state shall pick up these contributions by a compensation deduction through a reduction in the cash compensation of the member. Member contributions picked up shall be treated for all purposes of the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act in the same manner and to the extent as member contributions made prior to the date picked up.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 211, &#167; 4, p. 688; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 286, &#167; 6, p. 1085; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 387, &#167; 1, p. 1243; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 235, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1978), &#167; 60-444; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 462, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 218, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 506, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1287, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 369, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 514, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 503, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB324, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB382, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB553, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB467, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>