<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2118" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2118</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Licenses and registrations; expiration; fees.</catchline><para>All licenses or registrations issued under the State Electrical Act shall expire on December 31 of each even-numbered year. All license or registration applications shall include the applicant's social security number. </para><para>The board shall, by a unanimous vote of the board, set reasonable fees for examination, issuance, and renewal of licenses and registrations issued under the State Electrical Act in amounts necessary to cover the costs incurred by the State Electrical Division and the board in administering and carrying out the purposes of the State Electrical Act and in a manner that unnecessary surpluses are avoided. The board shall annually file a report with the Attorney General and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst stating the amount of the fees set by the board. Such reports shall be submitted on or before July 1 of each year. The report submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically. The board shall establish the following fees:</para><para>(1) For examination for the following licenses:</para><para>(a) Electrical contractor;</para><para>(b) Journeyman electrician;</para><para>(c) Residential journeyman electrician;</para><para>(d) Fire alarm installer; and</para><para>(e) Special electrician license, sixty dollars;</para><para>(2) For each year of the two-year license period for issuance and renewal of the following licenses:</para><para>(a) Electrical contractor; and</para><para>(b) Journeyman electrician, residential journeyman electrician, fire alarm installer, or special electrician;</para><para>(3) For each year of the two-year registration period for issuance and renewal as an apprentice electrician; and</para><para>(4) For renewal on or after September 9, 1993, of the following licenses issued prior to such date for each year of the two-year license period:</para><para>(a) Class B electrical contractor;</para><para>(b) Class A master electrician; and</para><para>(c) Class B journeyman electrician.</para><para>The holder of an expired license or registration may renew the license or registration for a period of three months from the date of expiration upon payment of the license or registration fee plus ten percent of the renewal fee for each month or portion thereof past the expiration date. All holders of licenses or registrations expired for more than three months shall apply for a new license or registration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 833, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 81-589; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 841, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 193, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 229; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 126, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 914, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB179, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB144, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB716, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB144, section 10, with LB716, section 2, to reflect all amendments.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>