<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id114" statutenumber="81-2004.08"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2004.08</statuteno><catchline id="id117">Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be established within the Nebraska State Patrol and administered by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety. The fund shall consist of all revenue credited pursuant to law, including any fund transfers authorized by the Legislature.</para><para>(2) The fund shall only be used to pay the patrol's direct costs related to administering, operating, and maintaining the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System, except that (a) any unobligated money in the fund may first be used to reduce the patrol's General Fund costs to operate the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System, and if additional unobligated money in the fund exists, the Legislature may transfer money from the fund to the State Fire Marshal and the Game and Parks Commission to reduce the General Fund costs to operate the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System, and (b) transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 202. </para><operativedate>May 22, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>