<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id280">
<sectno id="id281" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 20.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id282" statutenumber="81-2027.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id284">81-2027.03</statuteno><catchline id="id285">Benefits;
adjustment.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning July 1, 2000, and each
July 1 thereafter, current benefits paid to a member or beneficiary shall
be adjusted so that the purchasing power of the benefit being paid is not
less than sixty percent of the purchasing power of the initial benefit. The
purchasing power of the initial benefit in any year following the year in
which the initial benefit commenced shall be calculated by dividing the United
States Department of Labor, Bureau of Labor Statistics, Consumer Price Index
for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers factor on June 30 of the current
year by the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers
factor on June 30 of the year in which the benefit commenced. The result shall
be multiplied by the product that results when the amount of the initial benefit
is multiplied by sixty percent. In any year in which applying the adjustment
provided in subsection (2) of this section results in a benefit which would
be less than sixty percent of the purchasing power of the initial benefit
as calculated above, the adjustment shall instead be equal to the percentage
change in the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers
factor from the prior year to the current year. In all other years, the adjustment
provided under subsection (2) of this section shall be provided. The adjustment
pursuant to this subsection shall not cause a current benefit to be reduced.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (1) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Beginning July 1, 2000, and until July 1, 2001, the current
benefit of a member or the beneficiary of such a member shall be increased
annually by the lesser of (i) the percentage change in the Consumer Price
Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers factor published by the
Bureau of Labor Statistics of the United States Department of Labor for the
prior year or (ii) two percent; and</para>
<para>(b) Beginning July 1, 2001, the current benefit of a member
or the beneficiary of such a member shall be increased annually by the lesser
of (i) the percentage change in the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners
and Clerical Workers factor published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of
the United States Department of Labor for the prior year or (ii) two and one-half
percent.</para>
<para>(3) The state shall contribute to the State Patrol Retirement
Fund an annual level dollar payment certified by the board. For the 1996-97
fiscal year through the 2012-13 fiscal year, the annual
level dollar payment certified by the board shall equal 3.04888 percent of
six million eight hundred ninety-five thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(4) The board shall adjust the annual benefit adjustment
provided in this section so that the total amount of all cost-of-living adjustments
provided to the eligible retiree at the time of the annual benefit adjustment
does not exceed the percentage change in the National Consumer Price Index
for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers factor published by the Bureau
of Labor Statistics for the period between June 30 of the prior year to June
30 of the present year. If the consumer price index used in this section is
discontinued or replaced, a substitute index published by the United States
Department of Labor shall be selected by the board which shall be a reasonable
representative measurement of the cost of living for retired employees.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 700, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 674, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 711, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1147, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167;  20.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>