<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2129</statuteno><catchline>Installations; connected; certificate of safe operation; dismissal of condemnation or disconnection order; contents of certificate; transient projects; duty of board.</catchline><para>No electrical installation subject to inspection by the board shall be newly connected or reconnected for use until there is filed with the electrical utility supplying power a certificate of the property owner or licensed electrician directing the work that inspection has been requested and that the conditions of the installation are safe for energization. In all cases when an order of condemnation or disconnection has been issued against the installation or any part thereof, prior to connection or reconnection there shall also first be filed with the electrical utility supplying the power a copy of an order of the inspector or the board dismissing such prior order of condemnation or disconnection or approving the installation as being in compliance with accepted standards of construction for safety to life and property, based upon minimum standards set forth in the National Electrical Code. Any supplier may refuse service without liability for such refusal until such conditions have been met. With respect to transient projects, the certificate shall also contain a certification that the request for inspection has been or will be filed with the board so as to be received by it at least five days prior to the date and time energization of the installation by the utility is to occur, and that the request for inspection states such date and time, and it shall be the responsibility of the board to have inspection made of such transient project prior to the date and time at which the request states energization is to occur.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 29; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 81-599. </para></source></law></legaldoc>