
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id112">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id114" statutenumber="81-2004.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2004.08</statuteno><catchline id="id117">Nebraska
Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund
is created. The fund shall be established within the Nebraska State Patrol
and administered by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety.
The fund shall consist of all revenue credited pursuant to law, including
any fund transfers authorized by the Legislature. The fund shall only be used
to pay the patrol's direct costs related to administering, operating, and
maintaining the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System, except that any
unobligated money in the fund may first be used to reduce the patrol's General
Fund costs to operate the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System, and
if additional unobligated money in the fund exists, the Legislature may transfer
money from the fund to the State Fire Marshal and the Game and Parks Commission
to reduce the General Fund costs to operate the Nebraska Public Safety Communication
System. For fiscal year 2013-14,
transfers may be made from the fund to the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund
at the direction of the Legislature to support capital projects related to
Nebraska State Patrol law enforcement efforts. Any money in the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 33.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>