<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2108</statuteno><catchline>Wiring or installing; license required; exceptions; lending license prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section or in section 81-2110 or 81-2112, no person shall, for another, wire for or install electrical wiring, apparatus, or equipment unless he or she is licensed by the board as a Class B electrical contractor, an electrical contractor, a Class A master electrician, a Class B master electrician, or a fire alarm installer.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 81-2106, 81-2110, or 81-2112, no person shall wire for or install electrical wiring, apparatus, or equipment or supervise an apprentice electrician unless such person is licensed as a Class B journeyman electrician, a journeyman electrician, a residential journeyman electrician, or a fire alarm installer and is employed by a Class B electrical contractor, an electrical contractor, a Class A master electrician, a Class B master electrician, or a fire alarm installer.</para><para>For purposes of this section, the holder of a fire alarm installer license shall only supervise those apprentices engaged in the installation of fire alarm equipment and apparatus operating at fifty volts or less.</para><para>(3) No person licensed under the State Electrical Act may lend his or her license to any person or knowingly permit the use of such license by another.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 833, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 81-579; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 605, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 193, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 126, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 914, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>