<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2250"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2250</statuteno><catchline>Long-term care ombudsman program; established; contents.</catchline><para>The department shall establish a long-term care ombudsman program consisting of the state long-term care ombudsman and any local long-term care ombudsman programs. The program shall:</para><para>(1) Investigate and resolve complaints made by or on behalf of residents relating to action, inaction, or decisions of providers of long-term care services or their representatives, of public agencies, or of social service agencies which may adversely affect the health, safety, welfare, or rights of residents. The office shall implement procedures to ensure that no state long-term care ombudsman or ombudsman advocate investigates any complaint involving a provider with which the representative was once employed or associated;</para><para>(2) Provide for the training of the state long-term care ombudsman and ombudsman advocates and promote the development of citizen organizations to participate in the program, provide training to ombudsman advocates and staff of local long-term care ombudsman programs, issue certificates attesting to the successful completion of the prescribed training, and provide ongoing technical assistance to such local programs;</para><para>(3) Analyze and monitor the development and implementation of federal, state, and local laws, regulations, and policies with respect to long-term care facilities and services and recommend any changes in such laws, regulations, and policies deemed by the long-term care ombudsman program to be appropriate;</para><para>(4) Establish a statewide, uniform reporting system to collect and analyze data relating to complaints and conditions in long-term care facilities for the purpose of identifying and resolving significant problems. The data shall be submitted to the department at least on an annual basis;</para><para>(5) Prepare reports and provide policy, regulatory, and legislative recommendations to solve problems, resolve complaints, and improve the quality of care and life in long-term care facilities;</para><para>(6) Provide for public forums to discuss concerns and problems relating to action, inaction, or decisions that may adversely affect the health, safety, welfare, or civil rights of residents and resident representatives, public agencies and entities, and social service agencies; and</para><para>(7) Provide information to public agencies, legislators, and others regarding the problems and concerns, including recommendations related to such problems and concerns, of residents.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 677, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 884; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 769; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB903, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>