<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2231"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2231</statuteno><catchline>Care management units; certification; standards.</catchline><para>The care management units shall be certified by the Department of Health and Human Services which shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations within two hundred forty days of August 30, 1987, providing standards for certification. Such standards shall be developed in consultation with appropriate state agencies and professional organizations and shall provide that:</para><para>(1) The care management units shall be subject to periodic review by the department;</para><para>(2) The care management units shall provide an assessment of an individual's entire range of needs, including, but not limited to, functional, psychosocial, and environmental needs;</para><para>(3) The care management units shall develop a long-term care plan for each client in consultation with the individual and if possible his or her family utilizing and coordinating available and appropriate public and private resources;</para><para>(4) The care management units shall periodically monitor the delivery of services to each client and review the individual's plan to determine if the plan remains appropriate;</para><para>(5) The care management units shall be operated separately from any direct care programs provided by the area agencies on aging; and</para><para>(6) A standardized long-term care assessment document shall be developed that incorporates, when reasonably possible, (a) assessment procedures currently used by area agencies on aging and (b) assessment criteria designed to reduce duplication of effort with related long-term care services, both public and private, including assessment material necessary to determine service eligibility by the Department of Health and Human Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 42, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 877. </para></source></law></legaldoc>