<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id315">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id317" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-2026"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2026</statuteno><catchline id="id320">Retirement;
annuity; officers; surviving spouse; children; benefit; disability or death
in line of duty; benefit; maximum benefit;
direct transfer to retirement plan; death while performing qualified military
service; additional death benefit.</catchline><para>(1)(a)
Any officer qualified for an annuity as provided in section 81-2025 for reasons
other than disability shall be entitled to receive a monthly annuity for the
remainder of the officer's life. The annuity payments shall continue until
the end of the calendar month in which the officer dies. The amount of the
annuity shall be a percentage of the officer's final average monthly compensation.
For retirement on or after the fifty-fifth birthday of the member or on or
after the fiftieth birthday of a member who has been in the employ of the
state for twenty-five years, as calculated in section 81-2033, the percentage
shall be three percent multiplied by the number of years of creditable service,
as calculated in section 81-2033, except that the percentage shall never be
greater than seventy-five percent.</para>
<para>(b) For retirement pursuant to subsection (2) of section
81-2025 on or after the fiftieth birthday of the member but prior to the fifty-fifth
birthday of the member who has been in the employ of the state for less than
twenty-five years, as calculated in section 81-2033, the annuity which would
apply if the member were age fifty-five at the date of retirement shall be
reduced by five-ninths of one percent for each month by which the early retirement
date precedes age fifty-five or for each month by which the early retirement
date precedes the date upon which the member has served for twenty-five years,
whichever is earlier. Any officer who has completed thirty years of creditable
service with the Nebraska State Patrol shall have retirement benefits computed
as if the officer had reached age fifty-five.</para>
<para>(c) For purposes of this computation, final average monthly
compensation shall mean the sum of the officer's total compensation during
the three twelve-month periods of service as an officer in which compensation
was the greatest divided by thirty-six, and for any officer employed on or
before January 4, 1979, the officer's total compensation shall include payments
received for unused vacation and sick leave accumulated during the final three
years of service.</para>
<para>(2) Any officer qualified for an annuity as provided in section
81-2025 for reasons of disability shall be entitled to receive a monthly annuity
for the remainder of the period of disablement as provided in sections 81-2028
to 81-2030. The amount of the annuity shall be fifty percent of the officer's
monthly compensation at the date of disablement if the officer has completed
seventeen or fewer years of creditable service. If the officer has completed
more than seventeen years of creditable service, the amount of the annuity
shall be three percent of the final monthly compensation at the date of disablement
multiplied by the total years of creditable service but not to exceed seventy-five
percent of the final average monthly compensation as defined in subsection
(1) of this section. The date of disablement shall be the date on which the
benefits as provided in section 81-2028 have been exhausted.</para>
<para>(3) Upon the death of an officer after retirement for reasons
other than disability, benefits shall be provided as a percentage of the amount
of the officer's annuity, calculated as follows:</para>
<para>(a) If there is a surviving spouse but no dependent child
or children of the officer under nineteen years of age, the surviving spouse
shall receive a benefit equal to seventy-five percent of the amount of the
officer's annuity for the remainder of the surviving spouse's life;</para>
<para>(b) If there is a surviving spouse and the surviving spouse
has in his or her care a dependent child or children of the officer under
nineteen years of age and there is no other dependent child or children of
the officer not in the care of the surviving spouse under nineteen years of
age, the benefit shall be equal to one hundred percent of the officer's annuity.
When there is no remaining dependent child of the officer under nineteen years
of age, the benefit shall be seventy-five percent of the amount of the officer's
annuity to the surviving spouse for the remainder of the surviving spouse's
life;</para>
<para>(c) If there is a surviving spouse and the surviving spouse
has in his or her care a dependent child or children of the officer under
nineteen years of age or there is another dependent child or children of the
officer under nineteen years of age not in the care of the surviving spouse,
the benefit shall be twenty-five percent of the amount of the officer's annuity
to the surviving spouse and seventy-five percent of the amount of the officer's
annuity to the dependent children of the officer under nineteen years of age
to be divided equally among such dependent children but in no case shall the
benefit received by a surviving spouse and dependent children residing with
such spouse be less than fifty percent of the amount of the officer's annuity.
At such time as any dependent child of the officer attains nineteen years
of age, the benefit shall be divided equally among the remaining dependent
children of the officer who have not yet attained nineteen years of age. When
there is no remaining dependent child of the officer under nineteen years
of age, the benefit shall be seventy-five percent of the amount of the officer's
annuity to the surviving spouse for the remainder of the surviving spouse's
life;</para>
<para>(d) If there is no surviving spouse and a dependent child
or children of the officer under nineteen years of age, the benefit shall
be equal to seventy-five percent of the officer's annuity to the dependent
children of the officer under nineteen years of age to be divided equally
among such dependent children. At such time as any dependent child of the
officer attains nineteen years of age, the benefit shall be divided equally
among the remaining dependent children of the officer who have not yet attained
nineteen years of age; and</para>
<para>(e) If there is no surviving spouse or no dependent child
or children of the officer under nineteen years of age, the amount of benefit
such officer has received under the Nebraska State Patrol Retirement Act shall
be computed. If such amount is less than the contributions to the State Patrol
Retirement Fund made by such officer, plus regular interest, the difference
shall be paid to the officer's designated beneficiary or estate.</para>
<para>(4) Upon the death of an officer after retirement for reasons
of disability, benefits shall be provided as if the officer had retired for
reasons other than disability.</para>
<para>(5) Upon the death of an officer before retirement, benefits
shall be provided as if the officer had retired for reasons of disability
on the date of such officer's death, calculated as follows:</para>
<para>(a) If there is a surviving spouse but no dependent child
or children of the officer under nineteen years of age, the surviving spouse
shall receive a benefit equal to seventy-five percent of the amount of the
officer's annuity for the remainder of the surviving spouse's life;</para>
<para>(b) If there is a surviving spouse and the surviving spouse
has in his or her care a dependent child or children of the officer under
nineteen years of age and there is no other dependent child or children of
the officer not in the care of the surviving spouse under nineteen years of
age, the benefit shall be equal to one hundred percent of the officer's annuity.
When there is no remaining dependent child of the officer under nineteen years
of age, the benefit shall be seventy-five percent of the amount of the officer's
annuity to the surviving spouse for the remainder of the surviving spouse's
life;</para>
<para>(c) If there is a surviving spouse and the surviving spouse
has in his or her care a dependent child or children of the officer under
nineteen years of age or there is another dependent child or children of the
officer under nineteen years of age not in the care of the surviving spouse,
the benefit shall be twenty-five percent of the amount of the officer's annuity
to the surviving spouse and seventy-five percent of the amount of the officer's
annuity to the dependent children of the officer under nineteen years of age
to be divided equally among such dependent children but in no case shall the
benefit received by a surviving spouse and dependent children residing with
such spouse be less than fifty percent of the amount of the officer's annuity.
At such time as any dependent child of the officer attains nineteen years
of age, the benefit shall be divided equally among the remaining dependent
children of the officer who have not yet attained nineteen years of age. When
there is no remaining dependent child of the officer under nineteen years
of age, the benefit shall be seventy-five percent of the amount of the officer's
annuity to the surviving spouse for the remainder of the surviving spouse's
life;</para>
<para>(d) If there is no surviving spouse and a dependent child
or children of the officer under nineteen years of age, the benefit shall
be equal to seventy-five percent of the officer's annuity to the dependent
children of the officer under nineteen years of age to be divided equally
among such dependent children. At such time as any dependent child of the
officer attains nineteen years of age, the benefit shall be divided equally
among the remaining dependent children of the officer who have not yet attained
nineteen years of age; and</para>
<para>(e) If no benefits are paid to a surviving spouse or dependent
child or children of the officer, benefits will be paid as described in subsection
(1) of section 81-2031.</para>
<para>(6) A lump-sum
death benefit paid to the member's beneficiary, other than the member's estate,
that is an eligible distribution may be distributed in the form of a direct
transfer to a retirement plan eligible to receive such transfer under the
provisions of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(7) For any member whose death occurs on
or after January 1, 2007, while performing qualified military service as defined
in section 414(u) of the Internal Revenue Code, the member's beneficiary shall
be entitled to any additional death benefit that would have been provided,
other than the accrual of any benefit relating to the period of qualified
military service. The additional death benefit shall be determined as if the
member had returned to employment with the Nebraska State Patrol and such
employment had terminated on the date of the member's death.</para>
<para>(8) Any changes made to this
section by Laws 2004, LB 1097, shall apply only to retirements, disabilities,
and deaths occurring on or after July 16, 2004.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 333, &#167; 2, p. 1093; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 276, &#167; 1, p. 1004; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 296, &#167; 1, p. 1104; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 307, &#167; 6, p. 973; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 386, &#167; 2, p. 1241; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 510, &#167; 4, p. 2090; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 511, &#167; 8, p. 2095; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1004, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 235, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 644, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 347, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 107; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 60-452.01; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 462, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 493, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 506, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 953, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 724, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1306, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1273, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 29.</para><effectivedate>April 7, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Subsection (3) of this section, as it existed in 2002, is ambiguous as to the proper distribution of a deceased trooper's annuity where there are surviving minor children who are not all in the care of a surviving spouse. Consistent with the legislative intent of subsection (3) of this section, to provide benefits to the surviving members of a trooper's family, this section requires distribution of benefits to all of a deceased trooper's minor children, regardless of with whom they reside. Zach v. Eacker, 271 Neb. 868, 716 N.W.2d 437 (2006).</para><para>Where plaintiffs had been members of the system prior to administrative change in method of calculating "final average monthly salary" under this section and had been advised on the former method of calculation, their expectations that their retirement payment would be calculated under the former method amounted to a contractual right. Where state failed to produce evidence that violating patrolmen's contractual right to have retirement payments calculated under former method was demanded by a vital state interest or important public purpose, plaintiffs in this case were entitled to summary judgment against state. Halpin v. Nebraska State Patrolmen's Retirement System, 211 Neb. 892, 320 N.W.2d 910 (1982).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>