<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2606"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2606</statuteno><catchline>Commission; meetings; notice; quorum; attendance required; exception; annual report.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall meet at least quarterly. At least one of such meetings every calendar year shall be in the city in Nebraska with the largest African American population. In addition to the requirements of the Open Meetings Act, public notice of a meeting shall be required no later than seven calendar days prior to the date of such meeting and shall be published on the commission's website and social media and shared with local media outlets. Meetings shall be held in January, April, July, and October. Special meetings may be called at the request of eight voting members. Eight voting members of the commission shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. Commission meeting minutes shall be posted on the commission's website.</para><para>(2) The office of any member of the commission who, without a valid excuse, fails to attend annual or special meetings shall be vacant.</para><para>(3) The commission shall electronically submit an annual report to the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature containing a summary of the following:</para><para>(a) An overview of the commission's mission, key achievements, challenges, and primary goals for the coming year;</para><para>(b) Legislative advocacy and policy impact including the commission's role in supporting or proposing legislation, policies for which the commission advocated, supported, or implemented that impacted the African American community, and the progress made on the policies described in sections 81-2601 to 81-2607;</para><para>(c) Community engagement programs including initiatives, outreach, public forums, and partnerships with community organizations;</para><para>(d) Economic development initiatives including efforts to improve economic opportunities within the African American community, employment programs, small business support, training, and progress in reducing economic disparities;</para><para>(e) Education and workforce development including educational initiatives, such as scholarships, mentoring programs, partnerships with schools, and efforts to ensure African American youth and adults have access to career advancement opportunities;</para><para>(f) Health and wellness initiatives including programs that address health disparities, wellness promotion, and increasing access to health care resources;</para><para>(g) Criminal justice and public safety efforts including those that address disparities in the criminal justice system, programs for formerly incarcerated individuals, and improvements in police-community relations;</para><para>(h) Housing and community development including initiatives to address issues such as affordable housing, eviction prevention efforts, and partnerships with housing agencies;</para><para>(i) Metrics and key performance indicators including data that demonstrates the impact of each program or initiative, such as employment rates, graduation rates, health outcomes, and recidivism rates in the African American community;</para><para>(j) Financial information including the commission's budget, funding sources, expenditures, grants received, and public funds allocated;</para><para>(k) Public feedback and a community needs assessment including feedback from the community on the effectiveness of the commission's work and priority areas for improvement; and</para><para>(l) Future goals and strategic plans including goals for the upcoming year and long-term objectives with a focus on addressing challenges and advancing the commission's mission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB918, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB69, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>