
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2120</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; issued without examination based on reciprocity with other states, qualifications; issued based on reciprocal credentialing agreement, military occupational specialty, or apprenticeship training program; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) To the extent that any other state which provides for the licensing of electricians provides for similar action, the board may grant licenses, without examination, of the same grade and class to an electrician who has been licensed by such other state for at least one year, upon payment by the applicant of the required fee, and upon the board being furnished with proof that the qualifications of the applicant are equal to the qualifications of holders of similar licenses in Nebraska.</para><para>(2)(a) Subject to subdivision (b) of this subsection, the board shall issue a license to an individual upon application if:</para><para>(i)(A) The applicant holds (I) a credential in another state that has a reciprocal credentialing agreement with the State of Nebraska for such credential as determined by the board, (II) a military occupational specialty in the United States Military as defined in section 84-944.01, or (III) a license with a prerequisite of apprentice registration and successful completion of an apprenticeship training program registered by the United States Department of Labor; and</para><para>(B) Such credential, military occupational specialty, or license is for an occupation with a similar scope of practice, as determined by the board;</para><para>(ii) The applicant has held the credential, military occupational specialty, or license for at least one year;</para><para>(iii) To obtain such credential, military occupational specialty, or license, the applicant was required to pass an examination or meet education, training, or experience standards;</para><para>(iv) The applicant does not have a disqualifying criminal record as determined by the board;</para><para>(v) The applicant's credential, military occupational specialty, or license has not been revoked because of negligence or intentional misconduct related to the applicant's work in the occupation;</para><para>(vi) The applicant has not surrendered a credential, military occupational specialty, or license because of negligence or intentional misconduct related to the applicant's work in the occupation in any state, in the United States Military, or in an apprenticeship training program;</para><para>(vii) The applicant does not have a complaint, allegation, or investigation pending before a board in any state, the United States Military, or an apprenticeship training program that relates to unprofessional conduct or an alleged crime. If such a complaint, allegation, or investigation is pending, the State Electrical Board shall not issue or deny a license until the complaint, allegation, or investigation is resolved or the applicant otherwise meets the criteria for a license to the satisfaction of the board; and</para><para>(viii) The applicant has paid all applicable fees required for issuance of the license in this state.</para><para>(b) Prior to issuance of a license under this subsection, the board may require an applicant to pass a jurisprudential examination specific to relevant state statutes and administrative rules and regulations that regulate the occupation if issuance of such license in this state requires a person to pass such an examination.</para><para>(c)(i) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (ii) of this subdivision, the board shall approve or deny a license under this subsection in writing within sixty days after receiving a complete application under this subsection or within five business days after the next meeting of the board that is held after receiving a complete application under this subsection, whichever is sooner.</para><para>(ii) The board may delay the approval or denial of a license under this subsection past the deadline prescribed in subdivision (i) of this subdivision if the approval or denial is delayed because of the requirement to complete a criminal background check or a disciplinary history review, but the board shall approve or deny such license in writing within five business days after receiving the results of the background check and the disciplinary history review or within five business days after the next meeting of the board after receiving such results, whichever is sooner. The board shall document in writing each case in which approval or denial of an application is not provided within sixty days after receipt of the complete application.</para><para>(d) For a license that has a prerequisite of apprentice registration under the State Electrical Act, the board shall grant credit toward requirements for such license for completion of any portion of an apprenticeship training program registered by the United States Department of Labor.</para><para>(e) An applicant may appeal the denial of a license under this subsection. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(f) A license issued pursuant to this subsection is valid only in this state and does not make the individual eligible to work in another state, in the United States Military, or under an interstate compact or reciprocity agreement unless otherwise provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 81-591; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB16, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>