<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id523">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id525" statutenumber="81-2041"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2041</statuteno><catchline id="id528">DROP participation
authorized; requirements; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Any member
who meets the participation requirements of subsection (2) of this section
may participate in DROP. DROP provides that subsequent to attaining normal
age and service retirement eligibility, a member may voluntarily choose to
participate in DROP upon its adoption which, for purposes of this section,
shall be the earlier of September 1, 2008, or the first of the month following
a favorable letter determination by the Internal Revenue Service. If the member
chooses to participate in DROP, the member shall be deemed to have retired
but shall not be deemed to be terminated, and the member may continue in active
employment for up to a five-year period. During the DROP period, the member's
retirement benefit payments shall be deposited into the DROP account for the
benefit of the member until the member actually retires from active employment
at or before the expiration of the DROP period. Thereafter, future retirement
benefit payments shall be made directly to the member, and the member shall
have access to all funds in the DROP account designated for the benefit of
the member. DROP funds shall
be held and invested in a defined contribution account under section 414(k)
of the Internal Revenue Code and shall meet the limitations in section 415
of the code.</para>
<para>(2) To participate in the DROP program, a member shall meet
the following requirements:</para>
<para>(a) A member shall be eligible to enter DROP at any time
subsequent to the date when the member has (i) attained normal retirement
age and (ii) completed twenty-five years of service. Members having attained
normal retirement age and completed twenty-five years of service on or before
the date of adoption of DROP shall be eligible to enter DROP at any future
date;</para>
<para>(b) A member who elects to enter DROP shall be entitled to
receive regular age and service retirement benefits in accordance with section
81-2026. A member is entitled to remain in DROP for a maximum of five years
subsequent to the date of the member's DROP election. A member may separate
from service and thereby exit DROP at any time during the DROP period. On
or before the completion of the DROP period, the member must separate from
active employment and exit DROP. During the DROP period, a member's retirement
benefit shall be payable to the DROP account vendor designated in the member's
name. Amounts transferred or paid to a participating member's DROP account
shall not constitute annual additions under section 415 of the Internal Revenue
Code;</para>
<para>(c) A member electing to enter DROP shall choose an annuity
payment option. After the option is chosen, the member shall not be entitled
to any retirement benefit changes, for reasons including, but not limited
to, wage increases, promotions, and demotions, except that the restriction
on retirement benefit changes shall not apply in the event of duty-related
death or duty-related disability. The benefit amount shall be fixed as of
the date of election and shall be payable as if the employee retired on that
date and separated from active employment. Upon the death of a member during
the DROP period, monthly benefits shall be provided as a percentage of the
amount of the member's annuity as set forth in subsection (3) of section 81-2026
based upon the annuity benefit calculation made at commencement of the DROP
period. In addition, the balance of the DROP account, if any, shall be provided
to the beneficiary or beneficiaries of the member in accordance with subsection
(6) of section 81-2026 or, if no beneficiary is provided, to the estate of
the member. Upon the disability of a member during the DROP period, the member
shall be deemed to have completed the DROP period, shall begin receiving the
annuity benefit as calculated at the commencement of the DROP period, and
shall be paid the balance of the DROP account, if any;</para>
<para>(d) No member shall be allowed to continue making the required
contributions while the member is enrolled in DROP;</para>
<para>(e) During the DROP period, the Nebraska State Patrol shall
not be assessed the amount required under subsection (2) of section 81-2017
nor shall such amount be credited to the State Patrol Retirement Fund;</para>
<para>(f) The member shall be paid the balance of the DROP account
upon the member's separation from active employment or at the expiration of
the DROP period thereby ending the member's participation in DROP. If a member
has not voluntarily separated from active employment on or before the completion
of the DROP period, the member's retirement benefit shall be paid directly
to the member thereby ending the member's active employment. The member's
DROP account shall consist of accrued retirement benefits and interest on
such benefits;</para>
<para>(g) Any member that is enrolled in DROP shall be responsible
for directing the DROP account designated for the benefit of the member by
investing the account in any DROP investment options. There shall be no guaranteed
rate of investment return on DROP account assets. Any losses, charges, or
expenses incurred by the participating DROP member in such member's DROP account
by virtue of the investment options selected by the participating DROP member
shall not be made up by the retirement system but all of the same shall be
borne by the participating DROP member. The retirement system, the state,
the board, and the state investment officer shall not be responsible for any
investment results under the DROP agreement. Transfers between investment
options shall be in accordance with the rules and regulations of DROP. A DROP
account shall be established for each participating DROP member. Such DROP
account shall be adjusted no less frequently than annually for the member's
retirement benefit distributions and net investment earnings and losses;</para>
<para>(h) If the DROP account is subject to administrative or other
fees or charges, such fees or charges shall be charged to the participating
DROP member's DROP account; and</para>
<para>(i) Cost-of-living adjustments as provided for in section
81-2027.08 shall not be applied to retirement benefits during the DROP period.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB324, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 34.</para><effectivedate>April 25, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>