<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2135" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2135</statuteno><catchline>State inspections; fees; when due; when not applicable.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall, by a unanimous vote of the board, set reasonable fees for state electrical inspections under the State Electrical Act in amounts necessary to cover the costs incurred by the State Electrical Division and the board in administering and carrying out the purposes of the State Electrical Act and in a manner that unnecessary surpluses are avoided. The board shall annually file a report with the Attorney General and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst stating the amount of the fees set by the board. Such reports shall be submitted on or before July 1 of each year. The report submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(2) All state electrical inspection fees shall be due and payable to the board at or before commencement of the installation and shall be forwarded with the request for inspection. Inspection fees set by the board in accordance with this section shall not apply within the jurisdiction of any county, city, or village if the county, city, or village has adopted an ordinance or resolution as set forth in the State Electrical Act.</para><para>(3) The board shall establish the following fees:</para><para>(a) Minimum fee for each separate inspection of an installation, replacement, alteration, or repair;</para><para>(b) Services, change of services, temporary services, additions, alterations, or repairs on either primary or secondary services;</para><para>(c) Field irrigation system inspections;</para><para>(d) The first reinspection required as a result of a correction order; a second reinspection required as a result of noncompliance with the same correction order; and subsequent reinspections associated with the same correction order; and</para><para>(e) An inspection is requested by an owner.</para><para>(3) The fee for fire and accident inspections shall be computed at the rate set by the board per hour, and mileage and other expenses shall be reimbursed as provided in section 81-1176.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 525, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 833, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 957, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 81-5,105; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 841, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 193, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 126, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB716, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>