<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id810">
<sectno id="id811">Sec. 83.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id812" statutenumber="81-2004.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id814">81-2004.01</statuteno><catchline id="id815">Carrier
Enforcement Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Carrier Enforcement
Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be established within the Nebraska State
Patrol and administered by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public
Safety. The fund shall consist of fund transfers made each fiscal year from
the Roads Operations Cash Fund as authorized by the Legislature through the
budget process.</para>
<para>(2) The Carrier Enforcement
Cash Fund shall only be used to pay the costs associated with the operation
of the carrier enforcement division of the patrol, except that (a) the Legislature may authorize
fund transfers each fiscal year through the budget process from the Carrier
Enforcement Cash Fund to the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash
Fund to pay the carrier enforcement division's share of operations costs of
the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System and (b) transfers may be made from the Carrier Enforcement
Cash Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(3) Any money in the Carrier
Enforcement Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 83.</para><effectivedate>November 21, 2009</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>