<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-2034"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2034</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Retirement; method of crediting for military service; effect.</catchline><para id="id00" /><para id="id00">(1)(a) Any officer of the Nebraska State Patrol who is reemployed pursuant to 38 U.S.C. 4301 et seq., shall be treated as not having incurred a break in service by reason of the officer's period of military service. Such military service shall be credited for purposes of determining the nonforfeitability of the officer's accrued benefits and the accrual of benefits under the plan.</para><para id="id00">(b) The state shall be liable for funding any obligation of the plan to provide benefits based upon such period of military service. To satisfy the liability, the Nebraska State Patrol shall pay to the retirement system an amount equal to:</para><para>(i) The sum of the officer and employer contributions that would have been paid during such period of military service; and</para><para>(ii) Any actuarial costs necessary to fund the obligation of the plan to provide benefits based upon such period of military service. For the purposes of determining the amount of such liability and obligation of the plan, earnings and forfeitures, gains and losses, regular interest, or interest credits that would have accrued on the officer and employer contributions that are paid by the Nebraska State Patrol pursuant to this section shall not be included.</para><para>(c) The amount required in subdivision (b) of this subsection shall be paid to the retirement system as soon as reasonably practicable following the date of reemployment, but must be paid within eighteen months of the date the board notifies the Nebraska State Patrol of the amount due. If the Nebraska State Patrol fails to pay the required amount within such eighteen-month period, then the Nebraska State Patrol is also responsible for any actuarial costs and interest on actuarial costs that accrue from eighteen months after the date the Nebraska State Patrol is notified by the board until the date the amount is paid.</para><para>(d) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this subsection, including, but not limited to, rules and regulations on:</para><para>(i) How and when the officer and Nebraska State Patrol must notify the retirement system of a period of military service;</para><para>(ii) The acceptable methods of payment;</para><para>(iii) Determining the service and compensation upon which the contributions must be made;</para><para>(iv) Accelerating the payment from the employer due to unforeseen circumstances that occur before payment is made pursuant to this section, including, but not limited to, the officer's termination or retirement or the employer's reorganization, consolidation, merger, or closing; and</para><para>(v) The documentation required to substantiate that the officer was reemployed pursuant to 38 U.S.C. 4301 et seq.</para><para>(2) This section only applies to military service that falls within the definition of uniformed service under 38 U.S.C. 4301 et seq. Military service does not include service provided pursuant to sections 55-101 to 55-181.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 177, &#167; 1, p. 481; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 391, &#167; 5, p. 1216; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 987, &#167; 15; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1978), &#167; 60-461; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 44. </para><effectivedate>May 24, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>