<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id942"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-2013.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-2013.01</statuteno><catchline>Missing Native American women and children; Nebraska State Patrol; duties; report.</catchline><para>The Nebraska State Patrol shall conduct a study to determine how to increase state criminal justice protective and investigative resources for reporting and identifying missing Native American women and children in Nebraska. The Nebraska State Patrol shall work with the Commission on Indian Affairs to convene meetings with tribal and local law enforcement partners, federally recognized tribes, and urban Indian organizations to determine the scope of the problem, identify barriers, and find ways to create partnerships to increase reporting and investigation of missing Native American women and children. Consultation and collaboration with federally recognized tribes shall be conducted with respect for government-to-government relations. The Nebraska State Patrol shall work with the United States Department of Justice to increase information sharing and resource coordination to focus on reporting and investigating missing Native American women and children in Nebraska. The Nebraska State Patrol shall submit a report electronically to the Executive Board of the Legislative Council by June 1, 2020, on the results of such study. Such report shall include data and analysis of the number of missing Native American women and children in Nebraska, identification of barriers in providing state resources to address the issue, and recommendations, including any proposed legislation, to improve the reporting and identification of missing Native American women and children in Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB154, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>