
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3710"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3710</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Tourism Commission; created; members; terms; districts.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Tourism Commission is created. The members of the commission shall consist of the Director of Economic Development and twelve residents of the State of Nebraska appointed by the Governor, to include one member representing a state chamber of commerce organized under the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, and one member appointed from each of the eleven districts described in subsection (2) of this section. The members appointed by the Governor shall be subject to approval by the majority of the members of the Legislature. The term of the member representing a state chamber of commerce shall be four years, and the terms of the district members shall be as provided in subdivision (2)(b) of this section. No appointed member may serve more than two successive terms. Four of the district members shall have professional, volunteer, or public service experience that contributes to the fiduciary and governance duties of the commission. Seven of the district members shall be affiliated with the tourism industry.</para><para>(2)(a) For purposes of this section, the state is hereby divided into eleven districts. The limits and designations of the eleven districts shall be as follows:</para><para>(i) District No. 1. Douglas County;</para><para>(ii) District No. 2. Lancaster County;</para><para>(iii) District No. 3. The counties of Richardson, Pawnee, Nemaha, Johnson, Otoe, Gage, Saline, and Jefferson;</para><para>(iv) District No. 4. The counties of Cass and Sarpy;</para><para>(v) District No. 5. The counties of Saunders, Washington, Dodge, Colfax, Stanton, Cuming, Burt, Thurston, Wayne, Cedar, Dixon, and Dakota;</para><para>(vi) District No. 6. The counties of Butler, Polk, Platte, Merrick, Nance, Boone, Madison, Pierce, Antelope, Knox, Holt, and Boyd;</para><para>(vii) District No. 7. The counties of Thayer, Nuckolls, Webster, Adams, Clay, Fillmore, Seward, York, Hamilton, Franklin, and Harlan;</para><para>(viii) District No. 8. The counties of Kearney, Phelps, Hall, Howard, Greeley, Wheeler, Buffalo, Sherman, Valley, and Garfield;</para><para>(ix) District No. 9. The counties of Lincoln, Keya Paha, Rock, Brown, Loup, Blaine, Custer, Logan, McPherson, Arthur, Grant, Hooker, Thomas, and Cherry;</para><para>(x) District No. 10. The counties of Furnas, Red Willow, Hitchcock, Dundy, Chase, Hayes, Frontier, Gosper, Dawson, Perkins, and Keith; and</para><para>(xi) District No. 11. The counties of Deuel, Garden, Sheridan, Cheyenne, Morrill, Box Butte, Dawes, Sioux, Scotts Bluff, Banner, and Kimball.</para><para>(b) The Governor shall appoint members representing district numbers 1, 6, 8, and 11 to serve for terms ending April 1, 2019; members representing district numbers 2, 5, 7, and 10 to serve for terms ending April 1, 2021; and members representing district numbers 3, 4, and 9 to serve for terms ending April 1, 2023. The terms of their successors shall be four years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1053, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB222, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB624, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>