
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3540"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3540</statuteno><catchline>Geology examinations.</catchline><para>(1) The board or its
agent shall direct the time and place of geology examinations.
The board shall determine the acceptable grade on examinations.</para>
<para>(2) The examination shall be given in two sections as follows:</para>
<para>(a) A fundamentals of geology examination designed to test the academic
preparation of the applicant in geology. At the board's discretion, the examination
may be taken at any time following substantial completion
of the applicant's educational requirements. Passing this examination qualifies
the examinee for a geologist-intern enrollment card, if all other requirements
for enrollment as a geologist-intern are met; and</para>
<para>(b) A principles and practice of geology examination designed to test
the applicant's ability to apply geologic knowledge and to assume responsible
charge of geologic work. The geologic practice examination may be taken only
after the applicant has acquired the education
and experience required for licensure as a geologist.</para>
<para>(3) A candidate failing one examination may apply for reexamination,
which may be granted upon payment of a fee established by the board. In the
event of a second failure, the examinee may, at the discretion of the board,
be required to appear before the board with evidence of having acquired the
necessary additional knowledge to qualify before admission to the examination.</para>
<para>(4) The board may prepare and adopt specifications for the examinations.
The specifications shall be published and be available to any person interested
in being licensed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>