<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3435"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3435</statuteno><catchline>Application for licensure or enrollment; form; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Application for licensure as an architect or professional engineer or enrollment as an engineer-intern shall be made on a form prescribed and furnished by the board. It shall contain statements made under oath showing the applicant's education and a detailed summary of technical experience and shall include the names and complete mailing addresses of the references, none of whom should be members of the board. The board may accept the verified information contained in a valid Council Record issued by the National Council of Architectural Registration Board or the National Council of Examiners for Engineering and Surveying in lieu of the same information that is required on the form prescribed and furnished by the board.</para><para>(2) Application and licensure fees shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. Original and reciprocal fees shall not exceed three hundred dollars and shall be in addition to the examination fee which shall be set to recover the costs of examination and its administration.</para><para>(3) The fee for intern enrollment shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed one hundred dollars and shall be in addition to the examination fee which shall be set to recover the costs of the examination and its administration.</para><para>(4) The certificate of authorization fee for organizations shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed three hundred dollars per year.</para><para>(5) The fee for emeritus status shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed one hundred dollars per year.</para><para>(6) If the board denies the issuance of a certificate or enrollment to any applicant, including the application of an organization for a certificate of authorization, the board shall retain the fee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 35. </para></source></law></legaldoc>