<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id409"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3540"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3540</statuteno><catchline>Geology examinations.</catchline><para>(1) The board or an agent of the board shall direct the time, place, and delivery method of geology examinations under the Geologists Regulation Act.</para><para>(2) The board may:</para><para>(a) Establish guidelines for how the board will determine if a written reference is acceptable;</para><para>(b) Prepare and adopt specifications for any examination requirement under the Geologists Regulation Act;</para><para>(c) Adopt any examination, examination procedure, grading procedure, acceptable examination grade requirement, or other examination or grading guideline of the National Association of State Boards of Geology;</para><para>(d) Specify the requirements for what qualifies as acceptable progressive experience;</para><para>(e) Publish any specification or guideline adopted under this section; and</para><para>(f) Make any specification or guideline adopted under this section available to any individual upon request.</para><para>(3)(a) Any individual who fails the examination on the fundamentals of geology or the examination on the practice of geology may apply for reexamination, which may be granted by the board. The board may waive the fee for any first reexamination.</para><para>(b) In the event of a second or subsequent failure of the same examination described in subdivision (a) of this subsection, the board may require such individual to appear before the board with evidence that such individual has acquired the necessary additional knowledge to qualify before admission for reexamination. The board may waive the fee charged for any second or subsequent reexamination.</para><para>(c) The board may charge a fee of not more than one hundred dollars for any reexamination described in this subsection.</para><para>(4) Any examination material described in the Geologists Regulation Act is not a public record subject to public inspection pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 41. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>