<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN"  "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"> <section><sectno></sectno> <amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3451"> <bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo> <statuteno>81-3451</statuteno> <catchline>Professional engineer or engineer-intern; license; application; examination; requirements.</catchline> <para>(1) To be eligible for admission to examination to be a professional engineer or engineer-intern, an applicant must be of good moral character and reputation and shall submit five references with his or her application for licensure as a professional engineer or enrollment as an engineer-intern. Three of the references shall be professional engineers having personal knowledge of the applicant's engineering experience or, in the case of an application for enrollment as an engineer-intern, character references.</para> <para>(2)(a) A person holding a certificate of licensure to engage in the practice of engineering, issued by the proper authority of a state or possession of the United States, the District of Columbia, or any foreign country, based on requirements that do not conflict with the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act and were of a standard not lower than that specified in the applicable licensure law in effect in this state at the time such certificate was issued may, upon application, be licensed as a professional engineer without further examination.</para> <para>(b) A person holding an active Council Record with the National Council of Examiners for Engineering and Surveying whose qualifications as evidenced by the Council Record meet the requirements of the act may, upon application, be licensed as a professional engineer without further examination.</para> <para>(c) A graduate of an Accrediting Board for Engineering and Technology accredited engineering curriculum, enrolled as an engineer-intern, and having a specific record of an additional four years or more of progressive post-baccalaureate-degree experience on engineering projects of a grade and a character which indicates to the Board of Engineers and Architects that the applicant may be competent to practice engineering shall be admitted to an eight-hour examination, administered by the board, on the principles and practice of engineering. Upon passing the examination, the applicant shall be granted a certificate of licensure to practice engineering in this state if the applicant is otherwise qualified. Engineering teaching of advanced subjects and the design of engineering research and projects in a college or university offering an Accrediting Board for Engineering and Technology accredited engineering curriculum of four years or more may be considered as engineering experience. An applicant who does not hold an Accrediting Board for Engineering and Technology accredited engineering degree but who is enrolled as an engineer-intern in this state and has a specific record of an additional six years or more of progressive experience on engineering projects of a grade and a character which indicates to the Board of Engineers and Architects that the applicant may be competent to practice engineering shall be admitted to an eight-hour examination, administered by the board, in the principles and practice of engineering. Upon passing the examination, the applicant shall be granted a certificate of licensure to practice engineering in this state if otherwise qualified.</para> <para>(3)(a) A graduate of or senior in an Accrediting Board for Engineering and Technology accredited engineering curriculum, or the substantial equivalent as determined by the board, shall be admitted to an eight-hour examination on the fundamentals of engineering. Upon passing the examination and verification of graduation, the applicant shall be enrolled as an engineer-intern.</para> <para>(b) An applicant who does not hold an Accrediting Board for Engineering and Technology accredited engineering degree may be admitted to the fundamentals of engineering examination if he or she has six years of engineering work experience or engineering-related education. Upon passing the examination, the applicant shall be enrolled as an engineer-intern. This subdivision terminates on January 1, 2005.</para></amendatorysection></section> <source> <para>Laws 1997, LB 622, ยง 51; </para> <para>Laws 2004, LB 599, ยง 4; </para> <para>Laws 2004, LB 1069, ยง 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>  