<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3442"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3442</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited acts; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) It is unlawful for any person to:</para><para>(a) Practice or offer to practice architecture or engineering in this state without being licensed in accordance with the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act unless such practice or offer to practice is otherwise exempt under the act;</para><para>(b) Knowingly and intentionally employ or retain a person to practice architecture or engineering in this state who is not licensed in accordance with the act, except as provided in sections 81-3414 and 81-3415, and who is not exempted by section 81-3449 or 81-3453;</para><para>(c) Use the words architect, engineer, or any modification or derivative of such words in its name or form of business activity except as authorized in the act or in the Professional Landscape Architects Act;</para><para>(d) Advertise any title or description tending to convey the impression that he or she is a licensed architect or professional engineer unless the person is duly licensed under the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act;</para><para>(e) Present or attempt to use the certificate of licensure or the seal of another person;</para><para>(f) Give any false or forged evidence of any kind to the board or to any member of the board in obtaining or attempting to obtain a certificate;</para><para>(g) Falsely impersonate any other licensee of like or different name;</para><para>(h) Attempt to use an expired, suspended, revoked, or nonexistent certificate of licensure or practice or offer to practice when not qualified;</para><para>(i) Falsely claim that he or she is licensed or authorized under the act; or</para><para>(j) Violate the act.</para><para>(2) Any person who performs any of the actions described in subsection (1) of this section is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor for the first offense and a Class IV felony for the second or any subsequent offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 40. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Professional Landscape Architects Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,183.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>