<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3121"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3121</statuteno><catchline>Contracts, documents, funds, and records of departments transferred to Department of Health and Human Services; how treated.</catchline><para>On and after July 1, 2007, whenever the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Health and Human Services Finance and Support, or the Department of Health and Human Services Regulation and Licensure is referred to or designated by any contract or other document in connection with the duties and functions transferred to the Department of Health and Human Services pursuant to the Health and Human Services Act, such reference or designation shall apply to such department. All contracts entered into by the agencies prior to July 1, 2007, in connection with the duties and functions transferred to the department are hereby recognized, with the department succeeding to all rights and obligations under such contracts. Any cash funds, custodial funds, gifts, trusts, grants, and any appropriations of funds from prior fiscal years available to satisfy obligations incurred under such contracts shall be transferred and appropriated to the department for the payments of such obligations. All licenses, certificates, registrations, permits, seals, or other forms of approval issued by the departments in accordance with functions or duties transferred to the department shall remain valid as issued under the names of the original departments unless revoked or their effectiveness is otherwise terminated as provided by law. All documents and records transferred, or copies of the same, may be authenticated or certified by the department for all legal purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>