<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id964"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3544"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3544</statuteno><catchline>Professional geologist; licensure; eligibility; application.</catchline><para>(1) The following are required for an applicant to be eligible for licensure by the board as a professional geologist under this section:</para><para>(a) The applicant has completed the education requirement of graduating from a geology or geologic specialty program with a minimum of thirty semester hours or forty-five quarter hours of course work in geology that includes course work in the content domains and hours as prescribed by the board;</para><para>(b) The applicant has passed the examination on the fundamentals of geology or a similar examination that is approved by the board;</para><para>(c) The applicant has passed the examination on the practice of geology or a similar examination that is approved by the board;</para><para>(d) The applicant has passed an examination on the statutes, rules, regulations, and other requirements unique to Nebraska;</para><para>(e) The applicant has a documented record of four or more years of progressive experience, obtained subsequent to completion of the education requirement, in geologic work of a grade and character which indicates to the board that the applicant may be competent to practice geology;</para><para>(f) The applicant has submitted an application accompanied by the fee established by the board; and</para><para>(g) The applicant has submitted one or more acceptable written references.</para><para>(2)(a) Any individual may apply for licensure as a professional geologist after completing the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(b) The board may authorize the licensure as a professional geologist for any individual described in subdivision (a) of this subsection once the individual has completed the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(c) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that specify when an individual may apply for licensure as a professional geologist.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 34. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>