<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id842" statutenumber="81-3432"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3432</statuteno><catchline id="id845">Engineers and Architects Regulation Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Engineers and Architects Regulation Fund is created. The board shall receive and account for all money derived from the operation of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act and shall remit the money to the State Treasurer for credit to the Engineers and Architects Regulation Fund. All expenses certified by the board as properly and necessarily incurred in the discharge of duties, including compensation and administrative staff, and any expense incident to the administration of the act relating to other states shall be paid out of the fund. Debt repayments payable pursuant to section 81-3432.01 shall be paid out of the fund. Warrants for the payment of expenses shall be issued by the Director of Administrative Services and paid by the State Treasurer upon presentation of vouchers regularly drawn by the chairperson and secretary of the board and approved by the board. At no time shall the total amount of warrants exceed the total amount of the fees collected under the act and to the credit of the fund. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Money in the Engineers and Architects Regulation Fund may be transferred to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB446, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB755, &#167; 40. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>