<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id106"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-3437.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3437.01</statuteno><catchline>Seal; contents; use; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Each licensee authorized to practice architecture or engineering must obtain a seal. The design of the seal shall be determined by the board. If a professional engineer's license has been issued in a specific discipline, the discipline shall be specified on the seal. The following information shall be on the seal: State of Nebraska; licensee's name; licensee's license number; and the words Architect or Professional (discipline) Engineer.</para><para>(2) Whenever the seal is applied, the licensee's signature shall be across the seal. The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for application of the seal.</para><para>(3) The seal and the date of its placement shall be on all technical submissions and calculations whenever presented to a client or any public or governmental agency. It shall be unlawful for a licensee to affix his or her seal or to permit his or her seal to be affixed to any document after the expiration of the certificate or for the purpose of aiding or abetting any other person to evade or attempt to evade the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act.</para><para>(4) The seal and date shall be placed on all originals, copies, tracings, or other reproducible drawings and the first and last pages of specifications, reports, and studies in such a manner that the seal, signature, and date will be reproduced and be in compliance with rules and regulations of the board. The application of the licensee's seal shall constitute certification that the work was done by the licensee or under the licensee's control.</para><para>(5) In the case of a temporary permit issued to a licensee of another state, the licensee shall use his or her state of licensure seal and shall affix his or her signature and temporary permit to all his or her work.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 36. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>