<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id976"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3539"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3539</statuteno><catchline>Licensure; examination; applicant; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall consider the following as evidence that an applicant is eligible for admission to the examination on the fundamentals of geology that is adopted by the board:</para><para>(a) The applicant is a senior in or has graduated from a geology or geologic specialty program recognized by the board;</para><para>(b) The applicant has successfully completed a minimum of thirty semester hours or forty-five quarter hours of course work in geology that includes course work in the content domains and hours as prescribed by the board;</para><para>(c) The applicant has submitted an application accompanied by the fee established by the board; and</para><para>(d) The applicant has submitted one or more acceptable written references.</para><para>(2)(a) Any individual may apply for admission to the examination on the fundamentals of geology after completing the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(b) The board may authorize the admission to the examination on the fundamentals of geology for any individual described in subdivision (a) of this subsection once the individual has completed the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(c) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that specify when an individual may apply for admission to the examination on the fundamentals of geology.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 31. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>