<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id21"  statutenumber="81-3128"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3128</statuteno><catchline>Program administration; staffing;
considerations; caseworkers; activities; appointments; equipment.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Department
of Health and Human Services shall staff multiple, integrated access points
for economic assistance programs administered by the department in order to
assure that Nebraskans who rely on such programs will be able to utilize them
effectively.</para>
<para>(2) The department
shall staff existing local offices that provide access to economic assistance
programs throughout the state with caseworkers to provide in-person services
to department clients. The department shall provide sufficient numbers and
hours of staff to perform the activities described in this section and section
81-3129.</para><para>(3) The department shall determine appropriate numbers and hours
of staff for each existing local office based on a review of the need in each
service area. In determining the appropriate numbers and hours of staff, the
department shall, at a minimum, consider: (a) The need for staff to travel
to community-based organizations as provided in section 81-3131; (b) the volume
of economic assistance cases in the counties served by the existing local
office; (c) the number of community-based organizations in the counties served
by the existing local office; (d) the volume of call-center calls originating
in the counties served by the existing local office; and (e) the requirements
of sections 81-3127 to 81-3131.</para><para>(4) Caseworkers at existing local offices
shall perform the following activities by appointment and on a drop-in basis:</para>
<para>(a) Help clients
complete assistance and renewal applications;</para><para>(b) Screen clients for
program eligibility;</para><para>(c) Interview clients for assistance eligibility and assistance
renewal eligibility;</para><para>(d) Determine program eligibility of the client; and</para>
<para>(e) Answer
client questions in person.</para><para>(5) Department call centers for economic
assistance programs shall take appointments for face-to-face help for clients
regarding or relating to such assistance upon request of the client.</para>
<para>(6) Each existing
local office shall be equipped with a reasonable number of computers, telephones,
and scanning equipment for client use.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB825, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>