<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3421"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3421</statuteno><catchline>Practice of engineering, defined.</catchline><para>Practice of engineering means any service or creative work if the adequate performance of the service or work requires engineering education, training, and experience in the application of special knowledge of the mathematical, physical, and engineering sciences to include such services or creative work as consultation, investigation, evaluation, planning, design and design coordination of engineering works and systems, planning the use of land and water, performing engineering surveys and studies, the review of construction for the purpose of monitoring compliance with drawings and specifications, administration of construction contracts, and acting as a coordinating professional, and any of which embraces such services or work, either public or private, in connection with any utilities, structures, buildings, machines, equipment, processes, work systems, projects, and industrial or consumer products or equipment of a mechanical, electrical, hydraulic, pneumatic, or thermal nature, insofar as they involve safeguarding life, health, or property, and including such other professional services as may be necessary to the planning, progress, and completion of any engineering services. The practice of engineering does not include the practice of architecture.</para><para>Design coordination includes the review and coordination of those technical submissions prepared by others, including, but not limited to, as appropriate and without limitation, consulting engineers, architects, landscape architects, land surveyors, and other professionals working under the direction of the professional engineer.</para><para>Engineering surveys includes all survey activities required to support the sound conception, planning, design, construction, maintenance, and operation of engineering projects but excludes the surveying of real property for the establishment of land boundaries, rights-of-way, easements, and the dependent or independent surveys or resurveys of the public land survey system.</para><para>A person shall be construed to practice or offer to practice engineering, within the meaning and intent of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act, if he or she: (1) Practices any branch of the profession of engineering; (2) by verbal claim, sign, advertisement, letterhead, or card or in any other way, represents himself or herself to be a professional engineer; (3) through the use of some other title, implies that he or she is a professional engineer or licensed under the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act; or (4) holds himself or herself out as able to perform or does perform any engineering service or work or any other service designated by the practitioner which is recognized by the board as engineering. The practice of engineering does not include the services ordinarily performed by subordinates under direct supervision of a professional engineer or those commonly designated as locomotive, stationary, and marine operating engineers, power plant operating engineers, or manufacturers who supervise the operation of or operate machinery or equipment or who supervise construction within their own plant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc>