<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3539"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3539</statuteno><catchline>Licensure; enrollment; applicant; qualifications.</catchline><para>Applications for licensure as a professional geologist, for temporary or reciprocal licensure, or for enrollment as a geologist-intern shall be on forms prescribed and furnished by the board and shall be accompanied by the fee established by the board. The requirements of subdivisions (1) through (3) of this section may be considered by the board to be fulfilled if the applicant maintains a current certificate of licensure to practice geology issued pursuant to the authority of any state or possession of the United States or the District of Columbia based on requirements that do not conflict with the Geologists Regulation Act and were of a standard not lower than that specified in the applicable licensure law in effect in this state at the time the certification was issued. The following shall be considered as minimum evidence satisfactory to the board that the applicant is qualified for licensure as a professional geologist or enrollment as a geologist-intern:</para><para>(1) The applicant is of good character and reputation and submits four references with his or her application for licensure as a professional geologist. Two of the references shall be professional geologists having personal knowledge of his or her geological experience or, in the case of the application for enrollment as a geologist-intern, acting only as character references;</para><para>(2) The applicant has successfully completed a minimum of thirty semester hours or forty-five quarter hours of course work in geology and has received a baccalaureate or advanced degree in geology or a geologic specialty from a program accredited by an organization recognized by the board;</para><para>(3) The applicant has a documented record of a minimum of five years of progressive experience, obtained subsequent to completion of the education requirements, in geologic work of a grade and character which indicates to the board that the applicant is qualified to assume responsible charge of such work upon licensure as a geologist, except that no work experience is required for enrollment as a geologist-intern; and</para><para>(4) The applicant has completed an examination covering the fundamentals and practice of geology prescribed by the board. Upon passing the fundamentals of geology examination, the applicant may be enrolled as a geologist-intern. Upon passing the practice of geology examination, the applicant shall be granted a certificate of licensure to practice geology in this state if otherwise qualified. A person who holds a valid certificate of licensure to engage in the practice of geology, issued pursuant to the authority of any state or possession of the United States or the District of Columbia based on requirements that do not conflict with the act and were of a standard not lower than that specified in the applicable licensing law in effect in this state at the time the certificate was issued, may, upon application, be licensed without further examination. Geologic teaching of advanced subjects and the design of geologic research and projects in a college or university offering an accredited geologic curriculum may be considered by the board as geologic experience.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>