<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id13" statutenumber="81-3448"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3448</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Architect; license; application; fee; requirements; examination; temporary permit.</catchline><para>(1) The following shall be considered as the minimum evidence satisfactory to the board that an applicant is eligible for initial licensure as an architect:</para><para>(a)(i) Graduation from a program accredited by the National Architectural Accrediting Board;</para><para>(ii) Graduation from a program accredited by the Canadian Architectural Certification Board; or</para><para>(iii) Satisfying the requirements of the Education Standard of the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards as determined by the council;</para><para>(b) Passage of an examination on technical and professional subjects of architecture;</para><para>(c) Completion of the Architectural Experience Program of the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards, or its equivalent as determined by the council or the Board of Engineers and Architects;</para><para>(d) Passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state; and</para><para>(e) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure.</para><para>(2) An individual holding a license to practice architecture issued by a proper authority of any jurisdiction, based on credentials that do not conflict with subsection (1) of this section and other provisions of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act, may, upon application, be licensed as an architect after:</para><para>(a) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state; and</para><para>(b) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure.</para><para>(3) An individual who holds a current and valid certification issued by the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards and who submits satisfactory evidence of such certification to the board may, upon application, be licensed as an architect after:</para><para>(a) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state; and</para><para>(b) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure.</para><para>(4) An individual who has been licensed to practice architecture for fifteen years or more in one or more jurisdictions and who has practiced architecture for fifteen years in compliance with the licensing laws in the jurisdictions where his or her architectural practice has occurred since initial licensure may, upon application, be licensed as an architect after:</para><para>(a) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state; and</para><para>(b) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure.</para><para>(5) Upon application to the board in writing and payment of a fee established by the board, an individual who holds a valid license to practice architecture in another jurisdiction may be issued a temporary permit, valid for a definite period of time, to provide architectural services for a specific project. An individual may not be issued more than one temporary permit. No right to practice architecture accrues to such applicant with respect to any other work not set forth in the temporary permit. Temporary permit holders are subject to all of the provisions of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act governing the practice of architecture.</para><para>(6) None of the examination materials described in this section shall be considered public records.</para><para>(7) The board or its agent shall direct the time and place of the architectural examinations referenced in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(8) The board may adopt the examinations and grading procedures of the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards. The board may also adopt guidelines published by the council.</para><para>(9) Licensure shall be effective upon issuance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB755, &#167; 43. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>