<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id162"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3527"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3527</statuteno><catchline>Professional geologist, geologist-intern, or certificate of authorization; application; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Any person may apply under oath or affirmation to become a professional geologist, become a geologist-intern, or receive a certificate of authorization on a form prescribed and furnished by the board. The board may accept the verified information contained in a valid record issued by the National Association of State Boards of Geology in lieu of the same information that is required on the form prescribed and furnished by the board.</para><para>(2)(a) The fee for any application, renewal, licensure, certificate of authorization, or enrollment shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. Any such fee is nonrefundable and shall not exceed three hundred dollars for licensure as a geologist and one hundred dollars for enrollment as a geologist-intern and shall be in addition to the examination fee which shall be set to recover the costs of the examination and its administration.</para><para>(b) For any fee charged pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection, the board may charge an additional fee to cover the administrative costs of collecting such fee not to exceed one hundred dollars.</para><para>(3) The certificate of authorization fee for organizations shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed three hundred dollars.</para><para>(4) The fee for emeritus status shall be established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed one hundred dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>