<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3451"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3451</statuteno><catchline>Engineer-intern; enrollment; requirements; application; fee; professional engineer; license; application; fee; examination; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The following shall be considered as the minimum evidence satisfactory to the board that an applicant is eligible for enrollment as an engineer-intern:</para><para>(a) Graduation from a program accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, or meeting the Education Standard of the National Council of Examiners for Engineering and Surveying as determined by the council;</para><para>(b) Passage of an examination in the fundamentals of engineering as accepted by the board;</para><para>(c) Submittal of an application accompanied by the fee established by the board; and</para><para>(d) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for enrollment.</para><para>(2)(a) The following shall be considered as the minimum evidence satisfactory to the board that an applicant is eligible for admission to the examination on the principles and practice of engineering that is adopted by the board:</para><para>(i) Graduation from a program accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, or meeting the Education Standard of the National Council of Examiners for Engineering and Surveying as determined by the council;</para><para>(ii) A record of four years or more of progressive post-accredited-degree experience on engineering projects of a grade and character which indicates to the board that the applicant may be competent to practice engineering;</para><para>(iii) Passage of an examination in the fundamentals of engineering as accepted by the board;</para><para>(iv) Submittal of an application accompanied by the fee established by the board; and</para><para>(v) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application.</para><para>(b) A candidate who fails the principles and practice of engineering examination may apply for reexamination, which may be granted upon payment of a fee established by the board. In the event of a second or subsequent failure, the examinee may, at the discretion of the board, be required to appear before the board with evidence of having acquired the necessary additional knowledge to qualify before admission to the examination.</para><para>(3) The following shall be considered as the minimum evidence satisfactory to the board that an applicant is eligible for licensure as a professional engineer:</para><para>(a) Passage of the principles and practice of engineering examination as set forth in subsection (2) of this section;</para><para>(b) A record of four years or more of progressive post-accredited-degree experience on engineering projects of a grade and character which indicates to the board that the applicant may be competent to practice engineering;</para><para>(c) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure; and</para><para>(d) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state.</para><para>(4) An individual holding a license to practice engineering issued by a proper authority of any jurisdiction, based on credentials that do not conflict with subsections (2) and (3) of this section and other provisions of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act, may, upon application, be licensed as a professional engineer after:</para><para>(a) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure; and</para><para>(b) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state.</para><para>(5) An individual who has been licensed to practice engineering for fifteen years or more in one or more jurisdictions and who has practiced engineering for fifteen years in compliance with the licensing laws in the jurisdictions where his or her engineering practice has occurred since initial licensure may, upon application, be licensed as a professional engineer after:</para><para>(a) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the board shall be included in the application for licensure; and</para><para>(b) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules, and other requirements unique to this state.</para><para>(6) The board may designate a professional engineer as being licensed in a specific discipline or branch of engineering signifying the area in which the professional engineer has demonstrated competence.</para><para>(7) An individual who holds a valid license to practice engineering in another jurisdiction may be issued a temporary permit to provide engineering services for a specific project. An individual may not be issued more than one temporary permit. Temporary permit holders are subject to all of the provisions of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act governing the practice of engineering.</para><para>(8) None of the examination materials described in this section shall be considered public records.</para><para>(9) The board or its agent shall direct the time and place of the engineering examinations referenced in subsections (1), (2), and (3) of this section.</para><para>(10) The board may adopt the examinations and grading procedures of the National Council of Examiners for Engineering and Surveying. The board may also adopt guidelines published by the council.</para><para>(11) Licensure shall be effective upon issuance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 599, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1069, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 47. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>