<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3452"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3452</statuteno><catchline>Engineering examinations; board;
procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The board or its agent shall direct the time
and place of engineering examinations. The board shall determine the acceptable
grade on examinations.</para>
<para>(2) The examination will be given in at
least two sections and may be taken only after the applicant has
met the other minimum requirements as described in section 81-3451 and has
been approved by the board for admission to the examination as follows:</para>
<para>(a) The fundamentals of engineering examination consists of an eight-hour
test period on the fundamentals of engineering. Passing this examination qualifies
the examinee for an engineer-intern enrollment card if all other requirements
for certification are met; and</para>
<para>(b) The principles and practice of engineering examination consists
of at least an
eight-hour test period on applied engineering. Passing this examination qualifies
the examinee for licensure as a professional engineer if all other requirements
for certification are met.</para>
<para>(3) A candidate failing one examination may apply for reexamination,
which may be granted upon payment of a fee established by the board. In the
event of a second failure, the examinee may, at the discretion of the board,
be required to appear before the board with evidence of having acquired the
necessary additional knowledge to qualify before admission to the examination.</para>
<para>(4) The board may prepare and adopt specifications for the examinations.
They shall be published in brochure form and be available to any person interested
in being licensed or certified.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
