<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id6" statutenumber="81-3713"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3713</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Commission; duties; awarding of contracts.</catchline>
<para>(1) The commission shall
develop a program to provide promotional services and technical assistance
to local governments and industry members and to ensure the protection and
development of Nebraska's attraction resources.</para>
<para>(2) The commission shall develop
a statewide strategic plan to cultivate and promote tourism in Nebraska. The commission shall adopt policy
criteria to be used in the development of the plan. The plan shall include:</para>
<para>(a) A review of the existing
and potential sources of funding for tourism at the state and local levels;</para>
<para>(b) A comprehensive inventory
of local tourism boards, the structure of such boards, and their funding;</para>
<para>(c) Criteria for local tourism
boards in terms of appointments to such boards and for awarding grants by
such boards at the local level to ensure local resources are used to achieve
the greatest return;</para>
<para>(d) An examination of other
states' funding models for tourism;</para>
<para>(e) Marketing strategies for
promoting tourism;</para>
<para>(f) A proposal for creating
new or expanding existing tourism capacity which
may include encouraging regional cooperation, collaboration, or privatization;
and</para>
<para>(g) Recommended legislation
or funding requirements.</para>
<para>(3) All advertising contracts
awarded by the commission concerning travel
and tourism shall be based on competitive bids. Contracts shall be awarded
to the lowest responsible bidder, taking into consideration the best interests
of the state, the quality of performance of the services rendered, the conformity
with specifications, the purposes for which required, and the time of completion. In determining the lowest responsible bidder,
in addition to price, the commission shall consider: (a) The ability,
capacity, creativity, and skill of the bidder to perform the contract required;
(b) the character, integrity, reputation, judgment, experience, and efficiency
of the bidder; (c) whether the bidder can perform the contract within the
time specified; (d) the quality of performance of previous contracts; (e)
the previous and existing compliance by the bidder with laws relating to the
contract; and (f) such other information as may be secured having a bearing
on the decision to award the contract. The commission shall advertise
for bids for the awarding of contracts concerning travel and tourism pursuant
to sections 73-101 to 73-105. At least thirty working days shall elapse between
the time formal bids are advertised for and the time of their opening. Contracts
shall be awarded within sixty working days after the bidding has been closed.
Each person submitting a bid shall be notified by
certified mail as to whom the contract was awarded.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 965, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB684, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 81-1201.13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 193; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1053, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>