<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3437"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3437</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of licensure; issuance; seal; use; enrollment card; issuance.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall issue to any applicant who, on the basis of education, experience, and examination, has met the requirements of the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act a certificate of licensure giving the licensee proper authority to carry out the prerogatives of the act. The certificate of licensure shall carry the designation Licensed Architect or Licensed Professional (discipline) Engineer. The certificate shall give the full name of the licensee and license number and shall be signed by the chairperson of the board, the secretary of the board, and a board member representing the respective profession under the seal of the board.</para><para>(2) The certificate shall be prima facie evidence that the person is entitled to all rights, privileges, and responsibilities of an architect or a professional engineer while the certificate of licensure remains unrevoked and unexpired.</para><para>(3)(a) Each licensee authorized to practice architecture or engineering must obtain a seal. It shall be unlawful for a licensee to affix his or her seal and signature or to permit his or her seal and signature to be affixed to any document after the expiration of the certificate or for the purpose of aiding or abetting any other person to evade or attempt to evade the act.</para><para>(b) The seal may be a rubber stamp or may be generated electronically. Whenever the seal is applied, the licensee's written signature and the date shall be across the seal. No further words or wording are required. Electronic signatures applied to electronic seals must be protected with an electronic revision approval system. Documents without electronic revision approval protection that are transmitted electronically to a client or a governmental agency shall have the seal removed from the file. The electronic media shall have the following inserted in lieu of the seal, signature, and date: </para><para>This document was originally issued and sealed by (name of sealer), (license number), on (date of sealing). This media should not be considered a certified document.</para><para>(c) The seal, signature, and date shall be placed on all technical submissions and calculations whenever presented to a client or any public or governmental agency.</para><para>(d) The seal, signature, and date shall be placed on all originals, copies, tracings, or other reproducible drawings and the first and last pages of specifications, reports, and studies in such a manner that the seal, signature, and date will be reproduced and be in compliance with rules and regulations of the board. The application of the licensee's seal and signature shall constitute certification that the work was done by the licensee or under the licensee's control. In the case of multiple sealings, the first or title page shall be sealed, signed, and dated by all involved. In addition, each sheet shall be sealed, signed, and dated by the licensee responsible for each sheet. In the case of an organization, each sheet shall be sealed, signed, and dated by the licensee involved. The architect or professional engineer in responsible charge shall sign, seal, and date the title or first sheet.</para><para>(e) In the case of a temporary permit issued to a licensee of another state, the licensee shall use his or her state of licensure seal and shall affix his or her signature and temporary permit to all his or her work.</para><para>(f) The design of the seal shall be determined by the board. The following information shall be on the seal: State of Nebraska; licensee's name; licensee's license number; and the words Architect or Professional (discipline) Engineer.</para><para>(g) Projects involving more than one licensed architect or professional engineer shall have one designated as the coordinating professional. The coordinating professional shall apply his or her seal and signature and the date to the cover sheet of all documents and denote the seal as that of the coordinating professional.</para><para>(4) The board shall issue to any applicant who, in the opinion of the board, has met the requirements of the act an enrollment card as engineer-intern which indicates that his or her name has been recorded as such in the board office. The engineer-intern enrollment card does not authorize the holder to practice as a professional engineer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 37. </para></source></law></legaldoc>