<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id805"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3536" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3536</statuteno><catchline>Violation of act; charges; board; duties; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) Charges against any individual or organization involving any matter coming within the jurisdiction of the board shall be in writing and shall be filed with the board.</para><para>(2) The board shall hold a hearing on any such charges within a reasonable time and in accordance with the rules and regulations that have been adopted and promulgated by the board. Such hearing may include the use of a hearing officer. The accused shall have the right to appear personally with or without counsel, to cross-examine adverse witnesses, and to produce evidence and witnesses in defense of the accused.</para><para>(3) The board shall set the time and place for the hearing and shall cause a copy of the charges and a notice of the time and place fixed for the hearing to be delivered to the accused at least thirty days before the hearing. Such copy and notice shall be sent by registered mail to the accused at the last-known business or residence address of the accused known to the board.</para><para>(4) If, after the hearing, the board finds the accused has violated the Geologists Regulation Act or any rules or regulations, the board may issue any order described in section 81-3537. If the order revokes or suspends a license or places a license on probation, the board shall provide written notice of such revocation, suspension, or probation to the Secretary of State.</para><para>(5) The board may reissue a license to any person whose license has been revoked. Application for the reissuance of a license shall be made in accordance with sections 81-3544 to 81-3547 and in a manner as the board directs and shall be accompanied by a fee established by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 29. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>