<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id633"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3537"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3537</statuteno><catchline>Violation of act; disciplinary action; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) The board may after hearing, by majority vote, take any or all of the following actions, upon proof satisfactory to the board that any person or organization has violated the Geologists Regulation Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act:</para><para>(a) Issuance of censure or reprimand;</para><para>(b) Suspension of judgment;</para><para>(c) Placement of the offender on probation with the board;</para><para>(d) Placement of a limitation or limitations on the holder of a license and upon the right of the holder of a license to practice the profession to such extent, scope, or type of practice for such time and under such conditions as are found necessary and proper;</para><para>(e) Imposition of a civil penalty not to exceed ten thousand dollars. The amount of the penalty shall be based on the severity of the violation;</para><para>(f) Entrance of an order of revocation or suspension of the certificate of licensure;</para><para>(g) Issuance of a cease and desist order;</para><para>(h) Imposition of costs as in an ordinary civil action in the district court, which may include attorney's fees and hearing officer fees incurred by the board and the expenses of any investigation undertaken by the board; or</para><para>(i) Dismissal of the action.</para><para>(2) In hearings under this section, the board may take into account suitable evidence of reform.</para><para>(3) Civil penalties collected under subdivision (1)(e) of this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska. All costs collected under subdivision (1)(h) of this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Geologists Regulation Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 30. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>