<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3539"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3539</statuteno><catchline>Licensure; enrollment; applicant;
qualifications; waiver.</catchline><para>(1) Applications
for licensure as a professional geologist, for temporary or reciprocal licensure,
or for enrollment as a geologist-intern shall be on forms prescribed and furnished
by the board and shall be accompanied by the fee established by the board.</para>
<para>(2) The following shall be
considered as minimum evidence satisfactory to the board that the applicant
is qualified for licensure as a professional geologist or enrollment as a
geologist-intern:</para>
<para>(a) The applicant is of good
character and reputation and submits four references with his or her application
for licensure as a professional geologist. Two of the references shall be
professional geologists having personal knowledge of his or her geological
experience or, in the case of the application for enrollment as a geologist-intern,
acting only as character references;</para>
<para>(b) The applicant has successfully
completed a minimum of thirty semester hours or forty-five quarter hours of
course work in geology and has received a baccalaureate or advanced degree
in geology or a geologic specialty from a program recognized by
the board;</para>
<para>(c) The applicant has a documented
record of a minimum of five years of progressive experience, obtained subsequent
to completion of the education requirements, in geologic work of a grade and
character which indicates to the board that the applicant is qualified to
assume responsible charge of such work upon licensure as a geologist, including geologic teaching of advanced
subjects and the design of geologic research and projects in a college or
university offering a geologic curriculum, except that no work
experience is required for enrollment as a geologist-intern; and</para>
<para>(d) The applicant has completed
an examination covering the fundamentals and practice of geology prescribed
by the board. Upon passing the fundamentals of geology examination, the applicant
may be enrolled as a geologist-intern. Upon passing the practice of geology
examination, the applicant may be granted a certificate
of licensure to practice geology in this state if otherwise qualified.</para>
<para>(3) A person who holds a valid
certificate of licensure to engage in the practice of geology, issued pursuant
to the authority of any state or possession of the United States or the District
of Columbia based on requirements that do not conflict with the act and were
of a standard not lower than that specified in the applicable licensing law
in effect in this state at the time the certificate was issued, may, upon
application, be considered
by the board to have fulfilled the requirements of subdivisions (2)(b) and
(c) of this section and be licensed without further examination as
required under subdivision (2)(d) of this section.</para>
<para>(4) The requirements
of subdivisions (2)(b) through (d) of this section may be waived by the board
if the applicant is licensed to practice geology at the time of application
and has maintained a current certificate of licensure to practice geology
for at least fifteen years issued pursuant to the authority of a state or
possession of the United States or the District of Columbia based on requirements
that do not conflict with the Geologists Regulation Act and if the applicant
has lawfully practiced geology for at least fifteen years in such jurisdiction.
Lawful practice includes any practice that is in compliance with the licensure
law in effect in the jurisdiction where the practice occurs.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>