
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id00" statutenumber="81-3428"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3428</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of Engineers and Architects; created; members; terms; location.</catchline><para>(1) The Board of Engineers and Architects is created to administer the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act. The board shall consist of eight members appointed by the Governor for terms of five years terminating on the last day of February. The board shall consist of:</para><para>(a) Three architect members, two of whom shall be appointed after consulting with the appropriate architectural professional organizations, and one education member who is a faculty member of the University of Nebraska appointed upon the recommendation of the Dean of Architecture of the University of Nebraska;</para><para>(b) Four professional engineer members, three of whom shall be appointed after consulting with the appropriate engineering professional organizations, and one education member who is a faculty member of the University of Nebraska appointed upon the recommendation of the Dean of Engineering of the University of Nebraska; and</para><para>(c) One public member.</para><para>(2) Each member shall hold office after the expiration of his or her term until his or her successor is duly appointed and qualified. Vacancies in the membership of the board, however created, shall be filled for the unexpired term by appointment by the Governor. The Governor shall reappoint or replace existing members as their terms expire, and the public member shall be reappointed or replaced in the fifth year of his or her term. The Governor may remove any member of the board for misconduct, incompetency, or neglect of duty.</para><para>(3) Each member of the board shall be a citizen of the United States and a resident of the State of Nebraska for at least one year immediately preceding appointment. Each architect or professional engineer member shall have been engaged in the active practice of the design profession for at least ten years and shall have been licensed in the relevant profession for at least five years at the time of his or her appointment.</para><para>(4) The board may designate a former member of the board as an emeritus member, but for no more than ten years after his or her original board membership expires. Emeritus member status, when conferred, must be renewed annually.</para><para>(5) The board offices shall be located in Lincoln, Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB755, &#167; 38. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>