<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3717"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3717</statuteno><catchline>County Visitors Promotion Fund; County
Visitors Improvement Fund; visitors committee; establishment; purpose.</catchline>
<para>(1) The governing body of the county shall after a public hearing adopt
a resolution establishing a County Visitors Promotion Fund and a visitors
committee which shall serve as an advisory committee to the governing body
in administering the proceeds from the taxes provided to the county by the
Nebraska Visitors Development Act. The governing body of a county may also
after a public hearing adopt a resolution establishing a County Visitors Improvement
Fund. The proceeds of the County Visitors Promotion Fund shall be used generally
to promote, encourage, and attract visitors to come to the county and use
the travel and tourism facilities within the county. The proceeds of the County
Visitors Improvement Fund shall be used to improve the visitor attractions
and facilities in the county, except that no proceeds shall be used to improve
a facility in which parimutuel wagering is conducted. If the visitors committee
determines that the visitor attractions in the county are adequate and do
not require improvement, the governing body of the county, with the advice
of the committee, may only use
the County Visitors Improvement Fund to promote, encourage, and attract visitors
to the county to use the county's travel and tourism facilities or, with the advice of the visitors committee,
make grants to organizations to promote, encourage, and attract visitors to
the county to use the county's travel and tourism facilities, except that
no proceeds shall be granted to an organization to promote parimutuel wagering.
The committee shall consist of five or seven members appointed by the governing
body of the county. If the committee has five members, at least one but no
more than two members of the committee shall be in the hotel industry. If
the committee has seven members, at least two but no more than three members
of the committee shall be in the hotel industry.</para>
<para>(2) The members of the committee shall serve without compensation, except
for reimbursement for necessary expenses. Committee members shall serve for
terms of four years, except that at least half of those appointed shall be
appointed for initial terms of two years. Vacancies shall be filled in the
same manner as the initial appointments. The committee shall elect a chairperson
and vice-chairperson from among its members to serve for terms of two years.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 499, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 797, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 262, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 499, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 726, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB277, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2011, &#167; 81-1255; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1053, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB215, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>