
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3531"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3531</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of licensure; certificate
of authorization; renewal; form;
contents; notice; fee; continuing education; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Certificates
of licensure and certificates of authorization shall expire on a date established
by the board and shall become invalid after that date unless renewed. The
secretary of the board shall notify every person licensed under the Geologists
Regulation Act and every organization holding a certificate of authorization
under the act of the date of the expiration of the certificate of licensure
or certificate of authorization and the amount of the fee required for renewal.
The notice shall be mailed to the licensee or organization at the last-known
address on file with the board at least one month in advance of the date of
the expiration. Renewal may be effected at any time prior to or during the
period established by the board upon application pursuant to this section and payment of a renewal
fee. The fee shall not exceed two hundred dollars per year. Renewal of an
expired certificate may be effected under rules and regulations of the board
regarding requirements for reexamination and for penalty fees. The board may
adopt a program of continuing education as
a requirement for renewal for individual licensees.</para>
<para>(2) An applicant for
renewal of a certificate of licensure shall apply on a form prescribed and
furnished by the board. The application shall contain statements made under
oath showing the applicant's fitness to maintain licensure, including felony
convictions in any jurisdiction, convictions involving moral turpitude in
any jurisdiction, and suspension or revocation of a professional license in
any other jurisdiction. The board shall review the application for renewal.
If the board takes no action, the license shall be renewed. The board may
deny renewal if it determines the applicant does not meet the requirements
for licensure or renewal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 78; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>