
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id960"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3145"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3145</statuteno><catchline>Intergenerational Care Facility Incentive Grant Program; requirements; eligibility; use; priority.</catchline><para>(1) The Intergenerational Care Facility Incentive Grant Program is created. It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate three hundred thousand dollars from the Medicaid Managed Care Excess Profit Fund for fiscal year 2024-25 to the Department of Health and Human Services to provide grants pursuant to this section.</para><para>(2) The Department of Health and Human Services shall develop requirements for eligibility, application, and audits for grants in collaboration with statewide associations representing nursing homes as defined in section 38-2414 and other stakeholders. The department shall meet with such associations prior to October 1, 2024, to identify any statutes, rules, regulations, or other regulatory barriers that impede the development of an intergenerational care facility in which nursing services and child care are provided and develop recommendations to remediate such barriers that do not impact the safety of the staff or recipients of the nursing services and child care or the quality of nursing services and child care.</para><para>(3) The grants shall be awarded to facilities that are nursing homes as defined in section 38-2414 or assisted-living facilities as defined in section 71-5903 and that have been certified for participation in medicare or medicaid. The grants shall be used for one-time startup costs to provide for child care in such facilities. A facility may be awarded one grant under this section of up to one hundred thousand dollars. The grants shall be awarded for modification of structures, modification of outside campus space of the nursing facilities, purchase of child care equipment and supplies, or any combination of such purposes. A facility that is applying for or awarded a grant is not required to own or operate the child care services for which the grant is awarded.</para><para>(4) The department shall award the grants on the basis of date of application with priority given to rural communities, as defined in section 81-1228, for applications filed on the same date. A facility that was cited for substandard quality of care during its most recent survey is not eligible for a grant under this section. Each grant recipient shall establish a plan to participate in the quality rating and improvement system described in section 71-1956 within three years after the date the grant is awarded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB904, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>