<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3444"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3444</statuteno><catchline>Disciplinary actions authorized; civil penalties.</catchline><para>(1) The board may after hearing, by majority vote, take any or all of the following actions, upon proof satisfactory to the board that any person or organization has violated the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act or any rules or regulations. The following actions may be taken against a holder of a license upon a two-thirds majority vote of the board:</para><para>(a) Issuance of censure or reprimand;</para><para>(b) Suspension of judgment;</para><para>(c) Placement of the offender on probation;</para><para>(d) Placement of a limitation or limitations on the holder of a license and upon the right of the holder of a license to practice the profession to such extent, scope, or type of practice for such time and under such conditions as are found necessary and proper;</para><para>(e) Imposition of a civil penalty not to exceed ten thousand dollars for each offense. The amount of the penalty shall be based on the severity of the violation;</para><para>(f) Entrance of an order of revocation, suspension, or cancellation of the certificate of licensure;</para><para>(g) Issuance of a cease and desist order;</para><para>(h) Imposition of costs as in an ordinary civil action in the district court, which may include reasonable attorney's fees and hearing officer fees incurred by the board and the expenses of any investigation undertaken by the board; or</para><para>(i) Dismissal of the action.</para><para>(2) In hearings under this section, the board may take into account suitable evidence of reform.</para><para>(3) Civil penalties collected under subdivision (1)(e) of this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the permanent school fund. All costs collected under subdivision (1)(h) of this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Engineers and Architects Regulation Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 44. </para></source></law></legaldoc>