
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3520"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3520</statuteno><catchline>Board of Geologists; created; membership;
terms.</catchline><para>(1) The Board of Geologists is created to administer
the Geologists Regulation Act. The board may use any funds available to obtain
suitable office space within Lincoln, Nebraska, for the board. The board shall
consist of seven members appointed by the Governor for terms of five years
each, ending on the last day of February. The members shall include one education
member appointed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section and one public
member. All members of the board shall be professional geologists with the
exception of the one public member. Each member shall hold office after the
expiration of his or her term until his or her successor is duly appointed
and qualified. The length of the initial terms shall be staggered, as determined
by the board. The Governor may remove any member of the board for misconduct,
incompetency, or neglect of duty. Vacancies on the board, however created,
shall be filled for the unexpired term by appointment by the Governor.</para>
<para>(2) The membership of the board shall include one education member who
is licensed in geology and who is a member of the
professional faculty of a geology or related geosciences department of a college or university
located in Nebraska, recommended by the president of the respective college or university,
and appointed by the Governor.</para>
<para>(3) The membership of the board shall include one public member appointed
by the Governor. The appointment is for five years.</para>
<para>(4) The board may designate a former member of the board as an emeritus
member. Emeritus member status, when conferred, must be renewed annually.
The emeritus member shall be a nonvoting member.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>