<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id60"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3543"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3543</statuteno><catchline>Examination of the practice of geology; eligibility; application.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall consider the following as evidence that an applicant is eligible for admission to the examination on the practice of geology adopted by the board:</para><para>(a) The applicant has completed the education requirement of graduating from a geology or geologic specialty program with a minimum of thirty semester hours or forty-five quarter hours of course work in geology that includes course work in the content domains and hours as prescribed by the board;</para><para>(b) The applicant has passed the examination on the fundamentals of geology;</para><para>(c) The applicant has a documented record of a minimum of four years of progressive experience that was obtained subsequent to completion of the education requirements, in geologic work of a grade or character that indicates to the board that the applicant may be competent to practice geology;</para><para>(d) The applicant has submitted an application accompanied by the fee established by the board; and</para><para>(e) The applicant has submitted one or more acceptable written references.</para><para>(2)(a) Any individual may apply for admission to the examination on the practice of geology after completing the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(b) The board may authorize the admission to the examination on the practice of geology for any individual described in subdivision (a) of this subsection once the individual has completed the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(c) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that specify when an individual may apply for admission to the examination on the practice of geology.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 33. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>