<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id6"  statutenumber="81-3127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3127</statuteno><catchline>Program administration; terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes
of sections 81-3127 to 81-3132:</para>
<para>(1) Client means
an applicant for one or more economic assistance programs or his or her legal
representative;</para><para>(2) Community-based organization means:</para><para>(a) An area agency on aging
established pursuant to the Nebraska Community Aging Services Act;</para>
<para>(b) A Nebraska-based
community action agency designated under the federal Economic Opportunity
Act of 1964, 42 U.S.C. 2701 et seq.;</para><para>(c) A Nebraska-based center for independent
living established under the federal Rehabilitation Act of 1973, 29 U.S.C.
701 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2012;</para><para>(d) A Nebraska-based rural
health clinic established under the federal Rural Health Clinics Act of 1983,
42 U.S.C. 201 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2012;</para>
<para>(e) A Nebraska-based
federally qualified health center and rural health clinic as such terms are
defined in the federal Social Security Act, 42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa), as such section
existed on January 1, 2012; and</para><para>(f) Any other organization that demonstrates
to the Department of Health and Human Services that it can comply with the
requirements of subsection (2) of section 81-3131;</para><para>(3) Economic assistance
programs includes aid to dependent children; aid to the aged, blind, and disabled;
Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program; medicaid; child care; emergency
assistance; energy assistance; social services block grants; and other similar
programs administered by the department; and</para>
<para>(4) Existing local
office means all office locations for economic assistance programs of the
Department of Health and Human Services that existed on January 1, 2012.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB825, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Community Aging Services Act,</emphasis> see section 81-2201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>