<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id53">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id55" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-3131"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3131</statuteno><catchline>Program administration; contracts
with community-based organizations authorized; Department of Health and Human
Services; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall enter
into contracts with community-based organizations which allow the department
to keep caseworkers present at the community-based organization at the times
specified in the contract. A contract under this section shall specify sufficient
times to allow caseworkers to:</para>
<para>(a) Screen
and conduct interviews for assistance eligibility and assistance renewal;</para>
<para>(b) Assist
clients with assistance applications and renewals;</para><para>(c) Receive assistance
applications and renewals;</para><para>(d) Answer questions in person;</para>
<para>(e) Train and
provide technical assistance to staff of community-based organizations; and</para>
<para>(f) Conduct
face-to-face interviews with clients by appointment and on a drop-in basis.</para>
<para>(2) In addition
to the requirements specified in subsection (1) of this section, each such
contract shall allow the community-based organization to:</para>
<para>(a) Provide
quality, accurate information relating to economic assistance programs that
are targeted at populations known to have low participation rates in or difficulty
accessing such assistance programs;</para><para>(b) Provide quality outreach to clients
in the target populations who utilize economic assistance programs;</para>
<para>(c) Assist
clients in scheduling appointments with caseworkers at a community-based organization
facility or local office that provides access to economic assistance programs,
whichever the client prefers;</para><para>(d) Assist with organization of information
required for economic assistance application or renewal; and</para>
<para>(e) Negotiate
fair compensation for services provided to applicants for economic assistance
benefits as described in this section.</para><para>(3) The department shall maintain a sufficient
number of contracts to provide access to assistance for all Nebraska citizens
in establishing and maintaining eligibility for economic assistance programs.
In determining the number of contracts with community-based organizations,
the department shall, at a minimum, consider:</para><para>(a) The geographic distance
applicants would be required to travel to meet with a caseworker in person
and how to minimize that distance;</para><para>(b) The volume of economic assistance cases
in the service area and how to adequately serve those cases;</para>
<para>(c) The number
of clients in an area who have difficulty in verbal and written communication
due to hearing or vision impairment, language barriers, or literacy challenges
and how to accommodate their needs;</para><para>(d) The community-based organization's ability
to serve the need; and</para><para>(e) The number of existing local offices in the service area.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB825, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>