<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id246"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3147"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3147</statuteno><catchline>Rural Health Transformation Program; implementation; Department of Health and Human Services; awardee; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services, as the applicant on behalf of the State of Nebraska for money from the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services for the Rural Health Transformation Program that was authorized by the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, Section 71401 of Public Law 119-21, shall designate a unique budget subprogram for all spending related to such program. The money in the subprogram shall be expended for purposes authorized by the federal law and no other purpose.</para><para>(2) Any application on behalf of the State of Nebraska for money from the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services for the Rural Health Transformation Program that was authorized by the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, Section 71401 of Public Law 119-21, shall be electronically submitted to the Clerk of the Legislature. Any utilization of money received pursuant to an application shall be limited to the uses approved in the application. The applicant shall post all awards, direct and indirect, and all grants on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(3) The department shall electronically submit a report detailing utilization of such money to the Clerk of the Legislature annually through December 31, 2032. The report shall include a list of all beneficiaries that includes direct awards, indirect awards passed through from the direct awards, and any outcomes and metrics collected.</para><para>(4) No applicant on behalf of the State of Nebraska that receives money from the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services for the Rural Health Transformation Program that was authorized by the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, Section 71401 of Public Law 119-21, shall use the funds to supplant state rural health spending.</para><para>(5) Any potential awardee that applies to receive money through the subprogram shall receive approval for a sustainability plan prior to the distribution of any money.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1072, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>April 8, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>