<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id35" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="81-3133"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3133</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Division of Children and Family Services; reports; strategic plan; key goals; benchmarks; progress reports.</catchline><para>(1)(a) On or before July 30, 2012, the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department of Health and Human Services shall report in writing its expenditures between January 1, 2012, and June 30, 2012, and the outcomes relating to such expenditures to the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature. Such report shall identify any changes or movement of funds in excess of two hundred fifty thousand dollars relating to child welfare between subprograms within Budget Program 347 and Budget Program 354.</para><para>(b) Beginning with the third calendar quarter of 2012, the division shall report electronically its expenditures for each quarter and the outcomes relating to such expenditures within thirty days after the end of the quarter to the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature. Such report shall identify any changes or movement of funds in excess of two hundred fifty thousand dollars relating to child welfare between subprograms within Budget Program 347 and Budget Program 354.</para><para>(2)(a) For the biennium ending June 30, 2015, the biennium ending June 30, 2017, and the biennium ending June 30, 2019, the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department of Health and Human Services shall, as part of the appropriations request process pursuant to section 81-132, include a strategic plan that identifies the main purpose or purposes of each program, verifiable and auditable key goals that the division believes are fair measures of its progress in meeting each program's main purpose or purposes, and benchmarks for improving performance on the key goals for the state as a whole and for each Department of Health and Human Services service area designated pursuant to section 81-3116. The division shall also report whether the benchmarks are being met and, if not, the expected timeframes for meeting them. Such key goals and benchmarks shall be developed by the Division of Children and Family Services with the assistance of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services pursuant to subdivision (2) of section 81-1113.</para><para>(b) Not later than September 15, 2013, not later than September 15, 2015, and not later than September 15, 2017, the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department of Health and Human Services shall report electronically to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature on the progress towards the key goals identified pursuant to this subsection that occurred in the previous twelve months. The division shall annually appear at a joint hearing of the two legislative committees and present the report.</para><para>(3) On or before December 1, 2016, and each year thereafter, the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department of Health and Human Services shall report electronically to the Governor and the Legislature the number of families in all transitional child care assistance programs and the number of families no longer eligible for all transitional child care assistance programs due to failure to meet income guidelines.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB949, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB269, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB81, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>