
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id847">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id849" statutenumber="81-3524"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id851">81-3524</statuteno><catchline id="id852">Geologists
Regulation Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The
Geologists Regulation Fund is created. The secretary of the board shall receive
and account for all money derived from the operation of the Geologists Regulation
Act. The board shall remit the money to the State Treasurer for credit to
the Geologists Regulation Fund, which shall be continued from year to year
and shall be drawn against only as provided for in this section and, when
reappropriated for the succeeding biennium, shall not revert to the General
Fund. All expenses certified by the board as properly and necessarily incurred
in the discharge of duties, including compensation and administrative staff,
and any expense incident to the administration of the act relating to other
states, shall be paid out of the fund. Warrants for the payment of expenses
shall be issued by the Director of Administrative Services and paid by the
State Treasurer upon presentation of vouchers regularly drawn by the chairperson
and secretary of the board and approved by the board. At no time shall the
total amount of warrants exceed the total amount of the fees collected under
the act and to the credit of the fund. Transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any
money in the Geologists Regulation Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 87.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>