<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id607"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-3140"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3140</statuteno><catchline>Deposits to Health Care Homes for the Medically Underserved Fund; distribution; use.</catchline><para>(1) Twenty-five percent of the federal medicaid fraud settlement funds accruing to Nebraska annually shall be deposited in the Health Care Homes for the Medically Underserved Fund for distribution to federally qualified health centers in Nebraska. Such funds shall be distributed proportionately based on the unduplicated number of patients served in the previous year by such federally qualified health centers as reported through the uniform data system of the Health Resources and Services Administration of the United States Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(2) Funds distributed pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall be used for the following purposes:</para><para>(a) Hiring, training, certifying, and maintaining staff dedicated to patient-centered chronic disease management, including, but not limited to, case managers, health educators, social workers, outreach and enrollment workers, and community health workers;</para><para>(b) Providing services, including, but not limited to, interpreter services, transportation services, and social work assistance;</para><para>(c) Capital improvements, including, but not limited to, facility expansion, leasing additional space, and furnishing, equipment, or redesign of facilities to support patient-centered care;</para><para>(d) Medication management, including, but not limited to, clinical pharmacy services, pharmacists, clinical pharmacists, technology for monitoring and real-time notification, and care managers;</para><para>(e) Information technology, including, but not limited to, telehealth services, analytics tools, patient registries, and updates to electronic health records systems; and</para><para>(f) Reimbursement to health care providers, including, but not limited to, physicians, nurse practitioners, dieticians, diabetic educators, behavioral health providers, and oral health providers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB661, &#167; 19. </para><effectivedate>May 21, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>