<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3527"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3527</statuteno><catchline>Licensure; enrollment; application;
fees.</catchline><para>(1) Application for licensure as a geologist or enrollment
as a geologist-intern shall be made on a form prescribed and furnished by
the board. If required pursuant to section 81-3539,
the application shall contain statements made under oath showing
the applicant's education and a detailed summary of technical experience and
shall include the names and complete mailing addresses of the references,
none of whom shall be members of the board. The board may accept the verified
information contained in the National Association of State Boards of Geology
for applicants in lieu of the same information that is required on the form
prescribed and furnished by the board.</para>
<para>(2) Application, licensure, and enrollment fees shall be established
by the board and shall accompany the application. Original and reciprocal
fees shall not exceed three hundred dollars for licensure as a geologist and
one hundred dollars for enrollment as a geologist-intern and shall be in addition
to the examination fee which shall be set to recover the costs of the examination
and its administration.</para>
<para>(3) The certificate of authorization fee for organizations shall be
established by the board and shall accompany the application. The fee shall
not exceed three hundred dollars per year.</para>
<para>(4) The fee for emeritus status shall be established by the board and
shall accompany the application. The fee shall not exceed one hundred dollars
per year.</para>
<para>(5) If the board denies the issuance of a certificate to any applicant,
including the application of an organization for a certificate of authorization,
the board shall retain the fee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 890, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>