<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3451"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3451</statuteno><catchline>Professional engineer or engineer-intern;
license; application; examination; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) To be
eligible for admission to examination to be a professional engineer or engineer-intern,
an applicant must be of good moral character and reputation and shall submit
five references with his or her application for licensure as a professional
engineer or enrollment as an engineer-intern. Three of the references shall
be professional engineers having personal knowledge of the applicant's engineering
experience or, in the case of an application for enrollment as an engineer-intern,
character references.</para>
<para>(2)(a) A person holding a certificate of licensure to engage in the
practice of engineering, issued by the proper authority of a state, territory, or possession
of the United States, the District of Columbia, or any foreign country, based
on requirements that do not conflict with the Engineers and Architects Regulation
Act and were of a standard not lower than that specified in the applicable
licensure law in effect in this state at the time such certificate was issued
may, upon application, be licensed as a professional engineer without further
examination.</para>
<para>(b) A person holding an active Council Record with the National Council
of Examiners for Engineering and Surveying whose qualifications as evidenced
by the Council Record meet the requirements of the act may, upon application,
be licensed as a professional engineer after
passing an examination testing the applicant's knowledge of the applicable
statutes and rules and regulations unique to the State of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(c) A graduate of an ABET-accredited engineering curriculum, enrolled
as an engineer-intern, and having a specific record of an additional four
years or more of progressive post-accredited-degree experience
on engineering projects of a grade and a character which indicates to the
Board of Engineers and Architects that the applicant may be competent to practice
engineering shall be admitted to an examination of at least eight hours in length,
administered by the board, on the principles and practice of engineering.
Upon passing the examination, the applicant shall be granted a certificate
of licensure to practice engineering in this state if the applicant is otherwise
qualified. Engineering teaching of advanced subjects and the design of engineering
research and projects in a college or university offering an ABET-accredited engineering
curriculum of four years or more may be considered as engineering experience.
An applicant who does not hold an ABET-accredited engineering degree but who is
enrolled as an engineer-intern in this state and has a specific record of
an additional six years or more of progressive experience on engineering projects
of a grade and a character which indicates to the Board of Engineers and Architects
that the applicant may be competent to practice engineering shall be admitted
to an examination of at least eight hours in length,
administered by the board, in the principles and practice of engineering.
Upon passing the examination, the applicant shall be granted a certificate
of licensure to practice engineering in this state if otherwise qualified.</para>
<para>(3)(a) A graduate of or senior in an ABET-accredited engineering curriculum, or the
substantial equivalent as determined by the board, shall be admitted to an
eight-hour examination on the fundamentals of engineering. Upon passing the
examination and verification of graduation, the applicant shall be enrolled
as an engineer-intern.</para>
<para>(b) A person enrolled
as an engineer-intern in a state, territory, or possession of the United States,
the District of Columbia, or any foreign country, based on requirements that
do not conflict with the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act and were
of a standard not lower than that specified in the applicable law in effect
in this state at the time such person was enrolled and who is a resident of
this state may, upon application, be enrolled in this state as an engineer-intern.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source> <para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 51; </para> <para>Laws 2004, LB 599, &#167; 4; </para> <para>Laws 2004, LB 1069, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 15.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
