<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id378"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3545"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3545</statuteno><catchline>Professional geologist; licensure; application; eligibility, license issued outside of the state.</catchline><para>(1) An individual who holds a valid license issued outside of the State of Nebraska to engage in the practice of geology may apply to the board to be licensed as a professional geologist.</para><para>(2) The following are required for an applicant to be eligible for licensure by the board as a professional geologist under this section:</para><para>(a) The applicant has a documented record of four or more years of progressive experience in geologic work of a grade and character which indicates to the board that the applicant may be competent to practice geology. Such progressive experience shall have been completed after graduating from a geology or geologic specialty program with a minimum of thirty semester hours or forty-five quarter hours of course work in geology that includes course work in the content domains and hours as prescribed by the board;</para><para>(b) The applicant has passed the examination on the fundamentals of geology or a similar examination that is approved by the board;</para><para>(c) The applicant has passed the examination on the practice of geology or a similar examination that is approved by the board;</para><para>(d) The applicant has passed an examination on the statutes, rules, regulations, and other requirements unique to Nebraska;</para><para>(e) The applicant has submitted an application accompanied by the fee established by the board;</para><para>(f) The applicant has submitted one or more acceptable written references;</para><para>(g) The applicant has provided verification of licensure in good standing in another jurisdiction; and</para><para>(h) The jurisdiction where the applicant is licensed has laws that are consistent with the Geologists Regulation Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 35. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>