<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id194"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3141"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3141</statuteno><catchline>Limited Temporary Guardian Aid Program; covered county; state aid; legislative intent regarding appropriations.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Covered county means a county containing a city of the metropolitan class or a city of the primary class; and</para><para>(b) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(2) There is created a separate and distinct budgetary subprogram within the department to be known as the Limited Temporary Guardian Aid Program. Funds appropriated for the program shall be used to provide state aid to counties in the form of reimbursement to covered counties as provided in this section.</para><para>(3) A covered county that has paid expenses and fees for limited temporary guardians as provided in subdivision (k)(2) of section 30-2626 may apply to the department for reimbursement for such amounts and for reasonable administrative fees incurred by the county in paying such amounts and applying for reimbursement. The application shall be in a form and manner prescribed by the department and shall be submitted on a quarterly basis.</para><para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate the following amounts to the department to carry out the Limited Temporary Guardian Aid Program:</para><para>(a) For fiscal year 2024-25:</para><para>(i) One hundred sixty thousand dollars for state aid to covered counties containing a city of the metropolitan class; and</para><para>(ii) Ninety thousand dollars for state aid to covered counties containing a city of the primary class; and</para><para>(b) For fiscal year 2025-26:</para><para>(i) One hundred sixty thousand dollars for state aid to covered counties containing a city of the metropolitan class; and</para><para>(ii) Ninety thousand dollars for state aid to covered counties containing a city of the primary class.</para><para>(5) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as necessary to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB157, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Appointment of limited temporary guardian,</emphasis> see section 30-2626.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>