<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id220"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3143"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3143</statuteno><catchline>Department of Health and Human Services; Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program; funds; state plan amendment.</catchline><para>The Department of Health and Human Services shall submit a state plan amendment to the federal Administration for Children and Families, pursuant to section 404(a)(2) of the federal Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996, to allow the funds provided to the state for the Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program established in 42 U.S.C. 601 et seq., as such sections existed on January 1, 2023, to be used for the following purposes:</para><para>(1) Activities of child advocacy centers pursuant to sections 28-728 to 28-730;</para><para>(2) Coordination activities of the state chapter of child advocacy centers as defined in 34 U.S.C. 20302, as such section existed on January 1, 2023, including, but not limited to, development of a distribution formula for funding provided pursuant to subdivision (1) of this section, data collection and analysis required for reports to the federal Administration for Children and Families, accounting of the fund expenditures per state and federal requirements, and preparing the annual Temporary Assistance for Needy Families reports for funds appropriated pursuant to this subdivision and subdivision (1) of this section, which shall be filed with the Department of Health and Human Services on a date specified by the department;</para><para>(3) Domestic violence services; and</para><para>(4) Grants to nonprofit organizations holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code that distribute food in ten or more counties in Nebraska and qualify for the Emergency Food Assistance Program administered by the United States Department of Agriculture, which shall be applicable for FY2023-24 only.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 38. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>