<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" id="id13" statutenumber="81-3448"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3448</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Architect; license;
application; fee; requirements; examination; issuance.</catchline><para>(1)
A person applying to the Board of Engineers and Architects for initial licensure
as an architect shall submit an application accompanied by the fee established
by the board and satisfactory evidence that he or she holds a degree in architecture
accredited by the National Architectural Accrediting Board and that
he or she has completed practical training in architectural work as required
by the Board of Engineers and Architects. If an applicant is qualified, the
Board of Engineers and Architects shall, by means of a written or electronic
examination, examine the applicant on technical and professional subjects
as prescribed by the board. None of the examination materials shall be considered
public records. The board may exempt from the written examination an applicant
who holds a certification issued by the National Council of Architectural
Registration Boards. The Board of Engineers and Architects may adopt guidelines
published from time to time by the National Council of Architectural Registration
Boards. The Board of Engineers and Architects may also adopt the examinations
and grading procedures of the National Council of Architectural Registration
Boards and the accreditation decisions of the National Architectural Accrediting Board. The Board of Engineers and
Architects shall issue a certificate of licensure to each applicant who is
found to be of good moral character and who satisfies the requirements set
forth in this section. Licensure shall be effective upon issuance.</para>
<para>(2) A person applying for initial
licensure who does not hold a degree in
architecture accredited by the National Architectural Accrediting Board
shall submit an application accompanied by the fee established by the Board
of Engineers and Architects. The application shall demonstrate satisfactory
evidence of twelve years' combined architectural education and architectural
work experience, including the equivalent of the Intern Development Program
promulgated by the National Council of Architectural Registration Boards.
If an applicant is determined by the Board of Engineers and Architects to
meet this requirement, the board shall, by means of a written or electronic
examination, examine the applicant on technical and professional subjects
as prescribed by the board. Only an individual who has earned a bachelor
of science in architectural studies degree with an architecture emphasis prior
to December 31, 1999, may be considered under this
subsection.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
