<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>                 <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments"  statutenumber="81-3115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3115</statuteno><catchline>Division directors; appointment; chief medical officer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Governor shall appoint a director for each division created in section 81-3113 who shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor and shall report to the chief executive officer. Each division director shall be subject to confirmation by a majority of the members of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) If the Director of Public Health is licensed to practice medicine and surgery in the State of Nebraska, he or she shall also be the chief medical officer. If the Director of Public Health is not licensed to practice medicine and surgery in the State of Nebraska, the Governor shall appoint a chief medical officer in addition to the Director of Public Health. The chief medical officer shall be licensed to practice medicine and surgery in the State of Nebraska, shall serve at the pleasure of the Governor, and shall be subject to confirmation by a majority of the members of the Legislature.</para><para>(3) The chief medical officer shall perform duties under the Uniform Credentialing Act as provided in section 38-1,101, shall be the final decisionmaker in contested cases of health care facilities defined in the Health Care Facility Licensure Act arising under the act and sections 71-6042, 71-6732, and 81-604.03, and shall perform such other duties as provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1315.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>