<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id758"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Administrative Departments" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="81-3725"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3725</statuteno><catchline>Marketing assistance grants; applicant; duties; technical review committee; duties; final report.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall develop a program to provide marketing assistance grants to communities and organizations hosting national or international-caliber events held in Nebraska that have the potential to attract a significant percentage of out-of-state visitors and to generate favorable national or international press coverage for Nebraska.</para><para>(2) A community or organization applying for a grant shall provide a plan to the commission that includes: (a) Documentation that the event will attract out-of-state visitors; (b) details regarding the type of marketing that would be carried out with state funds; (c) methodologies used to track the impact of marketing efforts and the number of out-of-state visitors attending the event; and (d) details regarding the potential national or international press coverage that will be generated by the event.</para><para>(3) The executive director shall convene a technical review committee of no fewer than three individuals representing the public sector, the private sector, and citizens at large. The technical review committee and the executive director shall review and score applications and forward recommendations to the commission for approval by the commission or a subcommittee of the commission.</para><para>(4) Communities and organizations receiving grants authorized under this section shall provide a final report to the commission within ninety days after the completion date of the event that includes event attendance, the use of funds, and marketing impact information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB449, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>