<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id818"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3520"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3520</statuteno><catchline>Board of Geologists; created; members; qualifications; terms; emeritus members.</catchline><para>(1) The Board of Geologists is created to administer the Geologists Regulation Act. The board shall consist of the following seven members appointed by the Governor:</para><para>(a) Five professional geologists;</para><para>(b) One professional geologist who is also a faculty member of a geology or related geosciences department of a college or university located in Nebraska. Such member shall be recommended by the president of such college or university prior to appointment by the Governor in order to qualify as a board member under this subdivision (1)(b); and</para><para>(c) One individual who is not a professional geologist.</para><para>(2)(a) Each member shall serve for terms of five years terminating on the last day of February.</para><para>(b) Each member shall hold office after the expiration of such member's term until a successor is duly appointed and qualified.</para><para>(c) The Governor may remove any member of the board for misconduct, incompetency, or neglect of duty.</para><para>(d) Vacancies on the board, however created, shall be filled for the unexpired term by appointment by the Governor.</para><para>(3)(a) Each member of the board shall be a:</para><para>(i) Citizen of the United States; and</para><para>(ii) Resident of the State of Nebraska for at least one year immediately preceding the appointment of such member and continue such residency while serving as a member of the board.</para><para>(b) Each member of the board who is a professional geologist shall:</para><para>(i) Have actively practiced as a professional geologist for at least ten years prior to appointment to the board;</para><para>(ii) Have had responsible charge of, direct supervision of, or a combination of responsible charge and direct supervision of geologic work for at least five years prior to appointment to the board; and</para><para>(iii) Maintain status as a professional geologist licensed as a professional geologist in Nebraska during the member's time on the board.</para><para>(4)(a) The board may designate any number of former members of the board as emeritus members. Emeritus member status, when conferred, is valid for one year from the date of conferment and may be renewed by the board any number of times.</para><para>(b) An emeritus member is not counted for purposes of determining if a quorum is present under section 81-3523.</para><para>(c) An emeritus member shall not:</para><para>(i) Be an officer on the board;</para><para>(ii) Vote on board matters;</para><para>(iii) Receive compensation or reimbursement for expenses from the board; or</para><para>(iv) Receive compensation or reimbursement for expenses under sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 while tending to board matters.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB91, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB38, &#167; 17. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>