<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3443"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3443</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement procedures.</catchline><para>(1) A complaint against any person or organization involving any matter coming within the jurisdiction of the board shall be in writing and shall be filed with the board.</para><para>(2) A hearing on the complaint shall be held within a reasonable time in accordance with the rules and regulations and may be heard through the use of a hearing officer. The accused shall have the right to appear personally with or without counsel, to cross-examine adverse witnesses, and to produce evidence and witnesses in his, her, or its defense.</para><para>(3) The board shall set the time and place for the hearing and shall cause a copy of the complaint, together with a notice of the time and place fixed for the hearing, to be sent by registered mail to the accused, at his, her, or its last-known business or residence address known to the board, at least thirty days before the hearing.</para><para>(4) If after the hearing the board finds the accused has violated the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act or any rules or regulations, it may issue any order or take any action described in section 81-3444. If the order revokes, suspends, or cancels a license, the board shall notify, in writing, the Secretary of State. If the board finds no violation, it shall enter an order dismissing the complaint.</para><para>(5) The board may reissue a license that has been revoked. Application for the reissuance of a license shall be made in such a manner as the board directs and shall be accompanied by a fee established by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB45, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB23, &#167; 41. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>