<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3714"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3714</statuteno><catchline>State Visitors Promotion Cash Fund; created; uses; transfers; investment.</catchline><para>The State Visitors Promotion Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the commission. The fund shall consist of revenue deposited into the fund pursuant to section 81-3715 and money donated as gifts, bequests, or other contributions from public or private entities. Funds made available by any department or agency of the United States may also be credited to the fund if so directed by such department or agency. The commission shall use the proceeds of the fund to generally promote, encourage, and attract visitors to and within the State of Nebraska, to erect and replace highway tourism markers, to enhance the use of travel and tourism facilities within the state, to provide grants to communities and organizations, and to contract with the Department of Administrative Services to provide support services to the commission, including, but not limited to, accounting and personnel functions. The proceeds of the fund shall be in addition to funds appropriated to the commission from the General Fund. Transfers may be made from the State Visitors Promotion Cash Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer one million dollars from the State Visitors Promotion Cash Fund to the General Fund on or before June 30, 2019, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. Any money in the State Visitors Promotion Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 499, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 81-1252; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1053, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB449, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB222, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 26. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2018</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>