<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Administrative Departments" statutenumber="81-3602"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>81-3602</statuteno><catchline>Rural Development Commission; members;
terms; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Rural Development Commission
shall consist of members who represent a wide range of rural Nebraska interests.</para>
<para>(b) The Governor shall appoint five members to the commission.
The Governor shall appoint a representative of his or her office and the Director of Economic Development or his or her designee, the Director of Agriculture or his or her designee, the chief
executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee, and the Director
of the Nebraska State Historical Society or his or her designee.</para>
<para>(c) The Speaker of the Legislature shall appoint one member of the Legislature
to the commission. Such member
shall be a nonvoting member of the commission.</para>
<para>(d) Other members shall be appointed by the Governor to represent federal
agencies, local governments, tribal governments, nonprofit organizations,
regional economic development organizations, the private sector, postsecondary
education, and youth.</para>
<para>(e) The chairperson and vice-chairperson of the commission shall be
elected by a majority of the members of the commission at the first commission
meeting in odd-numbered years and shall each serve a two-year term as chairperson
and vice-chairperson, respectively.</para>
<para>(2) The commission shall meet at the call of the chairperson or a majority
of the members. The chairperson shall call such meetings as he or she determines
necessary to fulfill the duties of the commission. A quorum shall be one-half
of the members.</para>
<para>(3) The members of the commission shall be reimbursed for their actual
and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 and pursuant
to policies of the commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 190, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 81-1283; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1053, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 48, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 48, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 777; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB231, &#167;  1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>