<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Restraint of Trade" statutenumber="59-828"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-828</statuteno><catchline>Violations; prosecutions; duty of Attorney General and county attorney; evidence; discovery; immunity; scope and operation; proceeding by individual; costs.</catchline><para>(1) It is hereby made the duty of the Attorney General and the county attorney of each county under the direction of the Attorney General to institute and prosecute such proceedings as may be necessary to carry into effect sections 59-801 to 59-831. No person shall be prosecuted or be subjected to any penalty or forfeiture for or on account of any transaction, matter, or thing concerning which he or she may testify or produce evidence, documentary or otherwise, in any proceeding, suit, or prosecution under such sections. No person testifying shall be exempt from prosecution or punishment for perjury committed in so testifying.</para><para>(2) It shall be lawful for any person to institute proceedings pursuant to sections 59-801 to 59-831, at his or her own expense and by his or her own attorney, but in the action so brought by such person no recovery for costs and disbursements shall be had against the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1905, c. 162, &#167; 22, p. 645; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4066; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3469; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 59-822; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 59-828; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 1028, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1278, &#167; 17. </para></source><annotation><para>Attorney General is not authorized to bring action in name of state in ordinary labor disputes, but may do so to restrain willful and illegal acts affecting public generally. State v. Employers of Labor, 102 Neb. 768, 169 N.W. 717 (1918).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 