<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id401"><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Restraint of Trade" statutenumber="59-1403.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1403.03</statuteno><catchline>Music licensing agency; disclosures; representative or agent; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2019, before seeking payment or a contract for payment of royalties for the use of copyrighted works by that proprietor, a representative or agent for a music licensing agency shall identify himself or herself to the proprietor or the proprietor's employees, disclose that he or she is acting on behalf of a music licensing agency, and disclose the purpose for being on the premises.</para><para>(2) A representative or agent of a music licensing agency shall not:</para><para>(a) Use obscene, abusive, or profane language when communicating with a proprietor or his or her employees;</para><para>(b) Communicate by telephone or in person with a proprietor other than at the proprietor's place of business during the hours when the proprietor's business is open to the public unless otherwise authorized by the proprietor or the proprietor's agents, employees, or representatives;</para><para>(c) Engage in any coercive conduct, act, or practice that is substantially disruptive to a proprietor's business;</para><para>(d) Use or attempt to use any unfair or deceptive act or practice in negotiating with a proprietor; or</para><para>(e) Communicate with an unlicensed proprietor about licensing performances of musical works at the proprietor's establishment after receiving notification in writing from an attorney representing the proprietor that all further communications related to the licensing of the proprietor's establishment by the music licensing agency should be addressed to the attorney. However, the music licensing agency may resume communicating directly with the proprietor if the attorney fails to respond to communications from the music licensing agency within sixty days or the attorney becomes nonresponsive for a period of sixty days or more.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 35. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>