<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies And Unlawful Combinations" statutenumber="59-1751"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1751</statuteno><catchline>Seller; surety bond or trust account; establish; procedures.</catchline><para>If, pursuant to section 59-1728, a seller must obtain a surety bond or establish a trust account, the following procedures shall apply:</para><para>(1) If a bond is obtained, a copy of it shall be filed with the Department of Banking and Finance, and if a trust account is established, notification of the depository, the trustee, and the account number shall be filed with the Department of Banking and Finance;</para><para>(2) The bond or trust account required shall run in favor of the State of Nebraska for the benefit of any person who is damaged by any violation of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act or by the seller's breach of a contract subject to the act or of any obligation arising therefrom. The bond or trust account shall also run in favor of any person damaged by such practices;</para><para>(3) Any person claiming against the bond or trust account for a violation of the act may maintain an action at law against the seller and the surety or trustee. The aggregate liability of the surety or trustee to all persons damaged by a seller's violation of the act shall in no event exceed the amount of the bond or trust account; and</para><para>(4) The bond or the trust account shall be in an amount equal to the total amount of the initial payment of all seller-assisted marketing plan contracts which the seller has entered into during the previous year or three hundred thousand dollars, whichever is less, but in no case shall the amount be less than fifty thousand dollars. The amount required shall be adjusted twice a year. Such adjustment shall occur no later than the tenth day of the first month of the seller's fiscal year and no later than the tenth day of the seventh month of the seller's fiscal year. A seller need only establish a bond or trust account in the amount of fifty thousand dollars at the commencement of business and during the first six months the seller is in business. By the tenth day of the seller's seventh month in business, the amount of the bond shall be established as provided for in this section as if the seller had been in business for a year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 180, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 