<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Restraint of Trade" statutenumber="59-1725.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1725.01</statuteno><catchline>Seller-assisted marketing plan; cease and desist order; fine; injunction; procedures; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) The Director of Banking and Finance may summarily order a seller or any officer, director, employee, or agent of such seller to cease and desist from the further offer or sale of any seller-assisted marketing plan by the seller if the director finds:</para><para>(a) There has been a substantial failure to comply with any of the provisions of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act;</para><para>(b) The offer or sale of the plan would constitute misrepresentation to or deceit or fraud upon the purchasers; or</para><para>(c) Any person identified in the required disclosure document has been convicted of an offense described in subdivision (2)(a) of section 59-1735 or is subject to an order or has had a civil judgment entered against him or her as described in subdivision (2)(b) or (c) of section 59-1735, and the involvement of such person in the sale or management of the seller-assisted marketing plan creates an unreasonable risk to prospective purchasers.</para><para>(2) If the director believes, whether or not based upon an investigation conducted under section 59-1725, that any person has engaged in or is about to engage in any act or practice constituting a violation of any provision of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act or any rule, regulation, or order of the director, the director may:</para><para>(a) Issue a cease and desist order;</para><para>(b) Impose a fine not to exceed five thousand dollars per violation, in addition to costs of the investigation; or</para><para>(c) Initiate an action in any court of competent jurisdiction to enjoin such acts or practices and to enforce compliance with the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act or any order under the act.</para><para>(3) Upon a proper showing, a permanent or temporary injunction, restraining order, or writ of mandamus shall be granted. The director shall not be required to post a bond.</para><para>(4)(a) Any fines and costs imposed under this section shall be in addition to all other penalties imposed by the laws of this state. The Department of Banking and Finance shall collect the fines and costs and remit them to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit the costs to the Securities Act Cash Fund and distribute the fines in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(b) If a person fails to pay the administrative fine or investigation costs referred to in this section, a lien in the amount of such fine and costs may be imposed upon all assets and property of such person in this state and may be recovered by suit by the director. Failure of the person to pay such fine and costs shall constitute a separate violation of the act.</para><para>(5) Upon entry of an order pursuant to this section, the director shall, in writing, promptly notify all persons to whom such order is directed that it has been entered and of the reasons for such order and that any person to whom the order is directed may request a hearing in writing within fifteen business days after the issuance of the order. Upon receipt of such written request, the matter shall be set down for hearing to commence within thirty business days after the receipt unless the parties consent to a later date or the hearing officer sets a later date for good cause. If a hearing is not requested within fifteen business days and none is ordered by the director, the order shall automatically become final and shall remain in effect until it is modified or vacated by the director. If a hearing is requested or ordered, the director, after notice and hearing, shall enter his or her written findings of fact and conclusions of law and may affirm, modify, or vacate the order.</para><para>(6) The director may vacate or modify a cease and desist order if he or she finds that the conditions which caused its entry have changed or that it is otherwise in the public interest to do so.</para><para>(7) Any person aggrieved by a final order of the director may appeal the order. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 48. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>