<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id45">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Combinations" id="id47" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="59-1608.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1608.04</statuteno><catchline id="id50">State Settlement
Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The State
Settlement Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be maintained by the Department
of Justice and administered by the Attorney General. Except as otherwise provided
by law, the fund shall consist of all recoveries received pursuant to the
Consumer Protection Act, including any money, funds, securities, or other
things of value in the nature of civil damages or other payment, except criminal
penalties, whether such recovery is by way of verdict, judgment, compromise,
or settlement in or out of court, or other final disposition of any case or
controversy, or any other payments received on behalf of the state by the
Department of Justice and administered by the Attorney General for the benefit
of the state or the general welfare of its citizens, but excluding all funds
held in a trust capacity where specific benefits accrue to specific individuals,
organizations, or governments. The fund may be expended for any allowable
legal purposes as determined by the Attorney General. To provide
necessary financial accountability and management oversight, revenue from
individual settlement agreements or other separate sources credited to the
State Settlement Cash Fund may be tracked and accounted for within the state
accounting system through the use of separate and distinct funds, subfunds,
or any other available accounting mechanism specifically approved by the Accounting
Administrator for use by the Department of Justice. Any money in the fund
available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB190, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB549, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>