<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection statutenumber="59-1402" chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Combinations" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1402</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Music Licensing Agency Act:</para><para>(1) Copyright owner means the owner of a copyright of a nondramatic musical work recognized and enforceable under the copyright laws of the United States pursuant to 17 U.S.C. 101 et seq., as such sections existed on January 1, 2018, and does not include the owner of a copyright in a motion picture or audiovisual work or in part of a motion picture or audiovisual work;</para><para>(2) Music licensing agency means an association or corporation that licenses the public performance of nondramatic musical works on behalf of copyright owners;</para><para>(3) Performing right means the right to perform a copyrighted nondramatic musical work publicly for profit;</para><para>(4) Person means any individual, resident or nonresident of this state, and every domestic, foreign, or alien partnership, limited liability company, society, association, corporation, or music licensing agency;</para><para>(5) Proprietor means the owner of a retail establishment, restaurant, inn, bar, tavern, sports or entertainment facility, multi-family residential dwelling, or other similar place of business or professional office located in this state in which the public may assemble and in which nondramatic musical works or similar copyrighted works may be performed, broadcast, or otherwise transmitted for the enjoyment of members of the public there assembled; and</para><para>(6) Royalty means the fees payable to a copyright owner for a performing right.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1120, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB203, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>