<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies And Unlawful Combinations" statutenumber="59-1735"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1735</statuteno><catchline>Disclosure document; contents; requirements.</catchline><para>The disclosure document required by section 59-1732 shall contain the following:</para><para>(1) The name of and the office held by the seller's officers, directors, trustees, general or limited partners, and limited liability company members, as the case may be, and the names of those individuals who have management responsibilities in connection with the seller's business activities;</para><para>(2) A statement whether the seller or any person identified in subdivision (1) of this section:</para><para>(a) Has been convicted of a felony or misdemeanor or pleaded nolo contendere to a felony or misdemeanor charge if such felony or misdemeanor involved fraud, embezzlement, fraudulent conversion, or misappropriation of property;</para><para>(b) Has been held liable in a civil action by final judgment or consented to the entry of a stipulated judgment if the civil action alleged fraud, embezzlement, fraudulent conversion, misappropriation of property, the use of untrue or misleading representations in an attempt to sell or dispose of real or personal property, or the use of unfair, unlawful, or deceptive business practices; or</para><para>(c) Is subject to any currently effective injunction or restrictive order relating to business activity as the result of an action brought by a public agency or department, including, but not limited to, action affecting any vocational license; and</para><para>(3) With respect to persons identified in subdivision (1) of this section:</para><para>(a) A description of their work experience for the past five years, including a list of principal occupations and employers during such time. Such five-year period shall run from the date of the disclosure filed with the Department of Banking and Finance; and</para><para>(b) A listing of each such person's educational background, including the names and addresses of schools attended, dates of attendance, and degrees received.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 180, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 461, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 380; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 599, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 