<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies And Unlawful Combinations" statutenumber="59-1609"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1609</statuteno><catchline>Civil action for damages.</catchline><para>Any person who is injured in his or her business or property by a violation of sections 59-1602 to 59-1606, whether such injured person dealt directly or indirectly with the defendant, or any person so injured because he or she refuses to accede to a proposal for an arrangement which, if consummated, would be in violation of sections 59-1603 to 59-1606, may bring a civil action in the district court to enjoin further violations, to recover the actual damages sustained by him or her, or both, together with the costs of the suit, including a reasonable attorney's fee, and the court may in its discretion, increase the award of damages to an amount which bears a reasonable relation to the actual damages which have been sustained and which damages are not susceptible of measurement by ordinary pecuniary standards; except that such increased award for violation of section 59-1602 shall not exceed one thousand dollars. For the purpose of this section, person shall include the counties, the municipalities, and all political subdivisions of this state.</para><para>Whenever the State of Nebraska is injured by reason of a violation of sections 59-1603 to 59-1606, it may sue therefor in the district court to recover the actual damages sustained by it and to recover the costs of the suit including a reasonable attorney's fee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 1028, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1278, &#167; 26. </para></source><annotation><para>As related to a cause of action for any person injured in violation of section 59-1604, this section contemplates an action by indirect purchasers. Arthur v. Microsoft Corp., 267 Neb. 586, 676 N.W.2d 29 (2004).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 