<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Monopolies And Unlawful Combinations" statutenumber="59-1722"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1722</statuteno><catchline>Transaction; seller complied with
Federal Trade Commission trade regulation rule; exempt; exception; conditions;
fee.</catchline><para>(1) Any transaction in which the seller has complied
with the Federal Trade Commission trade regulation rule titled Disclosure
Requirements and Prohibitions Concerning Franchising, 16 C.F.R. 436,
shall be exempt from the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act, except that such
transactions shall be subject to subdivision (1)(d) of section 59-1757, those
provisions regulating or prescribing the use of the phrase buy-back or secured
investment or similar phrases as set forth in sections 59-1726 to 59-1728
and 59-1751, and all sections which provide for their enforcement. The exemption
shall only apply if:</para>
<para>(a) The seller uses a disclosure document prepared in accordance with
either the Federal Trade Commission trade regulation rule titled Disclosure
Requirements and Prohibitions Concerning Franchising, 16 C.F.R. 436,
or the then current guidelines for the preparation of the Uniform Franchise
Offering Circular adopted by the North American Securities Administrators Association;</para>
<para>(b) Before placing any advertisement in a Nebraska-based publication,
offering for sale to any prospective purchaser in Nebraska, or making any
representations in connection with such offer or sale to any prospective purchaser
in Nebraska, the seller files a notice with the Department of Banking and
Finance which contains (i) the name, address, and telephone number of the
seller and the name under which the seller intends to do business and (ii)
a brief description of the plan offered by the seller; and</para>
<para>(c) The seller pays a filing fee of one hundred dollars.</para>
<para>(2) The department may request a copy of the disclosure document upon
receipt of a written complaint or inquiry regarding the seller or upon a reasonable
belief that a violation of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act has occurred
or may occur. The seller shall provide such copy within ten business days
of receipt of the request.</para>
<para>(3) All funds collected by the department under this section shall be
remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Securities Act Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(4) The Director of Banking and Finance may by order deny or revoke
an exemption specified in this section with respect to a particular offering
of one or more business opportunities if the director finds that such an order
is in the public interest or is necessary for the protection of purchasers.
An order shall not be entered without appropriate prior notice to all interested
parties, an opportunity for hearing, and written findings of fact and conclusions
of law. If the public interest or the protection of purchasers so requires,
the director may by order summarily deny or revoke an exemption specified
in this section pending final determination of any proceedings under this
section. An order under this section shall not operate retroactively.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 180, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB214, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>