<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies And Unlawful Combinations" statutenumber="59-1757"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1757</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited acts; violation; penalty; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall, in connection with the offer, purchase, lease, or sale of any seller-assisted marketing plan:</para><para>(a) Use the trademark, service mark, trade name, logotype, or advertising or other commercial symbol of any business which does not either control the ownership interest in the seller or accept responsibility for all representations made by the seller in regard to the business opportunity unless it is clear from the circumstances that the owner of the commercial symbol has knowledge of and consents to such use and is not involved in the sale of the business opportunity;</para><para>(b) Make any claim or representation in advertising or promotional material or in any oral sales presentation, solicitation, or discussion between the seller and a prospective purchaser which is inconsistent with the information required to be disclosed by the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act;</para><para>(c) Make or cause to be made any representation to any prospective purchaser that the Department of Banking and Finance has found any document filed under the act to be true, complete, and not misleading or has passed in any way upon the merits of or recommended or given approval to any seller-assisted marketing plan; or</para><para>(d) Directly or indirectly (i) employ any device, scheme, or artifice to defraud, (ii) make any untrue statement of a material fact or omit to state a material fact, or (iii) engage in any act, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit upon any person.</para><para>(2) Any person, including, but not limited to, the seller, a salesperson, agent, or representative of the seller, or an independent contractor who attempts to sell or lease or sells or leases a seller-assisted marketing plan, who willfully violates any provision of the act or any order issued pursuant to section 59-1725.01 in connection with the offer, purchase, lease, or sale of any seller-assisted marketing plan shall be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para><para>(3) The Director of Banking and Finance may refer such evidence as is available concerning violations of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act or any order of the director to the Attorney General or county attorney who may, with or without reference from the director, initiate criminal proceedings pursuant to the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 180, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 24. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 