<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Restraint of Trade" statutenumber="59-1701"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1701</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent and findings; seller-assisted marketing plans.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds and declares that the widespread sale of seller-assisted marketing plans, often connected with the sale of vending machines, vending racks, or work-at-home paraphernalia, has created numerous problems in Nebraska for purchasers which are inimical to good business practice. Often purchasers of seller-assisted marketing plans are individuals inexperienced in business matters who use their life savings to purchase the seller-assisted marketing plan in the hope that they will earn enough money in addition to retirement income or salary to become or remain self-sufficient. Many purchasers are the elderly who are seeking a way to supplement their fixed incomes. The initial payment is usually in the form of a purchase of overpriced equipment or products. Nebraska purchasers have suffered substantial losses when they have failed to receive full and complete information regarding the seller-assisted marketing plan, the amount of money they can reasonably expect to earn, and the previous experience of the seller-assisted marketing plan seller. Seller-assisted marketing plan sellers have a significant impact upon the economy and well-being of this state and its local communities. The provisions of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act relating to seller-assisted marketing plans are necessary for the public welfare.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the act to provide each prospective seller-assisted marketing plan purchaser with the information necessary to make an intelligent decision regarding seller-assisted marketing plans being offered, to safeguard the public against deceit and financial hardship, to insure, foster, and encourage competition and fair dealing in the sale of seller-assisted marketing plans by requiring adequate disclosure, to prohibit representations that tend to mislead, and to prohibit or restrict unfair contract terms. The act shall be construed liberally in order to achieve such purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 180, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 