<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Monopolies and Unlawful Restraint of Trade" statutenumber="59-1722"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>59-1722</statuteno><catchline>Transaction involving the sale of a franchise; exempt; exception; conditions; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Any transaction involving the sale of a franchise as defined in 16 C.F.R. 436.1(h), as such regulation existed on January 1, 2024, shall be exempt from the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act, except that such transactions shall be subject to subdivision (1)(d) of section 59-1757, those provisions regulating or prescribing the use of the phrase buy-back or secured investment or similar phrases as set forth in sections 59-1726 to 59-1728 and 59-1751, and all sections which provide for their enforcement. The exemption shall only apply if:</para><para>(a) The franchise is offered and sold in compliance with the requirements of 16 C.F.R. part 436, Disclosure Requirements and Prohibitions Concerning Franchising, as such part existed on January 1, 2024;</para><para>(b) Before placing any advertisement in a Nebraska-based publication, offering for sale to any prospective purchaser in Nebraska, or making any representations in connection with such offer or sale to any prospective purchaser in Nebraska, the seller files a notice with the Department of Banking and Finance which contains (i) the name, address, and telephone number of the seller and the name under which the seller intends to do business and (ii) a brief description of the plan offered by the seller; and</para><para>(c) The seller pays a filing fee of one hundred dollars.</para><para>(2) The department may request a copy of the disclosure document upon receipt of a written complaint or inquiry regarding the seller or upon a reasonable belief that a violation of the Seller-Assisted Marketing Plan Act has occurred or may occur. The seller shall provide such copy within ten business days of receipt of the request.</para><para>(3) All funds collected by the department under this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Securities Act Cash Fund.</para><para>(4) The Director of Banking and Finance may by order deny or revoke an exemption specified in this section with respect to a particular offering of one or more business opportunities if the director finds that such an order is in the public interest or is necessary for the protection of purchasers. An order shall not be entered without appropriate prior notice to all interested parties, an opportunity for hearing, and written findings of fact and conclusions of law. If the public interest or the protection of purchasers so requires, the director may by order summarily deny or revoke an exemption specified in this section pending final determination of any proceedings under this section. An order under this section shall not operate retroactively.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 180, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 218, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 53, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB214, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB363, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB707, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB92, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 89. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>