<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id63"><amendatorysection chaptername="Natural Resources" statutenumber="61-520"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>61-520</statuteno><catchline>Public-private partnership delivery method; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) A public-private partnership delivery method may be used for projects under the Public Water and Natural Resources Project Contracting Act as provided in this section and rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section only to the extent allowed under the Constitution of Nebraska. State contracts using this method shall be awarded by competitive negotiation.</para><para>(2) The department utilizing a public-private partnership shall continue to be responsible for oversight of any function that is delegated to or otherwise performed by a private partner.</para><para>(3) On or before July 1, 2024, the Director of Natural Resources shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations setting forth criteria to be used in determining when a public-private partnership is to be used for a particular project. The rules and regulations shall reflect the intent of the Legislature to promote and encourage the use of public-private partnerships in the State of Nebraska. The Director of Natural Resources shall consult with design-builders, progressive design-builders, construction managers, other contractors and design professionals, including engineers and architects, and other appropriate professionals during the development of the rules and regulations.</para><para>(4) A request for proposals for a project utilizing a public-private partnership shall include at a minimum:</para><para>(a) The parameters of the proposed public-private partnership agreement;</para><para>(b) The duties and responsibilities to be performed by the private partner or private partners;</para><para>(c) The methods of oversight to be employed by the department;</para><para>(d) The duties and responsibilities that are to be performed by the department and any other parties to the contract;</para><para>(e) The evaluation factors and the relative weight of each factor to be used in the scoring of awards;</para><para>(f) Plans for financing and operating the project and the revenue, service payments, bond financings, and appropriations of public funds needed for the qualifying project;</para><para>(g) Comprehensive documentation of the experience, capabilities, capitalization and financial condition, and other relevant qualifications of the private entity submitting the proposal;</para><para>(h) The ability of a private partner or private partners to quickly respond to the needs presented in the request for proposals and the importance of economic development opportunities represented by the project. In evaluating proposals, preference shall be given to a plan that includes the involvement of small businesses as subcontractors, to the extent that small businesses can provide services in a competitive manner, unless any preference interferes with the qualification for federal or other funds; and</para><para>(i) Other information required by the department to evaluate the proposals submitted and the overall proposed public-private partnership.</para><para>(5) A private entity desiring to be a private partner shall demonstrate to the satisfaction of the department that it is capable of performing any duty, responsibility, or function it may be authorized or directed to perform as a term or condition of the public-private partnership agreement.</para><para>(6) A request for proposals may be canceled, or all proposals may be rejected, if it is determined in writing that such action is taken in the best interest of the State of Nebraska and approved by the purchasing officer.</para><para>(7) Upon execution of a public-private partnership agreement, the department shall ensure that the contract clearly identifies that a public-private partnership is being utilized.</para><para>(8) The department shall:</para><para>(a) Adhere to the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under this section when utilizing a public-private partnership for financing capital projects; and</para><para>(b) Electronically report annually to the Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature regarding private-public partnerships which have been considered or are approved pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB565, &#167; 20. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>