<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Natural Resources" statutenumber="61-201"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>61-201</statuteno><catchline>Chief Water Officer of the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment; qualifications; Division of Water; duties; Chief Water Officer; appointment; duties; oath.</catchline><para>The Chief Water Officer of the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment shall be qualified by training and business experience to manage and supervise the Division of Water of the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment. The Division of Water of the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment shall assist the Chief Water Officer in carrying out the Chief Water Officer's duties. The Chief Water Officer shall (1) be a professional engineer as provided in the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act or a professional geologist as provided in the Geologists Regulation Act and (2) have had at least five years' experience in a position of responsibility in irrigation work. The Chief Water Officer shall be appointed by the Governor, subject to confirmation by the Legislature. The Chief Water Officer shall report directly to the Director of Water, Energy, and Environment. The Chief Water Officer shall, before assuming the duties of the office, take and subscribe an oath, such as is required by state officers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 365, &#167; 19, p. 1241; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 219, &#167; 2, p. 767; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 386, &#167; 1, p. 1355; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 75; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1998), &#167; 46-701; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 327. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Engineers and Architects Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-3401.</para><para><emphasis>Geologists Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-3501.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>