<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Natural Resources" id="id6" statutenumber="61-218"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>61-218</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Water Resources
Cash Fund; created; use; investment; eligibility for funding; annual report;
contents; Nebraska Environmental
Trust Fund; grant application; use of funds; legislative intent; department;
establish subaccount.</catchline><para>(1) The Water
Resources Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Department
of Natural Resources. Any
money in the fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
<para>(2) The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund such money
as is (a) transferred to the fund by the Legislature, (b) paid to the state
as fees, deposits, payments, and repayments relating to the fund, both principal
and interest, (c) donated as gifts, bequests, or other contributions to such
fund from public or private entities, (d)
made available by any department or agency of the United States if so directed
by such department or agency,
and (e) allocated pursuant to section 81-15,175.</para>
<para>(3) The fund shall be expended by the department (a) to aid
management actions taken to reduce consumptive uses of water or to
enhance streamflows or ground water recharge in river basins, subbasins, or
reaches which are deemed by the department overappropriated pursuant to section
46-713 or fully appropriated pursuant to section 46-714 or are bound by an
interstate compact or decree or a formal state contract or agreement, (b) for purposes of projects or proposals
described in the grant application as set forth in subdivision (2)(h) of section
81-15,175, and (c) to the extent funds are not expended pursuant to subdivisions (a) and (b) of
this subsection, the department may conduct a statewide assessment of short-term
and long-term water management activities and funding needs to meet statutory
requirements in sections 46-713 to 46-718 and 46-739 and any requirements
of an interstate compact or decree or formal state contract or agreement.
The fund shall not be used to pay for administrative expenses or any salaries
for the department or any political subdivision.</para>
<para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature that three million three hundred thousand dollars
be transferred each fiscal year from the General Fund to the Water Resources
Cash Fund for FY2011-12 through FY2018-19.</para>
<para>(5)(a) Expenditures from the Water Resources Cash Fund may
be made to natural resources districts eligible under subsection (3) of this
section for activities to either achieve a sustainable balance of consumptive
water uses or assure compliance with an interstate compact or decree or a
formal state contract or agreement and shall require a match of local funding
in an amount equal to or greater than forty percent of the total cost of carrying
out the eligible activity. The department shall, no later than August 1 of
each year, beginning in 2007, determine the amount of funding that will be
made available to natural resources districts from the Water Resources Cash
Fund and notify natural resources districts of this determination. The department
shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing application for
and use of the Water Resources Cash Fund by natural resources districts. Such
rules and regulations shall, at a minimum, include the following components:</para>
<para>(i) Require an explanation of how the planned activity will achieve a sustainable balance of consumptive
water uses or will assure compliance with an interstate compact
or decree or a formal state contract or agreement as required by section 46-715
and the controls, rules, and regulations designed to carry out the activity;
and</para>
<para>(ii) A schedule of implementation of the activity or its components, including the local match as set forth
in subdivision (5)(a) of this section.</para>
<para>(b) Any natural resources district that fails to implement
and enforce its controls, rules, and regulations as required by section 46-715
shall not be eligible for funding from the Water Resources Cash Fund until
it is determined by the department that compliance with the provisions required
by section 46-715 has been established.</para>
<para>(6) The Department of Natural Resources shall submit an annual
report to the Legislature no later than October 1 of each year, beginning
in the year 2007, that shall detail the use of the Water Resources Cash Fund
in the previous year. The report shall provide:</para>
<para>(a) Details regarding the use and cost of activities carried
out by the department; and</para>
<para>(b) Details regarding the use and cost of activities carried
out by each natural resources district that received funds from the Water
Resources Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(7)(a) Prior
to the application deadline for fiscal year 2011-12, the Department of Natural
Resources shall apply for a grant of nine million nine hundred thousand dollars
from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund, to be paid out in three annual
installments of three million three hundred thousand dollars. The purposes
listed in the grant application shall be consistent with the uses of the Water
Resources Cash Fund provided in this section and shall be used to aid management
actions taken to reduce consumptive uses of water, to enhance streamflows,
to recharge ground water, or to support wildlife habitat in any river basin
determined to be fully appropriated pursuant to section 46-714 or designated
as overappropriated pursuant to section 46-713.</para><para>(b) If the application
is granted, funds received from such grant shall be remitted to the State
Treasurer for credit to the Water Resources Cash Fund for the purpose of supporting
the projects set forth in the grant application. The department shall include
in its grant application documentation that the Legislature has authorized
a transfer of three million three hundred thousand dollars from the General
Fund into the Water Resources Cash Fund for each of fiscal years 2011-12 and
2012-13 and has stated its intent to transfer three million three hundred
thousand dollars to the Water Resources Cash Fund for fiscal year 2013-14.</para>
<para>(c) It is the
intent of the Legislature that the department apply for an additional three-year
grant that would begin in fiscal year 2014-15 if the criteria established
in subsection (4) of section 81-15,175 are achieved.</para><para>(8) The department shall
establish a subaccount within the Water Resources Cash Fund for the accounting
of all money received as a grant from the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund
as the result of an application made pursuant to subsection (7) of this section.
At the end of each calendar month, the department shall calculate the amount
of interest earnings accruing to the subaccount and shall notify the State
Treasurer who shall then transfer a like amount from the Water Resources Cash
Fund to the Nebraska Environmental Trust Fund.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB689, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB993, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB229, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>May 18, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>