<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id368">
<sectno id="id369">Sec. 38.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Natural Resources" id="id370" statutenumber="61-210"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id372">61-210</statuteno><catchline id="id373">Department of
Natural Resources Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The
Department of Natural Resources Cash Fund is created. The State Treasurer
shall credit to such fund such money as is specifically appropriated or reappropriated
by the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall also credit such fund with payments,
if any, accepted for services rendered by the department and fees collected
pursuant to subsection (6) of section 46-606 and section 61-209. The funds
made available to the Department of Natural Resources by the United States,
through the Natural Resources Conservation Service of the Department of Agriculture
or through any other agencies, shall be credited to the fund by the State
Treasurer. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested
by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion
Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The Department of Natural
Resources shall allocate money from the fund to pay costs of the programs
or activities of the department. The Director of Administrative Services,
upon receipt of proper vouchers approved by the department, shall issue warrants
on the fund, and the State Treasurer shall countersign and pay from, but never
in excess of, the amounts to the credit of the fund. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund
at the direction of the Legislature.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 8, &#167; 13, p. 109; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 2-1913; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 2-1547; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 6, &#167; 25, p. 90; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 28, p. 2358; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 188, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 29, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 403, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1999, &#167; 2-1547; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 458, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 335, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 38.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>