<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id655"><amendatorysection chaptername="Natural Resources" statutenumber="61-305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>61-305</statuteno><catchline>Perkins County Canal Project Fund; created; use; investment; study; required.</catchline><para>(1) The Perkins County Canal Project Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Department of Natural Resources. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund any money transferred by the Legislature and such grants, loans, donations, gifts, bequests, or other money received from any federal or state agency or public or private source for use by the department for the canal project. Any money in the Perkins County Canal Project Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the fund.</para><para>(2)(a) The department shall use the fund for design, engineering, permitting, and options to purchase land related to building a canal as outlined by the South Platte River Compact and to contract with an independent firm for the purposes of completing a study of such canal. The study shall include, but may not be limited to, the following:</para><para>(i) Costs of completion of a canal and adjoining reservoirs as outlined in the South Platte River Compact;</para><para>(ii) A timeline for completion of a canal and adjoining reservoirs as outlined in the South Platte River Compact;</para><para>(iii) A cost-effectiveness study examining alternatives, including alternatives that may reduce environmental or financial impacts; and</para><para>(iv) The impacts of the canal on drinking water supplies for the cities of Lincoln and Omaha.</para><para>(b) The department shall provide the findings of such study electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature and present the findings at a public hearing held by the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature on or before December 31, 2022.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>