<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id861"><amendatorysection chaptername="Natural Resources" statutenumber="61-508"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>61-508</statuteno><catchline>Request for qualifications; prequalify design-builders and progressive design-builders; notice; short list.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall prepare a request for qualifications for design-build and progressive design-build proposals and shall prequalify design-builders and progressive design-builders. The request for qualifications shall describe the project in sufficient detail to permit a design-builder or a progressive design-builder to respond. The request for qualifications shall identify the maximum number of design-builders or progressive design-builders the department will place on a short list as qualified and eligible to receive a request for proposals.</para><para>(2) A person or organization hired by the department under section 61-505 shall be ineligible to compete for a design-build contract on the same project for which the person or organization was hired.</para><para>(3) The request for qualifications shall be (a) published in a newspaper of statewide circulation at least thirty days prior to the deadline for receiving the request for qualifications and (b) sent by first-class mail to any design-builder or progressive design-builder upon request.</para><para>(4) The department shall create a short list of qualified and eligible design-builders or progressive design-builders in accordance with the guidelines adopted pursuant to section 61-506. The department shall select at least two prospective design-builders or progressive design-builders, except that if only one design-builder or progressive design-builder has responded to the request for qualifications, the department may, in its discretion, proceed or cancel the procurement. The request for proposals shall be sent only to the design-builders or progressive design-builders placed on the short list.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB565, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>