<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Natural Resources" statutenumber="61-224"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>61-224</statuteno><catchline>Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>There is hereby created the Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund in the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment. The fund shall consist of funds appropriated or transferred by the Legislature. The fund shall be used by the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment (1) to provide a grant to a natural resources district to offset costs related to soil and water improvements intended to protect critical infrastructure facilities within the district which includes military installations, transportation routes, and wastewater treatment facilities, (2) to provide a grant to an irrigation district for reimbursement of costs related to temporary repairs to the main canal and tunnels of an interstate irrigation system which experienced a failure, and (3) to provide a grant to an entity within a county with a population exceeding one hundred thousand inhabitants formed pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act for the purpose of funding a portion of the cost of a wastewater system. Any funds remaining after all such project costs have been completely funded shall be transferred to the General Fund. Transfers may be made from the Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, and any interest earned by the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1009, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 342. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>