<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Natural Resources" id="id377" statutenumber="61-218"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id379">61-218</statuteno><catchline id="id380">Water Resources
Cash Fund; created; use; investment; eligibility for funding; annual report;
contents.</catchline><para>(1) The Water Resources Cash Fund is created. The
fund shall be administered by the Department of Natural Resources. Transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.
Any money in the Water Resources Cash Fund available for investment shall
be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund such money as is (a)
transferred to the fund by the Legislature, (b) paid to the state as fees,
deposits, payments, and repayments relating to the fund, both principal and
interest, (c) donated as gifts, bequests, or other contributions to such fund
from public or private entities, and (d)
made available by any department or agency of the United States if so directed
by such department or agency.</para>
<para>(3) The fund shall be expended by the department (a) to aid management
actions taken to reduce consumptive uses of water and to enhance streamflows or ground water recharge in
river basins, subbasins, or reaches which are deemed by the department overappropriated
pursuant to section 46-713 or fully appropriated pursuant to section 46-714
or are bound by an interstate compact or decree or a formal state contract
or agreement and (b) to the extent funds are not expended pursuant to subdivision
(a) of this subsection, the department may conduct a statewide assessment
of short-term and long-term water management activities and funding needs
to meet statutory requirements in sections 46-713 to 46-718 and 46-739 and
any requirements of an interstate compact or decree or formal state contract
or agreement. The fund shall not be used to pay for administrative expenses
or any salaries for the department or any political subdivision.</para>
<para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature that two million seven hundred
thousand dollars be transferred each fiscal year from the General Fund to
the Water Resources Cash Fund for FY2009-10 through FY2018-19.</para>
<para>(5)(a) Expenditures from the Water Resources Cash Fund may be made to
natural resources districts eligible under subsection (3) of this section
for activities to either achieve a sustainable balance of consumptive water
uses or assure compliance with an interstate compact or decree or a formal
state contract or agreement and shall require a match of local funding in
an amount equal to or greater than forty percent of the total cost of carrying
out the eligible activity. The department shall, no later than August 1 of
each year, beginning in 2007, determine the amount of funding that will be
made available to natural resources districts from the Water Resources Cash
Fund and notify natural resources districts of this determination. The department
shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing application for
and use of the Water Resources Cash Fund by natural resources districts. Such
rules and regulations shall, at a minimum, include the following components:</para>
<para>(i) Require an explanation of how the planned activity will assure compliance
with an interstate compact or decree or a formal state contract or agreement
as required by section 46-715 and the controls, rules, and regulations designed
to carry out the activity; and</para>
<para>(ii) A schedule of implementation of the activity or its components.</para>
<para>(b) Any natural resources district that fails to implement and enforce
its controls, rules, and regulations as required by section 46-715 shall not
be eligible for funding from the Water Resources Cash Fund until it is determined
by the department that compliance with the provisions required by section
46-715 has been established.</para>
<para>(6) The Department of Natural Resources shall submit an annual report
to the Legislature no later than October 1 of each year, beginning in the
year 2007, that shall detail the use of the Water Resources Cash Fund in the
previous year. The report shall provide:</para>
<para>(a) Details regarding the use and cost of activities carried out by
the department; and</para>
<para>(b) Details regarding the use and cost of activities carried out by
each natural resources district that received funds from the Water Resources
Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB689, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB993, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>