
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Natural Resources" statutenumber="61-224"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>61-224</statuteno><catchline>Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund; created; use; investment; transfers.</catchline><para>There is hereby created the Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund in the Department of Natural Resources. The fund shall consist of funds appropriated or transferred by the Legislature. The fund shall be used by the Department of Natural Resources to provide a grant to a natural resources district to offset costs related to soil and water improvements intended to protect critical infrastructure facilities within the district which includes military installations, transportation routes, and wastewater treatment facilities. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer three hundred eighty-four thousand two hundred twenty-two dollars plus any accrued interest through April 5, 2018, from the Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund to the General Fund on or before June 30, 2019, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. Any money in the Critical Infrastructure Facilities Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, and any interest earned by the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 16. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2018</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>