<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-123"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-123</statuteno><catchline>Record of credentials issued under act; department; duties; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall establish and maintain a record of all credentials issued pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act. The record shall contain identifying information for each credential holder and the credential issued pursuant to the act.</para><para>(2) For individual credential holders engaged in a profession:</para><para>(a) The record information shall include:</para><para>(i) The name, date and place of birth, and social security number;</para><para>(ii) The street, rural route, or post office address;</para><para>(iii) The school and date of graduation;</para><para>(iv) The name of examination, date of examination, and ratings or grades received, if any;</para><para>(v) The type of credential issued, the date the credential was issued, the identifying name and number assigned to the credential, and the basis on which the credential was issued;</para><para>(vi) The status of the credential; and</para><para>(vii) A description of any disciplinary action against the credential, including, but not limited to, the type of disciplinary action, the effective date of the disciplinary action, and a description of the basis for any such disciplinary action;</para><para>(b) The record may contain any additional information the department deems appropriate to advance or support the purpose of the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para><para>(c) The record may be maintained in computer files or paper copies and may be stored on microfilm or in similar form; and</para><para>(d) The record is a public record, except that social security numbers shall not be public information but may be shared as specified in subsection (5) of section 38-130.</para><para>(3) For credential holders engaged in a business:</para><para>(a) The record information shall include:</para><para>(i) The full name and address of the business;</para><para>(ii) The type of credential issued, the date the credential was issued, the identifying name and number assigned to the credential, and the basis on which the credential was issued;</para><para>(iii) The status of the credential; and</para><para>(iv) A description of any disciplinary action against the credential, including, but not limited to, the type of disciplinary action, the effective date of the disciplinary action, and a description of the basis for any such disciplinary action;</para><para>(b) The record may contain any additional information the department deems appropriate to advance or support the purpose of the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para><para>(c) The record may be maintained in computer files or paper copies and may be stored on microfilm or in similar form; and</para><para>(d) The record is a public record.</para><para>(4) If the department is required to provide notice or notify an applicant or credential holder under the Uniform Credentialing Act, such requirements shall be satisfied by mailing a written notice to such applicant or credential holder at his or her last address of record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc>