<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-515"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-515</statuteno><catchline>Practice of audiology or speech-language pathology; license; applicant; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Every applicant for a license to practice audiology shall (a)(i) for applicants graduating prior to September 1, 2007, present proof of a master's degree, a doctoral degree, or the equivalent of a master's degree or doctoral degree in audiology from an academic program approved by the board, and (ii) for applicants graduating on or after September 1, 2007, present proof of a doctoral degree or its equivalent in audiology, (b) present proof of no less than thirty-six weeks of full-time professional experience or equivalent half-time professional experience in audiology, supervised in the area in which licensure is sought, and (c) successfully complete an examination approved by the board.</para><para>(2) Every applicant for a license to practice speech-language pathology shall (a) present proof of a master's degree, a doctoral degree, or the equivalent of a master's degree or doctoral degree in speech-language pathology from an academic program approved by the board, (b) present proof of no less than thirty-six weeks of full-time professional experience or equivalent half-time professional experience in speech-language pathology, supervised in the area in which licensure is sought, and (c) successfully complete an examination approved by the board.</para><para>(3) Presentation of official documentation of certification by a nationwide professional accrediting organization approved by the board shall be deemed equivalent to the requirements of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 406, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 129, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 67; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,190; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 200; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1178.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>