<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1,110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1,110</statuteno><catchline>Complaint alleging dependence or disability; director; investigation; report; review by board; finding; effect.</catchline><para>(1) When the department has received a complaint or report by any person or any report has been made to the director by the Licensee Assistance Program under section 38-175 alleging that an applicant for a credential or a person credentialed to practice any profession is suffering from abuse of, dependence on, or active addiction to alcohol, any controlled substance, or any mind-altering substance that impairs the ability to practice the profession or illness, deterioration, or disability that impairs the ability to practice the profession, the director shall investigate such complaint to determine if any reasonable cause exists to question the qualification of the applicant or credential holder to practice or to continue to practice such profession.</para><para>(2) If the director on the basis of such investigation or, in the absence of such complaint, upon the basis of his or her own independent knowledge finds that reasonable cause exists to question the qualification of the applicant or credential holder to practice such profession because of abuse of, dependence on, or active addiction to alcohol, any controlled substance, or any mind-altering substance that impairs the ability to practice the profession or illness, deterioration, or disability that impairs the ability to practice the profession, the director shall report such finding and evidence supporting it to the appropriate board.</para><para>(3) If such board agrees that reasonable cause exists to question the qualification of such applicant or credential holder, the board shall appoint a committee of three qualified physicians or other qualified professionals to examine the applicant or credential holder and to report their findings and conclusions to the board. The cost of the examination shall be treated as a base cost of credentialing under section 38-152. The board shall then consider the findings and the conclusions of the physicians or other qualified professionals and any other evidence or material which may be submitted to that board by the applicant or credential holder, by the director, or by any other person and shall then determine if the applicant or credential holder is qualified to practice or to continue to practice such profession in the State of Nebraska. </para><para>(4) If such board finds the applicant or credential holder to be not qualified to practice or to continue to practice such profession because of abuse of, dependence on, or active addiction to alcohol, any controlled substance, or any mind-altering substance that impairs the ability to practice the profession or illness, deterioration, or disability that impairs the ability to practice the profession, the board shall so certify that fact to the director with a recommendation for the denial, refusal of renewal, limitation, suspension, or revocation of such credential. The director shall thereupon deny, refuse renewal of, suspend, or revoke the credential or limit the ability of the credential holder to practice such profession in the state in such manner and to such extent as the director determines to be necessary for the protection of the public.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 877, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 579, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 456, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 393; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 23; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-161.13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 315; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 110.</para></source></law></legaldoc>