<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id55">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id57" statutenumber="38-165"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-165</statuteno><catchline id="id60">Boards; public
members; qualifications.</catchline><para>A public member of a board
appointed under the Uniform Licensing Law prior to December 1, 2008, shall
remain subject to the requirements of the original appointment until reappointed
under the Uniform Credentialing Act. At the time of appointment and while
serving as a board member, a public member appointed to a board on or after
December 1, 2008, shall:</para>
<para>(1) Have been a resident of this state for one year;</para>
<para>(2) Remain a resident of Nebraska while serving as a board
member;</para>
<para>(3) Have attained the age of nineteen years;</para>
<para>(4) Represent the interests and viewpoints of the public;</para>
<para>(5) Not hold an active credential in any profession or business
which is subject to the Uniform Credentialing Act, issued in Nebraska or in
any other jurisdiction, at any time during the five years prior to appointment;</para>
<para>(6) Not be eligible for appointment to a board which regulates
a profession or business in which that person has ever held a credential;</para>
<para>(7) Not be or not have been, at any time during the year prior
to appointment, an employee of a member of a profession credentialed by the
department, of a facility credentialed pursuant to the Health Care Facility
Licensure Act, of
a business credentialed pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act, or of a business regulated by the board
to which the appointment is being made;</para>
<para>(8) Not be the parent, child, spouse, or household member
of any person presently regulated by the board to which the appointment is
being made;</para>
<para>(9) Have no material financial interest in the profession
or business regulated by such board; and</para>
<para>(10) Not be a member or employee of the legislative or judicial
branch of state government.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB132, &#167; 10.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>