<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-205</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; qualifications; terms.</catchline><para>(1) Until July 1, 2007, the board shall consist of (a) five advanced practice registered nurses representing different advanced practice registered nurse specialties for which a license has been issued, (b) five physicians licensed under the Uniform Licensing Law to practice medicine in Nebraska, at least three of whom shall have a current collaborating relationship with an advanced practice registered nurse, (c) three consumer members, and (d) one licensed pharmacist.</para><para>(2) On and after July 1, 2007, the board shall consist of:</para><para>(a) One nurse practitioner holding a license under the Nurse Practitioner Practice Act, one certified nurse midwife holding a license under the Certified Nurse Midwifery Practice Act, one certified registered nurse anesthetist holding a license under the Certified Registered Nurse Anesthetist Practice Act, and one clinical nurse specialist holding a license under the Clinical Nurse Specialist Practice Act, except that the initial clinical nurse specialist appointee may be a clinical nurse specialist practicing pursuant to the Nurse Practice Act as such act existed prior to July 1, 2007. Of the initial appointments under this subdivision, one shall be for a two-year term, one shall be for a three-year term, one shall be for a four-year term, and one shall be for a five-year term. All subsequent appointments under this subdivision shall be for five-year terms;</para><para>(b) Three physicians, one of whom shall have a professional relationship with a nurse practitioner, one of whom shall have a professional relationship with a certified nurse midwife, and one of whom shall have a professional relationship with a certified registered nurse anesthetist. Of the initial appointments under this subdivision, one shall be for a three-year term, one shall be for a four-year term, and one shall be for a five-year term. All subsequent appointments under this subdivision shall be for five-year terms; and</para><para>(c) Two public members. Of the initial appointments under this subdivision, one shall be for a three-year term, and one shall be for a four-year term. All subsequent appointments under this subdivision shall be for five-year terms.</para><para>(3) Members of the board serving immediately before July 1, 2007, shall serve until members are appointed and qualified under subsection (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 42; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1718.01; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-17,134; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB185, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 144.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Certified Nurse Midwifery Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-601.</para><para><emphasis>Certified Registered Nurse Anesthetist Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-701.</para><para><emphasis>Clinical Nurse Specialist Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-901.</para><para><emphasis>Nurse Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2201.</para><para><emphasis>Nurse Practitioner Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2301.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>