<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id14" statutenumber="38-157"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-157</statuteno><catchline id="id17">Professional and Occupational Credentialing Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Professional and Occupational Credentialing Cash Fund is created. Except as provided in section 71-17,113, the fund shall consist of all fees, gifts, grants, and other money, excluding fines and civil penalties, received or collected by the department under sections 38-151 to 38-156 and the Nebraska Regulation of Health Professions Act.</para><para>(2) The department shall use the fund for the administration and enforcement of such laws regulating the individuals and businesses listed in section 38-121. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the Professional and Occupational Credentialing Cash Fund for licensing activities under the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act on July 1, 2021, to the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Licensing Fund.</para><para>(3) Any money in the Professional and Occupational Credentialing Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 62, p. 471; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-702; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-163; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 146, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-163; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB834, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 46. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Regulation of Health Professions Act,</emphasis> see section 71-6201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 46-1201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>