<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-126"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-126</statuteno><catchline>Rules and regulations; board and department; adopt.</catchline><para>To protect the health, safety, and welfare of the public and to insure to the greatest extent possible the efficient, adequate, and safe practice of health services, health-related services, and environmental services:</para><para>(1)(a) The appropriate board may adopt rules and regulations to:</para><para>(i) Specify minimum standards required for a credential, including education, experience, and eligibility for taking the credentialing examination, specify methods to meet the minimum standards through military service as provided in section 38-1,141, and on or before December 15, 2017, specify standards and procedures for issuance of temporary credentials for military spouses as provided in section 38-129.01;</para><para>(ii) Designate credentialing examinations, specify the passing score on credentialing examinations, and specify standards, if any, for accepting examination results from other jurisdictions;</para><para>(iii) Set continuing competency requirements in conformance with section 38-145;</para><para>(iv) Set standards for waiver of continuing competency requirements in conformance with section 38-146;</para><para>(v) Set standards for courses of study; and</para><para>(vi) Specify acts in addition to those set out in section 38-179 that constitute unprofessional conduct; and</para><para>(b) The department shall promulgate and enforce such rules and regulations;</para><para>(2) For professions or businesses that do not have a board created by statute:</para><para>(a) The department may adopt, promulgate, and enforce such rules and regulations; and</para><para>(b) The department shall carry out any statutory powers and duties of the board;</para><para>(3) The department, with the recommendation of the appropriate board, if any, may adopt, promulgate, and enforce rules and regulations for the respective profession, other than those specified in subdivision (1) of this section, to carry out the Uniform Credentialing Act; and</para><para>(4) The department may adopt, promulgate, and enforce rules and regulations with general applicability to carry out the Uniform Credentialing Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 68, p. 472; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-902; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-169; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 401; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-169; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 321; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB264, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 32. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>