<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-411"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-411</statuteno><catchline>Applicant for licensure; qualifications; examination.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for licensure as an athletic trainer shall at the time of application provide proof to the department that the applicant meets one or more of the following qualifications:</para><para>(a) For any person who graduated prior to January 1, 2004:</para><para>(i) Graduation after successful completion of the curriculum requirements of an accredited athletic training education program at an accredited college or university approved by the board; or</para><para>(ii) Graduation with a four-year degree from an accredited college or university and completion of at least two consecutive years, military duty excepted, as an athletic training student under the supervision of an athletic trainer approved by the board; and</para><para>(b) For any person who graduated after January 1, 2004, graduation after successful completion of the curriculum requirements of an accredited athletic training education program at an accredited college or university approved by the board.</para><para>(2) In order to be licensed as an athletic trainer, an applicant shall, in addition to the requirements of subsection (1) of this section, successfully complete an examination approved by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 355, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,241; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 183; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB436, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>