<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-186"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>38-186</statuteno><catchline>Credential; discipline; petition by Attorney General; hearing; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) A petition shall be filed by the Attorney General in order for the director to discipline a credential obtained under the Uniform Credentialing Act to:</para><para>(a) Practice or represent oneself as being certified under any of the practice acts enumerated in subdivisions (1) through (19) and (21) through (35) of section 38-101; or</para><para>(b) Operate as a business for the provision of services in body art; cosmetology; emergency medical services; esthetics; funeral directing and embalming; massage therapy; and nail technology in accordance with subsection (3) of section 38-121.</para><para>(2) The petition shall be filed in the office of the director. The department may withhold a petition for discipline or a final decision from public access for a period of five days from the date of filing the petition or the date the decision is entered or until service is made, whichever is earliest.</para><para>(3) The proceeding shall be summary in its nature and triable as an equity action and shall be heard by the director or by a hearing officer designated by the director under rules and regulations of the department. Affidavits may be received in evidence in the discretion of the director or hearing officer. The department shall have the power to administer oaths, to subpoena witnesses and compel their attendance, and to issue subpoenas duces tecum and require the production of books, accounts, and documents in the same manner and to the same extent as the district courts of the state. Depositions may be used by either party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB831, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB255, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>