<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-179"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-179</statuteno><catchline>Disciplinary actions; unprofessional conduct, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of section 38-178, unprofessional conduct means any departure from or failure to conform to the standards of acceptable and prevailing practice of a profession or the ethics of the profession, regardless of whether a person, consumer, or entity is injured, or conduct that is likely to deceive or defraud the public or is detrimental to the public interest, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(1) Receipt of fees on the assurance that an incurable disease can be permanently cured;</para><para>(2) Division of fees, or agreeing to split or divide the fees, received for professional services with any person for bringing or referring a consumer other than (a) with a partner or employee of the applicant or credential holder or his or her office or clinic, (b) with a landlord of the applicant or credential holder pursuant to a written agreement that provides for payment of rent based on gross receipts, or (c) with a former partner or employee of the applicant or credential holder based on a retirement plan or separation agreement;</para><para>(3) Obtaining any fee for professional services by fraud, deceit, or misrepresentation, including, but not limited to, falsification of third-party claim documents;</para><para>(4) Cheating on or attempting to subvert the credentialing examination;</para><para>(5) Assisting in the care or treatment of a consumer without the consent of such consumer or his or her legal representative;</para><para>(6) Use of any letters, words, or terms, either as a prefix, affix, or suffix, on stationery, in advertisements, or otherwise, indicating that such person is entitled to practice a profession for which he or she is not credentialed;</para><para>(7) Performing, procuring, or aiding and abetting in the performance or procurement of a criminal abortion;</para><para>(8) Knowingly disclosing confidential information except as otherwise permitted by law;</para><para>(9) Commission of any act of sexual abuse, misconduct, or exploitation related to the practice of the profession of the applicant or credential holder;</para><para>(10) Failure to keep and maintain adequate records of treatment or service;</para><para>(11) Prescribing, administering, distributing, dispensing, giving, or selling any controlled substance or other drug recognized as addictive or dangerous for other than a medically accepted therapeutic purpose;</para><para>(12) Prescribing any controlled substance to (a) oneself or (b) except in the case of a medical emergency (i) one's spouse, (ii) one's child, (iii) one's parent, (iv) one's sibling, or (v) any other person living in the same household as the prescriber;</para><para>(13) Failure to comply with any federal, state, or municipal law, ordinance, rule, or regulation that pertains to the applicable profession;</para><para>(14) Disruptive behavior, whether verbal or physical, which interferes with consumer care or could reasonably be expected to interfere with such care; and</para><para>(15) Such other acts as may be defined in rules and regulations.</para><para>Nothing in this section shall be construed to exclude determination of additional conduct that is unprofessional by adjudication in individual contested cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 47, p. 466; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-602; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 141, &#167; 1, p. 518; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 71-602; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 11, p. 542; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-148; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 95, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 466, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 579, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 273, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 425, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 456, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 23, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-148; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 49. </para></source><annotation><para>Under the former law, the general definition in the introductory paragraph of this section does not include as unprofessional conduct a single act of ordinary negligence. Mahnke v. State, 276 Neb. 57, 751 N.W.2d 635 (2008).</para><para>Performance of a criminal abortion is immoral, unprofessional, and dishonorable conduct justifying revocation of license to practice medicine and surgery. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Lake, 121 Neb. 331, 236 N.W. 762 (1931).</para><para>Disclosure by a physician of the contagious or infectious nature of a patient's disease to a person who might become exposed is not a betrayal of a professional secret which will constitute unprofessional conduct. Simonsen v. Swenson, 104 Neb. 224, 177 N.W. 831 (1920), 9 A.L.R. 1250 (1920).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>