<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-129</statuteno><catchline>Issuance of credential; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) No individual shall be issued a credential under the Uniform Credentialing Act until he or she has furnished satisfactory evidence to the department that he or she is of good character and has attained the age of nineteen years except as otherwise specifically provided by statute, rule, or regulation.</para><para>(2) A credential may only be issued to (a) a citizen of the United States, (b) an alien lawfully admitted into the United States who is eligible for a credential under the Uniform Credentialing Act, (c) a nonimmigrant lawfully present in the United States who is eligible for a credential under the Uniform Credentialing Act, or (d) a person who submits (i) an unexpired employment authorization document issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security, Form I-766, and (ii) documentation issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security, the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services, or any other federal agency, such as one of the types of Form I-797 used by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services, demonstrating that such person is described in section 202(c)(2)(B)(i) through (ix) of the federal REAL ID Act of 2005, Public Law 109-13. Such credential shall be valid only for the period of time during which such person's employment authorization document is valid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 3, p. 455; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-202; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-103; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 560, &#167; 1, p. 2278; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 579, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-103; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB225, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB947, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>April 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>