<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="38-131"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>38-131</statuteno><catchline>Criminal background check; when required.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for an initial license to practice as a registered nurse or a licensed practical nurse or to practice a profession which is authorized to prescribe controlled substances shall be subject to a criminal background check. Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, the applicant shall submit with the application a full set of fingerprints which shall be forwarded to the Nebraska State Patrol to be submitted to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history record information check. The applicant shall authorize release of the results of the national criminal history record information check to the department. The applicant shall pay the actual cost of the fingerprinting and criminal background check.</para><para>(2) This section shall not apply to a dentist who is an applicant for a dental locum tenens under section 38-1122, to a physician or osteopathic physician who is an applicant for a physician locum tenens under section 38-2036, or to a veterinarian who is an applicant for a veterinarian locum tenens under section 38-3335.</para><para>(3) An applicant for a temporary educational permit as defined in section 38-2019 shall have ninety days from the issuance of the permit to comply with subsection (1) of this section and shall have his or her permit suspended after such ninety-day period if the criminal background check is not complete or revoked if the criminal background check reveals that the applicant was not qualified for the permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 833, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-104.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB481, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB687, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB129, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>