<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-317"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-317</statuteno><catchline>Clinical supervisor; requirements; duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The clinical supervisor for supervised clinical work experience under section 38-316 shall hold one of the following credentials:</para><para>(i) Licensure as an alcohol and drug counselor;</para><para>(ii) If the clinical work is acquired outside of Nebraska, a reciprocity level alcohol and drug counselor credential issued by a member jurisdiction of the International Certification and Reciprocity Consortium, Alcohol and Other Drug Abuse, Inc., or its successor;</para><para>(iii) The highest level alcohol and drug counselor credential issued by a jurisdiction that is not a member of the International Certification and Reciprocity Consortium, Alcohol and Other Drug Abuse, Inc., or its successor if the credential is based on education, experience, and examination that is substantially similar to the license issued in this state as determined by the board; or</para><para>(iv) Licensure as a physician or psychologist under the Uniform Credentialing Act, or an equivalent credential from another jurisdiction, and sufficient training as determined by the Board of Medicine and Surgery for physicians or the Board of Psychologists for psychologists, in consultation with the Board of Alcohol and Drug Counseling, and adopted and promulgated by the department in rules and regulations.</para><para>(b) The clinical supervisor shall be formally affiliated with the program or agency in which the work experience is gained.</para><para>(c) The clinical supervisor shall not be a family member.</para><para>(2) There shall be one hour of evaluative face-to-face clinical supervision for each forty hours of paid alcohol and drug counseling work experience. The format for supervision shall be either one-on-one or small group. Methods of supervision may include case review and discussion or direct observation of a counselor's clinical work.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 551, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,358; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 168.</para></source></law></legaldoc>