<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1,124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1,124</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement; investigations; violations; credential holder; duty to report; cease and desist order; violation; penalty; loss or theft of controlled substance; duty to report.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall enforce the Uniform Credentialing Act and for that purpose shall make necessary investigations. Every credential holder and every member of a board shall furnish the department such evidence as he or she may have relative to any alleged violation which is being investigated.</para><para>(2) Every credential holder shall report to the department the name of every person without a credential that he or she has reason to believe is engaged in practicing any profession or operating any business for which a credential is required by the Uniform Credentialing Act. The department may, along with the Attorney General and other law enforcement agencies, investigate such reports or other complaints of unauthorized practice. The director, with the recommendation of the appropriate board, may issue an order to cease and desist the unauthorized practice of such profession or the unauthorized operation of such business as a measure to obtain compliance with the applicable credentialing requirements by the person prior to referral of the matter to the Attorney General for action. Practice of such profession or operation of such business without a credential after receiving a cease and desist order is a Class III felony.</para><para>(3) Any credential holder who is required to file a report of loss or theft of a controlled substance to the federal Drug Enforcement Administration shall provide a copy of such report to the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 67, p. 472; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-901; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-168; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 579, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 456, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 563, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 222, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 306, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 361, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-168; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB859, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>March 10, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>