<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-130"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-130</statuteno><catchline>Credential; application; contents.</catchline><para>(1) An individual shall file an application for a credential to practice a profession with the department accompanied by the fee set pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act. The application shall contain:</para><para>(a) The legal name of the applicant;</para><para>(b) The date and place of birth of the applicant;</para><para>(c) The address of the applicant;</para><para>(d) The social security number of the applicant or the resident identification number of the applicant if the applicant is not a citizen of the United States and is otherwise eligible to be credentialed under section 38-129; and</para><para>(e) Any other information required by the department.</para><para>(2) A business shall file an application for a credential with the department accompanied by the fee set pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act. The application shall contain:</para><para>(a) The full name and address of the business;</para><para>(b) The full name and address of the owner of the business;</para><para>(c) The name of each person in control of the business;</para><para>(d) The social security number of the business if the applicant is a sole proprietorship; and</para><para>(e) Any other information required by the department.</para><para>(3) The applicant shall sign the application. If the applicant is a business, the application shall be signed by:</para><para>(a) The owner or owners if the applicant is a sole proprietorship, a partnership, or a limited liability company that has only one member;</para><para>(b) Two of its members if the applicant is a limited liability company that has more than one member;</para><para>(c) Two of its officers if the applicant is a corporation;</para><para>(d) The head of the governmental unit having jurisdiction over the business if the applicant is a governmental unit; or</para><para>(e) If the applicant is not an entity described in subdivisions (a) through (d) of this subsection, the owner or owners or, if there is no owner, the chief executive officer or comparable official.</para><para>(4) Each credential holder under the Uniform Credentialing Act shall notify the department of any change to the address of record so that the department can update the record of the credential holder under section 38-123.</para><para>(5) Social security numbers obtained under this section shall not be public information but may be shared by the department for administrative purposes if necessary and only under appropriate circumstances to ensure against any unauthorized access to such information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 8, p. 456; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-207; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-108; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 427, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 579, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 456, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 156; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-108; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 30.</para></source></law></legaldoc>