<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-149"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-149</statuteno><catchline>Application for reinstatement of credential for profession with board; when considered and acted upon; hearing; when allowed; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receipt of an application under section 38-148 for reinstatement of a credential in a profession that has a board, the application shall be sent to the board for consideration. Any application for reinstatement, accompanied by the required information and documentation, shall be acted upon by the board within one hundred eighty days after the filing of the completed application.</para><para>(2) The department, with the recommendation of the appropriate board, may:</para><para>(a) Conduct an investigation to determine if the applicant has committed acts or offenses prohibited by section 38-178;</para><para>(b) Require the applicant to submit to a complete diagnostic examination at the expense of the applicant by one or more physicians or other qualified professionals appointed by the board, the applicant being free also to consult a physician or physicians or other professionals of his or her own choice for an evaluation or diagnostic examination and to make available a report or reports thereof to the department and the appropriate board;</para><para>(c) Require the applicant to pass a written, oral, or practical examination or any combination of such examinations at the expense of the applicant;</para><para>(d) Require the applicant to successfully complete additional education at the expense of the applicant;</para><para>(e) Require the applicant to successfully pass an inspection of his or her practice site; or</para><para>(f) Take any combination of the actions in this subsection.</para><para>(3) On the basis of material submitted by the applicant, the results of any inspection or investigation by the department, and the completion of any requirements imposed under subsection (2) of this section, the board shall (a) deny the application for reinstatement or (b) recommend to the department (i) full reinstatement of the credential, (ii) modification of the suspension or limitation, or (iii) reinstatement of the credential subject to limitations or subject to probation with terms and conditions.</para><para>(4) The decision of the board shall become final thirty days after mailing the decision to the applicant unless the applicant requests a hearing within such thirty-day period. If the applicant requests a hearing before the board, the department shall mail notice of the date, time, and location of the hearing to the applicant at least thirty days prior to the hearing. If the applicant has been afforded a hearing or an opportunity for a hearing on an application for reinstatement within two years prior to filing the current application, the department may grant or deny such application without another hearing before the board. The affirmative vote of a majority of the members of the board shall be necessary to recommend reinstatement of a credential with or without terms, conditions, or restrictions.</para><para>(5)(a) The department may only consider applications for reinstatement with an affirmative recommendation of the appropriate board. If the board recommends (i) full reinstatement of the credential, (ii) modification of the suspension or limitation, or (iii) reinstatement of the credential subject to limitations or subject to probation with terms and conditions, the board's recommendation shall be sent to the applicant by certified mail and forwarded to the director for a decision.</para><para>(b) The director shall receive (i) the written recommendation of the board, including any finding of fact or order of the board, (ii) the application for reinstatement, (iii) the record of hearing if any, and (iv) any pleadings, motions, requests, preliminary or intermediate rulings and orders, and similar correspondence to or from the board and the applicant.</para><para>(c) The director shall then review the application and other documents and may affirm the recommendation of the board and grant reinstatement or may reverse or modify the recommendation if the board's recommendation is (i) in excess of statutory authority, (ii) made upon unlawful procedure, (iii) unsupported by competent, material, and substantial evidence in view of the entire record, or (iv) arbitrary or capricious.</para><para>(6) The director's decision may be appealed by any party to the decision. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(7) Denial by a board of an application for reinstatement may be appealed. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 877, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 579, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1064, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 390; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-161.06; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 312; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 49.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>