<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-520"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-520</statuteno><catchline>Audiologist or speech-language pathology assistant; supervision; termination.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall approve an application submitted by an audiologist or speech-language pathologist for supervision of an audiology or speech-language pathology assistant when:</para><para>(a) The audiology or speech-language pathology assistant meets the requirements for registration pursuant to section 38-519;</para><para>(b) The audiologist or speech-language pathologist has a valid Nebraska license; and</para><para>(c) The audiologist or speech-language pathologist practices in Nebraska.</para><para>(2) Any audiologist or speech-language pathologist seeking approval for supervision of an audiology or speech-language pathology assistant shall submit an application which is signed by the audiology or speech-language pathology assistant and the audiologist or speech-language pathologist with whom he or she is associated. Such application shall (a) identify the settings within which the audiology or speech-language pathology assistant is authorized to practice, (b) describe the agreed-upon functions that the audiology or speech-language pathology assistant may perform as provided in section 38-523, and (c) describe the provision for supervision by an alternate audiologist or speech-language pathologist when necessary.</para><para>(3) If the supervision of an audiology or speech-language pathology assistant is terminated by the audiologist, speech-language pathologist, or audiology or speech-language pathology assistant, the audiologist or speech-language pathologist shall notify the department of such termination. An audiologist or speech-language pathologist who thereafter assumes the responsibility for such supervision shall obtain a certificate of approval to supervise an audiology or speech-language pathology assistant from the department prior to the use of the audiology or speech-language pathology assistant in the practice of audiology or speech-language pathology.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 129, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 70; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,195.02; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 205.</para></source></law></legaldoc>