<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id5" statutenumber="38-155"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-155</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Credentialing fees; establishment and collection.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to subsection (3) of this section, the department, with the recommendation of the appropriate board if applicable, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish and collect the fees for the following credentials:</para><para>(a) Initial credentials, which include, but are not limited to:</para><para>(i) Licensure, certification, or registration;</para><para>(ii) Add-on or specialty credentials;</para><para>(iii) Temporary, provisional, or training credentials; and</para><para>(iv) Supervisory or collaborative relationship credentials;</para><para>(b) Applications to renew licenses, certifications, and registrations;</para><para>(c) Approval of continuing education courses and other methods of continuing competency; and</para><para>(d) Inspections and reinspections.</para><para>(2) When a credential will expire within one hundred eighty days after its initial issuance date or its reinstatement date and the initial credentialing or renewal fee is twenty-five dollars or more, the department shall collect twenty-five dollars or one-fourth of the initial credentialing or renewal fee, whichever is greater, for the initial or reinstated credential. The initial or reinstated credential shall be valid until the next subsequent renewal date.</para><para>(3) All fees for initial credentials under the Uniform Credentialing Act for low-income individuals, military families, and young workers shall be waived except the actual cost of the fingerprinting and criminal background check for an initial license under section 38-131.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 27; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-162.04; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB773, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB112, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 45. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>