<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-131"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-131</statuteno><catchline>Criminal background check; when required.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for an initial license to practice as a registered nurse, a licensed practical nurse, a physical therapist, a physical therapy assistant, a psychologist, an advanced emergency medical technician, an emergency medical technician, an audiologist, a speech-language pathologist, a licensed independent mental health practitioner, an occupational therapist, an occupational therapy assistant, a dietitian, a certified social worker, a certified master social worker, a licensed clinical social worker, a paramedic, a physician, an osteopathic physician, a physician or osteopathic physician who is an applicant for a temporary educational permit, a physician or osteopathic physician who is an applicant for a temporary visiting faculty permit, a physician assistant, a dentist, an optometrist, a podiatrist, a veterinarian, an advanced practice registered nurse-nurse practitioner, an advanced practice registered nurse-certified nurse midwife, or an advanced practice registered nurse-certified registered nurse anesthetist shall be subject to a criminal background check. Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, such an applicant for an initial license shall submit a full set of fingerprints to the Nebraska State Patrol for a criminal history record information check. The applicant shall authorize release of the results of the national criminal history record information check by the Federal Bureau of Investigation to the department. The applicant shall pay the actual cost of the fingerprinting and criminal background check.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska State Patrol is authorized to submit the fingerprints of such applicants to the Federal Bureau of Investigation and to issue a report to the department that includes the criminal history record information concerning the applicant. The Nebraska State Patrol shall forward submitted fingerprints to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history record information check. The Nebraska State Patrol shall issue a report to the department that includes the criminal history record information concerning the applicant.</para><para>(3) This section shall not apply to a dentist who is an applicant for a dental locum tenens under section 38-1122, to a physician or osteopathic physician who is an applicant for a physician locum tenens under section 38-2036, or to a veterinarian who is an applicant for a veterinarian locum tenens under section 38-3335.</para><para>(4) A physician or osteopathic physician who is an applicant for a temporary educational permit shall have ninety days from the issuance of the permit to comply with subsection (1) of this section and shall have such permit suspended after such ninety-day period if the criminal background check is not complete or revoked if the criminal background check reveals that the applicant was not qualified for the permit.</para><para>(5) The department and the Nebraska State Patrol may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations concerning costs associated with the fingerprinting and the national criminal history record information check.</para><para>(6) For purposes of interpretation by the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the term department in this section means the Division of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 833, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-104.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB481, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB687, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB129, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1034, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB752, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB932, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1214, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1215, &#167; 5. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB932, section 4, with LB1214, section 1, and LB1215, section 5, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB932 became operative January 1, 2025. Changes made by LB1214 became effective July 19, 2024. Changes made by LB1215 became operative January 1, 2025.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>