<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1,143"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1,143</statuteno><catchline>Telehealth; provider-patient relationship; prescription authority; applicability of section.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section, any credential holder under the Uniform Credentialing Act may establish a provider-patient relationship through telehealth.</para><para>(2) Any credential holder under the Uniform Credentialing Act who is providing a telehealth service to a patient may prescribe the patient a drug if the credential holder is authorized to prescribe under state and federal law.</para><para>(3) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations pursuant to section 38-126 that are consistent with this section.</para><para>(4) This section does not apply to a credential holder under the Cosmetology, Electrology, Esthetics, Nail Technology, and Body Art Practice Act, the Dialysis Patient Care Technician Registration Act, the Environmental Health Specialists Practice Act, the Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act, the Massage Therapy Practice Act, the Medical Radiography Practice Act, the Nursing Home Administrator Practice Act, the Perfusion Practice Act, the Surgical First Assistant Practice Act, or the Veterinary Medicine and Surgery Practice Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB29, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 53. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Cosmetology, Electrology, Esthetics, Nail Technology, and Body Art Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1001.</para><para><emphasis>Dialysis Patient Care Technician Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 38-3701.</para><para><emphasis>Environmental Health Specialists Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1301.</para><para><emphasis>Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1401.</para><para><emphasis>Massage Therapy Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1701.</para><para><emphasis>Medical Radiography Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1901.</para><para><emphasis>Nursing Home Administrator Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2401.</para><para><emphasis>Perfusion Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Surgical First Assistant Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-3501.</para><para><emphasis>Veterinary Medicine and Surgery Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-3301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>