<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id152"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1,148"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1,148</statuteno><catchline>Physician wellness program; participation; record; confidential; exception; disclosure not required, when.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Physician peer coach means any health care provider licensed to practice medicine or surgery who provides coaching, training, or mentoring through a physician wellness program to another health care provider licensed to practice medicine or surgery under the Uniform Credentialing Act or to a student of an accredited school or college of medicine; and</para><para>(b) Physician wellness program means a program that (i) provides coaching, training, and mentoring services by physician peer coaches or coaches certified by a nationally recognized credentialing program for coach practitioners for the purpose of addressing issues related to career fatigue and wellness for individuals licensed to practice medicine and surgery under the Uniform Credentialing Act and students of an accredited school or college of medicine and (ii) is established, organized, or contracted by any statewide association exempt from taxation under section 501(c)(6) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that primarily represents health care providers in multiple specialties who are licensed to practice medicine and surgery under the Uniform Credentialing Act. A physician wellness program does not include a program of evaluation, monitoring, treatment, or referral.</para><para>(2) Any record of a person's participation in a physician wellness program is confidential and not subject to discovery, subpoena, or a reporting requirement to the department unless the person voluntarily requests release of the information in writing or the physician peer coach determines that the person's condition constitutes a danger to the public health and safety by the person's continued practice of medicine or surgery.</para><para>(3) A person who contacts or participates in a physician wellness program shall not be required to disclose such contact or participation to any health care facility, hospital, medical staff person, accreditation organization, graduate medical education oversight body, health insurer, government agency, or other entity as a condition of participation, employment, credentialing, payment, licensure, compliance, or other requirement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>