<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1622"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1622</statuteno><catchline>Curriculum for training; department; duties; approved certification course; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations defining competencies required for enrollment in an approved certification course and acceptable means for measuring the competencies. Before enrolling in a course, a licensed practical nurse shall successfully demonstrate the prerequisite competencies.</para><para>(2) The department with the advice of the board shall prescribe a curriculum for training licensed practical nurses-certified, establish an examination, and adopt and promulgate rules and regulations setting minimum standards for approved certification courses, including faculty qualifications, record keeping, faculty-to-student ratios, and other aspects of conducting such courses. The department may approve certification courses developed by associations, educational institutions, or other entities if such courses meet the requirements of this section and the criteria prescribed in the rules and regulations.</para><para>(3) An approved certification course shall be no less than forty-eight hours of classroom instruction and shall include a clinical competency component as defined in rules and regulations of the board. Classroom instruction shall include the following: (a) State laws governing the administration of intravenous therapy; (b) anatomy and physiology of the circulatory system; (c) pharmacology; (d) fluid and electrolyte balance; (e) procedures and precautions in performing intravenous therapy; (f) types of equipment for intravenous therapy; (g) actions, interactions, and effects of medications in intravenous therapy; (h) documentation; and (i) other subjects relevant to the administration of intravenous therapy. An approved certification course shall be supervised by a registered nurse with a minimum of three years of clinical experience immediately prior to supervision of the course. An educator may be a physician, pharmacist, or other qualified professional. Nothing in this section shall be deemed to prohibit any courses from exceeding the minimum requirements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 213, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1780; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 604.</para></source></law></legaldoc>