<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-10,132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-10,132</statuteno><catchline>Nail technician or instructor; reciprocity; requirements.</catchline><para>The department may grant a license based on licensure in another jurisdiction to a nail technician or nail technology instructor who presents proof of the following:</para><para>(1) He or she has attained the age of seventeen years; </para><para>(2) He or she has completed formal education equivalent to a United States high school education; </para><para>(3) He or she is currently licensed as a nail technician or its equivalent or as a nail technology instructor or its equivalent in another jurisdiction and he or she has never been disciplined or had his or her license revoked; </para><para>(4) For licensure as a nail technician, evidence of:</para><para>(a) Completion of a program of nail technician studies consisting of a minimum of not less than one hundred fifty hours and not more than three hundred hours, as set by the board, and successful passage of a written examination. If a written examination was not required for licensure in another jurisdiction, the applicant must take the Nebraska written examination; or</para><para>(b) At least twelve months of practice as a nail technician following issuance of such license in another jurisdiction; and</para><para>(5) For licensure as a nail technology instructor, evidence of:</para><para>(a) Completion of a program of studies consisting of a minimum of not less than one hundred fifty hours and not more than three hundred hours, as set by the board, beyond the program of studies required for licensure in another jurisdiction as a nail technician, successful passage of a written examination, and current licensure as a nail technician in Nebraska as evidenced by possessing a valid Nebraska nail technician license. If a written examination was not required for licensure as a nail technology instructor, the applicant must take the Nebraska written examination; or</para><para>(b) At least twelve months of practice as a nail technology instructor following issuance of such license in another jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 68, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-3,191; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 394.</para></source></law></legaldoc>