<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1117</statuteno><catchline>Dentistry; license; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Every applicant for a license to practice dentistry shall (a) present proof of graduation with a Doctor of Dental Surgery degree or a Doctor of Dental Medicine degree from an accredited school or college of dentistry, (b) pass an examination approved by the Board of Dentistry which shall consist of the National Board Dental Examinations, both Part I and Part II, as constructed and administered by the American Dental Association Joint Commission on National Dental Examinations, (c) demonstrate the applicant's skill in clinical dentistry by passing the practical examination administered by the Central Regional Dental Testing Service or any other regional or state practical examination that the Board of Dentistry determines to be comparable to such practical examination, (d) pass a jurisprudence examination approved by the board that is based on the Nebraska statutes, rules, and regulations governing the practice of dentistry and dental hygiene, and (e) demonstrate continuing clinical competency as a condition of licensure if required by the board.</para><para>(2) Upon completion of these requirements, the department, with the recommendation of the board, shall issue the applicant a license to practice dentistry. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 84, p. 476; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 160, &#167; 1, p. 555; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-185; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 238, &#167; 4, p. 826; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 292, &#167; 2, p. 1049; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 470, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 250, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 34; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-185; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 450.</para></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis>general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>