<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1813"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1813</statuteno><catchline>Licensed dietitian nutritionist; eligibility; qualifications; prior licensure; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall be eligible to be a licensed dietitian nutritionist if such person is eighteen years of age or older, submits a completed application as required by the board, submits fees required by the board, and furnishes evidence of:</para><para>(a) A current, valid registration as a registered dietitian nutritionist with the Commission on Dietetic Registration or a similar successor entity approved by the department; or</para><para>(b)(i)(A) A master's or doctoral degree from a college or university accredited at the time of graduation from the appropriate accrediting agency recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation and the United States Department of Education with a major course of study in human nutrition, foods and nutrition, dietetics, food systems management, nutrition education, nutrition, nutrition science, clinical nutrition, applied clinical nutrition, nutrition counseling, nutrition and functional medicine, nutritional biochemistry, nutrition and integrative health, or an equivalent course of study that, as approved by the board, meets the competency requirements of an accredited didactic program in dietetics of the Accreditation Council for Education in Nutrition and Dietetics or a similar successor entity approved by the Department of Health and Human Services; or</para><para>(B) An academic degree from a foreign country that has been validated as equivalent by a credential evaluation agency recognized by the United States Department of Education and that, as approved by the board, meets the competency requirements of an accredited didactic program in dietetics of the Accreditation Council for Education in Nutrition and Dietetics;</para><para>(ii) Successful completion of a planned clinical program in an approved practice of dietetics and nutrition that, as approved by the board, meets the competency requirements of an accredited supervised practice experience in dietetics of the Accreditation Council for Education in Nutrition and Dietetics comprised of not less than one thousand hours of practice under the supervision of a registered dietitian nutritionist. A supervisor who obtained a doctoral degree outside of the United States and territories of the United States shall have the degree validated as equivalent to a doctoral degree conferred by an accredited college or university in the United States by a credential evaluation agency recognized by the United States Department of Education as approved by the Department of Health and Human Services; and</para><para>(iii) Successful completion of the examination for dietitian nutritionists administered by the Commission on Dietetic Registration of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics or a similar successor entity approved by the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(2) A person licensed as a licensed medical nutrition therapist and credentialed as a registered dietitian nutritionist by the Commission on Dietetic Registration or a similar successor entity recognized by the board on September 2, 2023, shall be deemed to be licensed as a licensed dietitian nutritionist for the term of the license. A person licensed as a licensed medical nutrition therapist who is not credentialed as a registered dietitian on September 2, 2023, shall be deemed to be licensed as a licensed nutritionist for the term of the license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 557, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,289; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 635; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1002, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 44. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>