<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id312"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1117</statuteno><catchline>Dentistry; license; examination; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Every applicant for a license to practice dentistry shall (a) present proof of graduation with a Doctor of Dental Surgery degree or a Doctor of Dental Medicine degree from an accredited school or college of dentistry, (b) pass an examination approved by the Board of Dentistry which shall consist of the Integrated National Board Dental Examination or both Part I and Part II of the National Board Dental Examination, as constructed and administered by the American Dental Association Joint Commission on National Dental Examinations, (c) demonstrate the applicant's psychomotor skill in clinical dentistry by passing a standardized national examination approved by the board, (d) pass a jurisprudence examination approved by the board that is based on the Nebraska statutes, rules, and regulations governing the practice of dentistry, and (e) demonstrate continuing clinical competency as a condition of licensure if required by the board.</para><para>(2)(a) An examination approved by the board under subdivision (1)(c) of this section shall be a simulation-based or manikin-based clinical competency psychomotor examination that demonstrates evidence of psychometric soundness and shall include (i) a simulation-based or manikin-based periodontal component, (ii) a simulation-based or manikin-based restorative component, (iii) a simulation-based or manikin-based prosthodontic component, (iv) a simulation-based or manikin-based endodontic component, and (v) a remediation policy to address candidate deficiencies.</para><para>(b) The board may review examinations annually and shall review examinations at least every three years.</para><para>(3) Upon completion of these requirements, the department, with the recommendation of the board, shall issue the applicant a license to practice dentistry. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 84, p. 476; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 160, &#167; 1, p. 555; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-185; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 238, &#167; 4, p. 826; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 292, &#167; 2, p. 1049; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 470, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 250, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 34; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-185; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 450; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB148, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>