<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1124</statuteno><catchline>Faculty license; requirements; renewal; continuing competency.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall issue a faculty license to any person who meets the requirements of subsection (3) or (4) of this section. A faculty licensee may practice dentistry only as a faculty member at an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska and may teach dentistry, conduct research, and participate in an institutionally administered faculty practice only at such accredited school or college of dentistry. A faculty licensee eligible for licensure under subsection (4) of this section shall limit his or her practice to the clinical discipline in which he or she has received postgraduate education at an accredited school or college of dentistry.</para><para>(2) Any person who desires a faculty license shall make a written application to the department. The application shall include information regarding the applicant's professional qualifications, experience, and licensure. The application shall be accompanied by a copy of the applicant's dental degree, any other degrees or certificates for postgraduate education of the applicant, the required fee, and certification from the dean of an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska at which the applicant has a contract to be employed as a full-time faculty member.</para><para>(3) An individual who graduated from an accredited school or college of dentistry shall be eligible for a faculty license if he or she:</para><para>(a) Has or had a license to practice dentistry within the past five years in some other state in the United States or a Canadian province;</para><para>(b) Has a contract to be employed as a full-time faculty member at an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(c) Passes a jurisprudence examination administered by the board; and</para><para>(d) Agrees to demonstrate continuing clinical competency as a condition of licensure if required by the board.</para><para>(4) An individual who graduated from a nonaccredited school or college of dentistry shall be eligible for a faculty license if he or she:</para><para>(a) Has completed at least two years of postgraduate education at an accredited school or college of dentistry and received a certificate or degree from such school or college of dentistry;</para><para>(b) Has a contract to be employed as a full-time faculty member at an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(c) Passes a jurisprudence examination administered by the board;</para><para>(d) Agrees to demonstrate continuing clinical competency as a condition of licensure if required by the board; and</para><para>(e) Has passed Part I and Part II of the National Board Dental Examinations or its equivalent as determined by the Board of Dentistry.</para><para>(5) A faculty license shall expire at the same time and be subject to the same renewal requirements as a regular dental license, except that such license shall remain valid and may only be renewed if:</para><para>(a) The faculty licensee remains employed as a full-time faculty member of an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska; and</para><para>(b) The faculty licensee demonstrates continuing clinical competency if required by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-185.03; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 457.</para></source></law></legaldoc>