<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id951"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1522"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1522</statuteno><catchline>Hearing testing; equipment; calibration; care.</catchline><para>(1) A licensed hearing instrument specialist shall use the following equipment as part of any hearing testing conducted for the purpose of dispensing of hearing instruments:</para><para>(a) An audiometer that has been calibrated within the twelve months preceding the test and that meets the specifications set forth under this section; and</para><para>(b) A speech audiometer that has been calibrated within the twelve months preceding the test and that meets the specifications set forth under this section.</para><para>(2) A licensed hearing instrument specialist shall provide for the calibration of the equipment utilized for hearing assessments required under section 38-1519 and in the dispensing of hearing instruments at least annually in conformance with current standards of the American National Standards Institute for ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments. A licensed hearing instrument specialist shall annually ensure that audiometric equipment has been evaluated electrically and acoustically, that the equipment has been adjusted or repaired if necessary, and that conformity with such standards was determined at that time. A licensed hearing instrument specialist shall maintain calibration records for ten years and shall make the records available for inspection by the department at any time. A licensed hearing instrument specialist shall also use routine procedures for the daily inspection of audiometric equipment, or prior to use if used less often than daily, to generally determine that the equipment is in normal working order.</para><para>(3) A licensed hearing instrument specialist shall provide the following care of the equipment used in the licensee's practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments:</para><para>(a) Hearing instruments, assistive-listening devices, and electronic equipment shall be maintained according to the manufacturer's specifications;</para><para>(b) Instrumental technology shall be maintained in proper working order and be properly calibrated according to accepted standards; and</para><para>(c) Proper infection control and sanitation procedures shall be utilized.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB332, &#167; 26. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>