<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1066"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1066</statuteno><catchline>Reciprocity; requirements; military spouse; temporary license.</catchline><para>(1) The department may grant a license based on licensure in another jurisdiction to any person who meets the requirements of subdivisions (1) and (2) of section 38-1062 and who presents proof of the following:</para><para>(a) That he or she is currently licensed in the appropriate category in another jurisdiction and that he or she has never been disciplined or had his or her license revoked. An applicant seeking licensure as an instructor in the manner provided in this section shall be licensed as an instructor in another jurisdiction. An applicant seeking licensure as a cosmetologist in the manner provided in this section shall be licensed as a cosmetologist in another jurisdiction. An applicant seeking licensure as an esthetician in the manner provided in this section shall be licensed as a cosmetologist, an esthetician, or an equivalent title in another jurisdiction. An applicant seeking licensure as an esthetics instructor in the manner provided in this section shall be licensed as a cosmetology instructor, esthetics instructor, or the equivalent in another jurisdiction. An applicant seeking licensure as an electrologist or an electrology instructor in the manner provided in this section shall be licensed as an electrologist or an electrology instructor, respectively, in another jurisdiction;</para><para>(b) That such license was issued on the basis of an examination and the results of the examination. If an examination was not required for licensure in the other jurisdiction, the applicant shall take the Nebraska examination; and</para><para>(c) That the applicant complies with the hour requirements of subdivision (5) of section 38-1062 through any combination of hours earned as a student or apprentice in a cosmetology establishment licensed or approved by the jurisdiction in which it was located and hour-equivalents granted for recent work experience, with hour-equivalents recognized as follows:</para><para>(i) Each month of full-time practice as an instructor within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as one hundred hour-equivalents toward an instructor's license;</para><para>(ii) Each month of full-time practice as a cosmetologist within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as one hundred hour-equivalents toward a cosmetology license;</para><para>(iii) Each month of full-time practice as an esthetician within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as one hundred hour-equivalents toward an esthetician's license;</para><para>(iv) Each month of full-time practice as an esthetics instructor within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as one hundred hour-equivalents toward an esthetics instructor's license; and</para><para>(v) Each month of full-time practice as an electrologist within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as one hundred hour-equivalents toward an electrologist's license.</para><para>(2) An applicant who is a military spouse may apply for a temporary license as provided in section 38-129.01 and may practice under the temporary license without supervision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 318, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 543, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 83, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 241, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-394; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 328; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 19. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>