<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-10,132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-10,132</statuteno><catchline>Nail technician or instructor; reciprocity; requirements; military spouse; temporary license.</catchline><para>(1) The department may grant a license based on licensure in another jurisdiction to a nail technician or nail technology instructor who presents proof of the following:</para><para>(a) He or she has attained the age of seventeen years;</para><para>(b) He or she has completed formal education equivalent to a United States high school education;</para><para>(c) He or she is currently licensed as a nail technician or its equivalent or as a nail technology instructor or its equivalent in another jurisdiction and he or she has never been disciplined or had his or her license revoked;</para><para>(d) For licensure as a nail technician, evidence of completion of a program of nail technician studies consisting of three hundred hours and successful passage of a written examination. If a written examination was not required for licensure in another jurisdiction, the applicant must take the Nebraska written examination. Each month of full-time practice as a nail technician within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as equivalent to one hundred hours toward a nail technician license; and</para><para>(e) For licensure as a nail technology instructor, evidence of completion of a program of studies consisting of three hundred hours beyond the program of studies required for licensure in another jurisdiction as a nail technician, successful passage of a written examination, and current licensure as a nail technician in Nebraska as evidenced by possessing a valid Nebraska nail technician license. If a written examination was not required for licensure as a nail technology instructor, the applicant must take the Nebraska written examination. Each month of full-time practice as a nail technology instructor within the five years immediately preceding application shall be valued as equivalent to one hundred hours toward a nail technology instructor license.</para><para>(2) An applicant who is a military spouse may apply for a temporary license as provided in section 38-129.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 68, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-3,191; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 394; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 48. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>