<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1813"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1813</statuteno><catchline>Licensed medical nutrition therapist; qualifications; practice; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall be qualified to be a licensed medical nutrition therapist if such person furnishes evidence that he or she:</para><para>(a) Has met the requirements for and is a registered dietitian by the American Dietetic Association or an equivalent entity recognized by the board;</para><para>(b)(i) Has satisfactorily passed an examination approved by the board;</para><para>(ii) Has received a baccalaureate degree from an accredited college or university with a major course of study in human nutrition, food and nutrition, dietetics, or an equivalent major course of study approved by the board; and</para><para>(iii) Has satisfactorily completed a program of supervised clinical experience approved by the department. Such clinical experience shall consist of not less than nine hundred hours of a planned continuous experience in human nutrition, food and nutrition, or dietetics under the supervision of an individual meeting the qualifications of this section; or</para><para>(c)(i) Has satisfactorily passed an examination approved by the board; and</para><para>(ii)(A) Has received a master's or doctorate degree from an accredited college or university in human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, or public health nutrition or in an equivalent major course of study approved by the board; or</para><para>(B) Has received a master's or doctorate degree from an accredited college or university which includes a major course of study in clinical nutrition. Such course of study shall consist of not less than a combined two hundred hours of biochemistry and physiology and not less than seventy-five hours in human nutrition.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, accredited college or university means an institution currently listed with the United States Secretary of Education as accredited. Applicants who have obtained their education outside of the United States and its territories shall have their academic degrees validated as equivalent to a baccalaureate or master's degree conferred by a United States accredited college or university.</para><para>(3)(a) The practice of medical nutrition therapy shall be performed under the consultation of a physician licensed pursuant to section 38-2026 or sections 38-2029 to 38-2033.</para><para>(b) A licensed medical nutrition therapist may order patient diets, including therapeutic diets, in accordance with this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 557, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,289; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 635; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1002, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>