<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1092"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1092</statuteno><catchline>Cosmetic establishment license; application; procedure; additional information; inspection.</catchline><para>(1) Any person seeking a license to operate a cosmetic establishment shall submit a completed application at least thirty days before the proposed opening of the cosmetic establishment for operation. Along with the application the applicant shall submit:</para><para>(a) A floor plan or blueprint sufficient to identify the location of the proposed cosmetic establishment within any larger structure and the location of handwashing facilities; and</para><para>(b) The names of all persons registered or proposed to be registered as cosmeticians to be employed in the cosmetic establishment.</para><para>(2) In the event that more than one counter or area within a larger commercial establishment will be used as a cosmetic establishment, only one license is required for all such counters or areas if all are identified on the floor plan or blueprint accompanying the application. </para><para>(3) Each application shall be reviewed by the department for compliance with the requirements of the Cosmetology, Electrology, Esthetics, Nail Technology, and Body Art Practice Act. In the event an application is denied, the applicant shall be informed in writing of the grounds for denial and such denial shall not prejudice future applications by the applicant. In the event an application is approved, the department shall issue the applicant a certificate of consideration to operate a cosmetic establishment pending an operation inspection. The department shall conduct an operation inspection of each cosmetic establishment issued a certificate of consideration within six months of the issuance of such certificate. Cosmetic establishments passing the inspection shall be issued a permanent license. Cosmetic establishments failing the inspection shall submit, within fifteen days, evidence of corrective action taken to improve those aspects of operation found deficient. If evidence is not submitted within fifteen days or if after a second inspection the cosmetic establishment does not receive a satisfactory rating, it shall immediately relinquish its certificate of consideration and cease operation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 318, &#167; 91; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-3,130; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 354.</para></source></law></legaldoc>