<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-10,103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>38-10,103</statuteno><catchline>School or apprentice salon; operation; student; apprentice; student instructor; requirements.</catchline><para>In order to maintain a school or apprentice salon license in good standing, each school or apprentice salon shall operate in accordance with the following:</para><para>(1) Every person accepted for enrollment as a standard student or apprentice shall show evidence that he or she attained the age of seventeen years on or before the date of his or her enrollment in a school of cosmetology, a school of esthetics, or an apprentice salon, has completed the equivalent of a high school education, has been accepted for enrollment at a school of cosmetology, a school of esthetics, or an apprentice salon, and has not undertaken any training in cosmetology or esthetics without being enrolled as a student or apprentice;</para><para>(2)(a) Every person accepted for enrollment as a special study student or apprentice shall show evidence that he or she:</para><para>(i) Has attained the age of seventeen years on or before the date of enrollment in a school of cosmetology, a school of esthetics, or an apprentice salon;</para><para>(ii) Has completed the tenth grade;</para><para>(iii) Has been accepted for enrollment at a school of cosmetology, a school of esthetics, or an apprentice salon; and</para><para>(iv) Is actively continuing his or her formal high school education on a full-time basis as determined by the department.</para><para>(b) An applicant for enrollment as a special study student or apprentice shall not have undertaken any training in cosmetology or esthetics without being enrolled as a student or apprentice.</para><para>(c) Special study students shall be limited to attending a school of cosmetology, a school of esthetics, or an apprentice salon for no more than eight hours per week during the school year;</para><para>(3) Every person accepted for enrollment as a student instructor shall show evidence of current licensure as a cosmetologist or esthetician in Nebraska and completion of formal education equivalent to a United States high school education; and</para><para>(4) No school of cosmetology, school of esthetics, or apprentice salon shall accept an individual for enrollment who does not provide evidence of meeting the age and education requirements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 318, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 543, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 83, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 241, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 28; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-3,102; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 365; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 30. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>