<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id427"><amendatorysection statutenumber="38-1071" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1071</statuteno><catchline>Temporary, nonrenewable event license; body art event; authorized practice; requirements; fee; inspection; violation.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall create and issue a temporary, nonrenewable event license for an individual who is attending a body art event which shall allow the individual to practice for no more than seven consecutive days in any twelve-month period. No more than two temporary event licenses shall be issued to the same individual in any twelve-month period. An individual holding an event license under this section shall practice within a licensed body art facility that has been inspected pursuant to subsection (5) of this section.</para><para>(2) An individual applying for an event license described in subsection (1) of this section shall hold a valid, unrestricted license or permit showing the individual is active in another state and shall submit the following documents to the department:</para><para>(a) A completed application form;</para><para>(b) A copy of a government-issued photographic identification showing the individual's proof of age;</para><para>(c) A copy of the individual's body art license; and</para><para>(d) A sponsorship letter from the owner or operator of a licensed body art facility at which the individual will practice under the event license.</para><para>(3) The event license shall include the (a) individual's name, (b) approved location or event, (c) expiration date, (d) state of issuance, and (e) number of the individual's license or permit.</para><para>(4) The department shall charge a fifty-dollar fee for issuance of the event license. The department shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer for credit to the Professional and Occupational Credentialing Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) The department may conduct an in-person inspection of the body art facility where body art practice will occur for a body art event to assess compliance with the department's rules and regulations. Such inspection may be conducted by a health specialist with body art training, including, but not limited to, a registered environmental health specialist.</para><para>(6) A violation of this section is subject to the same penalties as an individual or a facility holding a permanent license to practice body art under the Uniform Credentialing Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB720, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>March 13, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>