<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id329">
<sectno id="id330" opdate=" ">Sec. 14.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id331" statutenumber="38-1218"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id333">38-1218</statuteno><catchline id="id334">Licensure classification.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Legislature adopts all parts of the United States
Department of Transportation curricula, including appendices, and skills as
the training requirements and permitted practices and procedures for the licensure
classifications listed in subdivision (1)(a) of section 38-1217
until modified by the board
by rule and regulation. The
Legislature adopts the United States Department of Transportation National
Emergency Medical Services Education Standards and the National Emergency
Medical Services Scope of Practice for the licensure classifications listed
in subdivision (1)(b) of section 38-1217 until modified by the board by rule
and regulation. The board may approve curricula for the licensure classifications
listed in subdivision (1) of section 38-1217.</para>
<para>(2) The department and the board shall consider the following
factors, in addition to other factors required or permitted by the Emergency
Medical Services Practice Act, when adopting rules and regulations for a licensure
classification:</para>
<para>(a) Whether the initial training required for licensure in
the classification is sufficient to enable the out-of-hospital emergency care
provider to perform the practices and procedures authorized for the classification
in a manner which is beneficial to the patient and protects public health
and safety;</para>
<para>(b) Whether the practices and procedures to be authorized
are necessary to the efficient and effective delivery of out-of-hospital emergency
medical care;</para>
<para>(c) Whether morbidity can be reduced or recovery enhanced
by the use of the practices and procedures to be authorized for the classification;
and</para>
<para>(d) Whether continuing competency requirements are sufficient
to maintain the skills authorized for the classification.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 88; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-5179; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 502; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167;  14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>