<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1124"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1124</statuteno><catchline>Faculty license; practice; limitations; requirements; renewal; continuing competency.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall issue a faculty license to any person who meets the requirements of subsection (3) or (4) of this section. A faculty licensee may practice dentistry as a faculty member at an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska. A faculty licensee may also teach dentistry, conduct research, and participate in an institutionally administered faculty practice. A faculty licensee eligible for licensure under subsection (4) of this section shall limit practice under such license to the clinical disciplines in which the licensee has received education at an accredited school or college of dentistry or, with the approval of the board, the clinical disciplines in which the licensee has practiced under a license, including a faculty license or teaching permit, to practice dentistry within the past three years in another jurisdiction.</para><para>(2) Any person who desires a faculty license shall make a written application to the department. The application shall include information regarding the applicant's professional qualifications, experience, and licensure. The application shall be accompanied by a copy of the applicant's dental degree, any other degrees or certificates for postgraduate education of the applicant, the required fee, and certification from the dean of an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska at which the applicant has a contract to be employed as a full-time faculty member.</para><para>(3) An individual who graduated from an accredited school or college of dentistry shall be eligible for a faculty license if the individual:</para><para>(a) Has or had a license, including a faculty license or teaching permit, to practice dentistry within the past three years in another jurisdiction; and</para><para>(b) Passes a jurisprudence examination administered by the board.</para><para>(4) An individual who graduated from a nonaccredited school or college of dentistry shall be eligible for a faculty license if the individual:</para><para>(a)(i) Has or had a license, including a faculty license or teaching permit, to practice dentistry within the past three years in another jurisdiction;</para><para>(ii) Has completed at least two years of postgraduate education at an accredited school or college of dentistry recognized by the national commission and received a certificate or degree from such school or college of dentistry; or</para><para>(iii) Has additional education in dentistry at an accredited school or college of dentistry that is determined by the board to be equivalent to a program recognized by the national commission, including, but not limited to, a postgraduate certificate or degree in operative dentistry;</para><para>(b) Passes a jurisprudence examination administered by the board; and</para><para>(c) Has passed at least one of the following:</para><para>(i) Part I and Part II of the National Board Dental Examinations administered by the joint commission;</para><para>(ii) The Integrated National Board Dental Examination administered by the joint commission;</para><para>(iii) A specialty board examination recognized by the national commission;</para><para>(iv) An examination administered by the National Dental Examining Board of Canada; or</para><para>(v) An equivalent examination as determined by the Board of Dentistry.</para><para>(5) A faculty license shall expire at the same time and be subject to the same renewal requirements as a regular dental license, except that such license shall remain valid and may only be renewed if the faculty licensee completes continuing education as required by the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the Dentistry Practice Act and demonstrates continued employment at an accredited school or college of dentistry in the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(6) In order for an applicant to qualify for a faculty license pursuant to subdivision (4)(a)(iii) of this section, the applicant shall present, for review and approval by the board, a portfolio which includes, but is not limited to, academic achievements, credentials and certifications, letters of recommendation, and a list of publications.</para><para>(7) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Another jurisdiction means some other state in the United States, a territory or jurisdiction of the United States, or a Canadian province;</para><para>(b) Joint commission means the American Dental Association Joint Commission on National Dental Examinations; and</para><para>(c) National commission means the National Commission on Recognition of Dental Specialties and Certifying Boards.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-185.03; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 457; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB628, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>