<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1121" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1121</statuteno><catchline>Dental hygienist; licensed dental assistant; reciprocity; requirements; military license; temporary license.</catchline><para>(1) Every applicant for a license to practice dental hygiene based on a license in another state or territory of the United States or the District of Columbia shall meet the standards set by the board pursuant to section 38-126 and shall have been actively engaged in the practice of dental hygiene for at least three years, one of which must be within the three years immediately preceding the application, under a license in another state or territory of the United States or the District of Columbia. Practice in an accredited dental hygiene program for the purpose of completing a postgraduate or residency program in dental hygiene also serves as active practice toward meeting this requirement.</para><para>(2) An applicant who is a military spouse may apply for a temporary license as provided in section 38-129.01.</para><para>(3) Every applicant for a license to practice as a licensed dental assistant based on a license in another state or territory of the United States or the District of Columbia shall meet the standards set by the board pursuant to section 38-126 and shall have been actively engaged in practice as a licensed dental assistant for at least three years, one of which must be within the three years immediately preceding the application, under a license in another state or territory of the United States or the District of Columbia. Practice in an accredited dental assisting program for the purpose of completing a postgraduate or residency program in dental assisting also serves as active practice toward meeting this requirement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 454; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB18, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 47. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>