<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1135"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1135</statuteno><catchline>Dental assistants, licensed dental assistants, and expanded function dental assistants; employment; duties performed; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) Any licensed dentist, public institution, or school may employ dental assistants, licensed dental assistants, and expanded function dental assistants. Such dental assistants, under the supervision of a licensed dentist, may perform such duties as are prescribed in the Dentistry Practice Act in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department, with the recommendation of the board.</para><para>(2) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations pursuant to section 38-126 governing the performance of duties by dental assistants, licensed dental assistants, and expanded function dental assistants. The rules and regulations shall include the degree of supervision which must be provided by a licensed dentist and the education and proof of competency requirements that must be met for any procedures performed by a dental assistant, a licensed dental assistant, or an expanded function dental assistant.</para><para>(3) A dental assistant may perform duties delegated by a licensed dentist for the purpose of assisting the licensed dentist in the performance of the dentist’s clinical and clinical-related duties as allowed in the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the Dentistry Practice Act.</para><para>(4) Under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist, a dental assistant may (a) monitor nitrous oxide if the dental assistant has current and valid certification for cardiopulmonary resuscitation approved by the board and (b) place topical local anesthesia.</para><para>(5) Upon completion of education and testing approved by the board, a dental assistant may:</para><para>(a) Take X-rays under the general supervision of a licensed dentist; and</para><para>(b) Perform coronal polishing under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist.</para><para>(6) A licensed dental assistant may perform all procedures authorized for a dental assistant. Upon completion of education and testing approved by the board and with a permit from the department for the respective competency, a licensed dental assistant may, under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist, (a) take dental impressions for fixed prostheses, (b) take dental impressions and make minor adjustments for removable prostheses, (c) cement prefabricated fixed prostheses on primary teeth, and (d) monitor and administer nitrous oxide analgesia.</para><para>(7) Upon completion of education and testing approved by the board and with a permit from the department for the respective competency, an expanded function dental assistant may, under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist, place (a) restorative level one simple restorations (one surface) and (b) restorative level two complex restorations (multiple surfaces).</para><para>(8) A dental assistant may be a graduate of an accredited dental assisting program or may be trained on the job.</para><para>(9) No person shall practice as a licensed dental assistant in this state unless he or she holds a license as a licensed dental assistant under the Dentistry Practice Act.</para><para>(10) No person shall practice as an expanded function dental assistant in this state unless he or she holds a permit as an expanded function dental assistant under the act.</para><para>(11) A licensed dentist shall only delegate duties to a dental assistant, a licensed dental assistant, or an expanded function dental assistant in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Dentistry Practice Act. The licensed dentist supervising a dental assistant, a licensed dental assistant, or an expanded function dental assistant shall be responsible for patient care for each patient regardless of whether the patient care is rendered personally by the dentist or by a dental assistant, a licensed dental assistant, or an expanded function dental assistant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 587, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 572, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 413; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 800, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-193.13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 327; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 468; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB18, &#167; 20. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>