<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1139"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1139</statuteno><catchline>Permit to administer general anesthesia or deep sedation; issuance; conditions; existing permit; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall issue a permit to a Nebraska-licensed dentist to administer general anesthesia or deep sedation on an outpatient basis to dental patients if the dentist:</para><para>(a) Maintains a properly equipped facility for the administration of general anesthesia or deep sedation as determined by the board;</para><para>(b) Is currently certified in basic life-support skills for health care providers as determined by the board and either advanced cardiac life support or an appropriate emergency management course for anesthesia and dental sedation as determined by the board;</para><para>(c) Has successfully completed an onsite evaluation covering the areas of physical evaluation, monitoring, sedation, and emergency medicine; and</para><para>(d) Meets at least one of the following criteria:</para><para>(i) Has completed an advanced education program approved by the board that affords comprehensive and appropriate training necessary to administer and manage general anesthesia or deep sedation; or</para><para>(ii) Is a fellow of the American Dental Society of Anesthesiology.</para><para>(2) A dentist who has been issued a permit pursuant to this section may administer moderate or minimal sedation.</para><para>(3) A dentist who has been issued a permit to administer general anesthesia pursuant to this section prior to July 1, 2016, may administer deep, moderate, or minimal sedation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 438, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-193.26; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 472; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB80, &#167; 9. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>