<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1416"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1416</statuteno><catchline>Apprenticeship; apprentice license; examination.</catchline><para>(1) Before beginning an apprenticeship, an applicant shall apply for an apprentice license. The applicant shall show that he or she has completed twenty of the forty hours required in subdivision (1)(a) of section 38-1414. The applicant may complete the twelve-month apprenticeship in either a split apprenticeship or a full apprenticeship as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) A split apprenticeship shall be completed in the following manner:</para><para>(a) Application for an apprentice license to complete a six-month apprenticeship prior to attending an accredited school of mortuary science, which license shall be valid for six months from the date of issuance and shall not be extended by the board. The apprenticeship shall be completed over a continuous six-month period;</para><para>(b) Successful completion of a full course of study in an accredited school of mortuary science;</para><para>(c) Successful passage of the national standardized examination; and</para><para>(d) Application for an apprentice license to complete the final six-month apprenticeship, which license shall be valid for six months from the date of issuance and shall not be extended by the board. The apprenticeship shall be completed over a continuous six-month period.</para><para>(3) A full apprenticeship shall be completed in the following manner:</para><para>(a) Successful completion of a full course of study in an accredited school of mortuary science;</para><para>(b) Successful passage of the national standardized examination; and</para><para>(c) Application for an apprentice license to complete a twelve-month apprenticeship. This license shall be valid for twelve months from the date of issuance and shall not be extended by the board. The apprenticeship shall be completed over a continuous twelve-month period.</para><para>(4) An individual registered as an apprentice on December 1, 2008, shall be deemed to be licensed as an apprentice for the term of the apprenticeship on such date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 96, p. 481; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1305; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 357; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 155, &#167; 3, p. 613; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 71-1305; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-198; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 36; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 71-198; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 187, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 97; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1304; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 552; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB704, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>