<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id711"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id437" statutenumber="38-1509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1509</statuteno><catchline id="id440">Practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments; license required; exceptions; organization; filing required.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as otherwise provided in this section, it shall be unlawful for any person to engage in the practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments or display a sign or in any other way advertise or represent that the person is engaged in the practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments unless such person holds a current, unsuspended, and unrevoked hearing instrument specialist license issued by the department as provided in the Hearing Instrument Specialists Practice Act.</para><para>(b) A hearing instrument specialist license shall confer upon the holder the right to select, fit, and sell hearing instruments.</para><para>(2) A licensed audiologist shall be exempt from the requirement to be licensed as a hearing instrument specialist.</para><para>(3) A hearing instrument specialist or audiologist may order the use of devices pursuant to 21 C.F.R. 801.109, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2025.</para><para>(4)(a) Nothing in the Hearing Instrument Specialists Practice Act shall prohibit a corporation, partnership, limited liability company, trust, association, or other like organization maintaining an established business address from engaging in the business of selling or offering for sale hearing instruments at retail without a license if it employs only properly licensed natural persons in the direct sale and fitting of such products.</para><para>(b) Each such organization shall file annually with the department, on a form provided by the department, a list of the licensed hearing instrument specialists employed by the organization. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as necessary to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 767, &#167; 2, p. 2904; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 701, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 438; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-4702; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 573; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB14, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB332, &#167; 17. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Audiology and Speech-Language Pathology Interstate Compact,</emphasis> see section 38-4101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>