<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1310"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1310</statuteno><catchline>Registered environmental health specialist; provisional environmental health specialist; certification; term; renewal; continuing competency requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Certification as a registered environmental health specialist shall expire biennially. Certification as a provisional environmental health specialist shall be valid for one year and may be renewed for two additional one-year periods. In no case shall certification for a provisional environmental health specialist exceed a three-year period.</para><para>(2) Each registered environmental health specialist in active practice in the state shall complete continuing competency activities as approved by the board and adopted and promulgated by the department in rules and regulations as a prerequisite for the registrant's next subsequent biennial renewal. Continuing education is sufficient to meet continuing competency requirements. The requirements may also include, but not be limited to, one or more of the continuing competency activities listed in section 38-145 which a registered environmental health specialist may select as an alternative to continuing education.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 400, &#167; 10, p. 1283; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 578, &#167; 4, p. 2328; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 542, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 189; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 121; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-3710; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 531.</para></source></law></legaldoc>