<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id435">
<sectno id="id436" opdate=" ">Sec. 27.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id437" statutenumber="38-1509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id439">38-1509</statuteno><catchline id="id440">Sale or fitting
of hearing instruments; license required.</catchline>
<para>(1) No person shall engage in the sale of or practice of
fitting hearing instruments or display a sign
or in any other way advertise or represent himself or herself as a person
who practices the fitting and sale or dispensing of hearing instruments unless
he or she holds an unsuspended, unrevoked hearing
instrument specialist license issued by the department as provided
in the Hearing Instrument Specialists Practice Act.
A hearing instrument specialist license
shall confer upon the holder the right to select, fit, and sell hearing instruments. A person holding a license issued under the
act prior to August 30, 2009, may continue to practice under such license
until it expires under the terms of the license.</para>
<para>(2) A licensed audiologist who maintains a practice pursuant
to licensure as an audiologist in which hearing instruments are
regularly dispensed or who intends to maintain such a practice shall also
be licensed as a hearing instrument
specialist pursuant to subsection (4) of section 38-1512.</para>
<para>(3) Nothing in the act shall prohibit a corporation, partnership,
limited liability company, trust, association, or other like organization
maintaining an established business address from engaging in the business
of selling or offering for sale hearing instruments at retail without
a license if it employs only properly licensed natural persons in the direct
sale and fitting of such products.</para>
<para>(4) Nothing in the act shall prohibit the holder of a hearing instrument specialist license
from the fitting and sale of wearable instruments or devices designed for
or offered for the purpose of conservation or protection of hearing.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 767, &#167; 2, p. 2904; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 701, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 438; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-4702; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 573; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 27.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
