<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id72"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1820"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1820</statuteno><catchline>Medical nutrition therapy; authorized; use of titles, abbreviations, words; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) Unless otherwise authorized or exempted under the Medical Nutrition Therapy Practice Act:</para><para>(a) Only a licensed dietitian nutritionist or licensed nutritionist may provide medical nutrition therapy; and</para><para>(b) No person shall use the title dietitian nutritionist, nutritionist, dietitian, licensed dietitian nutritionist, licensed medical nutrition therapist, licensed nutritionist, medical nutrition therapist, or licensed nutrition specialist, or the abbreviation LDN or LN, or any other title, designation, word, letter, abbreviation, or insignia indicating that the person is a provider of medical nutrition therapy or licensed under the Medical Nutrition Therapy Practice Act unless the person is a licensed dietitian nutritionist or a licensed nutritionist.</para><para>(2) Only a person who is issued a license as a dietitian nutritionist under the act may use the words licensed dietitian nutritionist, dietitian nutritionist, or dietitian or the letters LDN in connection with such person's name. Only a person who is issued a license as a nutritionist under the act may use the words licensed nutritionist or the letters LN in connection with such person's name. Only a person licensed under the act may use the word nutritionist in connection with such person's name. A person may use any lawfully earned federally trademarked title, and the following persons may use the following words, titles, or letters: (a) A registered dietitian nutritionist may use registered dietitian, registered dietitian nutritionist, rd, or rdn; (b) a person who is credentialed by the Board for Certification of Nutrition Specialists as a certified nutrition specialist may use certified nutrition specialist or cns; or (c) a board-certified nutrition pharmacist may use the title nutrition specialist.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 48. </para><operativedate>September 2, 2023</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>