<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id790"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id484" statutenumber="38-1514"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1514</statuteno><catchline id="id487">Examination for licensure; contents; purpose.</catchline><para>(1) The examination required by section 38-1512 for licensure as a hearing instrument specialist shall be comprised of:</para><para>(a) A written or computer-based, psychometrically valid, competency examination approved by the board that tests the examinee for knowledge fundamental to the practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments;</para><para>(b) A practical examination approved by the board that requires the examinee to demonstrate competence in the practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments; and</para><para>(c) A jurisprudence examination approved by the board.</para><para>(2)(a) If an examinee fails more than one portion of the practical examination, the examinee shall retake the entire practical examination upon payment of the examination fee.</para><para>(b) If an examinee fails only one portion of the practical examination, the examinee may retake that portion of the examination without payment of a fee.</para><para>(c) If an examinee fails the jurisprudence examination or competency examination, the examinee shall retake the entire examination upon payment of the examination fee.</para><para>(d) If an examinee fails either the practical or competency component of the examination and fails two subsequent reexaminations, the examinee shall be disqualified from retaking the examination a fourth time until the examinee meets with the board, presents an acceptable written training plan to the board for passing the components of the examination, and successfully completes that plan.</para><para>(3) The qualifying examination provided in section 38-1512 shall be designed to demonstrate the applicant's adequate technical qualifications by:</para><para>(a) Tests of knowledge in the following areas as they pertain to the practice of ordering the use and fitting of hearing instruments:</para><para>(i) Basic physics of sound;</para><para>(ii) The anatomy and physiology of the ear; and</para><para>(iii) The function of hearing instruments; and</para><para>(b) Practical tests of proficiency in the following techniques as they pertain to the fitting of hearing instruments:</para><para>(i) Pure tone audiometry, including air conduction testing and bone conduction testing;</para><para>(ii) Live voice or recorded voice speech audiometry;</para><para>(iii) Masking when indicated;</para><para>(iv) Recording and evaluation of audiograms and speech audiometry to determine proper selection and adaptation of a hearing instrument; and</para><para>(v) Taking earmold impressions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 767, &#167; 9, p. 2908; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 701, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-4709; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 578; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB332, &#167; 22. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>