<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id960"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1424"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1424</statuteno><catchline>Funeral directors and embalmers and funeral establishments; prohibited acts; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to the grounds for disciplinary action found in sections 38-178 and 38-179, a credential issued under the Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act may be denied, refused renewal, limited, revoked, or suspended or have other disciplinary measures taken against it in accordance with section 38-196 when the applicant or credential holder is found guilty of any of the following acts or offenses:</para><para>(a) Solicitation of dead human bodies by the credential holder or his or her agents, assistants, or employees, either prior to or following death;</para><para>(b) The purchasing of funeral or embalming engagements or the payment of a commission either directly or indirectly or offer of payment of such commission to any agent, assistant, or employee for the purpose of securing business;</para><para>(c) Using indecent, profane, or obscene language in the presence of a dead human body or within the immediate presence or hearing of the family, relatives, or friends of the deceased prior to the burial of the deceased;</para><para>(d) Soliciting or accepting any remuneration, commission, bonus, or rebate in consideration of the recommending or causing a dead human body to be placed in any crematory, mausoleum, or cemetery;</para><para>(e) Using any casket or part thereof which has previously been used as a receptacle for, or in connection with, the shipment, burial, or other disposition of a dead human body without first identifying such item as used;</para><para>(f) Violations of any state law, municipal ordinance, or rule or regulation of the department or other body having regulatory powers, relating to the handling, custody, care, or transportation of dead human bodies;</para><para>(g) Refusal to surrender promptly the custody of a dead human body upon request of a person or persons lawfully entitled to the custody thereof;</para><para>(h) Taking undue advantage of a patron or patrons, or being found guilty of fraud, or misrepresentation in the selling of merchandise or service to patrons; or</para><para>(i) Failure to comply with section 38-1432.</para><para>(2) An applicant or a credential holder shall be subject to the penalty provisions of this section if found guilty of any of the following:</para><para>(a) Paying, directly or indirectly, any money or other thing of value as a commission or gratuity for the securing of business;</para><para>(b) The buying of a business of any person, firm, or corporation, or the paying of a commission to any person, firm, or corporation or to any hospital or any institution where death occurs or to any hospital superintendent, nurse, intern, or other employee, whether directly or indirectly; or</para><para>(c) Willful malpractice.</para><para>(3) Any funeral director and embalmer who commits any of the acts or things prohibited by this section or otherwise violates any of the provisions thereof shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit a licensed funeral director and embalmer from engaging in sales of funeral goods or services under the Burial Pre-Need Sale Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 295, &#167; 9, p. 1063; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 411, &#167; 1, p. 1331; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 94, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 187, &#167; 25; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1333; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 560; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB332, &#167; 10. </para><operativedate>May 21, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Burial Pre-Need Sale Act,</emphasis> see section 12-1101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>