<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id744"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id463" statutenumber="38-1512"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1512</statuteno><catchline id="id466">License; examination; conditions; waiver.</catchline><para>(1) Any person may obtain a hearing instrument specialist license under the Hearing Instrument Specialists Practice Act by successfully passing a qualifying examination pursuant to section 38-1514 if the applicant provides verification to the department, on a form provided by the department, that such person:</para><para>(a) Is at least twenty-one years of age;</para><para>(b) Has an education equivalent to a four-year course in an accredited high school; and</para><para>(c)(i) Has completed the minimum number of practicum hours prescribed by the board;</para><para>(ii) Has a two-year degree in hearing instrument sciences or an equivalent as determined by the board;</para><para>(iii) Has held a current, unsuspended, and unrevoked license to dispense hearing instruments from another jurisdiction for at least twelve of the last eighteen months prior to taking the examination;</para><para>(iv) Is certified by the National Board for Certification in Hearing Instrument Sciences at the time of taking the examination; or</para><para>(v) Holds an advanced credential offered by the International Hearing Society at the time of taking the examination.</para><para>(2) The department, with the recommendation of the board, may determine whether a person who has completed a licensure program outside of the United States may take the examination.</para><para>(3) The department, upon recommendation of the board, may waive components of the examination pursuant to section 38-1514 for licensure as a hearing instrument specialist if the person has passed the same examination as provided in section 38-1514 or a substantially equivalent examination as determined by the board.</para><para>(4) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall determine whether a person has met the requirements to be eligible to take the examination pursuant to the Hearing Instrument Specialists Practice Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 767, &#167; 7, p. 2907; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 701, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 153; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-4707; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 576; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB332, &#167; 20. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>