<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1131"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1131</statuteno><catchline>Licensed dental hygienist; procedures and functions authorized; enumerated.</catchline><para>When authorized by and under the general supervision of a licensed dentist, a licensed dental hygienist may perform the following intra and extra oral procedures and functions:</para><para>(1) Oral prophylaxis, periodontal scaling, and root planing which includes supragingival and subgingival debridement;</para><para>(2) Polish all exposed tooth surfaces, including restorations;</para><para>(3) Conduct and assess preliminary charting, probing, screening examinations, and indexing of dental and periodontal disease, with referral, when appropriate, for a dental diagnosis by a licensed dentist;</para><para>(4) Brush biopsies;</para><para>(5) Pulp vitality testing;</para><para>(6) Gingival curettage;</para><para>(7) Removal of sutures;</para><para>(8) Preventive measures, including the application of fluorides, sealants, and other recognized topical agents for the prevention of oral disease;</para><para>(9) Impressions for study casts;</para><para>(10) Application of topical and subgingival agents;</para><para>(11) Radiographic exposures;</para><para>(12) Oral health education, including conducting workshops and inservice training sessions on dental health;</para><para>(13) Application or administration of antimicrobial rinses, fluorides, and other anticariogenic agents;</para><para>(14) Upon completion of education and testing approved by the board, interim therapeutic restoration technique; and</para><para>(15) All of the duties that a dental assistant who is not licensed is authorized to perform.</para><para>Upon completion of education and testing approved by the board and when authorized by and under the general supervision of a licensed dentist, a licensed dental hygienist may write prescriptions for mouth rinses and fluoride products that help decrease the risk for tooth decay.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 572, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 800, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-193.17; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 464; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB18, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>