<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1125</statuteno><catchline>Practitioner's facility; requirements; inspections; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, practitioner's facility means a facility in which a licensed dentist practices his or her profession, other than a facility licensed pursuant to the Health Care Facility Licensure Act.</para><para>(2) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations which are approved by the State Board of Health for practitioners' facilities in order to insure that such facilities are safe and sanitary and use precautions necessary to prevent the creation and spread of infectious and contagious diseases. Based upon a formal complaint, the department or its employees may inspect any practitioner's facility in this state to insure compliance with such regulations.</para><para>(3) Within thirty days after an inspection of a practitioner's facility which the department or its employees find to be in violation of its rules and regulations, the department shall notify the Board of Dentistry of its findings in writing. The Attorney General shall file a petition for disciplinary action pursuant to section 38-186 if the violation of the rules and regulations is not corrected within thirty days after the licensee has received notice of such violation. The department shall send a written progress report of its inspection and actions taken to the board.</para><para>(4) It shall be considered unprofessional conduct for a licensee to practice in a facility that does not comply with the rules and regulations regarding sanitary practitioners' facilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 470, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 408; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 85; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-185.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 458.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Alcoholic liquor,</emphasis> possession and use in practice, see section 53-168.06.</para><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>