<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1136"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1136</statuteno><catchline>Licensed dental hygienists and expanded function dental hygienists; employment authorized; performance of duties; rules and regulations; license or permit required.</catchline><para>(1) Any licensed dentist, public institution, or school may employ licensed dental hygienists and expanded function dental hygienists.</para><para>(2) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the performance of duties by licensed dental hygienists and expanded function dental hygienists. The rules and regulations shall include the degree of supervision which must be provided by a licensed dentist and the education and proof of competency requirements that must be met for any procedures performed by a licensed dental hygienist or an expanded function dental hygienist.</para><para>(3) No person shall practice dental hygiene in this state unless he or she holds a license as a licensed dental hygienist under the Dentistry Practice Act.</para><para>(4) No person shall practice expanded function dental hygiene in this state unless he or she holds a permit as an expanded function dental hygienist under the act.</para><para>(5) A licensed dentist shall only delegate duties to a licensed dental hygienist or an expanded function dental hygienist in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Dentistry Practice Act. The licensed dentist supervising a licensed dental hygienist or an expanded function dental hygienist shall be responsible for patient care for each patient regardless of whether the patient care is rendered personally by the dentist or by a licensed dental hygienist or an expanded function dental hygienist.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 587, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 414; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 800, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 74; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-193.14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 469; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB18, &#167; 21. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>