<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-10,128"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>38-10,128</statuteno><catchline>Nail technician or instructor; licensure by examination; requirements.</catchline><para>In order to be licensed as a nail technician or nail technology instructor by examination, an individual shall meet, and present to the department evidence of meeting, the following requirements:</para><para>(1) He or she has attained the age of seventeen years on or before the beginning date of the examination for which application is being made;</para><para>(2) He or she has completed formal education equivalent to a United States high school education;</para><para>(3) He or she possesses sufficient ability to read the English language to permit the applicant to practice in a safe manner, as evidenced by successful completion of the written examination; and</para><para>(4) He or she has graduated from a school of cosmetology or nail technology school providing a nail technology program. Evidence of graduation shall include documentation of the total number of hours of training earned and a diploma or certificate from the school to the effect that the applicant has complied with the following:</para><para>(a) For licensure as a nail technician, the program of studies shall consist of three hundred hours; and</para><para>(b) For licensure as a nail technology instructor, the program of studies shall consist of three hundred hours beyond the program of studies required for licensure as a nail technician and the individual shall be currently licensed as a nail technician in Nebraska as evidenced by possession of a valid Nebraska nail technician license.</para><para>The department shall grant a license in the appropriate category to any person meeting the requirements specified in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 68, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-3,183; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 390; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 45. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>