<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1132"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1132</statuteno><catchline>Licensed dental hygienist; activities related to analgesia authorized; administer local anesthesia; when.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A licensed dental hygienist may monitor nitrous oxide analgesia under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist.</para><para>(b) Upon completion of education and testing approved by the board, a licensed dental hygienist may administer and titrate nitrous oxide analgesia under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist.</para><para>(2) A licensed dental hygienist may be approved by the department, with the recommendation of the board, to administer local anesthesia under the indirect supervision of a licensed dentist. The board may prescribe by rule and regulation: The necessary education and preparation, which shall include, but not be limited to, instruction in the areas of head and neck anatomy, osteology, physiology, pharmacology, medical emergencies, and clinical techniques; the necessary clinical experience; and the necessary examination for purposes of determining the competence of licensed dental hygienists to administer local anesthesia. The board may approve successful completion after July 1, 1994, of a course of instruction to determine competence to administer local anesthesia. The course of instruction must be at an accredited school or college of dentistry or an accredited dental hygiene program. The course of instruction must be taught by a faculty member or members of the school or college of dentistry or dental hygiene program presenting the course. The board may approve for purposes of this subsection a course of instruction if such course includes:</para><para>(a) At least twelve clock hours of classroom lecture, including instruction in (i) medical history evaluation procedures, (ii) anatomy of the head, neck, and oral cavity as it relates to administering local anesthetic agents, (iii) pharmacology of local anesthetic agents, vasoconstrictor, and preservatives, including physiologic actions, types of anesthetics, and maximum dose per weight, (iv) systemic conditions which influence selection and administration of anesthetic agents, (v) signs and symptoms of reactions to local anesthetic agents, including monitoring of vital signs, (vi) management of reactions to or complications associated with the administration of local anesthetic agents, (vii) selection and preparation of the armamentaria for administering various local anesthetic agents, and (viii) methods of administering local anesthetic agents;</para><para>(b) At least twelve clock hours of clinical instruction during which time at least three injections of each of the anterior, middle, and posterior superior alveolar, naso and greater palatine, inferior alveolar, lingual, mental, long buccal, and infiltration injections are administered; and</para><para>(c) Procedures, which shall include an examination, for purposes of determining whether the licensed dental hygienist has acquired the necessary knowledge and proficiency to administer local anesthetic agents.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 572, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 449, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 416; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 800, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 37; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-193.18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 329; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 465; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB18, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>