<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-10,109"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-10,109</statuteno><catchline>School licenses; renewal; requirements; inactive status; revocation; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The procedure for renewing a school license shall be in accordance with section 38-143, except that in addition to all other requirements, the school of cosmetology or school of esthetics shall provide evidence of minimal property damage, bodily injury, and liability insurance coverage and shall receive a satisfactory rating on an accreditation inspection conducted by the department within the six months immediately prior to the date of license renewal.</para><para>(2) Any school of cosmetology or school of esthetics which has current accreditation from a national accrediting organization approved by the board shall be considered to satisfy the accreditation requirements outlined in this section, except that successful completion of an operation inspection shall be required. Each school of cosmetology or school of esthetics, whether or not it is nationally accredited, shall satisfy all curriculum and sanitation requirements outlined in the Cosmetology, Electrology, Esthetics, Nail Technology, and Body Art Practice Act to maintain its license.</para><para>(3) Any school not able to meet the requirements for license renewal shall have its license placed on inactive status until all deficiencies have been corrected, and the school shall not operate in any manner during the time its license is inactive. If the deficiencies are not corrected within six months of the date of license renewal, the license may be revoked unless the department approves an extension of the time limit. The license of a school that has been revoked or expired for any reason shall not be reinstated. An original application for licensure shall be submitted and approved before such school may reopen.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 318, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 83, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 241, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 36; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-3,147; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 371.</para></source></law></legaldoc>