<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1621"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1621</statuteno><catchline>Intravenous therapy; performance of activities authorized; limitations; assessment required.</catchline><para>(1) Administration of intravenous therapy shall be a responsibility of the registered nurse as ordered by a licensed practitioner.</para><para>(2) A licensed practical nurse-certified may, under the direction of a licensed practitioner or registered nurse, perform the activities identified in section 38-1613 after the licensed practitioner or registered nurse has performed a physical assessment of the patient.</para><para>(3) A licensed practical nurse-certified shall perform appropriate activities associated with central venous lines only under direct supervision. Activities associated with central venous lines that are appropriate for the licensed practical nurse-certified to perform shall be defined in rules and regulations. A licensed practitioner or registered nurse shall provide direct supervision whenever a licensed practical nurse-certified is performing activities associated with central venous lines.</para><para>(4) A licensed practitioner or registered nurse need not be on the premises in order for the licensed practical nurse-certified to perform directed activities except for (a) initial venipuncture for purposes of peripheral intravenous therapy and (b) central-line activities.</para><para>(5) A licensed practitioner or registered nurse shall be present at least once during each twenty-four-hour interval and more frequently when a significant change in therapy or client condition has occurred to assess the client when the licensed practical nurse-certified is performing the activities identified in section 38-1613.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 213, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1775; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 603.</para></source></law></legaldoc>