<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1116</statuteno><catchline>Dentistry practice; exceptions.</catchline><para>The Dentistry Practice Act shall not require licensure as a dentist under the act for:</para><para>(1) The practice of his or her profession by a physician or surgeon licensed as such under the laws of this state unless he or she practices dentistry as a specialty;</para><para>(2) The giving by a qualified anesthetist or registered nurse of an anesthetic for a dental operation under the direct supervision of a licensed dentist or physician;</para><para>(3) The practice of dentistry by graduate dentists or dental surgeons who serve in the armed forces of the United States or the United States Public Health Service or who are employed by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs or other federal agencies, if their practice is limited to that service or employment;</para><para>(4) The practice of dentistry by a licensed dentist of other states or countries at meetings of the Nebraska Dental Association or components thereof, or other like dental organizations approved by the Board of Dentistry, while appearing as clinicians;</para><para>(5) The filling of work authorizations of a licensed and registered dentist as provided in this subdivision by any person or persons, association, corporation, or other entity for the construction, reproduction, or repair of prosthetic dentures, bridges, plates, or appliances to be used or worn as substitutes for natural teeth if such person or persons, association, corporation, or other entity does not solicit or advertise, directly or indirectly by mail, card, newspaper, pamphlet, radio, or otherwise, to the general public to construct, reproduce, or repair prosthetic dentures, bridges, plates, or other appliances to be used or worn as substitutes for natural teeth;</para><para>(6) The use of roentgen or X-ray machines or other rays for making radiograms or similar records of dental or oral tissues under the supervision of a licensed dentist or physician if such service is not advertised by any name whatever as an aid or inducement to secure dental patronage, and no person shall advertise that he or she has, leases, owns, or operates a roentgen or X-ray machine for the purpose of making dental radiograms of the human teeth or tissues or the oral cavity or administering treatment thereto for any disease thereof;</para><para>(7) The performance by a licensed dental hygienist, under the supervision of a licensed dentist, of the oral prophylaxis procedure which shall include the scaling and polishing of teeth and such additional procedures as are prescribed in accordance with rules and regulations adopted by the department;</para><para>(8) The performance, under the supervision of a licensed dentist, by a dental assistant, a licensed dental assistant, or an expanded function dental assistant, of duties prescribed in accordance with rules and regulations adopted by the department;</para><para>(9) The performance by a licensed dental hygienist or an expanded function dental hygienist, by virtue of training and professional ability, under the supervision of a licensed dentist, of taking dental roentgenograms. Any other person is hereby authorized, under the supervision of a licensed dentist, to take dental roentgenograms but shall not be authorized to do so until he or she has satisfactorily completed a course in dental radiology recommended by the board and approved by the department;</para><para>(10) Students of dentistry who practice dentistry upon patients in clinics in the regular course of instruction at an accredited school or college of dentistry;</para><para>(11) Licensed physicians and surgeons who extract teeth or treat diseases of the oral cavity, gums, teeth, or maxillary bones as an incident to the general practice of their profession;</para><para>(12) Dental hygiene students who practice dental hygiene or expanded function dental hygiene upon patients in clinics in the regular course of instruction at an accredited dental hygiene program. Such dental hygiene students are also not engaged in the unauthorized practice of dental hygiene or expanded function dental hygiene; or</para><para>(13) Dental assisting students who practice dental assisting or expanded function dental assisting upon patients in clinics in the regular course of instruction at an accredited dental assisting program. Such dental assisting students are also not engaged in the unauthorized practice of dental assisting, expanded function dental assisting, dental hygiene, or expanded function dental hygiene.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 226, &#167; 2, p. 823; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 227, &#167; 2, p. 827; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 587, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 470, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 2, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 407; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 800, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 89, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-183.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 449; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB18, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>