<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id308">
<sectno id="id309" opdate=" ">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id310" statutenumber="38-1217"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id312">38-1217</statuteno><catchline id="id313">Rules and regulations.</catchline>
<para>The board shall adopt rules and regulations necessary to:</para>
<para>(1)(a) For licenses issued prior to September
1, 2010, create the following licensure classifications of out-of-hospital
emergency care providers: (i) First responder; (ii) emergency medical technician; (iii) emergency medical technician-intermediate;
and (iv) emergency medical technician-paramedic; and (b) for licenses issued on or after
September 1, 2010, create the following licensure classifications of out-of-hospital
emergency care providers: (i) Emergency medical responder; (ii) emergency
medical technician; (iii) advanced emergency medical technician; and (iv)
paramedic. The rules and regulations creating the classifications
shall include the practices and procedures authorized for each classification,
training and testing requirements, renewal and reinstatement requirements,
and other criteria and qualifications for each classification determined to
be necessary for protection of public health and safety. A person holding a license issued prior to September 1,
2010, shall be authorized to practice in accordance with the laws, rules,
and regulations governing the license for the term of the license;</para>
<para>(2) Provide
for temporary licensure of an out-of-hospital emergency care provider who
has completed the educational requirements for a licensure classification
enumerated in subdivision (1)(b) of this section but has not completed the
testing requirements for licensure under such subdivision. Temporary licensure
shall be valid for one year or until a license is issued under such subdivision
and shall not be subject to renewal. The rules and regulations shall include
qualifications and training necessary for issuance of a temporary license,
the practices and procedures authorized for a temporary licensee, and supervision
required for a temporary licensee;</para><para>(3) Set standards for the licensure of basic
life support services and advanced life support services. The rules and regulations
providing for licensure shall include standards and requirements for: Vehicles,
equipment, maintenance, sanitation, inspections, personnel, training, medical
direction, records maintenance, practices and procedures to be provided by
employees or members of each classification of service, and other criteria
for licensure established by the board;</para>
<para>(4) Authorize emergency medical
services to provide differing practices and procedures depending upon the
qualifications of out-of-hospital emergency care providers available at the
time of service delivery. No emergency medical service shall be licensed to
provide practices or procedures without the use of personnel licensed to provide
the practices or procedures;</para>
<para>(5) Authorize out-of-hospital
emergency care providers to perform any practice or procedure which they are
authorized to perform with an emergency medical service other than the service
with which they are affiliated when requested by the other service and when
the patient for whom they are to render services is in danger of loss of life;</para>
<para>(6) Provide for the approval
of training agencies and establish minimum standards for services provided
by training agencies;</para>
<para>(7) Provide for the minimum
qualifications of a physician medical director in addition to the licensure
required by section 38-1212;</para>
<para>(8) Provide for the use of
physician medical directors, qualified physician surrogates, model protocols,
standing orders, operating procedures, and guidelines which may be necessary
or appropriate to carry out the purposes of the Emergency Medical Services
Practice Act. The model protocols, standing orders, operating procedures,
and guidelines may be modified by the physician medical director for use by
any out-of-hospital emergency care provider or emergency medical service before
or after adoption;</para>
<para>(9) Establish criteria for
approval of organizations issuing cardiopulmonary resuscitation certification
which shall include criteria for instructors, establishment of certification
periods and minimum curricula, and other aspects of training and certification;</para>
<para>(10) Establish renewal and
reinstatement requirements for out-of-hospital emergency care providers and
emergency medical services and establish continuing competency requirements.
Continuing education is sufficient to meet continuing competency requirements.
The requirements may also include, but not be limited to, one or more of the
continuing competency activities listed in section 38-145 which a licensed
person may select as an alternative to continuing education. The reinstatement
requirements for out-of-hospital emergency care providers shall allow reinstatement
at the same or any lower level of licensure for which the out-of-hospital
emergency care provider is determined to be qualified;</para>
<para>(11) Establish criteria for
deployment and use of automated external defibrillators as necessary for the
protection of the public health and safety;</para>
<para>(12) Create licensure, renewal,
and reinstatement requirements for emergency medical service instructors.
The rules and regulations shall include the practices and procedures for licensure,
renewal, and reinstatement;</para>
<para>(13) Establish criteria for
emergency medical technicians-intermediate,
advanced emergency medical technicians, emergency medical technicians-paramedic, or paramedics performing
activities within their scope of practice at a hospital or health clinic under
subsection (3) of section 38-1224. Such criteria shall include, but not be
limited to: (a) Requirements for the orientation of registered nurses, physician
assistants, and physicians involved in the supervision of such personnel;
(b) supervisory and training requirements for the physician medical director
or other person in charge of the medical staff at such hospital or health
clinic; and (c) a requirement that such activities shall only be performed
at the discretion of, and with the approval of, the governing authority of
such hospital or health clinic. For purposes of this subdivision, health clinic
has the definition found in section 71-416 and hospital has the definition
found in section 71-419; and</para>
<para>(14) Establish
criteria and requirements for emergency medical technicians-intermediate to
renew licenses issued prior to September 1, 2010, and continue to practice
after such classification has otherwise terminated under subdivision (1) of
this section. The rules and regulations shall include the qualifications necessary
to renew emergency medical technicians-intermediate licenses after September
1, 2010, the practices and procedures authorized for persons holding and renewing
such licenses, and the renewal and reinstatement requirements for holders
of such licenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 498, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 238, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1033, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-5178; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 501; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>