<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id113"><sectno id="id114" opdate="December 1, 2008">Sec. 11.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id115" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="38-1917.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1917.01</statuteno><catchline>Limited computed tomography radiographer; requirements; nuclear medicine technologist; activities authorized.</catchline><para>(1) A person licensed by the department, with the recommendation of the board, as a limited computed tomography radiographer may practice medical radiography restricted to computed tomography. An applicant for a license as a limited computed tomography radiographer shall:</para><para>(a) Complete an application in accordance with the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para><para>(b) Be certified by (i) the Nuclear Medicine Technology Certification Board or (ii) the American Registry of Radiologic Technologists in nuclear medicine technology; and</para><para>(c) Be certified by the American Registry of Radiologic Technologists in computed tomography.</para><para>(2) A nuclear medicine technologist may perform computed tomography without being licensed under the Medical Radiography Practice Act if such practice is limited to X-rays produced by a combination nuclear medicine-computed tomography system and administered as an integral part of a nuclear medicine procedure that uses a computed tomography protocol for purposes of attenuation correction and anatomical localization only and if the nuclear medicine technologist has received documented device-specific training on the combination nuclear medicine-computed tomography system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>
