<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1081"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1081</statuteno><catchline>Body art facility; operating requirements.</catchline><para>(1) In order to maintain a license in good standing, each body art facility or the owner of such facility or his or her agent shall:</para><para>(a) At all times comply with all applicable provisions of the Cosmetology, Electrology, Esthetics, Nail Technology, and Body Art Practice Act and all rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under such act;</para><para>(b) Notify the department at least thirty days prior to any change of ownership, name, or address, and within one week after a facility is permanently closed, except in emergency circumstances as determined by the department;</para><para>(c) Permit any duly authorized agent of the department to conduct an operation inspection or investigation at any time during normal operating hours, without prior notice, and the owner and manager shall assist the inspector by providing access to all areas, personnel, and records requested by the inspector; and</para><para>(d) Display in a conspicuous place near the place where body art is performed the following records:</para><para>(i) The then current license to operate the body art facility;</para><para>(ii) The then current license of each person performing body art; and</para><para>(iii) The inspection report from the most recent operation inspection.</para><para>(2) The owner of each body art facility shall have full responsibility for ensuring that the facility is operated in compliance with all applicable laws, rules, and regulations and shall be liable for any and all violations occurring in the facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 906, &#167; 27; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-3,119.03; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 343.</para></source></law></legaldoc>