<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-10,170"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-10,170</statuteno><catchline>Inspection; unsatisfactory rating; effect.</catchline><para>If a cosmetology establishment, a nail technology establishment, or a body art facility receives a rating of unsatisfactory, it shall submit evidence to the department within fifteen days providing proof of corrective action taken. A repeat inspection shall be conducted within sixty days after the original inspection to determine if corrective action has occurred. The department may assess a fee for each repeat inspection required. If the establishment or facility receives an unsatisfactory rating on the repeat inspection, the establishment shall be fined as determined by the department by rule and regulation. If the establishment or facility receives an unsatisfactory rating after the second unsatisfactory inspection or fails to pay the fine assessed within thirty days after notice, the license shall immediately be placed on inactive status pending action by the department, and the establishment or facility may not operate in any manner while its license is inactive.</para><para>The owner or manager of an establishment or a facility whose license has been placed on inactive status may appear before the board and the department to show cause why the department should not ask the Attorney General to initiate steps to revoke the license. The department may, as a result of such appearance, grant additional time for corrective action to occur, but the establishment or facility may not operate during such time. The establishment or facility may not return to operation until it has achieved a satisfactory rating on an inspection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 318, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 68, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 906, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-3,170; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 432.</para></source></law></legaldoc>