<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id843"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-1810.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1810.03</statuteno><catchline>Qualified supervisor, defined; qualifications; licensure; required, when.</catchline><para>(1) Qualified supervisor means:</para><para>(a) When supervising the provision of medical nutrition therapy by a person who is completing post-degree clinical practice experience, a person who either:</para><para>(i) Is a licensed dietitian nutritionist, a licensed nutritionist, or a health care provider licensed in any state or territory, including licensed or certified dietitian nutritionists and licensed nutritionists, whose scope of practice includes the provision of medical nutrition therapy; or</para><para>(ii) In the case of a person in a state that does not provide for such licensure or certification, meets such other criteria as the board may establish, including by a registered dietitian nutritionist or a certified nutrition specialist, or is a health care provider authorized in another state or territory to provide medical nutrition therapy; and</para><para>(b) When supervising the provision of nutrition-care services that does not constitute medical nutrition therapy, a person who:</para><para>(i) Meets the qualifications of subdivision (1)(a) of this section; or</para><para>(ii) Has worked in the field of clinical nutrition for at least three of the last five years immediately preceding commencement of the applicant's supervised practice experience and holds a master's or doctoral degree with a major course of study in dietetics, human nutrition, foods and nutrition, clinical nutrition, applied clinical nutrition, community nutrition, public health nutrition, naturopathic medicine, nutrition education, nutrition counseling, nutrition science, nutrition and functional medicine, nutritional biochemistry, or nutrition and integrative health, or an equivalent course of study as approved by the board.</para><para>(2) In order to qualify as a qualified supervisor in Nebraska, a supervisor obtaining a doctoral degree outside the United States or its territories shall have such degree validated by the board as equivalent to the doctoral degree conferred by an accredited college or university in the United States or its territories.</para><para>(3) A qualified supervisor shall be licensed under the Uniform Credentialing Act to provide medical nutrition therapy if supervising an applicant providing medical nutrition therapy to a person in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 38. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>