<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-1080"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-1080</statuteno><catchline>Body art facility; license required; renewal.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall establish or operate a body art facility in this state unless such facility is licensed by the department under the Cosmetology, Electrology, Esthetics, Nail Technology, and Body Art Practice Act. The department shall not issue or renew a license for a body art facility until all applicable requirements of the act have been complied with and the facility has been inspected by the department. No person shall engage in any of the practices of body art in any location or premises other than a licensed body art facility except as specifically permitted in the act. The department shall issue a license to operate a body art facility to each qualified applicant.</para><para>(2) The procedure for renewing a body art facility license shall be in accordance with section 38-143, except that in addition to all other requirements, no body art facility license may be renewed unless the facility has attained a rating of satisfactory on its most recent operation inspection. The license of any facility not attaining such rating shall be placed on inactive status and shall not be open to the public until all deficiencies have been corrected.</para><para>(3) The license of a body art facility that has been revoked for any reason shall not be reinstated. An original application for licensure shall be submitted and approved before such facility can reopen for business.</para><para>(4) Each body art facility license shall be in effect solely for the owner or owners and premises named thereon and shall expire automatically upon any change of ownership or location. An original application for licensure shall be submitted and approved before such facility may reopen for business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 906, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-3,119.02; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 342.</para></source></law></legaldoc>