<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions"  statutenumber="38-2927"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2927</statuteno><catchline>Physical therapist assistant; perform physical therapy services; when; limitations; supervising physical therapist; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) A physical therapist assistant may perform physical therapy services under the general supervision of a physical therapist, except that no physical therapist assistant shall perform the following:</para><para>(a) Interpretation of physician referrals;</para><para>(b) Development of a plan of care;</para><para>(c) Initial evaluations or reevaluation of patients;</para><para>(d) Readjustment of a plan of care without consultation with the supervising physical therapist; or</para><para>(e) Discharge planning for patients. </para><para>(2) A physical therapist may provide general supervision for no more than two physical therapist assistants. A physical therapist shall not establish a satellite office at which a physical therapist assistant provides care without the general supervision of the physical therapist.</para><para>(3) A physical therapist shall reevaluate or reexamine on a regular basis each patient receiving physical therapy services from a physical therapist assistant under the general supervision of the physical therapist.</para><para>(4) A supervising physical therapist and the physical therapist assistant under general supervision shall review the plan of care on a regular basis for each patient receiving physical therapy services from the physical therapist assistant.</para><para>(5) A physical therapist assistant may document physical therapy services provided by the physical therapist assistant without the signature of the supervising physical therapist.</para><para>(6) A physical therapist assistant may act as a clinical instructor for physical therapist assistant students in an approved educational program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 355, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-2810; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 141; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,385; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1020.</para></source></law></legaldoc>