<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id26">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id28" statutenumber="38-2420"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2420</statuteno><catchline id="id31">Administrator-in-training
program; mentoring program; certified preceptor; requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in subdivision (1)(a)(iv) of section
38-2419 and section 38-2426,
in order for a person to become licensed as a nursing home administrator,
he or she shall complete an administrator-in-training program or a mentoring
program. The administrator-in-training program shall occur in a nursing home
under the direct supervision of a certified preceptor, and it may be gained
as an internship which is part of an approved associate degree. A mentoring
program shall occur in a nursing home under the supervision of a certified
preceptor. The certified preceptor in a mentoring program need not be at such
facility during the period of such supervision but shall be available to assist
with questions or problems as needed. A mentoring program may be gained as
an internship which is part of a degree or advanced degree. A person in a
mentoring program may apply for a provisional license as provided in section
38-2423.</para>
<para>(2) An applicant may begin his or her administrator-in-training
or mentoring program upon application to the department with the required
fee, evidence that he or she has completed at least fifty percent of the core
educational requirements, and evidence of an agreement between the certified
preceptor and the applicant for at least six hundred forty hours of training
and experience, to be gained in not less than four months. Such training shall
occur in a Nebraska-licensed nursing home under a certified preceptor.</para>
<para>(3) The certified preceptor shall submit a report to the department
by the fifth day of each month for the duration of the administrator-in-training
or mentoring program, describing the nature and extent of training completed
to date. At the conclusion of the program, the certified preceptor shall report
to the department whether the applicant has successfully completed the board's
approved course for such program. With the concurrence of the certified preceptor,
the applicant may remain in such program until successfully completed or may
reapply to enter another administrator-in-training or mentoring program.</para>
<para>(4)(a) The administrator-in-training or mentoring program
shall occur under the supervision of a certified preceptor. An applicant to
become a certified preceptor shall (i) be currently licensed as a nursing
home administrator in the State of Nebraska, (ii) have three years of experience
as a nursing home administrator in the five years immediately preceding certification,
and (iii) complete a preceptor training course approved by the board.</para>
<para>(b) All preceptor certificates shall expire on December 31
of every fourth year beginning December 31, 2000. Before acting on an application
for renewal, the board shall review the performance of the applicant. Such
review may include consideration of survey and complaint information, student
evaluations, and any other related information deemed relevant by the board.
The board may deny an application for renewal upon a finding that the applicant's
performance has been unsatisfactory based on such review.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 693, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 733, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1989, &#167; 71-2041.03; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 455, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 411, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 134; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-6055; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 835; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB42, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>