<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2518"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2518</statuteno><catchline>Occupational therapist; license; application; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant applying for a license as an occupational therapist shall show to the satisfaction of the department that he or she:</para><para>(a) Has successfully completed the academic requirements of an educational program in occupational therapy recognized by the department and accredited by a nationally recognized medical association or nationally recognized occupational therapy association;</para><para>(b) Has successfully completed a period of supervised fieldwork experience at an educational institution approved by the department and where the applicant's academic work was completed or which is part of a training program approved by such educational institution. A minimum of six months of supervised fieldwork experience shall be required for an occupational therapist; and</para><para>(c) Has passed an examination as provided in section 38-2520.</para><para>(2) Residency in this state shall not be a requirement of licensure. A corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or association shall not be licensed as an occupational therapist pursuant to the Occupational Therapy Practice Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 761, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 344, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 452; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 194; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 139; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-6106; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 858.</para></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>