<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id737">
<sectno id="id738" opdate=" ">Sec. 50.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id739" statutenumber="38-2871"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id741">38-2871</statuteno><catchline id="id742">Prescription
information; transfer; requirements.</catchline><para>Original
prescription information for any controlled substances listed in Schedule
III, IV, or V of section 28-405 and other prescription drugs or devices not
listed in section 28-405 may be transferred between pharmacies for the purpose
of refill dispensing on a one-time basis, except that pharmacies electronically
accessing a real-time, on-line data base may transfer up to the maximum refills
permitted by law and as authorized by the prescribing practitioner on the prescription.
Transfers are subject to the following:</para>
<para>(1) The transfer is communicated directly between two pharmacists
or pharmacist interns except when the pharmacies can use a real-time, on-line
data base;</para>
<para>(2) The transferring pharmacist or pharmacist intern indicates
void on the record of the prescription;</para>
<para>(3) The transferring pharmacist or pharmacist intern indicates
on the record of the prescription the name, the address, and, if a controlled
substance, the Drug Enforcement Administration number of the pharmacy to which
the information was transferred, the name of the pharmacist or pharmacist
intern receiving the information, the date of transfer, and the name of the
transferring pharmacist or pharmacist intern;</para>
<para>(4) The receiving pharmacist or pharmacist intern indicates
on the record of the transferred prescription that the prescription is transferred;</para>
<para>(5) The transferred prescription includes the following information:</para>
<para>(a) The date of issuance of the original prescription;</para>
<para>(b) The original number of refills authorized;</para>
<para>(c) The date of original dispensing;</para>
<para>(d) The number of valid refills remaining;</para>
<para>(e) The date and location of last refill; and</para>
<para>(f) The name, the address, and, if a controlled substance,
the Drug Enforcement Administration number of the pharmacy from which the
transfer was made, the name of the pharmacist or pharmacist intern transferring
the information, the original prescription number, and the date of transfer;
and</para>
<para>(6) Both the original and transferred prescriptions must
be maintained by the transferring and receiving pharmacy for a period of five
years from the date of transfer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 36; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,146.02; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 967; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 50.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
