<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2119"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2119</statuteno><catchline>Social work practice or the practice of social work, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Social work practice or the practice of social work means the professional activity of helping individuals, groups, and families or larger systems such as organizations and communities to improve, restore, or enhance their capacities for personal and social functioning and the professional application of social work values, knowledge, principles, and methods in the following areas of practice:</para><para>(a) Information, resource identification and development, and referral services;</para><para>(b) Preparation and evaluation of psychosocial assessments and development of social work service plans;</para><para>(c) Case management, coordination, and monitoring of social work service plans in the areas of personal, social, or economic resources, conditions, or problems;</para><para>(d) Development, implementation, and evaluation of social work programs and policies;</para><para>(e) Supportive contacts to assist individuals and groups with personal adjustment to crisis, transition, economic change, or a personal or family member's health condition, especially in the area of services given in hospitals, health clinics, home health agencies, schools, shelters for the homeless, shelters for the urgent care of victims of sexual assault, child abuse, elder abuse, or domestic violence, nursing homes, and correctional facilities. Nothing in this subdivision shall be construed to prevent charitable and religious organizations, the clergy, governmental agencies, hospitals, health clinics, home health agencies, schools, shelters for the homeless, shelters for the urgent care of victims of sexual assault, child abuse, elder abuse, or domestic violence, nursing homes, or correctional facilities from providing supportive contacts to assist individuals and groups with adjustment to crisis, transition, economic change, or personal or a family member's health condition if such persons or organizations do not represent themselves to be social workers;</para><para>(f) Social casework for and prevention of psychosocial dysfunction, disability, or impairment; and</para><para>(g) Social work research, consultation, and education.</para><para>(2) Social work practice does not include the following:</para><para>(a) The measuring and testing of personality or intelligence;</para><para>(b) Accepting fees or compensation for the treatment of disease, injury, or deformity of persons by drugs, surgery, or any manual or mechanical treatment whatsoever;</para><para>(c) Prescribing drugs or electroconvulsive therapy; and</para><para>(d) Treating organic diseases or major psychiatric diseases.</para><para>(3) A certified master social worker who practices within the confines of this section shall not be required to be licensed as a mental health practitioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 286, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 71-1,248; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 669, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 98; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,311; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 737.</para></source></law></legaldoc>