<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id6" statutenumber="38-2854"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2854</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Pharmacist intern;
qualifications; registration; powers.</catchline><para>(1) A pharmacist
intern shall be (a) a student currently enrolled in an accredited pharmacy
program, (b) a graduate of an accredited pharmacy program serving his or her
internship, or (c) a graduate of a pharmacy program located outside the United
States which is not accredited and who has successfully passed equivalency
examinations approved by the board. Intern registration based on enrollment
in or graduation from an accredited pharmacy program shall expire not later
than fifteen months after the date of graduation or at the time of professional
licensure, whichever comes first. Intern registration based on graduation
from a pharmacy program located outside of the United States which is not
accredited shall expire not later than fifteen months after the date of issuance
of the registration or at the time of professional licensure, whichever comes
first.</para>
<para>(2) A pharmacist intern may compound and dispense drugs or
devices and fill prescriptions only in the presence of and under the immediate
personal supervision of a licensed pharmacist. Such licensed pharmacist shall
either be (a) the person to whom the pharmacy license is issued or a person
in the actual employ of the pharmacy licensee or (b) the delegating pharmacist
designated in a delegated dispensing agreement by a hospital with a delegated
dispensing permit.</para>
<para>(3) Performance
as a pharmacist intern under the supervision of a licensed pharmacist shall
be predominantly related to the practice of pharmacy and shall include the
keeping of records and the making of reports required under state and federal
statutes. The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall adopt
and promulgate rules and regulations as may be required to establish standards
for internship.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 14; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,144; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 950; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB179, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>