<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2225"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2225</statuteno><catchline>Nursing; temporary license; issuance; conditions; how long valid; extension.</catchline><para>(1) A temporary license to practice nursing may be issued to:</para><para>(a) An individual seeking to obtain licensure or reinstatement of his or her license as a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse when he or she has not practiced nursing in the last five years. A temporary license issued under this subdivision is valid only for the duration of the review course of study and only for nursing practice required for the review course of study;</para><para>(b) Graduates of approved programs of nursing who have passed the licensure examination, pending the completion of application for Nebraska licensure as a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse. A temporary license issued under this subdivision is valid for a period not to exceed sixty days;</para><para>(c) Nurses currently licensed in another state as either a registered nurse or a licensed practical nurse who have graduated from an educational program approved by the board, pending completion of application for Nebraska licensure as a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse. A temporary license issued under this subdivision shall be valid for a period not to exceed sixty days; or</para><para>(d) Military spouses as provided in section 38-129.01.</para><para>(2) A temporary license issued pursuant to subdivision (1)(a), (b), or (c) of this section may be extended by the department, with the recommendation of the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 245, &#167; 8(3), p. 841; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 422, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 847, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 563, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 24; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,132.16; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 781; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 73. </para></source><annotation><para>The Board of Nursing has power to deny a license upon proof applicant is guilty of unprofessional conduct, and upon review de novo district court may not substitute its own judgment on that issue. Scott v. State ex rel. Board of Nursing, 196 Neb. 681, 244 N.W.2d 683 (1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>