<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<sectno id="id11" opdate="January 1, 2010">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id12" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="38-2062"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2062</statuteno><catchline>Anatomic pathology service; unprofessional
conduct.</catchline><para>(1)
It shall be unprofessional conduct for any physician who orders but does not
supervise or perform a component of an anatomic pathology service to fail
to disclose in any bill for such service presented to a patient, entity, or
person:</para>
<para>(a) The name
and address of the physician or laboratory that provided the anatomic service;
and</para><para>(b) The actual amount paid or to be paid for each anatomic pathology
service provided to the patient by the physician or laboratory that performed
the service.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, anatomic pathology service means:</para><para>(a) Blood-banking services performed by pathologists;</para>
<para>(b) Cytopathology,
which means the microscopic examination of cells from the following: Fluids;
aspirates; washings; brushings; or smears, including the Pap test examination
performed by a physician or under the supervision of a physician;</para>
<para>(c) Hematology,
which means the microscopic evaluation of bone marrow aspirates and biopsies
performed by a physician or under the supervision of a physician and peripheral
blood smears when the attending or treating physician or technologist requests
that a blood smear be reviewed by the pathologist;</para><para>(d) Histopathology or surgical pathology,
which means the gross and microscopic examination and histologic processing
of organ tissue performed by a physician or under the supervision of a physician;
and</para><para>(e) Subcellular pathology and molecular pathology.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes
of this section, anatomic pathology service does not include the initial collection
or packaging of the specimen for transport.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB394, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>