<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id133">
<sectno id="id134" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 11.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id135" statutenumber="38-2867"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id137">38-2867</statuteno><catchline id="id138">Pharmacy; scope
of practice; prohibited acts; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as provided for pharmacy technicians in sections 38-2890 to 38-2897,
for persons described in subdivision (12) or
(13) of section 38-2850, and for individuals authorized to dispense
under a delegated dispensing permit, no person other than a licensed pharmacist,
a pharmacist intern, or a practitioner with a pharmacy license shall provide
pharmaceutical care, compound and dispense drugs or devices, or dispense pursuant
to a medical order. Notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary,
a pharmacist or pharmacist intern may dispense drugs or devices pursuant to
a medical order of a practitioner authorized to prescribe in another state
if such practitioner could be authorized to prescribe such drugs or devices
in this state.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided for pharmacy technicians in sections
38-2890 to 38-2897, for persons described in subdivision (12) or (13) of section 38-2850, and for individuals
authorized to dispense under a delegated dispensing permit, it shall be unlawful
for any person to permit or direct a person who is not a pharmacist intern,
a licensed pharmacist, or a practitioner with a pharmacy license to provide
pharmaceutical care, compound and dispense drugs or devices, or dispense pursuant
to a medical order.</para>
<para>(3) It shall be unlawful for any person to coerce or attempt
to coerce a pharmacist to enter into a delegated dispensing agreement or to
supervise any pharmacy technician for any purpose or in any manner contrary
to the professional judgment of the pharmacist. Violation of this subsection
by a health care professional regulated pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing
Act shall be considered an act of unprofessional conduct. A violation of this
subsection by a facility shall be prima facie evidence in an action against
the license of the facility pursuant to the Health Care Facility Licensure
Act. Any pharmacist subjected to coercion or attempted coercion pursuant to
this subsection has a cause of action against the person and may recover his
or her damages and reasonable attorney's fees.</para>
<para>(4) Violation of this section by an unlicensed person shall
be a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 127, p. 493; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1808; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1,147; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 339, &#167; 3, p. 1063; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 350, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 476, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 900, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 34; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,147; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 963; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB604, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 11.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>