<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id37">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id39" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="38-2426"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2426</statuteno><catchline>Administrator of facility operated
primarily for caring for persons with head injuries and associated disorders;
license required; qualifications; renewal.</catchline><para>(1) In order to qualify to function as the
administrator of a facility operated primarily for caring for persons with
head injuries and associated disorders, an individual shall be licensed as
a nursing home administrator if he or she meets the requirements of this section.
A license issued under this section permits the holder to serve as a nursing
home administrator only in a facility operated primarily for caring for persons
with head injuries and associated disorders.</para>
<para>(2) To receive
a credential to practice nursing home administration for a facility operated
primarily for caring for persons with head injuries and associated disorders,
an individual shall:</para><para>(a) Have at least four years of experience working with persons
with head injuries or severe physical disabilities, at least two of which
were spent in an administrative capacity; and</para><para>(b) Either:</para>
<para>(i) Hold a credential
as:</para><para>(A)
A psychologist pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act, with at least a
master's degree in psychology from an accredited college or university;</para>
<para>(B) A physician
licensed pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act to practice medicine and
surgery or psychiatry;</para><para>(C) An educator with at least a master's degree in education from
an accredited college or university;</para><para>(D) A certified social worker, a certified
master social worker, or a licensed mental health practitioner pursuant to
the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para><para>(E) A physical therapist, an occupational
therapist, or a speech-language pathologist pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing
Act; or</para><para>(F)
An administrator or executive of a health care facility as defined in section
71-413 who is a member in good standing with an organization that offers voluntary
certification for the purpose of demonstrating managerial knowledge and experience
for health care managers; or</para><para>(ii) Have at least eight years of experience working with persons
with head injuries or severe physical disabilities, at least five of which
were spent in an administrative capacity in a facility operated primarily
for caring for persons with head injuries or severe physical disabilities.</para>
<para>(3)
A license issued pursuant to this section shall be issued without examination
and without the requirement of completion of an administrator-in-training
or mentoring program. Such license may be renewed without the completion of
any continuing competency requirements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB42, &#167; 7.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>