<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2882"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2882</statuteno><catchline>Delegated dispensing permit; delegating pharmacist; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Each delegated dispensing permittee shall have an actively practicing Nebraska-licensed pharmacist listed as the delegating pharmacist in the delegated dispensing agreement. The delegating pharmacist shall be responsible for all activities set forth in his or her delegated dispensing agreement. The delegating pharmacist shall approve and maintain a policy and procedure manual governing those aspects of the practice of pharmacy covered by the delegated dispensing agreement.</para><para>(2) The delegating pharmacist for a public health clinic or a dialysis drug or device distributor shall be physically in the clinic or distributor's facility at least once every thirty days. The delegating pharmacist shall conduct and document monthly inspections of all activities and responsibilities listed in subsection (3) of this section and under his or her delegated dispensing agreement.</para><para>(3) The delegating pharmacist for a public health clinic shall be responsible for the security, environment, inventory, and record keeping of all drugs and devices received, stored, or dispensed by the public health clinic. The delegating pharmacist for a dialysis drug or device distributor shall be responsible for the distribution, record keeping, labeling, and delivery of all drugs and devices dispensed by the dialysis drug or device distributor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 900, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 57; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,147.50; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 978.</para></source></law></legaldoc>