<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id22" statutenumber="38-2605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2605</statuteno><catchline id="id25">Practice of optometry,
defined.</catchline><para>(1) The practice of optometry means one
or a combination of the following:</para>
<para>(a) The examination of the human eye to diagnose, treat, or
refer for consultation or treatment any abnormal condition of the human eye,
ocular adnexa, or visual system;</para>
<para>(b) The employment of instruments, devices, pharmaceutical
agents, and procedures intended for the purpose of investigating, examining,
diagnosing, treating, managing, or correcting visual defects or abnormal conditions
of the human eye, ocular adnexa, or visual system;</para>
<para>(c) The prescribing and application of lenses, devices containing
lenses, prisms, contact lenses, ophthalmic devices, orthoptics, vision training,
pharmaceutical agents, and prosthetic devices to correct, relieve, or treat
defects or abnormal conditions of the human eye, ocular adnexa, or visual
system;</para>
<para>(d) The dispensing and sale of a contact lens, including a
cosmetic or plano contact lens or a contact lens containing an ocular pharmaceutical
agent which an optometrist is authorized by law to prescribe and which is
classified by the federal Food and Drug Administration as a drug;</para>
<para>(e) The ordering of procedures and laboratory tests rational
to the diagnosis or treatment of conditions or diseases of the human eye,
ocular adnexa, or visual system; and</para>
<para>(f) The removal of superficial eyelid, conjunctival, and corneal
foreign bodies.</para>
<para>(2) The practice of optometry does not include the use of
surgery, the use of laser
surgery, or the treatment of infantile/congenital glaucoma, which
means the condition is present at birth.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 111, p. 487; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1,133; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 9, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 116, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 429, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 369, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,133; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 877; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB526, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>