<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2026"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2026</statuteno><catchline>Medicine and surgery; license; qualifications; foreign medical graduates; requirements.</catchline><para>Except as otherwise provided in sections 38-2026.01 and 38-2027, each applicant for a license to practice medicine and surgery shall:</para><para>(1)(a) Present proof that he or she is a graduate of an accredited school or college of medicine, (b) if a foreign medical graduate, provide a copy of a permanent certificate issued by the Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates that is currently effective and relates to such applicant or provide such credentials as are necessary to certify that such foreign medical graduate has successfully passed the Visa Qualifying Examination or its successor or equivalent examination required by the United States Department of Health and Human Services and the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services, or (c) if a graduate of a foreign medical school who has successfully completed a program of American medical training designated as the Fifth Pathway and who additionally has successfully passed the Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates examination but has not yet received the permanent certificate attesting to the same, provide such credentials as certify the same to the Division of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(2) Present proof that he or she has served at least one year of graduate medical education approved by the board or, if a foreign medical graduate, present proof that he or she has served at least two years of graduate medical education approved by the board;</para><para>(3) Pass a licensing examination approved by the board covering appropriate medical subjects; and</para><para>(4) Present proof satisfactory to the department that he or she, within the three years immediately preceding the application for licensure, (a) has been in the active practice of the profession of medicine and surgery in some other state, a territory, the District of Columbia, or Canada for a period of one year, (b) has had at least one year of graduate medical education as described in subdivision (2) of this section, (c) has completed continuing education in medicine and surgery approved by the board, (d) has completed a refresher course in medicine and surgery approved by the board, or (e) has completed the special purposes examination approved by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 102, p. 483; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1403; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 150, &#167; 20, p. 548; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1,104; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 408, &#167; 6, p. 1312; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 563, &#167; 3, p. 2293; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 150, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 92, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 877, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 761, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 250, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 390, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1064, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 400, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 421; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,104; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 332; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 684; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB406, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1034, &#167; 31. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The practice of chiropractic and the practice of medicine are distinct professions with different licensing requirements. Nelsen v. Grzywa, 9 Neb. App. 702, 618 N.W.2d 472 (2000).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>