<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="PUBLIC HEALTH AND WELFARE" id="id115" statutenumber="38-2850"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2850</statuteno><catchline id="id118">Pharmacy; practice; persons excepted.</catchline><para>As authorized by the Uniform Credentialing Act, the practice of pharmacy may be engaged in by a pharmacist, a pharmacist intern, or a practitioner with a pharmacy license. The practice of pharmacy shall not be construed to include:</para><para>(1) Practitioners, other than veterinarians, certified nurse midwives, certified registered nurse anesthetists, nurse practitioners, and physician assistants, who dispense drugs or devices as an incident to the practice of their profession, except that if such practitioner engages in dispensing such drugs or devices to his or her patients for which such patients are charged, such practitioner shall obtain a pharmacy license;</para><para>(2) Persons who sell, offer, or expose for sale nonprescription drugs or proprietary medicines, the sale of which is not in itself a violation of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act;</para><para>(3) Medical representatives, detail persons, or persons known by some name of like import, but only to the extent of permitting the relating of pharmaceutical information to health care professionals;</para><para>(4) Licensed veterinarians practicing within the scope of their profession;</para><para>(5) Certified nurse midwives, certified registered nurse anesthetists, nurse practitioners, and physician assistants who dispense sample medications which are provided by the manufacturer and are dispensed at no charge to the patient;</para><para>(6) Optometrists who prescribe or dispense eyeglasses or contact lenses to their own patients, including contact lenses that contain and deliver ocular pharmaceutical agents as authorized under the Optometry Practice Act, and ophthalmologists who prescribe or dispense eyeglasses or contact lenses to their own patients, including contact lenses that contain and deliver ocular pharmaceutical agents;</para><para>(7) Registered nurses or licensed practical nurses employed by a hospital who administer pursuant to a chart order, or procure for such purpose, single doses of drugs or devices from original drug or device containers or properly labeled repackaged or prepackaged drug or device containers to persons registered as patients and within the confines of the hospital;</para><para>(8) Persons employed by a facility where dispensed drugs and devices are delivered from a pharmacy for pickup by a patient or caregiver and no dispensing or storage of drugs or devices occurs;</para><para>(9) Persons who sell or purchase medical products, compounds, vaccines, or serums used in the prevention or cure of animal diseases and maintenance of animal health if such medical products, compounds, vaccines, or serums are not sold or purchased under a direct, specific, written medical order of a licensed veterinarian;</para><para>(10) A person accredited by an accrediting body who, pursuant to a medical order, (a) administers, dispenses, or distributes medical gas or medical gas devices to patients or ultimate users or (b) purchases or receives medical gas or medical gas devices for administration, dispensing, or distribution to patients or ultimate users; and</para><para>(11) A person accredited by an accrediting body who, pursuant to a medical order, (a) sells, delivers, or distributes devices described in subsection (2) of section 38-2841 to patients or ultimate users or (b) purchases or receives such devices with intent to sell, deliver, or distribute to patients or ultimate users.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 121, p. 490; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1802; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1,143; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 339, &#167; 2, p. 1062; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 350, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 476, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 900, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1108, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,143; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 946; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB604, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB37, &#167; 41. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para><para><emphasis>Optometry Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>