<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2892"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2892</statuteno><catchline>Pharmacy technicians; employer responsibility.</catchline><para>(1) A pharmacy employing pharmacy technicians shall be responsible for the supervision and performance of the pharmacy technicians.</para><para>(2) The pharmacist in charge shall be responsible for the practice of pharmacy and the establishment of written control procedures and guidelines governing the qualifications, onsite training, functions, supervision, and verification of the performance of pharmacy technicians. The supervision of such technicians at the place of employment shall be performed by the licensed pharmacist who is on duty in the facility with the pharmacy technicians.</para><para>(3)(a) Each pharmacy shall document, in a manner and method specified in the written control procedures and guidelines, the basic competence of the pharmacy technician prior to performance of tasks and functions by such technician. Such basic competence shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(i) Basic pharmaceutical nomenclature;</para><para>(ii) Metric system measures, both liquid and solid;</para><para>(iii) The meaning and use of Roman numerals;</para><para>(iv) Abbreviations used for dosages and directions to patients;</para><para>(v) Basic medical terms, including terms relating to ailments, diseases, or infirmities;</para><para>(vi) The use and operation of automated dispensing and record-keeping systems if used by the employing pharmacy;</para><para>(vii) Applicable statutes, rules, and regulations governing the preparation, compounding, dispensing, and distribution of drugs or devices, record keeping with regard to such functions, and the employment, use, and functions of pharmacy technicians; and</para><para>(viii) The contents of the written control procedures and guidelines.</para><para>(b) Written control procedures and guidelines shall specify the functions that pharmacy technicians may perform in the employing pharmacy. The written control procedures and guidelines shall specify the means used by the employing pharmacy to verify that the prescribed drug or device, the dosage form, and the directions provided to the patient or caregiver conform to the medical order authorizing the drug or device to be dispensed.</para><para>(c) The written control procedures and guidelines shall specify the manner in which the verification made prior to dispensing is documented.</para><para>(4) Each pharmacy or facility shall, before using pharmacy technicians, file with the board a copy of its written control procedures and guidelines and receive approval of its written control procedures and guidelines from the board. The board shall, within ninety days after the filing of such written control procedures and guidelines, review and either approve or disapprove them. The board shall notify the pharmacy or facility of the approval or disapproval. The board or its representatives shall have access to the approved written control procedures and guidelines upon request. Any written control procedures and guidelines for supportive pharmacy personnel that were filed by a pharmacy and approved by the board prior to September 1, 2007, shall be deemed to be approved and to apply to pharmacy technicians.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 33; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2007, &#167; 71-1,147.67.</para></source></law></legaldoc>