<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2125"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2125</statuteno><catchline>Reciprocity; privilege to practice under compact; marriage and family therapist; licensed in another jurisdiction; military spouse; temporary license.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this section, the department, with the recommendation of the board, may issue a license based on licensure in another jurisdiction to an individual who:</para><para>(a) Meets the licensure requirements of the Mental Health Practice Act or substantially equivalent requirements as determined by the department, with the recommendation of the board; or</para><para>(b) Has been in active practice in the appropriate discipline for at least five years following initial licensure or certification in another jurisdiction and has passed the Nebraska jurisprudence examination.</para><para>(2) The department may issue a license based on a privilege to practice in Nebraska under the Licensed Professional Counselors Interstate Compact as provided in section 5 of such compact.</para><para>(3) The department, with the recommendation of the board, shall, based on licensure in another jurisdiction, issue a mental health practitioner license or an independent mental health practitioner license to a marriage and family therapist who:</para><para>(a) Has a valid, independent, and unrestricted license as a marriage and family therapist in another state or territory that is in good standing with such state or territory;</para><para>(b) Completes an application and pays all applicable fees; and</para><para>(c) Has passed the Nebraska jurisprudence examination.</para><para>(4) An applicant for a license who is a military spouse may apply for a temporary license as provided in section 38-129.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 742; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1034, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB752, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB257, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Licensed Professional Counselors Interstate Compact,</emphasis> see section 38-4201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>