<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2214"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2214</statuteno><catchline>Board members; additional qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) Each licensed practical nurse educator on the board shall (a) be a registered nurse currently licensed in the state, (b) have graduated with a graduate degree in nursing or a related field of study, (c) have had a minimum of five years' experience in administration, teaching, or consultation in practical nurse education, and (d) be currently employed as a practical nurse educator.</para><para>(2) Each associate degree or diploma nurse educator on the board and the baccalaureate nurse educator on the board shall (a) be a registered nurse currently licensed in the state, (b) have graduated with a graduate degree in nursing, (c) have had a minimum of five years' experience in administration, teaching, or consultation in nursing education, and (d) be currently employed in the field being represented.</para><para>(3) Each staff nurse on the board shall (a) be a registered nurse currently licensed in the state, (b) have had a minimum of five years' experience in nursing, and (c) be currently employed as a staff nurse in the provision of patient care services.</para><para>(4) Each nursing service administrator on the board shall (a) be a registered nurse currently licensed in the state, (b) have had a minimum of five years' experience in nursing service administration, and (c) be currently employed in such field.</para><para>(5) Each licensed practical nurse member shall (a) have completed at least four years of high school study, (b) be licensed as a licensed practical nurse in this state, (c) have obtained a certificate or diploma from a state-approved practical nursing program, (d) have been actively engaged in practical nursing for at least five years, and (e) be currently employed in the provision of patient care services as a licensed practical nurse in the state.</para><para>(6) Each public member shall meet the requirements of section 38-165.</para><para>(7) The advanced practice registered nurse on the board shall (a) have a minimum of five years' experience as an advanced practice registered nurse, (b) be currently employed as an advanced practice registered nurse, and (c) be licensed as an advanced practice registered nurse.</para><para>(8) Members serving on December 1, 2008, may complete their respective terms even if they do not meet the requirements for appointment as changed by Laws 2007, LB 463. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 245, &#167; 4(2), p. 838; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 272, &#167; 4, p. 857; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 422, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 563, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,132.08; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 770.</para></source><annotation><para>The Board of Nursing has power to deny a license upon proof applicant is guilty of unprofessional conduct, and upon review de novo district court may not substitute its own judgment on that issue. Scott v. State ex rel. Board of Nursing, 196 Neb. 681, 244 N.W.2d 683 (1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>