<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2423"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2423</statuteno><catchline>Acting administrator; provisional license required; application; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A person selected to apply for a provisional license in nursing home administration to serve as the administrator of such facility shall apply to the department. Such license, if issued, shall be valid for no more than one hundred eighty calendar days and may be issued to an individual not otherwise qualified for licensure as a nursing home administrator in order to maintain the daily operations of the facility and may not be renewed. The department may grant an extension not to exceed ninety days if the person seeking the provisional license is in a mentoring program.</para><para>(2) The department may issue a provisional license to an individual who has applied for a mentoring program. Such provisional license will allow the applicant to serve as administrator in the specified facility for one hundred eighty calendar days and may not be renewed. The board may grant an extension not to exceed ninety days if the person seeking the provisional license is in a mentoring program.</para><para>(3) An applicant for a provisional license under this section shall: (a) Be at least twenty-one years of age; (b) be employed on a full-time basis of not less than forty hours per week to perform the duties of the nursing home administrator; and (c) have no history of unprofessional conduct or denial or disciplinary action against a nursing home administrator license or a license to practice any other profession by any lawful licensing authority.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1040, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 686, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1986), &#167; 71-2045.08; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 411, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 137; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-6063; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 838.</para></source></law></legaldoc>