<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2851"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2851</statuteno><catchline>Pharmacist; license; requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1) To be eligible to
take the pharmacist licensure examination, every applicant must present proof
of graduation from an accredited pharmacy program. A graduate of a pharmacy
program located outside of the United States and which is not accredited shall
be deemed to have satisfied the requirement of being a graduate of an accredited
pharmacy program upon providing evidence satisfactory to the department, with
the recommendation of the board, of graduation from such foreign pharmacy
program and upon successfully passing an equivalency examination approved
by the board.</para><para>(2)
Every applicant for licensure as a pharmacist shall (a) pass a pharmacist
licensure examination approved by the board, (b) have graduated from a pharmacy
program pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, and (c) present proof
satisfactory to the department, with the recommendation of the board, that
he or she has met one of the following requirements to demonstrate his or
her current competency: (i) Within the last three years, has passed a pharmacist
licensure examination approved by the board; (ii) has been in the active practice
of the profession of pharmacy in another state, territory, or the District
of Columbia for at least one year within the three years immediately preceding
the application for licensure; (iii) has become board certified in a specialty
recognized by the Board of Pharmacy Specialties or its successor within the
seven years immediately preceding the application for licensure; (iv) is duly
licensed as a pharmacist in some other state, territory, or the District of
Columbia in which, under like conditions, licensure as a pharmacist is granted
in this state; or (v) has completed continuing competency in pharmacy that
is approved by the Board of Pharmacy.</para><para>(3) Proof of
the qualifications for licensure prescribed in this section shall be made
to the satisfaction of the department, with the recommendation of the board. Graduation from an accredited pharmacy
program shall be certified by the appropriate school, college, or university
authority by the issuance of the degree granted to a graduate of such school,
college, or university.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 167, &#167; 123, p. 491; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-1804; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 91, &#167; 1, p. 393; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 71-1804; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 151, &#167; 2, p. 552; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1,145; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 350, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 476, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 449; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 110; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2000, &#167; 71-1,145; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 245, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 15; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,143.01; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 345; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 947; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB179, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
