<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id658"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2213"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2213</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to July 1, 2026, the board shall consist of eight registered nurse members, two licensed practical nurse members, and two public members. The registered nurses on the board shall be from the following areas: (a) One practical nurse educator; (b) one associate degree or diploma nurse educator; (c) one baccalaureate nurse educator; (d) two nursing service administrators; (e) two staff nurses; and (f) one advanced practice registered nurse.</para><para>(2) Beginning July 1, 2026, the board shall consist of ten registered nurse members, two licensed practical nurse members, and three public members. The registered nurses on the board shall be from the following areas: (a) One practical nurse educator; (b) one associate degree or diploma nurse educator; (c) one baccalaureate nurse educator; (d) one nursing service administrator; (e) two staff nurses; and (f) four advanced practice registered nurses.</para><para>(3) The State Board of Health shall attempt to ensure that the membership of the Board of Nursing is representative of acute care, long-term care, and community-based care. A minimum of three and a maximum of five members shall be appointed from each congressional district, and each member shall have been a bona fide resident of the congressional district from which he or she is appointed for a period of at least one year prior to the time of the appointment of such member.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 245, &#167; 4(1), p. 838; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 272, &#167; 3, p. 856; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 320, &#167; 2, p. 1171; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 338, &#167; 1, p. 1059; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 282, &#167; 4, p. 825; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 422, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 473, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 375, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 563, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 25; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,132.07; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 769; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB346, &#167; 16. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For limits and designations of congressional districts,</emphasis> see section 32-504.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>