<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id616" statutenumber="38-2050"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2050</statuteno><catchline id="id619">Physician assistants; supervision; supervising physician; requirements; collaborative agreement.</catchline><para>(1) To be a supervising physician, a person shall:</para><para>(a) Be licensed to practice medicine and surgery under the Uniform Credentialing Act;</para><para>(b) Have no restriction imposed by the board on his or her ability to supervise or collaborate with a physician assistant; and</para><para>(c) Be a party to a collaborative agreement with the physician assistant.</para><para>(2) The supervising physician shall keep the collaborative agreement on file at his or her primary practice site, shall keep a copy of the collaborative agreement on file at each practice site where the physician assistant provides medical services, and shall make the collaborative agreement available to the board and the department upon request.</para><para>(3) Supervision of a physician assistant by a supervising physician shall be continuous but shall not require the physical presence of the supervising physician at the time and place that the services are rendered. A physician assistant may render services in a setting that is geographically remote from the supervising physician.</para><para>(4) A supervising physician may supervise no more than four physician assistants at any one time. The board may consider an application for waiver of this limit and may waive the limit upon a showing that the supervising physician meets the minimum requirements for the waiver. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing minimum requirements for such waivers.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 101, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 85-179.09; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 132, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 316, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,107.20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 708; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB755, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>