<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id73"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2140"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2140</statuteno><catchline>Art therapist; certification; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, qualified supervisor means a qualified physician, a psychologist licensed to engage in the practice of psychology, a licensed mental health practitioner, a licensed independent mental health practitioner, or a certified art therapist who has met standards for supervision specified in rules and regulations approved by the board and adopted and promulgated by the department.</para><para>(2) A person who submits a complete application to the department for certification as an art therapist shall be qualified for such certification if such person:</para><para>(a) Provides evidence to the department that such person:</para><para>(i) Has a master's or doctoral degree in art therapy from an approved educational program or a master's degree in a related mental health field and graduate-level course work determined by the board to be equivalent in didactic content and supervised clinical experience to an approved educational program in art therapy; and</para><para>(ii) Has had at least three thousand hours of experience in art therapy supervised by a qualified supervisor following receipt of such graduate degree and at least one-half of such hours were supervised by a certified art therapist acting as the qualified supervisor. The three thousand hours of experience shall include at least one thousand five hundred hours of direct client contact, and at least one-half of such hours shall be supervised by a certified art therapist acting as the qualified supervisor. The direct-client-contact hours shall include at least one hundred hours of supervisor-supervisee-contact hours supervised by a qualified supervisor, with supervision provided at least one hour per week or two hours every two weeks, and at least one-half of such hours shall be supervised by a certified art therapist acting as the qualified supervisor; and</para><para>(b) Passes an examination approved by the board.</para><para>(3) An applicant for certification as a certified art therapist who has completed all or part of such applicant's qualifying experience in art therapy in another state or jurisdiction shall have completed not less than one-half of the required three thousand hours of experience and not less than one-half of the direct-client-contact hours and supervisor-supervisee-contact hours supervised by a certified art therapist or a person holding a credential as a Board Certified Art Therapist from the Art Therapy Credentials Board, Inc., as determined by the Board of Mental Health Practice acting as the qualified supervisor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB605, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>