<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="HEALTH OCCUPATIONS AND PROFESSIONS" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="38-2315"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2315</statuteno><catchline>Nurse practitioner; functions; scope.</catchline><para>(1) A nurse practitioner may provide health care services within specialty areas. A nurse practitioner shall function by establishing collaborative, consultative, and referral networks as appropriate with other health care professionals. Patients who require care beyond the scope of practice of a nurse practitioner shall be referred to an appropriate health care provider.</para><para>(2) Nurse practitioner practice means health promotion, health supervision, illness prevention and diagnosis, treatment, and management of common health problems and acute and chronic conditions, including:</para><para>(a) Assessing patients, ordering diagnostic tests and therapeutic treatments, synthesizing and analyzing data, and applying advanced nursing principles;</para><para>(b) Dispensing, incident to practice only, sample medications which are provided by the manufacturer and are provided at no charge to the patient; and</para><para>(c) Prescribing therapeutic measures and medications relating to health conditions within the scope of practice.</para><para>(3) A nurse practitioner who has proof of a current certification from an approved certification program in a psychiatric or mental health specialty may manage the care of patients committed under the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act. Patients who require care beyond the scope of practice of a nurse practitioner who has proof of a current certification from an approved certification program in a psychiatric or mental health specialty shall be referred to an appropriate health care provider.</para><para>(4) A nurse practitioner may pronounce death and may complete and sign death certificates and any other forms if such acts are within the scope of practice of the nurse practitioner and are not otherwise prohibited by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 379, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 724, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 96; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1721; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 807; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1042, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB243, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB107, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>