<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id21"><sectno id="id22" opdate="December 1, 2008">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id23" statutenumber="38-2116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id25">38-2116</statuteno><catchline id="id26">Mental health practitioner, independent mental health practitioner, defined; use of titles.</catchline><para>(1) Mental health practitioner means a person who holds himself or herself out as a person qualified to engage in mental health practice or a person who offers or renders mental health practice services. Independent mental health practitioner means a person who holds himself or herself out as a person qualified to engage in independent mental health practice or a person who offers or renders independent mental health practice services. </para><para>(2) A person who is licensed as a mental health practitioner and certified as a master social worker may use the title licensed clinical social worker. A person who is licensed as a mental health practitioner and certified as a professional counselor may use the title licensed professional counselor. A person who is licensed as a mental health practitioner and certified as a marriage and family therapist may use the title licensed marriage and family therapist. No person shall use the title licensed clinical social worker, licensed professional counselor, or licensed marriage and family therapist unless he or she is licensed and certified as provided in this subsection.</para><para>(3) A person who is licensed as an independent mental health practitioner and certified as a master social worker may use the title licensed independent clinical social worker. A person who is licensed as an independent mental health practitioner and certified as a professional counselor may use the title licensed independent professional counselor. A person who is licensed as an independent mental health practitioner and certified as a marriage and family therapist may use the title licensed independent marriage and family therapist. No person shall use the title licensed independent clinical social worker, licensed independent professional counselor, or licensed independent marriage and family therapist unless he or she is licensed and certified as provided in this subsection.</para><para>(4) A mental health practitioner shall not represent himself or herself as a physician or psychologist and shall not represent his or her services as being medical or psychological in nature. An independent mental health practitioner shall not represent himself or herself as a physician or psychologist.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 669, &#167; 27; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,308; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 734; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1108, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>