<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2712</statuteno><catchline>Perfusionist Committee; created; membership; powers and duties; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) There is created the Perfusionist Committee which shall review and make recommendations to the board regarding all matters relating to perfusionists that come before the board. Such matters shall include, but not be limited to, (a) applications for licensure, (b) perfusionist education, (c) scope of practice, (d) proceedings arising relating to disciplinary actions, (e) perfusionist licensure requirements, and (f) continuing competency. The committee shall be directly responsible to the board. </para><para>(2) The committee shall be appointed by the State Board of Health and shall be composed of two perfusionists and one physician who has clinical experience with perfusionists. The physician member may also be a member of the Board of Medicine and Surgery. The chairperson of the committee shall be elected by a majority vote of the committee members. All appointments shall be for five-year terms, at staggered intervals. Members shall serve no more than two consecutive terms. Reappointments shall be made by the State Board of Health.</para><para>(3) The committee shall meet on a regular basis, and committee members shall, in addition to necessary traveling and lodging expenses, receive a per diem for each day actually engaged in the discharge of his or her duties, including compensation for the time spent in traveling to and from the place of conducting business. Traveling and lodging expenses shall be reimbursed on the same basis as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The compensation shall not exceed fifty dollars per day and shall be determined by the committee with the approval of the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 19; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2007, &#167; 71-1,401.</para></source></law></legaldoc>