<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id483"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2531"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2531</statuteno><catchline>Rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations regarding role delineation for occupational therapy assistants and continuing competency requirements. Continuing education is sufficient to meet continuing competency requirements. Such requirements may also include, but not be limited to, one or more of the continuing competency activities listed in section 38-145 which a licensed person may select as an alternative to continuing education.</para><para>(2) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the training courses for an occupational therapist to be certified to administer physical agent and instrument-assisted modalities. The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the training course for an occupational therapy assistant to be certified to set up and implement superficial thermal agent modalities. In adopting such rules and regulations, the board shall give consideration to the levels of training and experience which are required, in the opinion of the board, to protect the public health, safety, and welfare and to insure, to the greatest extent possible, the efficient, adequate, and safe practice of occupational therapy. Such rules and regulations shall include the approval of examinations and the passing score for such examinations for certification.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 244, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-6123; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 871; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB257, &#167; 19. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>