<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id180"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2067"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2067</statuteno><catchline>Internationally trained physician; transitional license; eligibility; renewal.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the board, may issue a transitional license for no longer than three years to an internationally trained physician if such physician has:</para><para>(a) Practiced medicine for three years under the supervision of a participating health care entity;</para><para>(b) Completed and received satisfactory results on the participating health care entity's department-approved and board-recommended assessment and evaluation program which shall document, using multiple assessment methods, the physician's performance across the general competencies within the physician's intended scope of practice;</para><para>(c) Received a satisfactory score on step 3 of the licensing examination; and</para><para>(d) Completed additional prerequisites required by the board. Such prerequisites shall not include a medical education residency program.</para><para>(2) Prior to issuing a transitional license, the department shall receive from the participating health care entity a final assessment and evaluation report on a form prescribed by the department, with the recommendation of the board, affirming that, in the judgment of the participating health care entity, the physician has demonstrated the ability to engage in independent and unsupervised practice within the physician's intended scope of practice across all general competencies. The board shall be provided with a copy of the final assessment and evaluation report and may review the report and make a recommendation to the department regarding issuance, denial, or renewal of a provisional or transitional license under this section.</para><para>(3) The transitional license may be renewed for one three-year period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1212, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>August 1, 2027</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>