<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2310"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2310</statuteno><catchline>Integrated practice agreement, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Integrated practice agreement means a written agreement between a nurse practitioner and a collaborating physician in which the nurse practitioner and the collaborating physician provide for the delivery of health care through an integrated practice. The integrated practice agreement shall provide that the nurse practitioner and the collaborating physician will practice collaboratively within the framework of their respective scopes of practice. Each provider shall be responsible for his or her individual decisions in managing the health care of patients. Integrated practice includes consultation, collaboration, and referral.</para><para>(2) The nurse practitioner and the collaborating physician shall have joint responsibility for patient care, based upon the scope of practice of each practitioner. The collaborating physician shall be responsible for supervision of the nurse practitioner to ensure the quality of health care provided to patients.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Collaborating physician means a physician or osteopathic physician licensed in Nebraska and practicing in the same geographic area and practice specialty, related specialty, or field of practice as the nurse practitioner; and</para><para>(b) Supervision means the ready availability of the collaborating physician for consultation and direction of the activities of the nurse practitioner within the nurse practitioner's defined scope of practice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 724, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 54; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1716.03; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 802.</para></source></law></legaldoc>