<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2895"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2895</statuteno><catchline>Pharmacy technician; discipline against supervising pharmacist; enforcement orders.</catchline><para>(1) If a pharmacy technician performs functions requiring professional judgment and licensure as a pharmacist, performs functions not specified under approved written control procedures and guidelines, or performs functions without supervision and such acts are known to the pharmacist supervising the pharmacy technician or the pharmacist in charge or are of such a nature that they should have been known to a reasonable person, such acts may be considered acts of unprofessional conduct on the part of the pharmacist supervising the pharmacy technician or the pharmacist in charge pursuant to section 38-178, and disciplinary measures may be taken against such pharmacist supervising the pharmacy technician or the pharmacist in charge pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act.</para><para>(2) Acts described in subsection (1) of this section may be grounds for the department, with the recommendation of the board, to apply to the district court in the judicial district in which the pharmacy is located for an order to cease and desist from the performance of any unauthorized acts. On or at any time after such application the court may, in its discretion, issue an order restraining such pharmacy or its agents or employees from the performance of unauthorized acts. After a hearing the court shall either grant or deny the application. Such order shall continue until the court, after a hearing, finds the basis for such order has been removed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 36; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2007, &#167; 71-1,147.70; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 84.</para></source></law></legaldoc>