<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id19" statutenumber="38-2419"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2419</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Nursing home
administrator; license; issuance; qualifications; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall issue a license to an applicant who submits
(a) satisfactory evidence of completion of (i) an associate degree which includes
the core educational requirements and an administrator-in-training program
under a certified preceptor, (ii) a degree or an advanced degree and a mentoring
program under a certified preceptor, (iii) a nursing degree, previous work
experience in health care administration, and a mentoring program under a
certified preceptor, (iv) a degree or an advanced degree in health care and
previous work experience in health care administration, or (v) an associate
degree which includes the core educational requirements, previous work experience,
and a mentoring program under a certified preceptor, and (b) evidence of successful
passage of the National Association of Boards of Examiners for Nursing Home
Administration written examination.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall license administrators in accordance
with the Nursing Home Administrator Practice Act and standards, rules, and
regulations adopted and promulgated by the department, with the recommendation
of the board. The license shall not be transferable or assignable.</para>
<para>(3) Each administrator shall be responsible for and oversee
the operation of only one licensed facility or one integrated system, except
that an administrator may make application to the department for approval
to be responsible for and oversee the operations of a maximum of three licensed
facilities if such facilities are located within two hours' travel time of
each other or to act in the dual role of administrator and department head
but not in the dual role of administrator and director of nursing. In reviewing
the application, the department may consider the proximity of the facilities
and the number of licensed beds in each facility. An administrator responsible
for and overseeing the operations of any integrated system is subject to disciplinary
action against his or her license for any regulatory violations within each
system.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1040, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 686, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 126; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1986), &#167; 71-2045.02; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 693, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 344, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 733, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1989, &#167; 71-2041.02; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 58, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 456, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 669, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 608, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 193; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 411, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 133; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 246, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-6054; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 834; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB42, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis>general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>