<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-2027"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2027</statuteno><catchline>Department; waiver of requirements; authorized; conditions; disciplinary action authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the board, may waive any requirement for more than one year of approved graduate medical education, as set forth in subdivision (2) of section 38-2026, if the applicant has served at least one year of graduate medical education approved by the board and if the following conditions are met:</para><para>(a) The applicant meets all other qualifications for a license to practice medicine and surgery;</para><para>(b) The applicant submits satisfactory proof that the issuance of a license based on the waiver of the requirement of more than one year of approved graduate medical education will not jeopardize the health, safety, and welfare of the citizens of this state; and</para><para>(c) The applicant submits proof that he or she will enter into the practice of medicine in a health profession shortage area designated as such by the Nebraska Rural Health Advisory Commission immediately upon obtaining a license to practice medicine and surgery based upon a waiver of the requirement for more than one year of graduate medical education.</para><para>(2) A license issued on the basis of such a waiver shall be subject to the limitation that the licensee continue in practice in the health profession shortage area and such other limitations, if any, deemed appropriate under the circumstances by the director, with the recommendation of the board, which may include, but shall not be limited to, supervision by a medical practitioner, training, education, and scope of practice. After two years of practice under a limited license issued on the basis of a waiver of the requirement of more than one year of graduate medical education, a licensee may apply to the department for removal of the limitations. The director, with the recommendation of the board, may grant or deny such application or may continue the license with limitations.</para><para>(3) In addition to any other grounds for disciplinary action against the license contained in the Uniform Credentialing Act, the department may take disciplinary action against a license granted on the basis of a waiver of the requirement of more than one year of graduate medical education for violation of the limitations on the license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 685. </para></source></law></legaldoc>