<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id143">
<sectno id="id144" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id145" statutenumber="38-2869"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id147">38-2869</statuteno><catchline id="id148">Prospective
drug utilization review; counseling; requirements.</catchline><para>(1)(a)
Prior to the dispensing or the delivery of a drug or device pursuant to a
medical order to a patient or caregiver, a pharmacist shall in all care settings
conduct a prospective drug utilization review. Such prospective drug utilization
review shall involve monitoring the patient-specific medical history described
in subdivision (b) of this subsection and available to the pharmacist at the
practice site for:</para>
<para>(i) Therapeutic duplication;</para>
<para>(ii) Drug-disease contraindications;</para>
<para>(iii) Drug-drug interactions;</para>
<para>(iv) Incorrect drug dosage or duration of drug treatment;</para>
<para>(v) Drug-allergy interactions; and</para>
<para>(vi) Clinical abuse or misuse.</para>
<para>(b) A pharmacist conducting a prospective drug utilization
review shall ensure that a reasonable effort is made to obtain from the patient,
his or her caregiver, or his or her practitioner and to record and maintain
records of the following information to facilitate such review:</para>
<para>(i) The name, address, telephone number, date of birth, and
gender of the patient;</para>
<para>(ii) The patient's history of significant disease, known
allergies, and drug reactions and a comprehensive list of relevant drugs and
devices used by the patient; and</para>
<para>(iii) Any comments of the pharmacist relevant to the patient's
drug therapy.</para>
<para>(c) The assessment of data on drug use in any prospective
drug utilization review shall be based on predetermined standards, approved
by the board.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Prior to the dispensing or delivery of a drug or device
pursuant to a prescription, the pharmacist shall ensure that a verbal offer
to counsel the patient or caregiver is made. The counseling of the patient
or caregiver by the pharmacist shall be on elements which, in the exercise
of the pharmacist's professional judgment, the pharmacist deems significant
for the patient. Such elements may include, but need not be limited to, the
following:</para>
<para>(i) The name and description of the prescribed drug or device;</para>
<para>(ii) The route of administration, dosage form, dose, and
duration of therapy;</para>
<para>(iii) Special directions and precautions for preparation,
administration, and use by the patient or caregiver;</para>
<para>(iv) Common side effects, adverse effects or interactions,
and therapeutic contraindications that may be encountered, including avoidance,
and the action required if such effects, interactions, or contraindications
occur;</para>
<para>(v) Techniques for self-monitoring drug therapy;</para>
<para>(vi) Proper storage;</para>
<para>(vii) Prescription refill information; and</para>
<para>(viii) Action to be taken in the event of a missed dose.</para>
<para>(b) The patient counseling provided for in this subsection
shall be provided in person whenever practical or by the utilization of telephone
service which is available at no cost to the patient or caregiver.</para>
<para>(c) Patient counseling shall be appropriate to the individual
patient and shall be provided to the patient or caregiver.</para>
<para>(d) Written information may be provided to the patient or
caregiver to supplement the patient counseling provided for in this subsection
but shall not be used as a substitute for such patient counseling.</para>
<para>(e) This subsection shall not be construed to require a pharmacist
to provide patient counseling when:</para>
<para>(i) The patient or caregiver refuses patient counseling;</para>
<para>(ii) The pharmacist, in his or her professional judgment,
determines that patient counseling may be detrimental to the patient's care
or to the relationship between the patient and his or her practitioner;</para>
<para>(iii) The patient is a patient or resident of a health care
facility or health care service licensed under the Health Care Facility Licensure
Act to whom prescription drugs or devices are administered by a licensed or
certified staff member or consultant or a certified physician's assistant;</para>
<para>(iv) The practitioner authorized to prescribe drugs or devices
specifies that there shall be no patient counseling unless he or she is contacted
prior to such patient counseling. The prescribing practitioner shall specify
such prohibition in an oral prescription or in writing on the face of a written
prescription, including any prescription which is received by facsimile or
electronic transmission. The pharmacist shall note "Contact Before Counseling"
on the face of the prescription if such is communicated orally by the prescribing
practitioner;</para>
<para>(v) A medical gas or a medical gas device is administered,
dispensed, or distributed by a person described in subdivision (12) of section
38-2850; or</para>
<para>(vi) A device
described in subsection (2) of section 38-2841 is sold, distributed, or delivered
by a business or person described in subdivision (13) of section 38-2850.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,147.35; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 965; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB604, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 12.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>