<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2881"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2881</statuteno><catchline>Delegated dispensing permit; formularies.</catchline>
<para>(1) With the recommendation of the board, the director shall approve
a formulary to be used by individuals dispensing pursuant to a delegated dispensing
permit. A formulary shall consist of a list of drugs or devices appropriate
to delegated dispensing activities authorized by the delegated dispensing
permit. Except as otherwise provided in this section, if the board finds that
a formulary would be unnecessary to protect the public health and welfare
and promote public convenience and necessity, the board shall recommend that
no formulary be approved.</para>
<para>(2)(a) With the recommendation of the board, the director shall
approve the formulary to be used by public health clinics dispensing pursuant
to a delegated dispensing permit.</para>
<para>(b) The formulary for a public health clinic shall consist of a list
of drugs and devices for contraception, sexually transmitted diseases, and
vaginal infections which may be dispensed and stored, patient instruction
requirements which shall include directions on the use of drugs and devices,
potential side effects and drug interactions, criteria for contacting the
on-call pharmacist, and accompanying written patient information.</para>
<para>(c) In no event shall the director exclude any of the provisions for patient instruction approved
by the board.</para>
<para>(d) Drugs and devices with the following characteristics shall not be
eligible to be included in the formulary:</para>
<para>(i) Controlled substances;</para>
<para>(ii) Drugs with significant dietary interactions;</para>
<para>(iii) Drugs with significant drug-drug interactions; and</para>
<para>(iv) Drugs or devices with complex counseling profiles.</para>
<para>(3)(a) With the recommendation of the board, the director shall approve
a formulary to be used by dialysis drug or device distributors.</para>
<para>(b) The formulary for a dialysis drug or device distributor shall consist
of a list of drugs, solutions, supplies, and devices for the treatment of
chronic kidney failure which may be dispensed and stored.</para>
<para>(c) In no event shall the director approve for inclusion in the formulary
any drug or device not approved by the board.</para>
<para>(d) Controlled substances shall not be eligible to be included in the
formulary.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 900, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 467; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 56; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,147.48; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 352; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 977; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB154, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>