<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2417"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2417</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall consist of seven professional members and two public members appointed pursuant to section 38-158. The members shall meet the requirements of sections 38-164 and 38-165.</para><para>(2) The professional members shall consist of: (a) Two members who hold active licenses and are currently employed in the management, operation, or ownership of proprietary homes for the aged or infirm or nursing homes that serve the aged or infirm in Nebraska; (b) two members who hold active licenses and are currently employed in the management or operation of a nonprofit home for the aged or infirm or nursing home or hospital caring for chronically ill or infirm, aged patients; (c) one member who is a member of the faculty of a college or university located in the state who is actively engaged in a teaching program relating to business administration, social work, gerontology, or some other aspect of the administration of health care facilities; (d) one member who is a licensed physician and surgeon with a demonstrated interest in long-term care; and (e) one member who is a licensed registered nurse. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1040, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 686, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 693, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 344, &#167; 20; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1989, &#167; 71-2045.01; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 755; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 411, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 61; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-6065; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 649; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 832.</para></source></law></legaldoc>