<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-2890" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>38-2890</statuteno><catchline>Pharmacy technicians; registration; requirements; certification.</catchline><para>(1) All pharmacy technicians employed by a health care facility licensed under the Health Care Facility Licensure Act shall be registered with the Pharmacy Technician Registry created in section 38-2893. In order to be employed as a pharmacy technician in such a health care facility, a pharmacy technician (a) shall be certified by a state or national certifying body which is approved by the board (i) by January 1, 2017, if he or she was registered with the Pharmacy Technician Registry on January 1, 2016, or (ii) within one year after being registered with the Pharmacy Technician Registry, if he or she was so registered after January 1, 2016, and (b) upon being so certified, shall maintain current certification during the time he or she is so registered.</para><para>(2) To register as a pharmacy technician, an individual shall (a) be at least eighteen years of age, (b) be a high school graduate or be officially recognized by the State Department of Education as possessing the equivalent degree of education, (c) have never been convicted of any nonalcohol, drug-related misdemeanor or felony, (d) file an application with the Division of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services, and (e) pay the applicable fee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB236, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2007, &#167; 71-1,147.65; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB37, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB680, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>April 7, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>