<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="38-3419"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>38-3419</statuteno><catchline>Reciprocity; individual practicing before January 1, 2013; licensure; qualification; military spouse; temporary license.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the recommendation of the state board, may issue a license under the Genetic Counseling Practice Act based on licensure in another jurisdiction to an individual who meets the requirements of the Genetic Counseling Practice Act or substantially equivalent requirements as determined by the department, with the recommendation of the state board.</para><para>(2) An individual practicing genetic counseling in Nebraska before January 1, 2013, may apply for licensure under the act if, on or before July 1, 2013, he or she:</para><para>(a) Provides satisfactory evidence to the state board that he or she (i) has practiced genetic counseling for a minimum of ten years preceding January 1, 2013, (ii) has a postbaccalaureate degree at the master's level or higher in genetics or a related field of study, and (iii) has never failed the certification examination;</para><para>(b) Submits three letters of recommendation from at least one individual practicing genetic counseling who qualifies for licensure under the Genetic Counseling Practice Act and either a clinical geneticist or medical geneticist certified by the national medical genetics board. An individual submitting a letter of recommendation shall have worked with the applicant in an employment setting during at least five of the ten years preceding submission of the letter and be able to attest to the applicant's competency in providing genetic counseling; and</para><para>(c) Provides documentation of attending approved continuing education programs within the five years preceding application.</para><para>(3) An applicant who is a military spouse may apply for a temporary license as provided in section 38-129.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB831, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB88, &#167; 91. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>