<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-3114"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-3114</statuteno><catchline>Applicant for license; qualifications.</catchline><para>An applicant for licensure as a psychologist shall:</para><para>(1) Possess a doctoral degree from a program of graduate study in professional psychology from an institution of higher education. The degree shall be obtained from a program of graduate study in psychology that meets the standards of accreditation adopted by the American Psychological Association. Any applicant from a doctoral program in psychology that does not meet such standards shall present a certificate of retraining from a program of respecialization that does meet such standards;</para><para>(2) Prior to taking the examination, demonstrate that he or she has completed two years of supervised professional experience. One year of such experience shall be an internship meeting the standards of accreditation adopted by the American Psychological Association, and one year shall be supervised postdoctoral experience. The criteria for appropriate supervision shall be determined by the board. Postdoctoral experience shall be compatible with the knowledge and skills acquired during formal doctoral or postdoctoral education in accordance with professional requirements and relevant to the intended area of practice; and</para><para>(3) Pass an examination. The board shall approve and the board or department shall administer examinations to qualified applicants on at least an annual basis. The board shall determine the subject matter and scope of the examination and shall require a written examination, an oral examination, or both a written examination and an oral examination of each candidate for licensure. The board may approve a national standardized examination and any examination developed by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 77; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,206.15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1048.</para></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis> general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference> </law></legaldoc>