<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id994"><amendatorysection statutenumber="38-3512" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-3512</statuteno><catchline>Applicant; education and examination requirements; waiver; when.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for licensure under the Surgical First Assistant Practice Act shall:</para><para>(a) Be certified as a surgical first assistant by an approved certifying body;</para><para>(b) Have successfully completed an approved surgical first assistant education program approved by the board or other experiential or training program as approved by the board;</para><para>(c) Have passed a nationally recognized surgical first assistant examination adopted by the board; and</para><para>(d) Have a high school diploma or the equivalent as determined by the board.</para><para>(2) The department may waive the education and examination requirements under the Surgical First Assistant Practice Act for an applicant who:</para><para>(a) By January 1, 2017, submits demonstrated evidence satisfactory to the board that he or she has been functioning as a surgical first assistant as his or her primary function in a licensed health care facility within the last five years prior to September 1, 2016;</para><para>(b) By January 1, 2017, submits evidence of holding a current certification as a surgical first assistant issued by an approved certifying body; or</para><para>(c) Submits evidence of holding a credential as a surgical first assistant issued by another state or territory of the United States or the District of Columbia which has standards substantially equivalent to those of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB721, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credentialing,</emphasis>general requirements and issuance procedures, see section 38-121 et seq.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>