<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" id="id13" statutenumber="38-3330"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>38-3330</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Disclosure of
information; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) Unless required by any state or local law
for contagious or infectious disease reporting or other public health and
safety purpose, no veterinarian licensed under the Veterinary Medicine and
Surgery Practice Act shall be required to disclose any information concerning
the veterinarian's care of an animal except under a written authorization
or other waiver by the veterinarian's client or pursuant to a court order
or a subpoena. A veterinarian who releases information under a written authorization
or other waiver by the client or pursuant to a court order or a subpoena is
not liable to the client or any other person.</para>
<para>(2) The privilege provided
by this section is waived to the extent that the veterinarian's client or
the owner of the animal places the veterinarian's care and treatment of the
animal or the nature and extent of injuries to the animal at issue in any
civil or criminal proceeding.</para>
<para>(3) The privilege
provided by this section is waived to the extent and for purposes of notifying
any owner or manager of cattle that have a significant risk for exposure to
bovine trichomoniasis. A veterinarian who releases information about the risk
for exposure to bovine trichomoniasis is not liable to the client or any other
person.</para><para>(4) For
purposes of this section, veterinarian includes the employees or agents of
the licensed veterinarian while acting for or on behalf of such veterinarian.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 833, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,164; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1112; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB423, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>