<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" id="id5" statutenumber="38-3321"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>38-3321</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Veterinarian; veterinary
technician; animal therapist; license; required; exceptions.</catchline><para>No person may practice veterinary medicine and surgery in the state
who is not a licensed veterinarian, no person may perform delegated animal
health care tasks in the state who is not a licensed veterinary technician
or an unlicensed assistant performing such tasks within the limits established
under subdivision (2) of section 38-3326, and no person may perform health
care therapy on animals in the state who is not a licensed animal therapist.
The Veterinary Medicine and Surgery Practice Act shall not be construed to
prohibit:</para>
<para>(1) An employee of the federal, state, or local government
from performing his or her official duties;</para>
<para>(2) A person who is a student in a veterinary school from
performing duties or actions assigned by his or her instructors or from working
under the direct supervision of a licensed veterinarian;</para>
<para>(3) A person who is a student in an approved veterinary technician
program from performing duties or actions assigned by his or her instructors
or from working under the direct supervision of a licensed veterinarian or
a licensed veterinary technician;</para>
<para>(4) Any merchant or manufacturer from selling feed or feeds
whether medicated or nonmedicated;</para>
<para>(5) A veterinarian regularly licensed in another state from
consulting with a licensed veterinarian in this state;</para>
<para>(6) Any merchant or manufacturer from selling from his or
her established place of business medicines, appliances, or other products
used in the prevention or treatment of animal diseases or any merchant or
manufacturer's representative from conducting educational meetings to explain
the use of his or her products or from investigating and advising on problems
developing from the use of his or her products;</para>
<para>(7) An owner of livestock or a bona fide farm or ranch employee
from performing any act of vaccination, surgery, pregnancy testing, retrievable transplantation of embryos
on bovine, including recovering, freezing, and transferring embryos on bovine, or
the administration of drugs in the treatment of domestic animals under his
or her custody or ownership nor the exchange of services between persons or
bona fide employees who are principally farm or ranch operators or employees
in the performance of these acts;</para>
<para>(8) A member of the faculty of a veterinary school or veterinary
science department from performing his or her regular functions, or a person
lecturing or giving instructions or demonstrations at a veterinary school
or veterinary science department or in connection with a continuing competency
activity;</para>
<para>(9) Any person from selling or applying any pesticide, insecticide,
or herbicide;</para>
<para>(10) Any person from engaging in bona fide scientific research
which reasonably requires experimentation involving animals;</para>
<para>(11) Any person from treating or in any manner caring for
domestic chickens, turkeys, or waterfowl, which are specifically exempted
from the Veterinary Medicine and Surgery Practice Act;</para>
<para>(12) Any person from performing dehorning or castrating livestock,
not to include equidae.</para>
<para>For purposes of the Veterinary Medicine and Surgery Practice
Act, castration shall be limited to the removal or destruction of male testes;</para>
<para>(13) Any person who holds a valid credential in the State
of Nebraska in a health care profession or occupation regulated under the
Uniform Credentialing Act from consulting with a licensed veterinarian or
performing collaborative animal health care tasks on an animal under the care
of such veterinarian if all such tasks are performed under the immediate supervision
of such veterinarian; or</para>
<para>(14) A person
from performing a retrievable transplantation of embryos on bovine, including
recovering, freezing, and transferring embryos on bovine, if the procedure
is being performed by a person who (a) holds a doctorate degree in animal
science with an emphasis in reproductive physiology from an accredited college
or university and (b) has and can show proof of valid professional liability
insurance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 439, &#167; 3, p. 1354; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 926, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 301, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2006, &#167; 71-1,155; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1103; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB463, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB686, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Subsection (6) of this section applies to owners or bona fide farm or ranch employees who work on their own animals, not another person's animals, unless an exchange of services is involved. State ex rel. Dept. of Health v. Jeffrey, 247 Neb. 100, 525 N.W.2d 193 (1994).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>