<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Health Occupations And Professions" statutenumber="38-3122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>38-3122</statuteno><catchline>Provisional license; requirements.</catchline><para>A person who needs to obtain the required one year of supervised postdoctoral experience in psychology pursuant to subdivision (2) of section 38-3114 shall obtain a provisional license to practice psychology. An applicant for a provisional license to practice psychology shall:</para><para>(1) Have a doctoral degree from an institution of higher education in a program of graduate study in professional psychology that meets the standards of accreditation adopted by the American Psychological Association or its equivalent. If the program is not accredited by the American Psychological Association, it is the responsibility of the applicant to provide evidence of equivalence. Any applicant from a program that does not meet such standards shall present a certificate of retraining from a program of respecialization that does meet such standards;</para><para>(2) Have completed one year of supervised professional experience in an internship as provided in subdivision (2) of section 38-3114;</para><para>(3) Apply prior to beginning the year of registered supervised postdoctoral experience; and</para><para>(4) Submit to the department:</para><para>(a) An official transcript showing proof of a doctoral degree in psychology from an institution of higher education;</para><para>(b) A certified copy of the applicant's birth certificate or other evidence of having attained the age of nineteen years; and</para><para>(c) A registration of supervisory relationship pursuant to section 38-3116.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 366, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 71-1,206.32; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1056.</para></source></law></legaldoc>