<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id588"><amendatorysection chaptername="Health Occupations and Professions" statutenumber="38-4408"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>38-4408</statuteno><catchline>Practice of applied behavior analysis, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Practice of applied behavior analysis means the design, implementation, and evaluation of instructional and environmental modifications to produce socially significant improvements in human behavior.</para><para>(2) Practice of applied behavior analysis includes the empirical identification of functional relations between behavior and environmental factors, known as functional assessment and analysis.</para><para>(3) Applied behavior analysis interventions (a) are based on scientific research and direct and indirect observation and measurement of behavior and environment and (b) utilize contextual factors, motivating operations, antecedent stimuli, positive reinforcement, and other procedures to help individuals develop new behaviors, increase or decrease existing behaviors, and emit behaviors under specific environmental conditions.</para><para>(4) Practice of applied behavior analysis excludes (a) diagnosis of disorders, (b) psychological testing, (c) psychotherapy, (d) cognitive therapy, (e) psychoanalysis, (f) counseling, (g) functional movement analysis, (h) practice by persons required to be credentialed under the Audiology and Speech-Language Pathology Practice Act in the diagnosis or treatment of hearing, speech, communication, or swallowing disorders, or (i) practice by persons required to be credentialed under the Occupational Therapy Practice Act in the treatment of occupational performance dysfunction, such as activities of daily living and instrumental activities of daily living.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Audiology and Speech-Language Pathology Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-501.</para><para><emphasis>Occupational Therapy Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2501.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>