<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id53">
<sectno id="id54" opdate="September 30, 2009">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id55" statutenumber="43-512.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id57">43-512.03</statuteno><catchline id="id58">County attorney
or authorized attorney; duties; enumerated; department; powers; actions; real
party in interest; representation; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) The county attorney or authorized attorney shall:</para>
<para>(a) On request by the Department of Health and Human Services
as described in subsection (2) of this section or when the investigation or
application filed under section 43-512 or 43-512.02 justifies, file a complaint
against a nonsupporting party in
the district, county, or separate juvenile court praying for an order for
child or medical support in cases when there is no existing child or medical
support order. After notice and hearing, the court shall adjudicate the child and medical support
liability of either
party and enter an order accordingly;</para>
<para>(b) Enforce child, spousal, and medical support orders by
an action for income withholding pursuant to the Income Withholding for Child
Support Act;</para>
<para>(c) In addition to income withholding, enforce child, spousal,
and medical support orders by other civil actions or administrative actions,
citing the defendant for contempt, or filing a criminal complaint;</para>
<para>(d) Establish paternity and collect child and medical support
on behalf of children born out of wedlock; and</para>
<para>(e) Carry out sections 43-512.12 to 43-512.18.</para>
<para>(2) The department may periodically review cases of individuals
receiving enforcement services and make referrals to the county attorney or
authorized attorney.</para>
<para>(3) In any action brought by or intervened in by a county
attorney or authorized attorney under the Income Withholding for Child Support
Act, the License Suspension Act, the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act,
or sections 42-347 to 42-381, 43-290, 43-512 to 43-512.18, 43-1401
to 43-1418, and 43-3328 to 43-3339, such attorneys shall represent the State
of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(4) The State of Nebraska shall be a real party in interest
in any action brought by or intervened in by a county attorney or authorized
attorney for the purpose of establishing paternity or securing, modifying,
suspending, or terminating child or medical support or in any action brought
by or intervened in by a county attorney or authorized attorney to enforce
an order for child, spousal, or medical support.</para>
<para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to interpret
representation by a county attorney or an authorized attorney as creating
an attorney-client relationship between the county attorney or authorized
attorney and any party or witness to the action, other than the State of Nebraska,
regardless of the name in which the action is brought.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 926, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 425, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 345, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 522, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 371, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 600, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 37, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 715, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1224, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 3, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 158; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 229, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1207, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Income Withholding for Child Support Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1701.</para><para><emphasis>License Suspension Act,</emphasis> see section 43-3301.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Interstate Family Support Act,</emphasis> see section 42-701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>As a prerequisite for an action under this section, there cannot be an existing child support order in Nebraska or any other jurisdiction. State ex rel. Gaddis v. Gaddis, 237 Neb. 264, 465 N.W.2d 773 (1991).</para><para>The nonexistence of a support order is a prerequisite to an action by the State to establish support under this section, and a dissolution decree or modification order which addresses the issue of support, even if ordering that no support is due from either party, constitutes a support order which precludes the State from instituting such an action. State ex rel. Cammarata v. Chambers, 6 Neb. App. 467, 574 N.W.2d 530 (1998).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>