<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id277">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id279"  statutenumber="43-290.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-290.01</statuteno><catchline>Costs; payment.</catchline><para>(1) Payment
of costs for juveniles described in or alleged to be described in subdivision
(1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247, except as ordered by the court
pursuant to section 43-290, shall be paid by:</para>
<para>(a) The county
for the period of time prior to adjudication, except as provided in subdivision
(1)(b) of this section. Such costs paid for by the county include, but are
not limited to, the costs of detention, services, detention alternatives,
treatment, voluntary services, and transportation;</para><para>(b) The Office of Probation
Administration for:</para><para>(i) The period of time after adjudication until termination of
court jurisdiction, including, but not limited to, the costs of evaluations,
detention, services, placement that is not detention, detention alternatives,
treatment, voluntary services, and transportation, other than transportation
paid under subdivision (1)(c) of this section;</para><para>(ii) The time period
prior to adjudication for a juvenile who is on probation and is alleged to
have committed a new violation or is a juvenile who is subject to a motion
to revoke probation; and</para><para>(iii) Preadjudication evaluations and preadjudication placements
that are not detention; and</para><para>(c) The Office of Juvenile Services for
any period of time from when the court commits the juvenile to the Office
of Juvenile Services until the juvenile is discharged by the Office of Juvenile
Services, including, but not limited to, the costs of evaluations, placement,
services, detention including detention costs prior to placement, and transportation
to and from the youth rehabilitation and treatment center.</para>
<para>(2) For payment
of costs involved in the adjudication and disposition of juveniles, other
than those described in subsection (1) or (3) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) The Department
of Health and Human Services shall pay the costs incurred during an evaluation
or placement with the department that is ordered by the court except as otherwise
ordered by the court pursuant to section 43-290;</para><para>(b) Payment of costs
for juveniles with a court adjudication or disposition under section 43-284:
Upon a determination by the court that there are no parental, private, or
other funds available for the care, custody, education, and maintenance of
the juvenile, the court may order a reasonable sum for the care, custody,
education, and maintenance of the juvenile to be paid out of a fund appropriated
annually by the county where the petition is filed until suitable provisions
are made for the juvenile without such payment. The amount to be paid by a
county for education shall not exceed the average cost for education of a
public school student in the county in which the juvenile is placed and shall
be paid only for education in kindergarten through grade twelve; and</para>
<para>(c) Other
costs shall be as provided in section 43-290.</para><para>(3) Payment of costs
of medical expenses of juveniles under the Nebraska Juvenile Code shall be
as provided in section 43-290.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>