<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id18"><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id20" statutenumber="43-905"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>43-905</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Guardianship;
care; placement; duties of
department; contracts; payment for maintenance.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall be the legal
guardian of all children committed to it. The department shall afford temporary
care and shall use special diligence to provide suitable homes for such children. The department shall make reasonable efforts
to accomplish joint-sibling placement or sibling visitation or ongoing interaction
between siblings as provided in section 43-1311.02. The department
is authorized to place such children in suitable families for adoption, foster care, or guardianship or,
in the discretion of the department, on a written contract.</para>
<para>(2) The contract shall provide (a) for the children's education
in the public schools or otherwise, (b) for teaching them some useful occupation,
and (c) for kind and proper treatment as members of the family in which they
are placed.</para>
<para>(3) Whenever any child who has been committed to the department
becomes self-supporting, the department shall declare that fact and the guardianship
of the department shall cease. Thereafter the child shall be entitled to his
or her own earnings. Guardianship of and services by the department shall
never extend beyond the age of majority, except that services by the department
to a child shall continue until the child reaches the age of twenty-one if
the child is a student regularly attending a school, college, or university
or regularly attending a course of vocational or technical training designed
to prepare such child for gainful employment.</para>
<para>(4) Whenever the parents of any ward, whose parental rights
have not been terminated, have become able to support and educate their child,
the department shall restore the child to his or her parents if the home of
such parents would be a suitable home. The guardianship of the department
shall then cease.</para>
<para>(5) Whenever permanent free homes for the children cannot
be obtained, the department shall have the authority to provide and pay for
the maintenance of the children in private families, in foster care, in guardianship, in boarding
homes, or in institutions
for care of children.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 62, &#167; 5, p. 274; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7229; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6886; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 83-504; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 202, &#167; 1, p. 826; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 83-504; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 83-243; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 246, &#167; 1, p. 779; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 325, &#167; 1, p. 1097; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 344, &#167; 1, p. 1118; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 387, &#167; 1, p. 1345; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 443, &#167; 1, p. 1491; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 415, &#167; 32, p. 1261; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 245, &#167; 1, p. 695; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 248, &#167; 4, p. 657; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 349, &#167; 1, p. 1219; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 312, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 732, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 169, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 185; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB177, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Foster Parent Liability and Property Damage Fund,</emphasis> see section 43-1320.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>