<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-291"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-291</statuteno><catchline>Termination of parental rights; proceedings.</catchline><para>Facts may also be set forth in the original petition, a supplemental petition, or motion filed with the court alleging that grounds exist for the termination of parental rights. After a petition, a supplemental petition, or motion has been filed, the court shall cause to be endorsed on the summons and notice that the proceeding is one to terminate parental rights, shall set the time and place for the hearing, and shall cause summons and notice, with a copy of the petition, supplemental petition, or motion attached, to be given in the same manner as required in other cases before the juvenile court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 47. </para></source><annotation><para>The Nebraska Juvenile Code provides for the filing of an original petition seeking termination of parental rights under this section. Subsection (6) of section 43-247 and this section indicate that the juvenile court may properly acquire jurisdiction over an original action to terminate parental rights as provided in the Nebraska Juvenile Code without prior juvenile court action, including adjudication. The plain and ordinary meaning of this section and section 43-292, taken together, is that parental rights may be terminated in an original proceeding. In re Interest of Joshua M. et al., 256 Neb. 596, 591 N.W.2d 557 (1999).</para><para>Notice of action to terminate parental rights is required under this section. In re Interest of D.J. et al., 224 Neb. 226, 397 N.W.2d 616 (1986).</para><para>Although there may have been no prior juvenile court action, including adjudication, the juvenile court acquires jurisdiction to terminate parental rights when a motion to terminate parental rights containing the grounds for termination is filed under subsections (1) through (5) of section 43-292. In re Interest of Brook P. et al., 10 Neb. App. 577, 634 N.W.2d 290 (2001).</para><para>In a hearing on the termination of parental rights without a prior adjudication, where such termination is sought under subsections (1) through (5) of section 43-292, such proceedings must be accompanied by due process safeguards, as statutory provisions cannot abrogate constitutional rights. In re Interest of Brook P. et al., 10 Neb. App. 577, 634 N.W.2d 290 (2001).</para><para>Although adjudication and disposition proceedings may be combined, the adjudication proceeding may not be omitted altogether. In re Interest of Joelyann H., 6 Neb. App. 472, 574 N.W.2d 185 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>