<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-707"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-707</statuteno><catchline>Protection of children; Department of Health and Human Services; powers and duties.</catchline><para>The Department of Health and Human Services shall have the power and it shall be its duty:</para><para>(1) To promote the enforcement of laws for the protection and welfare of children born out of wedlock, mentally and physically handicapped children, and dependent, neglected, and delinquent children, except laws the administration of which is expressly vested in some other state department or division, and to take the initiative in all matters involving such children when adequate provision therefor has not already been made;</para><para>(2) To visit and inspect public and private institutions, agencies, societies, or persons caring for, receiving, placing out, or handling children;</para><para>(3) To prescribe the form of reports required by law to be made to the department by public officers, agencies, and institutions;</para><para>(4) To exercise general supervision over the administration and enforcement of all laws governing the placing out and adoption of children;</para><para>(5) To advise with judges and probation officers of courts of domestic relations and juvenile courts of the several counties, with a view to encouraging, standardizing, and coordinating the work of such courts and officers throughout the state; and</para><para>(6) To regulate the issuance of certificates or licenses to such institutions, agencies, societies, or persons and to revoke such licenses or certificates for good cause shown. If a license is refused or revoked, the refusal or revocation may be appealed, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 123, &#167; 2, p. 495; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 81-5715; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-617; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 170, &#167; 7, p. 546; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 204, &#167; 11, p. 615; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 22, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 179; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 73. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Associations receiving juveniles under the Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> supervision by Department of Health and Human Services, see section 43-296.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>