<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-295"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-295</statuteno><catchline>Juvenile court; continuing jurisdiction; exception.</catchline><para>Except when the juvenile has been legally adopted, the jurisdiction of the court shall continue over any juvenile brought before the court or committed under the Nebraska Juvenile Code and the court shall have power to order a change in the custody or care of any such juvenile if at any time it is made to appear to the court that it would be for the best interests of the juvenile to make such change.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 27.</para></source><annotation><para>A juvenile court, except where an adjudicated child has been legally adopted, may always order a change in the juvenile's custody or care when the change is in the best interests of the juvenile. In re Interest of Karlie D., 283 Neb. 581, 811 N.W.2d 214 (2012).</para><para>A separate juvenile court retains jurisdiction to order a temporary change in custody if it is in the child's best interests. In re Interest of Jedidiah P., 267 Neb. 258, 673 N.W.2d 553 (2004).</para><para>Any order regarding the disposition of a juvenile pending the resolution of an appeal of the adjudication can only be made on a temporary basis upon a finding by the court that such disposition would be in the best interests of the juvenile. In re Interest of Jedidiah P., 267 Neb. 258, 673 N.W.2d 553 (2004).</para><para>The exercise of a separate juvenile court's jurisdiction pending an appeal must be determined by the facts of each case. Pending an appeal from an adjudication, the juvenile court does not have the power to enter a permanent dispositional order. In re Interest of Jedidiah P., 267 Neb. 258, 673 N.W.2d 553 (2004).</para><para>When parental rights of the surviving parent have been terminated under this section, that parent's parents lack standing to request visitation rights. In re Interest of Ditter, 212 Neb. 855, 326 N.W.2d 675 (1982).</para><para>A juvenile court's commitment of a juvenile to a youth rehabilitation treatment center does not constitute a discharge within the meaning of section 43-247, and therefore, the juvenile court retains jurisdiction. In re Interest of David C., 6 Neb. App. 198, 572 N.W.2d 392 (1997).</para><para>The continuing jurisdiction of a juvenile court under this section does not include the power to terminate parental rights pending an appeal. In re Interest of Joshua M., et al., 4 Neb. App. 659, 548 N.W.2d 348 (1996).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>