<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id00" statutenumber="43-2,112"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,112</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Establishment; petition; election; clerk of county court; duties.</catchline><para id="id00">The question of whether or not there shall be established a separate juvenile court in any county having a population of seventy-five thousand or more inhabitants shall be submitted to the registered voters of any such county at the first statewide general election or at any special election held not less than four months after the filing with the Secretary of State of a petition requesting the establishment of such court signed by registered voters of such county in a number not less than five percent of the total votes cast for Governor in such county at the general state election next preceding the filing of the petition. The question shall be submitted to the registered voters of the county in the following form:</para><para id="id00">Shall there be established in .......... County a separate juvenile court?</para><para id="id00">...... Yes</para><para id="id00">...... No</para><para id="id00">The election shall be conducted and the ballots shall be counted and canvassed in the manner prescribed by the Election Act.</para><para id="id00">After a separate juvenile court has been established, the clerk of the county court shall forthwith transfer to the trial docket of the separate juvenile court all pending matters within the exclusive jurisdiction of the separate juvenile court for consideration and disposition by the judge thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 189, &#167; 2, p. 683; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 669, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 118, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 373, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 43-229; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 973, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 553; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 80. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2018</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>