<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id308">
<sectno id="id309">Sec. 25.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id310" statutenumber="43-2,106.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id312">43-2,106.01</statuteno><catchline id="id313">Judgments
or final orders; appeal; parties; cost.</catchline><para>(1) Any
final order or judgment entered by a juvenile court may be appealed to the
Court of Appeals in the same manner as an appeal from district court to the
Court of Appeals. The appellate court shall conduct its review in
an expedited manner and shall render the judgment and write its
opinion, if any, as speedily as possible.</para>
<para>(2) An appeal may be taken by:</para>
<para>(a) The juvenile;</para>
<para>(b) The guardian ad litem;</para>
<para>(c) The juvenile's parent, custodian, or guardian. For purposes
of this subdivision, custodian or guardian shall include, but not be limited
to, the Department of Health and Human Services, an association, or an individual
to whose care the juvenile has been awarded pursuant to the Nebraska Juvenile
Code; or</para>
<para>(d) The county attorney or petitioner, except that in any
case determining delinquency issues in which the juvenile has been placed
legally in jeopardy, an appeal of such issues may only be taken by exception
proceedings pursuant to sections 29-2317 to 29-2319.</para>
<para>(3) In all appeals from the county court sitting as a juvenile
court, the judgment of the appellate court shall be certified without cost
to the juvenile court for further proceedings consistent with the determination
of the appellate court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 189, &#167; 11, p. 686; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1305, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1978), &#167; 43-238; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 182, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 360, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 43-2,126; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1106, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167;  25.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Separate juvenile courts are treated as county courts under sections 29-2317 to 29-2319 for the purpose of exception proceedings under subsection (2)(d) of this section. In re Interest of Sean H., 271 Neb. 395, 711 N.W.2d 879 (2006).</para><para>A public defender appointed to represent a juvenile is not a party to the juvenile proceeding and may not bring an appeal based on error regarding an order unrelated to the disposition of the juvenile's case. In re Interest of William G., 256 Neb. 788, 592 N.W.2d 499 (1999).</para><para>Under subsection (2)(c) of this section, the term "custodian" extends beyond those having the care of a juvenile by means of an award under the Nebraska Juvenile Code. One empowered by parental authority to care for a child is a "custodian" and has standing to appeal a juvenile court's order. In re Interest of Artharena D., 253 Neb. 613, 571 N.W.2d 608 (1997).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>