<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id211">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id213" statutenumber="43-281">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-281</statuteno><catchline id="id216">Adjudication
of jurisdiction; temporary placement for evaluation; restrictions on placement; copy of report or evaluation.</catchline>
<para>(1) Following an adjudication of jurisdiction and prior to
final disposition, the court may place the juvenile with the Office of Juvenile
Services or the Department of Health and Human Services for evaluation, except
that on and after October 1, 2013, no juvenile adjudicated under subdivision
(1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 shall be placed with the office
or the department. The office or department shall arrange and pay for an appropriate
evaluation if the office or department determines that there are no parental
funds or private or public insurance available to pay for such evaluation,
except that on and after October 1, 2013, the office and the department shall
not be responsible for such evaluations of any juvenile adjudicated under
subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247.</para>
<para>(2) On and after October 1, 2013, following an adjudication
of jurisdiction under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247
and prior to final disposition, the court may order an evaluation to be arranged by the Office of Probation
Administration. For a juvenile in detention, the court shall order that
such evaluation be completed and the juvenile returned to the court within twenty-one
days after the evaluation.
For a juvenile who is not in detention, the evaluation shall be completed
and the juvenile returned to the court within thirty days. The physician,
psychologist, licensed mental health practitioner, licensed drug and alcohol
counselor, or other provider responsible for completing the evaluation shall
have up to ten days to complete the evaluation after receiving the referral
authorizing the evaluation.</para>
<para>(3) A juvenile pending evaluation ordered under subsection
(1) or (2) of this section shall not reside in a detention facility at the
time of the evaluation or while waiting for the completed evaluation to be
returned to the court unless detention of such juvenile is a matter of immediate
and urgent necessity for the protection of such juvenile or the person or
property of another or if it appears that such juvenile is likely to flee
the jurisdiction of the court.</para>
<para>(4) The court
shall provide copies of predisposition reports and evaluations of the juvenile
to the juvenile's attorney and the county attorney or city attorney prior
to any hearing in which the report or evaluation will be relied upon.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 787, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 436, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 18.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2014</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The juvenile court cannot order a specific placement of a juvenile for the purposes of the evaluation authorized by this section. In re Interest of Taylor W., 276 Neb. 679, 757 N.W.2d 1 (2008).</para><para>An order placing a juvenile in the Youth Development Center temporarily for the purpose of evaluation preliminary to a dispositional hearing is not a final order for the purposes of appeal. In re Interest of J.M.S., 218 Neb. 72, 352 N.W.2d 186 (1984).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>