<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-116</statuteno><catchline>Validity of decrees.</catchline><para>When any court in the State of Nebraska shall (1) have entered of record a decree of adoption prior to August 27, 1949, it shall be conclusively presumed that such adoption and all instruments and proceedings in connection therewith are valid in all respects notwithstanding some defect or defects may appear on the face of the record, or the absence of any record of such court, unless an action shall be brought within two years from August 27, 1949, attacking its validity, or (2) hereafter enter of record such a decree of adoption, it shall in like manner be conclusively presumed that the adoption and all instruments and proceedings in connection therewith are valid in all respects notwithstanding some defect or defects may appear on the face of the record, or the absence of any record of such court, unless an action is brought within two years from the entry of such decree of adoption attacking its validity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 130, &#167; 1, p. 340; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1041, &#167; 13. </para></source><annotation><para>Any action to set aside an adoption must be brought under this section. The matter of adoption is statutory, and the manner of procedure and terms are all specifically prescribed and must be followed. In re Adoption of Hemmer, 260 Neb. 827, 619 N.W.2d 848 (2000).</para><para>All instruments and proceedings connected with adoption are conclusively presumed valid unless decree is attacked within two years. Syrovatka ex rel. Syrovatka v. Graham, 190 Neb. 355, 208 N.W.2d 281 (1973).</para><para>After two years from entry of decree of adoption, there is conclusive presumption of validity of decree of adoption. Hiatt v. Menendez, 157 Neb. 914, 62 N.W.2d 123 (1954).</para><para>Natural parents are barred from collaterally challenging the adoption of their natural children once the statutory period of two years had passed for a direct appeal of the adoption order. Syrovatka v. Erlich, 608 F.2d 307 (8th Cir. 1979).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>