<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-292.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-292.01</statuteno><catchline>Termination of parental rights; appointment of guardian ad litem; when.</catchline><para>When termination of the parent-juvenile relationship is sought under subdivision (5) of section 43-292, the court shall appoint a guardian ad litem for the alleged incompetent parent. The court may, in any other case, appoint a guardian ad litem, as deemed necessary or desirable, for any party. The guardian ad litem shall be paid a reasonable fee set by the court and paid from the general fund of the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1041, &#167; 28. </para></source><annotation><para>A guardian ad litem appointed for a parent is entitled to participate fully in the proceeding to terminate parental rights. In re Interest of D.S. and T.S., 236 Neb. 413, 461 N.W.2d 415 (1990).</para><para>Appointment of a guardian ad litem for parents whose parental rights are sought to be terminated under subdivision (5) of section 43-292 is mandatory. Failure to appoint a guardian ad litem to protect the interests of such a parent is plain error which requires that the judgment be reversed. In re Interest of M.M., C.M., and D.M., 230 Neb. 388, 431 N.W.2d 611 (1988).</para><para>Supreme Court urges appointments of an attorney and of a guardian ad litem be separated. In re Interest of C.W., 226 Neb. 719, 414 N.W.2d 277 (1987).</para><para>Appointment of a guardian ad litem for a parent who is allegedly incompetent because of mental illness or mental deficiency is mandatory, and the failure to appoint a guardian ad litem is plain error which requires reversal of an order terminating the parent's rights. In re Interest of Presten O., 18 Neb. App. 259, 778 N.W.2d 759 (2010).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>