<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id165">
<sectno id="id166">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id167" statutenumber="43-246"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id169">43-246</statuteno><catchline id="id170">Code, how construed.</catchline><para>Acknowledging the responsibility of the juvenile court to
act to preserve the public peace and security, the Nebraska Juvenile Code
shall be construed to effectuate the following:</para>
<para>(1) To assure the rights of all juveniles to care and protection
and a safe and stable living environment and to development of their capacities
for a healthy personality, physical well-being, and useful citizenship and
to protect the public interest;</para>
<para>(2) To provide for the intervention of the juvenile court
in the interest of any juvenile who is within the provisions of the Nebraska
Juvenile Code, with due regard to parental rights and capacities and the availability
of nonjudicial resources;</para>
<para>(3) To remove juveniles who are within the Nebraska Juvenile
Code from the criminal justice system whenever possible and to reduce the
possibility of their committing future law violations through the provision
of social and rehabilitative services to such juveniles and their families;</para>
<para>(4) To offer selected juveniles the opportunity to take direct
personal responsibility for their individual actions by reconciling with the
victims through juvenile offender and victim mediation and fulfilling the
terms of the resulting agreement which may require restitution and community
service;</para>
<para>(5) To achieve the purposes of subdivisions (1) through (3)
of this section in the juvenile's own home whenever possible, separating the
juvenile from his or her parent when necessary for his or her welfare, the
juvenile's health and safety being of paramount concern, or in the interest
of public safety and, when temporary separation is necessary, to consider
the developmental needs of the individual juvenile in all placements, to consider
relatives as a preferred potential placement resource, and to make reasonable
efforts to preserve and reunify the family if required under section 43-283.01;</para>
<para>(6) To promote adoption, guardianship, or other permanent
arrangements for children in the custody of the Department of Health and Human
Services who are unable to return home;</para>
<para>(7) To provide a judicial procedure through which these purposes
and goals are accomplished and enforced in which the parties are assured a
fair hearing and their constitutional and other legal rights are recognized
and enforced;</para>
<para>(8) To assure compliance, in cases involving Indian children,
with the Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act;
and</para>
<para>(9) To make
any temporary placement of a juvenile in the least restrictive environment
consistent with the best interests of the juvenile and the safety of the community.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 787, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 255, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1001, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1041, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 13.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1501.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The state Department of Social Services is not required to institute a plan for rehabilitation of a parent whose child has been found to be dependent and neglected. In re Interest of L.C., J.C., and E.C., 235 Neb. 703, 457 N.W.2d 274 (1990).</para><para>The juvenile code must be liberally construed to effectuate its purpose of securing the best interests of those juveniles who fall within it. In re Interest of R.A. and V.A., 225 Neb. 157, 403 N.W.2d 357 (1987).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>