<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id146" statutenumber="43-251.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-251.01</statuteno><catchline id="id149">Juveniles; placements and commitments; restrictions.</catchline><para>All placements and commitments of juveniles for evaluations or as temporary or final dispositions are subject to the following:</para><para>(1) No juvenile shall be confined in an adult correctional facility as a disposition of the court;</para><para>(2) A juvenile who is found to be a juvenile as described in subdivision (3) of section 43-247 shall not be placed in an adult correctional facility, the secure youth confinement facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services, or a youth rehabilitation and treatment center or committed to the Office of Juvenile Services;</para><para>(3) A juvenile who is found to be a juvenile as described in subdivision (1), (2), or (4) of section 43-247 shall not be assigned or transferred to an adult correctional facility or the secure youth confinement facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services;</para><para>(4) A juvenile under the age of fourteen years shall not be placed with or committed to a youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(5)(a) Before July 1, 2019, a juvenile shall not be detained in secure detention or placed at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center unless detention or placement of such juvenile is a matter of immediate and urgent necessity for the protection of such juvenile or the person or property of another or if it appears that such juvenile is likely to flee the jurisdiction of the court; and</para><para>(b) On and after July 1, 2019:</para><para>(i) A juvenile shall not be detained unless the physical safety of persons in the community would be seriously threatened or detention is necessary to secure the presence of the juvenile at the next hearing, as evidenced by a demonstrable record of willful failure to appear at a scheduled court hearing within the last twelve months;</para><para>(ii) A child twelve years of age or younger shall not be placed in detention under any circumstances; and</para><para>(iii) A juvenile shall not be placed into detention:</para><para>(A) To allow a parent or guardian to avoid his or her legal responsibility;</para><para>(B) To punish, treat, or rehabilitate such juvenile;</para><para>(C) To permit more convenient administrative access to such juvenile;</para><para>(D) To facilitate further interrogation or investigation; or</para><para>(E) Due to a lack of more appropriate facilities;</para><para>(6) A juvenile alleged to be a juvenile as described in subdivision (3) of section 43-247 shall not be placed in a juvenile detention facility, including a wing labeled as staff secure at such facility, unless the designated staff secure portion of the facility fully complies with subdivision (5) of section 83-4,125 and the ingress and egress to the facility are restricted solely through staff supervision; and</para><para>(7) A juvenile alleged to be a juvenile as described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 shall not be placed out of his or her home as a dispositional order of the court unless:</para><para>(a) All available community-based resources have been exhausted to assist the juvenile and his or her family; and</para><para>(b) Maintaining the juvenile in the home presents a significant risk of harm to the juvenile or community.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB972, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB482, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB894, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB670, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>April 24, 2018</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Neither subsection (2) of this section nor section 43-278 prohibits a juvenile court from placing a juvenile at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center when the court has adjudicated a juvenile under section 43-247(2) and (3). In re Interest of Trey H., 281 Neb. 760, 798 N.W.2d 607 (2011).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>