<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id118">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id120" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="43-286.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-286.01</statuteno><catchline id="id123">Juveniles; substance abuse or noncriminal violations of probation;
administrative sanctions; probation officer; duties; powers; county attorney;
file action to revoke probation; when.</catchline><para>(1) For
purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Administrative sanction means additional probation requirements
imposed upon a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer
by his or her probation officer, with the full knowledge and consent of such
juvenile and such juvenile's parents or guardian, designed to hold such juvenile
accountable for substance abuse or noncriminal violations of conditions of
probation, including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(i) Counseling or reprimand by his or her probation officer;</para>
<para>(ii) Increased supervision contact requirements;</para>
<para>(iii) Increased substance abuse testing;</para>
<para>(iv) Referral for substance abuse or mental health evaluation
or other specialized assessment, counseling, or treatment;</para>
<para>(v) Modification of a designated curfew for a period not
to exceed thirty days;</para>
<para>(vi) Community service for a specified number of hours pursuant
to sections 29-2277 to 29-2279;</para>
<para>(vii) Travel restrictions to stay within his or her residence
or county of residence or employment unless otherwise permitted by the supervising
probation officer;</para>
<para>(viii) Restructuring court-imposed financial obligations
to mitigate their effect on the juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation
officer; and</para>
<para>(ix) Implementation of educational or cognitive behavioral
programming;</para>
<para>(b) Noncriminal violation means activities or behaviors of
a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer which create
the opportunity for re-offending or which diminish the effectiveness of probation
supervision resulting in a violation of an original condition of probation,
including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(i) Moving traffic violations;</para>
<para>(ii) Failure to report to his or her probation officer;</para>
<para>(iii) Leaving the juvenile's residence, jurisdiction of the
court, or the state without the permission of the court or his or her probation
officer;</para>
<para>(iv) Failure to regularly attend school, vocational training,
other training, counseling, treatment, programming, or employment;</para>
<para>(v) Noncompliance with school rules;</para>
<para>(vi) Continued violations of home rules;</para>
<para>(vii) Failure to notify his or her probation officer of change
of address, school, or employment;</para>
<para>(viii) Frequenting places where controlled substances are
illegally sold, used, distributed, or administered and association with persons
engaged in illegal activity;</para>
<para>(ix) Failure to perform community service as directed; and</para>
<para>(x) Curfew or electronic monitoring violations; and</para>
<para>(c) Substance abuse violation means activities or behaviors
of a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer associated
with the use of chemical substances or related treatment services resulting
in a violation of an original condition of probation, including, but not limited
to:</para>
<para>(i) Positive breath test for the consumption of alcohol;</para>
<para>(ii) Positive urinalysis for the illegal use of drugs;</para>
<para>(iii) Failure to report for alcohol testing or drug testing;</para>
<para>(iv) Failure to appear for or complete substance abuse or
mental health treatment evaluations or inpatient or outpatient treatment;
and</para>
<para>(v) Tampering with alcohol or drug testing.</para>
<para>(2) Whenever a probation officer has reasonable cause to
believe that a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer
has committed or is about to commit a substance abuse violation or noncriminal
violation while on probation, but that such juvenile will not attempt to leave
the jurisdiction and will not place lives or property in danger, the probation
officer shall either:</para>
<para>(a) Impose one or more administrative sanctions with the
approval of his or her chief probation officer or such chief's designee. The
decision to impose administrative sanctions in lieu of formal revocation proceedings
rests with the probation officer and his or her chief probation officer or
such chief's designee and shall be based upon such juvenile's risk level,
the severity of the violation, and the juvenile's response to the violation.
If administrative sanctions are to be imposed, such juvenile shall acknowledge
in writing the nature of the violation and agree upon the administrative sanction
with approval of such juvenile's parents or guardian. Such juvenile has the
right to decline to acknowledge the violation, and if he or she declines to
acknowledge the violation, the probation officer shall submit a written report
pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section. A copy of the report shall
be submitted to the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed;
or</para>
<para>(b) Submit a written report to the adjudicating court with
a copy to the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed, outlining
the nature of the probation violation and request that formal revocation proceedings
be instituted against the juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation
officer.</para>
<para>(3) Whenever a probation officer has reasonable cause to
believe that a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer
has violated or is about to violate a condition of probation other than a
substance abuse violation or noncriminal violation and that such juvenile
will not attempt to leave the jurisdiction and will not place lives or property
in danger, the probation officer shall submit a written report to the adjudicating
court, with a copy to the county attorney of the county where probation was
imposed, outlining the nature of the probation violation.</para>
<para>(4) Whenever a probation officer has reasonable cause to
believe that a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer
has violated or is about to violate a condition of his or her probation and
that such juvenile will attempt to leave the jurisdiction or will place lives
or property in danger, the probation officer shall take such juvenile into
temporary custody without a warrant and may call on any peace officer for
assistance as provided in section 43-248.</para>
<para>(5) Immediately after detention pursuant to subsection (4)
of this section, the probation officer shall notify the county attorney of
the county where probation was imposed and submit a written report of the
reason for such detention and of any violation of probation. After prompt
consideration of the written report, the county attorney shall:</para>
<para>(a) Order the release of the juvenile from confinement subject
to the supervision of a probation officer; or</para>
<para>(b) File with the adjudicating court a motion or information
to revoke the probation.</para>
<para>(6) Whenever a county attorney receives a report from a probation
officer that a juvenile subject to the supervision of a probation officer
has violated a condition of probation, the county attorney may file a motion
or information to revoke probation.</para>
<para>(7) The probation administrator shall adopt and promulgate
rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2010, &#167; 29-2262.08; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>