<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-268"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-268</statuteno><catchline>Summons, notice, subpoena; manner given; time.</catchline><para>(1) Service of summons shall be made by the delivery of a copy of the summons to the person summoned or by leaving one at his or her usual place of residence with some person of suitable age and discretion residing therein.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 43-264, notice, when required, shall be given in the manner provided for service of a summons in a civil action. Any published notice shall simply state that a proceeding concerning the juvenile is pending in the court and that an order making an adjudication and disposition will be entered therein. If the names of one or both parents or the guardian are unknown, he, she, or they may be notified as the parent or parents, or guardian of (naming or describing the juvenile) found (stating address or place where the juvenile was found). Such notice shall be published once each week for three weeks, the last publication of which shall be at least five days before the time of hearing.</para><para>(3) Personal or residence service shall be effected at least seventy-two hours before the time set for the hearing, but upon cause shown the court shall grant additional time to prepare for a hearing. A guardian ad litem, one of the parents, the person having custody if there be no guardian ad litem, or the attorney for such juvenile may waive such service for the juvenile, if such juvenile concurs in open court duly noted on the records of the court. Registered or certified mail shall be mailed at least five days before the time of the hearing.</para><para>(4) Service of summons, notice, or subpoena may be made by any suitable person under the direction of the court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 51. </para></source><annotation><para>Service by publication under this provision can only be made after a reasonably diligent search fails to locate the party to be served. A reasonably diligent search for the purpose of justifying service by publication does not require the use of all possible or conceivable means of discovery, but is such an inquiry as a reasonably prudent person would make in view of the circumstances and must extend to those places where information is likely to be obtained and to those persons who, in the ordinary course of events, would be likely to receive news of or from the absent person. In re Interest of A.W., 224 Neb. 764, 401 N.W.2d 477 (1987).</para><para>Notice of an adjudication hearing must be given to the biological father as well as the biological mother of the children. In re Interest of B.J.M. et al., 1 Neb. App. 851, 510 N.W.2d 418 (1993).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>