<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id453">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id455" statutenumber="43-413"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-413</statuteno><catchline id="id458">Evaluations
authorized; costs.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies to all juveniles placed with the Office
of Juvenile Services for evaluation prior to October 1, 2013. A
court may, pursuant to section 43-281, place a juvenile with the Office of
Juvenile Services or the Department of Health and Human Services for an evaluation
to aid the court in the disposition.</para>
<para>(2) A juvenile convicted as an adult shall be placed with
the Office of Juvenile Services for evaluation prior to sentencing as provided
by subsection (3) of section 29-2204.</para>
<para>(3) All juveniles shall be evaluated prior to commitment
to the Office of Juvenile Services unless
the court finds that (a) there has been a substantially equivalent evaluation
within the last twelve months that makes reevaluation unnecessary or (b) an
addendum to a previous evaluation rather than a reevaluation would be appropriate.
The court shall not commit such juvenile to the temporary custody of the Office
of Juvenile Services prior to disposition. The office may place a juvenile
in residential or nonresidential community-based evaluation services for purposes
of evaluation to assist the court in determining the initial level of treatment
for the juvenile.</para>
<para>(4) During any period of detention or evaluation prior to
disposition:</para>
<para>(a) Except as provided in subdivision (4)(b) of this section,
the county in which the case is pending is responsible for all detention costs
incurred before and after an evaluation period prior to disposition, the cost
of delivering the juvenile to the facility or institution for an evaluation,
and the cost of returning the juvenile to the court for disposition; and</para>
<para>(b) The state is responsible for (i) the costs incurred during
an evaluation unless otherwise ordered by the court pursuant to section 43-290
and (ii) the preevaluation detention costs for any days over the first ten
days from the date the evaluation is ordered by the court.</para>
<para>(5) The Office of Juvenile Services and the Department of
Health and Human Services are not responsible for predisposition costs except
as provided in subdivision (4)(b) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 814, &#167; 2, p. 3060; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 563, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 31, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 38; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 83-4,101; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 640, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 33.</para></source><annotation><para>The juvenile court cannot order a specific placement of a juvenile for the purposes of the evaluation authorized by this section. In re Interest of Taylor W., 276 Neb. 679, 757 N.W.2d 1 (2008).</para><para>By its language, the purpose of subsection (4) of this section is to make the State responsible for the costs incurred in evaluating a juvenile under subsection (1) of this section. In the absence of an immediate physical delivery of the juvenile upon adjudication into an evaluation program, detention is an unavoidable precursor of evaluation and is, therefore, part of the evaluation process under this section. In re Interest of Marie E., 260 Neb. 984, 621 N.W.2d 65 (2000).</para>
<para>Although the juvenile court did not err in placing the juvenile's custody with the Office of Juvenile Services for purposes only of an evaluation, the juvenile court exceeded its statutory authority in ordering that office to pay for all costs associated with its order which were not covered by insurance. Under the plain language of subsection (4)(b), the county is responsible for the cost of the first 10 days of detention after the court ordered the evaluation. Under subsection (4)(a), the county is also responsible for all detention costs incurred after an evaluation period prior to disposition, the cost of delivering the child to the facility or institution for an evaluation, and the cost of returning the child to the court for disposition. In re Interest of Michael S., 16 Neb. App. 240, 742 N.W.2d 791 (2007).</para>
<para>Pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, a juvenile may not be committed to the Office of Juvenile Services without a prior evaluation, nor may the court commit a juvenile to the temporary custody of the Office of Juvenile Services prior to disposition. In re Interest of Teneko P., 15 Neb. App. 463, 730 N.W.2d 128 (2007).</para>
</annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>