<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-293"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-293</statuteno><catchline>Termination of parental rights; effect; adoption; consent.</catchline><para>When the parental rights have been terminated under section 43-292 and the care of the juvenile is awarded to the Department of Health and Human Services, the department shall have authority to consent to the legal adoption of such juvenile and no other consent shall be required to authorize any court having jurisdiction to enter a legal decree of adoption of such juvenile. When the care of such juvenile is awarded to an individual or association and the parental rights have been terminated by the juvenile court, such individual or association may consent, only when authorized by order of such juvenile court, to the legal adoption of such juvenile and no other consent shall be required to authorize any court having jurisdiction to enter a legal decree of adoption of such juvenile. An order terminating the parent-juvenile relationship shall divest the parent and juvenile of all legal rights, privileges, duties, and obligations with respect to each other and the parents shall have no rights of inheritance with respect to such juvenile. The order terminating parental rights shall be final and may be appealed in the same manner as other final judgments of a juvenile court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 144.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Adoption of child,</emphasis> substitute consents, see sections 43-105 and 43-906.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>When parental rights of the surviving parent have been terminated under section 43-295, that parent's parents lack standing to request visitation rights. In re Interest of Ditter, 212 Neb. 855, 326 N.W.2d 675 (1982).</para><para>According to this section, an order terminating the parent‑juvenile relationship shall divest the parent and juvenile of all legal rights, privileges, duties, and obligations with respect to each other. In re Interest of Stacey D. &amp; Shannon D., 12 Neb. App. 707, 684 N.W.2d 594 (2004).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>