<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id435">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id437" statutenumber="43-410"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-410</statuteno><catchline id="id440">Juvenile absconding;
authority to apprehend.</catchline><para>(1) This subsection applies until July 1, 2014. Any
peace officer, juvenile parole officer, or direct care staff member of the
Office of Juvenile Services has the authority to apprehend and detain a juvenile
who has absconded or is attempting to abscond from a placement for evaluation
or commitment to the Office of Juvenile Services and shall cause the juvenile
to be returned to the facility or program or an appropriate juvenile detention
facility or staff secure juvenile
facility. For purposes of this subsection, direct care staff
member means any staff member charged with the day-to-day care and supervision
of juveniles housed at a facility or program operated directly by the office
or security staff who has received training in apprehension techniques and
procedures.</para>
<para>(2)(a) This
subsection applies beginning July 1, 2014. Any peace officer or direct care
staff member of the Office of Juvenile Services has the authority to apprehend
and detain a juvenile who has absconded or is attempting to abscond from commitment
to the Office of Juvenile Services and shall cause the juvenile to be returned
to the youth rehabilitation and treatment center or an appropriate juvenile
detention facility or staff secure juvenile facility.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this
subsection, direct care staff member means any staff member charged with the
day-to-day care and supervision of juveniles at a youth rehabilitation and
treatment center or security staff who has received training in apprehension
techniques and procedures.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>