<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id362"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id120" statutenumber="43-286.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>43-286.01</statuteno><catchline id="id123">Juvenile probationers; graduated response; probation officer; duties; powers; county attorney; file action to revoke probation; when.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Comprehensive supervision probationer means a juvenile designated as such under section 43-286.02;</para><para>(b) Criminal violation means a violation of a condition of probation involving commission of a misdemeanor or felony. Criminal violation does not include a traffic offense; and</para><para>(c) Graduated response means an accountability-based series of sanctions, incentives, and services designed to facilitate the juvenile's continued progress in changing behavior, ongoing compliance, and successful completion of probation. Graduated response does not include restrictions of liberty that would otherwise require a hearing under subsection (3) of section 43-253.</para><para>(2)(a) The Office of Probation Administration may establish a statewide standardized graduated response matrix of incentives for compliance and positive behaviors and sanctions for probationers who violate the terms and conditions of a court order. The graduated response system shall use recognized best practices and be developed with the input of stakeholders, including judges, probation officers, county attorneys, defense attorneys, juveniles, and parents. The office shall provide implementation and ongoing training to all probation officers on the graduated response options.</para><para>(b) Graduated response sanctions should be immediate, certain, consistent, and fair to appropriately address the behavior. Failure to complete a sanction may result in repeating the sanction, increasing the duration, or selecting a different sanction similar in nature. Continued failure to comply could result in a request for a motion to revoke probation. Once a sanction is successfully completed the alleged probation violation is deemed resolved and cannot be alleged as a violation in future proceedings.</para><para>(c) Graduated response incentives should provide positive reinforcement to encourage and support positive behavior change and compliance with court-ordered conditions of probation.</para><para>(3)(a) Subject to subdivisions (3)(b) and (c) of this section, when a probation officer has reasonable cause to believe that a juvenile probationer has committed a violation of the terms of the juvenile's probation, but that such juvenile will not attempt to leave the jurisdiction and will not place lives or property in danger, the probation officer shall either:</para><para>(i) Impose one or more graduated response sanctions with the approval of his or her chief probation officer or such chief's designee. The decision to impose graduated response sanctions in lieu of formal revocation proceedings rests with the probation officer and his or her chief probation officer or such chief's designee and shall be based upon such juvenile's risk level, the severity of the violation, and the juvenile's response to the violation. If graduated response sanctions are to be imposed, such juvenile shall acknowledge in writing the nature of the violation and agree upon the graduated response sanction with approval of such juvenile's parents or guardian. Such juvenile has the right to decline to acknowledge the violation, and if he or she declines to acknowledge the violation, the probation officer shall submit a written report pursuant to subdivision (3)(a)(ii) of this section. If the juvenile fails to satisfy the graduated response sanctions and the office determines that a motion to revoke probation should be pursued, the probation officer shall submit a written report pursuant to subdivision (3)(a)(ii) of this section. A copy of the report shall be submitted to the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed; or</para><para>(ii) Submit a written report to the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed and to the juvenile's attorney of record. The report shall outline the nature of the probation violation and request that formal revocation proceedings be instituted against the juvenile. The report shall also include a statement regarding why graduated response sanctions were not utilized or were ineffective. If there is no attorney of record for the juvenile, the office shall notify the court and counsel for the juvenile shall be appointed.</para><para>(b) For a juvenile who has been designated as a comprehensive supervision probationer, graduated response sanctions under subdivision (3)(a)(i) of this section may only be imposed one time. For any subsequent violations of the terms of the juvenile's probation, the probation officer shall proceed as provided in subdivision (3)(a)(ii) or subsection (4) of this section, as appropriate.</para><para>(c) When a probation officer has reasonable cause to believe that a juvenile probationer has committed a violation of the terms of the juvenile's probation that is a criminal violation, the probation officer shall not impose graduated response sanctions, but shall proceed as provided in subdivision (3)(a)(ii) or subsection (4) of this section, as appropriate.</para><para>(d) Whenever a graduated response sanction is imposed, the probation officer shall provide the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed with notice of the probation violation and the sanction.</para><para>(4) Whenever a probation officer has reasonable cause to believe that a juvenile probationer has violated a condition of his or her probation and that such juvenile will attempt to leave the jurisdiction or will place lives or property in danger, the probation officer shall take such juvenile into temporary custody without a warrant and may call on any peace officer for assistance as provided in section 43-248. Continued detention or deprivation of liberty shall be subject to the criteria and requirements of sections 43-251.01, 43-260, and 43-260.01 and subdivision (5)(b)(iv) of section 43-286, and a hearing shall be held before the court within twenty-four hours as provided in subsection (3) of section 43-253.</para><para>(5) Immediately after detention or deprivation of liberty pursuant to subsection (4) of this section, the probation officer shall notify the county attorney of the county where probation was imposed and the juvenile's attorney of record and submit a written report describing the risk of harm to lives or property or of fleeing the jurisdiction which precipitated the need for such detention or deprivation of liberty and of any violation of probation. If there is no attorney of record for the juvenile, the office shall notify the court and counsel for the juvenile shall be appointed. After prompt consideration of the written report, the county attorney shall:</para><para>(a) Order the release of the juvenile from confinement or alternative to detention subject to the supervision of a probation officer; or</para><para>(b) File with the adjudicating court a motion to revoke the probation.</para><para>(6) Whenever a county attorney receives a report from a probation officer that a juvenile probationer has violated a condition of probation and the probation officer is seeking revocation of probation, the county attorney may file a motion to revoke probation.</para><para>(7) Whenever a juvenile probationer is engaging in positive behavior, completion of goals, and compliance with the terms of probation, the probation officer shall use graduated incentives to provide positive reinforcement and encouragement of such behavior. The office shall keep records of all incentives and provide such records to the county attorney or the juvenile's attorney upon request.</para><para>(8) During the term of probation, the court, on application of a probation officer or of the juvenile or on its own motion, may reduce or eliminate any of the conditions imposed on the juvenile. Upon completion of the term of probation or the earlier discharge of the juvenile, the juvenile shall be relieved of any obligations imposed by the order of the court and his or her record shall be sealed pursuant to section 43-2,108.04.</para><para>(9) The probation administrator shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2010, &#167; 29-2262.08; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB8, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB530, &#167; 17. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>