<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id34">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id36" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-2,108.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,108.04</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Sealing of
records; notification of proceedings; order of court; hearing; notice; findings;
considerations.</catchline><para>(1) When
a proceeding to seal the record is initiated, the court shall promptly notify
the county attorney or city attorney involved in the case that
is the subject of the proceeding to seal the record of the proceedings,
and shall promptly notify the
Department of Health and Human Services of the proceedings if the juvenile whose
record is the subject of the proceeding is a ward of the state at the time the proceeding is initiated or if
the department was a party in the proceeding.</para>
<para>(2) A party notified under subsection (1) of this section
may file a response with the court within thirty days after receiving such
notice.</para>
<para>(3) If a party notified under subsection (1) of this section
does not file a response with the court or files a response that indicates
there is no objection to the sealing of the record, the court may: (a) Order  the record of the juvenile under consideration
be sealed without conducting a hearing on the motion; or (b) decide in its discretion to conduct a hearing on
the motion. If the court decides in its discretion to conduct
a hearing on the motion, the court shall conduct the hearing within sixty days after making that decision and shall
give notice, by regular mail, of the date, time, and location of the hearing
to the parties receiving notice under subsection (1) of this section and to
the juvenile who is the subject of the record under consideration.</para>
<para>(4) If a party receiving notice under subsection (1) of this
section files a response with the court objecting to the sealing of the record,
the court shall conduct a hearing on the motion within sixty days
after the court receives the response. The court shall give notice, by regular
mail, of the date, time, and location of the hearing to the parties receiving
notice under subsection (1) of this section and to the juvenile who is the
subject of the record under consideration.</para>
<para>(5) After conducting a hearing in accordance with this section,
the court may order the record of the juvenile that is the subject of the
motion be sealed
if it finds that the juvenile has been rehabilitated to a satisfactory degree.
In determining whether the juvenile has been rehabilitated to a satisfactory
degree, the court may consider all of the following:</para>
<para>(a) The age of the juvenile;</para>
<para>(b) The nature of the offense and the role of the juvenile
in the offense;</para>
<para>(c) The behavior of the juvenile after the disposition, adjudication, diversion, or sentence and the juvenile's
response to diversion, mediation,
probation, supervision, other treatment or rehabilitation program, or sentence;</para>
<para>(d) The education and employment history of the juvenile;
and</para>
<para>(e) Any other circumstances that may relate to the rehabilitation
of the juvenile.</para>
<para>(6) If, after conducting the hearing in accordance with this
section, the juvenile is not found to be satisfactorily rehabilitated such
that the record is not ordered to be sealed, a juvenile who is a person described
in section 43-2,108.01 or such
juvenile's parent or guardian may not move the court to seal the
record for one
year after the court's decision
not to seal the record is made, unless such time restriction is waived by the court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>