<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id387">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id389" statutenumber="43-407"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-407</statuteno><catchline id="id392">Office of Juvenile
Services; programs and treatment services; treatment plan; case management
and coordination process; funding utilization; intent.</catchline><para>(1) This subsection applies to all juveniles
committed to the Office of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation
and treatment center prior to July 1, 2013. The Office of Juvenile
Services shall design and make available programs and treatment services through
the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney and Youth Rehabilitation
and Treatment Center-Geneva. The programs and treatment services shall be
based upon the individual or family evaluation process and treatment plan.
The treatment plan shall be developed within fourteen days after admission.
If a juvenile placed at the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney
or Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva is assessed as needing
inpatient or subacute substance abuse or behavioral health residential treatment,
the juvenile may be transferred to a program or facility if the treatment
and security needs of the juvenile can be met. The assessment process shall
include involvement of both private and public sector behavioral health providers.
The selection of the treatment venue for each juvenile shall include individualized
case planning and incorporate the goals of the juvenile justice system pursuant
to section 43-402. Juveniles committed to the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment
Center-Kearney or Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva who are
transferred to alternative settings for treatment remain committed to the
Department of Health and Human Services and the Office of Juvenile Services
until discharged from such custody. Programs and treatment services shall
address:</para>
<para>(a) Behavioral impairments,
severe emotional disturbances, sex offender behaviors, and other mental health
or psychiatric disorders;</para>
<para>(b) Drug and alcohol addiction;</para>
<para>(c) Health and medical needs;</para>
<para>(d) Education, special education,
and related services;</para>
<para>(e) Individual, group, and
family counseling services as appropriate with any treatment plan related
to subdivisions (a) through (d) of
this subsection. Services shall
also be made available for juveniles who have been physically or sexually
abused;</para>
<para>(f) A case management and
coordination process, designed to assure appropriate reintegration of the
juvenile to his or her family, school, and community. This process shall follow
individualized planning which shall begin at intake and evaluation. Structured
programming shall be scheduled for all juveniles. This programming shall include
a strong academic program as well as classes in health education, living skills,
vocational training, behavior management and modification, money management,
family and parent responsibilities, substance abuse awareness, physical education,
job skills training, and job placement assistance. Participation shall be
required of all juveniles if such programming is determined to be age and
developmentally appropriate. The goal of such structured programming shall
be to provide the academic and life skills necessary for a juvenile to successfully
return to his or her home and community upon release; and</para>
<para>(g) The design and delivery
of treatment programs through the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers
as well as any licensing or certification requirements, and the office shall
follow the requirements as stated within Title XIX and Title IV-E of the federal
Social Security Act, as such act existed on May 25, 2007, the Special Education
Act, or other funding guidelines as appropriate. It is the intent of the Legislature
that these funding sources shall be utilized to support service needs of eligible
juveniles.</para>
<para>(2) This subsection
applies to all juveniles committed to the Office of Juvenile Services for
placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center on or after July
1, 2013. The Office of Juvenile Services shall design and make available programs
and treatment services through the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney
and Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva. The programs and treatment
services shall be based upon the individual or family evaluation process and
treatment plan. The treatment plan shall be developed within fourteen days
after admission. If a juvenile placed at the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment
Center-Kearney or Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva is assessed
as needing inpatient or subacute substance abuse or behavioral health residential
treatment, the Office of Juvenile Services may arrange for such treatment
to be provided at the Hastings Regional Center or may transition the juvenile
to another inpatient or subacute residential treatment facility in the State
of Nebraska. Except in a case requiring emergency admission to an inpatient
facility, the juvenile shall not be discharged by the Office of Juvenile Services
until the juvenile has been returned to the court for a review of his or her
conditions of probation and the juvenile has been transitioned to the clinically
appropriate level of care. Programs and treatment services shall address:</para>
<para>(a) Behavioral
impairments, severe emotional disturbances, sex offender behaviors, and other
mental health or psychiatric disorders;</para><para>(b) Drug and alcohol addiction;</para>
<para>(c) Health
and medical needs;</para><para>(d) Education, special education, and related services;</para>
<para>(e) Individual,
group, and family counseling services as appropriate with any treatment plan
related to subdivisions (a) through (d) of this subsection. Services shall
also be made available for juveniles who have been physically or sexually
abused;</para><para>(f) A case management and coordination process, designed to assure
appropriate reintegration of the juvenile to his or her family, school, and
community. This process shall follow individualized planning which shall begin
at intake and evaluation. Structured programming shall be scheduled for all
juveniles. This programming shall include a strong academic program as well
as classes in health education, living skills, vocational training, behavior
management and modification, money management, family and parent responsibilities,
substance abuse awareness, physical education, job skills training, and job
placement assistance. Participation shall be required of all juveniles if
such programming is determined to be age and developmentally appropriate.
The goal of such structured programming shall be to provide the academic and
life skills necessary for a juvenile to successfully return to his or her
home and community upon release; and</para><para>(g) The design and delivery of treatment
programs through the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers as well as
any licensing or certification requirements, and the office shall follow the
requirements as stated within Title XIX and Title IV-E of the federal Social
Security Act, as such act existed on January 1, 2013, the Special Education
Act, or other funding guidelines as appropriate. It is the intent of the Legislature
that these funding sources shall be utilized to support service needs of eligible
juveniles.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 882, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 83-925.06; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB542, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 29.</para><effectivedate>May 30, 2013</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Special Education Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1110.</para></crossreference>
  </law>
</legaldoc>