<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-274"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-274</statuteno><catchline>County attorney; preadjudication powers and duties; juvenile court petition, pretrial diversion, or mediation; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) The county attorney, having knowledge of a juvenile in his or her county who appears to be a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3), or (4) of section 43-247, may file with the clerk of the court having jurisdiction in the matter a petition in writing specifying which subdivision of section 43-247 is alleged, setting forth the facts verified by affidavit, and requesting the court to determine whether support will be ordered pursuant to section 43-290. Allegations under subdivisions (1), (2), and (4) of section 43-247 shall be made with the same specificity as a criminal complaint. It shall be sufficient if the affidavit is based upon information and belief. Such petition and all subsequent proceedings shall be entitled In the Interest of ..............., a Juvenile Under Eighteen Years of Age, inserting the juvenile's name in the blank.</para><para>(2) In all cases involving violation of a city or village ordinance, the city attorney or village prosecutor may file a petition in juvenile court. If such a petition is filed, for purposes of such proceeding, references in the Nebraska Juvenile Code to county attorney shall be construed to include a city attorney or village prosecutor.</para><para>(3) The county attorney or city attorney may offer pretrial diversion to the juvenile in accordance with a juvenile pretrial diversion program established pursuant to sections 43-260.02 to 43-260.07.</para><para>(4)(a) If a juvenile appears to be a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 because of a nonviolent act or acts, the county attorney may offer mediation to the juvenile and the victim of the juvenile's act. If both the juvenile and the victim agree to mediation, the juvenile, his or her parent, guardian, or custodian, and the victim shall sign a mediation consent form and select a mediator or approved center from the roster made available pursuant to section 25-2908. The county attorney shall refer the juvenile and the victim to such mediator or approved center. The mediation sessions shall occur within thirty days after the date the mediation referral is made unless an extension is approved by the county attorney. The juvenile or his or her parent, guardian, or custodian shall pay the mediation fees. The fee shall be determined by the mediator in private practice or by the approved center. A juvenile shall not be denied services at an approved center because of an inability to pay.</para><para>(b) Terms of the agreement shall specify monitoring, completion, and reporting requirements. The county attorney, the court, or the probation office shall be notified by the designated monitor if the juvenile does not complete the agreement within the agreement's specified time.</para><para>(c) Terms of the agreement may include one or more of the following:</para><para>(i) Participation by the juvenile in certain community service programs;</para><para>(ii) Payment of restitution by the juvenile to the victim;</para><para>(iii) Reconciliation between the juvenile and the victim; and</para><para>(iv) Any other areas of agreement.</para><para>(d) If no mediation agreement is reached, the mediator or approved center will report that fact to the county attorney within forty-eight hours of the final mediation session excluding nonjudicial days.</para><para>(e) If a mediation agreement is reached and the agreement does not violate public policy, the agreement shall be approved by the county attorney. If the agreement is not approved and the victim agrees to return to mediation (i) the juvenile may be referred back to mediation with suggestions for changes needed in the agreement to meet approval or (ii) the county attorney may proceed with the filing of a criminal charge or juvenile court petition. If the juvenile agrees to return to mediation but the victim does not agree to return to mediation, the county attorney may consider the juvenile's willingness to return to mediation when determining whether or not to file a criminal charge or a juvenile court petition.</para><para>(f) If the juvenile meets the terms of an approved mediation agreement, the county attorney shall not file a criminal charge or juvenile court petition against the juvenile for the acts for which the juvenile was referred to mediation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 638, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 43, &#167; 13.</para></source><annotation><para>Juvenile court did not err in refusing to allow an intervenor to proceed on the intervenor's petition where there was no evidence to establish the county attorney's consent to the filing of the intervenor's petition as required by this section. In re Interest of Jamie P., 12 Neb. App. 261, 670 N.W.2d 814 (2003).</para><para>A petition filed pursuant to this section, specifying facts under subsection (3)(a) of section 43-247, must allege facts which would show that a child lacks proper parental care by reason of the inadequacy of any parent whose custody or right to custody might be affected, so that both parents may understand that the litigation concerns their respective rights. In re Interest of Kelly D., 3 Neb. App. 251, 526 N.W.2d 439 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>