<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id251">
<sectno id="id252">Sec. 20.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id253" statutenumber="43-258"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id255">43-258</statuteno><catchline id="id256">Preadjudication
physical and mental evaluation; placement; restrictions; reports; costs.</catchline><para>(1) Pending the adjudication of any case under the Nebraska
Juvenile Code, the court may order the juvenile examined by a physician, surgeon,
psychiatrist, duly authorized community mental health service program, or
psychologist to aid the court in determining (a) a material allegation in
the petition relating to the juvenile's physical or mental condition, (b)
the juvenile's competence to participate in the proceedings, (c) the juvenile's
responsibility for his or her acts, or (d) whether or not to provide emergency
medical treatment.</para>
<para>(2) Pending the adjudication of any case under the Nebraska
Juvenile Code and after a showing of probable cause that the juvenile is within
the court's jurisdiction, for the purposes of subsection (1) of this section,
the court may order such juvenile to be placed in one of the facilities or
institutions of the State of Nebraska. Such juvenile shall not be placed in
an adult correctional facility, the secure youth confinement facility operated
by the Department of Correctional Services, or a youth rehabilitation and
treatment center. Any placement for evaluation may be made on a residential
or nonresidential basis for a period not to exceed thirty days except as provided
by section 43-415. The head of any facility or institution shall make a complete
evaluation of the juvenile, including any authorized area of inquiry requested
by the court. Any temporary
placement of a juvenile made under this section shall be in the least restrictive
environment consistent with the best interests of the juvenile and the safety
of the community.</para>
<para>(3) Upon completion of the evaluation, the juvenile shall
be returned to the court together with a written report of the results of
the evaluation. Such report shall include an assessment of the basic needs
of the juvenile and recommendations for continuous and long-term care and
shall be made to effectuate the purposes in subdivision (1) of section 43-246. The juvenile shall appear before the
court for a hearing on the report of the evaluation results within ten days
after the court receives the evaluation.</para>
<para>(4) In order to encourage the use of the procedure provided
in this section, all costs incurred during the period the juvenile is being
evaluated at a state facility or program funded by the Office of Juvenile
Services shall be the responsibility of the state unless otherwise ordered
by the court pursuant to section 43-290. The county in which the case is pending
shall be liable only for the cost of delivering the juvenile to the facility
or institution and the cost of returning him or her to the court for disposition.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 787, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 638, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 20.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not apply to requests for mental and physical examinations after a juvenile has been adjudicated under subsection (3)(a) of section 43-247. In re Interest of Ty M. &amp; Devon M., 265 Neb. 150, 655 N.W.2d 672 (2003).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (4) of this section, the Department of Social Services is not required to pay costs for preadjudication evaluation that is conducted at a private facility. In re Interest of Todd T., 249 Neb. 738, 545 N.W.2d 711 (1996).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>