<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-109</statuteno><catchline>Decree; conditions; content.</catchline><para>(1) If, upon the hearing, the court finds that such adoption is for
the best interests of such minor child or such adult child, a decree of adoption
shall be entered. No decree of adoption shall be entered unless (a) it appears
that the child has resided with the person or persons petitioning for such
adoption for at least six months next preceding the entering of the decree
of adoption, except that such residency requirement shall not apply in an
adoption of an adult child, (b) the medical histories required by subsection
(2) of section 43-107 have been made a part of the court record, (c) the court
record includes an affidavit or affidavits signed by the relinquishing biological
parent, or parents if both are available, in which it is affirmed that, pursuant
to section 43-106.02, prior to the relinquishment of the child for adoption,
the relinquishing parent was, or parents if both are available were, (i) presented
a copy or copies of the nonconsent form provided for in section 43-146.06
and (ii) given an explanation of the effects of filing or not filing the nonconsent
form, and (d) if the child to be adopted is committed to the Department of
Health and Human Services, the document required by subsection (3) of section
43-107 is a part of the court record. Subdivisions (b) and (c) of this subsection
shall only apply when the relinquishment or consent for an adoption is given
on or after September 1, 1988.</para>
<para>(2) If the adopted child was born out of wedlock, that fact shall not
appear in the decree of adoption.</para>
<para>(3) The court may decree such change of name for the adopted child as
the petitioner or petitioners may request.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 104, &#167; 7, p. 351; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 43-109; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 510, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 255, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 372, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 301, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 231, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB94, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB768, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The issue of the children's best interests in the context of adoption is within the dominion of the county court. Smith v. Smith, 242 Neb. 812, 497 N.W.2d 44 (1993).</para><para>A decision as to whether or not to permit adoption is required to be based on the best interests of the child. Nebraska Children's Home Soc. v. Collins, 195 Neb. 531, 239 N.W.2d 258 (1976).</para><para>Child must reside with adoptive parents at least six months preceding the rendition of decree. Hiatt v. Menendez, 157 Neb. 914, 62 N.W.2d 123 (1954).</para><para>Decree of adoption should be granted only if it will be for best interests of child. Krell v. Jenkins, 157 Neb. 554, 60 N.W.2d 613 (1953).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>