<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-512.13"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-512.13</statuteno><catchline>Title IV-D child support order; review; notice requirements; additional review.</catchline><para>(1) When review of a child support order pursuant to section 43-512.12 has been requested by one of the parents or initiated by the Department of Health and Human Services, the department shall send notice of the pending review to each parent affected by the order at the parent's last-known mailing address thirty days before the review is conducted. Such review shall require the parties to submit financial information as provided in sections 43-512.14 and 43-512.17.</para><para>(2) After the department completes the review of the child support order in accordance with section 43-512.12, it shall send notice to each parent of the determination to refer or not refer the order to the county attorney or authorized attorney for filing of an application for modification of the order in the district court. Each parent shall be allowed thirty days to submit to the department a written request for a review of such determination. The parent requesting review shall submit the request in writing to the department, stating the reasons for the request and providing written evidence to support the request. The department shall review the available verifiable financial information and make a final determination whether or not to refer the order to the county attorney or authorized attorney for filing of an application for modification of the child support order. Written notice of such final determination shall be sent to each parent affected by the order at the parent's last-known mailing address. A final determination under this subsection shall not be considered a contested case for purposes of the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 715, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 164; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 65. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>