<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-104.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-104.01</statuteno><catchline>Child born out of wedlock; biological father registry; Department of Health and Human Services; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall establish a biological father registry. The department shall maintain such registry and shall record the names and addresses of (a) any person adjudicated by a court of this state or by a court of another state or territory of the United States to be the biological father of a child born out of wedlock if a certified copy of the court order is filed with the registry by such person or any other person, (b) any putative father who has filed with the registry, prior to the receipt of notice under sections 43-104.12 to 43-104.16, a Request for Notification of Intended Adoption with respect to such child, and (c) any putative father who has filed with the registry a Notice of Objection to Adoption and Intent to Obtain Custody with respect to such child. </para><para>(2) A Request for Notification of Intended Adoption or a Notice of Objection to Adoption and Intent to Obtain Custody filed with the registry shall include (a) the putative father's name, address, and social security number, (b) the name and last-known address of the mother, (c) the month and year of the birth or the expected birth of the child, (d) the case name, court name, and location of any Nebraska court having jurisdiction over the custody of the child, and (e) a statement by the putative father that he acknowledges liability for contribution to the support and education of the child after birth and for contribution to the pregnancy-related medical expenses of the mother of the child. The person filing the notice shall notify the registry of any change of address pursuant to procedures prescribed in rules and regulations of the department.</para><para>(3) A request or notice filed under this section or section 43-104.02 shall be admissible in any action for paternity and shall estop the putative father from denying paternity of such child thereafter.</para><para>(4) Any putative father who files a Request for Notification of Intended Adoption or a Notice of Objection to Adoption and Intent to Obtain Custody with the biological father registry may revoke such filing. Upon receipt of such revocation by the registry, the effect shall be as if no filing had ever been made.</para><para>(5) The department shall not divulge the names and addresses of persons listed with the biological father registry to any other person except as authorized by law or upon order of a court of competent jurisdiction for good cause shown.</para><para>(6) The department may develop information about the registry and may distribute such information, through its existing publications, to the news media and the public. The department may provide information about the registry to the Department of Correctional Services, which may distribute such information through its existing publications.</para><para>(7) A person who has been adjudicated by a Nebraska court of competent jurisdiction to be the biological father of a child born out of wedlock who is the subject of a proposed adoption shall not be construed to be a putative father for purposes of sections 43-104.01 to 43-104.05 and shall not be subject to the provisions of such sections as applied to such fathers. Whether such person's consent is required for the proposed adoption shall be determined by the Nebraska court having jurisdiction over the custody of the child pursuant to section 43-104.22, as part of proceedings required under section 43-104 to obtain the court's consent to such adoption.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 712, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 105; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 63.</para></source></law></legaldoc>