<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id279">
<sectno id="id280">Sec. 22.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id281" statutenumber="43-278"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id283">43-278</statuteno><catchline id="id284">Adjudication
hearing; held within ninety days after petition is filed; additional reviews;
telephonic or videoconference hearing;
authorized.</catchline><para>Except as provided in sections 43-254.01
and 43-277.01, all cases filed under subdivision (3) of section 43-247 shall
have an adjudication hearing not more than ninety days after a petition is
filed. Upon a showing of good cause, the court may continue the case beyond
the ninety-day period. The court shall also review every case filed under
such subdivision which has been adjudicated or transferred to it for disposition
not less than once every six months. All communications, notices, orders,
authorizations, and requests authorized or required in the Nebraska Juvenile
Code; all nonevidentiary hearings;
and any evidentiary hearings approved by the court and by stipulation of all
parties may be heard by the court telephonically or by videoconferencing in
a manner that ensures the preservation of an accurate record. All of the orders generated by way of
a telephonic or videoconference hearing
shall be recorded as if the judge were conducting a hearing on the record.
Telephonic and videoconference hearings
allowed under this section shall not be in conflict with section 24-734.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167;  22.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>This section and section 43-271 confer a statutory right to a prompt adjudication hearing to all juveniles within section 43-247(1), (2), (3)(b), and (4). This section and section 43-271 are directory and do not require absolute discharge of a juvenile not adjudicated within the prescribed time period. In re Interest of Brandy M. et al., 250 Neb. 510, 550 N.W.2d 17 (1996).</para><para>The statutory provision requiring that an adjudication hearing be held within six months after a juvenile petition is filed is directory, not mandatory. In re Interest of C.P., 235 Neb. 276, 455 N.W.2d 138 (1990).</para><para>Section 43-271 provides a statutory right to a prompt adjudication hearing for all juveniles, but absolute discharge for the State's failure to comply with the 6-month period is not mandated and is within the discretion of the juvenile court, taking into consideration the best interests of the juvenile, the factors set forth in section 43-271 and this section, the right of the juvenile to a prompt and fair adjudication, and the future treatment and rehabilitation of the juvenile in the event of an adjudication. In re Interest of Britny S., 11 Neb. App. 704, 659 N.W.2d 831 (2003).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>