<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id355">
<sectno id="id356">Sec. 30.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id357" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-2,108.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,108.05</statuteno><catchline>Sealing of records; effect; court;
duties; inspection of records; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) If the court orders the records of
a juvenile sealed pursuant to section 43-2,108.04, the juvenile who is the
subject of the order properly may, and the court, county attorneys, city attorneys,
and institutions, persons, or agencies shall, reply that no record exists
with respect to the juvenile upon any public inquiry in the matter, and the
court shall do all of the following:</para>
<para>(a) Order
that any information or other data concerning any proceedings relating to
the arrest, taking into custody, petition, complaint, indictment, information,
trial, hearing, adjudication, correctional supervision, dismissal, or disposition
be deemed never to have occurred; and</para><para>(b) Send notice of the order to seal the
record to the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice
and, if the record includes impoundment or prohibition to obtain a license
or permit pursuant to section 43-287, to the Department of Motor Vehicles
and to any law enforcement agencies and county attorneys or city attorneys
and institutions, persons, or agencies, including treatment providers, therapists,
or other service providers, referenced in the court record and order that
all original records of the case be sealed.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3)
of this section, an order to seal the record applies to every public office
or agency that has a record relating to the case, regardless of whether it
receives notice of the hearing on the sealing of the record or a copy of the
order. Upon the written request of a person whose record has been sealed and
the presentation of a copy of such order, a public office or agency shall
seal all original records relating to the case.</para><para>(3) A sealed record is
still accessible to law enforcement officers, county attorneys, city attorneys,
and the sentencing judge in the investigation of crimes and in the prosecution
and sentencing of criminal defendants. Inspection of records that have been
ordered sealed under section 43-2,108.04 may be made only by the following
persons or for the following purposes:</para><para>(a) By the court or by any person allowed
to inspect such records by an order of the court for good cause shown;</para>
<para>(b) By the
Nebraska Probation System for purposes of juvenile intake services, for presentence
and other probation investigations, and for the direct supervision of persons
placed on probation;</para><para>(c) By the Department of Health and Human Services for purposes
of juvenile intake services, the preparation of case plans and reports, the
preparation of evaluations, or the supervision and protection of persons placed
with the department or for licensing or certification purposes under sections
71-1901 to 71-1906.01 or the Child Care Licensing Act;</para>
<para>(d) Upon application,
by the juvenile who is the subject of the sealed record and by the person
that is named in that application;</para><para>(e) At the request of a party in a civil
action that is based on a case the record for which is the subject of a sealing
order issued under section 43-2,108.04, as needed for the civil action. The
party also may copy the record as needed for the civil action. The sealed
record shall be used solely in the civil action and is otherwise confidential
and subject to this section; or</para><para>(f) By persons engaged in bona fide research,
with the permission of the court, only if the research results in no disclosure
of a juvenile's identity and protects the confidentiality of the record.</para>
<para>(4) No person
shall knowingly release, disseminate, or make available, for any purpose involving
employment, bonding, licensing, or education, to any person or to any department,
agency, or other instrumentality of the state or of any of its political subdivisions,
any information or other data concerning any arrest, taking into custody,
petition, complaint, indictment, information, trial, hearing, adjudication,
correctional supervision, dismissal, or disposition, the record of which has
been sealed pursuant to section 43-2,108.04 and the release, dissemination,
or making available of which is not expressly permitted by this section or
court order. Nothing in this section shall prohibit the Department of Health
and Human Services from releasing, disseminating, or making available information
from sealed records in the performance of its duties with respect to the supervision
and protection of persons served by the department. Any person who violates
this section may be held in contempt of court.</para><para>(5) In any application
for employment, license, or other right or privilege, any appearance as a
witness, or any other inquiry, a person cannot be questioned with respect
to any arrest or taking into custody for which the record is sealed. If an
inquiry is made in violation of this subsection, the person may respond as
if the sealed arrest or taking into custody did not occur, and the person
is not subject to any adverse action because of the arrest or taking into
custody or the response. Applications for employment shall contain specific
language that states that the applicant is not obligated to disclose a sealed
juvenile record or sentence. Employers shall not ask if an applicant has had
a juvenile record sealed. The Department of Labor shall develop a link on
the department's web site to inform employers that employers cannot ask if
an applicant had a juvenile record sealed and that an application for employment
shall contain specific language that states that the applicant is not obligated
to disclose a sealed juvenile record of arrest, custody, complaint, disposition,
diversion, adjudication, or sentence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 30.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child Care Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1908.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>