<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-104.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-104.05</statuteno><catchline>Child born out of wedlock; notice; filed; petition for adjudication of paternity; trial; guardian ad litem; court; jurisdiction.</catchline><para>(1) If a Notice of Objection to Adoption and Intent to Obtain Custody is timely filed with the biological father registry pursuant to section 43-104.02, either the putative father, the mother, or her agent specifically designated in writing shall, within thirty days after the filing of such notice, file a petition for adjudication of the notice and a determination of whether the putative father's consent to the proposed adoption is required. The petition shall be filed in the county court in the county where such child was born or, if a separate juvenile court already has jurisdiction over the custody of the child, in the county court of the county in which such separate juvenile court is located.</para><para>(2) If such a petition is not filed within thirty days after the filing of such notice and the mother of the child has executed a valid relinquishment and consent to the adoption within sixty days of the filing of such notice, the putative father's consent to adoption of the child shall not be required, he is not entitled to any further notice of the adoption proceedings, and any alleged parental rights and responsibilities of the putative father shall not be recognized thereafter in any court.</para><para>(3) After the timely filing of such petition, the court shall set a trial date upon proper notice to the parties not less than twenty nor more than thirty days after the date of such filing. If the mother contests the putative father's claim of paternity, the court shall order DNA testing to establish whether the putative father is the biological father. The court shall assess the costs of such testing between the parties in an equitable manner. Whether the putative father's consent to the adoption is required shall be determined pursuant to section 43-104.22. The court shall appoint a guardian ad litem to represent the best interests of the child.</para><para>(4)(a) The county court of the county where the child was born or the separate juvenile court having jurisdiction over the custody of the child shall have jurisdiction over proceedings under this section from the date of notice provided under section 43-104.12 or the last date of published notice under section 43-104.14, whichever notice is earlier, until thirty days after the conclusion of adoption proceedings concerning the child, including appeals, unless such jurisdiction is transferred under subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in this subdivision, the court shall, upon the motion of any party, transfer the case to the district court for further proceedings on the matters of custody, visitation, and child support with respect to such child if (i) such court determines under section 43-104.22 that the consent of the putative father is required for adoption of the minor child and the putative father refuses such consent or (ii) the mother of the child, within thirty days after the conclusion of proceedings under this section, including appeals, has not executed a valid relinquishment and consent to the adoption. The court, upon its own motion, may retain the case for good cause shown.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 224, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 712, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1041, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>A putative father who intends to claim paternity and obtain custody of a child born out of wedlock must file notice with the biological father registry and adjudicate his claim within 30 days. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>Section 43-104.02 and this section do not apply to a putative father who has been previously determined to be the biological father. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>This section requires a "claimant-father" to petition the county court where the child was born to adjudicate his claim of paternity and right to custody within 30 days of filing notice under section 43-104.02. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>Although under this section a father who fails to petition for an adjudication of paternity in county court within 30 days after filing his notice of intent to claim paternity would be precluded from claiming paternity in an adoption proceeding, such father would not be precluded from seeking to establish paternity under the paternity statutes in district court where there is no consent or relinquishment by the mother and no adoption proceeding is pending. Bohaboj v. Rausch, 272 Neb. 394, 721 N.W.2d 655 (2006).</para><para>The 30-day filing requirement of this section does not facially violate substantive due process. In re Adoption of Baby Girl H., 262 Neb. 775, 635 N.W.2d 256 (2001).</para><para>A petition to adjudicate paternity filed pursuant to this section is a matter of adoption over which the district courts have no subject matter jurisdiction. Armour v. L.H., 259 Neb. 138, 608 N.W.2d 599 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>