<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-512.14"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-512.14</statuteno><catchline>Title IV-D child support order; financial information; duty to provide; failure; effect; referral of order; effect.</catchline><para>Each parent requesting review shall provide the financial information as provided in section 43-512.17 to the Department of Health and Human Services upon request of the department. The parent requesting review shall also provide an affidavit regarding the financial circumstances of the nonrequesting parent upon the request of the department. Failure by a nonrequesting parent to provide adequate financial information shall create a rebuttable presumption that such parent's income has changed for purposes of section 43-512.12.</para><para>Referral of an order to a county attorney or authorized attorney under this section shall create a rebuttable presumption that there has been a material change in financial circumstances of one of the parents such that the child support obligation shall be increased at least ten percent if there is inadequate financial information regarding the noncustodial parent or that the child support obligation shall be decreased at least ten percent if there is inadequate financial information regarding the custodial parent. Such referral shall also be sufficient to rebut the presumption specified in section 42-364.16, and the court, after notice and an opportunity to be heard, may order a decrease or an increase of at least ten percent in the child support obligation as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 715, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 523, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 165; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 66. </para></source></law></legaldoc>