<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id126"  statutenumber="43-246.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-246.01</statuteno><catchline>Juvenile court; exclusive original and concurrent original jurisdiction.</catchline><para>The juvenile court shall have:</para><para>(1) Exclusive original jurisdiction as to:</para><para>(a) Any juvenile described in subdivision (3) or (11) of section 43-247;</para><para>(b) Any juvenile who was under sixteen years of age at the time the alleged offense was committed and the offense falls under subdivision (1) of section 43-247;</para><para>(c) A party or proceeding described in subdivision (5) or (7) of section 43-247; and</para><para>(d) Any juvenile who was under fourteen years of age at the time the alleged offense was committed and the offense falls under subdivision (2) of section 43-247;</para><para>(2) Exclusive original jurisdiction as to:</para><para>(a) Beginning January 1, 2015, any juvenile who is alleged to have committed an offense under subdivision (1) of section 43-247 and who was sixteen years of age at the time the alleged offense was committed, and beginning January 1, 2017, any juvenile who is alleged to have committed an offense under subdivision (1) of section 43-247 and who was sixteen years of age or seventeen years of age at the time the alleged offense was committed; and</para><para>(b) Any juvenile who was fourteen years of age or older at the time the alleged offense was committed and the offense falls under subdivision (2) of section 43-247 except offenses enumerated in subdivision (1)(a)(ii) of section 29-1816.</para><para>Proceedings initiated under this subdivision (2) may be transferred as provided in section 43-274; and</para><para>(3) Concurrent original jurisdiction with the county court or district court as to:</para><para>(a) Any juvenile described in subdivision (4) of section 43-247;</para><para>(b) Any proceeding under subdivision (6), (8), (9), or (10) of section 43-247;</para><para>(c) Any juvenile described in subdivision (1)(a)(ii) of section 29-1816; and</para><para>(d) Until January 1, 2017, any juvenile who is alleged to have committed an offense under subdivision (1) of section 43-247 and who was seventeen years of age at the time the alleged offense was committed.</para><para>Proceedings initiated under this subdivision (3) may be transferred as provided in section 43-274.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB265, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>County courts have not been given authority to decide motions to transfer to juvenile court in cases in which they lack jurisdiction to try the case. State v. A.D., 305 Neb. 154, 939 N.W.2d 484 (2020).</para><para>Subsection (3) of this section grants concurrent jurisdiction to the juvenile court and the county or district court over juvenile offenders who (1) are 11 years of age or older and commit a traffic offense that is not a felony or (2) are 14 years of age or older and commit a Class I, IA, IB, IC, ID, II, or IIA felony. State v. Comer, 26 Neb. App. 270, 918 N.W.2d 13 (2018).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>