<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id159"  statutenumber="43-512.12"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-512.12</statuteno><catchline id="id162">Title IV-D child support order; review by Department of Health and Human Services; when; noncustodial parent incarcerated; notice to parents.</catchline><para>(1) Child support orders in cases in which a party has applied for services under Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, shall be reviewed by the Department of Health and Human Services to determine whether to refer such orders to the county attorney or authorized attorney for filing of an application for modification. An order shall be reviewed by the department upon its own initiative or at the request of either parent when such review is required by Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, as amended. After review the department shall refer an order to a county attorney or authorized attorney when the verifiable financial information available to the department indicates:</para><para>(a) The present child support obligation varies from the Supreme Court child support guidelines pursuant to section 42-364.16 by more than the percentage, amount, or other criteria established by Supreme Court rule, and the variation is due to financial circumstances which have lasted at least three months and can reasonably be expected to last for an additional six months; or</para><para>(b) Health care coverage meeting the requirements of subsection (2) of section 42-369 is available to either party and the children do not have health care coverage other than the medical assistance program under the Medical Assistance Act.</para><para> Health care coverage cases may be modified within three years of entry of the order.</para><para>(2) Orders that are not addressed under subsection (1) of this section shall not be reviewed by the department if it has not been three years since the present child support obligation was ordered unless the requesting party demonstrates a substantial change in circumstances that is expected to last for the applicable time period established by subdivision (1)(a) of this section. Such substantial change in circumstances may include, but is not limited to, change in employment, earning capacity, or income or receipt of an ongoing source of income from a pension, gift, or lottery winnings. An order may be reviewed after one year if the department's determination after the previous review was not to refer to the county attorney or authorized attorney for filing of an application for modification because financial circumstances had not lasted or were not expected to last for the time periods established by subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding the time periods set forth in subdivision (1)(a) of this section, within fifteen business days of learning that a noncustodial parent will be incarcerated for more than one hundred eighty calendar days, the department shall send notice by first-class mail to both parents informing them of the right to request the state to review and, if appropriate, adjust the order. Such notice shall be sent to the incarcerated parent at the address of the facility at which the parent is incarcerated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 715, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 523, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 163; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB702, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Medical Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 68-901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>