<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-101"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>43-101</statuteno><catchline>Children eligible for adoption; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to sections 43-101 to 43-115 and except as otherwise provided in the Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act and subsections (4) and (5) of this section:</para><para>(a) Any minor child may be adopted by any adult person or persons;</para><para>(b) Any minor child may be adopted by the spouse of such child's parent; and</para><para>(c) Any minor child who has a sole legal parent may be adopted by a second adult person if:</para><para>(i) The sole legal parent consents as provided in section 43-104;</para><para>(ii) The child has a parent-child relationship with the second adult person;</para><para>(iii) The child is the biological child of the second adult person;</para><para>(iv) The second adult person has not previously had such person's parental rights to such child terminated; and</para><para>(v) An adoptive home study is completed as provided in section 43-107.</para><para>(2) Subject to sections 43-101 to 43-115 and except as otherwise provided in subsections (4) and (5) of this section:</para><para>(a) Any adult child may be adopted by the spouse of such adult child's parent; and</para><para>(b) The adoption of an adult child by another adult or adults who are not the stepparent of the adult child may be permitted if the adult child has had a parent-child relationship with the prospective parent or parents for a period of at least six months next preceding the adult child's age of majority and:</para><para>(i) The adult child has no living parents;</para><para>(ii) The adult child's parent or parents had been deprived of parental rights to such child by the order of any court of competent jurisdiction;</para><para>(iii) The parent or parents, if living, have relinquished the adult child for adoption by a written instrument;</para><para>(iv) The parent or parents had abandoned the child for at least six months next preceding the adult child's age of majority or for a substantial portion of the time since the adult child reached the age of majority;</para><para>(v) The parent or parents are incapable of consenting; or</para><para>(vi) The adult child has a sole legal parent who consents as provided in section 43-104.</para><para>(3) The substitute consent provisions of section 43-105 do not apply to adoptions under subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) No person with a spouse may adopt a minor child or an adult child unless the spouse of such person joins in the petition for adoption, in which case the adoption shall be made by such persons jointly.</para><para>(5) An adoption shall not be permitted under this section if it would result in a minor or adult child having more than two legal parents.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 104, &#167; 1, p. 349; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 43-101; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 510, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 255, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB741, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB70, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1501.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The plain language of this section allows a same-sex married couple to adopt a minor child. In re Adoption of Yasmin S., 308 Neb. 771, 956 N.W.2d 704 (2021).</para><para>Adoption proceedings are special proceedings. In re Adoption of David C., 280 Neb. 719, 790 N.W.2d 205 (2010).</para><para>For an adoption to be valid under Nebraska's adoption statutes, the record must show the following factors: (1) the existence of an adult person or persons entitled to adopt, (2) the existence of a child eligible for adoption, (3) compliance with statutory procedures providing for adoption, and (4) evidence that the proposed adoption is in the child's best interests. Reading the adoption statutes in their entirety, it is clear that aside from the stepparent adoption scenario, the parents' parental rights must be terminated or the existing nonterminated parent or parents must relinquish in order for the child to be eligible for adoption by any adult person or persons under this section. In re Adoption of Luke, 263 Neb. 365, 640 N.W.2d 374 (2002).</para><para>Husband and wife should join in petition for adoption. Hiatt v. Menendez, 157 Neb. 914, 62 N.W.2d 123 (1954).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>