<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id14">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id16" statutenumber="43-104.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-104.02</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Child born
out of wedlock; Notice of Objection to Adoption and Intent to Obtain Custody;
filing requirements.</catchline><para>A Notice of Objection to Adoption
and Intent to Obtain Custody shall be filed with the biological father registry
under section 43-104.01 on forms provided by the Department of Health and
Human Services (1) at any time during the pregnancy and no
later than five business days after the birth of the child or
(2) if the notice required by section 43-104.13 is
provided after the birth of the child (a) at any time during the pregnancy and no
later than five business days after receipt of the notice provided
under section 43-104.12 or (b) no later than five business
days after the last date of any published notice provided under section 43-104.14,
whichever notice is earlier. Such notice shall be considered to have been
filed if it is received by the department or postmarked prior to the end of
the fifth business day as provided in this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 224, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 712, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 106; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 97; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB908, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>Where the biological mother deliberately misrepresented or withheld information regarding the date of her child's birth to prevent the biological father from timely objecting to the adoption of the child, the biological mother could not use requirements in this section as a subterfuge for deception to prevent the biological father from objecting to the adoption. Jeremiah J. v. Dakota D., 285 Neb. 211, 826 N.W.2d 242 (2013).</para><para>A putative father who intends to claim paternity and obtain custody of a child born out of wedlock must file notice with the biological father registry and adjudicate his claim within 30 days. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>Section 43-102.05 requires a "claimant-father" to petition the county court where the child was born to adjudicate his claim of paternity and right to custody within 30 days of filing notice under this section. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>This section and section 43-104.05 do not apply to a putative father who has been previously determined to be the biological father. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>This section, by its very terms, has no application in a dispute between the biological father and mother of a child born out of wedlock. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>This section does not apply to a biological father opposing the adoption of his child who is no longer a newborn when the father had acknowledged and supported his child and established strong familial ties. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>This section requires "a person claiming to be the father of the child" to file notice of his intent to claim paternity and obtain custody with the biological father registry within 5 business days of the child's birth or published notification. In re Adoption of Jaden M., 272 Neb. 789, 725 N.W.2d 410 (2006).</para><para>Five-day filing requirement for paternity held constitutional as applied, because such requirement did not violate right of equal protection or procedural due process. Friehe v. Schaad, 249 Neb. 825, 545 N.W.2d 740 (1996).</para><para>This section held unconstitutional as applied in this case. In re Application of S.R.S. and M.B.S., 225 Neb. 759, 408 N.W.2d 272 (1987).</para><para>Five-day claim provision does not apply to a dispute between the father and mother of a child born out of wedlock. White v. Mertens, 225 Neb. 241, 404 N.W.2d 410 (1987).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>