<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id541">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id543" statutenumber="43-423"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-423</statuteno><catchline id="id546">Parole violation
hearing; requirements; appeal.</catchline><para>This section applies to all juveniles committed to the Office
of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment
center prior to July 1, 2013. At the parole violation hearing,
the hearing officer shall again advise the juvenile of his or her rights and
ensure that the juvenile has received the notice of allegations and the possible
consequences. Strict rules of evidence shall not be applied. The hearing officer
shall determine whether the detention of the juvenile or other restrictions
are necessary for the safety of the juvenile or for the public safety and
shall indicate to what extent the juvenile will continue to be detained or
restricted pending a final decision and administrative appeal. The hearing
officer shall issue a written recommended disposition to the Administrator
of the Office of Juvenile Services or his or her designee who shall promptly
affirm, modify, or reverse the recommended disposition. The final decision
of the administrator or his or her designee may be appealed pursuant to the
Administrative Procedure Act. The Department of Health and Human Services
shall be deemed to have acted within its jurisdiction if its action is in
the best interests of the juvenile with due consideration being given to public
safety. The appeal shall in all other respects be governed by the Administrative
Procedure Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 43.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  
<annotation><para>If a juvenile court revokes a juvenile's parole, rather than the Office of Juvenile Services, a juvenile is not granted all of the rights to which he or she was entitled. In re Interest of Sylvester L., 17 Neb. App. 791, 770 N.W.2d 669 (2009).</para></annotation>
</law>
</legaldoc>