<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id22" statutenumber="43-2,108.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,108.03</statuteno><catchline id="id25">Sealing of records; county attorney or city attorney; duties; motion to seal record authorized.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01 was taken into custody, arrested, cited in lieu of arrest, or referred for prosecution without citation but no juvenile petition or criminal complaint was filed against the juvenile with respect to the arrest or custody, the county attorney or city attorney shall notify the government agency responsible for the arrest, custody, citation in lieu of arrest, or referral for prosecution without citation that no criminal charge or juvenile court petition was filed. The county attorney or city attorney shall provide written notification to the juvenile that no juvenile petition or criminal complaint was filed and provide the juvenile with the notice described in section 43-2,108.02.</para><para>(b) If a juvenile described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section discovers that his or her record was not automatically sealed, such juvenile may notify the county attorney, who shall cause the record to be sealed by providing the notice required by subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(2)(a) If the county attorney or city attorney offered and a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01 has agreed to pretrial diversion, mediation, or restorative justice, the county attorney or city attorney shall notify the government agency responsible for the arrest or custody when the juvenile has satisfactorily completed the resulting diversion, mediation, or restorative justice. At the time the juvenile is offered diversion, mediation, or restorative justice, the county attorney or city attorney shall provide the notice described in section 43-2,108.02 to the juvenile. The county attorney or city attorney shall also provide written notification to the juvenile of his or her satisfactory or unsatisfactory completion of diversion, mediation, or restorative justice.</para><para>(b) If a juvenile who was satisfactorily discharged from diversion, mediation, or restorative justice discovers that his or her record was not automatically sealed, the juvenile may notify the county attorney, who shall cause the record to be sealed by providing the notice required by subdivision (2)(a) of this section.</para><para>(3)(a) If the juvenile was taken into custody, arrested, cited in lieu of arrest, or referred for prosecution without citation and charges were filed but the case was dismissed by the court, the court shall seal the record as set forth in section 43-2,108.05.</para><para>(b) If a juvenile described in subdivision (3)(a) discovers that his or her record was not automatically sealed, the juvenile may notify the court, which shall seal the record as set forth in section 43-2,108.05.</para><para>(4)(a) If a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01 has satisfactorily completed the probation, supervision, or other treatment or rehabilitation program provided under the Nebraska Juvenile Code or if the juvenile has satisfactorily completed the probation or sentence ordered by a county court, the court shall seal the records as set forth in section 43-2,108.05.</para><para>(b) If a juvenile described in subdivision (4)(a) discovers that his or her record was not automatically sealed, the juvenile may notify the court, which shall seal the record as set forth in section 43-2,108.05. </para><para>(5) A government agency or court that receives notice under subdivision (1)(a) or (2)(a) of this section shall, upon such receipt, immediately seal all records housed at that government agency or court pertaining to the citation, arrest, record of custody, complaint, disposition, diversion, mediation, or restorative justice.</para><para>(6) When a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01 whose records have not been automatically sealed as provided in subsection (1), (2), (3), or (4) of this section reaches the age of majority or six months have passed since the case was closed, whichever occurs sooner, such juvenile or his or her parent or guardian may file a motion in the court of record asking the court to seal the record pertaining to the offense which resulted in disposition, adjudication, or diversion in juvenile court or diversion or sentence of the county court. The motion shall set forth the facts supporting the argument that the individual who is the subject of the juvenile petition or criminal complaint has been satisfactorily rehabilitated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB354, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB595, &#167; 34. </para></source><annotation><para>An order sealing a juvenile record must demonstrate that the county attorney was given the required notice of the proceeding to seal the record. In re Interest of Candice H., 284 Neb. 935, 824 N.W.2d 34 (2012).</para><para>An order sealing a juvenile record must include a finding that the juvenile had satisfactorily completed probation. In re Interest of Candice H., 284 Neb. 935, 824 N.W.2d 34 (2012).</para><para>The requirements of this section must be met before a juvenile court can order that a record be sealed. In re Interest of Candice H., 284 Neb. 935, 824 N.W.2d 34 (2012).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>