<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id6" statutenumber="43-247.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>43-247.02</statuteno><catchline>Juvenile court; placement or commitment of juveniles; Department of Health and Human Services; Office of Juvenile Services; authority and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of Nebraska law, on and after October 1, 2013, a juvenile court shall not:</para><para>(a) Place any juvenile adjudicated or pending adjudication under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 with the Department of Health and Human Services or the Office of Juvenile Services, other than as allowed under subsection (2) or (3) of this section;</para><para>(b) Commit any juvenile adjudicated or pending adjudication under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 to the care and custody of the Department of Health and Human Services or the Office of Juvenile Services, other than as allowed under subsection (2) or (3) of this section;</para><para>(c) Require the Department of Health and Human Services or the Office of Juvenile Services to supervise any juvenile adjudicated or pending adjudication under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247, other than as allowed under subsection (2) or (3) of this section; or</para><para>(d) Require the Department of Health and Human Services or the Office of Juvenile Services to provide, arrange for, or pay for any services for any juvenile adjudicated or pending adjudication under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247, or for any party to cases under those subdivisions, other than as allowed under subsection (2) or (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding any other provision of Nebraska law, on and after July 1, 2013, a juvenile court shall not commit a juvenile to the Office of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center except as part of an order of intensive supervised probation under subsection (1) of section 43-286.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the authority or duties of the Department of Health and Human Services in relation to juveniles adjudicated under subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 who were committed to the care and custody of the Department of Health and Human Services prior to October 1, 2013, to the Office of Juvenile Services for community-based services prior to October 1, 2013, or to the Office of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center prior to July 1, 2013. The care and custody of such juveniles with the Department of Health and Human Services or the Office of Juvenile Services shall continue in accordance with the Nebraska Juvenile Code and the Juvenile Services Act as such acts existed on January 1, 2013, until:</para><para>(a) The juvenile reaches the age of majority;</para><para>(b) The juvenile is no longer under the care and custody of the department pursuant to a court order or for any other reason, a guardian other than the department is appointed for the juvenile, or the juvenile is adopted;</para><para>(c) The juvenile is discharged pursuant to section 43-412, as such section existed on January 1, 2013; or</para><para>(d) A juvenile court terminates its jurisdiction of the juvenile.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1148, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Juvenile Services Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>For purposes of this section, the date a juvenile is committed to the Office of Juvenile Services for treatment is controlling, not the date of a subsequent transfer to a youth rehabilitation and treatment center. In re Interest of Marcella G., 287 Neb. 566, 847 N.W.2d 276 (2014).</para><para>Where a juvenile was committed to the Office of Juvenile Services for community-based services before July 1, 2013, a juvenile court's transfer of the juvenile after that date to a youth rehabilitation and treatment center was not required to be made as a condition of intensive supervised probation. In re Interest of Marcella G., 287 Neb. 566, 847 N.W.2d 276 (2014).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>