<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id235">
<sectno id="id236">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id237" statutenumber="43-254.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id239">43-254.01</statuteno><catchline id="id240">Temporary
mental health placement; evaluation; procedure.</catchline><para>(1)
Any time a juvenile is temporarily placed at a mental health facility pursuant
to subsection (3) of section
43-250 or by a court as a juvenile who is mentally ill and dangerous, a mental
health professional as defined in section 71-906 shall evaluate the mental
condition of the juvenile as soon as reasonably possible but not later than
thirty-six hours after the juvenile's admission, unless the juvenile was evaluated
by a mental health professional immediately prior to the juvenile being placed
in temporary custody and the temporary custody is based upon the conclusions
of that evaluation. The mental health professional who performed the evaluation
prior to the temporary custody or immediately after the temporary custody
shall, without delay, convey the results of his or her evaluation to the county
attorney.</para>
<para>(2) If it is the judgment of the mental health professional
that the juvenile is not mentally ill and dangerous or that the harm described
in section 71-908 is not likely to occur before the matter may be heard by
a juvenile court, the mental health professional shall immediately notify
the county attorney of that conclusion and the county attorney shall either
proceed to hearing before the court within twenty-four hours or order the
immediate release of the juvenile from temporary custody. Such release shall
not prevent the county attorney from proceeding on the petition if he or she
so chooses.</para>
<para>(3) A juvenile taken into temporary protective custody under subsection (3) of section
43-250 shall have the opportunity to proceed to adjudication hearing within
seven days unless the matter is continued. Continuances shall be liberally
granted at the request of the juvenile, his or her guardian ad litem, attorney,
parents, or guardian. Continuances may be granted to permit the juvenile an
opportunity to obtain voluntary treatment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>