<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id300">
<sectno id="id301">Sec. 24.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id302" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-287"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>43-287</statuteno><catchline>Impoundment of permit issued under
Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act; other powers of court; copy of abstract
to Department of Motor Vehicles; fine for excessive absenteeism from school.</catchline><para>(1) When a juvenile
is adjudged to be a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or
(4) of section 43-247, the juvenile court may:</para>
<para>(a) If such
juvenile has one or more licenses or permits issued under the Motor Vehicle
Operator's License Act, impound any such licenses or permits for thirty days;
or</para><para>(b) If such juvenile does not have a permit or license issued under
the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act, prohibit such juvenile from obtaining
any permit or any license pursuant to the act for which such juvenile would
otherwise be eligible until thirty days after the date of such order.</para>
<para>(2) A copy of
an abstract of the juvenile court's adjudication shall be transmitted to the
Director of Motor Vehicles pursuant to sections 60-497.01 to 60-497.04 if
a license or permit is impounded or a juvenile is prohibited from obtaining
a license or permit under subsection (1) of this section. If a juvenile whose
operator's license or permit has been impounded by a juvenile court operates
a motor vehicle during any period that he or she is subject to the court order
not to operate any motor vehicle or after a period of impoundment but before
return of the license or permit, such violation shall be handled in the juvenile
court and not as a violation of section 60-4,108.</para><para>(3) When a juvenile is adjudged
to be a juvenile described in subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247 for excessive
absenteeism from school, the juvenile court may issue the parents or guardians
of such juvenile a fine not to exceed five hundred dollars for each offense
or order such parents or guardians to complete specified hours of community
service. For community service ordered under this subsection, the juvenile
court may require that all or part of the service be performed for a public
school district or nonpublic school if the court finds that service in the
school is appropriate under the circumstances.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 24.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act,</emphasis> see section 60-462.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>