<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id69">
<sectno id="id70" opdate="October 1, 2009">Sec. 9.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id71" statutenumber="43-512.07"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id73">43-512.07</statuteno><catchline id="id74">Assignment
of child, spousal, or medical support payments; when; duration; notice; unpaid
court-ordered support; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) Any action,
payment, aid, or assistance listed in this subsection shall constitute an assignment
by operation of law to the Department of Health and Human Services of any
right to spousal or medical support, when
ordered by the court, and
to child support, whether
or not ordered by the court, which
a person may have in his or
her own behalf or on behalf of any other person for whom such
person receives such payments, aid, or assistance:</para>
<para>(a) Application for and acceptance of one or more aid to dependent
children payments by a parent, another relative, or a custodian;</para>
<para>(b) Receipt of aid by or on behalf of any dependent child
as defined in section 43-504; or</para>
<para>(c) Receipt of aid from child welfare funds.</para>
<para>The assignment
under this section is the right to support payments that become due while
the person is receiving payments, aid, or assistance listed in this subsection. The
department shall be entitled to retain such child, spousal, or other support
up to the amount of payments, aid, or assistance provided to a recipient.
For purposes of this section, the right to receive child support shall belong
to the child and the assignment shall be effective as to any such support
even if the recipient of the payments, aid, or assistance is not the same
as the payee of court-ordered support.</para>
<para>(2) After notification of the State Disbursement Unit receiving
the child, spousal, or other support payments made pursuant to a court order
that the person for whom such support is ordered is a recipient of payments,
aid, or assistance listed in subsection (1) of this section, the department
shall also give notice to the payee named in the court order at his or her
last-known address.</para>
<para>(3) Upon written or other notification from the department
or from another state of such assignment of child, spousal, or other support
payments, the State Disbursement Unit shall transmit the support payments
received to the department or the other state without the requirement of a
subsequent order by the court. The State Disbursement Unit shall continue
to transmit the support payments for as long as the payments, aid, or assistance
listed in subsection (1) of this section continues.</para>
<para>(4) Any court-ordered child, spousal, or other support remaining
unpaid for
the months during which such payments, aid, or assistance was made shall
constitute a debt and a continuing assignment at the termination of payments,
aid, or assistance listed in subsection (1) of this section, collectible by
the department or other state as reimbursement for such payments, aid, or
assistance. The continuing assignment shall only
apply to support payments made during a calendar period which exceed the specific
amount of support ordered for that period. When payments, aid, or assistance
listed in subsection (1) of this section have ceased and upon notice by the
department or the other state, the State Disbursement Unit shall continue
to transmit to the department or the other state any support payments received in excess of
the amount of support ordered for that specific calendar period until notified
by the department or the other state that the debt has been paid in full.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 926, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 345, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 600, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 599, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 435, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 524, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 161; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 972, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>