<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id13" statutenumber="43-2,108.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,108.02</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Sealing of records; notice to juvenile; contents.</catchline><para>(1) By January 1, 2020, the Supreme Court shall promulgate a written notice that:</para><para>(a) States in developmentally appropriate language that, for a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01, the juvenile's record will be automatically sealed if (i) no charges are filed as a result of the determination of the prosecuting attorney, (ii) the charges are dismissed, (iii) the juvenile has satisfactorily completed the diversion, mediation, restorative justice, probation, supervision, or other treatment or rehabilitation program provided under the Nebraska Juvenile Code, or (iv) the juvenile has satisfactorily completed the county court diversion program, probation ordered by the court, or sentence ordered by the court;</para><para>(b) States in developmentally appropriate language that, if the record is not sealed as provided in subdivision (1)(a) of this section, the juvenile or the juvenile's parent or guardian may file a motion to seal the record with the court when the juvenile reaches the age of majority or six months have passed since the case was closed, whichever occurs sooner; and</para><para>(c) Explains in developmentally appropriate language what sealing the record means.</para><para>(2) For a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01, the county attorney or city attorney shall attach a copy of the notice to any juvenile petition or criminal complaint.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB354, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB595, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>