<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-287"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-287</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Impoundment of license or permit issued under
Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act; other powers of court; copy of abstract
to Department of Motor Vehicles; fine for excessive absenteeism from school; not eligible for ignition interlock
permit.</catchline><para>(1) When a juvenile is adjudged
to be a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section
43-247, the juvenile court may:</para>
<para>(a) If such juvenile holds
any license or permit issued under the Motor Vehicle Operator's
License Act, impound any such license
or permit for thirty days; or</para>
<para>(b) If such juvenile does not have a permit or license issued
under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act, prohibit such juvenile from
obtaining any permit or any license pursuant to the act for which such juvenile
would otherwise be eligible until thirty days after the date of such order.</para>
<para>(2) A copy of an abstract of the juvenile court's adjudication
shall be transmitted to the Director of Motor Vehicles pursuant to sections
60-497.01 to 60-497.04 if a license or permit is impounded or a juvenile is
prohibited from obtaining a license or permit under subsection (1) of this
section. If a juvenile whose operator's license or permit has been impounded
by a juvenile court operates a motor vehicle during any period that he or
she is subject to the court order not to operate any motor vehicle or after
a period of impoundment but before return of the license or permit, such violation
shall be handled in the juvenile court and not as a violation of section 60-4,108.</para>
<para>(3) When a juvenile is adjudged to be a juvenile described
in subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247 for excessive absenteeism from school,
the juvenile court may issue the parents or guardians of such juvenile a fine
not to exceed five hundred dollars for each offense or order such parents
or guardians to complete specified hours of community service. For community
service ordered under this subsection, the juvenile court may require that
all or part of the service be performed for a public school district or nonpublic
school if the court finds that service in the school is appropriate under
the circumstances.</para>
<para>(4) A juvenile
who holds any license or permit issued under the Motor Vehicle Operator's
License Act and has violated subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-306,
subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-394, or section 28-1254, 60-6,196,
60-6,197, or 60-6,197.06 shall not be eligible for an ignition interlock permit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 5.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act,</emphasis> see section 60-462.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>