<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id235">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id237" statutenumber="43-279.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-279.01</statuteno><catchline id="id240">Juvenile
in need of assistance or termination of parental rights; rights of parties; appointment of counsel; court; powers; proceedings.</catchline>
<para>(1) When the petition alleges the juvenile to be within the
provisions of subdivision (3)(a) of section 43-247 or when termination of
parental rights is sought pursuant to subdivision (6) of section 43-247 and the parent, custodian,
or guardian appears with or without counsel, the court shall inform
the parties of the:</para>
<para>(a) Nature of the proceedings and the possible consequences
or dispositions pursuant to sections 43-284, 43-285, and 43-288 to 43-295;</para>
<para>(b) Right of
the parent to engage counsel of his or her choice at his or her own expense or to have counsel appointed
if the parent is unable
to afford to hire a lawyer;</para>
<para>(c) Right
of a stepparent, custodian, or guardian to engage counsel of his or her choice
and, if there are allegations against the stepparent, custodian, or guardian
or when the petition is amended to include such allegations, to have counsel
appointed if the stepparent, custodian, or guardian is unable to afford to
hire a lawyer;</para><para>(d) Right
to remain silent as to any matter of inquiry if the testimony sought to be
elicited might tend to prove the party guilty
of any crime;</para>
<para>(e) Right to confront and
cross-examine witnesses;</para>
<para>(f) Right to testify and to
compel other witnesses to attend and testify;</para>
<para>(g) Right to a speedy adjudication
hearing; and</para>
<para>(h) Right to appeal and have
a transcript or record of the proceedings for such purpose.</para>
<para>(2) The court
shall have the discretion as to whether or not to appoint counsel for a person
who is not a party to the proceeding. If counsel is appointed, failure of
the party to maintain contact with his or her court-appointed counsel or to
keep such counsel advised of the party's current address may result in the
counsel being discharged by the court.</para><para>(3) After giving the parties the information
prescribed in subsection (1) of this section, the court may accept an in-court
admission, an answer of no contest, or a denial from any parent, custodian,
or guardian as to all or any part of the allegations in the petition.
The court shall ascertain a factual basis for an admission or an answer of
no contest.</para>
<para>(4) In the case of a denial,
the court shall allow a reasonable time for preparation if needed and then
proceed to determine the question of whether the juvenile falls under the
provisions of section 43-247 as alleged. After hearing the evidence, the court
shall make a finding and adjudication to be entered on the records of the
court as to whether the allegations in the petition have been proven by a
preponderance of the evidence in cases under subdivision (3)(a) of section
43-247 or by clear and convincing evidence in proceedings to terminate parental
rights. If an Indian child is involved, the standard of proof shall be in
compliance with the Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act, if applicable.</para>
<para>(5) If the court shall find
that the allegations of the petition or motion have not been proven by the
requisite standard of proof, it shall dismiss the case or motion. If the court
sustains the petition or motion, it shall allow a reasonable time for preparation
if needed and then proceed to inquire into the matter of the proper disposition
to be made of the juvenile.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 22, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 18.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1501.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Due Process</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Due Process</emphasis></para><para>If a parent has been afforded procedural due process at an adjudication hearing, allowing a parent who is incarcerated or otherwise confined in custody of a government to attend the adjudication is within the discretion of the trial court, whose decision will be upheld in the absence of an abuse of discretion. In re Interest of Mainor T. &amp; Estela T., 267 Neb. 232, 674 N.W.2d 442 (2004).</para><para>Adequate notice of the possibility of the termination of parental rights must be given in adjudication hearings before the juvenile court may accept an in-court admission, an answer of no contest, or a denial from a parent. A parent in a juvenile court case has the right to appointed counsel if unable to hire a lawyer. In re Interest of N.M. and J.M., 240 Neb. 690, 484 N.W.2d 77 (1992).</para><para>Eight-month delay between the time when the child is "temporarily" taken from the child's parent until an adjudication hearing is held cannot be condoned, even when the parties agree to repeated continuances. In re Interest of D.M.B., 240 Neb. 349, 481 N.W.2d 905 (1992).</para><para>To determine whether due process requires the assistance of counsel for the parent in a temporary detention proceeding under sections 43-247(3)(a) and 43-254, the court must weigh the interest of the parent, the interest of the State, and the risk of erroneous decision given the procedures in use. In re Interest of R.R., 239 Neb. 250, 475 N.W.2d 518 (1991).</para><para>The statutory provision requiring that an adjudication hearing be held within six months after a juvenile petition is filed is directory, not mandatory. In re Interest of C.P., 235 Neb. 276, 455 N.W.2d 138 (1990).</para><para>The trial court's failure to advise a mother of her rights, of the possible dispositions, or of the nature of juvenile court proceedings arising from the State's petition alleging that the mother inappropriately disciplined her 20-month-old child and that the child was without proper parental care through the mother's fault or habits violated the mother's due process rights, even though the mother vigorously defended against the charges. In re Interest of Billie B., 8 Neb. App. 791, 601 N.W.2d 799 (1999).</para><para>Failure to advise a party to a termination hearing of his or her rights as delineated in this section requires reversal of the order of termination. In re Interest of Joelyann H., 6 Neb. App. 472, 574 N.W.2d 185 (1998).</para><para>Failure of a court to provide the parties with explanations and warnings as mandated by this section results in a denial of due process. In re Interest of A.D.S. and A.D.S., 2 Neb. App. 469, 511 N.W.2d 208 (1994).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The lower standard of proof under subsection (3) of this section for the termination of parental rights to non-Indian children, as opposed to the higher standard of proof under the Nebraska Indian Child Welfare Act, sections 43-1501 to 43-1516, does not violate the equal protection rights of parents of non-Indian children. In re Interest of Phoenix L. et al., 270 Neb. 870, 708 N.W.2d 786 (2006).</para><para>Juvenile courts do not need to conduct an inquiry as to the whereabouts of every respondent parent who fails to appear for a scheduled hearing. In most situations, the burden to notify the juvenile court of a parent's incarceration or confinement is properly placed on the parent or the parent's attorney. In re Interest of Mainor T. &amp; Estela T., 267 Neb. 232, 674 N.W.2d 442 (2004).</para><para>Subsection (1) of this section states in part that when a petition alleges a juvenile to be within the provisions of subsection (3)(a) of section 43-247 and the parent or custodian appears with or without counsel, the court shall inform the parties of the right to confront and cross-examine witnesses. Subsection (3) of this section provides that when adjudicating whether a juvenile is dependent or neglected within the purview of subsection (3)(a) of section 43-247, the State must establish its allegations by a preponderance of the evidence. In re Interest of Danielle D. et al., 257 Neb. 198, 595 N.W.2d 544 (1999).</para><para>A ruling refusing to permit the withdrawal of an answer of no contest filed pursuant to the provisions of this section is not a final, appealable order. In re Interest of C.D.A., 231 Neb. 267, 435 N.W.2d 681 (1989).</para><para>Burden of proof and standard of proof are interchangeable terms. In re Interest of Jaden H., 10 Neb. App. 87, 625 N.W.2d 218 (2001).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>