<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id348">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id350" statutenumber="43-407">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-407</statuteno><catchline id="id353">Office of Juvenile
Services; programs and treatment services; treatment plan; case management
and coordination process; funding utilization; intent; implement evidence-based practices, policies, and procedures;
report; contents; Executive Board of Legislative Council; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) This subsection applies to all juveniles committed to
the Office of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and
treatment center prior to July 1, 2013. The Office of Juvenile Services shall
design and make available programs and treatment services through the Youth
Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney and Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment
Center-Geneva. The programs and treatment services shall be based upon the
individual or family evaluation process and treatment plan. The treatment
plan shall be developed within fourteen days after admission. If a juvenile
placed at the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney or Youth Rehabilitation
and Treatment Center-Geneva is assessed as needing inpatient or subacute substance
abuse or behavioral health residential treatment, the juvenile may be transferred
to a program or facility if the treatment and security needs of the juvenile
can be met. The assessment process shall include involvement of both private
and public sector behavioral health providers. The selection of the treatment
venue for each juvenile shall include individualized case planning and incorporate
the goals of the juvenile justice system pursuant to section 43-402. Juveniles
committed to the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney or Youth
Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva who are transferred to alternative
settings for treatment remain committed to the Department of Health and Human
Services and the Office of Juvenile Services until discharged from such custody.
Programs and treatment services shall address:</para>
<para>(a) Behavioral impairments, severe emotional disturbances,
sex offender behaviors, and other mental health or psychiatric disorders;</para>
<para>(b) Drug and alcohol addiction;</para>
<para>(c) Health and medical needs;</para>
<para>(d) Education, special education, and related services;</para>
<para>(e) Individual, group, and family counseling services as
appropriate with any treatment plan related to subdivisions (a) through (d)
of this subsection. Services shall also be made available for juveniles who
have been physically or sexually abused;</para>
<para>(f) A case management and coordination process, designed
to assure appropriate reintegration of the juvenile to his or her family,
school, and community. This process shall follow individualized planning which
shall begin at intake and evaluation. Structured programming shall be scheduled
for all juveniles. This programming shall include a strong academic program
as well as classes in health education, living skills, vocational training,
behavior management and modification, money management, family and parent
responsibilities, substance abuse awareness, physical education, job skills
training, and job placement assistance. Participation shall be required of
all juveniles if such programming is determined to be age and developmentally
appropriate. The goal of such structured programming shall be to provide the
academic and life skills necessary for a juvenile to successfully return to
his or her home and community upon release; and</para>
<para>(g) The design and delivery of treatment programs through
the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers as well as any licensing or
certification requirements, and the office shall follow the requirements as
stated within Title XIX and Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act,
as such act existed on May 25, 2007, the Special Education Act, or other funding
guidelines as appropriate. It is the intent of the Legislature that these
funding sources shall be utilized to support service needs of eligible juveniles.</para>
<para>(2) This subsection applies to all juveniles committed to
the Office of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and
treatment center on or after July 1, 2013. The Office of Juvenile Services
shall design and make available programs and treatment services through the
Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney and Youth Rehabilitation
and Treatment Center-Geneva. The programs and treatment services shall be
based upon the individual or family evaluation process and treatment plan.
The treatment plan shall be developed within fourteen days after admission.
If a juvenile placed at the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney
or Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva is assessed as needing
inpatient or subacute substance abuse or behavioral health residential treatment,
the Office of Juvenile Services may arrange for such treatment to be provided
at the Hastings Regional Center or may transition the juvenile to another
inpatient or subacute residential treatment facility in the State of Nebraska.
Except in a case requiring emergency admission to an inpatient facility, the
juvenile shall not be discharged by the Office of Juvenile Services until
the juvenile has been returned to the court for a review of his or her conditions
of probation and the juvenile has been transitioned to the clinically appropriate
level of care. Programs and treatment services shall address:</para>
<para>(a) Behavioral impairments, severe emotional disturbances,
sex offender behaviors, and other mental health or psychiatric disorders;</para>
<para>(b) Drug and alcohol addiction;</para>
<para>(c) Health and medical needs;</para>
<para>(d) Education, special education, and related services;</para>
<para>(e) Individual, group, and family counseling services as
appropriate with any treatment plan related to subdivisions (a) through (d)
of this subsection. Services shall also be made available for juveniles who
have been physically or sexually abused;</para>
<para>(f) A case management and coordination process, designed
to assure appropriate reintegration of the juvenile to his or her family,
school, and community. This process shall follow individualized planning which
shall begin at intake and evaluation. Structured programming shall be scheduled
for all juveniles. This programming shall include a strong academic program
as well as classes in health education, living skills, vocational training,
behavior management and modification, money management, family and parent
responsibilities, substance abuse awareness, physical education, job skills
training, and job placement assistance. Participation shall be required of
all juveniles if such programming is determined to be age and developmentally
appropriate. The goal of such structured programming shall be to provide the
academic and life skills necessary for a juvenile to successfully return to
his or her home and community upon release; and</para>
<para>(g) The design and delivery of treatment programs through
the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers as well as any licensing or
certification requirements, and the office shall follow the requirements as
stated within Title XIX and Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act,
as such act existed on January 1, 2013, the Special Education Act, or other
funding guidelines as appropriate. It is the intent of the Legislature that
these funding sources shall be utilized to support service needs of eligible
juveniles.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The
Office of Juvenile Services shall begin implementing evidence-based practices,
policies, and procedures by January 15, 2016, as determined by the office.
Thereafter, on November 1 of each year, the office shall submit to the Governor,
the Legislature, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, a comprehensive
report on its efforts to implement evidence-based practices. The report to
the Legislature shall be by electronic transmission. The report may be attached
to preexisting reporting duties. The report shall include at a minimum:</para>
<para>(i) The percentage
of juveniles being supervised in accordance with evidence-based practices;</para>
<para>(ii) The percentage
of state funds expended by each respective department for programs that are
evidence-based, and a list of all programs which are evidence-based;</para>
<para>(iii) Specification
of supervision policies, procedures, programs, and practices that were created,
modified, or eliminated; and</para><para>(iv) Recommendations of the office for
any additional collaboration with other state, regional, or local public agencies,
private entities, or faith-based and community organizations.</para>
<para>(b) Each report
and executive summary shall be available to the general public on the web
site of the office.</para><para>(c) The Executive Board of the Legislative Council may request
the Consortium for Crime and Justice Research and Juvenile Justice Institute
at the University of Nebraska at Omaha to review, study, and make policy recommendations
on the reports assigned by the executive board.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 882, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 83-925.06; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB542, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 27.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2014</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Special Education Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1110.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>