<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id990"><amendatorysection statutenumber="43-286.02" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>43-286.02</statuteno><catchline>Comprehensive supervision probationer; designation; hearing; conditions; services; dual involvement; coordination.</catchline><para>(1) If a juvenile court decides to place a juvenile on probation, the court shall conduct a hearing to determine whether the juvenile should be designated as a comprehensive supervision probationer. The hearing may be conducted together with the dispositional hearing or following a motion to revoke probation following the procedures provided in subdivision (5)(b) of section 43-286.</para><para>(2) The court shall designate a juvenile as a comprehensive supervision probationer if the court determines that the juvenile is unlikely to respond effectively to graduated response sanctions under section 43-286.01, taking into account:</para><para>(a) The nature of the adjudication;</para><para>(b) The effectiveness of any past interventions or sanctions;</para><para>(c) The pre-disposition investigation by the probation officer; and</para><para>(d) The recommendation from the county attorney or city attorney, including any input from law enforcement.</para><para>(3) Comprehensive supervision probationers shall receive prioritized services that assist with early identification of needs and intensive supports, such as therapeutic services, educational and vocational assistance, family engagement, mentorship, and behavioral interventions. When a youth is dually involved in both the probation and child welfare systems, the Office of Probation Administration shall work with the Department of Health and Human Services to ensure coordinated and adequate service delivery.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB530, &#167; 16. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>