<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id6" statutenumber="43-2,108.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,108.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Sealing of records; juveniles eligible.</catchline><para>(1) Sections 43-2,108.01 to 43-2,108.05 apply only to persons who were under the age of eighteen years when the offense took place and, after being taken into custody, arrested, cited in lieu of arrest, or referred for prosecution without citation, the county attorney or city attorney: </para><para>(a) Declined to file a juvenile petition or criminal complaint;</para><para>(b) Offered juvenile pretrial diversion, mediation, or restorative justice to the juvenile under the Nebraska Juvenile Code;</para><para>(c) Filed a juvenile court petition describing the juvenile as a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247;</para><para>(d) Filed a criminal complaint in county court against the juvenile under state statute or city or village ordinance for misdemeanor or infraction possession of marijuana or misdemeanor or infraction possession of drug paraphernalia;</para><para>(e) Filed a criminal complaint in county court against the juvenile for any other misdemeanor or infraction under state statute or city or village ordinance, other than for a traffic offense, when all offenses in the case are waivable offenses; or</para><para>(f) Filed a criminal complaint in county or district court for a felony offense under state law or a city or village ordinance that was subsequently transferred to juvenile court for ongoing jurisdiction.</para><para>(2) The changes made by Laws 2019, LB354, to the relief set forth in sections 43-2,108.03 to 43-2,108.05 shall apply to all persons described in this section, as amended by Laws 2019, LB354, for offenses occurring prior to, on, or after September 1, 2019.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB354, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB595, &#167; 32. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB354, section 2, with LB595, section 32, to reflect all amendments.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>