<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id119">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id121" statutenumber="43-289"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-289</statuteno><catchline id="id124">Juvenile committed;
release from confinement upon reaching age of majority; hospital treatment;
custody in state institutions; discharge.</catchline><para>In no
case shall a juvenile committed under the terms of the Nebraska Juvenile Code
be confined after he or she reaches the age of majority. The court may, when
the health or condition of any juvenile adjudged to be within the terms of
such code shall require it, cause the juvenile to be placed in a public hospital
or institution for treatment or special care or in an accredited and suitable
private hospital or institution which will receive the juvenile for like purposes.
Whenever any juvenile has been committed to the Department of Health and Human
Services, the department shall follow the court's orders, if any, concerning
the juvenile's specific needs for treatment or special care for his or her
physical well-being and healthy personality. If the court finds any such juvenile
to be a person with an
intellectual disability, the court may, upon attaching a physician's
certificate and a report as to the mental capacity of such person, commit
such juvenile directly to an authorized and appropriate state or local facility
or home.</para>
<para>The marriage of any juvenile committed to a state institution
under the age of nineteen years shall not make such juvenile of the age of
majority.</para>
<para>A juvenile committed to any such institution shall be subject
to the control of the superintendent thereof, and the superintendent, with
the advice and consent of the Department of Health and Human Services, shall
adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the promotion, paroling, and
final discharge of residents such as shall be considered mutually beneficial
for the institution and the residents. Upon final discharge of any resident,
such department shall file a certified copy of the discharge with the court
which committed the resident.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1177, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 182, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 141; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>