<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id374">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id376" statutenumber="43-406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-406</statuteno><catchline id="id379">Office of Juvenile
Services; treatment programs, services, and systems; requirements.</catchline><para>The Office of Juvenile Services shall utilize:</para>
<para>(1) Risk and needs assessment instruments for use in determining
the level of treatment for the juvenile;</para>
<para>(2) A case classification process to include levels of treatment
defined by rules and regulations and case management standards for each level
of treatment. The process shall provide for a balance of accountability, public
safety, and treatment;</para>
<para>(3) Case management for all juveniles committed to the office;</para>
<para>(4) Until July 1, 2014, a purchase-of-care
system which will facilitate the development of a statewide community-based
array of care with the involvement of the private sector and the local public
sector. Care services may be purchased from private providers to provide a
wider diversity of services. This system shall include accessing existing
Title IV-E funds of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, medicaid
funds, and other funding sources to support eligible community-based services.
Such services developed and purchased shall include, but not be limited to,
evaluation services. Services shall be offered and delivered on a regional
basis;</para>
<para>(5) Until October 1, 2013, community-based evaluation
programs, supplemented by one or more residential evaluation programs. A residential
evaluation program shall be provided in a county containing a city of the
metropolitan class. Community-based evaluation services shall replace the
residential evaluation services available at the Youth Diagnostic and Rehabilitation
Center by December 31, 1999; and</para>
<para>(6) A management information system. The system shall be
a unified, interdepartmental client information system which supports the
management function as well as the service function.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 371, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1141, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 229; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 882, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 83-925.07; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>