<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate=" April 14, 2010">Sec. 26.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id5" statutenumber="43-512.15"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">43-512.15</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Title IV-D child
support order; modification; when; procedures.</catchline><para>(1) The county
attorney or authorized attorney, upon referral from the Department of Health
and Human Services, shall file a complaint to modify a child support order
unless the attorney determines in the exercise of independent professional
judgment that:</para>
<para>(a) The variation from the Supreme Court child support guidelines pursuant
to section 42-364.16 is based on material misrepresentation of fact concerning
any financial information submitted to the attorney;</para>
<para>(b) The variation from the guidelines is due to a voluntary reduction
in net monthly income. For purposes of this section, a person who has been
incarcerated for a period of one year or more in a county or city jail or
a federal or state correctional facility shall be considered to have an involuntary
reduction of income unless (i) the incarceration is a result of a conviction
for criminal nonsupport pursuant to section 28-706 or a conviction for a violation
of any federal law or law of another state substantially similar to section
28-706, (ii) the incarcerated individual has a documented record of willfully
failing or neglecting to provide proper support which he or she knew or reasonably
should have known he or she was legally obligated to provide when he or she
had sufficient resources to provide such support, or (iii) the incarceration
is a result of a conviction for a crime in which the child who is the subject
of the child support order was victimized; or</para>
<para>(c) When the amount of the order is considered with all the other undisputed
facts in the case, no variation from the criteria set forth in subdivisions (1)(a) and (b) of section 43-512.12 exists.</para>
<para>(2) The department, a county attorney, or an authorized attorney shall
not in any case be responsible for reviewing or filing an application to modify
child support for individuals incarcerated as described in subdivision (1)(b)
of this section.</para>
<para>(3) The proceedings to modify a child support order shall comply with
section 42-364, and the county attorney or authorized attorney shall represent
the state in the proceedings.</para>
<para>(4) After a complaint to modify a child support order is filed, any
party may choose to be represented personally by private counsel. Any party
who retains private counsel shall so notify the county attorney or authorized
attorney in writing.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 715, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 523, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 166; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1207, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 26.</para></source>
<annotation>
<para>An individual who has been incarcerated for the minimum period of time specified in this section may file a complaint seeking modification of his or her child support obligation upon the basis that his or her incarceration is an involuntary reduction of income, unless the circumstances contained in subsection (1)(b) of this section are met. Rouse v. Rouse, 18 Neb. App. 128, 775 N.W.2d 457 (2009).</para>
<para>The statutory minimum period of incarceration is not limited to that occurring after sentencing, because a person continuously jailed while awaiting trial faces the same reduction in income as a person continuously incarcerated after sentencing. Rouse v. Rouse, 18 Neb. App. 128, 775 N.W.2d 457 (2009).</para>
<para>A child support obligor's incarceration is considered an involuntary reduction in income for purposes of modification when the obligor has been incarcerated for the statutorily specified minimum period of time, unless the circumstances contained in subsection (1)(b) of this section are met. Hopkins v. Stauffer, 18 Neb. App. 116, 775 N.W.2d 462 (2009).</para>
</annotation>
  </law>
</legaldoc>