<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id414"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-428"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>43-428</statuteno><catchline>Youth rehabilitation and treatment center; emergency plan.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall develop an emergency plan for the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva, the Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney, and any other facility operated and utilized as a youth rehabilitation and treatment center in compliance with state law.</para><para>(2) Each emergency plan shall:</para><para>(a) Identify and designate temporary placement facilities for the placement of juveniles in the event a youth rehabilitation and treatment center must be evacuated due to an emergency as defined in section 43-403. The administrator of a proposed temporary placement facility shall consent to be designated as a temporary placement facility in the emergency plan. A criminal detention facility or a juvenile detention facility shall only be designated as a temporary placement facility pursuant to section 43-430;</para><para>(b) Identify barriers to implementation of an effective emergency plan, including necessary administrative or legislative changes;</para><para>(c) Include procedures for the Office of Juvenile Services to provide reliable, effective, and timely notification that an emergency plan is to be implemented to:</para><para>(i) Staff at the youth rehabilitation and treatment center where the emergency plan is implemented and the administrator and staff at the temporary placement facility;</para><para>(ii) Juveniles placed at the youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(iii) Families and legal guardians of juveniles placed at the youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(iv) The State Court Administrator, in a form and manner prescribed by the State Court Administrator;</para><para>(v) The committing court of each juvenile placed at the youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(vi) The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature; and</para><para>(vii) The office of Public Counsel and the office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare;</para><para>(d) Detail the plan for transportation of juveniles to a temporary placement facility; and</para><para>(e) Include methods and schedules for implementing the emergency plan.</para><para>(3) Each emergency plan shall be developed on or before December 15, 2020.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1140, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>