<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id411" statutenumber="43-408"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>43-408</statuteno><catchline id="id414">Office of Juvenile Services; committing court; powers and duties; commitment review; hearing; annual review of commitment and placement; review status; when.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any juvenile is committed to the Office of Juvenile Services, the juvenile shall also be considered committed to the care and custody of the Department of Health and Human Services for the purpose of obtaining health care and treatment services.</para><para>(2) The committing court may order placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center for a juvenile committed to the Office of Juvenile Services following a commitment hearing pursuant to subdivision (1)(b)(iii) of section 43-286. The court shall continue to maintain jurisdiction over any juvenile committed to the Office of Juvenile Services, and the office shall provide the court and parties of record with the initial treatment plan and monthly updates regarding the progress of the juvenile.</para><para>(3) In addition to the hearings set forth in section 43-285, during a juvenile's term of commitment, any party may file a motion for commitment review to bring the case before the court for consideration of the juvenile's commitment to a youth rehabilitation and treatment center. A hearing shall be scheduled no later than thirty days after the filing of such motion. No later than five days prior to the hearing, the office shall provide information to the parties regarding the juvenile's individualized treatment plan and progress. A representative of the office or facility shall be physically present at the hearing to provide information to the court unless the court allows the representative to appear telephonically or by video. The juvenile and the juvenile's parent or guardian shall have the right to be physically present at the hearing. The court may enter such orders regarding the juvenile's care and treatment as are necessary and in the best interests of the juvenile, including an order for early discharge from commitment when appropriate. In entering an order for early discharge from commitment to intensive supervised probation in the community, the court shall consider to what extent:</para><para>(a) The juvenile has completed the goals of the juvenile's individualized treatment plan or received maximum benefit from institutional treatment;</para><para>(b) The juvenile would benefit from continued services under community supervision;</para><para>(c) The juvenile can function in a community setting with appropriate supports; and</para><para>(d) There is reason to believe that the juvenile will not commit further violations of law and will comply with the terms of intensive supervised probation.</para><para>(4) Each juvenile committed to the Office of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center shall also be entitled to an annual review of such commitment and placement for as long as the juvenile remains so committed and placed. At an annual review hearing, the court shall consider the factors described in subsection (3) of this section to assess the juvenile's progress and determine whether commitment remains in the best interests of the juvenile.</para><para>(5) If a juvenile is placed in detention while awaiting placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center and the placement has not occurred within fourteen days, the committing court shall hold a hearing every fourteen days to review the status of the juvenile. Placement of a juvenile in detention shall not be considered a treatment service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 962; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 83-925.12; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 598, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1148, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1188, &#167; 7. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB1148, section 13, with LB1188, section 7, to reflect all amendments.</note></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (2) of this section and section 43-247, a juvenile court has jurisdiction over an adjudicated juvenile whom the court has placed at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center. But despite that jurisdiction, subsection (2) of this section prohibits a juvenile court from reviewing the progress of a juvenile whom the court has placed at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center. In re Interest of Trey H., 281 Neb. 760, 798 N.W.2d 607 (2011).</para><para>When a court adjudicates a juvenile under section 43-247(2) and (3) and commits the juvenile to the Office of Juvenile Services with a placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center, it has determined that the subsection (2) adjudication will control the juvenile's disposition. The disposition determination controls which review hearing statute applies, and the requirement in section 43-278 for 6-month review hearings does not authorize the court to conduct review hearings. Instead, the prohibition in subsection (2) of this section of review hearings for juveniles placed at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center controls. In re Interest of Trey H., 281 Neb. 760, 798 N.W.2d 607 (2011).</para><para>Giving effect to the language of this section, while the Office of Juvenile Services may make an initial determination with regard to the advisability of the discharge of a juvenile committed to that office, the committing court, as a result of its statutorily imposed continuing jurisdiction, must approve the discharge of the juvenile. In re Interest of Tamantha S., 267 Neb. 78, 672 N.W.2d 24 (2003).</para><para>A juvenile court does not have the authority to enter an order prohibiting any change without prior court approval in the placement of a juvenile committed to the custody of the Office of Juvenile Services. In re Interest of Chelsey D., 14 Neb. App. 392, 707 N.W.2d 798 (2005).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>