<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id186" statutenumber="43-274"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>43-274</statuteno><catchline id="id189">County attorney; city attorney; preadjudication powers and duties; petition, pretrial diversion, or mediation; transfer; procedures; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) The county attorney or city attorney, having knowledge of a juvenile within his or her jurisdiction who appears to be a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 and taking into consideration the criteria in section 43-276, may proceed as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) The county attorney or city attorney may offer pretrial diversion to the juvenile in accordance with a juvenile pretrial diversion program established pursuant to sections 43-260.02 to 43-260.07.</para><para>(3)(a) If a juvenile appears to be a juvenile described in subdivision (1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 because of a nonviolent act or acts, the county attorney or city attorney may offer mediation to the juvenile and the victim of the juvenile's act. If both the juvenile and the victim agree to mediation, the juvenile, his or her parent, guardian, or custodian, and the victim shall sign a mediation consent form and select a mediator or approved center from the roster made available pursuant to section 25-2908. The county attorney or city attorney shall refer the juvenile and the victim to such mediator or approved center. The mediation sessions shall occur within thirty days after the date the mediation referral is made unless an extension is approved by the county attorney or city attorney. The juvenile or his or her parent, guardian, or custodian shall pay the mediation fees. The fee shall be determined by the mediator in private practice or by the approved center. A juvenile shall not be denied services at an approved center because of an inability to pay.</para><para>(b) Terms of the mediation agreement shall specify monitoring, completion, and reporting requirements. The county attorney or city attorney, the court, or the probation office shall be notified by the designated monitor if the juvenile does not complete the agreement within the agreement's specified time.</para><para>(c) Terms of the agreement may include one or more of the following:</para><para>(i) Participation by the juvenile in certain community service programs;</para><para>(ii) Payment of restitution by the juvenile to the victim;</para><para>(iii) Reconciliation between the juvenile and the victim; and</para><para>(iv) Any other areas of agreement.</para><para>(d) If no mediation agreement is reached, the mediator or approved center will report that fact to the county attorney or city attorney within forty-eight hours of the final mediation session excluding nonjudicial days.</para><para>(e) If a mediation agreement is reached and the agreement does not violate public policy, the agreement shall be approved by the county attorney or city attorney. If the agreement is not approved and the victim agrees to return to mediation (i) the juvenile may be referred back to mediation with suggestions for changes needed in the agreement to meet approval or (ii) the county attorney or city attorney may proceed with the filing of a criminal charge or juvenile court petition. If the juvenile agrees to return to mediation but the victim does not agree to return to mediation, the county attorney or city attorney may consider the juvenile's willingness to return to mediation when determining whether or not to file a criminal charge or a juvenile court petition.</para><para>(f) If the juvenile meets the terms of an approved mediation agreement, the county attorney or city attorney shall not file a criminal charge or juvenile court petition against the juvenile for the acts for which the juvenile was referred to mediation.</para><para>(4) The county attorney or city attorney shall file the petition in the court with jurisdiction as outlined in section 43-246.01.</para><para>(5) When a transfer from juvenile court to county court or district court is authorized because there is concurrent jurisdiction, the county attorney or city attorney may move to transfer the proceedings. Such motion shall be filed with the juvenile court petition unless otherwise permitted for good cause shown. The juvenile court shall schedule a hearing on such motion within fifteen days after the motion is filed. The county attorney or city attorney has the burden by a preponderance of the evidence to show why such proceeding should be transferred. The juvenile shall be represented by counsel at the hearing and may present the evidence as to why the proceeding should be retained. After considering all the evidence and reasons presented by both parties, the juvenile court shall retain the proceeding unless the court determines that a preponderance of the evidence shows that the proceeding should be transferred to the county court or district court. The court shall make a decision on the motion within thirty days after the hearing. The juvenile court shall set forth findings for the reason for its decision.</para><para>An order granting or denying transfer of the case from juvenile court to county or district court shall be considered a final order for the purposes of appeal. Upon the entry of an order, any party may appeal to the Court of Appeals within ten days. Such review shall be advanced on the court docket without an extension of time granted to any party except upon a showing of exceptional cause. Appeals shall be submitted, assigned, and scheduled for oral argument as soon as the appellee's brief is due to be filed. The Court of Appeals shall conduct its review in an expedited manner and shall render the judgment and opinion, if any, as speedily as possible. During the pendency of any such appeal, the juvenile court may continue to enter temporary orders in the best interests of the juvenile pursuant to section 43-295.</para><para> If the proceeding is transferred from juvenile court to the county court or district court, the county attorney or city attorney shall file a criminal information in the county court or district court, as appropriate, and the accused shall be arraigned as provided for a person eighteen years of age or older in subdivision (1)(b) of section 29-1816.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 638, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 43, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB11, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Subsection (1) of this section authorizes a county attorney with knowledge of a juvenile in his or her county falling within the purview of section 43-247(3)(a) to file a petition in that county's juvenile court. In re Interest of Tegan V., 18 Neb. App. 857, 794 N.W.2d 190 (2011).</para><para>Juvenile court did not err in refusing to allow an intervenor to proceed on the intervenor's petition where there was no evidence to establish the county attorney's consent to the filing of the intervenor's petition as required by this section. In re Interest of Jamie P., 12 Neb. App. 261, 670 N.W.2d 814 (2003).</para><para>A petition filed pursuant to this section, specifying facts under subsection (3)(a) of section 43-247, must allege facts which would show that a child lacks proper parental care by reason of the inadequacy of any parent whose custody or right to custody might be affected, so that both parents may understand that the litigation concerns their respective rights. In re Interest of Kelly D., 3 Neb. App. 251, 526 N.W.2d 439 (1994).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>