<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id176" statutenumber="43-260.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>43-260.04</statuteno><catchline id="id179">Juvenile pretrial diversion program; requirements.</catchline><para>A juvenile pretrial diversion program shall:</para><para>(1) Be an option available for the county attorney or city attorney based upon his or her determination under this subdivision. The county attorney or city attorney may use the following information:</para><para>(a) The juvenile's age;</para><para>(b) The nature of the offense and role of the juvenile in the offense;</para><para>(c) The number and nature of previous offenses involving the juvenile;</para><para>(d) The dangerousness or threat posed by the juvenile to persons or property; or</para><para>(e) The recommendations of the referring agency, victim, and advocates for the juvenile;</para><para>(2) Permit participation by a juvenile only on a voluntary basis and shall include a juvenile diversion agreement described in section 43-260.06;</para><para>(3) Allow the juvenile to consult with counsel prior to a decision to participate in the program;</para><para>(4) Be offered to the juvenile when practicable prior to the filing of a juvenile petition or a criminal charge but after the arrest of the juvenile or issuance of a citation to the juvenile if after the arrest or citation a decision has been made by the county attorney or city attorney that the offense will support the filing of a juvenile petition or criminal charges;</para><para>(5) Provide screening services for use in creating a diversion plan utilizing appropriate services for the juvenile;</para><para>(6) Result in dismissal of the juvenile petition or criminal charges if the juvenile successfully completes the program;</para><para>(7) Be designed and operated to further the goals stated in section 43-260.03 and comply with sections 43-260.04 to 43-260.07;</para><para>(8) Require information received by the program regarding the juvenile to remain confidential unless a release of information is signed upon admission to the program or is otherwise authorized by law; and</para><para>(9)(a) Respond to a public inquiry in the same manner as if there were no information or records concerning participation in the diversion program. Information or records pertaining to participation in the diversion program shall not be disseminated to any person other than:</para><para>(i) A criminal justice agency as defined in section 29-3509;</para><para>(ii) The individual who is the subject of the record or any persons authorized by such individual; or</para><para>(iii) Other persons or agencies authorized by law.</para><para>(b) An individual, a person, or an agency requesting information subject to subdivision (9)(a) of this section shall provide the diversion program with satisfactory verification of his, her, or its identity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 43, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB354, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>