<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-419"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-419</statuteno><catchline>Parole violation; preliminary hearing.</catchline><para>(1) When a juvenile is apprehended and detained for an alleged violation of juvenile parole, he or she shall have a preliminary hearing as soon as practicable and no later than within seventy-two hours of being apprehended and detained. An impartial hearing officer shall conduct the preliminary hearing. The impartial hearing officer shall not be the juvenile parole officer alleging the violation of parole or a witness to the alleged violation. The impartial hearing officer may be an employee of the Office of Juvenile Services, including a supervisor or a juvenile parole officer, other than the parole officer filing the allegations.</para><para>(2) The juvenile parolee shall receive notice of the preliminary hearing, its purpose, and the alleged violations prior to the commencement of the hearing. The juvenile parolee may present relevant information, question adverse witnesses, and make a statement regarding the alleged parole violations. The rules of evidence shall not apply at such hearings and the hearing officer may rely upon any available information.</para><para>(3) The hearing officer shall determine whether there is probable cause to believe that the juvenile has violated a term or condition of his or her parole and shall issue that decision in writing. The decision shall either indicate there is not probable cause to believe that the juvenile parolee has violated the terms of his or her parole and dismiss the allegations and return the juvenile to parole supervision, or it shall indicate there is probable cause to believe that the juvenile has violated a condition of parole and state where the juvenile will be held pending the revocation hearing. The preliminary hearing officer shall consider the seriousness of the alleged violation, the public safety, and the best interests of the juvenile in determining where the juvenile shall be held pending the revocation hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 51. </para></source></law></legaldoc>