<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id22" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-2,108.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2,108.03</statuteno><catchline id="id25">Sealing of
records; county attorney or city attorney; duties; motion to seal record authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) If a juvenile described
in section 43-2,108.01 was taken into custody, arrested, cited in lieu of arrest, or referred
for prosecution without citation but no juvenile petition or criminal
complaint was filed against the juvenile with respect to the arrest or custody,
the county attorney or city attorney shall notify the government agency responsible for the arrest, custody,
citation in lieu of arrest, or referral for prosecution without citation that
no criminal charge or juvenile court petition was filed.</para>
<para>(2) If the county attorney or city attorney offered and a juvenile described in section 43-2,108.01 has
agreed to pretrial diversion or mediation, the county attorney or city attorney
shall notify the government agency
responsible for the arrest or custody when the juvenile has satisfactorily
completed the resulting diversion or mediation.</para>
<para>(3) If the
juvenile was taken into custody, arrested, cited in lieu of arrest, or referred
for prosecution without citation and charges were filed but later dismissed
and any required pretrial diversion or mediation for any related charges have
been completed and no related charges remain under the jurisdiction of the
court, the county attorney or city attorney shall notify the government agency
responsible for the arrest, custody, citation in lieu of arrest, or referral
for prosecution without citation and the court where the charge or petition
was filed that the charge or juvenile court petition was dismissed.</para>
<para>(4) Upon receiving notice
under subsection (1), (2), or (3) of this section, the government agency or court shall immediately seal all records housed at
that government agency or court pertaining to the
citation, arrest, record of custody, complaint, disposition, diversion, or
mediation.</para>
<para>(5) If a juvenile described
in section 43-2,108.01 has satisfactorily completed such juvenile's probation,
supervision, or other treatment or rehabilitation program provided under the
Nebraska Juvenile Code or has satisfactorily completed such juvenile's diversion
or sentence in county court:</para>
<para>(a) The court
may initiate proceedings pursuant to section 43-2,108.04 to seal the record
pertaining to such disposition or adjudication under the juvenile code or
sentence of the county court; and</para><para>(b) If the juvenile has attained the age of seventeen
years, the court shall initiate proceedings pursuant
to section 43-2,108.04 to seal the record pertaining to such disposition or adjudication under the juvenile
code or diversion or sentence of the county court, except that the court is not required to initiate proceedings
to seal a record pertaining to a misdemeanor or infraction not described in
subdivision (4) of section 43-2,108.01 under a city or village ordinance that
has no possible jail sentence. Such a record may be sealed under subsection
(6) of this section.</para>
<para>(6) If a juvenile
described in section 43-2,108.01 has satisfactorily completed diversion, mediation,
probation, supervision, or other treatment or rehabilitation program provided
under the Nebraska Juvenile Code or has satisfactorily completed the diversion
or sentence ordered by a county court, the juvenile or the juvenile's parent
or guardian may file a motion in the court of record asking the court to seal
the record pertaining to the offense which resulted in such disposition, adjudication,
or diversion of the juvenile court or diversion or sentence of the county
court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB463, &#167; 8.</para></source><annotation><para>An order sealing a juvenile record must demonstrate that the county attorney was given the required notice of the proceeding to seal the record. In re Interest of Candice H., 284 Neb. 935, 824 N.W.2d 34 (2012).</para><para>An order sealing a juvenile record must include a finding that the juvenile had satisfactorily completed probation. In re Interest of Candice H., 284 Neb. 935, 824 N.W.2d 34 (2012).</para><para>The requirements of this section must be met before a juvenile court can order that a record be sealed. In re Interest of Candice H., 284 Neb. 935, 824 N.W.2d 34 (2012).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>