<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-153"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-153</statuteno><catchline>Child with special needs; medical assistance identification; how obtained; payment; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A child with special needs residing in this state who is the subject of an adoption assistance agreement with another state shall be entitled to receive a medical assistance identification from this state upon the filing with the department of a certified copy of the adoption assistance agreement obtained from the adoption assistance state. In accordance with rules and regulations of the department, the adoptive parents shall be required at least annually to show that the agreement is still in force or has been renewed.</para><para>(2) The department shall consider the holder of a medical assistance identification pursuant to this section the same as any other holder of a medical assistance identification under the laws of this state and shall process and make payment on claims on account of such holder in the same manner and pursuant to the same conditions and procedures as for other recipients of medical assistance.</para><para>(3) Any person who by means of a willfully false statement or representation or by impersonation or other device obtains or attempts to obtain or who aids or abets any other person in obtaining assistance under sections 43-147 to 43-154 shall, upon conviction thereof, be punished pursuant to section 68-1017.</para><para>(4) This section shall apply only to medical assistance for children under adoption assistance agreements from states that have entered into a compact with this state under which the other state provides medical assistance to children with special needs under adoption assistance agreements made by this state. All other children entitled to medical assistance pursuant to adoption assistance agreements entered into by this state shall be eligible to receive it in accordance with the laws and procedures applicable thereto.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>