<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id356">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id358" statutenumber="43-405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-405</statuteno><catchline id="id361">Office of Juvenile
Services; administrative duties.</catchline><para>The administrative
duties of the Office of Juvenile Services are to:</para>
<para>(1) Manage, establish policies for, and administer the office,
including all facilities and programs operated by the office or provided through
the office by contract with a provider;</para>
<para>(2) Supervise employees of the office, including employees
of the facilities and programs operated by the office;</para>
<para>(3) Have separate budgeting procedures and develop and report
budget information separately from the Department of Health and Human Services;</para>
<para>(4) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the levels
of treatment and for management, control, screening, treatment, rehabilitation, transfer, discharge, evaluation until October 1, 2013, and parole until July
1, 2014, of juveniles placed with or committed to the Office of
Juvenile Services;</para>
<para>(5) Ensure that statistical information concerning juveniles
placed with or committed to facilities or programs of the office is collected,
developed, and maintained for purposes of research and the development of
treatment programs;</para>
<para>(6) Monitor commitments, placements, and evaluations at facilities
and programs operated by the office or through contracts with providers and
submit electronically an annual report of its findings to the Legislature.
For 2012, 2013, and 2014, the office shall also provide an electronic copy of the report to the Health
and Human Services Committee of the Legislature on or before September 15.
The report shall include an assessment of the administrative costs of operating
the facilities, the cost of programming, the savings realized through reductions
in commitments, placements, and evaluations, and information regarding the
collaboration required by section 83-101;</para>
<para>(7) Coordinate the programs and services of the juvenile
justice system with other governmental agencies and political subdivisions;</para>
<para>(8) Coordinate educational, vocational, and social counseling;</para>
<para>(9) Until July 1, 2014, coordinate community-based
services for juveniles and their families;</para>
<para>(10) Until July 1, 2014, supervise and
coordinate juvenile parole and aftercare services; and</para>
<para>(11) Exercise all powers and perform all duties necessary
to carry out its responsibilities under the Health and Human Services, Office
of Juvenile Services Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB972, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 27.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>