<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id159">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id161" statutenumber="43-258">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-258</statuteno><catchline id="id164">Preadjudication
physical and mental evaluation; placement; restrictions; reports; costs.</catchline><para>(1)
Pending the adjudication of any case under the Nebraska Juvenile Code, the
court may order the juvenile examined by a physician, surgeon, psychiatrist,
duly authorized community mental health service program, or psychologist to
aid the court in determining (a) a material allegation in the petition relating
to the juvenile's physical or mental condition, (b) the juvenile's competence
to participate in the proceedings, (c) the juvenile's responsibility for his
or her acts, or (d) whether or not to provide emergency medical treatment.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Pending the adjudication of any case under the Nebraska
Juvenile Code and after a showing of probable cause that the juvenile is within
the court's jurisdiction, for the purposes of subsection (1) of this section,
the court may order such juvenile to be placed with the Department of Health
and Human Services for evaluation, except that on and after October 1, 2013,
no juvenile alleged to be a juvenile as described in subdivision (1), (2),
(3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 shall be placed with the Department of Health
and Human Services. If a juvenile is placed with the Department of Health
and Human Services under this subdivision, the department shall make arrangements
for an appropriate evaluation. The department shall determine whether the
evaluation will be made on a residential or nonresidential basis. Placement
with the department for the purposes of this section shall be for a period
not to exceed thirty days. If necessary to complete the evaluation, the court
may order an extension not to exceed an additional thirty days. Any temporary
placement of a juvenile made under this section shall be in the least restrictive
environment consistent with the best interests of the juvenile and the safety
of the community.</para>
<para>(b) Beginning October 1, 2013, pending the adjudication of
any case in which a juvenile is alleged to be a juvenile as described in subdivision
(1), (2), (3)(b), or (4) of section 43-247 and after a showing of probable
cause that the juvenile is within the court's jurisdiction, for the purposes
of subsection (1) of this section, the court may order an evaluation to be arranged by the Office of Probation
Administration. Any temporary placement of a juvenile made
under this section shall be in the least restrictive environment consistent
with the best interests of the juvenile and the safety of the community.</para>
<para>(3) Upon completion of the evaluation, the juvenile shall
be returned to the court together with a written or electronic report of the results of the evaluation.
Such report shall include an assessment of the basic needs of the juvenile
and recommendations for continuous and long-term care and shall be made to
effectuate the purposes in subdivision (1) of section 43-246. The juvenile
shall appear before the court for a hearing on the report of the evaluation
results within ten days after the court receives the evaluation.</para>
<para>(4) During any period of detention or evaluation prior to
adjudication, costs incurred
on behalf of a juvenile shall be paid as provided in section 43-290.01.</para>
<para>(5) The court
shall provide copies of the evaluation report and any evaluations of the juvenile
to the juvenile's attorney and the county attorney or city attorney prior
to any hearing in which the report or evaluation will be relied upon.</para>

</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 346, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 787, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 638, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB669, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 13.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not apply to requests for mental and physical examinations after a juvenile has been adjudicated under subsection (3)(a) of section 43-247. In re Interest of Ty M. &amp; Devon M., 265 Neb. 150, 655 N.W.2d 672 (2003).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (4) of this section, the Department of Social Services is not required to pay costs for preadjudication evaluation that is conducted at a private facility. In re Interest of Todd T., 249 Neb. 738, 545 N.W.2d 711 (1996).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>