<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-512.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-512.05</statuteno><catchline>Child, spousal, and medical support payments; district court clerks; furnish information; cooperative agreements; reimbursement for costs incurred.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be the duty of the clerks of the district courts to furnish the Department of Health and Human Services monthly statistical information and any other information required by the department to properly account for child, spousal, and medical support payments. The clerk of each district court shall negotiate and enter into a written agreement with the department in order to receive reimbursement for the costs incurred in carrying out sections 43-512 to 43-512.10 and 43-512.12 to 43-512.18.</para><para>(2) The department and the governing board of the county, county attorney, or authorized attorney may enter into a written agreement regarding the determination of paternity and child, spousal, and medical support enforcement for the purpose of implementing such sections. Paternity shall be established when it can be determined that the collection of child support is feasible.</para><para>(3) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations regarding the rate and manner of reimbursement for costs incurred in carrying out such sections, taking into account relevant federal law, available federal funds, and any appropriations made by the Legislature. Any reimbursement funds shall be added to the budgets of those county officials who have performed the services as called for in the cooperative agreements and carried over from year to year as required by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 926, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 960, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 345, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 371, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 417, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 715, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 159; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 61. </para></source><annotation><para>To the extent that a county board has already appropriated sufficient funding to pay the necessary salaries and expenses for performing child support enforcement duties, the board is entitled to deposit federal reimbursement funds into its general fund. But for any reimbursement funds that the county is not entitled to keep, subsection (3) of this section plainly requires such funds to be carried over from year to year in the county attorney's budget when his or her office is performing all of the child support enforcement duties. Wetovick v. County of Nance, 279 Neb. 773, 782 N.W.2d 298 (2010).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>