<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id504">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id506" statutenumber="43-419"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-419</statuteno><catchline id="id509">Parole violation;
preliminary hearing.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies to all juveniles committed to the Office
of Juvenile Services for placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment
center prior to July 1, 2013. When a juvenile is apprehended and
detained for an alleged violation of juvenile parole, he or she shall have
a preliminary hearing as soon as practicable and no later than within seventy-two
hours of being apprehended and detained. An impartial hearing officer shall
conduct the preliminary hearing. The impartial hearing officer shall not be
the juvenile parole officer alleging the violation of parole or a witness
to the alleged violation. The impartial hearing officer may be an employee
of the Office of Juvenile Services, including a supervisor or a juvenile parole
officer, other than the parole officer filing the allegations.</para>
<para>(2) The juvenile parolee shall receive notice of the preliminary
hearing, its purpose, and the alleged violations prior to the commencement
of the hearing. The juvenile parolee may present relevant information, question
adverse witnesses, and make a statement regarding the alleged parole violations.
The rules of evidence shall not apply at such hearings and the hearing officer
may rely upon any available information.</para>
<para>(3) The hearing officer shall determine whether there is
probable cause to believe that the juvenile has violated a term or condition
of his or her parole and shall issue that decision in writing. The decision
shall either indicate there is not probable cause to believe that the juvenile
parolee has violated the terms of his or her parole and dismiss the allegations
and return the juvenile to parole supervision, or it shall indicate there
is probable cause to believe that the juvenile has violated a condition of
parole and state where the juvenile will be held pending the revocation hearing.
The preliminary hearing officer shall consider the seriousness of the alleged
violation, the public safety, and the best interests of the juvenile in determining
where the juvenile shall be held pending the revocation hearing.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 39.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>