<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-402</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent; juvenile justice system; goal.</catchline><para>It is the intent of the Legislature that the juvenile justice system provide individualized accountability and individualized treatment for juveniles in a manner consistent with public safety to those juveniles who violate the law. The juvenile justice system shall also promote prevention efforts which are community-based and involve all sectors of the community. Prevention efforts shall be provided through the support of programs and services designed to meet the needs of those juveniles who are identified as being at risk of violating the law and those whose behavior is such that they endanger themselves or others. The goal of the juvenile justice system shall be to provide a range of programs and services which:</para><para>(1) Retain and support juveniles within their homes whenever possible and appropriate;</para><para>(2) Provide the least restrictive and most appropriate setting for juveniles while adequately protecting them and the community;</para><para>(3) Are community-based and are provided in as close proximity to the juvenile's community as possible and appropriate;</para><para>(4) Provide humane, secure, and therapeutic confinement to those juveniles who present a danger to the community;</para><para>(5) Provide followup and aftercare services to juveniles when returned to their families or communities to ensure that progress made and behaviors learned are integrated and continued;</para><para>(6) Hold juveniles accountable for their unlawful behavior in a manner consistent with their long-term needs, stressing the offender's responsibility to victims and the community;</para><para>(7) Base treatment planning and service provision upon an individual evaluation of the juvenile's needs recognizing the importance of meeting the educational needs of the juvenile in the juvenile justice system;</para><para>(8) Are family focused and include the juvenile's family in assessment, case planning, treatment, and service provision as appropriate and emphasize parental involvement and accountability in the rehabilitation of their children;</para><para>(9) Provide supervision and service coordination, as appropriate, to implement and monitor treatment plans and to prevent reoffending;</para><para>(10) Provide integrated service delivery through appropriate linkages to other human service agencies; and</para><para>(11) Promote the development and implementation of community-based programs designed to prevent unlawful behavior and to effectively minimize the depth and duration of the juvenile's involvement in the juvenile justice system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 83-925.01; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>