<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1402</statuteno><catchline>Child support; liability of parents.</catchline><para>The father of a child whose paternity is established either by judicial proceedings or by acknowledgment as hereinafter provided shall be liable for its support to the same extent and in the same manner as the father of a child born in lawful wedlock is liable for its support. The mother of a child shall also be liable for its support. The liability of each parent may be determined, enforced, and discharged in accordance with the methods hereinafter provided.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 81, &#167; 2, p. 322; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 43-702; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 13-102; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 13-102. </para></source><annotation><para>Under this section, establishment of paternity by acknowledgment is the equivalent of establishment of paternity by a judicial proceeding. In re Adoption of Jaelyn B., 293 Neb. 917, 883 N.W.2d 22 (2016).</para><para>A child born out of wedlock is entitled to child support retroactively to the date of birth because it is upon the child's birth that the parental duty of support commences. The same is true for a child born in wedlock, and such duty toward a minor child does not terminate upon divorce. At divorce, the duty of support is merely quantified. Willers ex rel. Powell v. Willers, 255 Neb. 769, 587 N.W.2d 390 (1998).</para><para>A parent has the duty to support a child, and a child born out of wedlock is entitled to support from the father to the same extent and in the same manner as a child born in wedlock. The duty to support one's child begins at birth, and there is no rational basis to distinguish support obligations to a child based upon whether the parents married. In a paternity action, a child who was not supported by a parent is ordinarily entitled to an award of retroactive child support. Retroactive child support is ordinarily determined in accordance with the Nebraska Child Support Guidelines, and the $50 minimum monthly support is presumptively correct absent contrary evidence. Sylvis v. Walling, 248 Neb. 168, 532 N.W.2d 312 (1995).</para><para>Child support obligations which are determined in a paternity action are to be reached in the same manner as cases of children born in lawful wedlock. Such determinations will not be reversed absent an abuse of discretion. State on behalf of S.M. v. Oglesby, 244 Neb. 880, 510 N.W.2d 53 (1994).</para><para>When paternity is legally established, there is no rational basis to distinguish the support obligations of a father to a child born out of wedlock from the support obligations of a father to a child born in wedlock, and an out-of-wedlock child should be entitled to support from its father from the time of birth. State on behalf of Matchett v. Dunkle, 244 Neb. 639, 508 N.W.2d 580 (1993).</para><para>Chapter 13 which provides for "Children Born Out of Wedlock" (transferred to Chapter 43, article 14) conflicts with the common law rule and must be strictly construed. Riederer v. Siciunas, 193 Neb. 580, 228 N.W.2d 283 (1975).</para><para>This section construed with section 42-364, authorizes court to modify amount of child support in paternity action in interests of children. Riederer v. Siciunas, 193 Neb. 580, 228 N.W.2d 283 (1975).</para><para>Liability of father of child born out of wedlock to support the child is the same as that of the father of a child born in lawful wedlock. State ex rel. Stobel v. Stanek, 176 Neb. 100, 125 N.W.2d 107 (1963).</para><para>An out-of-wedlock child has the statutory right to be supported to the same extent and in the same manner as a child born in lawful wedlock; the resulting duty of a parent to provide such support may, under appropriate circumstances, require the award of retroactive child support. Henke v. Guerrero, 13 Neb. App. 337, 692 N.W.2d 762 (2005).</para><para>Child support determinations made concomitantly in a filiation proceeding are characterized as "equitable" proceedings. Dworak v. Fugit, 1 Neb. App. 332, 495 N.W.2d 47 (1992).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>