<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1302"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1302</statuteno><catchline>State Foster Care Review Board; established;
members; disclosure required; terms;
expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The State Foster Care Review Board shall
be comprised of eleven members appointed by the Governor with the approval
of a majority of the members elected to the Legislature, consisting of: Three
members of local foster care review boards, one from each congressional district;
one practitioner of pediatric medicine, licensed under the Uniform Credentialing
Act; one practitioner of child clinical psychology, licensed under the Uniform
Credentialing Act; one social worker certified under the Uniform Credentialing
Act, with expertise in the area of child welfare; one attorney who is or has
been a guardian ad litem; one representative of a statewide child advocacy
group; one director of a child advocacy center; one director of a court appointed
special advocate program; and one member of the public who has a background
in business or finance. Prior
to appointment, each potential member shall disclose any and all funding he
or she or his or her employer receives from the Department of Health and Human
Services.</para>
<para>The terms of members appointed pursuant to this subsection shall
be three years, except that of the initial members of the state board, one-third
shall be appointed for terms of one year, one-third for terms of two years,
and one-third for terms of three years, as determined by the Governor. No
person appointed by the Governor to the state board shall serve more than
two consecutive three-year terms. An appointee to a vacancy occurring from
an unexpired term shall serve out the term of his or her predecessor. Members
whose terms have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have
been appointed and qualified. Members serving on the state board on December
31, 2005, shall continue in office until the members appointed under this subsection take office. The members of the state
board shall, to the extent possible, represent the three congressional districts
equally.</para>
<para>(2) The state board shall select a chairperson, vice-chairperson, and
such other officers as the state board deems necessary. Members of the state
board shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided
in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The state board shall employ or contract for
services from such persons as are necessary to aid it in carrying out its
duties.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 714, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 239, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1222, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 761, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1133; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB679, &#167; 1.</para></source> </law>
</legaldoc>