<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1736"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1736</statuteno><catchline>Foreign support order; discovery; testimony; evidence; voluntary testimony.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to other procedural devices available to a party, any party to an income withholding proceeding based on a foreign support order or a guardian ad litem or other representative of the child may adduce testimony of witnesses in another state, including the parties and any of the children, by deposition, by written discovery, by electronic discovery such as videotaped depositions, or by personal appearance before the court by telephone or electronic means. The court on its own motion may direct that the testimony of a person be taken in another state and may prescribe the manner in which and the terms upon which the testimony shall be taken.</para><para>(2) A court of this state may request the appropriate court or agency of another state to hold a hearing to adduce evidence, to permit a deposition to be taken before the court or agency, to order a party to produce or give evidence under other procedures of that state, and to forward to the court of this state certified copies of the evidence adduced in compliance with the request.</para><para>(3) Upon request of a court or agency of another state, the courts of this state which are competent to hear support matters may order a person in this state to appear at a hearing or deposition before the court to adduce evidence or to produce or give evidence under other procedures available in this state. A certified copy of the evidence adduced, such as a transcript or videotape, shall be forwarded by the clerk of the court to the requesting court or agency.</para><para>(4) A person within this state may voluntarily testify by statement or affidavit in this state for use in a proceeding to obtain income withholding outside this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 56. </para></source></law></legaldoc>