<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id78">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id80" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="43-1311.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>43-1311.01</statuteno><catchline>Child removed from home; notice
to noncustodial parent and certain relatives; when; information provided;
department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) When notified pursuant to section 43-1311 or upon voluntary
placement of a child, the Department of Health and Human Services shall, as
provided in this section, identify, locate, and provide written notification
of the removal of the child from his or her home, within thirty days after
removal, to any noncustodial parent and to all grandparents, adult siblings,
adult aunts, adult uncles, adult cousins, and adult relatives suggested by
the child or the child's parents, except when that relative's history of family
or domestic violence makes notification inappropriate. If the child is an
Indian child as defined in section 43-1503, the child's extended family members
as defined in such section shall be notified. Such notification shall include
all of the following information:</para>
<para>(a) The child
has been or is being removed from the custody of the parent or parents of
the child;</para><para>(b) An explanation of the options the relative has under federal,
state, and local law to participate in the care and placement of the child,
including any options that may be lost by failing to respond to the notice;</para>
<para>(c) A description
of the requirements for the relative to serve as a foster care provider or
other type of care provider for the child and the additional services, training,
and other support available for children receiving such care; and</para>
<para>(d) Information
concerning the option to apply for guardianship assistance payments.</para>
<para>(2) The department
shall investigate the names and locations of the relatives, including, but
not limited to, asking the child in an age-appropriate manner about relatives
important to the child and obtaining information regarding the location of
the relatives.</para><para>(3) The department shall provide to the court, within thirty calendar
days after removal of the child, the names and relationship to the child of
all relatives contacted, the method of contact, and the responses received
from the relatives.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB177, &#167; 6.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>