<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1904</statuteno><catchline>Board; powers and duties.</catchline><para>The board shall have the following powers and duties:</para><para>(1) To meet not less than twice annually at the call of the chairperson to conduct its official business;</para><para>(2) To require that at least five of the board members approve the awarding of grants made under subdivision (3)(b) of this section; and</para><para>(3) To develop, one year after the appointment of the original board and annually thereafter, a state plan for the distribution and disbursement of money in the fund. The plan developed under this subdivision shall assure that an equal opportunity exists for the establishment and maintenance of prevention programs and the receipt of money from the fund in all geographic areas of this state. The plan shall be transmitted to the department, the Governor, and the Legislature and made available to the general public. In carrying out a plan developed under this subdivision, the board shall establish procedures for:</para><para>(a) Developing and publicizing criteria for the awarding of grants for programs to be supported with money from the fund within the limits of appropriations made for that purpose;</para><para>(b) Awarding grants to agencies, organizations, or individuals for community-based child abuse prevention programs. The programs shall provide education, public awareness, or prevention services. In awarding grants under this subdivision, consideration shall be given by the board to factors such as need, geographic location, diversity, coordination with or improvement of existing services, and extensive use of volunteers;</para><para>(c) Supporting and encouraging the formation of local child abuse councils;</para><para>(d) Consulting with applicable state agencies, commissions, and boards to help determine probable effectiveness, fiscal soundness, and need for proposed community-based educational and service prevention programs;</para><para>(e) Facilitating information exchange among groups concerned with prevention programs; and</para><para>(f) Encouraging statewide educational and public awareness programs regarding the problems of families and children which (i) encourage professional persons and groups to recognize and deal with problems of families and children, (ii) make information regarding the problems of families and children and the prevention of such problems available to the general public in order to encourage citizens to become involved in the prevention of such problems, and (iii) encourage the development of community prevention programs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 333, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 134.</para></source></law></legaldoc>