<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id98">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id100" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="43-1311.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1311.03</statuteno><catchline>Written independent living transition
proposal; development; contents; transition team; department; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) When a
child placed in foster care turns sixteen years of age or enters foster care
and is at least sixteen years of age, a written independent living transition
proposal shall be developed by the Department of Health and Human Services
at the direction and involvement of the child to prepare for the transition
from foster care to adulthood. The transition proposal shall be personalized
based on the child's needs. The transition proposal shall include, but not
be limited to, the following needs:</para>
<para>(a) Education;</para>
<para>(b) Employment
services and other workforce support;</para><para>(c) Health and health care coverage;</para>
<para>(d) Financial
assistance, including education on credit card financing, banking, and other
services;</para><para>(e) Housing;</para><para>(f) Relationship development; and</para><para>(g) Adult services, if
the needs assessment indicates that the child is reasonably likely to need
or be eligible for services or other support from the adult services system.</para>
<para>(2) The transition
proposal shall be developed and frequently reviewed by the department in collaboration
with the child's transition team. The transition team shall be comprised of
the child, the child's caseworker, the child's guardian ad litem, individuals
selected by the child, and individuals who have knowledge of services available
to the child.</para><para>(3) The transition proposal shall be considered a working document
and shall be, at the least, updated for and reviewed at every permanency or
review hearing by the court.</para><para>(4) The final transition proposal prior
to the child's leaving foster care shall specifically identify how the need
for housing will be addressed.</para><para>(5) If the child is interested in pursuing
higher education, the transition proposal shall provide for the process in
applying for any applicable state, federal, or private aid.</para>
<para>(6) On or
before the date the child reaches nineteen years of age, the department shall
provide the child a certified copy of the child's birth certificate and facilitate
securing a federal social security card when the child is eligible for such
card. All fees associated with securing the certified copy shall be waived
by the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB177, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>