<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id00" statutenumber="43-1906"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1906</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Nebraska Child Abuse Prevention Fund; established; investment; use.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) There is hereby established the Nebraska Child Abuse Prevention Fund. The additional child abuse prevention fee as provided in section 33-106.03, the additional charge for supplying a certified copy of the record of any birth as provided in sections 71-612, 71-617.15, 71-627, and 71-628, and all amounts which may be received from grants, gifts, bequests, the federal government, or other sources granted or given for the purposes specified in sections 43-1901 to 43-1906 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Child Abuse Prevention Fund. The fund shall be administered and disbursed by the department.</para><para id="id00">(2) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para id="id00">(3) In any one fiscal year, no more than twenty percent of the annually appropriated funds shall be disbursed to any one agency, organization, or individual.</para><para id="id00">(4) Funds allocated from the fund shall only be used for purposes authorized under sections 43-1901 to 43-1906 and shall not be used to supplant any existing governmental program or service. No grants may be made to any state department or agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 333, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 48, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB307, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>