<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id272">
<sectno id="id273" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 37.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id274" statutenumber="43-1726">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id276">43-1726</statuteno><catchline id="id277">Notice to withhold
income; termination; exception; procedure.</catchline><para>When
an obligor ceases employment with or is no longer entitled to income from
an employer or other payor, the notice to withhold income shall not cease
to operate against the obligor and income withholding shall continue to apply
to any subsequent employment or income of the obligor. The notice to withhold
income shall terminate with respect to the employer or other payor without
any court action or action by the county attorney, the authorized attorney,
or the department thirty days after the obligor ceases employment with or
is no longer entitled to income from such employer or other payor, except
that a notice to withhold income shall not terminate with respect to unemployment
compensation benefits being withheld by the Commissioner of Labor pursuant
to section 48-647. The employer or other payor shall return a copy of the
notice to withhold income to the county attorney, the authorized attorney,
or the department, indicate that the employment or obligation to pay income
has ceased, and cooperate in providing any known forwarding information. The
county attorney, the authorized attorney, or the department shall notify the
clerk of the appropriate district court that such employment or obligation
to pay income has ceased. A notice to withhold income shall also terminate
when the child, spousal, or medical support obligation terminates, all past-due support has been paid, and any monetary judgments have been paid, in
which case the county attorney, the authorized attorney, or the department
shall notify the employer or other payor to cease withholding income.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 600, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 523, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 37.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>