<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id121"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="43-1322"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1322</statuteno><catchline>Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project; created; purpose; termination; Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project Advisory Group; created; members; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1) An Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project is created. The purpose of the project is to demonstrate, under the supervision of the Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project Advisory Group, how an existing state agency data system or systems currently used to account for children and juveniles in out-of-home placement could serve as a foundation for an independent, external oversight data warehouse. The pilot project shall be administered by the Foster Care Review Office and shall terminate on January 1, 2017.</para><para>(2) The Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project Advisory Group is created. The group shall include the Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare or his or her designee, the State Court Administrator or his or her designee, the probation administrator of the Office of Probation Administration or his or her designee, the executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice or his or her designee, the Commissioner of Education or his or her designee, the executive director of the Foster Care Review Office or his or her designee, a representative of the University of Nebraska at Omaha, Juvenile Justice Institute, the Chief Information Officer of the office of Chief Information Officer or his or her designee, and one representative each from the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department of Health and Human Services, the Division of Developmental Disabilities of the Department of Health and Human Services, the Division of Behavioral Health of the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care of the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(3) The purposes of the Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project Advisory Group are to oversee the Out-of-Home Data Pilot Project and to consider whether an independent, external oversight data warehouse could be created by building on an existing state agency data system or systems currently used to account for children and juveniles in out-of-home placement. The group shall consider the features and capabilities of existing state agency data systems that include: Information on children and juveniles in out-of-home placement; where an independent, external oversight data warehouse might be located within state government for administrative purposes; possible costs associated with establishing and operating an independent, external oversight data warehouse; challenges of data collection; barriers to data sharing; protection of confidential information; restrictions on access to confidential information; and other issues pertinent to the group's purpose. The group shall submit a report electronically to the Legislature, the Governor, and the Supreme Court by December 15, 2015.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, an independent, external oversight data warehouse means a data system which allows data analysis to: (a) Account for children and juveniles in out-of-home placement regardless of whether they entered out-of-home placement through the Department of Health and Human Services or through court involvement; (b) determine whether out-of-home placement outcomes for children and juveniles meet policy goals for children and juveniles in out-of-home placement; (c) determine whether children are better off as a result of out-of-home placement; (d) identify indicators for successful outcomes of out-of-home placement; and (e) project future needs for children and juveniles in out-of-home placement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB265, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>