<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id6" statutenumber="43-1005"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">43-1005</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Expense of returning
juvenile to state; how paid.</catchline><para>The expense of returning
juveniles to this state pursuant to the Interstate Compact for Juveniles
shall be paid as follows:</para>
<para>(1) In the case of a runaway, the court
making the requisition shall inquire summarily regarding the financial ability
of the petitioner to bear the expense and if it finds he or she is able to
do so shall order that he or she pay all such expenses; otherwise the court
shall arrange for the transportation at the expense of the county and order
that the county reimburse the person, if any, who returns the juvenile for
his or her actual and necessary expenses; and the court may order that the
petitioner reimburse the county for so much of said expense as the court finds
he or she is able to pay. If the petitioner fails, without good cause, or
refuses to pay such sum, he or she may be proceeded against for contempt.</para>
<para>(2) In the case of an escapee or absconder, if the juvenile is in the legal custody
of the Department of Health and Human Services it shall bear the expense of
his or her return; otherwise the appropriate court shall, on petition of the
person entitled to his or her custody or charged with his or her supervision,
arrange for the transportation at the expense of the county and order that
the county reimburse the person, if any, who returns the juvenile, for his
or her actual and necessary expenses. In this subdivision appropriate court
means the juvenile court which adjudged the juvenile to be delinquent or,
if the juvenile is under supervision for another state, then the juvenile court of the county
of the juvenile's residence during such supervision.</para>
<para>(3) In the case of a voluntary return of a runaway without
requisition, the person
entitled to his or her legal custody shall pay the expense of transportation
and the actual and necessary expenses of the person, if any, who returns such
juvenile; but if he or she is financially unable to pay all the expenses he
or she may petition the juvenile court of the county of the petitioner's residence
for an order arranging for the transportation as provided in subdivision (1)
of this section. The court shall inquire summarily into the financial ability
of the petitioner, and, if it finds he or she is unable to bear any or all
of the expense, the court shall arrange for such transportation at the expense
of the county and shall order the county to reimburse the person, if any,
who returns the juvenile, for his or her actual and necessary expenses. The
court may order that the petitioner reimburse the county for so much of said
expense as the court finds he or she is able to pay. If the petitioner fails,
without good cause, or refuses to pay such sum, he or she may be proceeded
against for contempt.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 248, &#167; 5, p. 756; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 192; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB237, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interstate Compact for Juveniles,</emphasis> see section 43-1011.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>