<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id669"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1306"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1306</statuteno><catchline>Children and Juveniles Data Feasibility Study Advisory Group; created; members; meetings; duties; Data Steering Subcommittee; Information-Sharing Subcommittee.</catchline><para>(1) The Children and Juveniles Data Feasibility Study Advisory Group is created. The advisory group shall oversee a feasibility study to identify how existing state agency data systems currently used to account for the use of all services, programs, and facilities by children and juveniles in the State of Nebraska can be used to establish an independent, external data warehouse. The Foster Care Review Office shall provide administrative support for the feasibility study and the advisory group.</para><para>(2) The advisory group shall include the Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare or his or her designee, the State Court Administrator or his or her designee, the probation administrator of the Office of Probation Administration or his or her designee, the executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice or his or her designee, the Commissioner of Education or his or her designee, the executive director of the Foster Care Review Office or his or her designee, the Chief Information Officer of the office of Chief Information Officer or his or her designee, and the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee.</para><para>(3) The advisory group shall:</para><para>(a) Meet at least twice a year;</para><para>(b) Carry out in good faith the duties provided in this section;</para><para>(c) Create a Data Steering Subcommittee. Each member of the advisory group shall designate one representative from his or her agency with specific technical knowledge of the agency’s data structure, limitation, and capabilities to serve on the subcommittee. The subcommittee shall meet regularly to manage and discuss data-related items, including the technological and system issues of each agency’s current data system, specific barriers that impact the implementation of a data warehouse, and steps necessary to establish and sustain a data warehouse. The subcommittee shall report its findings to the advisory group;</para><para>(d) Create an Information-Sharing Subcommittee. Each member of the advisory group shall designate one representative from his or her agency with specific knowledge of the agency’s legal and regulatory responsibilities and restrictions related to sharing data to serve on the subcommittee. The subcommittee shall meet regularly to manage and discuss the legal and regulatory barriers to establishing a data warehouse and to identify possible solutions. The subcommittee shall report its findings to the advisory group; and</para><para>(e) Submit a written report electronically to the Legislature on October 1 of 2017 and 2018, detailing the technical and legal steps necessary to establish the Children and Juveniles Data Warehouse by July 1, 2019. The report to be submitted on October 1, 2018, shall include the final results of the feasibility study to establish the data warehouse by July 1, 2019. The results of the feasibility study shall not be binding on any agency.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, independent, external data warehouse means a data system which allows for the collection, storage, and analysis of data from multiple agencies but is not solely controlled by the agencies providing the data.</para><para>(5) This section terminates on December 31, 2019.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB225, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>