<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id51">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id53" statutenumber="43-1302"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1302</statuteno><catchline id="id56">Foster Care Review Office; established; purpose; Foster Care Advisory Committee;
created; members; terms; meetings;
duties; expenses;
executive director; duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Foster Care
Review Office is hereby established. The purpose of the office is to provide
information and direct reporting to the courts, the Department of Health and
Human Services, and the Legislature regarding the foster care system in Nebraska;
to provide oversight of the foster care system; and to make recommendations
regarding foster care policy to the Legislature. The executive director of
the office shall provide information and reporting services, provide analysis
of information obtained, and oversee foster care file audit case reviews and
tracking of cases of children in the foster care system. The executive director
of the office shall, through information analysis and with the assistance
of the Foster Care Advisory Committee, (i) determine key issues of the foster
care system and ways to resolve the issues and to otherwise improve the system
and (ii) make policy recommendations.</para><para>(b) All equipment and effects of the State
Foster Care Review Board on July 1, 2012, shall be transferred to the Foster
Care Review Office, and all staff of the board, except the executive director
and interim executive director, shall be transferred to the office. The State
Foster Care Review Board shall terminate on July 1, 2012. Beginning on July
1, 2012, the data coordinator of the board, as such position existed prior
to such date, shall serve as the executive director of the office until the
Foster Care Advisory Committee hires an executive director as prescribed by
this section. It is the intent of the Legislature that the staff of the board
employed prior to July 1, 2012, shall continue to be employed by the office
until such time as the executive director is hired by the committee.</para>
<para>(c) It is the intent
of the Legislature that the funds appropriated to the State Foster Care Review
Board be transferred to the Foster Care Review Office for FY2012-13.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The
Foster Care Advisory Committee is created. The committee shall have five members
appointed by the Governor. The members shall have no pecuniary interest in
the foster care system and shall not be employed by the office, the Department
of Health and Human Services, a county, a child-caring agency, a child-placing
agency, or a court.</para><para>(b) The Governor shall appoint three members from a list of twelve
local board members submitted by the Health and Human Services Committee of
the Legislature, one member from a list of four persons with data analysis
experience submitted by the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature,
and one member from a list of four persons who are residents of the state
and are representative of the public at large submitted by the Health and
Human Services Committee of the Legislature. The Health and Human Services
Committee of the Legislature shall hold a confirmation hearing for the appointees,
and the appointments shall be subject to confirmation by the Legislature,
except that the initial members and members appointed while the Legislature
is not in session shall serve until the next session of the Legislature, at
which time a majority of the members of the Legislature shall approve or disapprove
of the appointments.</para><para>(c) The terms of the members shall be for three years, except that
the Governor shall designate two of the initial appointees to serve initial
terms ending on March 1, 2014, and three of the initial appointees to serve
initial terms ending on March 1, 2015. The Governor shall make the initial
appointments within thirty days after July 1, 2012. Members shall not serve
more than two consecutive terms, except that members shall serve until their
successors have been appointed and qualified. The Governor shall appoint members
to fill vacancies in the same manner as the original appointments to serve
for the remainder of the unexpired term.</para><para>(d) The Foster Care Advisory Committee shall
meet at least four times each calendar year. Each member shall attend at least
two meetings each calendar year and shall be subject to removal for failure
to attend at least two meetings unless excused by a majority of the members
of the committee. Members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary
expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(e) The duties of the
Foster Care Advisory Committee are to:</para><para>(i) Hire and fire an executive director
for the office who has training and experience in foster care; and</para>
<para>(ii) Support
and facilitate the work of the office, including the tracking of children
in foster care and reviewing foster care file audit case reviews.</para>
<para>(3) The executive
director of the office shall hire, fire, and supervise office staff and shall
be responsible for the duties of the office as provided by law, including
the annual report and other reporting, review, tracking, data collection and
analysis, and oversight and training of local boards.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 714, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 239, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1222, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 761, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1133; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB679, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB998, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>