<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1239"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1239</statuteno><catchline>Exclusive, continuing jurisdiction.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in section 43-1241, a court of this state which has made a child custody determination consistent with section 43-1238 or 43-1240 has exclusive, continuing jurisdiction over the determination until:</para><para>(1) a court of this state determines that neither the child, nor the child and one parent, nor the child and a person acting as a parent have a significant connection with this state and that substantial evidence is no longer available in this state concerning the child's care, protection, training, and personal relationships; or</para><para>(2) a court of this state or a court of another state determines that the child, the child's parents, and any person acting as a parent do not presently reside in this state.</para><para>(b) A court of this state which has made a child custody determination and does not have exclusive, continuing jurisdiction under this section may modify that determination only if it has jurisdiction to make an initial determination under section 43-1238.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 148, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>Subsection (a) of this section provides the rules for continuing jurisdiction under the Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act. Watson v. Watson, 272 Neb. 647, 724 N.W.2d 24 (2006).</para><para>Under subsection (a)(1) of this section, whether a court's exclusive and continuing jurisdiction has been lost is a determination to be made by a court of this state. Watson v. Watson, 272 Neb. 647, 724 N.W.2d 24 (2006).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>