<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1315"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1315</statuteno><catchline>Status and permanency plan review; placement order.</catchline><para>In reviewing the foster care status and permanency plan of a child and in determining its order for disposition, the court shall continue placement outside the home upon a written determination that return of the child to his or her home would be contrary to the welfare of such child and that reasonable efforts to preserve and reunify the family, if required under section 43-283.01, have been made. In making this determination, the court shall consider the goals of the foster care placement and the safety and appropriateness of the foster care plan or permanency plan established pursuant to section 43-1312.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 714, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 635, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1041, &#167; 42. </para></source><annotation><para>The Legislature intended that the issue of reasonable efforts required under section 43-283.01 must be reviewed by the juvenile court (1) when removing from the home a juvenile adjudged to be under subsections (3) or (4) of section 43-247 pursuant to section 43-284, (2) when the court continues a juvenile's out-of-home placement pending adjudication pursuant to section 43-254, (3) when the court reviews a juvenile's status and permanency planning pursuant to this section, and (4) when termination of parental rights to a juvenile is sought by the State under subsection (6) of section 43-292. In re Interest of DeWayne G., Jr. &amp; Devon G., 263 Neb. 43, 638 N.W.2d 510 (2002).</para><para>This section only applies to situations where the foster care status of a child is being reviewed, not all orders which are dispositional in nature. In re Interest of Gloria F., 254 Neb. 531, 577 N.W.2d 296 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>