<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-1237"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-1237</statuteno><catchline>Cooperation between courts; preservation of records.</catchline><para>(a) A court of this state may request the appropriate court of another state to:</para><para>(1) hold an evidentiary hearing;</para><para>(2) order a person to produce or give evidence pursuant to procedures of that state;</para><para>(3) order that an evaluation be made with respect to the custody of a child involved in a pending proceeding;</para><para>(4) forward to the court of this state a certified copy of the transcript of the record of the hearing, the evidence otherwise presented, and any evaluation prepared in compliance with the request; and</para><para>(5) order a party to a child custody proceeding or any person having physical custody of the child to appear in the proceeding with or without the child.</para><para>(b) Upon request of a court of another state, a court of this state may hold a hearing or enter an order described in subsection (a) of this section.</para><para>(c) Travel and other necessary and reasonable expenses incurred under subsections (a) and (b) of this section may be assessed against the parties according to the law of this state.</para><para>(d) A court of this state shall preserve the pleadings, orders, decrees, records of hearings, evaluations, and other pertinent records with respect to a child custody proceeding until the child attains eighteen years of age. Upon appropriate request by a court or law enforcement official of another state, the court shall forward a certified copy of those records.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 148, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>