<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id228">
<sectno id="id229" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 33.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id230" statutenumber="43-1720">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id232">43-1720</statuteno><catchline id="id233">Notice to employer,
payor, or obligor; contents.</catchline><para>If the department
has previously sent a notice of assignment and opportunity for hearing on
the same support order under section 48-647, the county attorney, authorized
attorney, or the department shall state the amount to be withheld
from an obligor's disposable income pursuant to section 43-1722 and shall
notify the obligor's employer or other payor pursuant to section 43-1723.
If the department has not previously sent such notice, and except in cases
in which the court has ordered income withholding pursuant to subsection (1)
of section 43-1718.01 or section 43-1718.02, upon receiving certification
pursuant to section 42-358 or notice of delinquent payments of medical support,
the county attorney, the authorized attorney, or the department shall send
a notice by certified mail to the last-known address of the obligor stating:</para>
<para>(1) That an assignment of his or her income by means of income
withholding will go into effect within fifteen days after the date the notice
is sent;</para>
<para>(2) That the income withholding will continue to apply to
any subsequent employer or other payor of the obligor;</para>
<para>(3) The amount of support and
any monetary judgment the obligor owes;</para>
<para>(4) The amount of income that will be withheld; and</para>
<para>(5) That within the fifteen-day period, the obligor may request
a hearing in the manner specified in the notice to contest a mistake of fact.
For purposes of this subdivision, mistake of fact shall mean (a) an error
in the amount of current or overdue support or
the amount of any monetary judgment, (b) an error in the identity
of the obligor, or (c) an error in the amount to be withheld as provided in
section 43-1722.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 7, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 600, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 457, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 523, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1224, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 205; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 33.</para></source><annotation><para>Unless a prior notice has been sent and except where a court has ordered income withholding for child support, the notice of income withholding is triggered by receipt of certification from the clerk of the district court made pursuant to section 42-358. McKibbin v. State, 5 Neb. App. 570, 560 N.W.2d 507 (1997).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>