<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id37">
<sectno id="id38" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id39" statutenumber="43-2937"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id41">43-2937</statuteno><catchline id="id42">Court referral
to mediation or specialized alternative dispute resolution; temporary relief;
specialized alternative dispute resolution rule; approval; mandatory court
order; when; waiver.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to those cases that are mandatorily referred
to mediation or specialized alternative dispute resolution under subsection
(3) of this section, a court may, at any time in the proceedings upon its
own motion or upon the motion of either party, refer a case to mediation or
specialized alternative dispute resolution in order to attempt resolution
of any relevant matter. The court may state a date for the case to return
to court, and the court shall not grant an extension of such date except for
cause. If the court refers a case to mediation or specialized alternative
dispute resolution, the court may, if appropriate, order temporary relief,
including necessary support and provision for payment of mediation costs.
Court referral shall be to a mediator agreed to by the parties and approved
by the court, an approved mediation center, or a court conciliation program.
The State Court Administrator's office shall develop a process to approve
mediators under the Parenting Act.</para>
<para>(2) Prior to July 1, 2010, if there are allegations of domestic
intimate partner abuse or unresolved parental conflict between the parties
in any proceeding, mediation shall not be required pursuant to the Parenting
Act or by local court rule, unless the court has established a specialized
alternative dispute resolution rule approved by the State Court Administrator.
The specialized alternative dispute resolution process shall include a method
for court consideration of precluding or disqualifying parties from participating;
provide an opportunity to educate both parties about the process; require
informed consent from both parties in order to proceed; provide safety protocols,
including separate individual sessions for each participant, informing each
party about the process, and obtaining informed consent from each party to
continue the process; allow support persons to attend sessions; and establish
opt-out-for-cause provisions. On and after July 1, 2010, all trial courts
shall have a mediation and specialized alternative dispute resolution rule
in accordance with the act.</para>
<para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (4) of
this section, for cases filed on or after July 1, 2010, all parties
who have not submitted a parenting plan to the court within the time specified
by the court shall be ordered to participate in mediation or specialized alternative
dispute resolution with a mediator, a court conciliation program, or an approved
mediation center as provided in section 43-2939.</para>
<para>(4) For good
cause shown and (a) when both parents agree and such parental agreement is
bona fide and not asserted to avoid the purposes of the Parenting Act, or
(b) when mediation or specialized alternative dispute resolution is not possible
without undue delay or hardship to either parent, the mediation or specialized
alternative dispute resolution requirement may be waived by the court. In
such a case where waiver of the mediation or specialized alternative dispute
resolution is sought, the court shall hold an evidentiary hearing and the
burden of proof for the party or parties seeking waiver is by clear and convincing
evidence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB901, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>