<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id655">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id657" statutenumber="43-2412"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2412</statuteno><catchline id="id660">Coalition;
powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Consistent with the purposes
and objectives of the Juvenile Services Act and the federal act, the coalition
shall:</para>
<para>(a) Make recommendations to the commission on the awarding
of grants under the Commission Grant Program to eligible applicants;</para>
<para>(b) Identify juvenile justice issues, share information,
and monitor and evaluate programs in the juvenile justice system;</para>
<para>(c) Recommend guidelines and supervision procedures to
be used to develop or expand local diversion programs for juveniles from the
juvenile justice system;</para>
<para>(d) Prepare an annual report to the Governor, the Legislature, the Office of Probation Administration, and
the Office of Juvenile Services including recommendations on administrative
and legislative actions which would improve the juvenile justice system. The
report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(e) Ensure widespread citizen involvement in all phases of
its work; and</para>
<para>(f) Meet at least four times each year.</para>
<para>(2) Consistent with the purposes and objectives of the acts
and within the limits of available time and appropriations, the coalition
may:</para>
<para>(a) Assist and advise state and local agencies
in the establishment of volunteer training programs and the utilization of
volunteers;</para>
<para>(b) Apply for and receive
funds from federal and private sources for carrying out its powers and duties;
and</para>
<para>(c) Provide technical assistance
to eligible applicants.</para>
<para>(3) In formulating, adopting, and promulgating the recommendations and guidelines provided
for in this section, the coalition shall consider the differences among counties
in population, in geography, and in the availability of local resources.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 663, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 447, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 424, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 640, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 50.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>