<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id81">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id83" statutenumber="43-2929"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2929</statuteno><catchline id="id86">Parenting plan;
developed; approved by court; contents.</catchline><para>(1) In
any proceeding in which parenting functions for a child are at issue under
Chapter 42, a parenting plan shall be developed and shall be approved by the
court. Court rule may provide for the parenting plan to be developed by the
parties or their counsel, a court conciliation program, an approved mediation
center, or a private mediator. When a parenting plan has not been developed
and submitted to the court, the court shall create the parenting plan in accordance
with the Parenting Act. A parenting plan shall serve the best interests of
the child pursuant to sections 42-364, 43-2923, and 43-2929.01 and shall:</para>
<para>(a) Assist in developing a restructured family that serves
the best interests of the child by accomplishing the parenting functions;
and</para>
<para>(b) Include, but not be limited to, determinations of the
following:</para>
<para>(i) Legal custody and physical custody of each child;</para>
<para>(ii) Apportionment of parenting time, visitation, or other
access for each child, including, but not limited to, specified religious
and secular holidays, birthdays, Mother's Day, Father's Day, school and family
vacations, and other special occasions, specifying dates and times for the
same, or a formula or method for determining such a schedule in sufficient
detail that, if necessary, the schedule can be enforced in subsequent proceedings
by the court, and set out appropriate times and numbers for telephone access;</para>
<para>(iii) Location of the child during the week, weekend, and
given days during the year;</para>
<para>(iv) A transition plan, including the time and places for
transfer of the child, method of communication or amount and type of contact
between the parties during transfers, and duties related to transportation
of the child during transfers;</para>
<para>(v) Procedures for making decisions regarding the day-to-day
care and control of the child consistent with the major decisions made by
the person or persons who have legal custody and responsibility for parenting
functions;</para>
<para>(vi) Provisions for a remediation process regarding future
modifications to such plan;</para>
<para>(vii) Arrangements to maximize the safety of all parties and
the child;</para>
<para>(viii) Provisions to ensure regular and continuous school
attendance and progress for school-age children of the parties; and</para>
<para>(ix) Provisions for safety when a preponderance of the evidence
establishes child abuse or neglect, domestic intimate partner abuse, unresolved
parental conflict, or criminal activity which is directly harmful to a child.</para>
<para>(2) A parenting plan shall require that the parties notify
each other of a change of address, except that the address or return address
shall only include the county and state for a party who is living or moving
to an undisclosed location because of safety concerns.</para>
<para>(3) When safe and appropriate for the best interests of the
child, the parenting plan may encourage mutual discussion of major decisions
regarding parenting functions including the child's education, health care,
and spiritual or religious upbringing. However, when a prior factual determination
of child abuse or neglect, domestic intimate partner abuse, or unresolved
parental conflict has been made, then consideration shall be given to inclusion
of provisions for safety and a transition plan that restrict communication
or the amount and type of contact between the parties during transfers.</para>
<para>(4) Regardless of the custody determinations in the parenting
plan, unless parental rights are terminated, both parents shall continue to
have the rights stated in section 42-381.</para>
<para>(5) In the development of a parenting plan, consideration
shall be given to the child's age, the child's developmental needs, and the
child's perspective, as well as consideration of enhancing healthy relationships
between the child and each party.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB673, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>