<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id529"><sectno id="id530" opdate="April 17, 2008">Sec. 57.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id531" statutenumber="43-2924"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id533">43-2924</statuteno><catchline id="id534">Applicability of act.</catchline><para>(1) The Parenting Act shall apply to proceedings or modifications filed on or after January 1, 2008, in which parenting functions for a child are at issue (a) under Chapter 42, including, but not limited to, proceedings or modification of orders for dissolution of marriage and child custody and (b) under sections 43-1401 to 43-1418. The Parenting Act may apply to proceedings or modifications in which parenting functions for a child are at issue under Chapter 30 or 43.</para><para>(2) The Parenting Act does not apply in any action filed by a county attorney or authorized attorney pursuant to his or her duties under section 42-358, 43-512 to 43-512.18, or 43-1401 to 43-1418, the Income Withholding for Child Support Act, the Revised Uniform Reciprocal Enforcement of Support Act before January 1, 1994, or the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act for purposes of the establishment of paternity and the establishment and enforcement of child and medical support. A county attorney or authorized attorney shall not participate in the development of or court review of a parenting plan under the Parenting Act. If both parents are parties to a paternity or support action filed by a county attorney or authorized attorney, the parents may proceed with a parenting plan.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 57.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Income Withholding for Child Support Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1701.</para><para><emphasis>Revised Uniform Reciprocal Enforcement of Support Act,</emphasis> see section 42-7,105.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Interstate Family Support Act,</emphasis> see section 42-701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>In a paternity case subject to the Parenting Act where neither party has requested joint custody, if the court determines that joint custody is, or may be, in the best interests of the child, the court shall give the parties notice and an opportunity to be heard by holding an evidentiary hearing on the issue of joint custody. State ex rel. Amanda M. v. Justin T., 279 Neb. 273, 777 N.W.2d 565 (2010).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>