<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id25">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id27" statutenumber="43-2007"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id29">43-2007</statuteno><catchline id="id30">Schools; exempt school; duties.</catchline><para>(1)
Upon notification by the patrol of a missing person, any school in which the
missing person is currently or was previously enrolled shall flag the school
records of such person in such school's possession. The school shall report
immediately any request concerning a flagged record or any knowledge of the
whereabouts of the missing person.</para>
<para>(2) Upon enrollment of a student for the first time in a public
school district or private school system, the school of enrollment shall notify
in writing the person enrolling the student that within thirty days he or
she must provide either (a) a certified copy of the student's birth certificate
or (b) other reliable proof of the student's identity and age accompanied
by an affidavit explaining the inability to produce a copy of the birth certificate.</para>
<para>(3) Upon
enrollment of a student who is receiving his or her education
in an exempt school subject to
sections 79-1601 to 79-1607,
the parent or guardian of such student  shall provide to the Commissioner of
Education either (a) a certified copy of the student's birth
certificate or (b) other reliable proof of the student's identity
and age accompanied by an affidavit explaining the inability to produce a
copy of the birth certificate.</para>
<para>(4) Upon failure of the person, parent, or guardian to comply
with subsection (2) or (3) of this section, the school or Commissioner of
Education shall notify such person, parent, or guardian in writing that unless
he or she complies within ten days the matter shall be referred to the local
law enforcement agency for investigation. If compliance is not obtained within
such ten-day period, the school or commissioner shall immediately report such
matter. Any affidavit received pursuant to subsection (2) or (3) of this section
that appears inaccurate or suspicious in form or content shall be reported
immediately to the local law enforcement agency by the school or commissioner.</para>
<para>(5) Any school requested to forward a copy of a transferred
student's record shall not forward a copy of such record to the requesting
school if the record has been flagged pursuant to subsection (1) of this section.
If such record has been flagged, the school to whom such request is made shall
notify the local law enforcement agency of the request and that such student
is a reported missing person.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 599, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 511, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 245, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1047; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB549, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>