<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id387" statutenumber="43-2404.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2404.02</statuteno><catchline id="id390">County Juvenile
Services Aid Program; created; use; reports.</catchline><para>(1) There is
created a separate and distinct budgetary program within the commission to
be known as the County Juvenile Services Aid Program. Funding acquired from
participation in the federal act, state General Funds, and funding acquired
from other sources which may be used for purposes consistent with the Juvenile
Services Act and the federal act shall be used to aid counties in the establishment
and provision of community-based services for accused and adjudicated juvenile
offenders and to increase capacity for community-based services to juveniles.</para>
<para>(2) The annual General Fund appropriation to the County Juvenile Services
Aid Program shall be apportioned to the counties as aid in accordance with
a formula established in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by
the commission. The formula shall be based on the total number of residents
per county who are twelve years of age through eighteen years of age and other
relevant factors as determined by the commission. The commission may require
a local match of up to forty percent from counties receiving aid under such
program. Any local expenditures for community-based programs for juveniles
may be applied toward such match requirement.</para>
<para>(3) Funds provided to counties under the County Juvenile Services Aid
Program shall be used exclusively to assist counties in implementation and
operation of programs or services identified in their comprehensive juvenile
services plan, including, but not limited to, programs for assessment and
evaluation, prevention of delinquent behavior, diversion, shelter care, intensive
juvenile probation services, restitution, family support services, and family
group conferencing. In distributing funds provided under the County Juvenile
Services Aid Program, counties shall prioritize programs and services that
will reduce the juvenile detention population. No funds appropriated or distributed
under the County Juvenile Services Aid Program shall be used for construction
of secure detention facilities, secure youth treatment facilities, or secure
youth confinement facilities. Aid received under this section shall not be
used for capital construction or the lease or acquisition of facilities and
shall not be used to replace existing funding for programs or services. Any
funds not distributed to counties under this subsection shall be retained
by the commission to be distributed on a competitive basis under the County
Juvenile Services Aid Program.</para>
<para>(4) Any county receiving funding under the County Juvenile Services
Aid Program shall file an annual report as required by rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated by the commission. The report shall include, but not
be limited to, information on the total number of juveniles served, the units
of service provided, a listing of the county's annual juvenile justice budgeted
and actual expenditures, and a listing of expenditures for detention, residential
treatment, and nonresidential treatment.</para>
<para>(5) The commission shall report annually to the Governor and the Legislature
on the distribution and use of funds appropriated under the County Juvenile
Services Aid Program. The report
submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(6) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to implement this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 640, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 193, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 47.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>