<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id621" statutenumber="43-2411"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2411</statuteno><catchline id="id624">Nebraska Coalition for Juvenile Justice; created; members; terms; expenses; task forces or subcommittee; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Coalition for Juvenile Justice is created. Coalition members who are members of the judicial branch of government shall be nonvoting members of the coalition. The coalition members shall be appointed by the Governor and shall include the members required under subsection (2) or (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) Before June 15, 2018:</para><para>(a) As provided in the federal act, there shall be no less than fifteen nor more than thirty-three members of the coalition;</para><para>(b) The coalition shall include:</para><para>(i) The Administrator of the Office of Juvenile Services;</para><para>(ii) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(iii) The Commissioner of Education or his or her designee;</para><para>(iv) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice or his or her designee;</para><para>(v) The executive director of the Nebraska Association of County Officials or his or her designee;</para><para>(vi) The probation administrator of the Office of Probation Administration or his or her designee;</para><para>(vii) One county commissioner or supervisor;</para><para>(viii) One person with data analysis experience;</para><para>(ix) One police chief;</para><para>(x) One sheriff;</para><para>(xi) The executive director of the Foster Care Review Office;</para><para>(xii) One separate juvenile court judge;</para><para>(xiii) One county court judge;</para><para>(xiv) One representative of mental health professionals who works directly with juveniles;</para><para>(xv) Three representatives, one from each congressional district, from community-based, private nonprofit organizations who work with juvenile offenders and their families;</para><para>(xvi) One volunteer who works with juvenile offenders or potential juvenile offenders;</para><para>(xvii) One person who works with an alternative to a detention program for juveniles;</para><para>(xviii) The director or his or her designee from a youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(xix) The director or his or her designee from a secure juvenile detention facility;</para><para>(xx) The director or his or her designee from a staff secure youth confinement facility;</para><para>(xxi) At least five members who are under twenty-four years of age when appointed;</para><para>(xxii) One person who works directly with juveniles who have learning or emotional difficulties or are abused or neglected;</para><para>(xxiii) One member of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice;</para><para>(xxiv) One member of a regional behavioral health authority established under section 71-808;</para><para>(xxv) One county attorney; and</para><para>(xxvi) One public defender;</para><para>(c) A majority of the coalition members, including the chairperson, shall not be full-time employees of federal, state, or local government. At least one-fifth of the coalition members shall be under the age of twenty-four years at the time of appointment; and</para><para>(d) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, the terms of members appointed pursuant to subdivisions (2)(b)(vii) through (2)(b)(xxvi) of this section shall be three years, except that the terms of the initial appointments of members of the coalition shall be staggered so that one-third of the members are appointed for terms of one year, one-third for terms of two years, and one-third for terms of three years, as determined by the Governor.</para><para>(3) On and after June 15, 2018, the coalition shall include:</para><para>(a) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The Commissioner of Education or his or her designee;</para><para>(c) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice or his or her designee;</para><para>(d) The executive director of the Nebraska Association of County Officials or his or her designee;</para><para>(e) The probation administrator of the Office of Probation Administration or his or her designee;</para><para>(f) One county commissioner or supervisor;</para><para>(g) One representative from law enforcement;</para><para>(h) The executive director of the Foster Care Review Office;</para><para>(i) One separate juvenile court judge;</para><para>(j) One county court judge;</para><para>(k) Three representatives, one from each congressional district, from community-based, private nonprofit organizations who work with juvenile offenders and their families;</para><para>(l) The director or his or her designee from a secure juvenile detention facility or a staff secure youth confinement facility;</para><para>(m) At least one member who is under twenty-four years of age when appointed, with juvenile justice experience preferred;</para><para>(n) One at-large member;</para><para>(o) One member of a regional behavioral health authority established under section 71-808;</para><para>(p) One county attorney; and</para><para>(q) One juvenile public defender or defense attorney.</para><para>(4)(a) Except as provided in subdivisions (c) through (e) of this subsection, members of the coalition serving prior to June 15, 2018, shall continue to serve on the coalition as representatives of the entity they were appointed to represent until their current terms of office expire and their successors are appointed and confirmed.</para><para>(b) The terms of the members appointed pursuant to subdivisions (3)(f) through (3)(q) of this section shall be three years.</para><para>(c) The positions created pursuant to subdivisions (2)(b)(i), (viii), (x), (xiv), (xvi), (xvii), (xviii), (xx), (xxii), and (xxiii) of this section shall cease to exist on June 15, 2018.</para><para>(d) The police chief appointed pursuant to subdivision (2)(b)(ix) of this section shall continue to serve until the representative from law enforcement under subdivision (3)(g) of this section is appointed.</para><para>(e) The director or his or her designee from a secure juvenile detention facility appointed pursuant to subdivision (2)(b)(xix) of this section shall continue to serve until the member under subdivision (3)(l) of this section is appointed.</para><para>(5) Any vacancy on the coalition shall be filled by appointment by the Governor. The coalition shall select a chairperson, a vice-chairperson, and such other officers as it deems necessary.</para><para>(6) Members of the coalition shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses pursuant to sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(7) The coalition may appoint task forces or subcommittees to carry out its work. Task force and subcommittee members shall have knowledge of, responsibility for, or interest in an area related to the duties of the coalition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 663, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 424, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 138; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB670, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>