<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-2006"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2006</statuteno><catchline>Flagged birth certificate; inquiry and request; how handled.</catchline><para>(1) If an inquiry is made regarding the flagged birth certificate, the department or county agency shall not furnish any information to such requesting person and shall request the name of the inquirer, address, and any other pertinent information. The department and such county agency shall immediately notify the patrol of such inquiry.</para><para>(2) If a request is made in person from the department or such county agency for a flagged birth certificate, the department or such county agency shall:</para><para>(a) Immediately notify the patrol or local law enforcement agency;</para><para>(b) Have the person requesting the flagged birth certificate fill in a form requesting such person's name, address, telephone number, social security number, and relationship to the person whose birth certificate is being requested and the name, address, and birthdate of the person whose birth certificate is being requested;</para><para>(c) Try to obtain a photocopy of the driver's license of the person making the request;</para><para>(d) Inform the person making the request that the birth certificate will be mailed to him or her;</para><para>(e) Report the description of such person making the request and any other relevant information to the patrol or other law enforcement agency; and</para><para>(f) Provide the patrol with copies of such documents but retain the original in the office of the department or county agency.</para><para>(3) If a request is made for such birth certificate in writing, the department or county agency shall notify the patrol and provide the patrol with a copy of the request but retain the original request in the office of the department or county agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 599, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 86. </para></source></law></legaldoc>