<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id399">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id401" statutenumber="43-2404.02">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2404.02</statuteno><catchline id="id404">Community-based
Juvenile Services Aid Program; created; use; reports.</catchline><para>(1)
There is created a separate and distinct budgetary program within the commission
to be known as the Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program. Funding
acquired from participation in the federal act, state General Funds, and funding
acquired from other sources which may be used for purposes consistent with
the Juvenile Services Act and the federal act shall be used to aid in the
establishment and provision of community-based services for juveniles who
come in contact with the juvenile justice system.</para>
<para>(2) The annual General Fund appropriation to the Community-based
Juvenile Services Aid Program shall be apportioned as aid in accordance with
a formula established in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by
the commission. The formula shall be based on the total number of residents
per county and federally recognized or state-recognized Indian tribe who are
twelve years of age through eighteen years of age and other relevant factors
as determined by the commission. The commission may require a local match
of up to forty percent from the county, multiple counties, federally recognized
or state-recognized Indian tribe or tribes, or any combination of the three
which is receiving aid under such program. Any local expenditures for community-based
programs for juveniles may be applied toward such match requirement.</para>
<para>(3)(a) In distributing
funds provided under the Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program, aid
recipients shall prioritize programs and services that will divert juveniles
from the juvenile justice system, reduce the population of juveniles in juvenile
detention and secure confinement, and assist in transitioning juveniles from
out-of-home placements.</para><para>(b) Funds received under the Community-based Juvenile Services
Aid Program shall be used exclusively to assist the aid recipient in the implementation
and operation of programs or the provision of services identified in the aid
recipient's comprehensive juvenile services plan, including programs for local
planning and service coordination; screening, assessment, and evaluation;
diversion; alternatives to detention; family support services; treatment services;
truancy prevention and intervention programs; pilot projects approved by the
commission; payment of transportation costs to and from placements, evaluations,
or services; personnel when the personnel are aligned with evidence-based
treatment principles, programs, or practices; contracting with other state
agencies or private organizations that provide evidence-based treatment or
programs; preexisting programs that are aligned with evidence-based practices
or best practices; and other services that will positively impact juveniles
and families in the juvenile justice system.</para><para>(c) Funds received under
the Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program shall not be used for the
following: Construction of secure detention facilities, secure youth treatment
facilities, or secure youth confinement facilities; capital construction or
the lease or acquisition of facilities; programs, services, treatments, evaluations,
or other preadjudication services that are not based on or grounded in evidence-based
practices, principles, and research, except that the commission may approve
pilot projects that authorize the use of such aid; or office equipment, office
supplies, or office space.</para><para>(d) Any aid not distributed to counties
under this subsection shall be retained by the commission to be distributed
on a competitive basis under the Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program
for a county, multiple counties, federally recognized or state-recognized
Indian tribe or tribes, or any combination of the three demonstrating additional
need in the funding areas identified in this subsection.</para>
<para>(e) If a county,
multiple counties, or a federally recognized or state-recognized Indian tribe
or tribes is denied aid under this section or receives no aid under this section,
the entity may request an appeal pursuant to the appeal process in rules and
regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. The commission shall
establish appeal and hearing procedures by December 15, 2014. The commission
shall make appeal and hearing procedures available on its web site.</para>
<para>(4) Any recipient of aid under the Community-based
Juvenile Services Aid Program shall file an annual report as required by rules
and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. The report shall
include, but not be limited to, the type of juvenile service, how the service
met the goals of the comprehensive juvenile services plan, demographic information
on the total number of juveniles served, program success rates, the total
number of juveniles sent to secure juvenile detention or residential treatment
and secure confinement, and a listing of the expenditures for detention, residential
treatment, and nonresidential treatment.</para>
<para>(5) The commission shall report annually to the Governor
and the Legislature on the distribution and use of funds for aid appropriated under the Community-based
Juvenile Services Aid Program. The report shall include, but not be limited
to, an aggregate report of the use of the Community-based Juvenile Services
Aid Program funds, including the types of juvenile services and programs that
were funded, demographic information on the total number of juveniles served,
program success rates, the total number of juveniles sent to secure juvenile
detention or residential treatment and secure confinement, and a listing of
the expenditures of all counties and federally recognized or state-recognized
Indian tribes for detention, residential treatment, and secure confinement.
The report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(6) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
for the Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program in consultation with
the Director of the Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program, the Director
of Juvenile Diversion Programs, the Office of Probation Administration, the
Nebraska Association of County Officials, and the University of Nebraska at
Omaha, Juvenile Justice Institute. The rules and regulations shall include,
but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The required elements of a comprehensive juvenile services
plan and planning process;</para>
<para>(b) The Community-based Juvenile Services Aid Program formula,
review process, match requirements, and fund distribution. The distribution
process shall ensure a conflict of interest policy;</para>
<para>(c) A distribution process for funds retained under subsection
(3) of this section;</para>
<para>(d) A plan for evaluating the effectiveness of plans and
programs receiving funding;</para>
<para>(e) A reporting process for aid recipients; and</para>
<para>(f) A reporting process for the commission to the Governor
and Legislature. The report shall be made electronically to the Governor and
the Legislature.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 640, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 193, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 30.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>