<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id619">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id621" statutenumber="43-2411"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2411</statuteno><catchline id="id624">Nebraska Coalition
for Juvenile Justice; created; members; terms; expenses; task forces or subcommittee;
authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Coalition for Juvenile
Justice is created. As provided in the federal act, there shall be no less
than fifteen nor more than thirty-three members of the coalition. Coalition members who are members of the
judicial branch of government shall be nonvoting members of the coalition. The
coalition members shall be appointed by the Governor and shall include:</para>
<para>(a) The Administrator of the Office of Juvenile Services;</para>
<para>(b) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health
and Human Services or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(c) The Commissioner of Education or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(d) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on
Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(e) The Executive Director of the Nebraska Association of
County Officials or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(f) The probation administrator of the Office of Probation
Administration or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(g) One county commissioner or supervisor;</para>
<para>(h) One person
with data analysis experience;</para><para>(i) One police chief;</para>
<para>(j) One sheriff;</para>
<para>(k) The executive
director of the Foster Care Review Office;</para><para>(l) One separate juvenile court judge;</para>
<para>(m) One county court judge;</para>
<para>(n) One representative of
mental health professionals who works directly with juveniles;</para>
<para>(o) Three representatives,
one from each congressional district, from community-based, private nonprofit
organizations who work with juvenile offenders and their families;</para>
<para>(p) One volunteer who works
with juvenile offenders or potential juvenile offenders;</para>
<para>(q) One person who works with
an alternative to a detention program for juveniles;</para>
<para>(r) The director or his or
her designee from a youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para>
<para>(s) The director or his or
her designee from a secure juvenile
detention facility;</para>
<para>(t) The director or his or
her designee from a staff secure youth confinement facility;</para>
<para>(u) At least five members
who are under twenty-four years of age when appointed;</para>
<para>(v) One person who works directly
with juveniles who have learning or emotional difficulties or are abused or
neglected;</para>
<para>(w) One member of the Nebraska
Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice;</para>
<para>(x) One member
of a regional behavioral health authority established under section 71-808;</para>
<para>(y) One county attorney; and</para>
<para>(z) One public defender.</para>
<para>(2) The terms of members appointed pursuant to subdivisions
(1)(g) through (1)(z) of this section shall
be three years, except that the terms of the initial appointments of members of the coalition shall
be staggered so that one-third of the members are appointed for terms of one
year, one-third for terms of two years, and one-third for terms of three years,
as determined by the Governor. A majority of the coalition members, including
the chairperson, shall not be full-time employees of federal, state, or local
government. At least one-fifth of the coalition members shall be under the
age of twenty-four at the time of appointment. Any vacancy on the coalition
shall be filled by appointment by the Governor. The coalition shall select
a chairperson, a vice-chairperson, and such other officers as it deems necessary.</para>
<para>(3) Members of the coalition shall be reimbursed for their
actual and necessary expenses pursuant to sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
<para>(4) The coalition may appoint task forces or subcommittees
to carry out its work. Task force and subcommittee members shall have knowledge
of, responsibility for, or interest in an area related to the duties of the
coalition.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 663, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 424, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 138; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 49.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>