<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id422"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-2629"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2629</statuteno><catchline>Child Care Capacity Building and Workforce Grant Program; department; statewide organization; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Child Care Capacity Building and Workforce Grant Program is created.</para><para>(2) The department shall contract with a statewide organization that supports children and families to administer the program, which may include providing technical assistance to any grant recipient. Up to five percent of the money appropriated to the department each fiscal year for purposes of the Child Care Capacity Building and Workforce Act may be reserved for such contract with a statewide organization.</para><para>(3) Under the guidance of the department, the statewide organization shall be responsible for the following under the program:</para><para>(a) Prescribing the form on which an eligible recipient may apply to receive a grant under the program;</para><para>(b) Reviewing applications and identifying potential grant recipients;</para><para>(c) Providing technical assistance to grant recipients; and</para><para>(d) Coordinating with the Department of Health and Human Services and the State Department of Education to determine if the grant request will help meet the child care needs of the eligible recipient.</para><para>(4) The Department of Economic Development shall:</para><para>(a) Award grants to eligible recipients across the state and in urban and rural areas to the fullest extent possible;</para><para>(b) Award a grant to an eligible recipient based upon a list of the potential grant recipients that are identified by the statewide organization; and</para><para>(c) Prioritize applicants that are requesting a grant to:</para><para>(i) Increase child care capacity for children three years of age or younger by creating a new licensed child care program or license-exempt child care program serving children enrolled in child care subsidy or expanding an existing licensed-child care or license-exempt child care program serving children enrolled in child care subsidy;</para><para>(ii) Support the child care workforce; or</para><para>(iii) Create a child care program in a county that is not served by any licensed or license-exempt child care program that offers full-day full-year care.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB164, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>