<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-2411"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2411</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Coalition for Juvenile Justice; created; members; terms; expenses; task forces or subcommittee; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Coalition for Juvenile Justice is created. As provided in the federal act, there shall be no less than fifteen nor more than thirty-three members of the coalition. The coalition members shall be appointed by the Governor and shall include:</para><para>(a) The Administrator of the Office of Juvenile Services;</para><para>(b) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(c) The Commissioner of Education or his or her designee;</para><para>(d) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice or his or her designee;</para><para>(e) The Executive Director of the Nebraska Association of County Officials or his or her designee;</para><para>(f) The probation administrator of the Office of Probation Administration or his or her designee;</para><para>(g) One county commissioner or supervisor;</para><para>(h) One police chief;</para><para>(i) One sheriff;</para><para>(j) One separate juvenile court judge;</para><para>(k) One county court judge;</para><para>(l) One representative of mental health professionals who works directly with juveniles;</para><para>(m) Three representatives, one from each congressional district, from community-based, private nonprofit organizations who work with juvenile offenders and their families;</para><para>(n) One volunteer who works with juvenile offenders or potential juvenile offenders;</para><para>(o) One person who works with an alternative to incarceration program for juveniles;</para><para>(p) The director or his or her designee from a youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(q) The director or his or her designee from a secure youth confinement facility;</para><para>(r) The director or his or her designee from a staff secure youth confinement facility;</para><para>(s) At least five members who are under twenty-four years of age when appointed;</para><para>(t) One person who works directly with juveniles who have learning or emotional difficulties or are abused or neglected;</para><para>(u) One member of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice;</para><para>(v) One county attorney; and</para><para>(w) One public defender.</para><para>(2) The terms of members appointed pursuant to subdivisions (1)(g) through (1)(w) of this section shall be three years, except that the terms of the initial members of the coalition shall be staggered so that one-third of the members are appointed for terms of one year, one-third for terms of two years, and one-third for terms of three years, as determined by the Governor. A majority of the coalition members, including the chairperson, shall not be full-time employees of federal, state, or local government. At least one-fifth of the coalition members shall be under the age of twenty-four at the time of appointment. Any vacancy on the coalition shall be filled by appointment by the Governor. The coalition shall select a chairperson, a vice-chairperson, and such other officers as it deems necessary.</para><para>(3) Members of the coalition shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses pursuant to sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(4) The coalition may appoint task forces or subcommittees to carry out its work. Task force and subcommittee members shall have knowledge of, responsibility for, or interest in an area related to the duties of the coalition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 663, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 424, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 138.</para></source></law></legaldoc>