<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-2925"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2925</statuteno><catchline>Proceeding in which parenting functions for child are at issue; information provided to parties; filing required.</catchline><para>(1) In any proceeding under Chapter 30 or 43 in which the parenting functions for a child are at issue, except any proceeding under the Revised Uniform Reciprocal Enforcement of Support Act or the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act, subsequent to the initial filing or upon filing of an application for modification of a decree, the parties shall receive from the clerk of the court information regarding the parenting plan, the mediation process, and resource materials, as well as the availability of mediation through court conciliation programs or approved mediation centers.</para><para>(2) In any proceeding under Chapter 42 and the Parenting Act in which the parenting functions for a child are at issue, subsequent to the filing of such proceeding all parties shall receive from the clerk of the court information regarding:</para><para>(a) The litigation process;</para><para>(b) A dissolution or separation process timeline;</para><para>(c) Healthy parenting approaches during and after the proceeding;</para><para>(d) Information on child abuse or neglect, domestic intimate partner abuse, and unresolved parental conflict;</para><para>(e) Mediation, specialized alternative dispute resolution, and other alternative dispute resolution processes available through court conciliation programs and approved mediation centers;</para><para>(f) Resource materials identifying the availability of services for victims of child abuse or neglect and domestic intimate partner abuse; and</para><para>(g) Intervention programs for batterers or abusers.</para><para>(3) The clerk of the court and counsel for represented parties shall file documentation of compliance with this section. Development of these informational materials and the implementation of this section shall be accomplished through the State Court Administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB554, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Revised Uniform Reciprocal Enforcement of Support Act,</emphasis> see section 42-7,105.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Interstate Family Support Act,</emphasis> see section 42-701.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>