<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-2412"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-2412</statuteno><catchline>Coalition; powers and duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Consistent with the purposes and objectives of the Juvenile Services
Act and the federal act, the coalition shall:</para>
<para>(a) Make recommendations to the commission on the awarding of grants
under the Commission Grant Program to eligible applicants;</para>
<para>(b) Identify juvenile justice issues, share information, and monitor
and evaluate programs in the juvenile justice system;</para>
<para>(c) Recommend guidelines and supervision procedures to the Office of
Juvenile Services to be used to develop or expand local diversion programs
for juveniles from the juvenile justice system;</para>
<para>(d) Prepare an annual report to the Governor, the Legislature, and the
Office of Juvenile Services including recommendations on administrative and
legislative actions which would improve the juvenile justice system. The report submitted to the Legislature
shall be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(e) Ensure widespread citizen involvement in all phases of its work;
and</para>
<para>(f) Meet at least four times each year.</para>
<para>(2) Consistent with the purposes and objectives of the acts and within
the limits of available time and appropriations, the coalition may:</para>
<para>(a) Recommend criteria to the Office of Juvenile Services for administrative
procedures, including, but not limited to, procedures for intake, detention,
petition filing, and probation supervision;</para>
<para>(b) Recommend to the Office of Juvenile Services minimum professional
standards, including requirements for continuing professional training, for
employees of community-based, youth-serving agencies;</para>
<para>(c) Recommend to the Office of Juvenile Services curricula for and cause
to have conducted training sessions for juvenile court judges and employees
of other community-based, youth-serving agencies;</para>
<para>(d) Assist and advise state and local agencies in the establishment
of volunteer training programs and the utilization of volunteers;</para>
<para>(e) Apply for and receive funds from federal and private sources for
carrying out its powers and duties; and</para>
<para>(f) Provide technical assistance to eligible applicants.</para>
<para>(3) In formulating, adopting, and promulgating the standards, recommendations,
and guidelines provided for in this section, the coalition shall consider
the differences among counties in population, in geography, and in the availability
of local resources.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 663, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 447, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 424, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 640, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 48.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>