<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id184" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-3001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3001</statuteno><catchline id="id187">Child in state custody; court records and information; court order authorized; information confidential; immunity from liability; school records as evidence; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of law regarding the confidentiality of records and when not prohibited by the federal Privacy Act of 1974, as amended, juvenile court records and any other pertinent information that may be in the possession of school districts, school personnel, county attorneys, the Attorney General, law enforcement agencies, child advocacy centers, state probation personnel, state parole personnel, youth detention facilities, medical personnel, treatment or placement programs, the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Correctional Services, the Foster Care Review Office, local foster care review boards, child abuse and neglect investigation teams, child abuse and neglect treatment teams, or other multidisciplinary teams for abuse, neglect, or delinquency concerning a child who is in the custody of the state may be shared with individuals and agencies who have been identified in a court order authorized by this section.</para><para>(2) In any judicial proceeding concerning a child who is currently, or who may become at the conclusion of the proceeding, a ward of the court or state or under the supervision of the court, an order may be issued which identifies individuals and agencies who shall be allowed to receive otherwise confidential information concerning the child for legitimate and official purposes. The individuals and agencies who may be identified in the court order are the child's attorney or guardian ad litem, the parents' attorney, foster parents, appropriate school personnel, county attorneys, the Attorney General, authorized court personnel, law enforcement agencies, state probation personnel, state parole personnel, youth detention facilities, medical personnel, court appointed special advocate volunteers, treatment or placement programs, the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Juvenile Services, the Department of Correctional Services, the Foster Care Review Office, local foster care review boards, the office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare, child abuse and neglect investigation teams, child abuse and neglect treatment teams, other multidisciplinary teams for abuse, neglect, or delinquency, and other individuals and agencies for which the court specifically finds, in writing, that it would be in the best interest of the juvenile to receive such information. Unless the order otherwise states, the order shall be effective until the child leaves the custody of the state or supervision of the court or until a new order is issued.</para><para>(3) All information acquired by an individual or agency pursuant to this section shall be confidential and shall not be disclosed except to other persons who have a legitimate and official interest in the information and are identified in the court order issued pursuant to this section with respect to the child in question. A person who receives such information or who cooperates in good faith with other individuals and agencies identified in the appropriate court order by providing information or records about a child shall be immune from any civil or criminal liability. The provisions of this section granting immunity from liability shall not be extended to any person alleged to have committed an act of child abuse or neglect.</para><para>(4) In any proceeding under this section relating to a child of school age, certified copies of school records relating to attendance and academic progress of such child are admissible in evidence.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, any person who publicly discloses information received pursuant to this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 719, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 988, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 233; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB998, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>