<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3342.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3342.04</statuteno><catchline>Title IV-D Division; establish
Customer Service Unit; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Title IV-D
Division shall establish a Customer Service Unit. In hiring the initial staff
for the unit, a hiring preference shall be given to employees of the clerks
of the district court. The duties of the Customer Service Unit include, but
are not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) Providing account information as well as addressing inquiries made
by customers of the State Disbursement Unit; and</para>
<para>(b) Administering two statewide toll-free telephone systems, one for
use by employers and one for use by all other customers, to provide responses
to inquiries regarding income withholding, the collection and disbursement
of support order payments made to the State Disbursement Unit, and other child
support enforcement issues, including establishing a call center with sufficient
telephone lines, a voice response unit, and adequate personnel available during
normal business hours to ensure that responses to inquiries are made by the
division's personnel or the division's designee.</para>
<para>(2) The physical location of the Customer Service Unit shall be in Nebraska
and shall result in the hiring of a number of new employees or contractor's
staff equal to at least one-fourth of one percent of the labor force in the
county or counties in which the Customer Service Unit is located. Customer
service staff responsible for providing account information related to the
State Disbursement Unit may be located at the same location as the State Disbursement
Unit.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall issue a report to the Governor and to the Legislature
on or before January 31 of each year which discloses information relating
to the operation of the State Disbursement Unit for the preceding calendar
year including, but not limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The number of transactions processed by the State Disbursement Unit;</para>
<para>(b) The dollar amount collected by the State Disbursement Unit;</para>
<para>(c) The dollar amount disbursed by the State Disbursement Unit;</para>
<para>(d) The percentage of identifiable collections disbursed within two
business days;</para>
<para>(e) The percentage of identifiable collections that are matched to the
correct case;</para>
<para>(f) The number and dollar amount of insufficient funds checks received
by the State Disbursement Unit;</para>
<para>(g) The number and dollar amount of insufficient funds checks received
by the State Disbursement Unit for which restitution is subsequently made
to the State Disbursement Unit;</para>
<para>(h) The number of incoming telephone calls processed through the Customer
Service Unit;</para>
<para>(i) The average length of incoming calls from employers;</para>
<para>(j) The average length of incoming calls from all other customers;</para>
<para>(k) The percentage of incoming calls resulting in abandonment by the
customer;</para>
<para>(l) The percentage of incoming calls resulting in a customer receiving
a busy signal;</para>
<para>(m) The average holding time for all incoming calls; and</para>
<para>(n) The percentage of calls handled by employees of the Customer Service
Unit that are resolved within twenty-four hours.</para>
<para>(4) The report issued
to the Legislature pursuant to subsection (3) of this section shall be issued
electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 972, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 169; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 50.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>