<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-3402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3402</statuteno><catchline>Council; advisory duties.</catchline>
<para>With respect to the Early Intervention Act, the Quality Child Care Act,
and sections 79-1101 to 79-1104, the Early Childhood Interagency Coordinating
Council shall serve in an advisory capacity to state agencies responsible
for early childhood care and education, including care for school-age children,
in order to:</para>
<para>(1) Promote the policies set forth in the Early Intervention Act, the
Quality Child Care Act, and sections 79-1101 to 79-1104;</para>
<para>(2) Facilitate collaboration with the federally administered Head Start
program;</para>
<para>(3) Make recommendations to the Department of Health and Human Services,
the State Department of Education, and other state agencies responsible for
the regulation or provision of early childhood care and education programs
on the needs, priorities, and policies relating to such programs throughout
the state;</para>
<para>(4) Make recommendations to the lead agency or agencies which prepare
and submit applications for federal funding;</para>
<para>(5) Review new or proposed revisions to rules and regulations governing
the registration or licensing of early childhood care and education programs;</para>
<para>(6) Study and recommend additional resources for early childhood care
and education programs; and</para>
<para>(7) Report biennially to the Governor and Legislature on the status
of early intervention and early childhood care and education in the state. The report submitted to the Legislature
shall be submitted electronically. Such report shall include (a)
the number of license applications received under section 71-1911, (b) the
number of such licenses issued, (c) the number of such license applications
denied, (d) the number of complaints investigated regarding such licensees,
(e) the number of such licenses revoked, (f) the number and dollar amount
of civil penalties levied pursuant to section 71-1920, and (g) information
which may assist the Legislature in determining the extent of cooperation
provided to the Department of Health and Human Services by other state and
local agencies pursuant to section 71-1914.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1135, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 171; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 51.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Early Intervention Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Quality Child Care Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2601.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>