<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3333"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3333</statuteno><catchline>Seizure of obligor's property; notice of arrearage; contents; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) In a case which is receiving services under Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, when the department has made reasonable efforts to verify and has reason to believe payment on a support order is in arrears in an amount equal to the support due and payable for more than a three-month period of time or upon the request of the state agency of another state which administers Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act, and therefor determines to seize an obligor's property, the department shall send written notice to the obligor by first-class mail to the last-known address of the obligor or to the last-known address of the obligor available to the court pursuant to section 42-364.13. For purposes of this section, reasonable efforts to verify means reviewing the case file and having written or oral communication with the clerk of the district court.</para><para>(2) The notice of arrearage shall:</para><para>(a) Specify the court or agency which issued the support order;</para><para>(b) Specify the arrearage under the support order which the obligor owes as of the date of the notice or other date certain;</para><para>(c) Specify that any enforcement action will incorporate any arrearage which may accrue in the future;</para><para>(d) State clearly, "Your property may be seized without further notice if you do not respond or clear up the arrearage"; and</para><para>(e) Specify that within twenty days after the notice is mailed, the obligor may request, in writing, a hearing to contest a mistake of fact. For purposes of this section, mistake of fact means an error in the amount of the arrearage or an error in the identity of the obligor.</para><para>(3) If the obligor files a written request for a hearing based upon a mistake of fact within twenty days after the notice is mailed, the department shall provide an opportunity for a hearing and shall stay enforcement action under sections 43-3333 to 43-3337 until the administrative appeal process is completed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 164.</para></source></law></legaldoc>