<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-3401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3401</statuteno><catchline>Early Childhood Interagency Coordinating Council; created; membership; terms; expenses.</catchline><para>The Early Childhood Interagency Coordinating Council is created. The council shall advise and assist the collaborating agencies in carrying out the provisions of the Early Intervention Act, the Quality Child Care Act, sections 79-1101 to 79-1104, and other early childhood care and education initiatives under state supervision. Membership and activities of the council shall comply with all applicable provisions of federal law. Members of the council shall be appointed by the Governor and shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(1) Parents of children who require early intervention services, early childhood special education, and other early childhood care and education services; and</para><para>(2) Representatives of school districts, social services, health and medical services, family child care and center-based early childhood care and education programs, agencies providing training to staff of child care programs, resource and referral agencies, mental health services, developmental disabilities services, educational service units, Head Start, higher education, physicians, the Legislature, business persons, and the collaborating agencies.</para><para>Terms of the members shall be for three years, and a member shall not serve more than two consecutive three-year terms. Members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses, including child care expenses, with funds provided for such purposes through the Early Intervention Act, the Quality Child Care Act, and sections 79-1101 to 79-1104.</para><para>Members of the Nebraska Interagency Coordinating Council serving on July 13, 2000, shall constitute the Early Childhood Interagency Coordinating Council and shall serve for the remainder of their terms. The Governor shall make additional appointments as required by this section and to fill vacancies as needed. The Governor shall set the initial terms of additional appointees to result in staggered terms for members of the council. The Department of Health and Human Services and the State Department of Education shall provide and coordinate staff assistance to the council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1135, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 170.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Early Intervention Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Quality Child Care Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2601.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>