<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3327"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3327</statuteno><catchline>Support orders and genetic testing; access to information without court or administrative order; fee authorized; confidentiality; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Authorized attorney has the same meaning as in section 43-1704;</para><para>(b) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(c) Genetic testing means genetic testing ordered pursuant to section 43-1414; and</para><para>(d) Support order has the same meaning as in section 43-1717.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding any other provision of law regarding the confidentiality of records, the department, a county attorney, or an authorized attorney may, without obtaining a court or administrative order:</para><para>(a) Compel by subpoena (i) information relevant to establishing, modifying, or enforcing a support order and (ii) genetic testing of an individual relevant to establishing, modifying, or enforcing a support order. Such information includes, but is not limited to, relevant financial records and other relevant records including the name, address, and listing of financial assets or liabilities from public or private entities. If a person fails or refuses to obey the subpoena, the department, a county attorney, or an authorized attorney may apply to a judge of the court of competent jurisdiction for an order directing such person to comply with the subpoena. Failure to obey such court order may be punished by the court as contempt of court; and</para><para>(b) Obtain access to information contained in the records, including automated data bases, of any state or local agency which is relevant to establishing, modifying, or enforcing a support order or to ordering genetic testing. Such records include, but are not limited to, vital records, state and local tax and revenue records, titles to real and personal property, employment security records, records of correctional institutions, and records concerning the ownership and control of business entities.</para><para>(3) The department shall subpoena or access information as provided in subsection (2) of this section at the request of a state agency of another state which administers Title IV-D of the federal Social Security Act for such information. The department may charge a fee for this service which does not exceed the cost of providing the service.</para><para>(4) All information acquired pursuant to this section is confidential and cannot be disclosed or released except to other agencies which have a legitimate and official interest in the information for carrying out the purposes of this section. A person who receives such information, subject to the provisions of this subsection on confidentiality and restrictions on disclosure or release, is immune from any civil or criminal liability. A person who cooperates in good faith by providing information or records under this section is immune from any civil or criminal liability. Any person acquiring information pursuant to this section who discloses or releases such information in violation of this subsection is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor. The disclosure or release of such information regarding an individual is a separate offense from information disclosed or released regarding any other individual.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 162.</para></source></law></legaldoc>