
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id92"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3604</statuteno><catchline>Youth Reentry and Transitional Support Program; created; transition plan; supervision.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Juvenile Services, the Office of Probation Administration, and the State Department of Education shall collaboratively establish the Youth Reentry and Transitional Support Program.</para><para>(b) The Department of Health and Human Services shall be responsible for supervision and programming for youth placed in the care, custody, and control of the department by court order pursuant to the Nebraska Juvenile Code. The Office of Probation Administration shall be responsible for supervision and programming for youth placed under probation supervision by court order pursuant to the Nebraska Juvenile Code.</para><para>(2) The Youth Reentry and Transitional Support Program shall provide for the following for each youth:</para><para>(a) Completion of a transition plan;</para><para>(b) Regular reviews of each youth's transition plan. These reviews shall be accomplished by a representative of the facility or the Office of Probation Administration, as appropriate, and shall occur weekly for detention or other short-term placements and monthly for all other placements, including placement at a youth rehabilitation and treatment center; and</para><para>(c) Supervision following re-entry by the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Juvenile Services, or the Office of Probation Administration, as appropriate, to ensure a successful  transition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB962, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>December 1, 2026</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> see section 43-2,129.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>