<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id272">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id274" statutenumber="43-3709"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3709</statuteno><catchline id="id277">Volunteers;
minimum qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) The minimum qualifications
for any prospective court appointed special advocate volunteer are that he
or she shall:</para>
<para>(a) Be at least twenty-one years of age or older and have
demonstrated an interest in children and their welfare;</para>
<para>(b) Be willing to commit to the court for a minimum of one
year of service to a child;</para>
<para>(c) Complete an application, including providing background
information required pursuant to subsection (2) of this section;</para>
<para>(d) Participate in a screening interview; and</para>
<para>(e) Participate in the training required pursuant to section
43-3708.</para>
<para>(2) As required background screening, the program director
shall obtain the following information regarding a volunteer applicant:</para>
<para>(a) A check of the applicant's criminal history record information
maintained by the Identification Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation
through the Nebraska State Patrol;</para>
<para>(b) A check of his or her record with the central registry of child protection cases maintained
under section 28-718;</para>
<para>(c) A check of his or her driving record; and</para>
<para>(d) At least three references who will attest to the applicant's
character, judgment, and suitability for the position of a court appointed
special advocate volunteer.</para>
<para>(3) If the applicant has lived in Nebraska for less than
twelve months, the program director shall obtain the records required in subdivisions
(2)(a) through (2)(c) of this section from all other jurisdictions in which
the applicant has lived during the preceding year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 27.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>