<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3336"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3336</statuteno><catchline>Order to withhold and deliver; co-owner; notice; contents; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) If, after receiving the information from the payor in subdivision (3)(b) of section 43-3334, the department has knowledge that another person has an ownership interest or may claim an ownership interest in any property sought to be reached which is in the possession or under the control of the payor as the property of the obligor, the department shall send written notice to such person or persons by certified mail, return receipt requested. The notice shall be dated and shall specify why the order to withhold and deliver was issued, the payor to which the order to withhold and deliver was sent, and that the person has a right to request a hearing by the department within fifteen days after the date of the notice to establish that the property or any part thereof is not the property of the obligor. The department shall provide an opportunity for hearing to a person making such request and shall stay enforcement actions under sections 43-3333 to 43-3337 until the administrative appeal process is completed.</para><para>(2) Any person other than the obligor claiming an ownership interest in any property sought to be reached which is in the possession or under the control of the payor as the property of the obligor has a right to timely request a hearing by the department to establish that the property or any part thereof is not the property of the obligor. The department shall provide an opportunity for hearing to a person making such request and shall stay enforcement actions under sections 43-3333 to 43-3337 until the administrative appeal process is completed. If the property or any part of the property which is in the possession or under the control of the payor is not the property of the obligor, the payor is discharged as to that property which is not the obligor's.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 167.</para></source></law></legaldoc>