<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id482"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3605</statuteno><catchline>Transition plan; development; when required; contents; family meetings; duplication of services.</catchline><para>(1) A transition plan shall be developed for each youth upon admission to a facility or admission to another congregate care placement or probation supervision.</para><para>(2) The transition plan shall be developed using validated assessment instruments, screenings, and evaluations. The transition plan shall be developed collaboratively with involvement from the youth, the youth's family or guardian, and facility representatives and the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Juvenile Services, or the Office of Probation Administration, as appropriate. When possible, development of the plan should include coordinating with local family resource centers, community-based providers, or other community resources in order to support the youth and the youth's family and identify long-term supports.</para><para>(3) A transition plan shall include provisions regarding:</para><para>(a) Treatment services, including continuity of behavioral health, medical, and medicaid services;</para><para>(b) Enrolling eligible youth in programs and services offered by the State Department of Education;</para><para>(c) Developing an individualized employment plan identifying career and training pathways for youth obtaining employment upon reentry;</para><para>(d) Services from community-based providers, including credible messenger mentoring or in-home supportive or behavioral health services;</para><para>(e) Coordinating with family resource centers to align family and community support;</para><para>(f) A housing stabilization strategy and safe placement;</para><para>(g) A school reentry or educational advancement plan;</para><para>(h) Assisting youth in applying for medicaid benefits and maintaining eligibility;</para><para>(i) Plans and processes to obtain identification documents and public benefits; and</para><para>(j) Family engagement and restorative justice objectives consistent with reforms enacted in Laws 2023, LB50.</para><para>(4) During the first ninety days following a youth's re-entry, a family team meeting shall be held at least once every thirty days. Such meeting shall include the youth and the youth's family or guardian and the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Juvenile Services, or the Office of Probation Administration, as appropriate.</para><para>(5) Youth who are eligible for participation in the bridge to independence program as provided in the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act shall be referred to that program. Services under the Youth Reentry and Transitional Support Act shall not duplicate services available under the bridge to independence program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB962, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>December 1, 2026</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act,</emphasis> see section 43-4501.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>