<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id139" statutenumber="43-3342.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3342.05</statuteno><catchline id="id142">Child Support Advisory Commission; created; members; terms; expenses; personnel; duties; Supreme Court; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Child Support Advisory Commission is created. Commission members shall include:</para><para>(a) Two district court judges whose jurisdiction includes domestic relations, to be appointed by the Supreme Court;</para><para>(b) One member of the Nebraska State Bar Association who practices primarily in the area of domestic relations;</para><para>(c) One county attorney who works in child support;</para><para>(d) One professional who works in the field of economics or mathematics or another field of expertise relevant to child support;</para><para>(e) One custodial parent who has a court order to receive child support;</para><para>(f) One noncustodial parent who is under a support order to pay child support;</para><para>(g) The chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature, who shall serve as the chairperson of the commission;</para><para>(h) The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature;</para><para>(i) The State Treasurer or his or her designee;</para><para>(j) The State Court Administrator or his or her designee; and</para><para>(k) The director of the Title IV-D Division or his or her designee.</para><para>(2)(a) The Supreme Court shall notify the Executive Board of the Legislative Council of its intent to review the child support guidelines pursuant to section 42-364.16. Following such notification, the chairperson of the commission shall call a meeting of the commission.</para><para>(b) Each time the commission meets pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section, the Supreme Court shall make appointments to fill the membership under subdivision (1)(a) of this section and the chairperson of the Executive Board shall make appointments to fill each membership under subdivisions (1)(b) through (f) of this section. The terms of these members shall expire after the commission has fulfilled its duties pursuant to subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(c) Members shall serve without compensation but shall be reimbursed for expenses incurred in the performance of their duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(d) If determined to be necessary to perform the duties of the commission, the commission may hire, contract, or otherwise obtain the services of consultants, researchers, aides, and other necessary support staff with prior approval of the chairperson of the Executive Board.</para><para>(e) For administrative purposes, the commission shall be managed and administered by the Legislative Council.</para><para>(3) The duties of the commission shall include, but are not limited to:</para><para>(a) Reviewing the child support guidelines adopted by the Supreme Court and recommending, if appropriate, any changes to the guidelines. Whenever practicable, the commission shall base its recommendations on economic data and statistics collected in the State of Nebraska. In reviewing the guidelines and formulating recommendations, the commission may conduct public hearings around the state; and</para><para>(b) Presenting reports, as deemed necessary, of its activities and recommendations to the Supreme Court and the Executive Board. Any reports submitted to the Executive Board shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(4) The Supreme Court shall review the commission's reports. The Supreme Court may amend the child support guidelines established pursuant to section 42-364.16 based upon the commission's recommendations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 972, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>