<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-3334"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3334</statuteno><catchline>Order to withhold and deliver; when; contents; payor; duties; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The department may send a payor an order to withhold and deliver specifically identified property of any kind due, owing, or belonging to an obligor if (a) the department has reason to and does believe that there is in the possession of the payor property which is due, owing, or belonging to an obligor, (b) payment on a support order is in arrears, (c) the department sent a notice of arrearage to the obligor pursuant to section 43-3333 at least thirty days prior to sending the notice to withhold and deliver, and (d) no hearing was requested or after a hearing the department determined that an arrearage did exist or that there was no mistake of fact.</para><para>(2) The order to withhold and deliver shall state that notice has been mailed to the obligor in accordance with the requirements of subdivision (1)(c) of this section and that the obligor has not requested a hearing or, after a hearing, the department has determined that an arrearage exists or that there was no mistake of fact, the amount in arrears, the social security number of the obligor, the court or agency to which the property is to be delivered, instructions for transmitting the property, and information regarding the requirements found in subsection (3) of this section. The order shall include written questions regarding the property of every description, including whether or not any other person has an ownership interest in the property, and the credits of the obligor which are in the possession or under the control of the payor at the time the order is received.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of an order to withhold and deliver, a payor shall:</para><para>(a) Hold property that is subject to the order and that is in the possession or under the control of the payor at the time the order to withhold and deliver was received, to the extent of the amount of the arrearage stated in the order until the payor receives further notice from the department;</para><para>(b) Answer all of the questions asked of the payor in the order, supply the name and address of any person that has an ownership interest in the property sought to be reached, and return such information to the department within five business days after receiving the order; and</para><para>(c) Upon further notice from the department, deliver any property which may be subject to the order to the court or agency designated in the order or release such property or portion thereof.</para><para>(4) An order to withhold and deliver shall have the same priority as a garnishment for the support of a person pursuant to subsection (4) of section 25-1056.</para><para>(5) If the payor is a financial institution, such financial institution may deduct and retain a processing fee from any amounts turned over to the department under this section. The processing fee shall not exceed ten dollars for each account turned over to the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 165.</para></source></law></legaldoc>