<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id5" statutenumber="43-3342.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>43-3342.03</statuteno><catchline id="id8">State Disbursement Unit; support order collection; fees authorized; State Disbursement Unit Cash Fund; created; use; investment; electronic remittance by employers.</catchline><para>(1) All support orders shall direct payment of support as provided in section 42-369. Any support order issued prior to the date that the State Disbursement Unit becomes operative for which the payment is to be made to the clerk of the district court shall be deemed to require payment to the State Disbursement Unit after a notice to the obligor is issued. Support order payments made to the clerk of the district court shall be forwarded to the State Disbursement Unit by electronic transfer.</para><para>(2) The State Disbursement Unit may collect a fee equal to the actual cost of processing any payments for returned check charges or charges for electronic payments not accepted, except that the fee shall not exceed thirty dollars. After a payor has originated one payment resulting in a returned check or an electronic payment not accepted within a period of two years, the unit may issue a notice to the originator that, for the following year, any payment shall be required to be paid by money order, cashier's check, certified check, or any other form of guaranteed payment as may be approved by the unit. After a payor has originated two payments resulting in returned checks or electronic payments not accepted, the unit may issue a notice to the originator that all future payments shall be paid by money order, cashier's check, certified check, or any other form of guaranteed payment as may be approved by the unit, except that pursuant to rule and regulation and at least two years after such issuance of notice, the unit may waive for good cause shown such requirements for methods of payment. The fees shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Disbursement Unit Cash Fund, which is hereby created, which funds shall be used to offset the expenses incurred in the collection of child support bad debt and other collection expenses incurred by the unit. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) The State Disbursement Unit shall use automated procedures, electronic processes, and computer-driven technology to the maximum extent feasible, efficient, and economical for the collection and disbursement of support payments.</para><para>(4) Employers with more than fifty employees who have an employee with a child support order shall remit child support payments electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 972, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 116, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB620, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB505, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>