<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id29">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id31" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4405</statuteno><catchline>Statewide automated child welfare
information system; report; contents.</catchline><para>On or before December 1, 2012,
the department, with assistance from other agencies as necessary, including
the data coordinator for the State Foster Care Review Board or a successor
entity to the powers and duties of the board, shall report in writing to the
Legislature on a plan for the statewide automated child welfare information
system described in section 43-4404. The report shall include a review of
the design, development, implementation, and cost of the system. The report
shall describe the requirements of the system and all available options and
compare costs of the options. The report shall include, but not be limited
to, a review of the options for (1) system functionality, (2) the potential
of the system's use of shared services in areas including, but not limited
to, intake, rules, financial information, and reporting, (3) integration,
(4) maintenance costs, (5) application architecture to enable flexibility
and scalability, (6) deployment costs, (7) licensing fees, (8) training requirements,
and (9) operational costs and support needs. The report shall compare the
costs and benefits of a custom-built system and a commercial off-the-shelf
system, the total cost of ownership, including both direct and indirect costs,
and the costs of any other options considered. In conjunction with the report,
the department shall prepare the advance planning document required to qualify
for federal funding for the statewide automated child welfare information
system pursuant to 45 C.F.R. 1355.50 through 1355.57, implementing section
474(a)(3)(C) and (D) of Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act, 42
U.S.C. 674(a)(3)(C) and (D), as such regulations and section existed on January
1, 2012. The advance planning document shall describe the proposed plan for
managing the design, development, and operations of a statewide automated
child welfare information system that meets such federal requirements and
the state's needs in an efficient, comprehensive, and cost-effective manner. </para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 5.</para><operativedate>April 12, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>