<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id313"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-4810"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4810</statuteno><catchline>Judgment of emancipation; effect; certified copy; use by third party.</catchline><para>(1) A judgment of emancipation removes the disability of minority insofar as that disability may affect: (a) Establishment of his or her own residence; (b) incurring indebtedness or contractual obligations of any kind; (c) consenting to medical, dental, or psychiatric care without the consent, knowledge, or liability of parents or a guardian; (d) enlisting in the military without a parent’s or guardian's consent; (e) marrying without a parent’s or guardian's consent; (f) being individually eligible for public assistance; (g) the litigation and settlement of controversies; (h) enrolling in any school or college; and (i) acquiring, encumbering, and conveying property or any interest therein. For the purposes described in this subsection, the minor shall be considered in law as an adult and any obligation or benefit he or she incurs is enforceable by and against such minor without regard to his or her minority.</para><para>(2) A minor emancipated by court order shall be considered to have the rights and responsibilities of an adult, except for those specific constitutional and statutory age requirements regarding voting, use of alcoholic beverages, gambling, use of tobacco, and other health and safety regulations relevant to the minor because of his or her age.</para><para>(3) The emancipated minor shall be provided a certified copy of the judgment of emancipation at the time the judgment is entered. Upon presentation of the judgment of emancipation, a third party shall be allowed to retain a copy of the same as proof of the minor’s ability to act as stated in this section.</para><para>(4) Unless otherwise provided in the judgment of emancipation, the judgment of emancipation shall explicitly suspend any order regarding custody, parenting time, or support of the minor and be reported by the district court clerk to the jurisdiction that issued such order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB714, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>