<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id70">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id72" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4507"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4507</statuteno><catchline>Termination of voluntary services
and support agreement; notice; appeal; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A young adult may choose to terminate
the voluntary services and support agreement and stop receiving services and
support under the extended services program at any time. If a young adult
chooses to terminate the voluntary services and support agreement, the department
shall provide the young adult with a clear and developmentally appropriate
written notice informing the young adult of the potential negative effects
of terminating the voluntary services and support agreement early, the option
to reenter the extended services program at any time before attaining twenty-one
years of age, and the procedures for reentering the extended services program.</para>
<para>(2) If the
department determines that the young adult is no longer eligible under section
43-4504, the department may terminate the voluntary services and support agreement
and stop providing services and support to the young adult. Academic breaks
in postsecondary education attendance, such as semester and seasonal breaks,
and other transitions between eligibility requirements under section 43-4504,
including education and employment transitions of no longer than thirty days,
shall not be a basis for termination. Even if a young adult's voluntary services
and support agreement has been previously terminated by either the department
or the young adult, the young adult may come back into the extended services
program by entering into another voluntary services and support agreement
at any time, so long as he or she is eligible under section 43-4504. At least
thirty days prior to the termination of the voluntary services and support
agreement, the department shall provide a clear and developmentally appropriate
written notice to the young adult informing the young adult of the termination
of the voluntary services and support agreement and a clear and developmentally
appropriate explanation of the basis for the termination. The written termination
notice shall also provide information about the process for appealing the
termination, information about the option to enter into another voluntary
services and support agreement once the young adult reestablishes eligibility
under section 43-4504, and information about and contact information for community
resources that may benefit the young adult, specifically including information
regarding state programs established pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 677. The young
adult may appeal the termination of the voluntary services and support agreement,
and such appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 7.</para><effectivedate>June 5, 2013</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>