<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id13">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id15" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4202</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Children's Commission; created;
duties; members; expenses; meetings; staff; consultant; termination of commission.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Nebraska
Children's Commission is created as a high-level leadership body to (a) create
a statewide strategic plan for reform of the child welfare system programs
and services in the State of Nebraska and (b) review the operations of the
Department of Health and Human Services regarding child welfare programs and
services and recommend, as a part of the statewide strategic plan, options
for attaining the legislative intent stated in section 43-4201, either by
the establishment of a new division within the department or the establishment
of a new state agency to provide all child welfare programs and services which
are the responsibility of the state. The commission shall provide a permanent
forum for collaboration among state, local, community, public, and private
stakeholders in child welfare programs and services.</para>
<para>(2) The commission
shall include the following voting members:</para><para>(a) The chief executive officer of the Department
of Health and Human Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The Director of
Children and Family Services or his or her designee; and</para>
<para>(c) Sixteen
members appointed by the Governor within thirty days after April 12, 2012.
The members appointed pursuant to this subdivision shall represent stakeholders
in the child welfare system and shall include: (i) A director of a child advocacy
center; (ii) an administrator of a behavioral health region established pursuant
to section 71-807; (iii) a community representative from each of the service
areas designated pursuant to section 81-3116. In the eastern service area
designated pursuant to such section, the representative may be from a lead
agency of a pilot project established under Legislative Bill 961, One Hundred
Second Legislature, Second Session, 2012, or a collaborative member; (iv)
a prosecuting attorney who practices in juvenile court; (v) a guardian ad
litem; (vi) a biological parent currently or previously involved in the child
welfare system; (vii) a foster parent; (viii) a court-appointed special advocate
volunteer; (ix) a member of the State Foster Care Review Board or any entity
that succeeds to the powers and duties of the board or a member of a local
foster care review board; (x) a child welfare service agency that directly
provides a wide range of child welfare services and is not a member of a lead
agency collaborative; (xi) a young adult previously in foster care; and (xii)
a representative of a child advocacy organization that deals with legal and
policy issues that include child welfare.</para><para>(3) The commission shall have the following
nonvoting, ex officio members: (a) The chairperson of the Health and Human
Services Committee of the Legislature or a committee member designated by
the chairperson; (b) the chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature
or a committee member designated by the chairperson; (c) the chairperson of
the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature or a committee member designated
by the chairperson; and (d) three persons appointed by the State Court Administrator.
The nonvoting, ex officio members may attend commission meetings and participate
in the discussions of the commission, provide information to the commission
on the policies, programs, and processes of each of their respective bodies,
gather information for the commission, and provide information back to their
respective bodies from the commission. The nonvoting, ex officio members shall
not vote on decisions by the commission or on the direction or development
of the statewide strategic plan pursuant to section 43-4204.</para>
<para>(4) The commission
shall meet within sixty days after April 12, 2012, and shall select from among
its members a chairperson and vice-chairperson and conduct any other business
necessary to the organization of the commission. The commission shall meet
not less often than once every three months, and meetings of the commission
may be held at any time on the call of the chairperson. The commission shall
be within the office of the chief executive officer of the Department of Health
and Human Services. The commission may hire staff to carry out the responsibilities
of the commission. The commission shall hire a consultant with experience
in facilitating strategic planning to provide neutral, independent assistance
in developing the statewide strategic plan. The commission shall terminate
on June 30, 2014, unless continued by the Legislature.</para>
<para>(5) Members of
the commission shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses
as members of such commission as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>