<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id131">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id133" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4506</statuteno><catchline id="id136">Participation
in bridge to independence program;
voluntary services and support agreement; contents; services provided; independence coordinator; department;
duties.</catchline><para>(1) If a young adult chooses to participate
in the bridge to independence program
and is eligible under section 43-4504, the young adult and the department
shall sign, and the young adult shall be provided a copy of, a voluntary services
and support agreement that includes, at a minimum, information regarding all
of the following:</para>
<para>(a) The requirement that the young adult continue to be eligible
under section 43-4504 for the duration of the voluntary services and support
agreement and any other expectations of the young adult;</para>
<para>(b) The services and support the young adult shall receive
through the bridge to independence program;</para>
<para>(c) The voluntary nature of the young adult's participation
and the young adult's right to terminate the voluntary services and support
agreement at any time; and</para>
<para>(d) Conditions that may result in the termination of the
voluntary services and support agreement and the young adult's early discharge
from the bridge to independence program
as described in section 43-4507.</para>
<para>(2) As soon as the young adult and the department sign the
voluntary services and support agreement and the department determines that
the young adult is eligible for
the bridge to independence program under section 43-4504, but
not longer than forty-five days after signing the agreement, the department
shall provide services and support to the young adult in accordance with the
voluntary services and support agreement.</para>
<para>(3) A young adult participating in the bridge to independence program shall be assigned an independence coordinator to
provide case management services for the young adult. Independence coordinators and their supervisors shall
be specialized in primarily providing services for young adults in the bridge to independence program
or shall, at minimum, have specialized training in providing transition services
and support to young adults.</para>
<para>(4) The department shall provide continued efforts at achieving
permanency and creating permanent connections for a young adult participating
in the bridge to independence program.</para>
<para>(5) The department shall fulfill all case plan obligations
consistent with 42 U.S.C. 675(1).</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 35.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>