<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id133">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id135" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4317"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4317</statuteno><catchline>Office of Inspector General of Nebraska
Child Welfare; created; purpose; Inspector General; appointment; term; certification;
employees; removal.</catchline><para>(1) The office of Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare
is created within the office of Public Counsel for the purpose of conducting
investigations, audits, inspections, and other reviews of the Nebraska child
welfare system. The Inspector General shall be appointed by the Public Counsel
with approval from the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative
Council and the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of
the Legislature.</para>
<para>(2) The Inspector
General shall be appointed for a term of five years and may be reappointed.
The Inspector General shall be selected without regard to political affiliation
and on the basis of integrity, capability for strong leadership, and demonstrated
ability in accounting, auditing, financial analysis, law, management analysis,
public administration, investigation, or criminal justice administration or
other closely related fields. No former or current executive or manager of
the department may be appointed Inspector General within five years after
such former or current executive's or manager's period of service with the
department. Not later than two years after the date of appointment, the Inspector
General shall obtain certification as a Certified Inspector General by the
Association of Inspectors General, its successor, or another nationally recognized
organization that provides and sponsors educational programs and establishes
professional qualifications, certifications, and licensing for inspectors
general. During his or her employment, the Inspector General shall not be
actively involved in partisan affairs.</para><para>(3) The Inspector General shall employ
such investigators and support staff as he or she deems necessary to carry
out the duties of the office within the amount available by appropriation
through the office of Public Counsel for the office of Inspector General of
Nebraska Child Welfare. The Inspector General shall be subject to the control
and supervision of the Public Counsel, except that removal of the Inspector
General shall require approval of the chairperson of the Executive Board of
the Legislative Council and the chairperson of the Health and Human Services
Committee of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 24.</para><effectivedate>April 12, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>