<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id199">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id201" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4514"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4514</statuteno><catchline id="id204">Department;
submit state plan amendment to seek federal funding; approval; effect; denial;
effect; rules and regulations; references to United States Code; how construed.</catchline>
<para>(1) The department shall submit a state plan amendment by
October 15, 2013, to seek federal Title IV-E funding under 42 U.S.C. 672 and
42 U.S.C. 673 for the bridge
to independence program pursuant to the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act.</para>
<para>(2) The bridge
to independence program or the state-extended guardianship assistance
program under either subsection (3) or (4) of this section shall not begin
prior to January 1, 2014.</para>
<para>(3) If the state plan amendment is approved:</para>
<para>(a) The department shall implement the bridge to independence program in accordance
with the federal Fostering Connections to Success and Increasing Adoptions
Act of 2008, 42 U.S.C. 673 and 42 U.S.C. 675(8)(B) and in accordance with
requirements necessary to obtain federal Title IV-E funding under 42 U.S.C.
672 and 42 U.S.C. 673. If the department does not contract with a private
agency to implement the bridge
to independence program, the bridge
to independence program shall take effect within sixty days after
the department receives the notice of approval of the state plan amendment.
If the department contracts with a private agency to implement the bridge to independence program,
the bridge to independence program
shall take effect within ninety days after the department receives the notice
of approval of the state plan amendment; and</para>
<para>(b) The department shall implement a state-extended guardianship
assistance program. The state-extended guardianship assistance program shall
not be construed to create an entitlement. Under the state-extended guardianship
assistance program, a young adult (i) for whom the state has entered into
a guardianship assistance agreement at sixteen years of age or older that
is not with a licensed relative and (ii) who meets at least one of the conditions
of eligibility under subdivisions (1)(a)
through (e) of section 43-4511, the department shall continue
making guardianship assistance payments on behalf of such young adult until
he or she attains twenty-one years of age to the extent possible within funds
appropriated for the state-extended guardianship assistance program. It is
the intent of the Legislature to appropriate four hundred thousand dollars
for fiscal years 2013-14 and 2014-15 for the state-extended guardianship assistance
program.</para>
<para>(4) If the state plan amendment is denied, the department
shall implement the bridge
to independence program as a state-only pilot program within sixty
days after the department receives the notice of denial. If implemented as
a state-only pilot program, it is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate
two million dollars for fiscal years 2013-14 and 2014-15 for such state-only
pilot program. The department shall administer the state-only pilot program
to serve as many eligible young adults as possible within the funds appropriated.
If a state-only pilot program is established, the Bridge to Independence Advisory
Committee shall make recommendations to the department and the Nebraska Children's
Commission regarding eligibility criteria and private or alternative funding
options within thirty days after the department receives the notice of denial.</para>
<para>(5) Prior to January 1, 2014, the department shall adopt
and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act.</para>
<para>(6) All references to the United States Code in the Young
Adult Bridge
to Independence Act refer to sections of the code as such sections
existed on January 1, 2013.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 44.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>