<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id23" statutenumber="43-4216"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4216</statuteno><catchline>Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee; created; members; terms; vacancies.</catchline><para>(1) The Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee is created. The committee shall be convened at least once every four years.</para><para>(2) The Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee shall consist of no fewer than nine members, including:</para><para>(a) The following voting members: (i) Representatives from a child welfare agency that contracts directly with foster parents, from each of the service areas designated pursuant to section 81-3116; (ii) a representative from an advocacy organization which deals with legal and policy issues that include child welfare; (iii) a representative from an advocacy organization, the singular focus of which is issues impacting children; (iv) a representative from a foster and adoptive parent association; (v) a representative from a lead agency; (vi) a representative from a child advocacy organization that supports young adults who were in foster care as children; (vii) a foster parent who contracts directly with the Department of Health and Human Services; and (viii) a foster parent who contracts with a child welfare agency; and</para><para>(b) The following nonvoting, ex officio members: (i) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee and (ii) representatives from the Division of Children and Family Services of the department from each service area designated pursuant to section 81-3116, including at least one division employee with a thorough understanding of the current foster care payment system and at least one division employee with a thorough understanding of the N-FOCUS electronic data collection system. The nonvoting, ex officio members of the committee may attend committee meetings and participate in discussions of the committee and shall gather and provide information to the committee on the policies, programs, and processes of each of their respective bodies. The nonvoting, ex officio members shall not vote on decisions or recommendations by the committee.</para><para>(3) Members of the committee shall serve for terms of four years and until their successors are appointed and qualified. The Nebraska Children's Commission shall appoint the members of the committee and the chairperson of the committee and may fill vacancies on the committee as they occur.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB530, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB600, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>