<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id216">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id218"  statutenumber="43-4407"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4407</statuteno><catchline id="id221">Service area
administrator; lead agency; pilot project; annual survey; duties; reports.</catchline><para>(1) Each service area administrator and any lead agency or
the pilot project shall annually survey children, parents, foster parents,
judges, guardians ad litem, attorneys representing parents, and service providers
involved with the child welfare system to monitor satisfaction with (a) adequacy
of communication by the case manager, (b) response by the department, any
lead agency, or the pilot project to requests and problems, (c) transportation
issues, (d) medical and psychological services for children and parents, (e)
visitation schedules, (f) payments, (g) support services to foster parents,
(h) adequacy of information about foster children provided to foster parents,
and (i) the case manager's fulfillment of his or her responsibilities. A summary
of the survey shall be reported electronically to
the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature on September 15,
2012, and each September 15 thereafter.</para>
<para>(2) Each service area administrator and any lead agency or
the pilot project shall provide monthly reports to the child advocacy center
that corresponds with the geographic location of the child regarding the services
provided through the department or a lead agency or the pilot project when
the child is identified as a voluntary or non-court-involved child welfare
case. The monthly report shall include the plan implemented by the department, the lead agency, or the pilot
project for the child and family and the status of compliance by the family
with the plan. The child advocacy center shall report electronically to the Health and Human Services
Committee of the Legislature on September 15, 2012, and every September 15
thereafter, or more frequently if requested by the committee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>