<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id208"><amendatorysection statutenumber="43-4713" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4713</statuteno><catchline>Plan for child; contents; document; copy to child; public posting by child-care institution.</catchline><para>(1) The plan as provided in subsection (2) of section 43-285 for any child in a foster family home or child-care institution who has attained fourteen years of age shall include:</para><para>(a) A document that describes the rights of the child with respect to education, health, visitation, and court participation, the right to be provided with a copy of any consumer report pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 675(5)(I), as such section existed on January 1, 2016, and the right to stay safe and avoid exploitation. The document shall also describe the right of the child to be provided documents relating to his or her education, health, visitation, court participation, and the right to stay safe and avoid exploitation. The document shall also describe additional rights of the child, including, but not limited to, the right to:</para><para>(i) Understand the system or systems in which the child is involved;</para><para>(ii) Have his or her voice heard in his or her case;</para><para>(iii) Maintain family connections;</para><para>(iv) Access personal information;</para><para>(v) Honest and clear communication;</para><para>(vi) Have his or her basic needs met;</para><para>(vii) Learn life skills needed to successfully transition to adulthood; and</para><para>(viii) Live in the most family-like setting that is safe, healthy, and comfortable and meets the child’s needs; and</para><para>(b) A signed acknowledgment by the child that the child has been provided with a copy of the document described in this section and that the rights contained in the document have been explained to the child in an age or developmentally appropriate manner.</para><para>(2) The document shall be provided to the child in a hard copy and offered to the child within seventy-two hours of being placed in a foster family home or child-care institution and at every dispositional, review, and permanency planning hearing.</para><para>(3) The department shall require, as a condition of each contract entered into by a child-care institution to provide foster care, that the child-care institution publicly post the document described in this section in an accessible location.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB746, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>