<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id218" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4328"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4328</statuteno><catchline>Report; director, probation administrator, or executive director; accept, reject, or request modification; when final; written response; corrected report; credentialing issue; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) Within fifteen days after a report is presented to the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director under section 43-4327, he or she shall determine whether to accept, reject, or request in writing modification of the recommendations contained in the report. The written response may include corrections of factual errors. The Inspector General, with input from the Public Counsel, may consider the director's, probation administrator's, or executive director's request for modifications but is not obligated to accept such request. Such report shall become final upon the decision of the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director to accept or reject the recommendations in the report or, if the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director requests modifications, within fifteen days after such request or after the Inspector General incorporates such modifications, whichever occurs earlier.</para><para>(2) After the recommendations have been accepted, rejected, or modified, the report shall be presented to the foster parent, private agency, licensed child care facility, or other provider of child welfare services or juvenile justice services that is the subject of the report and to persons involved in the implementation of the recommendations in the report. Within thirty days after receipt of the report, the foster parent, private agency, licensed child care facility, or other provider may submit a written response to the office to correct any factual errors in the report and shall determine whether to accept, reject, or request in writing modification of the recommendations contained in the report. The Inspector General, with input from the Public Counsel, shall consider all materials submitted under this subsection to determine whether a corrected report shall be issued. If the Inspector General determines that a corrected report is necessary, the corrected report shall be issued within fifteen days after receipt of the written response.</para><para>(3) If the Inspector General does not issue a corrected report pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, or if the corrected report does not address all issues raised in the written response, the foster parent, private agency, licensed child care facility, or other provider may request that its written response, or portions of the response, be appended to the report or corrected report.</para><para>(4) A report which raises issues related to credentialing under the Uniform Credentialing Act shall be submitted to the appropriate credentialing board under the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB207, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>