<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id42" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4212"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4212</statuteno><catchline>Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee;
convened; members; duties; reports; contents; Nebraska Children's Commission;
powers.</catchline><para>(1)
The Department of Health and Human Services shall convene a Foster Care Reimbursement
Rate Committee to develop a standard statewide foster care reimbursement rate
structure for children in foster care in Nebraska. Such structure shall include
a statewide standardized level of care assessment and shall tie performance
with payments to achieve permanency outcomes for children and families.</para>
<para>(2) The committee
shall include (a) the chief executive officer of the department or his or
her designee, (b) representatives from the Division of Children and Family
Services of the department from each service area designated pursuant to section
81-3116, including at least one division employee with a thorough understanding
of the current foster care payment system and at least one division employee
with a thorough understanding of the N-FOCUS electronic data collection system,
(c) representatives from a child welfare agency that contracts directly with
foster parents, from each of such service areas, (d) a representative from
an advocacy organization which deals with legal and policy issues that include
child welfare, (e) a representative from an advocacy organization the singular
focus of which is issues impacting children, (f) a representative from a foster
and adoptive parent association, (g) a representative from a lead agency,
(h) a representative from a child advocacy organization that supports young
adults who were in foster care as children, (i) a foster parent who contracts
directly with the department, and (j) a foster parent who contracts with a
child welfare agency. The members described in subdivisions (b) through (j)
of this subsection shall be appointed by the chief executive officer of the
department. The committee shall meet and organize as soon as possible after
April 12, 2012.</para><para>(3) The committee shall use the study described in subdivision (3)
of section 43-4211 as a beginning standard for setting reimbursement rates.
The committee shall adjust the standard to reflect the reasonable cost of
achieving measurable outcomes for all children in foster care in Nebraska.
The committee shall (a) analyze consumer expenditure data reflecting the costs
of caring for a child in Nebraska, (b) identify and account for additional
costs specific to children in foster care, and (c) apply a geographic cost-of-living
adjustment for Nebraska. The reimbursement rate structure shall comply with
funding requirements related to Title IV-E of the federal Social Security
Act, as amended, and other federal programs as appropriate to maximize the
utilization of federal funds to support foster care.</para><para>(4) The committee shall
develop a statewide standardized level of care assessment containing standardized
criteria to determine a foster child's placement needs and to appropriately
identify the foster care reimbursement rate. The committee shall review other
states' assessment models and foster care reimbursement rate structures in
completing the statewide standardized level of care assessment and the standard
statewide foster care reimbursement rate structure. The statewide standardized
level of care assessment shall be research-based, supported by evidence-based
practices, and reflect the commitment to systems of care and a trauma-informed,
child-centered, family-involved, coordinated process. The committee shall
develop the statewide standardized level of care assessment and the standard
statewide foster care reimbursement rate structure in a manner that provides
incentives to tie performance in achieving the goals of safety, maintaining
family connection, permanency, stability, and well-being to reimbursements
received.</para><para>(5) The committee shall provide written reports to the Health and
Human Services Committee of the Legislature on July 1, 2012, and September
15, 2012, and a final report to the committee and the Governor, with recommendations
for the statewide level of care assessment system and the foster care reimbursement
rate structure, on December 15, 2012.</para><para>(6) If the Nebraska Children's Commission
is created by the One Hundred Second Legislature, Second Session, 2012, the
Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee shall immediately come under the
commission's jurisdiction. The commission may make any changes necessary to
comply with sections 43-4211 to 43-4213.</para><?Pub Caret?></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB820, &#167; 5.</para><operativedate>April 12, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>