<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id147" statutenumber="43-4001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4001</statuteno><catchline id="id150">Children's Behavioral Health Task Force; created; members; expenses; chairperson.</catchline><para>(1) The Children's Behavioral Health Task Force is created. The task force shall consist of the following members:</para><para>(a) The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature or another member of the committee as his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The chairperson of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature or another member of the committee as his or her designee;</para><para>(c) Two providers of community-based behavioral health services to children, appointed by the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature;</para><para>(d) One regional administrator appointed under section 71-808, appointed by the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature;</para><para>(e) Two representatives of organizations advocating on behalf of consumers of children's behavioral health services and their families, appointed by the chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature;</para><para>(f) One juvenile court judge, appointed by the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court; and</para><para>(g) The probation administrator or his or her designee.</para><para>(2) Members of the task force shall serve without compensation but shall be reimbursed from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(3) The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee shall serve as chairperson of the task force. Administrative and staff support for the task force shall be provided by the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB542, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB540, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 35. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>