<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id309"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-4809"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4809</statuteno><catchline>Burden of proof; advisement by court; judgment of emancipation.</catchline><para>(1) The minor has the burden of proving by clear and convincing evidence that the requirements for ordering emancipation under this section have been met. Prior to entering a judgment of emancipation, the court shall advise the minor of the consequences of emancipation, including, but not limited to, the benefits and services available to an emancipated minor and the risks involved with being emancipated. Such advisements shall include, at a minimum, the words to the following effect:</para><para>(a) If you become emancipated, you will have some of the rights that come with adulthood. These rights include: Handling your own affairs; living where you choose; entering into contracts; keeping and spending your money; making decisions regarding your own health care, medical care, dental care, and mental health care, without parental knowledge; enlisting in the military without your parent’s consent; marrying without your parent’s consent; applying for public assistance; suing someone or being sued; enrolling in school or college; and owning real property;</para><para>(b) Even if you are emancipated, you still must: Stay in school as required by Nebraska law; be subject to child labor laws and work permit rules limiting the number of hours you can work; and be of legal age to consume alcohol; and</para><para>(c) When you become emancipated: You lose your right to have financial support for basic living expenses for food, clothing, and shelter, and health care paid for by your parents or guardian; your parents or guardian will no longer be legally or financially responsible if you injure someone; and being emancipated does not automatically make you eligible for public assistance or benefits.</para><para>(2) If, after hearing, the court determines that emancipation is in the best interests of the minor and that the minor understands his or her rights and responsibilities under sections 43-4801 to 43-4812 as an emancipated minor, the court shall enter a judgment of emancipation. In making its determination regarding the petition for emancipation, the court shall determine whether the petitioner has proven each of the facts set forth in subdivision (9) of section 43-4803.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB714, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>