<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id218" statutenumber="43-4407"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4407</statuteno><catchline id="id221">Service area administrator; annual survey; duties; reports.</catchline><para>(1) Each service area administrator shall annually survey children, parents, foster parents, judges, guardians ad litem, attorneys representing parents, and service providers involved with the child welfare system to monitor satisfaction with (a) adequacy of communication by the case manager, (b) response by the department to requests and problems, (c) transportation issues, (d) medical and psychological services for children and parents, (e) visitation schedules, (f) payments, (g) support services to foster parents, (h) adequacy of information about foster children provided to foster parents, and (i) the case manager's fulfillment of his or her responsibilities. A summary of the survey shall be reported electronically to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature on September 15, 2012, and each September 15 thereafter.</para><para>(2) Each service area administrator shall provide monthly reports to the child advocacy center that corresponds with the geographic location of the child regarding the services provided through the department when the child is identified as a voluntary or non-court-involved child welfare case. The monthly report shall include the plan implemented by the department for the child and family and the status of compliance by the family with the plan. The child advocacy center shall report electronically to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature on September 15, 2012, and every September 15 thereafter, or more frequently if requested by the committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB222, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1173, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>