<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id156">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id158" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4508"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4508</statuteno><catchline id="id161">Department;
filing with juvenile court; contents; jurisdiction of court; bridge to independence program file; hearing
for permanency review; appointment of hearing officer; department; duties; court review services and support.</catchline>
<para>(1) Within forty-five days after the voluntary services and
support agreement is signed, the department shall file a petition with the juvenile court describing
the young adult's current situation, including the young adult's name, date
of birth, and current address and the reasons why it is in the young adult's
best interests to participate
in the bridge to independence program. The department shall also
provide the juvenile court with a copy of the signed voluntary services and
support agreement, a copy of the case plan, and any other information the
department or the young adult wants the court to consider.</para>
<para>(2) To ensure continuity of care and eligibility, the voluntary
services and support agreement should be signed prior to and filed with the
court at the last court hearing before the young adult is discharged from
foster care for all young adults who choose to participate in the bridge to independence program
at that time.</para>
<para>(3) The court has the jurisdiction to review the voluntary
services and support agreement signed by the department and the young adult
under section 43-4506 and to
conduct permanency reviews as described in this section. Upon
the filing of a petition
under subsection (1) of this section, the court shall open a bridge to independence program file
for the young adult for the purpose of determining whether continuing in such program is in the young
adult's best interests and for the purpose of conducting permanency reviews.</para>
<para>(4) The court shall make the best interests determination
as described in subsection (3) of this section not later than one hundred
eighty days after the young adult and the department enter into the voluntary
services and support agreement.</para>
<para>(5) The court shall conduct a hearing for permanency review
consistent with 42 U.S.C. 675(5)(C) as described in subsection (6) of this
section regarding the voluntary services and support agreement at least once
per year and may conduct such
hearing at additional times,
but not more times than is reasonably practicable, at the request
of the young adult, the department, or any other party to the proceeding.
The juvenile court may request the appointment of a hearing officer pursuant
to section 24-230 to conduct permanency review hearings. The department is
not required to have legal counsel present at such hearings. The juvenile court shall conduct the permanency reviews
in an expedited manner and shall issue findings and orders, if any, as speedily
as possible.</para>
<para>(6)(a) The primary purpose
of the permanency review is to ensure that the bridge to independence program is providing the young
adult with the needed services and
support to help the young adult move toward permanency and self-sufficiency.
This shall include that, in
all permanency reviews or hearings regarding the transition of the young adult
from foster care to independent living, the court shall consult, in an age-appropriate
manner, with the young adult regarding the proposed permanency or transition
plan for the young adult. The
young adult shall have a clear self-advocacy role in the permanency review
in accordance with section 43-4510, and the hearing shall support the active
engagement of the young adult in key decisions. Permanency reviews shall be
conducted on the record and in
an informal manner and, whenever possible, outside of the courtroom.</para>
<para>(b) The department
shall prepare and present to the juvenile court a report, at the direction
of the young adult, addressing progress made in meeting the goals in the case
plan, including the independent living transition proposal, and shall propose
modifications as necessary to further those goals.</para><para>(c) The court shall determine
whether the bridge to independence program is providing the appropriate services
and support as provided in the voluntary services and support agreement to
carry out the case plan. The court has the authority to determine whether
the young adult is receiving the services and support he or she is entitled
to receive under the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act and the department's
policies or state or federal law to help the young adult move toward permanency
and self-sufficiency. If the court believes that the young adult requires
additional services and support to achieve the goals documented in the case
plan or under the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act and the department's
policies or state or federal law, the court may make appropriate findings
or order the department to take action to ensure that the young adult receives
the identified services and support.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 37.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>