<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id5"  statutenumber="43-4214"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4214</statuteno><catchline>Foster care reimbursement; foster
care system; legislative findings and intent.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature (a) finds that
it was the intent of sections 43-4208 to 43-4213 to provide bridge funding
to bring Nebraska's foster care reimbursement rates in line with foster care
reimbursement rates in the rest of the country and (b) recognizes the importance
of a stable payment to foster parents to ensure that families are able to
budget for needs while caring for foster children.</para>
<para>(2) The Legislature further
finds that Nebraska's foster care system has begun to stabilize. In recognition
of the essential contributions of foster parents and foster care providers
to foster children in Nebraska, it is the intent of the Legislature to continue
existing contractual arrangements for payment to ensure the continued stabilization
of the foster care system in Nebraska.</para><para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature:</para>
<para>(a) To ensure
that fair rates continue into the future to stem attrition of foster parents
and to recruit, support, and maintain high-quality foster parents;</para>
<para>(b) That foster
care reimbursement rates accurately reflect the cost of raising the child
in the care of the state;</para><para>(c) To ensure that contracted foster care service provider agencies
do not pay increased rates out of budgets determined in contracts with the
Department of Health and Human Services prior to any change in rates;</para>
<para>(d)
To maintain comparable foster care reimbursement rates to ensure retention
and recruitment of high-quality foster parents and to ensure that foster children's
best interests are served; and</para><para>(e) To appropriate funds to permanently
replace the bridge funding described in subsection (1) of this section and
provide the necessary additional funds to bring foster care reimbursement
rates in compliance with the recommendations of the research and study completed
by the Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee as required pursuant to section
43-4212 as such section existed before June 5, 2013.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB530, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>