<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id34">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id36" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4505"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4505</statuteno><catchline>Extended services and support; services
enumerated.</catchline><para>Extended
services and support provided under the extended services program include,
but are not limited to:</para>
<para>(1) Medical
care under the medical assistance program;</para><para>(2) Housing, placement, and support in the
form of continued foster care maintenance payments which shall remain at least
at the rate set immediately prior to the young adult's exit from foster care.
As decided by and with the young adult, young adults may reside in a foster
family home, a supervised independent living setting, an institution, or a
foster care facility. Placement in an institution or a foster care facility
should occur only if necessary due to a young adult's developmental level
or medical condition. A young adult who is residing in a foster care facility
upon leaving foster care may choose to temporarily stay until he or she is
able to transition to a more age-appropriate setting. For young adults residing
in a supervised independent living setting:</para><para>(a) The department may send all or part
of the foster care maintenance payments directly to the young adult. This
should be decided on a case-by-case basis by and with the young adult in a
manner that respects the independence of the young adult; and</para>
<para>(b) Rules and
restrictions regarding housing options should be respectful of the young adult's
autonomy and developmental maturity. Specifically, safety assessments of the
living arrangements shall be age-appropriate and consistent with federal guidance
on a supervised setting in which the individual lives independently. A clean
background check shall not be required for an individual residing in the same
residence as the young adult; and</para><para>(3) Case management services that are young-adult
driven. Case management shall be a continuation of the independent living
transition proposal in section 43-1311.03, including a written description
of additional resources that will help the young adult in creating permanent
relationships and preparing for the transition to adulthood and independent
living. Case management shall include the development of a case plan, developed
jointly by the department and the young adult, that includes a description
of the identified housing situation or living arrangement and the resources
to assist the young adult in the transition from the extended services program
to adulthood. The case plan shall incorporate the independent living transition
proposal in section 43-1311.03. Case management shall also include, but not
be limited to, documentation that assistance has been offered and provided
that would help the young adult meet his or her individual goals, if such
assistance is appropriate and if the young adult is eligible and consents
to receive such assistance. This shall include, but not be limited to, assisting
the young adult to:</para><para>(a) Obtain employment or other financial support;</para>
<para>(b) Obtain
a government-issued identification card;</para><para>(c) Open and maintain a bank account;</para>
<para>(d) Obtain
appropriate community resources, including health, mental health, developmental
disability, and other disability services and support;</para>
<para>(e) When appropriate,
satisfy any juvenile justice system requirements and assist with sealing the
young adult's juvenile court record if the young adult is eligible under section
43-2,108.01;</para><para>(f) Complete secondary education;</para><para>(g) Apply for admission and aid for postsecondary
education or vocational courses;</para><para>(h) Obtain the necessary state court findings
and then apply for special immigrant juvenile status as defined in 8 U.S.C.
1101(a)(27)(J) or apply for other immigration relief that the young adult
may be eligible for;</para><para>(i) Create a health care power of attorney as required by the federal
Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act, Public Law 111-148;</para>
<para>(j) Obtain
a copy of health and education records of the young adult;</para>
<para>(k) Apply for
any public benefits or benefits that he or she may be eligible for or may
be due through his or her parents or relatives, including, but not limited
to, aid to dependent children, supplemental security income, social security
disability insurance, social security survivors benefits, the Special Supplemental
Nutrition Program for Women, Infants, and Children, the Supplemental Nutrition
Assistance Program, and low-income home energy assistance programs;</para>
<para>(l) Maintain
relationships with individuals who are important to the young adult, including
searching for individuals with whom the young adult has lost contact;</para>
<para>(m) Access
information about maternal and paternal relatives, including any siblings;</para>
<para>(n) Access
young adult empowerment opportunities, such as Project Everlast and peer support
groups; and</para><para>(o) Access pregnancy and parenting resources and services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>