<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4208"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4208</statuteno><catchline>Title IV-E Demonstration Project
Committee; created; members; duties; powers; implementation plan; contents;
report; Nebraska Children's Commission; powers.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Title IV-E Demonstration Project
Committee is created. The members of the committee shall be appointed by the
Director of Children and Family Services or his or her designee and shall
include representatives of the Department of Health and Human Services and
representatives of child welfare stakeholder entities, including one advocacy
organization which deals with legal and policy issues that include child welfare,
one advocacy organization the singular focus of which is issues impacting
children, two child welfare service agencies that provide a wide range of
child welfare services, and one entity which is a lead agency as of March
1, 2012. Members of the committee shall have experience or knowledge in the
area of child welfare that involves Title IV-E eligibility criteria and activities.
In addition, there shall be at least one ex officio member of the committee,
appointed by the State Court Administrator. The ex officio member or members
shall not be involved in decisionmaking, implementation plans, or reporting
but may attend committee meetings, provide information to the committee about
the processes and programs of the court system involving children and juveniles,
and inform the State Court Administrator of the committee's activities. The
committee shall be convened by the director within thirty days after April
12, 2012.</para>
<para>(b) The committee
shall review, report, and provide recommendations regarding the application
of the Department of Health and Human Services for a demonstration project
pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 1320a-9 to obtain a waiver as provided in 42 U.S.C.
1320a-9(b), as such section existed on January 1, 2012. The committee may
engage a consultant with expertise in Title IV-E demonstration project applications
and requirements.</para><para>(c) The committee shall (i) review Nebraska's current status of Title
IV-E participation and penetration rates, (ii) review strategies and solutions
for raising Nebraska's participation rate and reimbursement for Title IV-E
in child placement, case management, replacement, training, adoption, court
findings, and proceedings, and (iii) recommend specific actions for addressing
barriers to participation and reimbursement.</para><para>(d) The committee shall
provide an implementation plan and a timeline for making application for a
Title IV-E waiver. The implementation plan shall support and align with the
goals of the statewide strategic plan required pursuant to Legislative Bill
821, One Hundred Second Legislature, Second Session, 2012, including, but
not limited to, maximizing federal funding to be able to utilize state and
federal funding for a broad array of services for children, including prevention,
intervention, and community-based, in-home, and out-of-home services to attain
positive outcomes for the safety and well-being of and to expedite permanency
for children. The committee shall report on its activities to the Health and
Human Services Committee of the Legislature on or before July 1, 2012, September
1, 2012, and November 1, 2012, and shall provide a final written report to
the department, the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature,
and the Governor by December 15, 2012.</para><para>(e) If the Nebraska Children's Commission
is created by the One Hundred Second Legislature, Second Session, 2012, the
Title IV-E Demonstration Project Committee shall thereupon come under the
commission's jurisdiction. The commission may make changes it deems necessary
to comply with this subsection to facilitate the application for such demonstration
project.</para><para>(2) The committee's implementation plan shall address the demonstration
project designed to meet the requirements of 42 U.S.C. 1320a-9, including,
but not limited to, the following:</para><para>(a) Increasing permanency for children by
reducing the time in foster care placements when possible and promoting a
successful transition to adulthood for older youth;</para><para>(b) Increasing positive outcomes
for children and families in their homes and communities, including tribal
communities, and improving the safety and well-being of children;</para>
<para>(c) Preventing
child abuse and neglect and the reentry of children into foster care; and</para>
<para>(d) Considering
the options of developing a program to (i) permit foster care maintenance
payments to be made under Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act, as
such act existed on January 1, 2012, to a long-term therapeutic family treatment
center on behalf of children residing in such a center or (ii) identify and
address domestic violence that endangers children and results in the placement
of children in foster care.</para><para>(3) The implementation plan for the demonstration project shall
include information showing:</para><para>(a) The ability and capacity of the department to effectively use
the authority to conduct a demonstration project under this section by identifying
changes the department has made or plans to make in policies, procedures,
or other elements of the state's child welfare program that will enable the
state to successfully achieve the goal or goals of the project; and</para>
<para>(b) That the department
has implemented, or plans to implement within three years after the date of
submission of its application under this section or within two years after
the date on which the United States Secretary of Health and Human Services
approves such application, whichever is later, at least two of the child welfare
program improvement policies described in 42 U.S.C. 1320a-9(a)(7), as such
section existed on January 1, 2012.</para><para>(4) At least one of the child welfare program
improvement policies to be implemented by the Department of Health and Human
Services under the demonstration project shall be a policy that the state
has not previously implemented as of the date of submission of its application
under this section.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, long-term therapeutic family treatment
center has the definition found in 42 U.S.C. 1320a-9(a)(8), as such section
existed on January 1, 2012.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB820, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>