<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id48">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id50" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4101"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4101</statuteno><catchline id="id53">Nebraska Juvenile
Service Delivery Project; established; purpose; evaluation; reimbursement for costs; Department of Health and Human
Services; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Juvenile Service Delivery Project
shall be established as a pilot program administered by the Office of Probation
Administration. The pilot program shall be evaluated by the University of
Nebraska Medical Center's College of Public Health. The project may be expanded
by the Office of Probation Administration. The purpose of the pilot program
is to (a) provide access to services
in the community for juveniles placed on probation, (b) prevent
unnecessary commitment of juveniles to the Department of Health and Human
Services and to the Office of Juvenile Services, (c) eliminate
barriers preventing juveniles from receiving needed services, (d) prevent
unnecessary penetration of juveniles further into the juvenile justice system, (e) enable the juvenile's needs to be met in
the least intrusive and least restrictive manner while maintaining the safety
of the juvenile and the community, (f) reduce the duplication
of resources within the juvenile justice system through intense coordinated
case management and supervision, and (g) use evidence-based practices
and responsive case management to improve outcomes for adjudicated juveniles.</para>
<para>(2) On or before
July 1, 2013, the Department of Health and Human Services shall apply for
reimbursement under Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act, as amended,
for reimbursable costs associated with the Nebraska Juvenile Service Delivery
Project. The reimbursed funds received by the department shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Probation Program Cash Fund for reimbursement
of expenses incurred by the Office of Probation Administration pursuant to
the Nebraska Juvenile Service Delivery Project.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB985, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB269, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>