<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id30">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id32"  statutenumber="43-4211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4211</statuteno><catchline>Foster care payments; legislative
findings.</catchline><para>The
Legislature finds that:</para>
<para>(1) Surveys of
foster parents demonstrate that the safety net provided by foster families
is fragile and damaged;</para><para>(2) Increased focus on recruiting and retaining high quality, trained,
and experienced foster parents should be a priority under reform of the child
welfare system in Nebraska;</para><para>(3) A 2007 study entitled Foster Care Minimum Adequate Rates for
Children completed by Children's Rights, the National Foster Parent Association,
and the University of Maryland School of Social Work analyzed foster care
maintenance payments under Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act,
as amended, which are defined as the cost of providing food, clothing, shelter,
daily supervision, school supplies, personal incidentals, insurance, and travel
for visitation with the biological family;</para><para>(4) The study set a basic foster care payment
rate, calculated by (a) analyzing consumer expenditure data reflecting the
costs of caring for a child, (b) identifying and accounting for additional
costs specific to children in foster care, and (c) applying a geographic cost-of-living
adjustment in order to develop rates for each of the fifty states and the
District of Columbia. The rate includes adequate funds to meet a foster child's
basic physical needs and the cost of activities such as athletic and artistic
programs which are important for children who have been traumatized or isolated
by abuse, neglect, and placement in foster care;</para><para>(5) The study found
that Nebraska's foster care payment rates were the lowest in the country,
with an average payment of two hundred twenty-six dollars per month for a
child two years of age. The next lowest foster care payment rate was Missouri,
paying two hundred seventy-one dollars per month; and</para><para>(6) Foster care
placements with relatives are more stable and more likely to result in legal
guardianship with a relative of the child. Children in relative placements
are less likely to reenter the child welfare system after reunification with
their parents and report that they feel more loved and less stigmatized when
living with family.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB820, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>