<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id190">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id192" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4513"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4513</statuteno><catchline id="id195">Bridge to Independence Advisory
Committee; members; terms; duties; meetings; report; contents.</catchline>
<para>(1) On or before July 1, 2013, the Nebraska Children's Commission
shall appoint a Bridge
to Independence Advisory Committee to make recommendations to
the department and the Nebraska Children's Commission for a statewide implementation
plan meeting the bridge to independence program
requirements of the Young Adult Bridge
to Independence Act. The committee shall provide a written report
regarding the initial implementation of the program to the Nebraska Children's
Commission, the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature, the
department, and the Governor by October 1, 2013. The report shall also specifically
address recommendations for maximizing and making efficient use of funding
for a state-extended guardianship assistance program described in section
43-4514. The report to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature
shall be submitted electronically. The Bridge to Independence Advisory Committee shall
meet on a biannual basis thereafter to advise the department and the Nebraska
Children's Commission regarding ongoing implementation of the bridge to independence program and shall provide
a written report regarding ongoing implementation, including bridge to independence program participation
and early discharge rates and reasons obtained from the department, to the
Nebraska Children's Commission, the Health and Human Services Committee of
the Legislature, the department, and the Governor by December 15th of each
year. By December 15, 2015, the committee shall develop specific recommendations
for expanding to or improving outcomes for similar groups of at-risk young
adults and for the adaptation or continuation of assistance under the state-extended
guardianship assistance program described in section 43-4514. The report to
the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature shall be submitted
electronically.</para>
<para>(2) The members of the Bridge to Independence Advisory Committee shall
include, but not be limited to, (a) representatives from all three branches
of government, and the representatives from the legislative and judicial branches
of government shall be nonvoting, ex officio members, (b) no less than three
young adults currently or previously in foster care, which may be filled on
a rotating basis by members of Project Everlast or a similar youth support
or advocacy group, (c) one or more representatives from a child welfare advocacy
organization, (d) one or more representatives from a child welfare service
agency, and (e) one or more representatives from an agency providing independent
living services.</para>
<para>(3) Members of the committee shall be appointed for terms
of two years. The Nebraska Children's Commission shall appoint the chairperson
of the committee and may fill vacancies on the committee as they occur.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 43.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>