<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id154" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4320"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4320</statuteno><catchline>Complaints to office; form; full investigation; when; notice.</catchline><para>(1) Complaints to the office may be made in writing. The office shall also maintain a toll-free telephone line for complaints. A complaint shall be evaluated to determine if it alleges possible misconduct, misfeasance, malfeasance, or violation of a statute or of rules and regulations pursuant to section 43-4318. All complaints shall be evaluated to determine whether a full investigation is warranted.</para><para>(2) The office shall not conduct a full investigation of a complaint unless:</para><para>(a) The complaint alleges misconduct, misfeasance, malfeasance, or violation of a statute or of rules and regulations pursuant to section 43-4318;</para><para>(b) The complaint is against a person within the jurisdiction of the office; and</para><para>(c) The allegations can be independently verified through investigation.</para><para>(3) The Inspector General shall determine within fourteen days after receipt of a complaint whether it will conduct a full investigation. A complaint alleging facts which, if verified, would provide a basis for discipline under the Uniform Credentialing Act shall be referred to the appropriate credentialing board under the act.</para><para>(4) When a full investigation is opened on a private agency that contracts with the Office of Probation Administration, the Inspector General shall give notice of such investigation to the Office of Probation Administration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 15. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>