<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-4218"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4218</statuteno><catchline>Normalcy Task Force; Nebraska Strengthening Families Act Committee; created; duties; members; term; vacancy; report; contents.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Normalcy Task Force is created. On July 1, 2017, the Normalcy Task Force shall become the Nebraska Strengthening Families Act Committee.</para><para>(b)(i) Beginning July 1, 2016, until July 1, 2017, the Normalcy Task Force shall monitor and make recommendations regarding the implementation in Nebraska of the federal Preventing Sex Trafficking and Strengthening Families Act, Public Law 113-183, as such act existed on January 1, 2016.</para><para> (ii) On and after July 1, 2017, the Nebraska Strengthening Families Act Committee shall monitor and make recommendations regarding the implementation in Nebraska of the federal Preventing Sex Trafficking and Strengthening Families Act, Public Law 113-183, as such act existed on January 1, 2017, and the Nebraska Strengthening Families Act.</para><para>(2) Until July 1, 2017, the members of the task force, and on and after July 1, 2017, the members of the committee shall include, but not be limited to, (a) representatives from the legislative, executive, and judicial branches of government. The representatives from the legislative and judicial branches shall be nonvoting, ex officio members, (b) no fewer than three young adults currently or previously in foster care which may be filled on a rotating basis by members of Project Everlast or a similar youth support or advocacy group, (c) a representative from the juvenile probation system, (d) the executive director of the Foster Care Review Office, (e) one or more representatives from a child welfare advocacy organization, (f) one or more representatives from a child welfare service agency, (g) one or more representatives from an agency providing independent living services, (h) one or more representatives of a child-care institution as defined in section 43-4703, (i) one or more current or former foster parents, (j) one or more parents who have experience in the foster care system, (k) one or more professionals who have relevant practical experience such as a caseworker, and (l) one or more guardians ad litem who practice in juvenile court.</para><para>(3) On or before July 1, 2016, the Nebraska Children’s Commission shall appoint the members of the task force. On July 1, 2017, the members of the task force shall become members of the committee, shall serve the amount of time remaining on their initial terms of office, and are eligible for reappointment by the Nebraska Children’s Commission. Members shall be appointed for terms of two years. The commission shall appoint a chairperson or chairpersons of the committee and may fill vacancies on the committee as such vacancies occur.</para><para>(4) The committee shall provide a written report with recommendations regarding the initial and ongoing implementation of the federal Preventing Sex Trafficking and Strengthening Families Act, as such act existed on January 1, 2017, and the Nebraska Strengthening Families Act and related efforts to improve normalcy for children in foster care and related populations to the Nebraska Children's Commission, the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature, the Department of Health and Human Services, and the Governor by December 15 of each year. The report to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB746, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB225, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>April 28, 2017</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Strengthening Families Act,</emphasis> see section 43-4701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>