<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id70" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4302">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4302</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent.</catchline><para>(1)
It is the intent of the Legislature to:</para>
<para>(a) Establish a full-time program of investigation and performance review
to provide increased accountability and oversight of the Nebraska child welfare
system;</para>
<para>(b) Assist in improving operations of the department and the Nebraska
child welfare system;</para>
<para>(c) Provide an independent form of inquiry for concerns regarding the
actions of individuals and agencies responsible for the care and protection
of children in the Nebraska child welfare system. Confusion of the roles,
responsibilities, and accountability structures between individuals, private
contractors, and agencies in the current system make it difficult to monitor
and oversee the Nebraska child welfare system; and</para>
<para>(d) Provide a process for investigation and review to determine if individual
complaints and issues of investigation and inquiry reveal a problem in the
child welfare system, not just individual cases, that necessitates legislative
action for improved policies and restructuring of the child welfare system.</para>
<para>(2) It is not the intent of the Legislature in enacting the Office of
Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare Act to interfere with the duties
of the Legislative Auditor or the
Legislative Fiscal Analyst or to interfere with the statutorily defined investigative
responsibilities or prerogatives of any officer, agency, board, bureau, commission,
association, society, or institution of the executive branch of state government,
except that the act does not preclude an inquiry on the sole basis that another
agency has the same responsibility. The act shall not be construed to interfere
with or supplant the responsibilities or prerogatives of the Governor to investigate,
monitor, and report on the activities of the agencies, boards, bureaus, commissions,
associations, societies, and institutions of the executive branch under his
or her administrative direction.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB39, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>