<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id400"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="43-4605"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4605</statuteno><catchline>Notification required of deploying parent.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (d) of this section and subject to subsection (c) of this section, a deploying parent shall notify in a record the other parent of a pending deployment not later than seven days after receiving notice of deployment unless reasonably prevented from doing so by the circumstances of service. If the circumstances of service prevent giving notification within the seven days, the deploying parent shall give the notification as soon as reasonably possible.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (d) of this section and subject to subsection (c) of this section, each parent shall provide in a record the other parent with a plan for fulfilling that parent's share of custodial responsibility during deployment. Each parent shall provide the plan as soon as reasonably possible after notification of deployment is given under subsection (a) of this section.</para><para>(c) If a court order currently in effect prohibits disclosure of the address or contact information of the other parent, notification of deployment under subsection (a) of this section, or notification of a plan for custodial responsibility during deployment under subsection (b) of this section, may be made only to the issuing court. If the address of the other parent is available to the issuing court, the court shall forward the notification to the other parent. The court shall keep confidential the address or contact information of the other parent.</para><para>(d) Notification in a record under subsection (a) or (b) of this section is not required if the parents are living in the same residence and both parents have actual notice of the deployment or plan.</para><para>(e) In a proceeding regarding custodial responsibility, a court may consider the reasonableness of a parent's efforts to comply with this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB219, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>