<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id6" statutenumber="43-4511"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4511</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Extended guardianship assistance and medical care; eligibility; use.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall provide extended guardianship assistance and medical care under the medical assistance program for a young adult who has attained the age of eligibility but is less than twenty-one years of age and with respect to whom a kinship guardianship assistance agreement was in effect pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 673 if the young adult had attained sixteen years of age before the agreement became effective or with respect to whom a state-funded guardianship assistance agreement was in effect if the young adult had attained sixteen years of age before the agreement became effective and if the young adult meets at least one of the following conditions for eligibility:</para><para>(a) The young adult is completing secondary education or an educational program leading to an equivalent credential;</para><para>(b) The young adult is enrolled in an institution that provides postsecondary or vocational education;</para><para>(c) The young adult is employed for at least eighty hours per month;</para><para>(d) The young adult is participating in a program or activity designed to promote employment or remove barriers to employment; or</para><para>(e) The young adult is incapable of doing any part of the activities in subdivisions (1)(a) through (d) of this section due to a medical condition, which incapacity must be supported by regularly updated information in the case plan of the young adult.</para><para>(2) The guardian shall ensure that any guardianship assistance funds provided by the department and received by the guardian shall be used for the benefit of the young adult. The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations defining services and supports encompassed by such benefit.</para><para>(3) The changes made to this section by Laws 2015, LB243, become operative on July 1, 2015.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB243, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB848, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>