<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id13">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id15" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4215"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4215</statuteno><catchline>Reimbursement rate recommendations;
Division of Children and Family Services of Department of Health and Human
Services; implementation; pilot project; reports; contents.</catchline><para>(1) On or
before July 1, 2014, the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department
of Health and Human Services shall implement the reimbursement rate recommendations
of the Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee as reported to the Legislature
pursuant to section 43-4212 as such section existed before June 5, 2013.</para>
<para>(2)(a) On or
before July 1, 2013, the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department
of Health and Human Services shall develop a pilot project as provided in
this subsection to implement the standardized level of care assessment tools
recommended by the Foster Care Reimbursement Rate Committee as reported to
the Legislature pursuant to section 43-4212 as such section existed before
June 5, 2013.</para><para>(b)(i) The pilot project shall comprise two groups: One in an urban
area and one in a rural area. The size of each group shall be determined by
the division to ensure an accurate estimate of the effectiveness and cost
of implementing such tools statewide.</para><para>(ii) The Nebraska Children's Commission
shall review and provide a progress report on the pilot project by October
1, 2013, to the department and electronically to the Health and Human Services
Committee of the Legislature; shall provide to the department and electronically
to the committee by December 1, 2013, a report including recommendations and
any legislation necessary, including appropriations, to adopt the recommendations,
regarding the adaptation or continuation of the implementation of a statewide
standardized level of care assessment; and shall provide to the department
and electronically to the committee by February 1, 2014, a final report and
final recommendations of the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB530, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>