<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id951"><amendatorysection statutenumber="43-4703" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4703</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Strengthening Families Act:</para><para>(1) Age or developmentally appropriate means activities or items that are generally accepted as suitable for a child of the same chronological age or level of maturity or that are determined to be developmentally appropriate for a child, based on the development of cognitive, emotional, physical, and behavioral capacities that are typical for an age or age group and, in the case of a specific child, activities or items that are suitable for the child based on the developmental stages attained by the child with respect to the cognitive, emotional, physical, and behavioral capacities of the child;</para><para>(2) Caregiver means a foster parent with whom a child in foster care has been placed or a designated official for a child-care institution in which a child in foster care has been placed;</para><para>(3) Child-care institution has the definition found in 42 U.S.C. 672(c), as such section existed on January 1, 2016, and also includes the definition of residential child-caring agency as found in section 71-1926;</para><para>(4) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(5) Foster family home has the definition found in 42 U.S.C. 672(c), as such section existed on January 1, 2016, and also includes the definition as found in section 71-1901; and</para><para>(6) Reasonable and prudent parent standard means the standard characterized by careful and sensible parental decisions that maintain the health, safety, and best interest of a child while at the same time encouraging the emotional and developmental growth of the child that a caregiver shall use when determining whether to allow a child in foster care under the responsibility of the state to participate in extracurricular, enrichment, cultural, and social activities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB746, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>