<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id35" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4204</statuteno><catchline>Statewide strategic plan; created;
considerations; lead agency; duties; commission; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Children's
Commission shall create a statewide strategic plan to carry out the legislative
intent stated in section 43-4201 for child welfare program and service reform
in Nebraska. In developing the statewide strategic plan, the commission shall
consider, but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The potential
of contracting with private nonprofit entities as a lead agency, subject to
the requirements of subsection (2) of this section. Such lead-agency utilization
shall be in a manner that maximizes the strengths, experience, skills, and
continuum of care of the lead agencies. Any lead-agency contracts entered
into or amended after April 12, 2012, shall detail how qualified licensed
agencies as part of efforts to develop the local capacity for a community-based
system of coordinated care will implement community-based care through competitively
procuring either (i) the specific components of foster care and related services
or (ii) comprehensive services for defined eligible populations of children
and families;</para><para>(b) Provision of leadership for strategies to support high-quality
evidence-based prevention and early intervention services that reduce risk
and enhance protection for children;</para><para>(c) Realignment of service areas designated
pursuant to section 81-3116 to be coterminous with the judicial districts
described in section 24-301.02;</para><para>(d) Identification of the type of information
needed for a clear and thorough analysis of progress on child welfare indicators;
and</para><para>(e)
Such other elements as the commission deems necessary and appropriate.</para>
<para>(2) A lead agency used
after April 12, 2012, shall:</para><para>(a) Have a board of directors of which at least fifty-one
percent of the membership is comprised of Nebraska residents who are not employed
by the lead agency or by a subcontractor of the lead agency;</para>
<para>(b) Complete a readiness
assessment as developed by the Department of Health and Human Services to
determine the lead agency's viability. The readiness assessment shall evaluate
organizational, operational, and programmatic capabilities and performance,
including review of: The strength of the board of directors; compliance and
oversight; financial risk management; financial liquidity and performance;
infrastructure maintenance; funding sources, including state, federal, and
external private funding; and operations, including reporting, staffing, evaluation,
training, supervision, contract monitoring, and program performance tracking
capabilities;</para><para>(c)
Have the ability to provide directly or by contract through a local network
of providers the services required of a lead agency. A lead agency shall not
directly provide more than thirty-five percent of direct services required
under the contract; and</para><para>(d)
Provide accountability for meeting the outcomes and performance standards
related to child welfare services established by Nebraska child welfare policy
and the federal government.</para><para>(3) The commission shall review the operations
of the department regarding child welfare programs and services and recommend,
as a part of the statewide strategic plan, options for attaining the legislative
intent stated in section 43-4201, either by the establishment of a new division
within the department or the establishment of a new state agency to provide
all child welfare programs and services which are the responsibility of the
state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>