<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id6"  statutenumber="43-4201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4201</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings, declarations,
and intent.</catchline><para>(1)
The Legislature finds and declares that:</para>
<para>(a) The Health
and Human Services Committee of the Legislature documented serious problems
with the child welfare system in its 2011 report of the study that was conducted
under Legislative Resolution 37, One Hundred Second Legislature, First Session,
2011;</para><para>(b) Improving the safety and well-being of Nebraska's children and
families is a critical priority which must guide policy decisions in a variety
of areas;</para><para>(c) To improve the safety and well-being of children and families
in Nebraska, the legislative, judicial, and executive branches of government
must work together to ensure:</para><para>(i) The integration, coordination, and accessibility
of all services provided by the state, whether directly or pursuant to contract;</para>
<para>(ii) Reasonable access
to appropriate services statewide and efficiency in service delivery; and</para>
<para>(iii) The availability
of accurate and complete data as well as ongoing data analysis to identify
important trends and problems as they arise; and</para><para>(d) As the primary state
agency serving children and families, the Department of Health and Human Services
must exemplify leadership, responsiveness, transparency, and efficiency and
program managers within the agency must strive cooperatively to ensure that
their programs view the needs of children and families comprehensively as
a system rather than individually in isolation, including pooling funding
when possible and appropriate.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature
in creating the Nebraska Children's Commission to provide for the needs identified
in subsection (1) of this section, to provide a broad restructuring of the
goals of the child welfare system, and to provide a structure to the commission
that maintains the framework of the three branches of government and their
respective powers and duties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>