<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" statutenumber="43-4511.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4511.01</statuteno><catchline>Participation in extended guardianship or bridge to independence program; participation in extended adoption assistance or bridge to independence program; choice of participant; notice; contents; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Young adults who are eligible to participate under both extended guardianship assistance as provided in section 43-4511 and the bridge to independence program as provided in subdivision (2)(b) of section 43-4504 may choose to participate in either program.</para><para>(b) Young adults who are eligible to participate under both extended adoption assistance as provided in section 43-4512 and the bridge to independence program as provided in subdivision (2)(b) of section 43-4504 may choose to participate in either program.</para><para>(2) The department shall create a clear and developmentally appropriate written notice discussing the rights of young adults who are eligible under both extended guardianship assistance and the bridge to independence program and a notice for young adults who are eligible under both extended adoption assistance and the bridge to independence program. The notice shall explain the benefits and responsibilities and the process to apply. The department shall provide the written notice and make efforts to provide a verbal explanation to a young adult with respect to whom a kinship guardianship assistance agreement or an adoption assistance agreement was in effect pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 673 if the young adult had attained sixteen years of age before the agreement became effective or with respect to whom a state-funded guardianship assistance agreement or state-funded adoption assistance agreement was in effect if the young adult had attained sixteen years of age before the agreement became effective. The department shall provide the notice yearly thereafter until such young adult reaches nineteen years of age and not later than ninety days prior to the young adult attaining nineteen years of age.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB243, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB600, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>