<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id184" statutenumber="43-4510"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4510</statuteno><catchline id="id187">Court-appointed attorney; continuation of guardian ad litem or defense counsel; independence coordinator; duties; notice; court appointed special advocate volunteer.</catchline><para>(1) If desired by the young adult, the young adult shall be provided a court-appointed attorney who has received training appropriate to the role. The attorney's representation of the young adult shall be client-directed. The attorney shall protect the young adult's legal rights and vigorously advocate for the young adult's wishes and goals, including assisting the young adult as necessary to ensure that the bridge to independence program is providing the young adult with the services and support required under the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act. For young adults who were appointed a guardian ad litem or defense counsel before the young adult attained the age of eligibility, the guardian ad litem's or defense counsel's appointment may be continued, with consent from the young adult, but under a client-directed model of representation. Before entering into a voluntary services and support agreement and at least sixty days prior to each permanency and case review, the independence coordinator shall notify the young adult of his or her right to request a client-directed attorney if the young adult would like an attorney to be appointed and shall provide the young adult with a clear and developmentally appropriate written notice regarding the young adult's right to request a client-directed attorney, the benefits and role of such attorney, and the specific steps to take to request that an attorney be appointed if the young adult would like an attorney appointed.</para><para>(2) The court has discretion to appoint a court appointed special advocate volunteer or continue the appointment of a previously appointed court appointed special advocate volunteer with the consent of the young adult.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB848, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB50, &#167; 29. </para><effectivedate>September 2, 2023</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>