<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id174">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id176" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="43-4509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4509</statuteno><catchline id="id179">Department; periodic case reviews; written notice; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The
department and at least one person who is not responsible for case management,
in collaboration with the young adult and additional persons identified by
the young adult, shall conduct periodic case reviews consistent with 42 U.S.C.
675(5)(B) not less than once every one hundred eighty days to evaluate progress
made toward meeting the goals set forth in the case plan. The department is
not required to have legal counsel present at such reviews. The department
shall utilize a team approach in conducting such reviews and shall seek to facilitate the participation of the young
adult. Reviews
shall be conducted in an informal manner and, whenever possible, scheduled
at times that allow for the attendance and participation of the young adult.</para>
<para>(2) At the
end of each case review, the reviewer conducting the periodic case review
shall notify the young adult of his or her right to request a client-directed
attorney and an additional permanency review and shall provide the young adult
with a clear and developmentally appropriate written notice regarding the
young adult's right to request a client-directed attorney, the benefits and
role of such attorney, the specific steps to take to request that an attorney
be appointed, the young adult's right to request an additional permanency
review hearing, the potential benefits and purpose of such a hearing, and
the specific steps to take to request an additional permanency review hearing.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 39.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>