<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id212" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4327"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4327</statuteno><catchline>Inspector General's report of investigation; contents; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) The Inspector General's report of an investigation shall be in writing to the Public Counsel and shall contain recommendations. The report may recommend systemic reform or case-specific action, including a recommendation for discharge or discipline of employees or for sanctions against a foster parent, private agency, licensed child care facility, or other provider of child welfare services or juvenile justice services. All recommendations to pursue discipline shall be in writing and signed by the Inspector General. A report of an investigation shall be presented to the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director within fifteen days after the report is presented to the Public Counsel.</para><para>(2) Any person receiving a report under this section shall not further distribute the report or any confidential information contained in the report. The Inspector General, upon notifying the Public Counsel and the director, the probation administrator, or the executive director, may distribute the report, to the extent that it is relevant to a child's welfare, to the guardian ad litem and attorneys in the juvenile court in which a case is pending involving the child or family who is the subject of the report. The report shall not be distributed beyond the parties except through the appropriate court procedures to the judge.</para><para>(3) A report that identifies misconduct, misfeasance, malfeasance, or violation of statute, rules, or regulations by an employee of the department, the juvenile services division, the commission, a private agency, a licensed child care facility, or another provider that is relevant to providing appropriate supervision of an employee may be shared with the employer of such employee. The employer may not further distribute the report or any confidential information contained in the report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB821, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB347, &#167; 20. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>