<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id770"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" statutenumber="43-4812"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4812</statuteno><catchline>Rescission; motion; grounds; when granted; hearing; notice; effect on prior order of custody, parenting time, or support.</catchline><para>(1) A motion for rescission may be filed by any interested person or public agency in order to rescind a judgment of emancipation on the following grounds:</para><para>(a) The minor has become indigent and has insufficient means of support; or</para><para>(b) The judgment of emancipation was obtained by fraud, misrepresentation, or the withholding of material information.</para><para>(2) The motion for rescission shall be filed in the district court in which the petition for emancipation was filed. The motion for rescission of a judgment of emancipation shall be granted if it is proven:</para><para>(a) That rescinding the judgment of emancipation is in the best interests of the emancipated minor; and</para><para>(b)(i) That the minor has become indigent and has insufficient means of support; or</para><para>(ii) That the judgment of emancipation was obtained by fraud, misrepresentation, or the withholding of material information.</para><para>(3) Upon the filing of a motion for rescission, the court shall fix a time for a hearing on the motion. The hearing shall be held not less than forty-five days and not more than sixty days after the filing of such motion unless any party for good cause shown requests a continuance of the hearing or all parties agree to a continuance.</para><para>(4)(a) Upon filing a motion pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, and at least thirty days prior to the hearing date, the movant shall serve a notice of filing, together with a copy of the motion for rescission and a summons to appear at the hearing, upon:</para><para>(i) The emancipated person;</para><para>(ii) The parents or the person who was the legal guardian of the emancipated person or, if the parents or legal guardian cannot be found, the nearest known relative of the emancipated person residing within the state, if any; and</para><para>(iii) The legal custodian of the emancipated person prior to emancipation, if any.</para><para>(b) Service and summons shall be made in accordance with section 25-505.01.</para><para>(c) Upon a motion and showing by affidavit that service cannot be made with reasonable diligence by any other method provided by statute, the court may permit service to be made (i) by leaving the process at the party's usual place of residence and mailing a copy by first-class mail to the party's last-known address, (ii) by publication, or (iii) by any manner reasonably calculated under the circumstances to provide the party with actual notice of the proceedings and an opportunity to be heard.</para><para>(d) The emancipated minor may file a written response objecting to the motion to rescind emancipation within thirty days after service of the notice of the hearing.</para><para>(5) If, after hearing, the court determines by clear and convincing evidence that rescinding the judgment of emancipation is in the best interests of the minor because the minor has become indigent and has insufficient means of support, or because the judgment of emancipation was obtained by fraud, misrepresentation, or the withholding of material information, the court shall rescind the judgment of emancipation.</para><para>(6) If a prior order regarding custody, parenting time, or support of the minor was suspended by the judgment of emancipation, the order rescinding the judgment of emancipation shall be reported by the district court clerk to the jurisdiction that issued such order and shall serve to reinstate such prior order of custody, parenting time, or support.</para><para>(7) The parents or legal guardian or legal custodian of a minor emancipated by court order are not liable for any debts incurred by the minor child during the period of emancipation.</para><para>(8) Rescinding a judgment of emancipation does not affect an obligation, responsibility, right, or interest that arose during the period of time that the judgment of emancipation was in effect.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB714, &#167; 12. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>