<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id201" statutenumber="43-4514"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4514</statuteno><catchline id="id204">Department; submit amended state plan amendment to seek federal funding; department; duties; rules and regulations; references to United States Code; how construed.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall submit an amended state plan amendment by October 15, 2019, to seek federal Title IV-E funding under 42 U.S.C. 672 for any newly eligible young adult who was adjudicated to be a juvenile described in subdivision (8) of section 43-247 if such young adult's guardianship or state-funded adoption assistance agreement was disrupted or terminated after the young adult had attained the age of sixteen years and for any newly eligible young adult with respect to whom an adoption assistance agreement was in effect pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 673 if the child had attained sixteen years of age before the agreement became effective or with respect to whom a state-funded adoption assistance agreement was in effect if the child had attained sixteen years of age before the agreement became effective pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of section 43-4504.</para><para>(2) The department shall implement the bridge to independence program, extended guardianship assistance described in section 43-4511, and extended adoption assistance described in section 43-4512 in accordance with the federal Fostering Connections to Success and Increasing Adoptions Act of 2008, 42 U.S.C. 673 and 42 U.S.C. 675(8)(B) and in accordance with requirements necessary to obtain federal Title IV-E funding under 42 U.S.C. 672 and 42 U.S.C. 673.</para><para>(3) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as needed to carry out this section by October 15, 2015.</para><para>(4) All references to the United States Code in the Young Adult Bridge to Independence Act refer to sections of the code as such sections existed on January 1, 2015.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB216, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB243, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB600, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>