<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id425">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" id="id427" statutenumber="43-4102">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4102</statuteno><catchline id="id430">Nebraska Juvenile
Service Delivery Project; expansion; funding; information-sharing process;
established.</catchline>
<para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that the Nebraska
Juvenile Service Delivery Project, established as a pilot program under section
43-4101 within the Office of Probation Administration, be expanded statewide
in a three-step, phase-in process beginning July 1, 2013, with full implementation
by July 1, 2014. The expansion of the project will result in the Office of
Probation Administration taking over the duties of the Office of Juvenile
Services with respect to its previous functions of community supervision and
parole of juvenile law violators and of evaluations for such juveniles. The
Office of Juvenile Services shall continue for the purpose of operating the
youth rehabilitation and treatment centers and the care and custody of the
juveniles placed at such centers. Expansion of the project shall be funded
by the transfer of funds from the Department of Health and Human Services
and the Office of Juvenile Services used to fully fund community-based services
and juvenile parole to the Office of Probation Administration.</para>
<para>(2) There shall be established through the use of technology
an information-sharing process to support and enhance the exchange of information
between the Department of Health and Human Services, the Office of Probation
Administration, and the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal
Justice. It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate two hundred fifty
thousand dollars from the General Fund to the Office of Probation Administration
to facilitate the information-sharing process.</para>

<para>(3) Costs
incurred on behalf of juveniles under the Nebraska Juvenile Service Delivery
Project shall be paid as provided in section 43-290.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB464, &#167; 32.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>