<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id728">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id730" statutenumber="43-4102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4102</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Juvenile Service Delivery
Project; expansion; funding; information-sharing process; established; detention
costs; payment.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that the Nebraska Juvenile
Service Delivery Project, established as a pilot program under section 43-4101
within the Office of Probation Administration, be expanded statewide in a
three-step, phase-in process beginning July 1, 2013, with full implementation
by July 1, 2014. The expansion of the project will result in the Office of
Probation Administration taking over the duties of the Office of Juvenile
Services with respect to its previous functions of community supervision and
parole of juvenile law violators and of evaluations for such juveniles. The
Office of Juvenile Services shall continue for the purpose of operating the
youth rehabilitation and treatment centers and the care and custody of the
juveniles placed at such centers. Expansion of the project shall be funded
by the transfer of funds from the Department of Health and Human Services
and the Office of Juvenile Services used to fully fund community-based services
and juvenile parole to the Office of Probation Administration.</para>
<para>(2) There
shall be established through the use of technology an information-sharing
process to support and enhance the exchange of information between the Department
of Health and Human Services, the Office of Probation Administration, and
the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice. It is the
intent of the Legislature to appropriate two hundred fifty thousand dollars
from the General Fund to the Office of Probation Administration to facilitate
the information-sharing process.</para><para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature
that detention costs for a juvenile shall be paid by the county containing
the court which issued the order to detain in the following situations:</para>
<para>(a)
A juvenile has no prior contact with the juvenile justice system and is placed
in predisposition detention; or</para><para>(b) A juvenile is placed in predisposition
detention for a new violation of law while under the supervision of the Office
of Probation Administration.</para><para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature
that detention costs for a juvenile shall be paid by the Office of Probation
Administration in the following situations:</para><para>(a) A juvenile is placed in detention as
the result of an alleged violation of probation; or</para><para>(b) A juvenile
is placed in post-disposition detention under the supervision of the Office
of Probation Administration while awaiting placement.</para><para>(5) For purposes
of this section, detention means a secure juvenile detention facility or staff
secure juvenile facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 55.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>