<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id84">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Infants and Juveniles" id="id86" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="43-4409"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4409</statuteno><catchline>Evaluation of child welfare system;
nationally recognized evaluator; duties; qualification; evaluation; contents;
report.</catchline><para>(1)
The department shall engage a nationally recognized evaluator to provide an
evaluation of the child welfare system.</para>
<para>(2)(a)
The evaluator shall:</para><para>(i) Be a national entity that can demonstrate
direct involvement with public and tribal child welfare agencies, partnerships
with national advocacy organizations, think tanks, or technical assistance
providers, collaboration with community agencies, and independent research;
and</para><para>(ii) Be independent of the department and any lead agency or the
pilot project, shall not have been involved in a contractual relationship
with the department, any lead agency, or the pilot project within the preceding
three years, and shall not have served as a consultant to the department,
any lead agency, or the pilot project within the preceding three years.</para>
<para>(b)
The department shall give consideration to evaluator candidates who have experience
in: (i) Outcome measurement, including, but not limited to: Measuring change
for organizations, systems, and communities, with an emphasis on organizational
assessment, child welfare system evaluation, and complex environmental factors;
assessing the quality of child welfare programs and services across the continuum
of care, with differential consideration of in-home and foster care populations
and advanced research and evaluation methodologies, including qualitative
and mixed-method approaches; (ii) use of data, including, but not limited
to: Using existing administrative data sets, with an emphasis on longitudinal
data analysis; integrating data across multiple systems and interoperability;
developing and using data exchange standards; and using continuous quality
improvement methods to assist with child welfare policy decisionmaking; (iii)
intervention research and evaluation, including, but not limited to: Designing,
replicating, and adapting interventions, including the identification of counter
factuals; and evaluating programmatic and policy interventions for efficacy,
effectiveness, and cost; and (iv) dissemination and implementation research,
including, but not limited to: Measuring fidelity; describing and evaluating
the effectiveness of implementation processes; effectively disseminating relevant,
accessible, and useful findings and results; and measuring the acceptability,
adoption, use, and sustainability of evidence-based and evidence-informed
practices and programs.</para><para>(3) The evaluation shall include the following
key areas: </para><para>(a) The degree to which privatization of child welfare services
in the eastern service area has been successful in improving outcomes for
children and parents, including, but not limited to, whether the outcomes
are consistent with the objectives of the Families Matter program or the pilot
project and whether the cost is reasonable, given the outcomes and cost of
privatization;</para><para>(b) A review of the readiness and capacity of any lead agency or
the pilot project and the department to perform essential child welfare service
delivery and administrative management functions according to nationally recognized
standards for network management entities, with special focus on case management.
The readiness review shall include, but not be limited to, strengths, areas
where functional improvement is needed, areas with current duplication and
overlap in effort, and areas where coordination needs improvement; and</para>
<para>(c)
A complete review of the preceding three years of placements of children in
residential treatment settings, by service area and by any lead agency or
the pilot project. The review shall include all placements made or paid for
by the child welfare system, the Office of Juvenile Services, the State Department
of Education, or local education agencies; any lead agency or the pilot project
through letters of agreement; and the medical assistance program. The review
shall include, but not be limited to: (i) Child variables; (ii) reasons for
placement; (iii) the percentage of children denied medicaid-reimbursed services
and denied the level of placement originally requested; (iv) with respect
to each child in residential treatment setting: (A) If there was a denial
of initial placement request, the length and level of each placement subsequent
to denial of initial placement request and the status of each child before
and immediately after, six months after, and twelve months after placement;
(B) funds expended and length of placements; (C) number and level of placements;
(D) facility variables; (E) identification of specific services unavailable
in the child's community that, if available, could have prevented the need
for residential treatment; and (F) percentage of children denied reauthorization
requests or subsequent review of initial authorization; (v) identification
of child welfare services unavailable in the state that, if available, could
prevent out-of-state placements; and (vi) recommendations for improved utilization,
gatekeeping, and community-level placement prevention initiatives and an analysis
of child welfare services that would be more effective and cost efficient
in keeping children safe at home.</para><para>(4) The evaluation required pursuant to
this section shall be completed and a report issued on or before December
1, 2012, to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and
the Governor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 9.</para><operativedate>April 12, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>