<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id928"><amendatorysection chaptername="Infants And Juveniles" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="43-4604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>43-4604</statuteno><catchline>Jurisdiction.</catchline><para>(a) A court may issue an order regarding custodial responsibility under the Uniform Deployed Parents Custody and Visitation Act only if the court has jurisdiction under the Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act.</para><para>(b) If a court has issued a temporary order regarding custodial responsibility pursuant to sections 43-4613 to 43-4623, the residence of the deploying parent is not changed by reason of the deployment for the purposes of the Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act during the deployment.</para><para>(c) If a court has issued a permanent order regarding custodial responsibility before notice of deployment and the parents modify that order temporarily by agreement pursuant to sections 43-4608 to 43-4612, the residence of the deploying parent is not changed by reason of the deployment for the purposes of the Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act.</para><para>(d) If a court in another state has issued a temporary order regarding custodial responsibility as a result of impending or current deployment, the residence of the deploying parent is not changed by reason of the deployment for the purposes of the Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act.</para><para>(e) This section does not prevent a court from exercising temporary emergency jurisdiction under the Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB219, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction and Enforcement Act,</emphasis> see section 43-1226.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>