<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 25.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-125"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>21-125</statuteno><catchline>Biennial report.</catchline><para>(ULLCA 209) (a) Each odd-numbered year,
a limited liability company or a foreign limited liability company authorized
to transact business in this state shall deliver to the Secretary of State
for filing a biennial report that states:</para>
<para>(1) the name of the company;</para>
<para>(2) the street and mailing
addresses of the company's designated office and the name and street and mailing
addresses and post office box number, if any, of its agent for service of
process in this state;</para><para>(3)
the street and mailing addresses of its principal office; and</para>
<para>(4) in the case of a
foreign limited liability company, the state or other jurisdiction under whose
law the company is formed and any alternate name adopted under subsection
(a) of section 21-159.</para><para>(b)
Information in a biennial report under this section must be current as of
the date the report is delivered to the Secretary of State for filing.</para>
<para>(c) The first biennial
report under this section must be delivered to the Secretary of State between
January 1 and April 1 of the odd-numbered year following the calendar year
in which a limited liability company was formed or a foreign limited liability
company was authorized to transact business. A report must be delivered to
the Secretary of State between January 1 and April 1 of each subsequent odd-numbered
calendar year.</para><para>(d)
If a biennial report under this section does not contain the information required
in subsection (a) of this section, the Secretary of State shall promptly notify
the reporting limited liability company or foreign limited liability company
and return the report to it for correction. If the report is corrected to
contain the information required in subsection (a) of this section and delivered
to the Secretary of State within thirty days after the effective date of the
notice, it is timely delivered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 25.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>