<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,135" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,135</statuteno><catchline>Articles of nonprofit conversion.</catchline><para>(MBCA 9.32) (a) After a plan of nonprofit conversion providing for the conversion of a domestic business corporation to a domestic nonprofit corporation has been adopted and approved as required by the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act, articles of nonprofit conversion shall be signed on behalf of the corporation by any officer or other duly authorized representative. The articles shall set forth:</para><para>(1) The name of the corporation immediately before the filing of the articles of nonprofit conversion and if that name does not satisfy the requirements of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, or the corporation desires to change its name in connection with the conversion, a name that satisfies the requirements of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act; and</para><para>(2) A statement that the plan of nonprofit conversion was duly approved by the shareholders in the manner required by the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act and the articles of incorporation.</para><para>(b) The articles of nonprofit conversion shall either contain all of the provisions that the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act requires to be set forth in articles of incorporation of a domestic nonprofit corporation and any other desired provisions permitted by the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act or shall have attached articles of incorporation that satisfy the requirements of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act. In either case, provisions that would not be required to be included in restated articles of incorporation of a domestic nonprofit corporation may be omitted.</para><para>(c) The articles of nonprofit conversion shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing and shall take effect at the effective time provided in section 21-206. Within ten business days after the articles of nonprofit conversion take effect, a domestic business corporation converting into a domestic nonprofit corporation shall send written notice of conversion to the last-known address of any holder of a security interest in collateral of such domestic business corporation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 135; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB99, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>