<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,181"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,181</statuteno><catchline>Court action.</catchline><para>(MBCA 13.30) (a) If a shareholder makes demand
for payment under section 21-2,180 which remains unsettled, the corporation
shall commence a proceeding within sixty days after receiving the payment
demand and petition the court to determine the fair value of the shares and
accrued interest. If the corporation does not commence the proceeding within
the sixty-day period, it shall pay in cash to each shareholder the amount
the shareholder demanded pursuant to section 21-2,180 plus interest.</para>
<para>(b) The corporation shall
commence the proceeding in the district court of the county where the corporation's
principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered office, is located.
If the corporation is a foreign corporation without a registered office in
this state, it shall commence the proceeding in the county in this state where
the principal office or registered office of the domestic corporation merged
with the foreign corporation was located at the time of the transaction.</para>
<para>(c) The corporation shall
make all shareholders, whether or not residents of this state, whose demands
remain unsettled parties to the proceeding as in an action against their shares,
and all parties must be served with a copy of the petition. Nonresidents may
be served by registered or certified mail or by publication as provided by
law.</para><para>(d)
The jurisdiction of the court in which the proceeding is commenced under subsection
(b) of this section is plenary and exclusive. The court may appoint one or
more persons as appraisers to receive evidence and recommend a decision on
the question of fair value. The appraisers shall have the powers described
in the order appointing them or in any amendment to it. The shareholders demanding
appraisal rights are entitled to the same discovery rights as parties in other
civil proceedings. There shall be no right to a jury trial.</para>
<para>(e) Each shareholder made
a party to the proceeding is entitled to judgment (1) for the amount, if any,
by which the court finds the fair value of the shareholder's shares, plus
interest, exceeds the amount paid by the corporation to the shareholder for
such shares or (2) for the fair value, plus interest, of the shareholder's
shares for which the corporation elected to withhold payment under section
21-2,179.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 181.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>