<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-412" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-412</statuteno><catchline>Limitation on actions and claims; liability; benefit enforcement proceeding; when authorized.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except in a benefit enforcement proceeding, no person may bring an action or assert a claim against a benefit corporation or its directors or officers with respect to:</para><para>(i) Failure to pursue or create general public benefit or a specific public benefit set forth in its articles of incorporation; or</para><para>(ii) Violation of an obligation, duty, or standard of conduct under the Nebraska Benefit Corporation Act.</para><para>(b) A benefit corporation is not liable for monetary damages under the act for any failure of the benefit corporation to pursue or create general public benefit or a specific public benefit.</para><para>(2) A benefit enforcement proceeding may be commenced or maintained only:</para><para>(a) Directly by the benefit corporation; or</para><para>(b) Derivatively in accordance with the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act by:</para><para>(i) A person or group of persons that owned beneficially or of record at least two percent of the total number of shares of a class or series outstanding at the time of the act or omission complained of;</para><para>(ii) A director;</para><para>(iii) A person or group of persons that owned beneficially or of record five percent or more of the outstanding equity interests in an entity of which the benefit corporation is a subsidiary at the time of the act or omission complained of; or</para><para>(iv) Other persons as specified in the articles of incorporation or bylaws of the benefit corporation.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, a person is the beneficial owner of shares or equity interests if the shares or equity interests are held in a voting trust or by a nominee on behalf of the beneficial owner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB751, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB35, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>