
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,203</statuteno><catchline>Authority to transact business required.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 15.01) (a) A foreign
corporation may not transact business in this state until it obtains a certificate
of authority from the Secretary of State.</para>
<para>(b) The following activities,
among others, do not constitute transacting business within the meaning of
subsection (a) of this section:</para><para>(1) Maintaining, defending, or settling any proceeding;</para>
<para>(2) Holding meetings of the
board of directors or shareholders or carrying on other activities concerning
internal corporate affairs;</para><para>(3)
Maintaining bank accounts;</para><para>(4)
Maintaining offices or agencies for the transfer, exchange, and registration
of the corporation's own securities or maintaining trustees or depositaries
with respect to those securities;</para><para>(5) Selling through independent contractors;</para>
<para>(6) Soliciting or obtaining
orders, whether by mail or through employees or agents or otherwise, if the
orders require acceptance outside this state before they become contracts;</para>
<para>(7) Creating or acquiring
indebtedness, mortgages, and security interests in real or personal property;</para>
<para>(8) Securing or collecting
debts or enforcing mortgages and security interests in property securing the
debts;</para><para>(9)
Owning, without more, real or personal property;</para><para>(10) Conducting an isolated transaction
that is completed within thirty days and that is not one in the course of
repeated transactions of a like nature;</para><para>(11) Transacting business in interstate commerce;
or</para><para>(12)
Acting as a foreign corporate trustee to the extent authorized under section
30-3820.</para><para>(c)
The list of activities in subsection (b) of this section is not exhaustive.</para>
<para>(d) The requirements of the
Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act are not applicable to foreign or alien
insurers which are subject to the requirements of Chapter 44.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 203.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>