
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-306"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-306</statuteno><catchline>Foreign corporations; occupation tax;
investigation by Secretary of State for collection purposes.</catchline><para>Upon
the delivery of the biennial report
required under section 21-304 to the Secretary of State,
it shall be the duty of every foreign corporation doing business in this state to pay to the Secretary
of State an
occupation tax each even-numbered calendar year beginning January
1 and become due and assessable on March 1 of that year and become delinquent
if not paid by April 15 of each even-numbered year. The occupation
tax shall be measured by the property employed by the foreign
corporation in the conduct of its business in this state. For such purpose the property shall
consist of the sum total of the actual value of all real estate and personal
property employed in this state by such foreign
corporation in the transaction of its business. The occupation
tax to be paid by such foreign corporation shall be based upon
the sum so determined and
shall be considered the capital stock of such foreign corporation in this
state for the purpose of the occupation
tax. The schedule of payment shall be double the occupation
tax set forth in section 21-303, or any amendments thereto, except
that the occupation tax shall not exceed
thirty thousand dollars, and the Secretary of State, or any person deputized
by the Secretary of State, shall have authority to investigate and obtain
information from such corporation or any state, county, or city official.
Such officers are authorized by this section to furnish such information to
the Secretary of State, or anyone deputized by the Secretary of State, in
order to determine all facts and give effect to the collection of the occupation tax.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 240, &#167; 6, p. 749; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 766; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 684; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 24-1706; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 32, &#167; 1, p. 212; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 47, &#167; 1, p. 172; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 24-1706; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 21-306; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 63, &#167; 4, p. 203; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 87, &#167; 2, p. 353; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 101, &#167; 6, p. 313; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 124, &#167; 4, p. 571; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 524, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 243.</para></source><annotation><para>Occupation tax of foreign corporation is computed upon basis of paid-up capital stock employed in this state. State ex rel. J. I. Case Threshing Machine Co. v. Marsh, 117 Neb. 832, 223 N.W. 126 (1929).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>