<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-520"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-520</statuteno><catchline>Limitations on liability.</catchline><para>(a) A person is not liable, directly or indirectly, by way of contribution or otherwise, for a debt, obligation, or other liability of:</para><para>(1) a protected series of a series limited liability company solely by reason of being or acting as:</para><para>(A) an associated member, protected-series manager, or protected-series transferee of the protected series; or</para><para>(B) a member, manager, or a transferee of the company; or</para><para>(2) a series limited liability company solely by reason of being or acting as an associated member, protected-series manager, or protected-series transferee of a protected series of the company.</para><para>(b) Subject to section 21-523, the following rules apply:</para><para>(1) A debt, obligation, or other liability of a series limited liability company is solely the debt, obligation, or liability of the company.</para><para>(2) A debt, obligation, or other liability of a protected series is solely the debt, obligation, or liability of the protected series.</para><para>(3) A series limited liability company is not liable, directly or indirectly, by way of contribution or otherwise, for a debt, obligation, or other liability of a protected series of the company solely by reason of the protected series being a protected series of the company or the company:</para><para>(A) being or acting as a protected-series manager of the protected series;</para><para>(B) having the protected series manage the company; or</para><para>(C) owning a protected-series transferable interest of the protected series.</para><para>(4) A protected series of a series limited liability company is not liable, directly or indirectly, by way of contribution or otherwise, for a debt, obligation, or other liability of the company or another protected series of the company solely by reason of:</para><para>(A) being a protected series of the company;</para><para>(B) being or acting as a manager of the company or a protected-series manager of another protected series of the company; or</para><para>(C) having the company or another protected series of the company be or act as a protected-series manager of the protected series.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB78, &#167; 9. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>