
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,144"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,144</statuteno><catchline>Plan of entity conversion.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 9.51) (a) A plan
of entity conversion must include:</para>
<para>(1) A statement of
the type of other entity the surviving entity will be and, if it will be a
foreign other entity, its jurisdiction of organization;</para>
<para>(2) The terms and conditions
of the conversion;</para><para>(3)
The manner and basis of converting the shares of the domestic business corporation
following its conversion into interests or other securities, obligations,
rights to acquire interests or other securities, cash, other property, or
any combination of the foregoing; and</para><para>(4) The full text, as they will be in effect immediately
after consummation of the conversion, of the organic documents of the surviving
entity.</para><para>(b)
The plan of entity conversion may also include a provision that the plan may
be amended prior to filing articles of entity conversion, except that subsequent
to approval of the plan by the shareholders the plan may not be amended to
change:</para><para>(1)
The amount or kind of shares or other securities, interests, obligations,
rights to acquire shares, other securities, or interests, cash, or other property
to be received under the plan by the shareholders;</para><para>(2) The organic documents that
will be in effect immediately following the conversion, except for changes
permitted by a provision of the organic law of the surviving entity comparable
to section 21-2,154; or</para><para>(3)
Any of the other terms or conditions of the plan if the change would adversely
affect any of the shareholders in any material respect.</para>
<para>(c) Terms of a plan
of entity conversion may be made dependent upon facts objectively ascertainable
outside the plan in accordance with subsection (k) of section 21-203.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 144.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>