
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-157"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-157</statuteno><catchline>Activities not constituting transacting
business.</catchline><para>(RULLCA
803) (a) Activities of a foreign limited liability company which do not constitute
transacting business in this state within the meaning of sections 21-155 to
21-163 include:</para>
<para>(1) maintaining, defending,
or settling an action or proceeding;</para><para>(2) carrying on any activity concerning its internal
affairs, including holding meetings of its members or managers;</para>
<para>(3) maintaining accounts
in financial institutions;</para><para>(4) maintaining offices or agencies for the transfer,
exchange, and registration of the company's own securities or maintaining
trustees or depositories with respect to those securities;</para>
<para>(5) selling through independent
contractors;</para><para>(6)
soliciting or obtaining orders, whether by mail or electronic means or through
employees or agents or otherwise, if the orders require acceptance outside
this state before they become contracts;</para><para>(7) creating or acquiring indebtedness, mortgages,
or security interests in real or personal property;</para><para>(8) securing or collecting debts
or enforcing mortgages or other security interests in property securing the
debts and holding, protecting, or maintaining property so acquired;</para>
<para>(9) conducting an isolated
transaction that is completed within thirty days and is not in the course
of similar transactions; and</para><para>(10) transacting business in interstate commerce.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of sections
21-155 to 21-163, the ownership in this state of income-producing real property
or tangible personal property, other than property excluded under subsection
(a) of this section, constitutes transacting business in this state.</para>
<para>(c) This section does
not apply in determining the contacts or activities that may subject a foreign
limited liability company to service of process, taxation, or regulation under
law of this state other than the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company
Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 57.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>