<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-114"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-114</statuteno><catchline>Change of designated office or agent
for service of process; change
of address.</catchline><para>(ULLCA 114) (a) A limited liability
company or foreign limited liability company may change its designated office,
its agent for service of process, or the address of its agent for service
of process by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing a statement
of change containing:</para>
<para>(1) the name of the company;</para>
<para>(2) the street and mailing addresses of its current designated office;</para>
<para>(3) if the current designated office is to be changed, the street and
mailing addresses of the new designated office;</para>
<para>(4) the name and street and mailing addresses and post office box number,
if any, of its current agent for service of process; and</para>
<para>(5) if the current agent for service of process or an address of the
agent is to be changed, the new information.</para>
<para>(b) Subject to subsection (c) of section 21-121, a statement of change
is effective when filed by the Secretary of State.</para>
<para>(c) An agent for service
of process may change the agent's street and mailing addresses and post office
box number, if any, for any limited liability company or foreign limited liability
company for which the agent is designated by notifying the limited liability
company or foreign limited liability company in writing of the change containing
the new information, and by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing
a statement of change of address for an agent for service of process which
complies with the requirements of subdivisions (a)(1), (4), and (5) of this
section and states that the limited liability company or foreign limited liability
company has been notified of the change.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB753, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>