<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-136"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-136</statuteno><catchline>Management of limited liability company.</catchline><para>(RULLCA 407) (a) A limited
liability company is a member-managed limited liability company unless the
operating agreement:</para>
<para>(1) expressly provides
that:</para><para>(A)
the company is or will be manager-managed;</para><para>(B) the company is or will be managed by managers;
or</para><para>(C)
management of the company is or will be vested in managers; or</para>
<para>(2) includes words of
similar import.</para><para>(b)
In a member-managed limited liability company, the following rules apply:</para>
<para>(1) The management and
conduct of the company are vested in the members.</para><para>(2) Each member has equal rights
in the management and conduct of the company's activities.</para>
<para>(3) A difference arising
among members as to a matter in the ordinary course of the activities of the
company may be decided by a majority of the members.</para><para>(4) An act outside the ordinary
course of the activities of the company may be undertaken only with the consent
of all members.</para><para>(5)
The operating agreement may be amended only with the consent of all members.</para>
<para>(c) In a manager-managed
limited liability company, the following rules apply:</para><para>(1) Except as otherwise expressly
provided in the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act, any matter
relating to the activities of the company is decided exclusively by the managers.</para>
<para>(2) Each manager has
equal rights in the management and conduct of the activities of the company.</para>
<para>(3) A difference arising
among managers as to a matter in the ordinary course of the activities of
the company may be decided by a majority of the managers.</para>
<para>(4) The consent of all
members is required to:</para><para>(A)
sell, lease, exchange, or otherwise dispose of all, or substantially all,
of the company's property, with or without the goodwill, outside the ordinary
course of the company's activities;</para><para>(B) approve a merger, conversion, or domestication
under sections 21-170 to 21-184;</para><para>(C) undertake any other act outside the ordinary course
of the company's activities; and</para><para>(D) amend the operating agreement.</para>
<para>(5) A manager may be
chosen at any time by the consent of a majority of the members and remains
a manager until a successor has been chosen, unless the manager at an earlier
time resigns, is removed, or dies, or, in the case of a manager that is not
an individual, terminates. A manager may be removed at any time by the consent
of a majority of the members without notice or cause.</para><para>(6) A person need not be a member
to be a manager, but the dissociation of a member that is also a manager removes
the person as a manager. If a person that is both a manager and a member ceases
to be a manager, that cessation does not by itself dissociate the person as
a member.</para><para>(7)
A person's ceasing to be a manager does not discharge any debt, obligation,
or other liability to the limited liability company or members which the person
incurred while a manager.</para><para>(d)
An action requiring the consent of members under the Nebraska Uniform Limited
Liability Company Act may be taken without a meeting, and a member may appoint
a proxy or other agent to consent or otherwise act for the member by signing
an appointing record, personally or by the member's agent.</para>
<para>(e) The dissolution of
a limited liability company does not affect the applicability of this section.
However, a person that wrongfully causes dissolution of the company loses
the right to participate in management as a member and a manager.</para>
<para>(f) The Nebraska Uniform
Limited Liability Company Act does not entitle a member to remuneration for
services performed for a member-managed limited liability company, except
for reasonable compensation for services rendered in winding up the activities
of the company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 36.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>