<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 77.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-177"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-177</statuteno><catchline>Filings required for conversion; effective
date.</catchline><para>(ULLCA
1008) (a) After a plan of conversion is approved:</para>
<para>(1) a converting limited
liability company shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing articles
of conversion, which must be signed as provided in subsection (a) of section
21-119 and must include:</para><para>(A)
a statement that the limited liability company has been converted into another
organization;</para><para>(B)
the name and form of the organization and the jurisdiction of its governing
statute;</para><para>(C)
the date the conversion is effective under the governing statute of the converted
organization;</para><para>(D)
a statement that the conversion was approved as required by the Nebraska Uniform
Limited Liability Company Act; and</para><para>(E) a statement that the conversion was approved as
required by the governing statute of the converted organization; and</para>
<para>(2) if the converting
organization is not a converting limited liability company, the converting
organization shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing a certificate
of organization, which must include, in addition to the information required
by subsection (b) of section 21-117:</para><para>(A) a statement that the converted organization was
converted from another organization;</para><para>(B) the name and form of that converting organization
and the jurisdiction of its governing statute; and</para><para>(C) a statement that the conversion
was approved in a manner that complied with the converting organization's
governing statute.</para><para>(b)
A conversion becomes effective:</para><para>(1) if the converted organization is a limited liability
company, when the certificate of organization takes effect; and</para>
<para>(2) if the converted
organization is not a limited liability company, as provided by the governing
statute of the converted organization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 77.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>