<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,140" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,140</statuteno><catchline>Articles of domestication and conversion.</catchline><para>(MBCA 9.41) (a) After the conversion of a foreign nonprofit corporation to a domestic business corporation has been authorized as required by the laws of the foreign jurisdiction, articles of domestication and conversion shall be signed by any officer or other duly authorized representative. The articles shall set forth:</para><para>(1) The name of the corporation immediately before the filing of the articles of domestication and conversion and, if that name is unavailable for use in this state or the corporation desires to change its name in connection with the domestication and conversion, a name that satisfies the requirements of section 21-230;</para><para>(2) The jurisdiction of incorporation of the corporation immediately before the filing of the articles of domestication and conversion and the date the corporation was incorporated in that jurisdiction; and</para><para>(3) A statement that the domestication and conversion of the corporation in this state was duly authorized as required by the laws of the jurisdiction in which the corporation was incorporated immediately before its domestication and conversion in this state.</para><para>(b) The articles of domestication and conversion shall either contain all of the provisions that subsection (a) of section 21-220 requires to be set forth in articles of incorporation and any other desired provisions that subsection (b) of section 21-220 permits to be included in articles of incorporation or shall have attached articles of incorporation. In either case, provisions that would not be required to be included in restated articles of incorporation may be omitted.</para><para>(c) The articles of domestication and conversion shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing and shall take effect at the effective time provided in section 21-206. Within ten business days after the articles of domestication and conversion take effect, a foreign nonprofit corporation converting into a domestic business corporation shall send written notice of domestication and conversion to the last-known address of any holder of a security interest in collateral of such foreign nonprofit corporation.</para><para>(d) If the foreign nonprofit corporation is authorized to transact business in this state under the foreign qualification provision of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, its certificate of authority shall be canceled automatically on the effective date of its domestication and conversion.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 140; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB99, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>