<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-303"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-303</statuteno><catchline>Corporations; occupation tax; amount; stock without par value, determination of amount.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the delivery of the biennial report required under section 21-301 to the Secretary of State, it shall be the duty of every corporation for profit, registered in the office of the Secretary of State on January 1, whether incorporated under the laws of this state or incorporated under the laws of any other state when such corporations have domesticated in this state pursuant to section 21-2,220.01, to pay to the Secretary of State an occupation tax in each even-numbered calendar year beginning January 1, which occupation tax shall be due and assessable on such date and delinquent if not paid on or before April 15 of each even-numbered year.</para><para>(2) The occupation tax shall be as follows: When the paid-up capital stock of a corporation does not exceed ten thousand dollars, an occupation tax of twenty-six dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds ten thousand dollars but does not exceed twenty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of forty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds twenty thousand dollars but does not exceed thirty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of sixty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds thirty thousand dollars but does not exceed forty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of eighty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds forty thousand dollars but does not exceed fifty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one hundred dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds fifty thousand dollars but does not exceed sixty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one hundred twenty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds sixty thousand dollars but does not exceed seventy thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one hundred forty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds seventy thousand dollars but does not exceed eighty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one hundred sixty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds eighty thousand dollars but does not exceed ninety thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one hundred eighty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds ninety thousand dollars but does not exceed one hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of two hundred dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds one hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed one hundred twenty-five thousand dollars, an occupation tax of two hundred forty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds one hundred twenty-five thousand dollars but does not exceed one hundred fifty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of two hundred eighty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds one hundred fifty thousand dollars but does not exceed one hundred seventy-five thousand dollars, an occupation tax of three hundred twenty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds one hundred seventy-five thousand dollars but does not exceed two hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of three hundred sixty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds two hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed two hundred twenty-five thousand dollars, an occupation tax of four hundred dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds two hundred twenty-five thousand dollars but does not exceed two hundred fifty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of four hundred forty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds two hundred fifty thousand dollars but does not exceed two hundred seventy-five thousand dollars, an occupation tax of four hundred eighty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds two hundred seventy-five thousand dollars but does not exceed three hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of five hundred twenty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds three hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed three hundred twenty-five thousand dollars, an occupation tax of five hundred sixty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds three hundred twenty-five thousand dollars but does not exceed three hundred fifty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of six hundred dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds three hundred fifty thousand dollars but does not exceed four hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of six hundred sixty-six dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds four hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed four hundred fifty thousand dollars, an occupation tax of seven hundred thirty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds four hundred fifty thousand dollars but does not exceed five hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of eight hundred dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds five hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed six hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of nine hundred ten dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds six hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed seven hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one thousand ten dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds seven hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed eight hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one thousand one hundred twenty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds eight hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed nine hundred thousand dollars, an occupation tax of one thousand two hundred thirty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds nine hundred thousand dollars but does not exceed one million dollars, an occupation tax of one thousand three hundred thirty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds one million dollars but does not exceed ten million dollars, an occupation tax of one thousand three hundred thirty dollars, and eight hundred dollars additional for each million or fraction thereof over and above one million dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds ten million dollars but does not exceed fifteen million dollars, an occupation tax of twelve thousand dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds fifteen million dollars but does not exceed twenty million dollars, an occupation tax of fourteen thousand six hundred sixty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds twenty million dollars but does not exceed twenty-five million dollars, an occupation tax of seventeen thousand three hundred thirty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds twenty-five million dollars but does not exceed fifty million dollars, an occupation tax of twenty thousand six hundred sixty dollars; when such paid-up capital stock exceeds fifty million dollars but does not exceed one hundred million dollars, an occupation tax of twenty-one thousand three hundred thirty dollars; and when such paid-up capital stock exceeds one hundred million dollars, an occupation tax of twenty-three thousand nine hundred ninety dollars. The minimum occupation tax for filing such report shall be twenty-six dollars. For purposes of determining the occupation tax, the stock of corporations incorporated under the laws of any other state, which corporations have domesticated in this state pursuant to section 21-2,220.01 and which stock is without par value, shall be deemed to have a par value of an amount equal to the amount paid in as capital for such shares at the time of the issuance thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 240, &#167; 3, p. 745; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 763; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 681; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 24-1703; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 21-303; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 55, &#167; 1, p. 185; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 63, &#167; 2, p. 200; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 350; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 101, &#167; 3, p. 310; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 124, &#167; 2, p. 568; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 524, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 240; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB794, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Distinction between domestic and domesticated foreign corporation is recognized. Omaha Nat. Bank v. Jensen, 157 Neb. 22, 58 N.W.2d 582 (1953).</para><para>Under former law, all occupation taxes assessed against domestic corporation for profit were a lien upon all property of corporation. Licking v. Hays Lumber Co., 146 Neb. 240, 19 N.W.2d 148 (1945).</para><para>Tax hereunder is in nature of franchise tax, rather than tax upon property, capital stock, or business, and it is not a tax on interstate commerce. State of Nebraska ex rel. Beatrice Creamery Co. v. Marsh, 119 Neb. 197, 227 N.W. 926 (1929), appeal dismissed 282 U.S. 799 (1930).</para><para>Paid-up capital of Nebraska corporation means amount of authorized capital stock employed in business. State ex rel. J. I. Case Threshing Machine Co. v. Marsh, 117 Neb. 832, 223 N.W. 126 (1929).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>