<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-414" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-414</statuteno><catchline>Annual benefit report; distribution; posting; Secretary of State; filing; fee.</catchline><para>(1) A benefit corporation shall send its annual benefit report to each shareholder:</para><para>(a) Within one hundred twenty days following the end of the fiscal year of the benefit corporation; or</para><para>(b) At the same time that the benefit corporation delivers any other annual report to its shareholders.</para><para>(2) A benefit corporation shall post all of its benefit reports on the public portion of its Internet website, if any, except that the compensation paid to directors and financial or proprietary information included in the benefit reports may be omitted from the benefit reports as posted.</para><para>(3) If a benefit corporation does not have an Internet website, the benefit corporation shall provide a copy of its most recent benefit report, without charge, to any person that requests a copy, except that the compensation paid to directors and financial or proprietary information included in the benefit report may be omitted from the copy of the benefit report provided.</para><para>(4)(a) Concurrently with the delivery of the benefit report to shareholders under subsection (1) of this section, the benefit corporation shall deliver a copy of the benefit report to the Secretary of State for filing, except that the compensation paid to directors and financial or proprietary information included in the benefit report may be omitted from the benefit report as delivered to the Secretary of State.</para><para>(b) The Secretary of State shall charge a fee in the amount prescribed in subdivision (a)(12) of section 21-205 for filing a benefit report. The Secretary of State shall collect the fees imposed in this section and remit the fees to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit sixty percent of the fees to the General Fund and forty percent of the fees to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB751, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB35, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 6. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>