<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,153"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,153</statuteno><catchline>Voting on amendments by voting groups.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 10.04) (a) If a
corporation has more than one class of shares outstanding, the holders of
the outstanding shares of a class are entitled to vote as a separate voting
group, if shareholder voting is otherwise required by the Nebraska Model Business
Corporation Act, on a proposed amendment to the articles of incorporation
if the amendment would:</para>
<para>(1) Effect an exchange
or reclassification of all or part of the shares of the class into shares
of another class;</para><para>(2)
Effect an exchange or reclassification or create the right of exchange of
all or part of the shares of another class into shares of the class;</para>
<para>(3) Change the rights,
preferences, or limitations of all or part of the shares of the class;</para>
<para>(4) Change the shares
of all or part of the class into a different number of shares of the same
class;</para><para>(5)
Create a new class of shares having rights or preferences with respect to
distributions that are prior or superior to the shares of the class;</para>
<para>(6) Increase the rights,
preferences, or number of authorized shares of any class that, after giving
effect to the amendment, have rights or preferences with respect to distributions
that are prior or superior to the shares of the class;</para>
<para>(7) Limit or deny an
existing preemptive right of all or part of the shares of the class; or</para>
<para>(8) Cancel or otherwise
affect rights to distributions that have accumulated but not yet been authorized
on all or part of the shares of the class.</para><para>(b) If a proposed amendment would affect a series
of a class of shares in one or more of the ways described in subsection (a)
of this section, the holders of shares of that series are entitled to vote
as a separate voting group on the proposed amendment.</para><para>(c) If a proposed amendment that
entitles the holders of two or more classes or series of shares to vote as
separate voting groups under this section would affect those two or more classes
or series in the same or a substantially similar way, the holders of shares
of all the classes or series so affected must vote together as a single voting
group on the proposed amendment unless otherwise provided in the articles
of incorporation or required by the board of directors.</para>
<para>(d) A class or series
of shares is entitled to the voting rights granted by this section although
the articles of incorporation provide that the shares are nonvoting shares.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 153.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>