<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,222"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,222</statuteno><catchline>Inspection of records by shareholders.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 16.02) (a) A shareholder
of a corporation is entitled to inspect and copy, during regular business
hours at the corporation's principal office, any of the records of the corporation
described in subsection (e) of section 21-2,221 if the shareholder gives the
corporation a signed written notice of the shareholder's demand at least five
business days before the date on which the shareholder wishes to inspect and
copy.</para>
<para>(b) For any meeting of shareholders
for which the record date for determining shareholders entitled to vote at
the meeting is different than the record date for notice of the meeting, any
person who becomes a shareholder subsequent to the record date for notice
of the meeting and is entitled to vote at the meeting is entitled to obtain
from the corporation upon request the notice and any other information provided
by the corporation to shareholders in connection with the meeting unless the
corporation has made such information generally available to shareholders
by posting it on its web site or by other generally recognized means. Failure
of a corporation to provide such information does not affect the validity
of action taken at the meeting.</para><para>(c) A shareholder of a corporation is entitled to
inspect and copy, during regular business hours at a reasonable location specified
by the corporation, any of the following records of the corporation if the
shareholder meets the requirements of subsection (d) of this section and gives
the corporation a signed written notice of the shareholder's demand at least
five business days before the date on which the shareholder wishes to inspect
and copy:</para><para>(1)
Excerpts from minutes of any meeting of the board of directors or a committee
of the board of directors while acting in place of the board of directors
on behalf of the corporation, minutes of any meeting of the shareholders,
and records of action taken by the shareholders, board of directors, or a
committee of the board without a meeting, to the extent not subject to inspection
under subsection (a) of this section;</para><para>(2) Accounting records of the corporation; and</para>
<para>(3) The record of shareholders.</para>
<para>(d) A shareholder may inspect
and copy the records described in subsection (c) of this section only if:</para>
<para>(1) The shareholder's demand
is made in good faith and for a proper purpose;</para><para>(2) The shareholder describes with reasonable
particularity the shareholder's purpose and the records the shareholder desires
to inspect; and</para><para>(3)
The records are directly connected with the shareholder's purpose.</para>
<para>(e) The right of inspection
granted by this section may not be abolished or limited by a corporation's
articles of incorporation or bylaws.</para><para>(f) This section does not affect:</para>
<para>(1) The right of a shareholder
to inspect records under section 21-262 or, if the shareholder is in litigation
with the corporation, to the same extent as any other litigant; or</para>
<para>(2) The power of a court,
independently of the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act, to compel the
production of corporate records for examination.</para><para>(g) For purposes of this section, shareholder
includes a beneficial owner whose shares are held in a voting trust or by
a nominee on the shareholder's behalf.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 222.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>