<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-118</statuteno><catchline>Amendment or restatement of certificate
of organization.</catchline><para>(RULLCA
202) (a) A certificate of organization may be amended or restated at any time.</para>
<para>(b) To amend its certificate
of organization, a limited liability company must deliver to the Secretary
of State for filing an amendment stating:</para><para>(1) the name of the company;</para><para>(2) the date of filing of its certificate
of organization; and</para><para>(3)
the changes the amendment makes to the certificate as most recently amended
or restated.</para><para>(c)
To restate its certificate of organization, a limited liability company must
deliver to the Secretary of State for filing a restatement, designated as
such in its heading, stating:</para><para>(1) in the heading or an introductory paragraph, the
company's present name and the date of the filing of the company's initial
certificate of organization;</para><para>(2) if the company's name has been changed at any
time since the company's formation, each of the company's former names; and</para>
<para>(3) the changes the restatement
makes to the certificate as most recently amended or restated.</para>
<para>(d) Subject to subsection
(c) of section 21-112 and subsection (c) of section 21-121, an amendment to
or restatement of a certificate of organization is effective when filed by
the Secretary of State.</para><para>(e)
If a member of a member-managed limited liability company, or a manager of
a manager-managed limited liability company, knows that any information in
a filed certificate of organization was inaccurate when the certificate was
filed or has become inaccurate owing to changed circumstances, the member
or manager shall promptly:</para><para>(1) cause the certificate to be amended; or</para>
<para>(2) if appropriate, deliver
to the Secretary of State for filing a statement of change under section 21-114
or a statement of correction under section 21-122.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>