<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-264"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-264</statuteno><catchline>Proxies.</catchline><para>(MBCA 7.22) (a) A shareholder may vote the
shareholder's shares in person or by proxy.</para>
<para>(b) A shareholder, or the
shareholder's agent or attorney-in-fact, may appoint a proxy to vote or otherwise
act for the shareholder by signing an appointment form or by an electronic
transmission. An electronic transmission must contain or be accompanied by
information from which the recipient can determine the date of the transmission
and that the transmission was authorized by the sender or the sender's agent
or attorney-in-fact.</para><para>(c)
An appointment of a proxy is effective when a signed appointment form or an
electronic transmission of the appointment is received by the inspector of
election or the officer or agent of the corporation authorized to tabulate
votes. An appointment is valid for eleven months unless a longer period is
expressly provided in the appointment form.</para><para>(d) An appointment of a proxy is revocable unless
the appointment form or electronic transmission states that it is irrevocable
and the appointment is coupled with an interest. Appointments coupled with
an interest include the appointment of:</para><para>(1) A pledgee;</para><para>(2) A person who purchased or agreed to purchase the
shares;</para><para>(3)
A creditor of the corporation who extended it credit under terms requiring
the appointment;</para><para>(4)
An employee of the corporation whose employment contract requires the appointment;
or</para><para>(5)
A party to a voting agreement created under section 21-273.</para>
<para>(e) The death or incapacity
of the shareholder appointing a proxy does not affect the right of the corporation
to accept the proxy's authority unless notice of the death or incapacity is
received by the secretary or other officer or agent authorized to tabulate
votes before the proxy exercises authority under the appointment.</para>
<para>(f) An appointment made
irrevocable under subsection (d) of this section is revoked when the interest
with which it is coupled is extinguished.</para><para>(g) A transferee for value of shares subject to an
irrevocable appointment may revoke the appointment if the transferee did not
know of its existence when acquiring the shares and the existence of the irrevocable
appointment was not noted conspicuously on the certificate representing the
shares or on the information statement for shares without certificates.</para>
<para>(h) Subject to section 21-266
and to any express limitation on the proxy's authority stated in the appointment
form or electronic transmission, a corporation is entitled to accept the proxy's
vote or other action as that of the shareholder making the appointment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 64.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>