<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,229"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,229</statuteno><catchline>Notice of incorporation, amendment,
merger, or share exchange; notice of dissolution.</catchline><para>(a) Notice of incorporation, amendment, merger,
or share exchange of a domestic corporation shall be published for three successive
weeks in some legal newspaper of general circulation in the county where the
corporation's principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered
office, is located.</para>
<para>A notice of incorporation
shall show (1) the corporate name for the corporation, (2) the number of shares
the corporation is authorized to issue, (3) the street address of the corporation's
initial registered office and the name of its initial registered agent at
that office, and (4) the name and street address of each incorporator.</para>
<para>A brief resume of any amendment,
merger, or share exchange of the corporation shall be published in the same
manner and for the same period of time as a notice of incorporation is required
to be published.</para><para>(b)
Notice of the dissolution of a domestic corporation and the terms and conditions
of such dissolution and the names of the persons who are to wind up and liquidate
its business and affairs and their official titles with a statement of assets
and liabilities of the corporation shall be published for three successive
weeks in some legal newspaper of general circulation in the county where the
corporation's principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered
office, is located.</para><para>(c)
Proof of publication of any of the notices required to be published under
this section shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. In the
event any notice required to be given pursuant to this section is not given
but is subsequently published for the required time and proof of the publication
thereof is filed in the office of the Secretary of State, the acts of such
corporation prior to, as well as after, such publication shall be valid.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 229.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>