<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-521"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-521</statuteno><catchline>Claim seeking to disregard limitation of liability.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (b) of this section, a claim seeking to disregard a limitation in section 21-520 is governed by the principles of law and equity, including a principle providing a right to a creditor or holding a person liable for a debt, obligation, or other liability of another person, which would apply if each protected series of a series limited liability company were a limited liability company formed separately from the series limited liability company and distinct from the series limited liability company and any other protected series of the series limited liability company.</para><para>(b) The failure of a limited liability company or a protected series to observe formalities relating to the exercise of its powers or management of its activities and affairs is not a ground to disregard a limitation in subsection (a) of section 21-520 but may be a ground to disregard a limitation in subsection (b) of section 21-520.</para><para>(c) This section applies to a claim seeking to disregard a limitation of liability applicable to a foreign series limited liability company or foreign protected series and comparable to a limitation stated in section 21-520, if:</para><para>(1) the claimant is a resident of this state or doing business or authorized to do business in this state; or</para><para>(2) the claim is to establish or enforce a liability arising under law of this state other than the Nebraska Uniform Protected Series Act or from an act or omission in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB78, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>