<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,215"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,215</statuteno><catchline>Withdrawal upon conversion to a
nonfiling entity.</catchline><para>(MBCA
15.22) (a) A foreign corporation authorized to transact business in this state
that converts to a domestic or foreign nonfiling entity shall apply for a
certificate of withdrawal by delivering an application to the Secretary of
State for filing. The application must set forth:</para>
<para>(1) The name of the foreign
corporation and the name of the state or country under whose law it was incorporated
before the conversion;</para><para>(2)
That it surrenders its authority to transact business in this state as a foreign
corporation;</para><para>(3)
The type of unincorporated entity to which it has been converted and the jurisdiction
whose laws govern its internal affairs; and</para><para>(4) If it has been converted to a foreign unincorporated
entity:</para><para>(i)
That it revokes the authority of its registered agent to accept service on
its behalf and consents that service of process in any proceeding based on
a cause of action arising during the time it was authorized to transact business
in this state may thereafter be made on such foreign unincorporated entity
outside this state; and</para><para>(ii)
A mailing address at which process against the foreign unincorporated entity
may be served.</para><para>(b)
After the withdrawal under this section of a corporation that has converted
to a domestic unincorporated entity is effective, service of process shall
be made on the unincorporated entity in accordance with the regular procedures
for service of process on the form of unincorporated entity to which the corporation
was converted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 215.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>