<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-325"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-325</statuteno><catchline>Foreign corporations; reports and
taxes; notice; failure to pay; authority
to transact business revoked; lien; priority.</catchline><para>(1)
Prior to January 1 of each even-numbered year, the Secretary of State shall
cause to be mailed by first-class mail to the last-known address of each foreign
corporation subject to sections 21-301 to 21-330 a notice stating that
on or before March 1 of each even-numbered year occupation taxes are due to
be paid and a properly executed and signed biennial report
is due to be filed. If such occupation taxes are not paid and the report
is not filed by April 15 of each even-numbered year, (a) such taxes and report
shall become delinquent, (b) the authority
of the delinquent corporation to
transact business in this state shall be administratively revoked on
April 16 of such year for nonpayment of occupation taxes and failure to file
the report, and (c) the delinquent occupation tax shall be a lien upon the
assets of the corporation subject only to state, county, and municipal taxes.</para>
<para>(2) Upon the failure of any foreign corporation to pay its occupation
tax and deliver the biennial report within the time limited by sections
21-301 to 21-330, the Secretary of State
shall on April 16 of such year administratively
revoke the authority of the corporation to transact business in this state for
nonpayment of taxes and shall bar the corporation from doing business in this state under the corporation
laws of this state and make such entry
and showing upon the records of his or her office.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The Secretary of State shall administratively
revoke the authority of a foreign corporation by signing
a certificate of revocation of authority to transact business in this state
that recites the ground or grounds for revocation and its effective date.
The Secretary of State shall file the original of the certificate and serve
a copy on the foreign corporation under section 21-2,212.</para>
<para>(b) The authority of a foreign corporation to transact business in this
state shall cease on the date shown on the certificate revoking its certificate
of authority.</para>
<para>(c) Revocation of a foreign corporation's certificate of authority shall
not terminate the authority of the registered agent of the corporation.</para>
<para>(4) All delinquent corporation occupation taxes
of the foreign corporation
shall be a lien upon the assets of the corporation within the state, subsequent
only to state, county, and municipal taxes. Nothing in sections 21-322 to 21-330 shall be construed to allow a foreign
corporation to do business in this state without complying
with the laws of this
state.</para>
<para>(5) No foreign corporation shall be voluntarily withdrawn until all
occupation taxes due to or assessable by this state have been paid
and the biennial report
filed by such corporation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 240, &#167; 23, p. 752; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 783; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 173, &#167; 2, p. 668; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 701; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 24-1723; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 21-325; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 242, &#167; 11, p. 824; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 101, &#167; 13, p. 316; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 124, &#167; 10, p. 574; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 200; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 524, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 256.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Business Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-2001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>