<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-211</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of existence.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 1.28) (a) Anyone may
apply to the Secretary of State to furnish a certificate of existence for
a domestic corporation or a certificate of authorization for a foreign corporation.</para>
<para>(b) A certificate of existence
or authorization sets forth:</para><para>(1)
The domestic corporation's corporate name or the foreign corporation's corporate
name used in this state;</para><para>(2)
That:</para><para>(i)
The domestic corporation is duly incorporated under the law of this state,
the date of its incorporation, and the period of its duration if less than
perpetual; or</para><para>(ii)
That the foreign corporation is authorized to transact business in this state;</para>
<para>(3) That all fees, taxes,
and penalties owed to this state have been paid, if:</para><para>(i) Payment is reflected in the records
of the Secretary of State; and</para><para>(ii) Nonpayment affects the existence or authorization
of the domestic or foreign corporation;</para><para>(4) That its most recent biennial report required
by section 21-2,228 has been filed with the Secretary of State;</para>
<para>(5) That articles of dissolution
have not been filed; and</para><para>(6)
Other facts of record in the office of the Secretary of State that may be
requested by the applicant.</para><para>(c)
Subject to any qualification stated in the certificate, a certificate of existence
or authorization issued by the Secretary of State may be relied upon as conclusive
evidence that the domestic or foreign corporation is in existence or is authorized
to transact business in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>