<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,212"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,212</statuteno><catchline>Service on foreign corporation.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 15.10) (a) The registered
agent of a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in this state
is the corporation's agent for service of process, notice, or demand required
or permitted by law to be served on the foreign corporation. By being authorized
to transact business in this state, the foreign corporation's agent for service
of process also consents to service of process directed to the foreign corporation's
agent in this state for a search warrant issued pursuant to sections 28-807
to 28-829, or for any other validly issued and properly served subpoena, including
those authorized under section 86-2,112, for records or documents that are
in the possession of the foreign corporation and are located inside or outside
of this state. The consent to service of a subpoena or search warrant applies
to a foreign corporation that is a party or nonparty to the matter for which
the search warrant is sought.</para>
<para>(b) A foreign corporation
may be served by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested, addressed
to the secretary of the foreign corporation or the designated custodian of
records at its principal office shown in its application for a certificate
of authority or in its most recent biennial report if the foreign corporation:</para>
<para>(1) Has no registered agent
or its registered agent cannot with reasonable diligence be served;</para>
<para>(2) Has withdrawn from transacting
business in this state under section 21-2,213; or</para><para>(3) Has had its certificate of authority
revoked under section 21-2,218.</para><para>(c) Service is perfected under subsection (b) of this
section at the earliest of:</para><para>(1)
The date the foreign corporation receives the mail;</para><para>(2) The date shown on the return receipt,
if signed on behalf of the foreign corporation; or</para><para>(3) Five days after its deposit in the
United States mail, as evidenced by the postmark, if mailed postpaid and correctly
addressed.</para><para>(d)
This section does not prescribe the only means, or necessarily the required
means, of serving a foreign corporation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 212.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>