<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-257"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-257</statuteno><catchline>Notice of meeting.</catchline><para>(MBCA 7.05) (a) A corporation shall notify
shareholders of the date, time, and place of each annual and special shareholders'
meeting no fewer than ten nor more than sixty days before the meeting date.
If the board of directors has authorized participation by means of remote
communication pursuant to section 21-261 for any class or series of shareholders,
the notice to such class or series of shareholders shall describe the means
of remote communication to be used. The notice shall include the record date
for determining the shareholders entitled to vote at the meeting, if such
date is different than the record date for determining shareholders entitled
to notice of the meeting. Unless the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act
or the articles of incorporation require otherwise, the corporation is required
to give notice only to shareholders entitled to vote at the meeting as of
the record date for determining the shareholders entitled to notice of the
meeting.</para>
<para>(b) Unless the Nebraska
Model Business Corporation Act or the articles of incorporation require otherwise,
notice of an annual meeting need not include a description of the purpose
or purposes for which the meeting is called.</para><para>(c) Notice of a special meeting must
include a description of the purpose or purposes for which the meeting is
called.</para><para>(d)
If not otherwise fixed under section 21-255 or 21-259, the record date for
determining shareholders entitled to notice of and to vote at an annual or
special shareholders' meeting is the day before the first notice is delivered
to shareholders.</para><para>(e)
Unless the bylaws require otherwise, if an annual or special shareholders'
meeting is adjourned to a different date, time, or place, notice need not
be given of the new date, time, or place if the new date, time, or place is
announced at the meeting before adjournment. If a new record date for the
adjourned meeting is or must be fixed under section 21-259, however, notice
of the adjourned meeting must be given under this section to shareholders
entitled to vote at such adjourned meeting as of the record date fixed for
notice of such adjourned meeting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 57.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>