<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-186" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>21-186</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of registration; application; contents; display; electronic records; use; license verification; Secretary of State; duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) An application for issuance of a certificate of registration shall be made by the limited liability company to the regulatory body in writing and shall contain the names of all of those members, managers, professional employees, and agents of the limited liability company who are required by law to be licensed or otherwise authorized to render the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized to do business or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders, the street address at which the applicant proposes to render a professional service, and such other information as may be required by the regulatory body. If it appears to the regulatory body that each member, manager, professional employee, and agent of the applicant required by law to be licensed is licensed or otherwise authorized to practice the profession for which the applicant is organized to do business and that each member, manager, professional employee, or agent required by law to be licensed or otherwise authorized to practice the profession for which the applicant is organized to do business is not otherwise disqualified from rendering the professional service of the applicant, such regulatory body shall issue a certificate in duplicate upon a form bearing its date of issuance and prescribed by such regulatory body certifying that the proposed or existing limited liability company complies with the provisions of the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act and of the applicable rules and regulations of the regulatory body. Each applicant for such certificate shall pay the regulatory body a fee of twenty-five dollars for the issuance of the certificate.</para><para>(b) One copy of a certificate of registration issued pursuant to this subsection shall be prominently displayed to public view upon the premises of the principal place of business of the limited liability company, and, except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, one copy shall be delivered for filing to the Secretary of State who shall charge a fee as specified in section 21-192 for filing the same. The certificate shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing with the certificate of organization. A certificate of registration bearing an issuance date more than twelve months old shall not be eligible for filing by the Secretary of State.</para><para>(2) When licensing records of regulatory bodies are electronically accessible to the Secretary of State, the regulatory body, in conjunction with the Secretary of State, shall develop an automated process to allow the Secretary of State to electronically access and verify the records. The access of the records shall be made in lieu of a certificate of registration being prepared and issued by the regulatory body for delivery to the Secretary of State for filing. The limited liability company shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing an application setting forth the names of all of those members, managers, professional employees, and agents of such limited liability company who are required by law to be licensed or otherwise authorized to render the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized to do business, or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders, as of the last day of the month preceding the date of application and shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing an annual update thereafter. The application shall be completed on a form prescribed by the Secretary of State and shall contain such other information as the Secretary of State may require. The application shall be accompanied by a license verification fee as specified in section 21-192.</para><para>The Secretary of State shall verify that all of those members, managers, professional employees, and agents who are required by law to do so are duly licensed or otherwise legally authorized to render the professional service for which the applicant is organized to do business or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders through electronic accessing of the regulatory body's records or through compacts or other certifying organizations recognized by the regulatory body. If any member, manager, professional employee, or agent who is required by law to be licensed or otherwise authorized to render the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized to do business, or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders, is not licensed or otherwise legally authorized to render the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized to do business or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders, the limited liability company shall be suspended. The suspension shall remain in effect and a biennial report shall not be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing or filed by the Secretary of State until the limited liability company attests in writing that all of those members, managers, professional employees, or agents who are required by law to be licensed or otherwise authorized to render the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized to do business, or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders, are duly licensed or otherwise legally authorized to render the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized to do business or a service ancillary to those which the limited liability company renders and that information is verified by the Secretary of State or all unlicensed or unauthorized members, managers, professional employees, or agents are no longer members, managers, professional employees, or agents of the limited liability company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB628, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>