<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id607"><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-513"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-513</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of good standing for protected series.</catchline><para>(a) On request of any person, the Secretary of State shall issue a certificate of good standing for a protected series of a series limited liability company or a certificate of registration for a foreign protected series if:</para><para>(1) in the case of a protected series:</para><para>(A) no statement of dissolution, termination, or relocation pertaining to the protected series has been filed; and</para><para>(B) the company has delivered to the Secretary of State for filing the most recent biennial report required by section 21-125 and the report includes the name of the protected series, unless:</para><para>(i) when the company delivered the report for filing, the protected series designation pertaining to the protected series had not yet taken effect; or</para><para>(ii) after the company delivered the report for filing, the company delivered to the Secretary of State for filing a statement of designation change changing the name of the protected series; or</para><para>(2) in the case of a foreign protected series, it is registered to do business in this state.</para><para>(b) A certificate issued under subsection (a) of this section must state:</para><para>(1) in the case of a protected series:</para><para>(A) the name of the protected series of the series limited liability company and the name of the company;</para><para>(B) that the requirements of subsection (a) of this section are met;</para><para>(C) the date the protected-series designation pertaining to the protected series took effect; and</para><para>(D) if a statement of designation change pertaining to the protected series has been filed, the effective date and contents of the statement;</para><para>(2) in the case of a foreign protected series, that it is registered to do business in this state;</para><para>(3) that the fees, taxes, interest, and penalties owed to this state by the protected series or foreign protected series and collected through the Secretary of State have been paid, if:</para><para>(A) payment is reflected in the records of the Secretary of State; and</para><para>(B) nonpayment affects the good standing of the protected series; and</para><para>(4) other facts reflected in the records of the Secretary of State pertaining to the protected series or foreign protected series which the person requesting the certificate reasonably requests.</para><para>(c) Subject to any qualification stated by the Secretary of State in a certificate issued under subsection (a) of this section, the certificate may be relied on as conclusive evidence of the facts stated in the certificate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>