
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,221"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,221</statuteno><catchline>Corporate records.</catchline><para>(MBCA 16.01) (a) A corporation shall keep
as permanent records minutes of all meetings of its shareholders and board
of directors, a record of all actions taken by the shareholders or board of
directors without a meeting, and a record of all actions taken by a committee
of the board of directors in place of the board of directors on behalf of
the corporation.</para>
<para>(b) A corporation shall maintain
appropriate accounting records.</para><para>(c) A corporation or its agent shall maintain a record
of its shareholders, in a form that permits preparation of a list of the names
and addresses of all shareholders, in alphabetical order by class of shares
showing the number and class of shares held by each.</para><para>(d) A corporation shall maintain its
records in the form of a document, including an electronic record or in another
form capable of conversion into paper form within a reasonable time.</para>
<para>(e) A corporation shall keep
a copy of the following records at its principal office:</para>
<para>(1) Its articles or restated
articles of incorporation, all amendments to them currently in effect, and
any notices to shareholders referred to in subdivision (k)(5) of section 21-203
regarding facts on which a filed document is dependent;</para>
<para>(2) Its bylaws or restated
bylaws and all amendments to them currently in effect;</para>
<para>(3) Resolutions adopted by
its board of directors creating one or more classes or series of shares and
fixing their relative rights, preferences, and limitations if shares issued
pursuant to those resolutions are outstanding;</para><para>(4) The minutes of all shareholders'
meetings and records of all action taken by shareholders without a meeting
for the past three years;</para><para>(5)
All written communications to shareholders generally within the past three
years, including the financial statements furnished for the past three years
under section 21-2,227;</para><para>(6)
A list of the names and business addresses of its current directors and officers;
and</para><para>(7)
Its most recent biennial report delivered to the Secretary of State under
section 21-2,228.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 221.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>