<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,166"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,166</statuteno><catchline>Articles of merger or share exchange.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 11.06) (a) After a
plan of merger or share exchange has been adopted and approved as required
by the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act, articles of merger or share
exchange shall be signed on behalf of each party to the merger or share exchange
by any officer or other duly authorized representative. The articles shall
set forth:</para>
<para>(1) The names of the parties
to the merger or share exchange;</para><para>(2) If the articles of incorporation of the survivor
of a merger are amended, or if a new corporation is created as a result of
a merger, the amendments to the survivor's articles of incorporation or the
articles of incorporation of the new corporation;</para><para>(3) If the plan of merger or share exchange
required approval by the shareholders of a domestic corporation that was a
party to the merger or share exchange, a statement that the plan was duly
approved by the shareholders and, if voting by any separate voting group was
required, by each such separate voting group, in the manner required by the
act and the articles of incorporation;</para><para>(4) If the plan of merger or share exchange did not
require approval by the shareholders of a domestic corporation that was a
party to the merger or share exchange, a statement to that effect; and</para>
<para>(5) As to each foreign corporation
or eligible entity that was a party to the merger or share exchange, a statement
that the participation of the foreign corporation or eligible entity was duly
authorized as required by the organic law of the corporation or eligible entity.</para>
<para>(b) Articles of merger or
share exchange shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing by
the survivor of the merger or the acquiring corporation in a share exchange
and shall take effect at the effective time provided in section 21-206. Articles
of merger or share exchange filed under this section may be combined with
any filing required under the organic law of any domestic eligible entity
involved in the transaction if the combined filing satisfies the requirements
of both this section and the other organic law.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 166.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>