<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-232"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-232</statuteno><catchline>Registered name.</catchline><para>(MBCA 4.03) (a) A foreign corporation may
register its corporate name, or its corporate name with any addition required
by section 21-2,208, if the name is not the same as or deceptively similar
to, upon the records of the Secretary of State, the corporate names that are
not available under subsection (b) of section 21-230.</para>
<para>(b) A foreign corporation
registers its corporate name, or its corporate name with any addition required
by section 21-2,208, by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing an
application:</para><para>(1)
Setting forth its corporate name, or its corporate name with any addition
required by section 21-2,208, the state or country and date of its incorporation,
and a brief description of the nature of the business in which it is engaged;
and</para><para>(2)
Accompanied by a certificate of existence, or a document of similar import,
from the state or country of incorporation. Such certificate or document shall
not bear a date of more than sixty days prior to the date the application
is delivered.</para><para>(c)
The name is registered for the applicant's exclusive use upon the effective
date of the application.</para><para>(d)
A foreign corporation whose registration is effective may renew it for successive
years by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing a renewal application,
which complies with the requirements of subsection (b) of this section, between
October 1 and December 31 of the preceding year. The renewal application when
filed renews the registration for the following calendar year.</para>
<para>(e) A foreign corporation
whose registration is effective may thereafter qualify as a foreign corporation
under the registered name or consent in writing to the use of that name by
a corporation thereafter incorporated under the Nebraska Model Business Corporation
Act or by another foreign corporation thereafter authorized to transact business
in this state. The registration terminates when the domestic corporation is
incorporated or the foreign corporation qualifies or consents to the qualification
of another foreign corporation under the registered name.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 32.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>