<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,100"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,100</statuteno><catchline>Committees.</catchline><para>(MBCA 8.25) (a) Unless the Nebraska Model
Business Corporation Act or the articles of incorporation or bylaws provide
otherwise, a board of directors may create one or more committees and appoint
one or more members of the board of directors to serve on any such committee.</para>
<para>(b) Unless the Nebraska
Model Business Corporation Act otherwise provides, the creation of a committee
and appointment of members to it must be approved by the greater of (1) a
majority of all the directors in office when the action is taken or (2) the
number of directors required by the articles of incorporation or bylaws to
take action under section 21-299.</para><para>(c) Sections 21-295 to 21-299 apply both to committees
of the board and to their members.</para><para>(d) To the extent specified by the board of directors
or in the articles of incorporation or bylaws, each committee may exercise
the powers of the board of directors under section 21-284.</para>
<para>(e) A committee may not,
however:</para><para>(1)
Authorize or approve distributions, except according to a formula or method,
or within limits, prescribed by the board of directors;</para>
<para>(2) Approve or propose
to shareholders action that the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act requires
be approved by shareholders;</para><para>(3) Fill vacancies on the board of directors or, subject
to subsection (g) of this section, on any of its committees; or</para>
<para>(4) Adopt, amend, or
repeal bylaws.</para><para>(f)
The creation of, delegation of authority to, or action by a committee does
not alone constitute compliance by a director with the standards of conduct
described in section 21-2,102.</para><para>(g) The board of directors may appoint one or more
directors as alternate members of any committee to replace any absent or disqualified
member during the member's absence or disqualification. Unless the articles
of incorporation or the bylaws or the resolution creating the committee provide
otherwise, in the event of the absence or disqualification of a member of
a committee, the member or members present at any meeting and not disqualified
from voting, unanimously, may appoint another director to act in place of
the absent or disqualified member.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 100.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>