<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,111"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,111</statuteno><catchline>Permissible indemnification.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 8.51) (a) Except
as otherwise provided in this section, a corporation may indemnify an individual
who is a party to a proceeding because the individual is a director against
liability incurred in the proceeding if:</para>
<para>(1)(i) The director conducted
himself or herself in good faith; and</para><para>(ii) Reasonably believed:</para><para>(A) In the case of conduct in an
official capacity, that his or her conduct was in the best interests of the
corporation; and</para><para>(B)
In all other cases, that the director's conduct was at least not opposed to
the best interests of the corporation; and</para><para>(iii) In the case of any criminal proceeding, the
director had no reasonable cause to believe his or her conduct was unlawful;
or</para><para>(2)
The director engaged in conduct for which broader indemnification has been
made permissible or obligatory under a provision of the articles of incorporation,
as authorized by subdivision (b)(5) of section 21-220.</para>
<para>(b) A director's conduct
with respect to an employee benefit plan for a purpose the director reasonably
believed to be in the interests of the participants in, and the beneficiaries
of, the plan is conduct that satisfies the requirement of subdivision (a)(1)(ii)(B)
of this section.</para><para>(c)
The termination of a proceeding by judgment, order, settlement, or conviction,
or upon a plea of nolo contendere or its equivalent, is not, of itself, determinative
that the director did not meet the relevant standard of conduct described
in this section.</para><para>(d)
Unless ordered by a court under subdivision (a)(3) of section 21-2,114, a
corporation may not indemnify a director:</para><para>(1) In connection with a proceeding by or in the right
of the corporation, except for expenses incurred in connection with the proceeding
if it is determined that the director has met the relevant standard of conduct
under subsection (a) of this section; or</para><para>(2) In connection with any proceeding with respect
to conduct for which the director was adjudged liable on the basis of receiving
a financial benefit to which he or she was not entitled, whether or not involving
action in the director's official capacity.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 111.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>