<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,146" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,146</statuteno><catchline>Articles of entity conversion.</catchline><para>(MBCA 9.53) (a) After the conversion of a domestic business corporation to a domestic unincorporated entity has been adopted and approved as required by the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act, articles of entity conversion shall be signed on behalf of the corporation by any officer or other duly authorized representative. The articles shall:</para><para>(1) Set forth the name of the corporation immediately before the filing of the articles of entity conversion and the name to which the name of the corporation is to be changed, which shall be a name that satisfies the organic law of the surviving entity;</para><para>(2) State the type of unincorporated entity that the surviving entity will be;</para><para>(3) Set forth a statement that the plan of entity conversion was duly approved by the shareholders in the manner required by the act and the articles of incorporation; and</para><para>(4) If the surviving entity is a filing entity, either contain all of the provisions required to be set forth in its public organic document and any other desired provisions that are permitted or have attached a public organic document; except that, in either case, provisions that would not be required to be included in a restated public organic document may be omitted.</para><para>(b) After the conversion of a domestic unincorporated entity to a domestic business corporation has been adopted and approved as required by the organic law of the unincorporated entity, articles of entity conversion shall be signed on behalf of the unincorporated entity by any officer or other duly authorized representative. The articles shall:</para><para>(1) Set forth the name of the unincorporated entity immediately before the filing of the articles of entity conversion and the name to which the name of the unincorporated entity is to be changed which shall be a name that satisfies the requirements of section 21-230;</para><para>(2) Set forth a statement that the plan of entity conversion was duly approved in accordance with the organic law of the unincorporated entity; and</para><para>(3) Either contain all of the provisions that subsection (a) of section 21-220 requires to be set forth in articles of incorporation and any other desired provisions that subsection (b) of section 21-220 permits to be included in articles of incorporation or have attached articles of incorporation; except that, in either case, provisions that would not be required to be included in restated articles of incorporation of a domestic business corporation may be omitted.</para><para>(c) After the conversion of a foreign unincorporated entity to a domestic business corporation has been authorized as required by the laws of the foreign jurisdiction, articles of entity conversion shall be signed on behalf of the foreign unincorporated entity by any officer or other duly authorized representative. The articles shall:</para><para>(1) Set forth the name of the unincorporated entity immediately before the filing of the articles of entity conversion and the name to which the name of the unincorporated entity is to be changed which shall be a name that satisfies the requirements of section 21-230;</para><para>(2) Set forth the jurisdiction under the laws of which the unincorporated entity was organized immediately before the filing of the articles of entity conversion and the date on which the unincorporated entity was organized in that jurisdiction;</para><para>(3) Set forth a statement that the conversion of the unincorporated entity was duly approved in the manner required by its organic law; and</para><para>(4) Either contain all of the provisions that subsection (a) of section 21-220 requires to be set forth in articles of incorporation and any other desired provisions that subsection (b) of section 21-220 permits to be included in articles of incorporation or have attached articles of incorporation; except that, in either case, provisions that would not be required to be included in restated articles of incorporation of a domestic business corporation may be omitted.</para><para>(d) The articles of entity conversion shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing and shall take effect at the effective time provided in section 21-206. Within ten business days after the articles of entity conversion take effect, the converting entity shall send written notice of conversion to the last-known address of any holder of a security interest in collateral of the converting entity. Articles of entity conversion under subsection (a) or (b) of this section may be combined with any required conversion filing under the organic law of the domestic unincorporated entity if the combined filing satisfies the requirements of both this section and the other organic law.</para><para>(e) If the converting entity is a foreign unincorporated entity that is authorized to transact business in this state under a provision of law similar to sections 21-2,203 to 21-2,220, its certificate of authority or other type of foreign qualification shall be canceled automatically on the effective date of its conversion.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 146; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB99, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>