<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 60.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-160"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>21-160</statuteno><catchline>Revocation of certificate of authority.</catchline><para>(ULLCA 806) (a) A certificate
of authority of a foreign limited liability company to transact business in
this state may be revoked by the Secretary of State in the manner provided
in subsections (b) and (c) of this section if the company does not:</para>
<para>(1) pay, within sixty
days after the due date, any fee, tax, or penalty due to the Secretary of
State under the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act or law other
than the act;</para><para>(2)
deliver, within sixty days after the due date, its biennial report required
under section 21-125; </para><para>(3)
appoint and maintain an agent for service of process as required by subsection
(b) of section 21-113; or</para><para>(4)
deliver for filing a statement of a change under section 21-114 within thirty
days after a change has occurred in the name or address of the agent.</para>
<para>(b) To revoke a certificate
of authority of a foreign limited liability company, the Secretary of State
must prepare, sign, and file a notice of revocation and send a copy to the
company's agent for service of process in this state, or if the company does
not appoint and maintain a proper agent in this state, to the company's designated
office. The notice must state:</para><para>(1) the revocation's effective date, which must be
at least sixty days after the date the Secretary of State sends the copy;
and</para><para>(2)
the grounds for revocation under subsection (a) of this section.</para>
<para>(c) The authority of
a foreign limited liability company to transact business in this state ceases
on the effective date of the notice of revocation unless before that date
the company cures each ground for revocation stated in the notice filed under
subsection (b) of this section. If the company cures each ground, the Secretary
of State shall file a record so stating.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 60.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>