<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-205" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-205</statuteno><catchline>Filing, service, and copying fees.</catchline><para>(MBCA 1.22) (a) The Secretary of State shall collect the following fees when the documents described in this subsection are delivered to the Secretary of State for filing:</para><para>(1) Articles of incorporation, articles of domestication, or articles of domestication and conversion:</para><para>(i) If the capital stock is $10,000 or less, the fee shall be $60;</para><para>(ii) If the capital stock is more than $10,000 but does not exceed $25,000, the fee shall be $100;</para><para>(iii) If the capital stock is more than $25,000 but does not exceed $50,000, the fee shall be $150;</para><para>(iv) If the capital stock is more than $50,000 but does not exceed $75,000, the fee shall be $225;</para><para>(v) If the capital stock is more than $75,000 but does not exceed $100,000, the fee shall be $300; and</para><para>(vi) If the capital stock is more than $100,000, the fee shall be $300, plus $3 additional for each $1,000 in excess of $100,000.</para><para>For purposes of computing this fee, the capital stock of a corporation organized under the laws of any other state that domesticates in this state, and which stock does not have a par value, shall be deemed to have a par value of an amount per share equal to the amount paid in as capital for each of such shares as are then issued and outstanding, and in no event less than one dollar per share;</para><para>(2) Articles of incorporation or articles of domestication if filed by an insurer holding a certificate of authority issued by the Director of Insurance, the fee shall be $300;</para><para>(3) Application for use of deceptively similar name...$25;</para><para>(4) Application for reserved name...$25;</para><para>(5) Notice of transfer of reserved name...$25;</para><para>(6) Application for registered name...$25;</para><para>(7) Application for renewal of registered name...$25;</para><para>(8) Corporation's statement of change of registered agent or registered office or both...$25;</para><para>(9) Agent's statement of change of registered office for each affected corporation...$25 not to exceed a total of...$1,000;</para><para>(10) Agent's statement of resignation...No fee;</para><para>(11) Articles of charter surrender...$25;</para><para>(12) Articles of nonprofit conversion...$25;</para><para>(13) Articles of entity conversion...$25;</para><para>(14) Amendment of articles of incorporation...$25;</para><para>(15) Restatement of articles of incorporation...$25</para><para>with amendment of articles...$25;</para><para>(16) Articles of merger or share exchange...$25;</para><para>(17) Articles of dissolution...$45;</para><para>(18) Articles of revocation of dissolution...$25;</para><para>(19) Certificate of administrative dissolution...No fee;</para><para>(20) Application for reinstatement following administrative dissolution or revocation...$25;</para><para>(21) Application for reinstatement more than five years after the effective date of an administrative dissolution or administrative revocation...$500;</para><para>(22) Certificate of reinstatement...No fee;</para><para>(23) Certificate of judicial dissolution...No fee;</para><para>(24) Application for certificate of authority...$130;</para><para>(25) Application for amended certificate of authority...$25;</para><para>(26) Application for certificate of withdrawal...$25;</para><para>(27) Application for transfer of authority...$25;</para><para>(28) Certificate of revocation of authority to transact business...No fee;</para><para>(29) Articles of correction...$25;</para><para>(30) Application for certificate of existence or authorization...$25; and</para><para>(31) Any other document required or permitted to be filed by the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act...$25.</para><para>(b) The Secretary of State shall collect a recording fee of five dollars per page in addition to the fees set forth in subsection (a) of this section.</para><para>(c) The Secretary of State shall collect the following fees for copying and certifying the copy of any filed document relating to a domestic or foreign corporation:</para><para>(1) One dollar per page for copying; and</para><para>(2) Ten dollars for the certificate.</para><para>(d) All fees set forth in this section shall be collected by the Secretary of State and remitted to the State Treasurer and credited two-thirds to the General Fund and one-third to the Corporation Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>