<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id178"><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-508"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-508</statuteno><catchline>Rules for applying Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act to specified provisions of act.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (b) of this section and section 21-507, the following rules apply in applying section 21-506, subsections (c) and (f) of section 21-518, subdivision (4)(A) of section 21-524, subsection (a) of section 21-525, and subdivision (2) of section 21-526:</para><para>(1) A protected series of a series limited liability company is deemed to be a limited liability company that is formed separately from the series limited liability company and is distinct from the series limited liability company and any other protected series of the series limited liability company.</para><para>(2) An associated member of the protected series is deemed to be a member of the company deemed to exist under subdivision (a)(1) of this section.</para><para>(3) A protected-series transferee of the protected series is deemed to be a transferee of the company deemed to exist under subdivision (a)(1) of this section.</para><para>(4) A protected-series transferable interest of the protected series is deemed to be a transferable interest of the company deemed to exist under subdivision (a)(1) of this section.</para><para>(5) A protected-series manager is deemed to be a manager of the company deemed to exist under subdivision (a)(1) of this section.</para><para>(6) An asset of the protected series is deemed to be an asset of the company deemed to exist under subdivision (a)(1) of this section, whether or not the asset is an associated asset of the protected series.</para><para>(7) Any creditor or other obligee of the protected series is deemed to be a creditor or obligee of the company deemed to exist under subdivision (a)(1) of this section.</para><para>(b) Subsection (a) of this section does not apply if its application would:</para><para>(1) contravene section 21-110; or</para><para>(2) authorize or require the Secretary of State to:</para><para>(A) accept for filing a type of record that neither the Nebraska Uniform Protected Series Act nor the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act authorizes or requires a person to deliver to the Secretary of State for filing; or</para><para>(B) make or deliver a record that neither the Nebraska Uniform Protected Series Act nor the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act authorizes or requires the Secretary of State to make or deliver.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act,</emphasis> see section 21-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>