
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-141"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-141</statuteno><catchline>Transfer of transferable interest.</catchline><para>(RULLCA 502) (a) A transfer,
in whole or in part, of a transferable interest:</para>
<para>(1) is permissible;</para>
<para>(2) does not by itself
cause a member's dissociation or a dissolution and winding up of the limited
liability company's activities; and</para><para>(3) subject to section 21-143, does not entitle the
transferee to:</para><para>(A)
participate in the management or conduct of the company's activities; or</para>
<para>(B) except as otherwise
provided in subsection (c) of this section, have access to records or other
information concerning the company's activities.</para><para>(b) A transferee has the right to
receive, in accordance with the transfer, distributions to which the transferor
would otherwise be entitled.</para><para>(c) In a dissolution and winding up of a limited liability
company, a transferee is entitled to an account of the company's transactions
only from the date of dissolution.</para><para>(d) A transferable interest may be evidenced by a
certificate of the interest issued by the limited liability company in a record,
and, subject to this section, the interest represented by the certificate
may be transferred by a transfer of the certificate.</para><para>(e) A limited liability company
need not give effect to a transferee's rights under this section until the
company has notice of the transfer.</para><para>(f) A transfer of a transferable interest in violation
of a restriction on transfer contained in the operating agreement is ineffective
as to a person having notice of the restriction at the time of transfer.</para>
<para>(g) Except as otherwise
provided in subdivision (4)(B) of section 21-145, when a member transfers
a transferable interest, the transferor retains the rights of a member other
than the interest in distributions transferred and retains all duties and
obligations of a member.</para><para>(h)
When a member transfers a transferable interest to a person that becomes a
member with respect to the transferred interest, the transferee is liable
for the member's obligations under section 21-132 and subsection (c) of section
21-135 known to the transferee when the transferee becomes a member.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 41.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>