
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,114" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,114</statuteno><catchline>Court-ordered indemnification and advance for expenses.</catchline><para>(MBCA 8.54) (a) A director who is a party to a proceeding because he or she is a director may apply for indemnification or an advance for expenses to the court conducting the proceeding or to another court of competent jurisdiction. After receipt of an application and after giving any notice it considers necessary, the court shall:</para><para>(1) Order indemnification if the court determines that the director is entitled to mandatory indemnification under section 21-2,112;</para><para>(2) Order indemnification or advance for expenses if the court determines that the director is entitled to indemnification or advance for expenses pursuant to a provision authorized by subsection (a) of section 21-2,118; or</para><para>(3) Order indemnification or advance for expenses if the court determines, in view of all the relevant circumstances, that it is fair and reasonable:</para><para>(i) To indemnify the director; or</para><para>(ii) To advance expenses to the director, even if, in the case of subdivision (a)(3)(i) or (ii) of this section he or she has not met the relevant standard of conduct set forth in subsection (a) of section 21-2,111, failed to comply with section 21-2,113, or was adjudged liable in a proceeding referred to in subdivision (d)(1) or (2) of section 21-2,111, but if the director was adjudged so liable indemnification shall be limited to expenses incurred in connection with the proceeding.</para><para>(b) If the court determines that the director is entitled to indemnification under subdivision (a)(1) of this section or to indemnification or advance for expenses under subdivision (a)(2) of this section, it shall also order the corporation to pay the director's expenses incurred in connection with obtaining court-ordered indemnification or advance for expenses. If the court determines that the director is entitled to indemnification or advance for expenses under subdivision (a)(3) of this section, it may also order the corporation to pay the director's expenses to obtain court-ordered indemnification or advance for expenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB35, &#167; 17. </para></source><annotation><para>Because this section provides that a director may apply for indemnification for attorney fees "to the court
        conducting the proceeding" and because "proceeding" includes an appeal, this section provides that a director may
        apply to an appellate court for indemnification related to an appeal that took place in the appellate court. Gerber v.
        P &amp;  L Finance Co., 301 Neb. 463, 919 N.W.2d 116 (2018).
    </para><para>"Proceeding," as used in this section, includes appeals, and therefore, this section applies to indemnification for
        attorney fees incurred in an appeal. Gerber v. P &amp;  L Finance Co., 301 Neb. 463, 919 N.W.2d 116 (2018).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>