
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-110</statuteno><catchline>Operating agreement; scope, function,
and limitations.</catchline><para>(RULLCA
110) (a) To the extent the operating agreement does not otherwise provide
for a matter, the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act governs the
matter.</para>
<para>(b) An operating agreement
may not:</para><para>(1)
vary a limited liability company's capacity under section 21-105 to sue and
be sued in its own name;</para><para>(2)
vary the law applicable under section 21-106;</para><para>(3) vary the power of the court
under section 21-120;</para><para>(4)
subject to subsections (c) through (f) of this section, eliminate the duty
of loyalty or the duty of care;</para><para>(5) subject to subsections (c) through (f) of this
section, eliminate the contractual obligation of good faith and fair dealing
under subsection (d) of section 21-138;</para><para>(6) unreasonably restrict the duties and rights stated
in section 21-139;</para><para>(7)
vary the power of a court to decree dissolution in the circumstances specified
in subdivisions (a)(4) and (5) of section 21-147;</para><para>(8) vary the requirement to wind
up a limited liability company's business as specified in subsection (a) and
subdivision (b)(1)(A) of section 21-148;</para><para>(9) unreasonably restrict the right of a member to
maintain an action under sections 21-164 to 21-169;</para><para>(10) except as otherwise provided
in section 21-183, restrict the right to approve a merger, conversion, or
domestication of a member that will have personal liability with respect to
a surviving, converted, or domesticated organization; or</para>
<para>(11) except as otherwise
provided in subsection (b) of section 21-112, restrict the rights under the
act of a person other than a member or manager.</para><para>(c) If not manifestly unreasonable,
the operating agreement may:</para><para>(1) restrict or eliminate the duty:</para>
<para>(A) as required in subdivision
(b)(1) and subsection (g) of section 21-138, to account to the limited liability
company and to hold as trustee for it any property, profit, or benefit derived
by the member in the conduct or winding up of the company's business, from
a use by the member of the company's property, or from the appropriation of
a limited liability company opportunity;</para><para>(B) as required in subdivision (b)(2) and subsection
(g) of section 21-138, to refrain from dealing with the company in the conduct
or winding up of the company's business as or on behalf of a party having
an interest adverse to the company; and</para><para>(C) as required by subdivision (b)(3) and subsection
(g) of section 21-138, to refrain from competing with the company in the conduct
of the company's business before the dissolution of the company;</para>
<para>(2) identify specific
types or categories of activities that do not violate the duty of loyalty;</para>
<para>(3) alter the duty of
care, except to authorize intentional misconduct or knowing violation of law;</para>
<para>(4) alter any other fiduciary
duty, including eliminating particular aspects of that duty; and</para>
<para>(5) prescribe the standards
by which to measure the performance of the contractual obligation of good
faith and fair dealing under subsection (d) of section 21-138.</para>
<para>(d) The operating agreement
may specify the method by which a specific act or transaction that would otherwise
violate the duty of loyalty may be authorized or ratified by one or more disinterested
and independent persons after full disclosure of all material facts.</para>
<para>(e) To the extent the
operating agreement of a member-managed limited liability company expressly
relieves a member of a responsibility that the member would otherwise have
under the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act and imposes the responsibility
on one or more other members, the operating agreement may, to the benefit
of the member that the operating agreement relieves of the responsibility,
also eliminate or limit any fiduciary duty that would have pertained to the
responsibility.</para><para>(f)
The operating agreement may alter or eliminate the indemnification for a member
or manager provided by subsection (a) of section 21-137 and may eliminate
or limit a member's or manager's liability to the limited liability company
and members for money damages, except for:</para><para>(1) breach of the duty of loyalty;</para>
<para>(2) a financial benefit
received by the member or manager to which the member or manager is not entitled;</para>
<para>(3) a breach of a duty
under section 21-135;</para><para>(4)
intentional infliction of harm on the company or a member; or</para>
<para>(5) an intentional violation
of criminal law.</para><para>(g)
The court shall decide any claim under subsection (c) of this section that
a term of an operating agreement is manifestly unreasonable. The court:</para>
<para>(1) shall make its determination
as of the time the challenged term became part of the operating agreement
and by considering only circumstances existing at that time; and</para>
<para>(2) may invalidate the
term only if, in light of the purposes and activities of the limited liability
company, it is readily apparent that:</para><para>(A) the objective of the term is unreasonable; or</para>
<para>(B) the term is an unreasonable
means to achieve the provision's objective.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>