<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-323.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>21-323.01</statuteno><catchline>Domestic corporation administratively dissolved; reinstatement; application; procedure; payment required.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Until January 1, 2017, the provisions of this subsection apply. A corporation automatically dissolved under section 21-323 may apply to the Secretary of State for reinstatement within five years after the effective date of its automatic dissolution. The application shall:</para><para>(i) Recite the name of the corporation and the effective date of its automatic dissolution;</para><para>(ii) State that the ground or grounds for dissolution either did not exist or have been eliminated;</para><para>(iii) State that the corporation's name satisfies the requirements of section 21-2028; and</para><para>(iv) Be accompanied by a fee in the amount prescribed in section 21-2005, as such section may from time to time be amended, for an application for reinstatement.</para><para>(b) If the Secretary of State determines (i) that the application for reinstatement contains the information required by subdivision (a) of this subsection and that the information is correct and (ii) that the corporation has complied with subdivision (f) of this subsection, he or she shall cancel the certificate of dissolution, prepare a certificate of reinstatement that recites his or her determination and the effective date of reinstatement, file the original of the certificate, and serve a copy on the corporation under section 21-2034.</para><para>(c) A corporation that has been automatically dissolved under section 21-323 for more than five years may apply to the Secretary of State for late reinstatement. The application shall:</para><para>(i) Recite the name of the corporation and the effective date of its automatic dissolution;</para><para>(ii) State that the ground or grounds for dissolution either did not exist or have been eliminated;</para><para>(iii) State that the corporation's name satisfies the requirements of section 21-2028;</para><para>(iv) State that a legitimate reason exists for reinstatement and what such legitimate reason is;</para><para>(v) State that such reinstatement does not constitute fraud on the public; and</para><para>(vi) Be accompanied by a fee in the amount prescribed in section 21-2005, as such section may from time to time be amended, for an application for late reinstatement.</para><para>(d) If the Secretary of State determines (i) that an application for late reinstatement contains the information required by subdivision (c) of this subsection and that the information is correct and (ii) that the corporation has complied with subdivision (f) of this subsection, he or she shall cancel the certificate of dissolution, prepare a certificate of late reinstatement that recites his or her determination and the effective date of the reinstatement, file the original of the certificate, and serve a copy on the corporation under section 21-2034.</para><para>(e) When the reinstatement is effective, it shall relate back to and take effect as of the effective date of the automatic dissolution and the corporation shall resume carrying on its business as if the automatic dissolution had never occurred.</para><para>(f) A corporation applying for reinstatement under this subsection shall:</para><para>(i)(A) Pay to the Secretary of State a sum equal to all occupation taxes delinquent at the time the corporation was automatically dissolved, plus a sum equal to all occupation taxes which would otherwise have been due for the years the corporation was automatically dissolved; and (B) deliver to the Secretary of State a properly executed and signed biennial report for the most recent even-numbered year; and</para><para>(ii) Pay to the Secretary of State an additional amount derived by multiplying the rate specified in section 45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted, times the amount of occupation taxes required to be paid by it for each year that such corporation was automatically dissolved.</para><para>(2)(a) Beginning January 1, 2017, the provisions of this subsection apply. A corporation administratively dissolved under section 21-323 may apply to the Secretary of State for reinstatement within five years after the effective date of its administrative dissolution. The application shall:</para><para>(i) Recite the name of the corporation and the effective date of its administrative dissolution;</para><para>(ii) State that the ground or grounds for dissolution either did not exist or have been eliminated;</para><para>(iii) State that the corporation's name satisfies the requirements of section 21-230; and</para><para>(iv) Be accompanied by a fee in the amount prescribed in section 21-205, as such section may from time to time be amended, for an application for reinstatement.</para><para>(b) If the Secretary of State determines (i) that the application for reinstatement contains the information required by subdivision (a) of this subsection and that the information is correct and (ii) that the corporation has complied with subdivision (f) of this subsection, he or she shall cancel the certificate of dissolution, prepare a certificate of reinstatement that recites his or her determination and the effective date of reinstatement, file the original of the certificate, and serve a copy on the corporation under section 21-236.</para><para>(c) A corporation administratively dissolved under section 21-323 for more than five years may apply to the Secretary of State for late reinstatement. The application shall:</para><para>(i) Recite the name of the corporation and the effective date of its administrative dissolution;</para><para>(ii) State that the ground or grounds for dissolution either did not exist or have been eliminated;</para><para>(iii) State that the corporation's name satisfies the requirements of section 21-230;</para><para>(iv) State that a legitimate reason exists for reinstatement and what such legitimate reason is;</para><para>(v) State that such reinstatement does not constitute fraud on the public; and</para><para>(vi) Be accompanied by a fee in the amount prescribed in section 21-205, as such section may from time to time be amended, for an application for late reinstatement.</para><para>(d) If the Secretary of State determines (i) that the application for late reinstatement contains the information required by subdivision (c) of this subsection and that the information is correct and (ii) that the corporation has complied with subdivision (f) of this subsection, he or she shall cancel the certificate of dissolution, prepare a certificate of late reinstatement that recites his or her determination and the effective date of reinstatement, file the original of the certificate, and serve a copy on the corporation under section 21-236.</para><para>(e) When the reinstatement is effective, it shall relate back to and take effect as of the effective date of the administrative dissolution and the corporation shall resume carrying on its business as if the administrative dissolution had never occurred.</para><para>(f) A corporation applying for reinstatement under this subsection shall:</para><para>(i)(A) Pay to the Secretary of State a sum equal to all occupation taxes delinquent at the time the corporation was administratively dissolved, plus a sum equal to all occupation taxes which would otherwise have been due for the years the corporation was administratively dissolved and (B) deliver to the Secretary of State a properly executed and signed biennial report for the most recent even-numbered year; and</para><para>(ii) Pay to the Secretary of State an additional amount derived by multiplying the rate specified in section 45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted, times the amount of occupation taxes required to be paid by it for each year that such corporation was administratively dissolved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 198; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1036, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 524, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB854, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 254; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>