<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-234"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-234</statuteno><catchline>Change of registered office or registered
agent.</catchline><para>(MBCA
5.02) (a) A corporation may change its registered office or registered agent
by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing a statement of change that
sets forth:</para>
<para>(1) The name of the corporation;</para>
<para>(2) The street address of
its current registered office;</para><para>(3) If the current registered office is to be changed,
the street address of the new registered office;</para><para>(4) The name and street address of
its current registered agent. A post office box number may be provided in
addition to the street address;</para><para>(5) If the current registered agent is to be changed,
the name of the new registered agent and the new agent's written consent,
either on the statement or attached to it, to the appointment; and</para>
<para>(6) That after the change
or changes are made, the street addresses of its registered office and the
business office of its registered agent will be identical.</para>
<para>(b) If the street address
or post office box number of a registered agent's business office changes,
the agent may change the street address or, if one exists, the post office
box number, of the registered office of any corporation for which the agent
is the registered agent by delivering a signed written notice of the change
to the corporation and signing, either manually or in facsimile, and delivering
to the Secretary of State for filing a signed statement that complies with
the requirements of subsection (a) of this section and recites that the corporation
has been notified of the change.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 34.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>