<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,141</statuteno><catchline>Effect of foreign nonprofit domestication
and conversion.</catchline><para>(MBCA
9.42) (a) When a domestication and conversion of a foreign nonprofit corporation
to a domestic business corporation becomes effective:</para>
<para>(1) The title to all
real and personal property, both tangible and intangible, of the corporation
remains in the corporation without reversion or impairment;</para>
<para>(2) The liabilities
of the corporation remain the liabilities of the corporation;</para>
<para>(3) An action or proceeding
pending against the corporation continues against the corporation as if the
domestication and conversion had not occurred;</para><para>(4) The articles of domestication
and conversion, or the articles of incorporation attached to the articles
of domestication and conversion, constitute the articles of incorporation
of the corporation;</para><para>(5)
Shares, other securities, obligations, rights to acquire shares or other securities
of the corporation, or cash or other property shall be issued or paid as provided
pursuant to the laws of the foreign jurisdiction so long as at least one share
is outstanding immediately after the effective time; and</para>
<para>(6) The corporation
is deemed to:</para><para>(i)
Be a domestic corporation for all purposes;</para><para>(ii) Be the same corporation without interruption
as the foreign nonprofit corporation; and</para><para>(iii) Have been incorporated on the date the foreign
nonprofit corporation was originally incorporated.</para><para>(b) The owner liability of a member
of a foreign nonprofit corporation that domesticates and converts to a domestic
business corporation shall be as follows:</para><para>(1) The domestication and conversion does not discharge
any owner liability under the laws of the foreign jurisdiction to the extent
any such owner liability arose before the effective time of the articles of
domestication and conversion;</para><para>(2) The member shall not have owner liability under
the laws of the foreign jurisdiction for any debt, obligation, or liability
of the corporation that arises after the effective time of the articles of
domestication and conversion;</para><para>(3) The provisions of the laws of the foreign jurisdiction
shall continue to apply to the collection or discharge of any owner liability
preserved by subdivision (1) of this subsection as if the domestication and
conversion had not occurred; and</para><para>(4) The member shall have whatever rights of contribution
from other members are provided by the laws of the foreign jurisdiction with
respect to any owner liability preserved by subdivision (1) of this subsection
as if the domestication and conversion had not occurred.</para>
<para>(c) A member of a foreign
nonprofit corporation who becomes subject to owner liability for some or all
of the debts, obligations, or liabilities of the corporation as a result of
its domestication and conversion in this state shall have owner liability
only for those debts, obligations, or liabilities of the corporation that
arise after the effective time of the articles of domestication and conversion.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 141.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>