<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,187"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,187</statuteno><catchline>Revocation of dissolution.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 14.04) (a) A corporation
may revoke its dissolution within one hundred twenty days of its effective
date.</para>
<para>(b) Revocation of dissolution
must be authorized in the same manner as the dissolution was authorized unless
that authorization permitted revocation by action of the board of directors
alone, in which event the board of directors may revoke the dissolution without
shareholder action.</para><para>(c)
After the revocation of dissolution is authorized, the corporation may revoke
the dissolution by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing articles
of revocation of dissolution, together with a copy of its articles of dissolution,
that set forth:</para><para>(1)
The name of the corporation;</para><para>(2)
The effective date of the dissolution that was revoked;</para>
<para>(3) The date that the revocation
of dissolution was authorized;</para><para>(4) If the corporation's board of directors, or incorporators,
revoked the dissolution, a statement to that effect;</para><para>(5) If the corporation's board of directors
revoked a dissolution authorized by the shareholders, a statement that revocation
was permitted by action by the board of directors alone pursuant to that authorization;
and</para><para>(6)
If shareholder action was required to revoke the dissolution, the information
required by subdivision (a)(3) of section 21-2,186.</para><para>(d) Revocation of dissolution is effective
upon the effective date of the articles of revocation of dissolution.</para>
<para>(e) When the revocation of
dissolution is effective, it relates back to and takes effect as of the effective
date of the dissolution and the corporation resumes carrying on its business
as if dissolution had never occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 187.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>