<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,110</statuteno><catchline>Subpart definitions.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 8.50) In sections
21-2,110 to 21-2,119:</para>
<para>(1) Corporation includes
any domestic or foreign predecessor entity of a corporation in a merger.</para>
<para>(2) Director or officer
means an individual who is or was a director or officer, respectively, of
a corporation or who, while a director or officer of the corporation, is or
was serving at the corporation's request as a director, officer, manager,
partner, trustee, employee, or agent of another entity or employee benefit
plan. A director or officer is considered to be serving an employee benefit
plan at the corporation's request if the individual's duties to the corporation
also impose duties on, or otherwise involve services by, the individual to
the plan or to participants in or beneficiaries of the plan. Director or officer
includes, unless the context requires otherwise, the estate or personal representative
of a director or officer.</para><para>(3)
Liability means the obligation to pay a judgment, settlement, penalty, fine,
including an excise tax assessed with respect to an employee benefit plan,
or reasonable expenses incurred with respect to a proceeding.</para>
<para>(4) Official capacity
means (i) when used with respect to a director, the office of director in
a corporation and (ii) when used with respect to an officer, as contemplated
in section 21-2,116, the office in a corporation held by the officer. Official
capacity does not include service for any other domestic or foreign corporation
or any partnership, joint venture, trust, employee benefit plan, or other
entity.</para><para>(5)
Party means an individual who was, is, or is threatened to be made, a defendant
or respondent in a proceeding.</para><para>(6) Proceeding means any threatened, pending, or completed
action, suit, or proceeding, whether civil, criminal, administrative, arbitrative,
or investigative and whether formal or informal.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 110.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>