<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,204</statuteno><catchline>Consequences of transacting business
without authority.</catchline><para>(MBCA
15.02) (a) A foreign corporation transacting business in this state without
a certificate of authority may not maintain a proceeding in any court in this
state until it obtains a certificate of authority.</para>
<para>(b) The successor to a foreign
corporation that transacted business in this state without a certificate of
authority and the assignee of a cause of action arising out of that business
may not maintain a proceeding based on that cause of action in any court in
this state until the foreign corporation or its successor obtains a certificate
of authority.</para><para>(c)
A court may stay a proceeding commenced by a foreign corporation, its successor,
or assignee until it determines whether the foreign corporation or its successor
requires a certificate of authority. If it so determines, the court may further
stay the proceeding until the foreign corporation or its successor obtains
the certificate.</para><para>(d)
A foreign corporation is liable for a civil penalty of five hundred dollars
for each day, but not to exceed a total of ten thousand dollars for each year,
it transacts business in this state without a certificate of authority. The
Attorney General may collect all penalties due under this subsection and shall
remit them to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article
VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(e) Notwithstanding subsections (a)
and (b) of this section, the failure of a foreign corporation to obtain a
certificate of authority does not impair the validity of its corporate acts
or prevent it from defending any proceeding in this state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 204.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>