<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-285" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>21-285</statuteno><catchline>Qualifications of directors.</catchline><para>(MBCA 8.02) (a) The articles of incorporation or bylaws may prescribe qualifications for directors or for nominees for directors. Qualifications must be reasonable as applied to the corporation and must be lawful.</para><para>(b) A requirement that is based on a past, current, or prospective action, or expression of an opinion, by a nominee or director that could limit the ability of a nominee or director to discharge his or her duties as a director is not a permissible qualification under this section. Notwithstanding the foregoing, qualifications may include not being or having been subject to specified criminal, civil, or regulatory sanctions or not having been removed as a director by judicial action or for cause.</para><para>(c) A director need not be a resident of this state or a shareholder of the corporation unless the articles of incorporation or bylaws so prescribe.</para><para>(d) A qualification for nomination for director prescribed before a person's nomination shall apply to such person at the time of nomination. A qualification for nomination for director prescribed after a person's nomination shall not apply to such person with respect to such nomination.</para><para>(e) A qualification for director prescribed before the start of a director's term may apply only at the time an individual becomes a director or may apply during a director's term. A qualification prescribed during a director's term shall not apply to that director before the end of that term.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB35, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>