<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,145" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,145</statuteno><catchline>Action on a plan of entity conversion.</catchline><para>(MBCA 9.52) In the case of an entity conversion of a domestic business corporation to a domestic or foreign unincorporated entity:</para><para>(1) The plan of entity conversion must be adopted by the board of directors.</para><para>(2) After adopting the plan of entity conversion, the board of directors must submit the plan to the shareholders for their approval. The board of directors must also transmit to the shareholders a recommendation that the shareholders approve the plan unless (i) the board of directors makes a determination that because of conflicts of interest or other special circumstances it should not make such a recommendation or (ii) section 21-2,101 applies. If subdivision (2)(i) or (ii) of this section applies, the board must transmit to the shareholders the basis for so proceeding.</para><para>(3) The board of directors may condition its submission of the plan of entity conversion to the shareholders on any basis.</para><para>(4) If the approval of the shareholders is to be given at a meeting, the corporation must notify each shareholder, whether or not entitled to vote, of the meeting of shareholders at which the plan of entity conversion is to be submitted for approval. The notice must state that the purpose, or one of the purposes, of the meeting is to consider the plan and must contain or be accompanied by a copy or summary of the plan. The notice shall include or be accompanied by a copy of the organic documents as they will be in effect immediately after the entity conversion.</para><para>(5) Unless the articles of incorporation, or the board of directors acting pursuant to subdivision (3) of this section, requires a greater vote or a greater number of votes to be present, approval of the plan of entity conversion requires the approval of each class or series of shares of the corporation voting as a separate voting group at a meeting at which a quorum of the voting group consisting of at least a majority of the votes entitled to be cast on the conversion by that voting group exists.</para><para>(6) If any provision of the articles of incorporation, bylaws, or an agreement to which any of the directors or shareholders are parties, adopted or entered into before January 1, 2017, applies to a merger of the corporation, other than a provision that limits or eliminates voting or appraisal rights, and the document does not refer to an entity conversion of the corporation, the provision shall be deemed to apply to an entity conversion of the corporation until such time as the provision is subsequently amended.</para><para>(7) If as a result of the conversion one or more shareholders of the corporation would become subject to owner liability for the debts, obligations, or liabilities of any other person or entity, approval of the plan of conversion shall require the signing, by each such shareholder, of a separate written consent to become subject to such owner liability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>