
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-121"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-121</statuteno><catchline>Delivery to and filing of records
by Secretary of State; effective time and date.</catchline><para>(RULLCA 205) (a) A record authorized or
required to be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing under the Nebraska
Uniform Limited Liability Company Act must be captioned to describe the record's
purpose, be in a medium permitted by the Secretary of State, and be delivered
to the Secretary of State. If the filing fees have been paid, unless the Secretary
of State determines that a record does not comply with the filing requirements
of the act, the Secretary of State shall file the record and:</para>
<para>(1) for a statement of
denial under section 21-128, send a copy of the filed statement and a receipt
for the fees to the person on whose behalf the statement was delivered for
filing and to the limited liability company; and</para><para>(2) for all other records, send
a copy of the filed record and a receipt for the fees to the person on whose
behalf the record was filed.</para><para>(b) Upon request and payment of the requisite fee,
the Secretary of State shall send to the requester a certified copy of a requested
record.</para><para>(c)
Except as otherwise provided in sections 21-115 and 21-122, a record delivered
to the Secretary of State for filing under the act may specify an effective
time and a delayed effective date. Subject to section 21-115, subdivision
(d)(1) of section 21-117, and section 21-122, a record filed by the Secretary
of State is effective:</para><para>(1)
if the record does not specify either an effective time or a delayed effective
date, on the date and at the time the record is filed as evidenced by the
Secretary of State's endorsement of the date and time on the record;</para>
<para>(2) if the record specifies
an effective time but not a delayed effective date, on the date the record
is filed at the time specified in the record;</para><para>(3) if the record specifies a delayed
effective date but not an effective time, at 12:01 a.m. on the earlier of:</para>
<para>(A) the specified date;
or</para><para>(B)
the ninetieth day after the record is filed; or</para><para>(4) if the record specifies an effective
time and a delayed effective date, at the specified time on the earlier of:</para>
<para>(A) the specified date;
or</para><para>(B)
the ninetieth day after the record is filed.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>