
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-534"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-534</statuteno><catchline>Application of section 21-523 after merger.</catchline><para>(a) A creditor’s right that existed under section 21-523 immediately before a merger under section 21-530 may be enforced after the merger in accordance with the following rules:</para><para>(1) A creditor’s right that existed immediately before the merger against the surviving company, a continuing protected series, or a relocated protected series continues without change after the merger.</para><para>(2) A creditor’s right that existed immediately before the merger against a nonsurviving company:</para><para>(A) may be asserted against an asset of the nonsurviving company which vested in the surviving company as a result of the merger; and</para><para>(B) does not otherwise change.</para><para>(3) Subject to subsection (b) of this section, the following rules apply:</para><para>(A) In addition to the remedy stated in subdivision (a)(1) of this section, a creditor with a right under section 21-523 which existed immediately before the merger against a nonsurviving company or a relocated protected series may assert the right against:</para><para>(i) an asset of the surviving company, other than an asset of the nonsurviving company which vested in the surviving company as a result of the merger;</para><para>(ii) an asset of a continuing protected series; or</para><para>(iii) an asset of a protected series established by the surviving company as a result of the merger;</para><para>(iv) if the creditor’s right was against an asset of the nonsurviving company, an asset of a relocated series; or</para><para>(v) if the creditor’s right was against an asset of a relocated protected series, an asset of another relocated protected series.</para><para>(B) In addition to the remedy stated in subdivision (a)(2) of this section, a creditor with a right that existed immediately before the merger against the surviving company or a continuing protected series may assert the right against:</para><para>(i) an asset of a relocated protected series; or</para><para>(ii) an asset of a nonsurviving company which vested in the surviving company as a result of the merger.</para><para>(b) For the purposes of subdivision (a)(3) of this section and subdivisions (b)(1)(A), (b)(2)(A), and (b)(3)(A) of section 21-523, the incurrence date is deemed to be the date on which the merger becomes effective.</para><para>(c) A merger under section 21-530 does not affect the manner in which section 21-523 applies to a liability incurred after the merger.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB78, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>