
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies"  statutenumber="21-2,227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,227</statuteno><catchline>Financial statements for shareholders.</catchline>
<para>(MBCA 16.20) (a) A corporation
shall deliver to its shareholders annual financial statements, which may be
consolidated or combined statements of the corporation and one or more of
its subsidiaries, as appropriate, that include a balance sheet as of the end
of the fiscal year, an income statement for that year, and a statement of
changes in shareholders' equity for the year unless that information appears
elsewhere in the financial statements. If financial statements are prepared
for the corporation on the basis of generally accepted accounting principles,
the annual financial statements must also be prepared on that basis.</para>
<para>(b) If the annual financial
statements are reported upon by a public accountant, the report must accompany
them. If not, the statements must be accompanied by a statement of the president
or the person responsible for the corporation's accounting records:</para>
<para>(1) Stating such person's
reasonable belief whether the statements were prepared on the basis of generally
accepted accounting principles and, if not, describing the basis of preparation;
and</para><para>(2)
Describing any respects in which the statements were not prepared on a basis
of accounting consistent with the statements prepared for the preceding year.</para>
<para>(c) Within one hundred twenty
days after the close of each fiscal year, the corporation shall send the annual
financial statements to each shareholder. Thereafter, on written request from
a shareholder to whom the statements were not sent, the corporation shall
send the shareholder the latest financial statements. A public corporation
may fulfill its responsibilities under this section by delivering the specified
financial statements or otherwise making them available in any manner permitted
by the applicable rules and regulations of the United States Securities and
Exchange Commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 227.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>