<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id426"><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-512"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-512</statuteno><catchline>Service of process, notice, demand, or other record.</catchline><para>(a) A protected series of a series limited liability company may be served with a process, notice, demand, or other record required or permitted by law by:</para><para>(1) serving the company;</para><para>(2) serving the registered agent of the protected series; or</para><para>(3) other means authorized by law of this state other than the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act.</para><para>(b) Service of a summons and complaint on a series limited liability company is notice to each protected series of the company of service of the summons and complaint and the contents of the complaint.</para><para>(c) Service of a summons and complaint on a protected series of a series limited liability company is notice to the company and any other protected series of the company of service of the summons and complaint and the contents of the complaint.</para><para>(d) Service of a summons and complaint on a foreign series limited liability company is notice to each foreign protected series of the foreign company of service of the summons and complaint and the contents of the complaint.</para><para>(e) Service of a summons and complaint on a foreign protected series of a foreign series limited liability company is notice to the foreign company and any other foreign protected series of the company of service of the summons and complaint and the contents of the complaint.</para><para>(f) Notice to a person under subsection (b), (c), (d), or (e) of this section is effective whether or not the summons and complaint identify the person if the summons and complaint name as a party and identify:</para><para>(1) the series limited liability company or a protected series of the company; or</para><para>(2) the foreign series limited liability company or a foreign protected series of the foreign company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>