<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2,120" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2,120</statuteno><catchline>Subpart definitions.</catchline><para>(MBCA 8.60) In sections 21-2,120 to 21-2,123:</para><para>(1) Director's conflicting interest transaction means a transaction effected or proposed to be effected by the corporation or by an entity controlled by the corporation:</para><para>(i) To which, at the relevant time, the director is a party;</para><para>(ii) Respecting which, at the relevant time, the director had knowledge and a material financial interest known to the director; or</para><para>(iii) Respecting which, at the relevant time, the director knew that a related person was a party or had a material financial interest.</para><para>(2) Control, including the term controlled by, means (i) having the power, directly or indirectly, to elect or remove a majority of the members of the board of directors or other governing body of an entity, whether through the ownership of voting shares or interests, by contract, or otherwise, or (ii) being subject to a majority of the risk of loss from the entity's activities or entitled to receive a majority of the entity's residual returns.</para><para>(3) Relevant time means (i) the time at which directors' action respecting the transaction is taken in compliance with section 21-2,122, or (ii) if the transaction is not brought before the board of directors of the corporation, or its committee, for action under section 21-2,122, at the time the corporation, or an entity controlled by the corporation, becomes legally obligated to consummate the transaction.</para><para>(4) Material financial interest means a financial interest in a transaction that would reasonably be expected to impair the objectivity of the director's judgment when participating in action on the authorization of the transaction.</para><para>(5) Related person means:</para><para>(i) The individual's spouse;</para><para>(ii) A child, stepchild, grandchild, parent, stepparent, grandparent, sibling, stepsibling, half-sibling, aunt, uncle, niece, or nephew, or spouse of any thereof, of the individual or of the individual's spouse;</para><para>(iii) A natural person living in the same home as the individual;</para><para>(iv) An entity, other than the corporation or an entity controlled by the corporation, controlled by the individual or any person specified in subdivisions (5)(i) through (iii) of this section;</para><para>(v) A domestic or foreign (A) business or nonprofit corporation, other than the corporation or an entity controlled by the corporation, of which the individual is a director, (B) unincorporated entity of which the individual is a general partner or a member of the governing body, or (C) individual, trust, or estate for whom or of which the individual is a trustee, guardian, personal representative, or like fiduciary; or</para><para>(vi) A person that is, or an entity that is controlled by, an employer of the individual.</para><para>(6) Fair to the corporation means, for purposes of subdivision (b)(3) of section 21-2,121, that the transaction as a whole was beneficial to the corporation, taking into appropriate account whether it was (i) fair in terms of the director's dealings with the corporation and (ii) comparable to what might have been obtainable in an arm's length transaction, given the consideration paid or received by the corporation.</para><para>(7) Required disclosure means disclosure of (i) the existence and nature of the director's conflicting interest and (ii) all facts known to the director respecting the subject matter of the transaction that a director free of such conflicting interest would reasonably believe to be material in deciding whether to proceed with the transaction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 120; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB35, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>