<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-525"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-525</statuteno><catchline>Winding up dissolved protected series.</catchline><para>(a) Subject to subsections (b) and (c) of this section and in accordance with section 21-508:</para><para>(1) a dissolved protected series shall wind up its activities and affairs in the same manner that a limited liability company winds up its activities and affairs under sections 21-147 to 21-154, subject to the same requirements and conditions and with the same effects; and</para><para>(2) judicial supervision or another judicial remedy is available in the winding up of the protected series to the same extent, in the same manner, under the same conditions, and with the same effects that apply under subsection (e) of section 21-148.</para><para>(b) When a protected series of a series limited liability company dissolves, the company shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing a statement of protected-series dissolution stating the name of the company and the protected series and that the protected series is dissolved. The filing of the statement by the Secretary of State has the same effect as the filing by the Secretary of State of a statement of dissolution under subdivision (d)(2)(A) of section 21-103.</para><para>(c) When a protected series of a series limited liability company has completed winding up, the company may deliver to the Secretary of State for filing a statement of designation cancellation stating the name of the company and the protected series and that the protected series is terminated. The filing of the statement by the Secretary of State has the same effect as the filing by the Secretary of State of a statement of termination under subdivision (d)(2)(B) of section 21-103.</para><para>(d) A series limited liability company has not completed its winding up until each of the protected series of the company has completed its winding up.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1121, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB78, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>