<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1732"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1732</statuteno><catchline>Director; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the Credit Union Act.</para><para>(2) The director may issue a cease and desist order when (a) the director has determined from competent and substantial evidence that a credit union is engaged in or has engaged in an unsafe or unsound practice or is violating or has violated a material provision of any law, rule, regulation, or any condition imposed in writing by the director or any written agreement made with the director or (b) the director has reasonable cause to believe a credit union is about to engage in an unsafe or unsound practice or is violating or has violated a material provision of any law, rule, regulation, or any condition imposed in writing by the director or any written agreement made with the director or the director has reasonable cause to believe a credit union is about to violate a material provision of any law, rule, regulation, or any condition imposed in writing by the director or any written agreement made with the director.</para><para>(3) The director may restrict the making of loans by a credit union and the withdrawal from and the deposit to share accounts of a credit union when he or she finds circumstances that make such restriction necessary for the protection of the shareholders.</para><para>(4) The director may suspend from office and prohibit from further participation in any manner in the conduct of the affairs of a credit union any official who has committed any violation of a law, rule, regulation, or cease and desist order, who has engaged in or participated in any unsafe or unsound practice in connection with a credit union, or who has committed or engaged in any act, omission, or practice which constitutes a breach of that person's fiduciary duty as an official, when the director has determined that such action or actions have resulted or will result in substantial financial loss or other damage that will seriously prejudice the interest of the credit union members.</para><para>(5) The director shall consider applications brought before the department pursuant to section 21-1725.01.</para><para>(6) The director may subpoena witnesses, compel their attendance, require the production of evidence, administer oaths, and examine any person under oath in connection with any subject relating to a duty upon or a power vested in the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 16. </para></source></law></legaldoc>