<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,173"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,173</statuteno><catchline>Notice of incorporation, amendment, merger, or dissolution; publication.</catchline><para>(a) Notice of incorporation, amendment, or merger of a domestic corporation subject to the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act shall be published for three successive weeks in some legal newspaper of general circulation in the county where the corporation's principal office or, if none in this state, its registered office is located.</para><para>A notice of incorporation shall show (1) the corporate name of the corporation, (2) whether the corporation is a public benefit, mutual benefit, or religious corporation, (3) the street address of the corporation's initial registered office and the name of its initial registered agent at that office, (4) the name and street address of each incorporator, and (5) whether or not the corporation will have members.</para><para>A brief resume of any amendment or merger of the corporation shall be published in the same manner for the same period of time as a notice of incorporation is required to be published.</para><para>(b) Notice of dissolution of a domestic corporation shall be published for three successive weeks in some legal newspaper of general circulation in the county where the corporation's principal office or, if none in this state, its registered office is located. A notice of dissolution shall show (1) the terms and conditions of such dissolution, (2) the names of the persons who are to wind up and liquidate its affairs and their official titles, and (3) a statement of assets and liabilities of the corporation.</para><para>(c) Proof of publication of any of the notices required to be published under this section shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. In the event any notice required to be given pursuant to this section is not given, but is subsequently published for the required time, and proof of the subsequent publication thereof is filed in the office of the Secretary of State, the acts of such corporation prior to, as well as after, such publication shall be valid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 173. </para></source></law></legaldoc>