<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,115</statuteno><catchline>Class voting by members on amendments.</catchline><para>(a) The members of a class in a public benefit corporation are entitled to vote as a class on a proposed amendment to the bylaws if the amendment would change the rights of that class as to voting in a manner different than such amendment affects another class or members of another class.</para><para>(b) The members of a class in a mutual benefit corporation are entitled to vote as a class on a proposed amendment to the bylaws if the amendment would:</para><para>(1) Affect the rights, privileges, preferences, restrictions, or conditions of that class as to voting, dissolution, redemption, or transfer of memberships in a manner different than such amendment would affect another class;</para><para>(2) Change the rights, privileges, preferences, restrictions, or conditions of that class as to voting, dissolution, redemption, or transfer by changing the rights, privileges, preferences, restrictions, or conditions of another class;</para><para>(3) Increase or decrease the number of memberships authorized for that class;</para><para>(4) Increase the number of memberships authorized for another class;</para><para>(5) Effect an exchange, reclassification, or termination of all or part of the memberships of that class; or</para><para>(6) Authorize a new class of memberships.</para><para>(c) The members of a class of a religious corporation are entitled to vote as a class on a proposed amendment to the bylaws only if a class vote is provided for in the articles or bylaws.</para><para>(d) If a class is to be divided into two or more classes as a result of an amendment to the bylaws, the amendment must be approved by the members of each class that would be created by the amendment; and</para><para>(e) If a class vote is required to approve an amendment to the bylaws, the amendment must be approved by the members of the class by two-thirds of the votes cast by the class or a majority of the voting power of the class, whichever is less.</para><para>(f) A class of members is entitled to the voting rights granted by this section although the articles and bylaws provide that the class may not vote on the proposed amendment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 115. </para></source></law></legaldoc>