<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1955"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1955</statuteno><catchline>Notice of meeting.</catchline><para>(a) A corporation shall give notice consistent with its bylaws of meetings of members in a fair and reasonable manner.</para><para>(b) Any notice that conforms to the requirements of subsection (c) of this section is fair and reasonable, but other means of giving notice may also be fair and reasonable when all the circumstances are considered. Notice of matters referred to in subdivision (c)(2) of this section, however, must be given as provided in subsection (c) of this section.</para><para>(c) Notice is fair and reasonable if:</para><para>(1) The corporation notifies its members of the place, date, and time of each annual, regular, and special meeting of members no fewer than ten (or if notice is mailed by other than first-class or registered mail, thirty) nor more than sixty days before the meeting date;</para><para>(2) Notice of an annual or regular meeting includes a description of any matter or matters that must be approved by the members under section 21-1987, 21-19,102, 21-19,107, 21-19,114, 21-19,121, 21-19,126, 21-19,129, or 21-19,130; and</para><para>(3) Notice of a special meeting includes a description of the matter or matters for which the meeting is called.</para><para>(d) Unless the bylaws require otherwise, if an annual, regular, or special meeting of members is adjourned to a different date, time, or place, notice need not be given of the new date, time, or place, if the new date, time or place is announced at the meeting before adjournment. If a new record date for the adjourned meeting is or must be fixed under section 21-1957, however, notice of the adjourned meeting must be given under this section to the members of record as of the new record date.</para><para>(e) When giving notice of an annual, regular, or special meeting of members, a corporation shall give notice of a matter a member intends to raise at the meeting if: (1) Requested in writing to do so by a person entitled to call a special meeting; and (2) the request is received by the secretary or president of the corporation at least ten days before the corporation gives notice of the meeting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 55. </para></source></law></legaldoc>