<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1933"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1933</statuteno><catchline>Registered name.</catchline><para>(a)
A foreign corporation may register its corporate name, or its corporate name
with any change required by section 21-19,151, if the name is not the same
as or deceptively similar to, upon the records of the Secretary of State:</para>
<para>(1) The corporate name of a nonprofit or business corporation incorporated
or authorized to do business in this state;</para>
<para>(2) A corporate name reserved under section 21-231 or 21-1932 or registered under this section;
and</para>
<para>(3) Any other business entity name registered or filed with the Secretary
of State pursuant to Nebraska law.</para>
<para>(b) A foreign corporation registers its corporate name, or its corporate
name with any change required by section 21-19,151, by delivering to the Secretary
of State an application:</para>
<para>(1) Setting forth its corporate name, or its corporate name with any
change required by section 21-19,151, the state or country and date of its
incorporation, and a brief description of the nature of the activities in
which it is engaged; and</para>
<para>(2) Accompanied by a certificate of existence (or a document of similar
import) from the state or country of incorporation. Such certificate or document
shall not bear a date of more than sixty days prior to the date the application
is filed in this state.</para>
<para>(c) The corporate name is registered for the applicant's exclusive use
upon the effective date of the application.</para>
<para>(d) A foreign corporation whose registration is effective may renew
it for successive years by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing
a renewal application, which complies with the requirements of subsection
(b) of this section, between October 1 and December 31 of the preceding year.
The renewal application renews the registration for the following calendar
year.</para>
<para>(e) A foreign corporation whose registration is effective may thereafter
qualify as a foreign corporation under that name or consent in writing to
the use of that name by a corporation or other business entity thereafter
incorporated under the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act or authorized to
transact business in this state or by another foreign corporation or business
entity thereafter authorized to transact business in this state. The registration
terminates when the domestic corporation is incorporated or the foreign corporation
or business entity qualifies or consents to the qualification of another foreign
corporation or business entity under the registered name.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 44, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 464, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 264.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>