<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1721"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1721</statuteno><catchline>Risk assets, defined.</catchline><para>Risk assets shall mean all assets except the following:</para><para>(1) Cash on hand;</para><para>(2) Deposits or shares in federally insured or state-insured banks, savings and loan associations, and credit unions that have a remaining maturity of five years or less;</para><para>(3) Assets that have a remaining maturity of five years or less and which are insured by, fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by, or due from the United States Government, its agencies, the Federal National Mortgage Association, the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation, or the Government National Mortgage Association. Collateralized mortgage obligations that are comprised of government-guaranteed mortgage loans shall be included in this asset category;</para><para>(4) Loans to other credit unions that have a remaining maturity of five years or less;</para><para>(5) Student loans insured under Title IV, Part B, of the federal Higher Education Act of 1965, 20 U.S.C. 1071 et seq. or similar state insurance programs that have a remaining maturity of five years or less;</para><para>(6) Loans that have a remaining maturity of five years or less and are fully insured or guaranteed by the federal government, a state government, or any agency thereof;</para><para>(7) Share accounts or deposit accounts in a corporate central credit union that have a remaining maturity of five years or less or, if the maturity is greater than five years, an asset that is being carried on the credit union's records at the lower of cost or market value or is being marked to market value monthly;</para><para>(8) Common trust investments, including mutual funds, which deal exclusively in investments authorized by the Credit Union Act or the Federal Credit Union Act that are either carried on the credit union's records at the lower of cost or market value or are being marked to market value monthly;</para><para>(9) Prepaid expenses;</para><para>(10) Accrued interest on non risk investments;</para><para>(11) Loans fully secured by a pledge of share accounts in the lending credit union which are equal to and maintained to at least the amount of each loan outstanding;</para><para>(12) Loans which are purchased from liquidating credit unions and guaranteed by the National Credit Union Administration;</para><para>(13) National Credit Union Share Insurance Fund Guaranty Accounts established by the National Credit Union Administration pursuant to 12 U.S.C. 1783 of the Federal Credit Union Act;</para><para>(14) Investments in shares of the National Credit Union Administration Central Liquidity Facility, 12 U.S.C. 1795;</para><para>(15) Assets included in subdivisions (2) through (7) of this section with maturities greater than five years if each asset is being carried on the credit union's records at the lower of cost or market value or is being marked to market value monthly;</para><para>(16) Assets included in subdivisions (2) through (7) of this section with remaining maturities greater than five years if each asset meets the following criteria, irrespective of whether or not each asset is being carried on the credit union's records at the lower of cost or market value or is being marked to market value monthly:</para><para>(a) The interest rate of the asset is reset at least annually;</para><para>(b) The interest rate of the asset is less than the maximum allowable interest rate for the asset on the date of the required reserve transfer; and</para><para>(c) The interest rate of the asset varies directly, not inversely, with the index upon which it is based and is not reset as a multiple of the change in the related index;</para><para>(17) Fixed assets; and</para><para>(18) A deposit in the National Credit Union Share Insurance Fund, 12 U.S.C. 1783, representing a federally insured credit union's capitalization account balance of one percent of insured shares.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 21. </para></source></law></legaldoc>