<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-17,111"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-17,111</statuteno><catchline>Conversion from state to federal credit union.</catchline><para>(1) Any credit union organized under the Credit Union Act may, with the approval of the department and with the approval of a majority of the credit union members attending an annual or special meeting of the credit union, be converted into a federal credit union. The conversion shall not release the state-organized credit union from its obligations to pay or discharge all liabilities created by law or incurred by it before the conversion, from any tax imposed by the laws of this state up to the day of the conversion in proportion to the time which has elapsed since the last preceding payment on such obligations or liabilities, or from any assessment, penalty, or forfeiture imposed or incurred under the laws of this state up to the date of the conversion. Conversion shall be made pursuant to a conversion plan approved by the department and shall not be made (a) to defeat or defraud any of the creditors of the credit union or (b) to avoid the requirements of any law of this state designed to protect consumers. The conversion plan shall address required notices and disclosures of information concerning advantages and disadvantages to the credit union and its members of the proposed conversion. Certified copies of all proceedings had by the board of directors and by the members of the credit union shall be filed by the board of directors with the department, and in addition, the credit union shall furnish to the department a certified copy of consent or approval of the National Credit Union Administration if such consent is required by the laws of the United States. Two copies of the proceedings shall be filed with the department. The department shall certify and forward by registered mail one copy of the proceedings to the county clerk of the county in which the credit union is located.</para><para>(2) When conversion becomes effective, all property of the credit union, including all rights, title, and interest in and to all kinds of property, whether real, personal, or mixed, and things in action, and every right, privilege, interest, and asset of any conceivable value or benefit then existing, belonging, or pertaining to it, or which would inure to it, shall immediately by act of law and without any conveyance or transfer, and without any further act or deed, be vested in and remain the property of the converted credit union, which shall have, hold, and enjoy the property in its own right as fully and to the same extent as the property was possessed, held, and enjoyed prior to the conversion. The converted credit union shall be deemed to be a continuation of the same entity. All the rights, obligations, and relations of the credit union to or in respect to any person, estate, creditor, member, trust, trustee, or beneficiary of any trust or fiduciary function shall remain unimpaired. The credit union shall continue to hold all the rights, obligations, relations, and trusts, and the duties and liabilities connected therewith, and shall execute and perform every trust and relation in the same manner as if the credit union had not converted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 111. </para></source></law></legaldoc>