
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1905"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1905</statuteno><catchline>Fees.</catchline><para>(a) The Secretary of State shall collect the following fees when the documents described in this subsection are delivered for filing:</para><para>(1)(i) Articles of incorporation or (ii) documents relating to domestication:</para><para>(A) If the filing is submitted in writing, the fee shall be $30; and</para><para>(B) If the filing is submitted electronically pursuant to section 84-511, the fee shall be $25;</para><para>(2) Agent's statement of change of registered office for each affected corporation...$25.00 (not to exceed a total of $1,000)</para><para>(3) Agent's statement of resignation...no fee</para><para>(4) Certificate of administrative dissolution...no fee</para><para>(5) Application for reinstatement more than five years after the effective date of an administrative dissolution or administrative revocation...$500.00</para><para>(6) Certificate of reinstatement...no fee</para><para>(7) Certificate of judicial dissolution...no fee</para><para>(8) Certificate of authority:</para><para>(i) If the filing is submitted in writing, the fee shall be $30; and</para><para>(ii) If the filing is submitted electronically pursuant to section 84-511, the fee shall be $25;</para><para>(9) Certificate of revocation of authority to transact business...no fee</para><para>(10) Application for certificate of good standing...$10.00</para><para>(11) Any other document required or permitted to be filed by the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act:</para><para>(i) If the filing is submitted in writing, the fee shall be $30; and</para><para>(ii) If the filing is submitted electronically pursuant to section 84-511, the fee shall be $25.</para><para>(b) The Secretary of State shall collect the following fees for copying and certifying the copy of any filed document relating to a domestic or foreign corporation:</para><para>(1) $1.00 per page; and</para><para>(2) $10.00 for the certificate.</para><para>(c) All fees set forth in this section shall be collected by the Secretary of State and remitted to the State Treasurer and credited sixty percent to the General Fund and forty percent to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB907, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB749, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>