<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-17,109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>21-17,109</statuteno><catchline>Merger or consolidation.</catchline><para>(1) Any credit union organized under the Credit Union Act may, with the approval of the department, merge or consolidate with one or more other credit unions organized under the act or under the laws of the United States, if the credit unions merging or consolidating possess coinciding common bonds of association.</para><para>(2) When two or more credit unions merge or consolidate, one shall be designated as the continuing credit union or a totally new credit union shall be organized. If the latter procedure is followed, the new credit union shall be organized under the Credit Union Act or under the laws of the United States. All participating credit unions other than the continuing or new credit union shall be designated as merging credit unions.</para><para>(3) Any merger or consolidation of credit unions shall be done according to a plan of merger or consolidation. After approval by the boards of directors of all participating credit unions, the plan shall be submitted to the department for preliminary approval. If the plan includes the organization of a new credit union, all documents required pursuant to section 21-1724 shall be submitted as a part of the plan. In addition, each participating credit union shall submit the following information:</para><para>(a) The time and place of the meeting of the boards of directors at which the plan of merger or consolidation was agreed upon;</para><para>(b) The vote of the directors in favor of the adoption of the plan; and</para><para>(c) A copy of a resolution or other action by which the plan was agreed upon.</para><para>The department shall grant preliminary approval if the plan has been approved properly by the boards of directors and if the documentation required to organize a new credit union, if any, complies with section 21-1724. The director, in his or her discretion, may order a hearing be held if he or she determines that the condition of the acquiring credit union warrants a hearing or that the plan of merger would be unfair to the merging credit union.</para><para>(4) After the department grants preliminary approval, each merging credit union, except the continuing credit union, shall, unless waived by the department, conduct a membership vote on its participation in the plan. The vote shall be conducted either at a special meeting called for that purpose or by mail ballot. If a majority of the members voting approve the plan, the credit union shall submit a record of that fact to the department indicating the vote by which the members approved the plan and either the time and place of the membership meeting or the mailing date and closing date of the mail ballot.</para><para>(5) The department may waive any voting requirements described in the Credit Union Act for any credit union upon the determination that it is in the best interests of the membership or that the credit union is insolvent or in imminent danger of becoming insolvent.</para><para>(6) The director shall grant final approval of the plan of merger or consolidation after determining that the requirements of subsections (1) through (4) of this section have been met in the case of each merging credit union. If the plan of merger or consolidation includes the organization of a new credit union, the department must approve the organization of the new credit union under section 21-1724 as part of the approval of the plan of merger or consolidation. The department shall notify all participating credit unions of the plan.</para><para>(7) Upon final approval of the plan by the department, all property, property rights, and members' interests in each merging credit union shall vest in the continuing or new credit union as applicable without deed, obligations, and other instruments of transfer, and all debts, obligations, and liabilities of each merging credit union shall be deemed to have been assumed by the continuing or new credit union. The rights and privileges of the members of each participating credit union shall remain intact. If a person is a member of more than one of the participating credit unions, the person shall be entitled to only a single set of membership rights in the continuing or new credit union.</para><para>(8) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the department may authorize a merger or consolidation of a credit union which is insolvent or which is in danger of insolvency with any other credit union or may authorize a credit union to purchase any of the assets of or assume any of the liabilities of any other credit union which is insolvent or which is in danger of insolvency, if the department is satisfied that:</para><para>(a) An emergency requiring expeditious action exists with respect to such credit union;</para><para>(b) Other alternatives for such credit union are not reasonably available; and</para><para>(c) The public interest would best be served by the approval of such merger, consolidation, purchase, or assumption.</para><para>(9) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the director may authorize an institution, the deposits or accounts of which are insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or any derivative thereof, to purchase any assets of or assume any liabilities of a credit union which is insolvent or in danger of insolvency, except that prior to exercising this authority the director shall attempt to effect a merger or consolidation with, or purchase or assumption by, another credit union as provided in subsection (8) of this section.</para><para>(10) For purposes of the authority contained in subsection (9) of this section, insured share accounts of each credit union may, upon consummation of the purchase or assumption, be converted to insured deposits or other comparable accounts in the acquiring institution, and the department and the National Credit Union Share Insurance Fund shall be absolved of any liability to the credit union's members with respect to those accounts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 72. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>