<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1740" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1740</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Credit union; powers.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A credit union shall have all the powers specified in this section and all the powers specified by any other provision of the Credit Union Act.</para><para id="id00">(2) A credit union may make contracts.</para><para id="id00">(3) A credit union may sue and be sued.</para><para id="id00">(4) A credit union may adopt a seal and alter the same.</para><para id="id00">(5) A credit union may individually or jointly with other credit unions purchase, lease, or otherwise acquire and hold tangible personal property necessary or incidental to its operations. A credit union shall depreciate or appreciate such personal property in the manner and at the rates the director may prescribe by rule or order from time to time.</para><para id="id00">(6) A credit union may, in whole or part, sell, lease, assign, pledge, hypothecate, or otherwise dispose of its tangible personal property, including such property obtained as a result of defaults under obligations owing to it.</para><para id="id00">(7) A credit union may incur and pay necessary and incidental operating expenses.</para><para id="id00">(8) A credit union may receive, from a member, from another credit union, from an officer, or from an employee, payments representing equity on (a) share accounts which may be issued at varying dividend rates, (b) share account certificates which may be issued at varying dividend rates and maturities, and (c) share draft accounts, subject to such terms, rates, and conditions as may be established by the board of directors, within limitations prescribed by the department. A credit union shall provide for the transfer and withdrawal of funds from accounts by the means and through the payment system that the board of directors determines best serves the convenience and needs of members.</para><para id="id00">(9) A credit union may lend its funds to its members as provided in the Credit Union Act.</para><para id="id00">(10) A credit union may borrow from any source in an amount not exceeding fifty percent of its capital and deposits.</para><para id="id00">(11) A credit union may provide debt counseling and other financial counseling services to its members.</para><para id="id00">(12) A credit union may, in whole or in part, discount, sell, assign, pledge, hypothecate, or otherwise dispose of its intangible personal property. The approval of the director shall be required before a credit union may discount, sell, assign, pledge, hypothecate, or otherwise dispose of twenty percent or more of its intangible personal property within one month unless the credit union is in liquidation.</para><para id="id00">(13) A credit union may purchase any of the assets of another financial institution or assume any of the liabilities of another financial institution with the approval of the director. A credit union may also purchase any of the assets of a financial institution which is in liquidation or receivership.</para><para id="id00">(14) A credit union may make deposits in or loans to banks, savings banks, savings and loan associations, and trust companies, purchase shares in mutual savings and loan associations, and make deposits in or loans to or purchase shares of other credit unions, including corporate central credit unions, if such institutions are either insured by an agency of the federal government or are eligible under the laws of the United States to apply for such insurance and invest funds as otherwise provided in sections 21-17,100 to 21-17,102.</para><para id="id00">(15) A credit union may make deposits in, make loans to, or purchase shares of any federal reserve bank or central liquidity facility established under state or federal law.</para><para id="id00">(16) A credit union may hold membership in associations and organizations controlled by or fostering the interests of credit unions, including a central liquidity facility organized under state or federal law.</para><para id="id00">(17) A credit union may engage in activities and programs of the federal government, any state, or any agency or political subdivision thereof when approved by the board of directors and not inconsistent with the Credit Union Act.</para><para id="id00">(18) A credit union may receive funds either as shares or deposits from other credit unions.</para><para id="id00">(19) A credit union may lease tangible personal property to its members if the credit union acquires no interest in the property prior to its selection by the member.</para><para id="id00">(20) A credit union may, in whole or in part, purchase, sell, pledge, discount, or otherwise acquire and dispose of obligations of its members in accordance with the rules and regulations promulgated by the director. This subsection shall not apply to participation loans originated pursuant to section 21-1794.</para><para id="id00">(21) A credit union may, at its own expense, purchase insurance for its members in connection with its members' shares, loans, and other accounts.</para><para id="id00">(22) A credit union may establish, operate, participate in, and hold membership in systems that allow the transfer of credit union funds and funds of its members by electronic or other means, including, but not limited to, clearinghouse associations, data processing and other electronic networks, the federal reserve system, or any other government payment or liquidity program.</para><para id="id00">(23) A credit union may issue credit cards and debit cards to allow members to obtain access to their shares and extensions of credit if such issuance is not inconsistent with the rules of the department. The department may by rule or regulation allow the use of devices similar to credit cards and debit cards to allow members to access their shares and extensions of credit.</para><para id="id00">(24) A credit union may service the loans it sells, in whole or in part, to a third party.</para><para id="id00">(25) In addition to loan and investment powers otherwise authorized by the Credit Union Act, a credit union may organize, invest in, and make loans to corporations or other organizations (a) which engage in activities incidental to the conduct of a credit union or in activities which further or facilitate the purposes of a credit union or (b) which furnish services to credit unions. The director shall determine by rule, regulation, or order the activities and services which fall within the meaning of this subsection. A credit union shall notify the director of any such investment or loan if it would cause the aggregate of such investments and loans to exceed two percent of the credit union's capital and deposits. Such investments and loans may not, in the aggregate, exceed five percent of the capital and deposits of the credit union.</para><para id="id00">(26) A credit union may purchase, lease, construct, or otherwise acquire and hold land and buildings for the purpose of providing adequate facilities for the transaction of present and potential future business. A credit union may use such land and buildings for the principal office functions, service facilities, and any other activity in which it engages. A credit union may rent excess space as a source of income. A credit union shall depreciate or appreciate such buildings owned by it in the manner and at the rates the director may prescribe by rule, regulation, or order from time to time. A credit union's investment and contractual obligations, direct, indirect, or contingent, in land and buildings under this subsection shall not exceed seven percent of its capital and deposits without prior approval of the director. This subsection shall not affect the legality of investments in land and buildings made prior to October 1, 1996.</para><para id="id00">(27) A credit union may, in whole or in part, sell, lease, assign, mortgage, pledge, hypothecate, or otherwise dispose of its land and buildings, including land and buildings obtained as a result of defaults under obligations owing to it.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB375, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>