<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1986"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1986</statuteno><catchline>General standards for directors.</catchline><para>(a) A director shall discharge his or her duties as a director, including his or her duties as a member of a committee:</para><para>(1) In good faith;</para><para>(2) With the care an ordinarily prudent person in a like position would exercise under similar circumstances; and</para><para>(3) In a manner he or she reasonably believes to be in the best interests of the corporation.</para><para>(b) In discharging his or her duties, a director is entitled to rely on information, opinions, reports, or statements, including financial statements and other financial data, if prepared or presented by:</para><para>(1) One or more officers or employees of the corporation whom the director reasonably believes to be reliable and competent in the matters presented;</para><para>(2) Legal counsel, public accountants, or other persons as to matters the director reasonably believes are within the person's professional or expert competence;</para><para>(3) A committee of the board of which the director is not a member as to matters within its jurisdiction if the director reasonably believes the committee merits confidence; or</para><para>(4) In the case of religious corporations, religious authorities and ministers, priests, rabbis, or other persons whose position or duties in the religious organization the director believes justify reliance and confidence and whom the director believes to be reliable and competent in the matters presented.</para><para>(c) A director is not acting in good faith if the director has knowledge concerning the matter in question that makes reliance otherwise permitted by subsection (b) of this section unwarranted.</para><para>(d) A director is not liable to the corporation, any member, or any other person for any action taken or not taken as a director, if the director acted in compliance with this section.</para><para>(e) A director shall not be deemed to be a trustee with respect to the corporation or with respect to any property held or administered by the corporation, including without limit, property that may be subject to restrictions imposed by the donor or transferor of such property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 86. </para></source></law></legaldoc>