<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1735"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1735</statuteno><catchline>National Credit Union Administration Board; appointment as receiver or liquidator.</catchline><para>(1) The National Credit Union Administration Board, as created by 12 U.S.C. 1752(a), shall be authorized to accept the appointment by the director as receiver or liquidator, without bond, of any credit union in the possession of the department and whose shares are to any extent insured by the National Credit Union Administration under section 201 et seq. of the Federal Credit Union Act, 12 U.S.C. 1781 et seq. Any credit union which fails to maintain such insurance may be voluntarily dissolved or liquidated by the board of directors of such credit union or may be taken in possession by the director and involuntarily liquidated as in the case of insolvency.</para><para>(2) Whenever the director takes possession of a credit union subject to the jurisdiction of the department, the director may tender to the National Credit Union Administration Board the appointment as receiver or liquidator of such credit union. If the board accepts such appointment, it shall have and possess all the powers and privileges provided by the laws of this state with respect to a receiver or liquidator of a credit union and its shareholders and other creditors and shall be subject to all the duties of such receiver or liquidator, except insofar as such powers, privileges, or duties are in conflict with the Federal Credit Union Act, 12 U.S.C. 1781 et seq.</para><para>(3) Whenever the National Credit Union Administration Board has been appointed as receiver or liquidator of a credit union pursuant to this section, it shall be subrogated to all the rights and interests against such credit union of all the shareholders or other creditors of the credit union to the full extent of such rights and interests in the credit union. The rights of shareholders or other creditors of the credit union shall be determined in accordance with the laws of this state.</para><para>(4) Upon acceptance by the National Credit Union Administration Board of the appointment as receiver or liquidator of a credit union from the director and subject to the approval of the district court of the judicial district in which the credit union has its principal place of business, the possession of and title to all the assets, business, and property of every kind and nature of the credit union shall pass to and vest in the board without the execution of any instrument of conveyance, assignment, transfer, or endorsement.</para><para>(5) In addition to its powers and duties as receiver or liquidator, the National Credit Union Administration Board shall have the right and authority upon the order of any court of record of competent jurisdiction to enforce the individual liability of the members of the board of directors of any credit union.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 35. </para></source></law></legaldoc>