<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1915"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1915</statuteno><catchline>Notice.</catchline><para>(a) Notice
may be oral or written.</para>
<para>(b) Notice may be communicated in person, by mail or other method of delivery, or by
telephone or other electronic means. If these forms of personal
notice are impracticable, notice may be communicated by a newspaper of general
circulation in the area where published, by radio, by television, or by other
form of public broadcast communication.</para>
<para>(c) Oral notice is effective when communicated if communicated in a
comprehensible manner.</para>
<para>(d) Written notice, if in a comprehensible form, is effective at the
earliest of the following:</para>
<para>(1) When received;</para>
<para>(2) Five days after its deposit in the United States mail, as evidenced
by the postmark, if mailed correctly addressed and with first-class postage
affixed;</para>
<para>(3) On the date shown on the return receipt, if sent by registered or
certified mail, return receipt requested, and the receipt is signed by or
on behalf of the addressee; or</para>
<para>(4) Thirty days after its deposit in the United States mail, as evidenced
by the postmark, if mailed correctly addressed and with other than first class,
registered or certified postage affixed.</para>
<para>(e) Written notice is correctly addressed to a member of a domestic
or foreign corporation if addressed to the member's address shown in the corporation's
current list of members.</para>
<para>(f) A written notice or report delivered as part of a newsletter, magazine,
or other publication regularly sent to members shall constitute a written
notice or report (1) if
addressed or delivered to the member's address shown in the corporation's
current list of members, (2) in the case of members
who are residents of the same household and who have the same address in the
corporation's current list of members, if addressed or delivered to one of
such members at the address appearing on the current list of members, or (3) if electronically transmitted
to a member in a manner authorized by the member.</para>
<para>(g) Written notice is correctly addressed to a domestic or foreign corporation
(authorized to transact business in this state), other than in its capacity
as a member, if addressed to its registered agent or to its secretary at its
principal office shown in its most recent biennial report or, in the case
of a foreign corporation that has not yet delivered a biennial report, in
its application for a certificate of authority.</para>
<para>(h) If any other provision of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act
prescribes notice requirements for particular circumstances, such as subsection
(b) of section 21-1955, those requirements govern. If articles or bylaws prescribe
notice requirements not inconsistent with this section or other provisions
of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, those requirements govern.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB890, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>