<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1977"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1977</statuteno><catchline>Removal of directors by judicial proceeding.</catchline><para>(a) The district court of the county where a corporation's principal office (or, if none in this state, its registered office) is located may remove any director of the corporation from office in a proceeding commenced either by the corporation, its members holding at least ten percent of the voting power of any class, or the Attorney General in the case of a public benefit corporation, if it finds that (1)(i) the director engaged in fraudulent or dishonest conduct, (ii) the director engaged in a gross abuse of authority or discretion, with respect to the corporation, or (iii) a final judgment has been entered finding that the director has violated a duty set forth in sections 21-1986 to 21-1989 and (2) removal is in the best interest of the corporation.</para><para>(b) The district court may bar the removed director from serving on the board for a period prescribed by the court.</para><para>(c) If members or the Attorney General commence a proceeding under subsection (a) of this section the corporation shall be made a party defendant.</para><para>(d) If a public benefit corporation or its members commence a proceeding under subsection (a) of this section, they shall give the Attorney General written notice of the proceeding.</para><para>(e) The articles or bylaws of a religious corporation may limit or prohibit the application of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 77. </para></source><annotation><para>Effective notice to the Attorney General is an essential prerequisite to proceeding in any action involving a public benefit corporation for which such notice is required. Hitchcock Foundation v. Kountze, 272 Neb. 251, 720 N.W.2d 31 (2006).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>