<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,172"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,172</statuteno><catchline>Biennial report; contents.</catchline>
<para>(a) Commencing in 1999 and each odd-numbered year thereafter, each domestic
corporation, and each foreign corporation authorized to transact business
in this state, shall deliver to the Secretary of State a biennial report on
a form prescribed and furnished by the Secretary of State that sets forth:</para>
<para>(1) The name of the corporation and the state or country under whose
law it is incorporated;</para>
<para>(2) The street address of its registered office and the name of its
current registered agent at the office in this state. A post office box number
may be provided in addition to the street address;</para>
<para>(3) The street address of its principal office;</para>
<para>(4) The names and business or residence addresses of its directors and
principal officers;</para>
<para>(5) A brief description of the nature of its activities;</para>
<para>(6) Whether or not it has members;</para>
<para>(7) If it is a domestic corporation, whether it is a public benefit,
mutual benefit, or religious corporation; and</para>
<para>(8) If it is a foreign corporation, whether it would be a public benefit,
mutual benefit, or religious corporation had it been incorporated in this
state.</para>
<para>(b) The information in the biennial report must be current on the date
the biennial report is executed on behalf of the corporation.</para>
<para>(c) The first biennial report must be delivered to the Secretary of
State between January 1 and April 1 of the odd-numbered year following the
calendar year in which a domestic corporation was incorporated or a foreign
corporation was authorized to transact business. Subsequent biennial reports
must be delivered to the Secretary of State between January 1 and April 1
of the following odd-numbered years. For purposes of the Nebraska Nonprofit
Corporation Act, the biennial report is due on April 1 of the odd-numbered
year in which it must be delivered to the Secretary of State as required by
this section.</para>
<para>(d) If a biennial report does not contain the information required by
this section, the Secretary of State shall promptly notify the reporting domestic
or foreign corporation in writing and return the report to it for correction.
If the report is corrected to contain the information required by this section
and delivered to the Secretary of State within thirty days after the effective
date of notice, it is deemed to be timely filed.</para>
<para>(e) Upon the delivery of the biennial report as provided in this section,
the Secretary of State shall charge and collect a fee as prescribed in section
21-1905. For purposes of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, the fee is
due on April 1 of the odd-numbered year in which the biennial report must
be delivered to the Secretary of State as required by this section.</para>
<para>(f) Biennial reports shall be filed in 1997 pursuant to sections 21-1981
and 21-1982 (Reissue 1991) as if such sections had not been repealed by Laws
1996, LB 681. Fees, including penalties, due or delinquent prior to 1999 shall
be paid pursuant to section 21-1982 (Reissue 1991) as if such section had
not been repealed by Laws 1996, LB 681.</para>
<para>(g) A correction or an
amendment to the biennial report may be delivered to the Secretary of State
for filing at any time.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 172; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB774, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>