<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1975"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1975</statuteno><catchline>Removal of directors elected by members or directors.</catchline><para>(a) The members may remove one or more directors elected by them without cause.</para><para>(b) If a director is elected by a class, chapter, or other organizational unit or by region or other geographic grouping, the director may be removed only by the members of that class, chapter, unit, or grouping.</para><para>(c) Except as provided in subsection (i) of this section, a director may be removed under subsection (a) or (b) of this section only if the number of votes cast to remove the director would be sufficient to elect the director at a meeting to elect directors.</para><para>(d) If cumulative voting is authorized, a director may not be removed if the number of votes (or if the director was elected by a class, chapter, unit, or grouping of members, the number of votes of that class, chapter, unit, or grouping) sufficient to elect the director under cumulative voting is voted against the director's removal.</para><para>(e) A director elected by members may be removed by the members only at a meeting called for the purpose of removing the director. The meeting notice must state that the purpose, or one of the purposes, of the meeting is removal of the director.</para><para>(f) In computing whether a director is protected from removal under subsections (b) through (d) of this section, it should be assumed that the votes against removal are cast in an election for the number of directors of the class to which the director to be removed belonged on the date of that director's election.</para><para>(g) An entire board of directors may be removed under subsections (a) through (e) of this section.</para><para>(h) A director elected by the board may be removed without cause by the vote of two-thirds of the directors then in office or such greater number as is set forth in the articles or bylaws. A director elected by the board to fill the vacancy of a director elected by the members may be removed without cause by the members, but not the board.</para><para>(i) If, at the beginning of a director's term on the board, the articles or bylaws provide that the director may be removed for missing a specified number of board meetings, the board may remove the director for failing to attend the specified number of meetings. The director may be removed only if a majority of the directors then in office vote for the removal.</para><para>(j) The articles or bylaws of a religious corporation may:</para><para>(1) Limit the application of this section; and</para><para>(2) Set forth the vote and procedures by which the board or any person may remove with or without cause a director elected by the members or the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 75. </para></source></law></legaldoc>