<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1727"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1727</statuteno><catchline>Articles and bylaws; amendments.</catchline><para>(1) The articles of association may be amended at any regular or special meeting at which a quorum of the members as provided in the bylaws is present if the notice of the meeting contained a copy of the proposed amendment. An amendment shall not become effective until it has been filed with and approved in writing by the department and the fee prescribed by section 8-602 has been paid. One copy of an amendment or amendments to the articles of association shall be filed in the office of the county clerk of the county where the credit union has its principal place of business, for which a fee of fifty cents shall be charged.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, the bylaws may be amended at any regular or special meeting of the board of directors by a majority of the total directors if the notice of the meeting contained a copy of the proposed amendment. An amendment shall not become effective until it has been filed with and approved in writing by the department and the fee prescribed by section 8-602 has been paid.</para><para>(3)(a) The board of directors may adopt by resolution standard bylaw amendments adopted and promulgated by the department from time to time. The standard amendments may include two or more alternatives that the board of directors may elect. The standard bylaw amendments may also include companion amendments which shall be adopted as a unit.</para><para>(b) The board of directors may adopt any standard bylaw amendment without prior approval of the department as long as the standard bylaw amendment is adopted without any change in wording and a Certificate of Resolution adopting such amendment is submitted to the department containing the adopted language within ten days after the adoption of such amendment. Certificate of Resolution forms shall be furnished by the department upon request. The fee prescribed by section 8-602 shall not be charged when standard bylaw amendments are adopted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc>