<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-17,102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-17,102</statuteno><catchline>Authorized investments.</catchline><para>(1) Funds not used in loans to members may be invested:</para><para>(a) In securities, obligations, or other instruments of or issued by or fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by the United States of America or any agency or instrumentality thereof or in any trust or trusts established for investing directly or collectively in the same;</para><para>(b) In securities, obligations, or other instruments of any state of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and the several territories organized by Congress or any political subdivision thereof;</para><para>(c) In deposits, obligations, or other accounts of financial institutions organized under state or federal law;</para><para>(d) In loans to or in share accounts of other credit unions or corporate central credit unions;</para><para>(e) In obligations issued by banks for cooperatives, federal land banks, federal intermediate credit banks, federal home loan banks, the Federal Home Loan Bank Board, or any corporation designated in 31 U.S.C. 9101 as a wholly owned government corporation; in obligations, participation certificates, or other instruments of or insured by or fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Government National Mortgage Association; in mortgages, obligations, or other securities which are or ever have been sold by the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation pursuant to section 305 or section 306 of the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation Act, 12 U.S.C. 1454 et seq.; in obligations or other instruments or securities of the Student Loan Marketing Association; or in obligations, participation, securities, or other instruments of or issued by or fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by any other agency of the United States. A state credit union may issue and sell securities which are guaranteed pursuant to section 306(g) of the National Housing Act, 12 U.S.C. 1721(g);</para><para>(f) In participation certificates evidencing a beneficial interest in obligations or in a right to receive interest and principal collections therefrom, which obligations have been subjected by one or more government agencies to a trust or trusts for which any executive department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States or administrator thereof has been named to act as trustee;</para><para>(g) In share accounts or deposit accounts of any corporate central credit union in which such investments are specifically authorized by the board of directors of the credit union making the investment;</para><para>(h) In the shares, stock, or other obligations of any other organization, not to exceed ten percent of the credit union's capital and not to exceed five percent of the credit union's capital in any one corporation's stock, bonds, or other obligations, unless otherwise approved by the director. Such authority shall not include the power to acquire control, directly or indirectly, of another financial institution, nor invest in shares, stocks, or obligations of any insurance company or trade association except as otherwise expressly provided for or approved by the director;</para><para>(i) In the capital stock of the National Credit Union Administration Central Liquidity Facility;</para><para>(j) In obligations of or issued by any state or political subdivision thereof, including any agency, corporation, or instrumentality of a state or political subdivision, except that no credit union may invest more than ten percent of its capital in the obligations of any one issuer, exclusive of general obligations of the issuer;</para><para>(k) In securities issued pursuant to the Nebraska Business Development Corporation Act; and</para><para>(l) In participation loans with other credit unions, credit union organizations, or other organizations.</para><para>(2) In addition to investments expressly permitted by the Credit Union Act, a credit union may make any other type of investment approved by the department by rule, regulation, or order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 31.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Business Development Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-2101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>