
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id26" statutenumber="21-19,151">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,151</statuteno><catchline id="id29">Foreign corporation;
corporate name.</catchline><para>(a) If the corporate name of a foreign corporation
does not satisfy the requirements of section 21-1931, the foreign corporation,
to obtain or maintain a certificate of authority to transact business in this
state, may use a fictitious name to transact business in this state if its
real name is unavailable and it delivers to the Secretary of State for filing
a copy of the resolution of its board of directors, certified by its secretary,
adopting the fictitious name.</para>
<para>(b) Except as authorized by subsections (c) and (d) of this section,
the corporate name (including a fictitious name) of a foreign corporation
shall not be the same as or deceptively similar to, upon the records of the
Secretary of State, any of the names referenced in subdivisions (b)(1) through
(5) of this section:</para>
<para>(1) The corporate name of a nonprofit or business corporation incorporated
or authorized to transact business in this state;</para>
<para>(2) A corporate name reserved or registered under section 21-231, 21-232, 21-1932, or 21-1933;</para>
<para>(3) The fictitious name of another foreign business or nonprofit corporation
authorized to transact business in this state;</para>
<para>(4) A trade name registered in this state pursuant to sections 87-208
to 87-219.01; and</para>
<para>(5) Any other business entity name registered or filed with the Secretary
of State pursuant to Nebraska law.</para>
<para>(c) A foreign corporation may apply to the Secretary of State for authorization
to use in this state the name of another corporation or business entity (incorporated
or authorized to transact business in this state) that is deceptively similar
to, upon the records of the Secretary of State, the name applied for. The
Secretary of State shall authorize use of the name applied for if:</para>
<para>(1) The other corporation or business entity consents in writing to
the use; or</para>
<para>(2) The applying corporation delivers to the Secretary of State a certified
copy of a final judgment of a court of competent jurisdiction establishing
its right to use the name applied for in this state.</para>
<para>(d) A foreign corporation may use in this state the name (including
the fictitious name) of another domestic or foreign business or nonprofit
corporation or business entity that is used in this state if the other corporation
or business entity is incorporated or authorized to transact business in this
state and the foreign corporation:</para>
<para>(1) Has merged with the other corporation or business entity;</para>
<para>(2) Has been formed by a reorganization of the other corporation or
business entity; or</para>
<para>(3) Has acquired all or substantially all of the assets, including the
name, of the other corporation or business entity.</para>
<para>(e) If a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in this
state changes its corporate name to one that does not satisfy the requirements
of section 21-1931, it shall not transact business in this state under the
changed name until it adopts a name satisfying the requirements of section
21-1931 and obtains an amended certificate of authority under section 21-19,149.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 151; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 44, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 453, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 464, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB462, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 265.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>