<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,146"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,146</statuteno><catchline>Foreign corporation; authority to transact business required.</catchline><para>(a) A foreign corporation may not transact business in this state until it obtains a certificate of authority from the Secretary of State.</para><para>(b) The following activities, among others, do not constitute transacting business within the meaning of subsection (a) of this section:</para><para>(1) Maintaining, defending, or settling any proceeding;</para><para>(2) Holding meetings of the board of directors or members or carrying on other activities concerning internal corporate affairs;</para><para>(3) Maintaining bank accounts;</para><para>(4) Maintaining offices or agencies for the transfer, exchange, and registration of memberships or securities or maintaining trustees or depositaries with respect to those securities;</para><para>(5) Selling through independent contractors;</para><para>(6) Soliciting or obtaining orders, whether by mail or through employees or agents or otherwise, if the orders require acceptance outside this state before they become contracts;</para><para>(7) Creating or acquiring indebtedness, mortgages, and security interests in real or personal property;</para><para>(8) Securing or collecting debts or enforcing mortgages and security interests in property securing the debts;</para><para>(9) Owning, without more, real or personal property;</para><para>(10) Conducting an isolated transaction which is completed within thirty days and which is not one in the course of repeated transactions of a like nature; or</para><para>(11) Transacting business in interstate commerce.</para><para>(c) The list of activities in subsection (b) of this section is not exhaustive.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 146. </para></source></law></legaldoc>