<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-17,108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-17,108</statuteno><catchline>Liquidation.</catchline><para>(1) A credit union may elect to dissolve voluntarily and liquidate its affairs in the manner prescribed in this section.</para><para>(2) If the board of directors decides to begin dissolution procedures, the board shall adopt a resolution recommending that the credit union be dissolved voluntarily and directing that the question of liquidation be submitted to the credit union members.</para><para>(3) Within ten days after the board of directors decides to submit the question of liquidation to the members, the president shall notify the department and the National Credit Union Administration in writing of such decision and setting forth the reasons for the proposed liquidation. Within ten days after the members act on the question of liquidation, the president shall notify the department and the National Credit Union Administration in writing as to the action of the members on the proposal.</para><para>(4) As soon as the board of directors decides to submit the question of liquidation to the members, payments on, withdrawal of, and making any transfer of share accounts to loans and interest, making investments of any kind, and granting of loans may be restricted or suspended pending action by the members on the proposal to dissolve. Upon approval by the members of the question of liquidation, all business transactions shall be permanently discontinued. Necessary expenses of operation shall continue to be paid upon the authorization of the board or the liquidating agent during the period of liquidation.</para><para>(5) For a credit union to enter voluntary liquidation, approval by a majority of the members in writing or by a two-thirds majority of the members present at a regular or special meeting of the members shall be required. When authorization for liquidation is to be obtained at a meeting of the members, notice in writing shall be given to each member, by first-class mail, at least ten days prior to such meeting.</para><para>(6) A liquidating credit union shall continue in existence for the purpose of discharging its debts, collecting on loans and distributing its assets, and doing all acts required in order to conclude its business and may sue and be sued for the purpose of enforcing such debts and obligations until its affairs are fully concluded.</para><para>(7) The board of directors or the liquidating agent shall distribute the assets of the credit union or the proceeds of any disposition of the assets pursuant to section 21-1734.</para><para>(8) As soon as the board of directors or the liquidating agent determines that all assets from which there is a reasonable expectancy of realization have been liquidated and distributed pursuant to section 21-1734, the board or the liquidating agent shall execute a certificate of dissolution on a form prescribed by the department and shall file the same, together with all pertinent books and records of the liquidating credit union, with the department and the credit union shall be dissolved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 108. </para></source></law></legaldoc>