<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,165"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,165</statuteno><catchline>Corporate records.</catchline><para>(a) A corporation shall keep as permanent records minutes of all meetings of its members and board of directors, a record of all actions taken by the members or directors without a meeting, and a record of all actions taken by committees of the board of directors as authorized by subsection (d) of section 21-1985.</para><para>(b) A corporation shall maintain appropriate accounting records.</para><para>(c) A corporation or its agent shall maintain a record of its members in a form that permits preparation of a list of the names and addresses of all members, in alphabetical order by class, showing the number of votes each member is entitled to cast.</para><para>(d) A corporation shall maintain its records in written form or in another form capable of conversion into written form within a reasonable time.</para><para>(e) A corporation shall keep a copy of the following records at its principal office:</para><para>(1) Its articles or restated articles of incorporation and all amendments to them currently in effect;</para><para>(2) Its bylaws or restated bylaws and all amendments to them currently in effect;</para><para>(3) Resolutions adopted by its board of directors relating to the characteristics, qualifications, rights, limitations, and obligations of members or any class or category of members;</para><para>(4) The minutes of all meetings of members and records of all actions approved by the members for the past three years;</para><para>(5) All written communications to members generally within the past three years, including the financial statements furnished for the past three years under section 21-19,170;</para><para>(6) A list of the names and business or home addresses of its current directors and officers; and</para><para>(7) Its most recent biennial report delivered to the Secretary of State under section 21-19,172.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 165. </para></source><annotation><para>Pursuant to subsection (a) of section 21-19,166, a member is permitted to inspect and copy, without conditions,
    those records described in subsection (e) of this section, which include financial statements that include a balance
    sheet as of the end of the fiscal year and a statement of operations for that year. Dunbar v. Twin Towers Condo.
    Assn., 26 Neb. App. 354, 920 N.W.2d 1 (2018).
</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>