<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1921"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1921</statuteno><catchline>Articles of incorporation.</catchline><para>(a) The articles of incorporation shall set forth:</para><para>(1) A corporate name for the corporation that satisfies the requirements of section 21-1931;</para><para>(2) One of the following statements:</para><para>(i) This corporation is a public benefit corporation;</para><para>(ii) This corporation is a mutual benefit corporation; or</para><para>(iii) This corporation is a religious corporation;</para><para>(3) The street address of the corporation's initial registered office and the name of its initial registered agent at that office. A post office box number may be provided in addition to the street address;</para><para>(4) The name and street address of each incorporator;</para><para>(5) Whether or not the corporation will have members; and</para><para>(6) Provisions not inconsistent with law regarding the distribution of assets on dissolution.</para><para>(b) The articles of incorporation may set forth:</para><para>(1) The purpose or purposes for which the corporation is organized, which may be, either alone or in combination with other purposes, the transaction of any lawful activity;</para><para>(2) The names and street addresses of the individuals who are to serve as the initial directors;</para><para>(3) Provisions not inconsistent with law regarding:</para><para>(i) Managing and regulating the affairs of the corporation;</para><para>(ii) Defining, limiting, and regulating the powers of the corporation, its board of directors, and members (or any class of members); and</para><para>(iii) The characteristics, qualifications, rights, limitations, and obligations attaching to each or any class of members.</para><para>(4) Any provision that under the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act is required or permitted to be set forth in the bylaws.</para><para>(c) Each incorporator and director named in the articles must sign the articles.</para><para>(d) The articles of incorporation need not set forth any of the corporate powers enumerated in the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167;  7.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
