<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,147"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,147</statuteno><catchline>Foreign corporation; transacting business without authority; consequences; civil penalty.</catchline><para>(a) A foreign corporation transacting business in this state without a certificate of authority may not maintain a proceeding in any court in this state until it obtains a certificate of authority.</para><para>(b) The successor to a foreign corporation that transacted business in this state without a certificate of authority and the assignee of a cause of action arising out of that business may not maintain a proceeding on that cause of action in any court in this state until the foreign corporation or its successor obtains a certificate of authority.</para><para>(c) A court may stay a proceeding commenced by a foreign corporation, its successor, or assignee until it determines whether the foreign corporation or its successor requires a certificate of authority. If it so determines, the court may further stay the proceeding until the foreign corporation or its successor obtains the certificate.</para><para>(d) A foreign corporation is liable for a civil penalty of five hundred dollars for each day, but not to exceed a total of ten thousand dollars for each year, it transacts business in this state without a certificate of authority. The Attorney General may collect all penalties due under this subsection. All civil penalties collected under this subsection shall be remitted by the Attorney General for credit to the permanent school fund.</para><para>(e) Notwithstanding subsections (a) and (b) of this section, the failure of a foreign corporation to obtain a certificate of authority does not impair the validity of its corporate acts or prevent it from defending any proceeding in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 147. </para></source></law></legaldoc>