<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1799"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1799</statuteno><catchline>Federally authorized plans; powers; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) All credit unions chartered under the laws of Nebraska shall be qualified to act as a trustee or custodian within the provisions of the federal Self-Employed Individuals Tax Retirement Act of 1962 or under the terms and provisions of section 408(a) of the Internal Revenue Code if the provisions of such retirement plan require the funds of such trust or custodianship to be invested exclusively in shares or accounts in the credit union or other credit unions.</para><para>(2) All credit unions chartered under the laws of Nebraska are qualified to act as trustee or custodian of a medical savings account created within the provisions of section 220 of the Internal Revenue Code and a health savings account created within the provisions of section 223 of the Internal Revenue Code. Except for judgments against the medical savings account holder or health savings account holder or his or her dependents for qualified medical expenses as defined under section 223(d)(2) of the Internal Revenue Code, funds credited to a medical savings account or health savings account below twenty-five thousand dollars are not susceptible to levy, execution, judgment, or other operation of law, garnishment, or other judicial enforcement and are not an asset or property of the account holder for purposes of bankruptcy law.</para><para>(3) All credit unions chartered under the laws of Nebraska are qualified to act as trustee or custodian of an education individual retirement account created within the provisions of section 530 of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(4) All credit unions chartered under the laws of Nebraska are qualified to act as trustee or custodian of a Roth IRA created within the provisions of section 408A of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(5) If any such plan, in the judgment of the credit union, constitutes a qualified plan under the federal Self-Employed Individuals Tax Retirement Act of 1962, or under the terms and provisions of section 220, 223, 408(a), 408A, or 530 of the Internal Revenue Code, and the regulations promulgated thereunder at the time the trust was established and accepted by the credit union is subsequently determined not to be such a qualified plan, or subsequently ceases to be such a qualified plan, in whole or in part, the credit union may continue to act as trustee of any deposits which have been made under such plan and to dispose of such deposits in accordance with the directions of the member and beneficiaries thereof.</para><para>(6) No credit union, with respect to savings made under this section, shall be required to segregate such savings from other assets of the credit union, but the credit union shall keep appropriate records showing in detail all transactions engaged in pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 107, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 465, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>