<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1964"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1964</statuteno><catchline>Cumulative voting for directors.</catchline><para>(a) If the articles or bylaws provide for cumulative voting by members, members may so vote, by multiplying the number of votes the members are entitled to cast by the number of directors for whom they are entitled to vote, and cast the product for a single candidate or distribute the product among two or more candidates.</para><para>(b) Cumulative voting is not authorized at a particular meeting unless:</para><para>(1) The meeting notice or statement accompanying the notice states that cumulative voting will take place; or</para><para>(2) A member gives notice during the meeting and before the vote is taken of the member's intent to cumulate votes, and if one member gives this notice all other members participating in the election are entitled to cumulate their votes without giving further notice.</para><para>(c) A director elected by cumulative voting may be removed by the members without cause if the requirements of section 21-1975 are met unless the votes cast against removal, or not consenting in writing to such removal, would be sufficient to elect such director if voted cumulatively at an election at which the same total number of votes were cast (or, if such action is taken by written ballot, all memberships entitled to vote were voted) and the entire number of directors authorized at the time of the director's most recent election were then being elected.</para><para>(d) Members may not cumulatively vote if the directors and members are identical.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 64. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Cumulative voting for directors,</emphasis> see Chapter XII, article 1, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>