<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1724" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1724</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Organization; procedure; hearing.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Any nine or more individuals residing in the State of Nebraska who are nineteen years of age or older and who have a common bond pursuant to section 21-1743 may apply to the department on forms prescribed by the department for permission to organize a credit union and to become charter members and subscribers of the credit union.</para><para id="id00">(2) The subscribers shall execute in duplicate articles of association and shall agree to the terms of the articles of association. The terms shall state:</para><para id="id00">(a) The name, which shall include the words "credit union" and shall not be the same as the name of any other credit union in this state, whether or not organized under the Credit Union Act, and the location where the proposed credit union will have its principal place of business;</para><para id="id00">(b) The names and addresses of the subscribers to the articles of association and the number of shares subscribed by each;</para><para id="id00">(c) The par value of the shares of the credit union which shall be established by its board of directors. A credit union may have more than one class of shares;</para><para id="id00">(d) The common bond of members of the credit union; and</para><para id="id00">(e) That the existence of the credit union shall be perpetual.</para><para id="id00">(3) The subscribers shall prepare and adopt bylaws for the governance of the credit union. The bylaws shall be consistent with the Credit Union Act and shall be executed in duplicate.</para><para id="id00">(4) The subscribers shall select at least five qualified individuals to serve on the board of directors of the credit union, at least three qualified individuals to serve on the supervisory committee of the credit union, and at least three qualified individuals to serve on the credit committee of the credit union, if any. Such individuals shall execute a signed agreement to serve in these capacities until the first annual meeting or until the election of their successors, whichever is later.</para><para id="id00">(5) The articles of association and the bylaws, both executed in duplicate, shall be forwarded by the subscribers along with the required fee, if any, to the director, as an application for a certificate of approval.</para><para id="id00">(6) The director shall within one hundred twenty calendar days after receipt of the articles of association and the bylaws: (a) Act upon the application to determine whether the articles of association conform with this section and whether or not the character of the applicants and the conditions existing are favorable for the success of the credit union; and (b) notify the applicants of his or her decision.</para><para id="id00">(7) If the decision is favorable, the director shall issue a certificate of approval to the credit union. The certificate of approval shall be attached to the duplicate articles of association and returned, with the duplicate bylaws, to such subscribers.</para><para id="id00">(8) The subscribers shall file the certificate of approval with the articles of association attached in the office of the county clerk of the county in which the credit union is to locate its principal place of business. The county clerk shall accept and record the documents if they are accompanied by the proper fee and, after indexing, forward to the department proper documentation that the certificate of approval with the articles of association attached have been properly filed and recorded. When the documents are so recorded, the credit union shall be organized in accordance with the Credit Union Act and may begin transacting business.</para><para id="id00">(9) If the director's decision on the application is unfavorable, he or she shall notify the subscribers of the reasons for the decision. The subscribers may then request a public hearing if no such hearing was held at the time the application was submitted for consideration.</para><para id="id00">(10) The request for a public hearing shall be made in writing to the director not more than thirty calendar days after his or her decision. The director, within ten calendar days after receipt of a request for a hearing, shall set a date for the hearing at a time and place convenient to the director and the subscribers, but no longer than sixty calendar days after receipt of such request. The director may request a stenographic record of the hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB375, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>