<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1725.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1725.01</statuteno><catchline>New credit union; branch credit
union; application; procedure; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receiving
an application to establish a new credit union, a public hearing shall be
held on each application. Notice of the filing of the application shall be
published by the department for three weeks in a legal newspaper published
in or of general circulation in the county where the applicant proposes to
operate the credit union. The date for hearing the application shall be not
less than thirty days after the last publication of notice of hearing and
not more than ninety days after filing the application unless the applicant
agrees to a later date. Notice of the filing of the application shall be sent
by the department to all financial institutions located in the county where
the applicant proposes to operate.</para>
<para>(2) When application is made to establish a branch of a credit union,
the director shall hold a hearing on the matter if he or she determines, in
his or her discretion, that the condition of the applicant credit union warrants
a hearing. If the director determines that the condition of the credit union
does not warrant a hearing, the director shall (a) publish a notice of the
filing of the application in a newspaper of general circulation in the county
where the proposed branch would be located and (b) give notice of such application
to all financial institutions located within the county where the proposed
credit union branch would be located and to such other interested parties
as the director may determine. If the director receives any substantive objection
to the proposed credit union branch within fifteen days after publication
of such notice, he or she shall hold a hearing on the application. Notice
of a hearing held pursuant to this subsection shall be published for two consecutive
weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where the proposed
branch would be located. The date for hearing the application shall be not
less than thirty days after the last publication of notice of hearing and
not more than ninety days after the filing of the application unless the applicant
agrees to a later date.</para>
<para>(3) The director may, in his or her discretion, hold a public hearing
on amendments to a credit union's articles of association or bylaws which
are brought before the department.</para>
<para>(4) The director shall send any notice to financial institutions required
by this section by first-class
mail, postage prepaid, or electronic mail. Electronic mail may
be used if the financial institution agrees in advance to receive such notices
by electronic mail. A financial
institution may designate one office for receipt of any such notice if it
has more than one office located within the county where such notice is to
be sent or a main office in a county other than the county where such notice
is to be sent.</para>
<para>(5) The expense of any publication and mailing required by this section shall
be paid by the applicant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 957, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 217, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB890, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>