<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-17,112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-17,112</statuteno><catchline>Conversion from federal to state credit union.</catchline><para>(1) A federal credit union organized under the Federal Credit Union Act, 12 U.S.C. 1753 et seq., and meeting all the requirements to become a state credit union organized under the Credit Union Act may, with the approval of the department and in compliance with the applicable law under which it was organized, be converted into a state credit union organized under the Credit Union Act. The required articles of association may be executed by a majority of the board of directors of the converting credit union and presented to the department for appropriate examination and approval. A majority of the directors, after executing the articles of association in duplicate, may execute all other papers, including the adoption of bylaws for the general government of the credit union consistent with the Credit Union Act, and do whatever may be required to complete its conversion.</para><para>(2) The board of directors of the converting credit union may continue to be directors of the credit union. If the director approves the articles of association as presented by the board of directors, the director shall notify the board of directors of his or her decision and shall immediately issue a certificate of approval attached to the duplicate articles of association and return it to the credit union. The certificate shall indicate that the laws of this state have been complied with and that the credit union and all its members, officials, and employees shall have the same rights, powers, and privileges and shall be subject to the same duties, liabilities, and obligations in all respects, as shall be applicable to credit unions originally organized under the Credit Union Act.</para><para>(3) The approval of the department shall be based on an examination of the credit union and the proceedings had by its board of directors and members with respect to conversion. A conversion shall not be made to defeat or defraud any of the creditors of the credit union. The expenses of an examination, which shall be computed in accordance with sections 8-605 and 8-606, shall be paid by the credit union.</para><para>(4) When the conversion becomes effective, all property of the converted credit union, including all its right, title, and interest in and to all property of whatsoever kind, whether real, personal, or mixed, and things in action, and every right, privilege, interest, and asset of any conceivable value or benefit then existing, belonging, or pertaining to it, or which would inure to it, shall immediately by act of law and without any conveyance or transfer, and without any further act or deed, be vested in and remain the property of the converted credit union, which shall have, hold, and enjoy the property in its own right as fully and to the same extent as the property was previously possessed, held, and enjoyed by it. The converted credit union shall be deemed to be a continuation of the same entity. All the rights, obligations, and relations of the credit union to or in respect to any person, estate, creditor, member, trustee, or beneficiary of any trust or fiduciary function shall remain unimpaired. The credit union shall continue to hold all the rights, obligations, relations, and trusts, and the duties and liabilities connected therewith, and shall execute and perform every trust and relation in the same manner as if it had after the conversion assumed the trust or relation and obligation and liabilities connected with the trust or relation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 137, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 20.</para></source></law></legaldoc>