<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,166"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,166</statuteno><catchline>Inspection of records by members.</catchline><para>(a) Subject to subsection (e) of this section and subsection (c) of section 21-19,167, a member is entitled to inspect and copy, at a reasonable time and location specified by the corporation, any of the records of the corporation described in subsection (e) of section 21-19,165 if the member gives the corporation written notice or a written demand at least five business days before the date on which the member wishes to inspect and copy.</para><para>(b) Subject to subsection (e) of this section, a member is entitled to inspect and copy, at a reasonable time and reasonable location specified by the corporation, any of the following records of the corporation if the member meets the requirements of subsection (c) of this section and gives the corporation written notice at least five business days before the date on which the member wishes to inspect and copy:</para><para>(1) Excerpts from any records required to be maintained under subsection (a) of section 21-19,165, to the extent not subject to inspection under subsection (a) of this section;</para><para>(2) Accounting records of the corporation; and</para><para>(3) Subject to section 21-19,169, the membership list.</para><para>(c) A member may inspect and copy the records identified in subsection (b) of this section only if:</para><para>(1) The member's demand is made in good faith and for a proper purpose;</para><para>(2) The member describes with reasonable particularity the purpose and the records the member desires to inspect; and</para><para>(3) The records are directly connected with this purpose.</para><para>(d) This section does not affect:</para><para>(1) The right of a member to inspect records under section 21-1959 or, if the member is in litigation with the corporation, to the same extent as any other litigant; or</para><para>(2) The power of a court, independent of the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, to compel the production of corporate records for examination.</para><para>(e) The articles or bylaws of a religious corporation may limit or abolish the right of a member under this section to inspect and copy any corporate record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 166. </para></source></law></legaldoc>