<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-19,143"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-19,143</statuteno><catchline>Receivership or custodianship.</catchline><para>(a) The district court in a proceeding brought to dissolve a public benefit or mutual benefit corporation may appoint one or more receivers to wind up and liquidate, or one or more custodians to manage, the affairs of the corporation. The court shall hold a hearing, after notifying all parties to the proceeding and any interested persons designated by the court, before appointing a receiver or custodian. The district court appointing a receiver or custodian has exclusive jurisdiction over the corporation and all of its property wherever located.</para><para>(b) The district court may appoint an individual or a domestic or foreign business or nonprofit corporation (authorized to transact business in this state) as a receiver or custodian. The court may require the receiver or custodian to post bond, with or without sureties, in an amount the court directs.</para><para>(c) The district court shall describe the powers and duties of the receiver or custodian in its appointing order, which order may be amended from time to time. Among other powers:</para><para>(1) The receiver (i) may dispose of all or any part of the assets of the corporation wherever located, at a public or private sale, if authorized by the district court. The receiver's power to dispose of the assets of the corporation is subject to any trust and any other restrictions that would be applicable to the corporation; and (ii) may sue and defend in the receiver's or custodian's name as receiver or custodian of the corporation in all courts of this state;</para><para>(2) The custodian may exercise all of the powers of the corporation, through or in place of its board of directors or officers, to the extent necessary to manage the affairs of the corporation in the best interests of its members and creditors.</para><para>(d) The district court during a receivership may redesignate the receiver as a custodian, and during a custodianship may redesignate the custodian as a receiver, if doing so is in the best interests of the corporation, its members, and creditors.</para><para>(e) The district court from time to time during the receivership or custodianship may order compensation paid and expense disbursements or reimbursements made to the receiver or custodian and the receiver or custodian's counsel from the assets of the corporation or proceeds from the sale of the assets.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 143. </para></source></law></legaldoc>