<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1767"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1767</statuteno><catchline>Meetings of directors.</catchline><para>(1) The board of directors shall have regular meetings as often as necessary but not less frequently than six meetings annually with at least one meeting in each calendar quarter. A new credit union shall have regular meetings as often as necessary but not less frequently than once each month for the first five years of the existence of the credit union. Special meetings of the board may be called as provided in the bylaws.</para><para>(2) Unless the articles of association or bylaws provide otherwise, the board of directors may permit any or all directors to participate in a regular or special meeting by, or conduct the meeting through the use of, any means of communication by which all directors participating may simultaneously hear each other during the meeting. A director participating in a meeting by this means shall be deemed to be present in person at the meeting.</para><para>(3) If the Director of Banking and Finance deems it expedient, he or she may call a meeting of the board of directors of any credit union, for any purpose, by giving notice to the directors of the time, place, and purpose thereof at least three business days prior to the meeting, either by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to their last-known addresses as shown on the credit union books.</para><para>(4) A full and complete record of the proceedings and business of all meetings of the board of directors shall be recorded in the minutes of the meeting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 69. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>