<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1997"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1997</statuteno><catchline>Authority to indemnify.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in subsection (d) of this section a corporation may indemnify an individual made a party to a proceeding because the individual is or was a director against liability incurred in the proceeding if the individual:</para><para>(1) Conducted himself or herself in good faith; and</para><para>(2) Reasonably believed:</para><para>(i) In the case of conduct in his or her official capacity with the corporation, that his or her conduct was in its best interests; and</para><para>(ii) In all other cases, that his or her conduct was at least not opposed to its best interests; and</para><para>(3) In the case of any criminal proceeding, had no reasonable cause to believe his or her conduct was unlawful.</para><para>(b) A director's conduct with respect to an employee benefit plan for a purpose the director reasonably believed to be in the best interests of the participants in and beneficiaries of the plan is conduct that satisfies the requirements of subdivision (a)(2)(ii) of this section.</para><para>(c) The termination of a proceeding by judgment, order, settlement, conviction, or upon a plea of nolo contendere or its equivalent is not, of itself, determinative that the director did not meet the standard of conduct described in this section.</para><para>(d) A corporation may not indemnify a director under this section:</para><para>(1) In connection with a proceeding by or in the right of the corporation in which the director was adjudged liable to the corporation; or</para><para>(2) In connection with any other proceeding charging improper personal benefit to the director, whether or not involving action in his or her official capacity, in which the director was adjudged liable on the basis that personal benefit was improperly received by the director.</para><para>(e) Indemnification permitted under this section in connection with a proceeding by or in the right of the corporation is limited to reasonable expenses incurred in connection with the proceeding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 97. </para></source></law></legaldoc>