<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-1737"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-1737</statuteno><catchline>Records.</catchline><para>(1) A credit union shall maintain all books, records, accounting systems, and procedures in accordance with the rules and regulations as the director from time to time may prescribe.</para><para>(2) Credit unions shall preserve or keep their records or files, or photographic or microphotographic copies thereof, for a period of not less than six years after the first day of January of the year following the time of the making or filing of such records or files except as provided in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3)(a) Ledger sheets showing unpaid balances in favor of members of credit unions shall not be destroyed unless the credit union has remitted such unpaid balances to the State Treasurer in accordance with the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act. Credit unions shall retain a record of every such remittance for ten years following the date of such remittance.</para><para>(b) Corporate records that relate to the corporation or the corporate existence of the credit union shall not be destroyed.</para><para>(4) A credit union shall not be liable for destroying records after the expiration of the record retention period provided in this section except for records involved in an official investigation or examination about which the credit union has received notice.</para><para>(5) A reproduction of any credit union records shall be admissible as evidence of transactions with the credit union as provided in section 25-12,112.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 948, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 21. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act,</emphasis> see section 69-1329.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>