<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2631.01" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2631.01</statuteno><catchline>Registration certificate; application; contents; issuance; fees; display; Secretary of State; access electronic licensing records; verification; suspension.</catchline><para>(1) An application for issuance of a registration certificate shall be made by the limited liability company to the regulatory body in writing and shall contain the names of all members, managers, and professional employees of the limited liability company, the street address at which the applicant proposes to perform a professional service, and such other information as may be required by the regulatory body. If it appears to the regulatory body that each member, manager, and professional employee of the applicant required by law to be licensed is licensed or otherwise authorized to practice the profession of the applicant and that each member, manager, or professional employee required by law to be licensed is not otherwise disqualified from performing the professional service of the applicant, such regulatory body shall certify in duplicate upon a form bearing its date of issuance and prescribed by such regulatory body that the proposed or existing limited liability company complies with the provisions of the Limited Liability Company Act and of the applicable rules and regulations of the regulatory body. Each applicant for such registration certificate shall pay the regulatory body a fee of twenty-five dollars for the issuance of the certificate.</para><para>One copy of such certificate shall be prominently displayed to public view upon the premises of the principal place of business of the limited liability company, and one copy shall be filed with the Secretary of State who shall charge a fee of twenty-five dollars for filing the same. The certificate shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State with the articles of organization. A registration certificate bearing an issuance date more than twelve months old shall not be eligible for filing with the Secretary of State.</para><para>(2) When licensing records of regulating boards are electronically accessible to the Secretary of State, the Secretary of State shall access the records. The access of the records shall be made in lieu of the certificate of registration or registration certificate being prepared and issued by the regulating board. The limited liability company shall file with the Secretary of State an application setting forth the names of all members, managers, and professional employees of such limited liability company who are required by law to be licensed or otherwise authorized to practice the professional service for which the limited liability company is organized as of the last day of the month preceding the date of application and shall file with the Secretary of State an annual update thereafter. The application shall be completed on a form prescribed by the Secretary of State and shall contain such other information as the Secretary of State may require. The application shall be accompanied by a license verification fee of fifty dollars.</para><para>The Secretary of State shall verify that all members, managers, and professional employees who are required by law to do so are duly licensed or otherwise legally authorized to render the same professional service or ancillary service as those which the limited liability company renders through electronic accessing of the regulating board's records. If any member, manager, or professional employee is not licensed or otherwise legally authorized to perform the professional service that the limited liability company was organized to render, the limited liability company shall be suspended. The suspension shall remain in effect and a biennial report shall not be filed in the office of the Secretary of State until the limited liability company attests in writing that all members, managers, or professional employees are duly licensed or otherwise legally authorized to render the appropriate service and that information is verified by the Secretary of State or all unlicensed or unauthorized members, managers, or professional employees are no longer members, managers, or professional employees of the limited liability company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 189; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 647, &#167; 14. </para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc>