<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id5" statutenumber="21-2014"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">21-2014</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Business Corporation Act, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Articles of incorporation shall include amended and restated
articles of incorporation and articles of merger;</para>
<para>(2) Authorized shares shall mean the shares of all classes
a domestic or foreign corporation is authorized to issue;</para>
<para>(3) Conspicuous shall mean so written that a reasonable person
against whom the writing is to operate should have noticed it. For example,
printing in italics or boldface or contrasting color, or typing in capitals
or underlined, shall be considered conspicuous;</para>
<para>(4) Corporation or domestic corporation shall mean a corporation
for profit, which is not a foreign corporation, incorporated under or subject
to the provisions of the act;</para>
<para>(5) Deliver or
delivery shall mean any method of delivery used in conventional commercial
practice, including delivery by hand, mail, commercial delivery, and electronic
transmission;</para>
<para>(6) Distribution shall mean a direct or indirect transfer
of money or other property, except a corporation's own shares, or incurrence
of indebtedness by a corporation to or for the benefit of its shareholders
in respect of any of its shares. A distribution may be in the form of a declaration
or payment of a dividend, a purchase, redemption, or other acquisition of
shares, a distribution of indebtedness, or otherwise;</para>
<para>(7) Effective date of notice shall have the same meaning as
in section 21-2015;</para>
<para>(8) Electronic
transmission or electronically transmitted shall mean any process of communication
not directly involving the physical transfer of paper that is suitable for
the retention, retrieval, and reproduction of information by the recipient;</para>
<para>(9) Employee shall include
an officer but not a director. A director may accept duties that make him
or her also an employee;</para>
<para>(10) Entity shall include
corporation and foreign corporation, not-for-profit corporation, limited liability
company, profit and not-for-profit unincorporated association, business trust,
estate, partnership, trust, two or more persons having a joint or common economic
interest, state, United States, and foreign government;</para>
<para>(11) Foreign corporation shall
mean a corporation for profit incorporated under a law other than the law
of this state;</para>
<para>(12) Governmental subdivision
shall include authority, county, district, and municipality;</para>
<para>(13) Individual shall include
the estate of an incompetent or deceased individual;</para>
<para>(14) Notice shall have the
same meaning as in section 21-2015;</para>
<para>(15) Person shall include
individual and entity;</para>
<para>(16) Principal office shall
mean the office, in or out of this state, so designated in the annual report
where the principal executive offices of a domestic or foreign corporation
are located;</para>
<para>(17) Proceeding shall include
civil suit or action and criminal, administrative, and investigatory action;</para>
<para>(18) Record date shall mean
the date established under sections 21-2035 to 21-2050 or 21-2051 to 21-2077
on which a corporation determines the identity of its shareholders and their
shareholdings for purposes of the act. The determinations shall be made as
of the close of business on the record date unless another time for doing
so is specified when the record date is fixed;</para>
<para>(19) Secretary shall mean
the corporate officer to whom the board of directors has delegated responsibility
under subsection (3) of section 21-2097 for custody of the minutes of the
meetings of the board of directors and of the shareholders and for authenticating
records of the corporation;</para>
<para>(20) Share shall mean the
unit into which the proprietary interests in a corporation are divided;</para>
<para>(21) Shareholder shall mean
the person in whose name shares are registered in the records of a corporation
or the beneficial owner of shares to the extent of the rights granted by a
nominee certificate on file with a corporation;</para>
<para>(22) State, when referring
to a part of the United States, shall include a state and commonwealth, and
their agencies and governmental subdivisions, and a territory and insular
possession, and their agencies and governmental subdivisions, of the United
States;</para>
<para>(23) Subscriber shall mean
a person who subscribes for shares in a corporation, whether before or after
incorporation;</para>
<para>(24) United States shall include
district, authority, bureau, commission, department, and any other agency
of the United States; and</para>
<para>(25) Voting group shall mean
all shares of one or more classes or series that under the articles of incorporation
or the act are entitled to vote and be counted together collectively on a
matter at a meeting of shareholders. All shares entitled by the articles of
incorporation or the act to vote generally on the matter are for that purpose
a single voting group.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB528, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
