<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id54">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id56" statutenumber="21-20,128"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,128</statuteno><catchline id="id59">Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Merger; plan.</catchline>
<para>(1) One or more corporations may merge with one or more corporations or business entities, subject
to section 21-20,134, if the board of directors of each corporation
adopts and its shareholders, if required by section 21-20,130, approve a plan
of merger, and if each business
entity approves the plan of merger in accordance with the laws under which
the business entity was formed and in accordance with the applicable requirements
of its organizational documents.</para>
<para>(2) The plan of merger shall set forth:</para>
<para>(a) The name of each corporation or business entity planning to merge and the
name of the surviving corporation or
business entity into which each corporation or business entity plans to
merge;</para>
<para>(b) The terms and conditions of the merger; and</para>
<para>(c) The manner and basis of converting the shares of each merging corporation or the interests of each merging business
entity into any
combination of shares, obligations, securities, interests, or rights in the surviving corporation or business
entity or other consideration.</para>
<para>(3) The plan of merger may set forth:</para>
<para>(a) Amendments to the articles of incorporation of the surviving
corporation or amendments to
the organizational documents of the surviving business entity;
and</para>
<para>(b) Other provisions relating to the merger.</para>
<para>(4) As used
in this section:</para><para>(a) Business entity means a foreign corporation; a domestic or foreign
partnership; a domestic or foreign limited partnership; or a domestic or foreign
limited liability company; and</para><para>(b) Organizational documents includes:</para>
<para>(i) For a foreign
corporation, its articles of incorporation, bylaws, and other agreements among
its shareholders which are authorized by its governing statute or comparable
records as provided in its governing statute;</para><para>(ii) For a domestic or
foreign partnership, its partnership agreement;</para><para>(iii) For a domestic or
foreign limited partnership, its certificate of limited partnership and partnership
agreement; and</para><para>(iv) For a domestic or foreign limited liability company, its certificate
or articles of organization and operating agreement or comparable records
as provided in its governing statute.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 128; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1018, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>