<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2109"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2109</statuteno><catchline>Membership; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any financial institution is authorized to become a member of and to invest in a development corporation by making application to the board of directors on such form and in such manner as the board of directors may require, and membership shall become effective upon acceptance of such application by such board. Membership shall be for the duration of the corporation, except that upon written notice given to the corporation two years in advance, a member may withdraw from membership at the expiration date of such notice and shall not, after the expiration date of such notice, be obligated to make any loans to the corporation. No financial institution shall become a member of more than one development corporation.</para><para>(2) Each such member shall make loans to the corporation as and when called upon to do so, upon such terms and conditions as approved from time to time by the board of directors, subject to the following conditions:</para><para>(a) All loans shall be evidenced by negotiable instruments of the corporation and shall bear interest at the rate determined by the board of directors to be the prime rate on unsecured commercial loans as of the date of the loan;</para><para>(b) All loan limits shall be established at the thousand dollar amount nearest the amount computed in accordance with this section;</para><para>(c) The total amount outstanding at any one time on loans to a development corporation made by any member, other than an insurance company, reciprocal exchange, or fraternal benefit society, shall not exceed the following limit, to be determined as of the time such member becomes a member, on the basis of figures contained in the most recent year-end statement prior to its application for membership:</para><para>(i) Banking associations, three percent of the paid-in capital and surplus;</para><para>(ii) Savings and loan associations, three percent of the general reserve account and surplus; and</para><para>(iii) Other financial institutions, such limits as may be approved from time to time by the board of directors of the development corporation;</para><para>(d) In the case of an insurance company, reciprocal exchange, and fraternal benefit society, the total amount outstanding at any time on loans to a development corporation shall be limited as follows: (i) For stock life insurance companies, one percent of capital and unassigned surplus, which amount loaned shall be included in and be a part of those investments authorized for stock life insurance companies under section 44-5153; (ii) for mutual life insurance companies or fraternal benefit societies, one percent of unassigned surplus, which amount loaned shall be included in and be a part of those investments authorized under such section; and (iii) for other insurance companies or reciprocal exchanges, one-tenth of one percent of admitted assets, which amount loaned shall be included in and be a part of those investments authorized under such section; and</para><para>(e) Each call for loans made by the corporation shall be prorated among the members of the corporation in substantially the same proportion that the loan limit of each member bears to the aggregate loan limits of all members.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 100, &#167; 9, p. 305; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1241, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 237, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 300, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>