<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,159"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,159</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Administrative dissolution; procedure and effect.</catchline><para>(1) If the Secretary of State determines that one or more grounds exist under section 21-20,158 for dissolving a corporation, he or she shall serve the corporation with written notice of his or her determination under section 21-2034.</para><para>(2) If the corporation does not correct each ground for dissolution or demonstrate to the reasonable satisfaction of the Secretary of State that each ground determined by the Secretary of State does not exist within sixty days after service of the notice is perfected under section 21-2034, the Secretary of State shall administratively dissolve the corporation by signing a certificate of dissolution that recites the ground or grounds for dissolution and its effective date. The Secretary of State shall file the original of the certificate and serve a copy on the corporation under section 21-2034.</para><para>(3) A corporation administratively dissolved continues its corporate existence but may not carry on any business, except that business necessary to wind up and liquidate its business and affairs under section 21-20,155 and notify claimants under sections 21-20,156 and 21-20,157.</para><para>(4) The administrative dissolution of a corporation shall not terminate the authority of its registered agent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 159. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Dissolved corporation,</emphasis> suit authorized, see section 25-312.01.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>
