<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2216"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2216</statuteno><catchline>Regulating board; certificate of registration; contents; filing; fee; display; electronic access; Secretary of State; duty; corporate suspension or dissolution; when.</catchline><para>(1) No corporation shall open, operate, or maintain an establishment or do business for any purposes set forth in the Nebraska Professional Corporation Act without (a) filing with the Secretary of State a certificate of registration from the regulating board of the particular profession for which the professional corporation is organized to do business, which certificate shall set forth the name and addresses of all shareholders as of the last day of the month preceding such filing, and (b) certifying that all shareholders, directors, and officers, except the secretary and the assistant secretary, are duly licensed to render the same professional services as those for which the corporation was organized. Application for a certificate of registration shall be made by the professional corporation to the regulating board in writing and shall contain the names of all officers, directors, shareholders, and professional employees of the professional corporation, the street address at which the applicant proposes to perform professional services, and such other information as may be required by the regulating board.</para><para>(2) If it appears to the regulating board that each shareholder, officer, director, and professional employee of the applicant, except the secretary and the assistant secretary, is licensed to practice the profession of the applicant and that each shareholder, officer, director, or professional employee is not otherwise disqualified from performing the professional services of the applicant, such regulating board shall certify, in duplicate upon a form bearing its date of issuance and prescribed by such regulating board, that such proposed or existing professional corporation complies with the provisions of the act and of the applicable rules and regulations of such regulating board. Each applicant for such registration certificate shall pay such regulating board a fee of twenty-five dollars for the issuance of such duplicate certificate.</para><para>(3) One copy of such certificate shall be prominently exposed to public view upon the premises of the principal place of business of each professional corporation organized under the act, and one copy shall be filed by the professional corporation with the Secretary of State who shall charge a fee as specified in section 21-205. The certificate from the regulating board shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State together with the articles of incorporation. A registration certificate bearing an issuance date more than twelve months old shall not be eligible for filing with the Secretary of State.</para><para>(4) When licensing records of regulating boards are electronically accessible, the regulating board, in conjunction with the Secretary of State, shall develop an automated process to allow the Secretary of State to electronically access and verify the records. The access shall be made in lieu of the certificate of registration or registration certificate being prepared and issued by the regulating board. The professional corporation shall file with the Secretary of State an application setting forth the name and residence addresses of all officers, directors, shareholders, and professional employees as of the last day of the month preceding the date of the application and shall file with the Secretary of State an annual update thereafter. Each application shall be accompanied by a licensure verification fee as specified in section 21-205. The Secretary of State shall verify that all of the directors, officers, shareholders, and professional employees listed on the application, except for the secretary and assistant secretary, are duly licensed or otherwise legally authorized to render the same professional service for which the professional corporation was organized or a service ancillary to those which the professional corporation renders. Verification shall be done by electronically accessing the regulating board's licensing records or through compacts or other certifying organizations recognized by the regulating board. If any director, officer, shareholder, or professional employee is not licensed or otherwise legally authorized to perform the professional service that the professional corporation was organized to render, or a service ancillary to those which the professional corporation renders, the corporation will be suspended. The biennial report and tax cannot be filed and paid in the office of the Secretary of State until the corporation attests in writing that the director, officer, shareholder, or professional employee is licensed or otherwise legally authorized to practice, which shall be verified by the Secretary of State, or is no longer a director, officer, shareholder, or professional employee of the corporation. When the biennial report and the tax become delinquent, the corporation shall be dissolved for nonpayment of taxes in compliance with section 21-323.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 121, &#167; 16, p. 560; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 489, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 157, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 749, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 524, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB628, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>