<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id281"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id283" statutenumber="21-29,117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id285">21-29,117</statuteno><catchline id="id286">Merger and consolidation; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 21-29,117 to 21-29,127:</para><para>(1) Constituent limited cooperative association means a limited cooperative association that is a party to a merger or consolidation;</para><para>(2) Constituent organization means an organization, other than a limited cooperative association, that is a party to a merger or consolidation;</para><para>(3) Governing statute of an organization means the statute that governs the organization's internal affairs;</para><para>(4) Organization means a limited cooperative association, limited cooperative association governed by a law other than the Nebraska Limited Cooperative Association Act, a general partnership, a limited liability partnership, a limited partnership, a limited liability company, a business trust, a corporation, a cooperative, or any other person having a governing statute. The term includes domestic and foreign organizations whether or not organized for profit;</para><para>(5) Personal liability means personal liability for a debt, liability, or other obligation of an organization which is imposed on a person that co-owns, has an interest in, or is a member of the organization:</para><para>(a) By the organization's governing statute solely by reason of co-owning, having an interest in, or being a member of the organization; or</para><para>(b) By the organization's organizational documents under a provision of the organization's governing statute authorizing those documents to make one or more specified persons liable for all or for specified debts, liabilities, and other obligations of the organization solely by reason of co-owning, having an interest in, or being a member of the organization; and</para><para>(6) Surviving organization means an organization into which one or more other organizations are merged or consolidated. A surviving organization may exist before the merger or consolidation or be created by the merger or consolidation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB848, &#167;  27.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
