<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2607" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2607</statuteno><catchline>Filing of articles of organization and current registration certificate.</catchline><para>(1) Duplicate originals of the articles of organization of a limited liability company shall be delivered to the Secretary of State along with the filing fees required by section 21-2634. If the limited liability company is organized to render a professional service, a current registration certificate as provided in sections 21-2631 to 21-2632 shall be delivered to the Secretary of State with such articles of organization and fees. If the Secretary of State finds that the articles of organization conform to law and, if applicable, a current registration certificate has been filed, the Secretary of State shall:</para><para>(a) Endorse on each of the duplicate originals the word filed and the month, day, and year of the filing thereof;</para><para>(b) File one of the duplicate originals and any registration certificate, if applicable, in his or her office; and</para><para>(c) Issue a certificate of organization to which he or she shall affix the other duplicate original.</para><para>(2) The certificate of organization, together with a duplicate original of the articles of organization affixed to it by the Secretary of State, shall be returned to the principal office of the limited liability company or to its representative.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 16, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 647, &#167; 8. </para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc>