<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2604</statuteno><catchline>Name.</catchline><para>(1) The words limited liability company, ltd. liability company, or ltd. liability co., or the abbreviation L.L.C. or LLC, shall be the last words of the name of every limited liability company, and the limited liability company name may not:</para><para>(a) Contain a word or phrase which indicates or implies that it is organized for a purpose other than one or more of the purposes contained in its articles of organization; or</para><para>(b) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, be the same as or deceptively similar to the name of a limited liability company or corporation existing under the laws of this state or a foreign limited liability company or corporation authorized to transact business in this state or a name the exclusive right to which is reserved in any manner provided under the laws of this state.</para><para>(2) A limited liability company may apply to the Secretary of State for authorization to use a name that is deceptively similar to, upon the records of the Secretary of State, one or more of the names described in subsection (1) of this section. The Secretary of State shall authorize use of the name applied for if:</para><para>(a) The other limited liability company or business entity consents to the use in writing; or</para><para>(b) The applicant delivers to the Secretary of State a certified copy of the final judgment of a court of competent jurisdiction that establishes the applicant's right to use the name applied for in this state.</para><para>(3) Omission of the words or an abbreviation required by subsection (1) of this section in the use of the name of the limited liability company shall render any person who participates in the omission or who knowingly acquiesces in such omission liable for indebtedness, damage, or liability caused by the omission.</para><para>(4) Identification as a limited liability company in the manner required by subsection (1) of this section shall appear at the end of the name of the limited liability company on all correspondence, stationery, checks, invoices, and documents executed by the limited liability company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 631, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB907, &#167; 3.</para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source>  </law></legaldoc>