<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,134"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,134</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Merger or share exchange with foreign corporation.</catchline><para>(1) One or more foreign corporations may merge or enter into a share exchange with one or more domestic corporations if:</para><para>(a) In a merger, the merger is permitted by the law of the state or country under whose law each foreign corporation is incorporated and each foreign corporation complies with that law in effecting the merger;</para><para>(b) In a share exchange, the corporation whose shares will be acquired is a domestic corporation, whether or not a share exchange is permitted by the law of the state or country under whose law the acquiring corporation is incorporated;</para><para>(c) The foreign corporation complies with section 21-20,132 if it is the surviving corporation of the merger or acquiring corporation of the share exchange; and</para><para>(d) Each domestic corporation complies with the applicable provisions of sections 21-20,128 to 21-20,131 and, if it is the surviving corporation of the merger or acquiring corporation of the share exchange, with section 21-20,132.</para><para>(2) Upon the merger or share exchange taking effect, the surviving foreign corporation of a merger and the acquiring foreign corporation of a share exchange shall be deemed:</para><para>(a) To agree that it may be served with process within or without this state in a proceeding in the courts of this state to enforce any obligation or the rights of dissenting shareholders of each domestic corporation party to the merger or share exchange; and</para><para>(b) To agree that it will promptly pay to the dissenting shareholder of each domestic corporation party to the merger or share exchange the amount, if any, to which they are entitled under sections 21-20,137 to 21-20,150.</para><para>(3) This section shall not limit the power of a foreign corporation to acquire all or part of the shares of one or more classes or series of a domestic corporation through a voluntary exchange or otherwise.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 134. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
