<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id6" statutenumber="21-2003"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">21-2003</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Filing requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A document shall satisfy the requirements of this section and of
any other provision of law that adds to or varies these requirements to be
entitled to filing by the Secretary of State.</para>
<para>(2) The Business Corporation Act shall require or permit filing the
document in the office of the Secretary of State.</para>
<para>(3) The document shall contain the information required by the act.
It may contain other information as well.</para>
<para>(4) The document shall be typewritten or printed.</para>
<para>(5) The document shall be in the English language. A corporate name
shall not be required to be in English if written in English letters or Arabic
or Roman numerals. The certificate of existence required of foreign corporations
shall not be required to be in English if accompanied by a reasonably authenticated
English translation.</para>
<para>(6) The document shall be executed:</para>
<para>(a) By the chairperson of the board of directors of a domestic or foreign
corporation, by its president, or by another of its officers;</para>
<para>(b) If directors have not been selected or the corporation has not been
formed, by an incorporator; or</para>
<para>(c) If the corporation is in the hands of a receiver, trustee, or other
court-appointed fiduciary, by that fiduciary.</para>
<para>(7) The person executing the document shall sign it and state beneath
or opposite his or her signature his or her name and the capacity in which
he or she signs. The document may, but shall not be required to, contain (a)
the corporate seal, (b) an attestation by the secretary or an assistant secretary,
and (c) an acknowledgment, verification, or proof.</para>
<para>(8) If the Secretary of State has prescribed a mandatory form for the
document under section 21-2004, the document shall be in or on the prescribed
form.</para>
<para>(9) The document shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing
and shall be accompanied by one exact or conformed copy, except as provided
in sections 21-2033 and 21-20,176, the correct filing fee, and any tax, license
fee, or penalty required by law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB528, &#167;  1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB791, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Occupation tax,</emphasis> see Chapter 21, article 3.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>