<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2628"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2628</statuteno><catchline>Amendment of articles of organization.</catchline><para>(1) The articles of organization of a limited liability company shall be amended when:</para><para>(a) There is a change in the name of the limited liability company;</para><para>(b) There is a change in the purpose for which the limited liability company is organized;</para><para>(c) There is a change in stated capital that reduces the stated capital below the amount in the articles of organization;</para><para>(d) There is a change in the time, if any, stated in the articles of organization for the dissolution of the limited liability company;</para><para>(e) A time is fixed for the dissolution of the limited liability company if no time is specified in the articles of organization; or</para><para>(f) The members desire to make a change in any other statement in the articles of organization so the articles will accurately represent the agreement between the members.</para><para>(2) The form for evidencing an amendment to the articles of organization of a limited liability company shall be prescribed by the Secretary of State and shall contain such terms and provisions as determined by the Secretary of State. The articles of organization may be amended upon the affirmative vote of a majority in interest of the members or in such other manner as is provided in the articles of organization. The amendment shall be executed by an authorized representative of the limited liability company. Duplicate originals of the amendment shall be forwarded to the Secretary of State for filing with the filing fee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 187; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 631, &#167; 16. </para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc>