<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2606</statuteno><catchline>Articles of organization.</catchline><para>(1) The articles of organization of a limited liability company shall set forth:</para><para>(a) The name of the limited liability company;</para><para>(b) The purpose for which the limited liability company is organized but, if the limited liability company provides a professional service, the articles of organization shall contain a statement of the profession to be practiced by the limited liability company;</para><para>(c) The address of its principal place of business in this state and the name and address of its current registered agent in this state. A post office box number may be provided in addition to the street address;</para><para>(d) The total amount of cash contributed to stated capital and a description and agreed value of property other than cash contributed;</para><para>(e) The total additional contributions agreed to be made by all members and the times at which or events upon the happening of which the contributions will be made;</para><para>(f) The right, if given, of the members to admit additional members and the terms and conditions of the admission; and</para><para>(g) If the limited liability company is to be managed by one or more managers, the names and addresses of the persons who will serve as managers until the successor is elected, or if the management of a limited liability company is reserved to the one or more classes of members, the names and addresses of such members.</para><para>(2) The articles of organization of a limited liability company may set forth:</para><para>(a) The period of its duration, which may be perpetual. If the articles of organization do not state a period of duration, the limited liability company shall have perpetual existence; and</para><para>(b) Any other provision not inconsistent with law which the members elect to set out in the articles of organization for the regulation of the internal affairs of the limited liability company, including any provisions which are required or permitted to be set out in the operating agreement of the limited liability company.</para><para>(3) It shall not be necessary to set out in the articles of organization any of the powers enumerated in the Limited Liability Company Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 631, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 647, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167;  23.</para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source>  </law></legaldoc>