
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2209"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2209</statuteno><catchline>Provision of services in another
jurisdiction; license required, when; foreign corporation; requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1) A professional corporation may provide professional services in
another jurisdiction if such corporation complies with all applicable laws
of such jurisdiction regulating the rendering of professional services. Notwithstanding
any other provision of the Nebraska Professional Corporation Act, no shareholder,
director, officer, employee, or agent of a professional corporation shall
be required to be licensed to render professional services in this state or
to reside in this state if such shareholder, director, officer, employee,
or agent does not render professional services in this state and is licensed
in one or more states, territories of the United States, or the District of
Columbia to render a professional service described in the professional corporation's
articles of incorporation.</para>
<para>(2) A foreign professional corporation shall not transact business in
this state unless it renders one of the professional services specified in
subdivision (3) of section 21-2202 and complies with the provisions of the
act, including, without limitation, registration with the appropriate regulating
board in this state as provided in sections 21-2216 to 21-2218. A foreign
professional corporation shall not transact business in this state if the
laws of the jurisdiction under which such foreign professional corporation
is incorporated do not allow for a professional corporation incorporated under
the laws of this state to transact business in such jurisdiction.</para>
<para>(3)(a) A foreign professional corporation shall (i) apply for a certificate
of authority in the same manner as a foreign business corporation pursuant
to sections 21-2,203 to 21-2,220 and (ii)
file with the Secretary of State a current certificate of registration as
provided in sections 21-2216 to 21-2218.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in the Nebraska Professional Corporation
Act, foreign professional corporations shall enjoy all the powers, benefits,
and privileges and shall be subject to all the duties, restrictions, and liabilities
of a foreign business corporation under sections 21-301 to 21-325.02 and
the Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act.</para>
<para>(c) A foreign professional corporation shall not be required as a condition
to obtaining a certificate of authority to have all of its shareholders, directors,
and officers licensed to render professional services in this state if all
of its shareholders, directors, and officers, except the secretary and assistant
secretary, are licensed in one or more states or territories of the United
States or the District of Columbia to render a professional service described
in its articles of incorporation and any shareholder, director, officer, employee,
or agent who renders professional services within this state on behalf of
the foreign professional corporation is licensed to render professional services
in this state.</para>
<para>(d) A foreign professional corporation is
not required to obtain a certificate of authority to transact
business in this state unless it maintains or intends to maintain an office
in this state for the conduct of business or professional practice.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section, foreign professional corporation means a corporation which is organized under
the law of any other state or territory of the United States or the District
of Columbia for the specific purpose of rendering professional services and
which has as its shareholders only individuals who are duly licensed or otherwise
legally authorized to render the same professional services as the corporation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 488, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 210; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 16, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 272.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Model Business Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>