<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,166"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,166</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2017. Judicial dissolution; election to purchase.</catchline><para>(1) In a proceeding under subdivision (2) of section 21-20,162 to dissolve a corporation that has no shares listed on a national securities exchange or regularly traded in a market maintained by one or more members of a national or affiliated securities association, the corporation may elect or, if it fails to elect, one or more shareholders may elect to purchase all shares owned by the petitioning shareholder at the fair value of the shares. An election pursuant to this section shall be irrevocable unless the court determines that it is equitable to set aside or modify the election.</para><para>(2) An election to purchase pursuant to this section may be filed with the court at any time within ninety days after the filing of the petition under subdivision (2) of section 21-20,162 or at such later time as the court in its discretion may allow. If the election to purchase is filed by one or more shareholders, the corporation shall, within ten days thereafter, give written notice to all shareholders, other than the petitioner. The notice shall state the name and number of shares owned by the petitioner and the name and number of shares owned by each electing shareholder and shall advise the recipients of their right to join in the election to purchase shares in accordance with this section. Shareholders who wish to participate shall file notice of their intention to join in the purchase no later than thirty days after the effective date of the notice to them. All shareholders who have filed an election or notice of their intention to participate in the election to purchase thereby become parties to the proceeding and shall participate in the purchase in proportion to their ownership of shares as of the date the first election was filed, unless they otherwise agree or the court otherwise directs. After an election has been filed by the corporation or one or more shareholders, the proceeding under subdivision (2) of section 21-20,162 may not be discontinued or settled, nor may the petitioning shareholder sell or otherwise dispose of his or her shares, unless the court determines that it would be equitable to the corporation and the shareholders, other than the petitioner, to permit such discontinuance, settlement, sale, or other disposition.</para><para>(3) If, within sixty days of the filing of the first election, the parties reach agreement as to the fair value and terms of purchase of the petitioner's shares, the court shall enter an order directing the purchase of the petitioner's shares upon the terms and conditions agreed to by the parties.</para><para>(4) If the parties are unable to reach an agreement as provided for in subsection (3) of this section, the court, upon application of any party, shall stay such proceedings and determine the fair value of the petitioner's shares as of the day before the date on which the petition under subdivision (2) of section 21-20,162 was filed or as of such other date as the court deems appropriate under the circumstances.</para><para>(5)(a) Upon determining the fair value of the shares, the court shall enter an order directing the purchase upon such terms and conditions as the court deems appropriate, which may include payment of the purchase price in installments when necessary in the interest of equity, provision for security to assure payment of the purchase price and any additional costs, fees, and expenses as may have been awarded, and, if the shares are to be purchased by shareholders, the allocation of shares among them. In allocating petitioner's shares among holders of different classes of shares, the court should attempt to preserve the existing distribution of voting rights among holders of different classes insofar as practicable and may direct that holders of a specific class or classes shall not participate in the purchase. Interest may be allowed at the rate specified in section 45-104, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, and from the date determined by the court to be equitable, but if the court finds that the refusal of the petitioning shareholder to accept an offer of payment was arbitrary or otherwise not in good faith, no interest shall be allowed.</para><para>(b) If the court finds that the petitioning shareholder had probable grounds for relief under subdivision (2)(a)(ii) or (iv) of section 21-20,162, it may award to the petitioning shareholder reasonable attorney's fees and expenses and fees and expenses of any experts employed by him or her.</para><para>(6) Upon entry of an order under subsection (3) or subdivision (5)(a) of this section, the court shall dismiss the petition to dissolve the corporation under section 21-20,162, and the petitioning shareholder shall no longer have any rights or status as a shareholder of the corporation, except the right to receive the amounts awarded to him or her by the order of the court which shall be enforceable in the same manner as any other judgment.</para><para>(7) The purchase ordered pursuant to subdivision (5)(a) of this section shall be made within ten days after the date the order becomes final unless before that time the corporation files with the court a notice of its intention to adopt articles of dissolution pursuant to sections 21-20,152 and 21-20,153, which articles shall then be adopted and filed within fifty days thereafter. Upon the filing of such articles of dissolution the corporation shall be dissolved in accordance with the provisions of sections 21-20,155 to 21-20,157 and the order entered pursuant to subsection (5) of this section shall no longer be of any force or effect except that the court may award the petitioning shareholder reasonable fees and expenses in accordance with the provisions of subdivision (5)(b) of this section and the petitioner may continue to pursue any claims previously asserted on behalf of the corporation.</para><para>(8) Any payment by the corporation pursuant to an order under subsection (3) or (5) of this section, other than an award of fees and expenses pursuant to subsection (5) of this section, shall be subject to the provisions of section 21-2050.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 166; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 396, &#167; 23.</para></source><annotation><para>A trial court's valuation of a closely held corporation is reasonable if it has an acceptable basis in fact and principle. Detter v. Miracle Hills Animal Hosp., 269 Neb. 164, 691 N.W.2d 107 (2005).</para><para>The existence of professional goodwill as a distributable asset in an action for the dissolution of a professional entity presents a question of fact. Detter v. Miracle Hills Animal Hosp., 269 Neb. 164, 691 N.W.2d 107 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
