<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id123">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id125" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-20,196"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,196</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Conversion; articles of conversion.</catchline>
<para>(1) After
a plan of conversion is approved, a domestic corporation that is being converted
shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing articles of conversion,
which shall include all of the following:</para>
<para>(a) A statement
that the domestic corporation has been converted into another entity;</para>
<para>(b) The name
and form of the other entity and the jurisdiction of its governing statute;</para>
<para>(c) The date
the conversion is effective under the governing statute of the converted entity;</para>
<para>(d) A statement
that the conversion was approved as required by section 21-20,195;</para>
<para>(e) A statement
that the conversion was approved as required by the governing statute of the
converted entity; and</para><para>(f) A domestic corporation converting into a foreign limited liability
company shall deliver to the office of the Secretary of State for filing (i)
a certificate which sets forth all of the information required to be in the
certificate or other instrument of conversion filed pursuant to the laws under
which the resulting foreign limited liability company is formed and (ii) an
agreement that the resulting foreign limited liability company may be served
with process within or outside this state in any proceeding in the courts
of this state for the enforcement of any obligation of the former domestic
corporation.</para><para>(2) The conversion becomes effective as provided by the governing
statute of the domestic or foreign limited liability company.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1018, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
