<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id51">
<sectno id="id52">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id53" statutenumber="21-2060"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno id="id55">21-2060</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Proxies.</catchline>
<para>(1) A shareholder may vote his or her shares in person or
by proxy.</para>
<para>(2) A shareholder or
the shareholder's agent or attorney in fact may appoint a proxy
to vote or otherwise act for the shareholder by
signing an appointment form or by an
electronic transmission. An electronic transmission shall contain or be accompanied
by information from which one can determine that the shareholder or the shareholder's
agent or attorney in fact authorized the transmission.</para>
<para>(3) An appointment of a proxy shall be effective when a signed appointment form or an electronic
transmission of the appointment is received by the inspector of election or the secretary
or other officer or agent of
the corporation authorized to tabulate votes. An appointment shall
be valid for eleven months unless a longer period is expressly provided in
the appointment form or electronic
transmission.</para>
<para>(4) An appointment of a proxy shall be revocable by the shareholder
unless the appointment form or
electronic transmission conspicuously states that it is irrevocable
and the appointment is coupled with an interest. Appointments coupled with
an interest shall include the appointment of:</para>
<para>(a) A pledgee;</para>
<para>(b) A person who purchased or agreed to purchase the shares;</para>
<para>(c) A creditor of the corporation who extended it credit under
terms requiring the appointment;</para>
<para>(d) An employee of the corporation whose employment contract
requires the appointment; or</para>
<para>(e) A party to a voting agreement created under section 21-2068.</para>
<para>(5) The death or incapacity of the shareholder appointing
a proxy shall not affect the right of the corporation to accept the proxy's
authority unless notice of the death or incapacity is received by the secretary
or other officer or agent authorized to tabulate votes before the proxy exercises
his or her authority under the appointment.</para>
<para>(6) An appointment made irrevocable under subsection (4) of
this section shall be revoked when the interest with which it is coupled is
extinguished.</para>
<para>(7) A transferee for value of shares subject to an irrevocable
appointment may revoke the appointment if he or she did not know of its existence
when he or she acquired the shares and the existence of the irrevocable appointment
was not noted conspicuously on the certificate representing the shares or
on the information statement for shares without certificates.</para>
<para>(8) Subject to section 21-2062 and to any express limitation
on the proxy's authority appearing on the face of the appointment form or electronic transmission,
a corporation shall be entitled to accept the proxy's vote or other action
as that of the shareholder making the appointment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB528, &#167; 4.</para></source><annotation><para>Although subsection (4) of this section lists several examples of "[a]ppointments coupled with an interest," these examples are not exhaustive and other arrangements may also be held to be "coupled with an interest." In that regard, subsection (4) incorporates the common-law test, based on principles of agency law, for whether an appointment is coupled with an interest. Bamford v. Bamford, Inc., 279 Neb. 259, 777 N.W.2d 573 (2010).</para><para>An appointment made irrevocable under subsection (4) of this section is revoked when the interest with which it is coupled is extinguished. Bamford v. Bamford, Inc., 279 Neb. 259, 777 N.W.2d 573 (2010).</para><para>This section provides that shareholders may vote in person or by proxy and establishes the basic rules for appointing a proxy. Bamford v. Bamford, Inc., 279 Neb. 259, 777 N.W.2d 573 (2010).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
