<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,185"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,185</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Corporate records; court-ordered inspection.</catchline><para>(1) If a corporation does not allow a shareholder who complies with subsection (1) of section 21-20,183 to inspect and copy any records required by that subsection to be available for inspection, the district court of the county where the corporation's principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered office, is located, may summarily order inspection and copying of the records demanded at the corporation's expense upon application of the shareholder.</para><para>(2) If a corporation does not within a reasonable time allow a shareholder to inspect and copy any other record, the shareholder who complies with subsections (2) and (3) of section 21-20,183 may apply to the district court in the county where the corporation's principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered office, is located, for an order to permit inspection and copying of the records demanded. The court shall dispose of an application under this subsection on an expedited basis.</para><para>(3) If the court orders inspection and copying of the records demanded, it shall also order the corporation to pay the shareholder's costs, including reasonable attorney's fees, incurred to obtain the order, unless the corporation proves that it refused inspection in good faith because it had a reasonable basis for doubt about the right of the shareholder to inspect the records demanded.</para><para>(4) If the court orders inspection and copying of the records demanded, it may impose reasonable restrictions on the use or distribution of the records by the demanding shareholder.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 185. </para></source></law></legaldoc>