<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2074"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2074</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Derivative proceedings; dismissal.</catchline><para>(1) A derivative proceeding shall be dismissed by the court on motion by the corporation if one of the groups specified in subsection (2) or (6) of this section has determined, in good faith, after conducting a reasonable inquiry upon which its conclusions are based, that the maintenance of the derivative proceeding is not in the best interests of the corporation.</para><para>(2) Unless a panel is appointed pursuant to subsection (6) of this section, the determination in subsection (1) of this section shall be made by:</para><para>(a) A majority vote of independent directors present at a meeting of the board of directors if the independent directors constitute a quorum; or</para><para>(b) A majority vote of a committee consisting of two or more independent directors appointed by a majority vote of independent directors present at a meeting of the board of directors, whether or not such independent directors constituted a quorum.</para><para>(3) None of the following shall by itself cause a director to be considered not independent for purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) The nomination or election of the director by persons who are defendants in the derivative proceeding or against whom action is demanded;</para><para>(b) The naming of the director as a defendant in the derivative proceeding or as a person against whom action is demanded; or</para><para>(c) The approval by the director of the act being challenged in the derivative proceeding or demand if the act resulted in no personal benefit to the director.</para><para>(4) If a derivative proceeding is commenced after a determination has been made rejecting a demand by a shareholder, the complaint shall allege with particularity facts establishing either (a) that a majority of the board of directors did not consist of independent directors at the time the determination was made or (b) that the requirements of subsection (1) of this section have not been met.</para><para>(5) If a majority of the board of directors does not consist of independent directors at the time the determination is made, the corporation shall have the burden of proving that the requirements of subsection (1) of this section have been met. If a majority of the board of directors consists of independent directors at the time the determination is made, the plaintiff shall have the burden of proving that the requirements of subsection (1) of this section have not been met.</para><para>(6) The court may appoint a panel of one or more independent persons upon motion by the corporation to make a determination whether the maintenance of the derivative proceeding is in the best interests of the corporation. In such case, the plaintiff shall have the burden of proving that the requirements of subsection (1) of this section have not been met.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 74. </para></source></law></legaldoc>