<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,183"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,183</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Inspection of corporate records by shareholders.</catchline><para>(1) A shareholder of a corporation shall be entitled to inspect and copy during regular business hours at the corporation's principal office any of the records of the corporation described in subsection (5) of section 21-20,182 if he or she gives the corporation written notice of his or her demand at least five business days before the date on which he or she wishes to inspect and copy.</para><para>(2) A shareholder of a corporation shall be entitled to inspect and copy during regular business hours at a reasonable location specified by the corporation any of the following records of the corporation if the shareholder meets the requirements of subsection (3) of this section and gives the corporation written notice of his or her demand at least five business days before the date on which he or she wishes to inspect and copy:</para><para>(a) Excerpts from minutes of any meeting of the board of directors, records of any action of a committee of the board of directors while acting in place of the board of directors on behalf of the corporation, minutes of any meeting of the shareholders, and records of action taken by the shareholders or board of directors without a meeting, to the extent not subject to inspection under subsection (1) of this section;</para><para>(b) Accounting records of the corporation; and</para><para>(c) The record of shareholders.</para><para>(3) A shareholder may inspect and copy the records described in subsection (2) of this section only if:</para><para>(a) The shareholder's demand is made in good faith and for a proper purpose;</para><para>(b) The shareholder describes with reasonable particularity his or her purpose and the records he or she desires to inspect; and</para><para>(c) The records are directly connected with the shareholder's purpose.</para><para>(4) The right of inspection granted by this section may not be abolished or limited by a corporation's articles of incorporation or bylaws.</para><para>(5) This section shall not affect:</para><para>(a) The right of a shareholder to inspect records under section 21-2058 or, if the shareholder is in litigation with the corporation, to the same extent as any other litigant; or</para><para>(b) The power of a court, independently of the Business Corporation Act, to compel the production of corporate records for examination.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section, shareholder shall include a beneficial owner whose shares are held in a voting trust or by a nominee on his or her behalf.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 183. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
