<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,137"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,137</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Dissenters' rights; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 21-20,137 to 21-20,150:</para><para>(1) Beneficial shareholder shall mean the person who is a beneficial owner of shares held in a voting trust or by a nominee as the record shareholder;</para><para>(2) Corporation shall mean the issuer of the shares held by a dissenter before the corporate action or the surviving or acquiring corporation by merger or share exchange of that issuer;</para><para>(3) Dissenter shall mean a shareholder who is entitled to dissent from corporate action under section 21-20,138 and who exercises that right when and in the manner required by sections 21-20,140 to 21-20,148;</para><para>(4) Fair value, with respect to a dissenter's shares, shall mean the value of the shares immediately before the effectuation of the corporate action to which the dissenter objects, excluding any appreciation or depreciation in anticipation of the corporate action unless exclusion would be inequitable;</para><para>(5) Interest shall mean interest from the effective date of the corporate action until the date of payment at the rate specified in section 45-104, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature;</para><para>(6) Record shareholder shall mean the person in whose name shares are registered in the records of a corporation or the beneficial shareholder to the extent of the rights granted by a nominee certificate on file with a corporation; and</para><para>(7) Shareholder shall mean the record shareholder or the beneficial shareholder.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 137. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
