<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,169"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,169</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Foreign corporation; transacting business without certificate of authority; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A foreign corporation transacting business in this state without a certificate of authority may not maintain a proceeding in any court in this state until it obtains a certificate of authority.</para><para>(2) The successor to a foreign corporation that transacted business in this state without a certificate of authority and the assignee of a cause of action arising out of that business may not maintain a proceeding based on that cause of action in any court in this state until the foreign corporation or its successor obtains a certificate of authority.</para><para>(3) A court in this state may stay a proceeding commenced by a foreign corporation, its successor, or its assignee until it determines whether the foreign corporation or its successor requires a certificate of authority. If the court determines that a certificate of authority is required, the court may further stay the proceeding until the foreign corporation or its successor obtains the certificate.</para><para>(4) A foreign corporation shall be liable for a civil penalty of five hundred dollars for each day, but not to exceed a total of ten thousand dollars for each year, it transacts business in this state without a certificate of authority. The Attorney General may collect all penalties due under this subsection and shall remit them to the State Treasurer for credit to the permanent school fund.</para><para>(5) Notwithstanding subsections (1) and (2) of this section, the failure of a foreign corporation to obtain a certificate of authority shall not impair the validity of its corporate acts or prevent it from defending any proceeding in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 169. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Permanent school fund,</emphasis> see Article VII, section 5, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>
