<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id12" statutenumber="21-2005"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2005</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Fees.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Secretary of State shall collect the fees prescribed
by this section when the documents described in this subsection are delivered
to him or her for filing:</para>
<para>(a) Articles of incorporation or documents relating to domestication:</para>
<para>(i) If the capital stock is $10,000 or less, the fee shall
be $60;</para>
<para>(ii) If the capital stock is more than $10,000 but does not
exceed $25,000, the fee shall be $100;</para>
<para>(iii) If the capital stock is more than $25,000 but does not
exceed $50,000, the fee shall be $150;</para>
<para>(iv) If the capital stock is more than $50,000 but does not
exceed $75,000, the fee shall be $225;</para>
<para>(v) If the capital stock is more than $75,000 but does not
exceed $100,000, the fee shall be $300; and</para>
<para>(vi) If the capital stock is more than $100,000, the fee shall
be $300, plus $3 additional for each $1,000 in excess of $100,000.</para>
<para>For purposes of computing this fee, the capital stock of a
corporation organized under the laws of any other state that domesticates
in this state, and which stock does not have a par value, shall be deemed
to have a par value of an amount per share equal to the amount paid in as
capital for each of such shares as are then issued and outstanding, and in
no event less than one dollar per share.</para>
<para>(b) Articles of incorporation or documents relating to domestication
if filed by an insurer holding a certificate of authority issued by the Director
of Insurance, the fee shall be $300.</para>
<para>(c) Application for reserved name...$25</para>
<para>(d) Notice of transfer of reserved name...$25</para>
<para>(e) Application for registered name...$25</para>
<para>(f) Application for renewal of registered name...$25</para>
<para>(g) Corporation's statement of change of registered agent
or registered office or both...$25</para>
<para>(h) Agent's statement of change of registered office for each
affected corporation...$25 not to exceed a total of...$1,000</para>
<para>(i) Agent's statement of resignation...No fee</para>
<para>(j) Amendment of articles of incorporation...$25</para>
<para>(k) Restatement of articles of incorporation...$25 with amendment
of articles...$25</para>
<para>(l) Articles of merger, share exchange, or conversion...$25</para>
<para>(m) Articles of dissolution...$45</para>
<para>(n) Articles of revocation of dissolution...$25</para>
<para>(o) Certificate of administrative dissolution...No fee</para>
<para>(p) Application for reinstatement...$25</para>
<para>(q) Certificate of reinstatement...No fee</para>
<para>(r) Certificate of judicial dissolution...No fee</para>
<para>(s) Application for certificate of authority...$130</para>
<para>(t) Application for amended certificate of authority...$25</para>
<para>(u) Application for certificate of withdrawal...$25</para>
<para>(v) Certificate of revocation of authority to transact business...No
fee</para>
<para>(w) Articles of correction...$25</para>
<para>(x) Application for certificate of existence or authorization...$25</para>
<para>(y) Any other document required or permitted to be filed by
the Business Corporation Act...$25.</para>
<para>(2) The Secretary of State shall collect a recording fee of
five dollars per page in addition to the fees set forth in subsection (1)
of this section.</para>
<para>(3) The Secretary of State shall collect the following fees
for copying and certifying the copy of any filed document relating to a domestic
or foreign corporation:</para>
<para>(a) One dollar per page for copying; and</para>
<para>(b) Ten dollars for the certificate.</para>
<para>(4) All fees set forth in this section shall be collected
by the Secretary of State and remitted to the State Treasurer and credited
two-thirds to the General Fund and one-third to the Corporation Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1036, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB117, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB907, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1018, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
