<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,113</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Director; conflict of interest; judicial action.</catchline><para>(1) A transaction effected or proposed to be effected by a corporation or by a subsidiary of the corporation or any other entity in which the corporation has a controlling interest, that is not a director's conflicting interest transaction, may not be enjoined or set aside or give rise to an award of damages or other sanctions in a proceeding by a shareholder or by or in the right of the corporation because a director of the corporation, or any person with whom or which he or she has a personal, economic, or other association, has an interest in the transaction.</para><para>(2) A director's conflicting interest transaction may not be enjoined or set aside or give rise to an award of damages or other sanctions in a proceeding by a shareholder or by or in the right of the corporation because the director, or any person with whom or which he or she has a personal, economic, or other association, has an interest in the transaction, if:</para><para>(a) Directors' action respecting the transaction was at any time taken in compliance with section 21-20,114;</para><para>(b) Shareholders' action respecting the transaction was at any time taken in compliance with section 21-20,115; or</para><para>(c) The transaction, judged according to the circumstances at the time of commitment, is established to have been fair to the corporation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 113. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
