<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-29,103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-29,103</statuteno><catchline>Application for certificate of authority.</catchline><para>(1) A foreign limited cooperative association may apply for a certificate of authority to transact business in this state by delivering an application to the Secretary of State for filing. The application shall state:</para><para>(a) The name of the foreign limited cooperative association and, if the name does not comply with section 21-2908, an alternative name adopted pursuant to section 21-29,106;</para><para>(b) The name of the state or other jurisdiction under whose law the foreign limited cooperative association is organized;</para><para>(c) The street and mailing addresses of the foreign limited cooperative association's designated office and, if the laws of the jurisdiction under which the foreign limited cooperative association is organized require the foreign limited cooperative association to maintain an office in that jurisdiction, the street and mailing addresses of the required office;</para><para>(d) The name and street and mailing addresses of the foreign limited cooperative association's agent for service of process in this state; and</para><para>(e) The name and street and mailing addresses of each of the foreign limited cooperative association's current directors and officers.</para><para>(2) A foreign limited cooperative association shall deliver with the completed application a certificate of good standing or existence or a similar record signed by the Secretary of State or other official having custody of the foreign limited cooperative association's publicly filed records in the state or other jurisdiction under whose law the foreign limited cooperative association is organized.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 103.</para></source></law></legaldoc>