<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id119"><sectno id="id120">Sec. 33.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id121" statutenumber="21-29,127"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id123">21-29,127</statuteno><catchline id="id124">Effect of merger or consolidation.</catchline><para>When a merger or consolidation becomes effective:</para><para>(1) The surviving organization continues or comes into existence;</para><para>(2) Each constituent organization that merges or consolidates into the surviving organization ceases to exist as a separate entity;</para><para>(3) All property owned by each constituent organization that ceases to exist vests in the surviving organization;</para><para>(4) All debts, liabilities, and other obligations of each constituent organization that ceases to exist continue as obligations of the surviving organization;</para><para>(5) An action or proceeding pending by or against any constituent organization that ceases to exist may be continued as if the merger or consolidation had not occurred;</para><para>(6) Except as prohibited by other law, all of the rights, privileges, immunities, powers, and purposes of each constituent organization that ceases to exist vest in the surviving organization;</para><para>(7) Except as otherwise provided in the plan of merger or consolidation, the terms and conditions of the plan take effect;</para><para>(8) Except as otherwise agreed, if a constituent limited cooperative association ceases to exist, the merger or consolidation does not dissolve the limited cooperative association for purposes of section 21-2987;</para><para>(9) If the surviving organization is created by the merger or consolidation:</para><para>(a) If it is a limited cooperative association, the articles of organization become effective; or</para><para>(b) If it is an organization other than a limited cooperative association, the organizational document that creates the organization becomes effective; and</para><para>(10) If the surviving organization exists before the merger or consolidation, any amendments provided for in the articles of merger or consolidation for the organizational document that created the organization become effective.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 127; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB848, &#167;  33.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
