<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,168"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,168</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Foreign corporation; certificate of authority.</catchline><para>(1) A foreign corporation may not transact business in this state until it obtains a certificate of authority from the Secretary of State.</para><para>(2) The following activities, among others, shall not constitute transacting business within the meaning of subsection (1) of this section:</para><para>(a) Maintaining, defending, or settling any proceeding;</para><para>(b) Holding meetings of the board of directors or shareholders or carrying on other activities concerning internal corporate affairs;</para><para>(c) Maintaining bank accounts;</para><para>(d) Maintaining offices or agencies for the transfer, exchange, and registration of the corporation's own securities or maintaining trustees or depositaries with respect to those securities;</para><para>(e) Selling through independent contractors;</para><para>(f) Soliciting or obtaining orders, whether by mail or through employees or agents or otherwise, if the orders require acceptance outside this state before they become contracts;</para><para>(g) Creating or acquiring indebtedness, mortgages, and security interests in real or personal property;</para><para>(h) Securing or collecting debts or enforcing mortgages and security interests in property securing the debts;</para><para>(i) Owning, without more, real or personal property;</para><para>(j) Conducting an isolated transaction that is completed within thirty days and that is not one in the course of repeated transactions of a like nature;</para><para>(k) Transacting business in interstate commerce; or</para><para>(l) Acting as a foreign corporate trustee to the extent authorized under section 30-3820.</para><para>(3) The list of activities in subsection (2) of this section shall not be construed as exhaustive.</para><para>(4) The requirements of the Business Corporation Act shall not be applicable to foreign or alien insurers which are subject to the requirements of Chapter 44.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 168; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 113.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
