<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id210"><sectno id="id211">Sec. 20.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id212" statutenumber="21-2980"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id214">21-2980</statuteno><catchline id="id215">Allocation of profits and losses.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to subsection (2) of this section, the articles of organization or bylaws shall provide for the allocation of net proceeds, savings, margins, profits, and losses between classes or groups of members.</para><para>(2)(a) Unless the articles of organization or bylaws otherwise provide, patron members shall be allocated at least fifty percent of the net proceeds, savings, margins, profits, and losses in any fiscal year. The articles of organization or bylaws shall not reduce the percentage allocated to patron members to less than fifteen percent of the net proceeds.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this subsection, the following rules apply:</para><para>(i) Amounts paid or due on contracts for the delivery to the association by patron members of products, goods, or services are not considered amounts allocated to patron members; and</para><para>(ii) Amounts paid, due, or allocated to investor members as a stated, fixed return on equity are not considered amounts allocated to investor members.</para><para>(3) Unless otherwise provided in the articles of organization or bylaws, in order to determine the amount of net proceeds, savings, margins, and profits, the board of directors may set aside a portion of the revenue, whether or not allocated to members, after accounting for other expenses, for purposes of:</para><para>(a) Creating or accumulating a capital reserve; and</para><para>(b) Creating or accumulating reserves for specific purposes, including expansion and replacement of capital assets and other necessary business purposes.</para><para>(4) Subject to subsection (5) of this section and the articles of organization or bylaws, the board of directors shall allocate the amount remaining after the allocations under subsections (1) through (3) of this section:</para><para>(a) To patron members annually in accordance with the ratio of each member's patronage during the period to total patronage of all patron members during the period; and</para><para>(b) To investor members, if any, in accordance with the ratio of each investor member's limited contribution to the total initial contribution of all investor members.</para><para>(5) For purposes of allocation of net proceeds, savings, margins, profits, and losses to patron members, the articles of organization or bylaws may establish allocation units based on function, division, district, department, allocation units, pooling arrangements, members' contributions, or other methods.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB848, &#167;  20.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
