<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,156"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,156</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Voluntary dissolution; known claims against dissolved corporation.</catchline><para>(1) A dissolved corporation may dispose of the known claims against it by following the procedure described in this section.</para><para>(2) The dissolved corporation shall notify its known claimants in writing of the dissolution at any time after its effective date. The written notice shall:</para><para>(a) Describe the information that shall be included in a claim;</para><para>(b) Provide a mailing address where a claim may be sent;</para><para>(c) State the deadline, which may not be fewer than one hundred twenty days from the effective date of the written notice, by which the dissolved corporation shall receive the claim; and</para><para>(d) State that the claim will be barred if not received by the deadline.</para><para>(3) A claim against the dissolved corporation shall be barred:</para><para>(a) If a claimant who was given written notice under subsection (2) of this section does not deliver the claim to the dissolved corporation by the deadline; or</para><para>(b) If a claimant whose claim was rejected by the dissolved corporation does not commence a proceeding to enforce the claim within ninety days from the effective date of the rejection notice.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, claim shall not include a contingent liability or a claim based on an event occurring after the effective date of dissolution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 156. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
