<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id95"><sectno id="id96">Sec. 32.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id97" statutenumber="21-29,126"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id99">21-29,126</statuteno><catchline id="id100">Filings required for merger or consolidation; effective date.</catchline><para>(1) After each constituent organization has approved a merger or consolidation, articles of merger or consolidation shall be signed on behalf of each other preexisting constituent organization by an authorized representative.</para><para>(2) The articles of merger or consolidation shall include:</para><para>(a) The name and form of each constituent organization and the jurisdiction of its governing statute;</para><para>(b) The name and form of the surviving organization, the jurisdiction of its governing statute, and, if the surviving organization is created by the merger or consolidation, a statement to that effect;</para><para>(c) The date the merger or consolidation is effective under the governing statute of the surviving organization;</para><para>(d) If the surviving organization is to be created by the merger or consolidation:</para><para>(i) If it will be a limited cooperative association, the limited cooperative association's articles of organization; or</para><para>(ii) If it will be an organization other than a limited cooperative association, the organizational document that creates the organization;</para><para>(e) If the surviving organization preexists the merger or consolidation, any amendments provided for in the plan of merger or consolidation for the organizational document that created the organization;</para><para>(f) A statement as to each constituent organization that the merger or consolidation was approved as required by the organization's governing statute;</para><para>(g) If the surviving organization is a foreign organization not authorized to transact business in this state, the street and mailing addresses of an office which the Secretary of State may use for the purposes of service of process; and</para><para>(h) Any additional information required by the governing statute of any constituent organization.</para><para>(3) Each constituent limited cooperative association shall deliver the articles of merger or consolidation for filing in the office of the Secretary of State.</para><para>(4) A merger or consolidation becomes effective under this section:</para><para>(a) If the surviving organization is a limited cooperative association, upon the later of:</para><para>(i) Compliance with subsection (3) of this section; or</para><para>(ii) Subject to section 21-2919, as specified in the articles of merger or consolidation; or</para><para>(b) If the surviving organization is not a limited cooperative association, as provided by the governing statute of the surviving organization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 126; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB848, &#167;  32.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
