<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,103</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Indemnification authority.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section, a corporation may indemnify an individual who is a party to a proceeding because he or she is a director against liability incurred in the proceeding if:</para><para>(a)(i) He or she conducted himself or herself in good faith;</para><para>(ii) He or she reasonably believed:</para><para>(A) In the case of conduct in his or her official capacity, that his or her conduct was in the best interests of the corporation; and</para><para>(B) In all other cases that his or her conduct was at least not opposed to the best interests of the corporation; and</para><para>(iii) In the case of any criminal proceeding, he or she had no reasonable cause to believe his or her conduct was unlawful; or</para><para>(b) He or she engaged in conduct for which broader indemnification has been made permissible or obligatory under a provision of the articles of incorporation as authorized by subdivision (2)(e) of section 21-2018.</para><para>(2) A director's conduct with respect to an employee benefit plan for a purpose he or she reasonably believed to be in the interests of the participants in and beneficiaries of the plan shall be conduct that satisfies the requirement of subdivision (1)(a)(ii)(B) of this section.</para><para>(3) The termination of a proceeding by judgment, order, settlement, or conviction or upon a plea of nolo contendere or its equivalent shall not be, of itself, determinative that the director did not meet the relevant standard of conduct described in this section.</para><para>(4) Unless ordered by a court under subdivision (1)(c) of section 21-20,106, a corporation may not indemnify a director under this section:</para><para>(a) In connection with a proceeding by or in the right of the corporation, except for reasonable expenses incurred in connection with the proceeding if it is determined that the director has met the relevant standard of conduct under subsection (1) of this section; or</para><para>(b) In connection with any proceeding with respect to conduct for which he or she was adjudged liable on the basis that he or she received a financial benefit to which he or she was not entitled, whether or not involving action in his or her official capacity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 103. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
