<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,180.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,180.01</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10; Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 19. Operative date January 1, 2017. Foreign corporation; revocation of certificate of authority; reinstatement; procedure; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A foreign corporation, the certificate of authority of which has been revoked under section 21-20,180, may apply to the Secretary of State for reinstatement within five years after the effective date of the revocation. The application shall:</para><para>(a) Recite the name of the foreign corporation and the effective date of the revocation;</para><para>(b) State that the ground or grounds for revocation either did not exist or have been eliminated; and</para><para>(c) State that the foreign corporation's name satisfies the requirements of section 21-20,173.</para><para>(2) If the Secretary of State determines (a) that the application for reinstatement contains the information required by subsection (1) of this section and that the information is correct and (b) that the foreign corporation has paid to the Secretary of State all delinquent occupation taxes and has forwarded to the Secretary of State a properly executed and signed biennial report for the current year, he or she shall cancel the certificate of revocation, prepare a certificate of reinstatement that recites his or her determination and the effective date of reinstatement, file the original of the certificate, and serve a copy on the foreign corporation under section 21-20,177.</para><para>(3) A foreign corporation, the certificate of authority of which has been revoked under section 21-20,180 for more than five years, may apply to the Secretary of State for late reinstatement. The application, along with the fee set forth in section 21-2005, shall:</para><para>(a) Recite the name of the foreign corporation and the effective date of the revocation;</para><para>(b) State that the ground or grounds for revocation either did not exist or have been eliminated;</para><para>(c) State that the foreign corporation's name satisfies the requirements of section 21-20,173;</para><para>(d) State that a legitimate reason exists for reinstatement and what such legitimate reason is; and</para><para>(e) State that such reinstatement does not constitute fraud on the public.</para><para>(4) If the Secretary of State determines (a) that the application for late reinstatement contains the information required by subsection (3) of this section and that the information is correct and (b) that the foreign corporation has paid to the Secretary of State all delinquent occupation taxes and has forwarded to the Secretary of State a properly executed and signed biennial report for the current year, he or she shall cancel the certificate of revocation, prepare a certificate of late reinstatement that recites his or her determination and the effective date of reinstatement, file the original certificate, and serve a copy on the foreign corporation under section 21-20,177.</para><para>(5) When the reinstatement is effective, it shall relate back to and take effect as of the effective date of the revocation and the foreign corporation shall resume carrying on its business as if the revocation had never occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1036, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB854, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 14. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Biennial report,</emphasis> see section 21-304.</para><para><emphasis>Occupation tax,</emphasis> see Chapter 21, article 3.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>