<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<sectno id="id23">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id24" statutenumber="21-20,186"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id26">21-20,186</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Financial statements
for shareholders.</catchline><para>(1) A corporation shall furnish
its shareholders annual financial statements which may be consolidated or
combined statements of the corporation and one or more of its subsidiaries,
as appropriate, that include a balance sheet as of the end of the fiscal year,
an income statement for that year, and a statement of changes in shareholders'
equity for that year unless such information appears elsewhere in the financial
statements. If financial statements are prepared for the corporation on the
basis of generally accepted accounting principles, the annual financial statements
shall also be prepared on that basis.</para>
<para>(2) If the annual financial statements are reported upon by
a public accountant, the accountant's report shall accompany the financial
statements. If not, the financial statements shall be accompanied by a statement
of the president or the person responsible for the corporation's accounting
records:</para>
<para>(a) Stating his or her reasonable belief whether the financial
statements were prepared on the basis of generally accepted accounting principles
and, if not, describing the basis of preparation; and</para>
<para>(b) Describing any respects in which the statements were not
prepared on a basis of accounting consistent with the statements prepared
for the preceding year.</para>
<para>(3) A corporation shall deliver the annual financial
statements to each shareholder within one hundred twenty days after the close
of each fiscal year. Thereafter, on written request from a shareholder who
was not delivered the statements,
the corporation shall deliver to him or her the
latest financial statements.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 186; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB528, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
