<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4" opdate="May 21, 2009">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" id="id5" statutenumber="21-20,177"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">21-20,177</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2016. Foreign corporation;
service; consent to service
of search warrant or subpoena.</catchline><para>(1) The
registered agent of a foreign corporation authorized to transact business
in this state shall be the corporation's agent for service of process, notice,
or demand required or permitted by law to be served on the foreign corporation. By being authorized to transact business
in this state, the foreign corporation's agent for service of process shall
also consent to service of process directed to the foreign corporation's agent
in Nebraska for a search warrant issued pursuant to sections 28-807 to 28-829,
or for any other validly issued and properly served subpoena, including those
authorized under section 86-2,112, for records or documents that are in the
possession of the foreign corporation and are located inside or outside of
this state. The consent to service of a subpoena or search warrant applies
to a foreign corporation that is a party or nonparty to the matter for which
the search warrant is sought.</para>
<para>(2) A foreign corporation may be served by registered or certified
mail, return receipt requested, addressed to the secretary of the foreign
corporation or the designated
custodian of records at its principal office shown in its application
for a certificate of authority or in its most recent annual report if the
foreign corporation has:</para>
<para>(a) No registered agent or its registered agent cannot with
reasonable diligence be served;</para>
<para>(b) Withdrawn from transacting business in this state under
section 21-20,178; or</para>
<para>(c) Had its certificate of authority revoked under section
21-20,180.</para>
<para>(3) Service shall be perfected under subsection (2) of this
section at the earliest of:</para>
<para>(a) The date the foreign corporation receives the mail;</para>
<para>(b) The date shown on the return receipt if signed on behalf
of the foreign corporation; or</para>
<para>(c) Five days after its deposit in the United States mail
as evidenced by the postmark if mailed postage prepaid and correctly addressed.</para>
<para>(4) This section shall not be construed to prescribe the only
means or necessarily the required means of serving a foreign corporation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
