<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2923"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2923</statuteno><catchline>Biennial report.</catchline><para>(1) A limited cooperative association or a foreign limited cooperative association authorized to transact business in this state shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing a biennial report that states:</para><para>(a) The name of the limited cooperative association or foreign limited cooperative association;</para><para>(b) The street and mailing addresses of the limited cooperative association's or foreign limited cooperative association's designated office and the name and street and mailing addresses of its agent for service of process in this state;</para><para>(c) In the case of a limited cooperative association, the street and mailing addresses of its principal office if different from its designated office; and</para><para>(d) In the case of a foreign limited cooperative association, the state or other jurisdiction under whose law the foreign limited cooperative association is formed and any alternative name adopted under section 21-29,106.</para><para>(2) Information in the biennial report must be current as of the date the biennial report is delivered to the Secretary of State.</para><para>(3) Commencing on January 1, 2009, a biennial report shall be filed between January 1 and April 1 of each odd-numbered year following the year in which a limited cooperative association files articles of organization or a foreign limited cooperative association becomes authorized to transact business in this state. A correction or amendment to a biennial report may be filed at any time.</para><para>(4) If a biennial report does not contain the information required in subsection (1) of this section, the Secretary of State shall promptly notify the reporting limited cooperative association or foreign limited cooperative association and return the report for correction. If the report is corrected to contain the information required in subsection (1) of this section and delivered to the Secretary of State within thirty days after the effective date of the notice, it is timely delivered.</para><para>(5) If a filed biennial report contains an address of a designated office or the name or address of an agent for service of process which differs from the information shown in the records of the Secretary of State immediately before the filing, the differing information in the biennial report is considered a statement of change under section 21-2914.</para><para>(6) If a limited cooperative association fails to file a biennial report under this section, the Secretary of State may proceed under section 21-2994 to administratively dissolve the limited cooperative association.</para><para>(7) If a foreign limited cooperative association fails to file a biennial report under this section, the Secretary of State may proceed under section 21-29,107 to revoke the certificate of authority of the foreign limited cooperative association.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 23.</para></source></law></legaldoc>