<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2610"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2610</statuteno><catchline>Change of registered office or registered agent.</catchline><para>(1) A limited liability company, whether foreign or domestic, may change its registered office or registered agent upon filing with the Secretary of State a statement setting forth:</para><para>(a) The name of the limited liability company;</para><para>(b) The street address of its current registered office;</para><para>(c) If the address of its registered office is to be changed, the new address;</para><para>(d) The name and street address of its current registered agent. A post office box number may be provided in addition to the street address;</para><para>(e) If its registered agent is to be changed, the name of the successor registered agent;</para><para>(f) That the address of its registered office and the address of the business office of its registered agent, as changed, will be identical; and</para><para>(g) That the change was authorized by an affirmative vote of a majority in interest of the members of the limited liability company or in any other manner authorized by the articles of organization.</para><para>(2) The statement shall be executed by an authorized representative of the limited liability company and delivered to the Secretary of State. If the Secretary of State finds that the statement conforms to the requirements of this section, he or she shall file the statement in his or her office, and upon filing, the change of address of the registered office or the appointment of a new registered agent shall be effective.</para><para>(3) A registered agent may resign as registered agent of a limited liability company upon filing a written notice, executed in duplicate, with the Secretary of State who shall mail a copy thereof to the limited liability company at its place of business if known to the Secretary of State, otherwise at its registered office. The appointment of the registered agent shall terminate upon the expiration of thirty days after receipt of notice by the Secretary of State.</para><para>(4) If a registered agent changes the street address or post office box number for his or her business office, he or she may change the street address, or, if one exists, the post office box number,  of the registered office of any limited liability company for which he or she is the registered agent by notifying the limited liability company in writing of the change and signing, either manually or in facsimile, and delivering to the Secretary of State for filing a statement that complies with the requirements of subsection (1) of this section and recites that the limited liability company has been notified of the change.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 631, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 647, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167;  24.</para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source>  </law></legaldoc>
