<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id246"><sectno id="id247">Sec. 23.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id248" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="21-2981.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2981.03</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited distribution; director liability; member or holder of financial rights liability; actions authorized; statute of limitation.</catchline><para>(1) A director who consents to a distribution made in violation of section 21-2981 is personally liable to the limited cooperative association for the amount of the distribution which exceeds the amount that could have been distributed without the violation if it is established that in consenting to the distribution the director failed to comply with section 21-2970 or 21-2971.</para><para>(2) A member or holder of financial rights which received a distribution knowing that the distribution to the member or holder was made in violation of section 21-2981.02 is personally liable to the limited cooperative association but only to the extent that the distribution received by the member or holder exceeded the amount that could have been properly paid under section 21-2981.02.</para><para>(3) A director against whom an action is commenced under subsection (1) of this section may:</para><para>(a) Implead in the action any other director that is liable under subsection (1) of this section and compel contribution from the person; and</para><para>(b) Implead in the action any person that is liable under subsection (2) of this section and compel contribution from the person in the amount the person received as described in such subsection.</para><para>(4) An action under this section is barred if it is not commenced within two years after the distribution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB848, &#167;  23.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
