<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2617.01" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2617.01</statuteno><catchline>Biennial report; contents; dissolution of company; revocation of certificate; Secretary of State; powers; procedure; revival or restoration; when.</catchline><para>(1) A limited liability company and a foreign limited liability company authorized to transact business in the state shall file a biennial report in the office of the Secretary of State which contains:</para><para>(a) The name of the limited liability company and the state or other jurisdiction under whose laws the limited liability company or foreign limited liability company is formed; and </para><para>(b) The street address of the limited liability company's principal place of business in this state or, if the limited liability company does not have an office in this state, the name and street address of the company's agent for service of process.</para><para>(2) Commencing on January 1, 2007, a biennial report shall be filed between January 1 and April 1 of each odd-numbered year following the year in which a limited liability company files articles of organization or a foreign limited liability company becomes authorized to transact business in this state. A correction or amendment to a biennial report may be filed at any time.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State may dissolve a limited liability company or revoke the certificate of authority to transact business of a foreign limited liability company that fails to file a biennial report when due or pay the required filing fee provided in section 21-2634. To do so, the Secretary of State shall provide the company at least sixty days' written notice of intent to dissolve or revoke. The notice shall be mailed to the company at its principal office or the office of the agent for service of process as set forth in the articles of organization, biennial report, or other filing designating the agent for service of process, whichever was most recently filed. The notice shall specify the biennial report that has not been filed, the fee that has not been paid, and the effective date of the dissolution or revocation. The dissolution or revocation is not effective if the biennial report is filed and the fee is paid before the effective date of the dissolution or revocation.</para><para>(4) Revival or restoration of the authority of a company dissolved or whose certificate of authority has been revoked pursuant to this section shall be accomplished as provided in section 21-2611, and upon completion of such requirements for revival or restoration, the revival or restoration shall relate back to the date of dissolution or revocation as if such dissolution or revocation had not occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 647, &#167; 11.</para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc>