<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,163"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,163</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2017. Judicial dissolution; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Venue for a proceeding by the Attorney General to dissolve a corporation shall lie in the district court of the county where the corporation's principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered office, is located, or the district court of Lancaster County. Venue for a proceeding brought by any other party named in section 21-20,162 shall lie in the district court of the county where the corporation's principal office, or, if none in this state, its registered office, is or was last located.</para><para>(2) It shall not be necessary to make shareholders parties to a proceeding to dissolve a corporation unless relief is sought against them individually.</para><para>(3) A court in a proceeding brought to dissolve a corporation may issue injunctions, appoint a receiver or custodian pendente lite with all powers and duties the court directs, take other action required to preserve the corporate assets wherever located, and carry on the business of the corporation until a full hearing can be held.</para><para>(4) Within ten days of the commencement of a proceeding under subdivision (2) of section 21-20,162 to dissolve a corporation that has no shares listed on a national securities exchange or regularly traded in a market maintained by one or more members of a national securities exchange, the corporation shall send to all shareholders, other than the petitioner, a notice stating that the shareholders are entitled to avoid the dissolution of the corporation by electing to purchase the petitioner's shares under section 21-20,166 and accompanied by a copy of such section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 163. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
