<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-29,107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-29,107</statuteno><catchline>Revocation of certificate of authority.</catchline><para>(1) A certificate of authority of a foreign limited cooperative association to transact business in this state may be revoked by the Secretary of State in the manner provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section if the foreign limited cooperative association does not:</para><para>(a) Pay, within sixty days after the due date, any fee, tax, or penalty due to the Secretary of State under the Nebraska Limited Cooperative Association Act or other law;</para><para>(b) Deliver, within sixty days after the due date, its biennial report required under section 21-2994;</para><para>(c) Appoint and maintain an agent for service of process as required by section 21-29,103; or</para><para>(d) Deliver for filing a statement of a change under section 21-2914 within thirty days after a change has occurred in the name or address of the agent.</para><para>(2) To revoke a certificate of authority, the Secretary of State shall prepare, sign, and file a certificate of revocation and send a copy to the foreign limited cooperative association's registered agent for service of process in this state, or if the foreign limited cooperative association does not appoint and maintain an agent for service of process in this state, to the foreign limited cooperative association's designated office. The notice shall state:</para><para>(a) The revocation's effective date, which shall be at least sixty days after the date the Secretary of State sends the copy; and</para><para>(b) The foreign limited cooperative association's noncompliance with subsection (1) of this section which is the reason for the revocation.</para><para>(3) The authority of the foreign limited cooperative association to transact business in this state ceases on the effective date of the certificate of revocation unless before that date the foreign limited cooperative association cures each failure to comply with subsection (1) of this section stated in the notice. If the foreign limited cooperative association cures the failures, the Secretary of State shall so indicate on the filed notice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 107.</para></source></law></legaldoc>