<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2919"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2919</statuteno><catchline>Delivery to and filing of records by Secretary of State; effective time and date.</catchline><para>(1) A record authorized to be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing under the Nebraska Limited Cooperative Association Act shall be captioned to describe the record's purpose and be delivered to the Secretary of State in a medium authorized by the Secretary of State. Unless the Secretary of State determines that a record does not comply with the filing requirements of the act and if all filing fees have been paid the Secretary of State shall file the record and send a copy of the filed record and a receipt for the fees to the person on whose behalf the record was filed.</para><para>(2) Upon request and payment of a fee, the Secretary of State shall send to the requester a certified copy of the requested record.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in the act, a record delivered to the Secretary of State for filing under the act may specify an effective time and a delayed effective date. Except as otherwise provided in the act, a record filed by the Secretary of State is effective:</para><para>(a) If the record does not specify an effective time and does not specify a delayed effective date, on the date and at the time the record is filed as evidenced by the Secretary of State's endorsement of the date and time on the record;</para><para>(b) If the record specifies an effective time but not a delayed effective date, on the date the record is filed at the time specified in the record;</para><para>(c) If the record specifies a delayed effective date but not an effective time, at 12:01 a.m. on the earlier of:</para><para>(i) The specified date; or</para><para>(ii) The ninetieth day after the record is filed; or</para><para>(d) If the record specifies an effective time and a delayed effective date, at the specified time on the earlier of:</para><para>(i) The specified date; or</para><para>(ii) Ninety days after the record is filed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 19.</para></source></law></legaldoc>