<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2018"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2018</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Articles of incorporation.</catchline><para>(1) The articles of incorporation shall set forth:</para><para>(a) The corporate name for the corporation that satisfies the requirements of section 21-2028;</para><para>(b) The number of shares the corporation is authorized to issue and, if such shares are to consist of one class only, the par value of each of such shares or, if such shares are to be divided into classes, the number of shares of each class and a statement of the par value of the shares of each such class;</para><para>(c) The street address of the corporation's initial registered office and the name of its initial registered agent at that office. A post office box number may be provided in addition to the street address;</para><para>(d) The name and street address of each incorporator; and</para><para>(e) Any provision limiting or eliminating the requirement to hold an annual meeting of the shareholders if the corporation is registered or intends to register as an investment company under the federal Investment Company Act of 1940. The provision shall not be effective if such corporation does not become or ceases to be so registered.</para><para>(2) The articles of incorporation may set forth:</para><para>(a) The names and street addresses of the individuals who are to serve as the initial directors;</para><para>(b) Provisions not inconsistent with law regarding:</para><para>(i) The purpose or purposes for which the corporation is organized;</para><para>(ii) Managing the business and regulating the affairs of the corporation;</para><para>(iii) Defining, limiting, and regulating the powers of the corporation, its board of directors, and its shareholders; and</para><para>(iv) The imposition of personal liability on shareholders for the debts of the corporation to a specified extent and upon specified conditions;</para><para>(c) Any provision that under the Business Corporation Act is required or permitted to be set forth in the bylaws;</para><para>(d) A provision eliminating or limiting the liability of a director to the corporation or its shareholders for money damages for any action taken, or any failure to take any action, as a director, except liability for:</para><para>(i) The amount of a financial benefit received by a director to which he or she is not entitled;</para><para>(ii) An intentional infliction of harm on the corporation or the shareholders;</para><para>(iii) A violation of section 21-2096; or</para><para>(iv) An intentional violation of criminal law; and</para><para>(e) A provision permitting or making obligatory indemnification of a director for liability, as defined in section 21-20,102, to any person for any action taken, or any failure to take any action, as a director, except liability for (i) receipt of a financial benefit to which he or she is not entitled, (ii) an intentional infliction of harm on the corporation or its shareholders, (iii) a violation of section 21-2096, or (iv) an intentional violation of criminal law.</para><para>(3) The articles of incorporation shall not be required to set forth any of the corporate powers enumerated in the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167;  15.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
