<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2639" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2639</statuteno><catchline>Foreign limited liability company; filing of certificate of authority and current registration certificate.</catchline><para>The original and a duplicate original of the application of a foreign limited liability company for a certificate of authority shall be delivered to the Secretary of State along with the filing fees required by section 21-2634. If the foreign limited liability company is organized to render a professional service, a current registration certificate as provided in sections 21-2631 to 21-2632 shall be delivered to the Secretary of State with such application and fees. If the Secretary of State finds that the application conforms to law and, if applicable, a current registration certificate has been filed, the Secretary of State shall:</para><para>(1) Endorse on each of such documents the word filed and the month, day, and year of the filing thereof;</para><para>(2) File in his or her office the original of the application and any registration certificate, if applicable; and</para><para>(3) Issue a certificate of authority to transact business in this state to which he or she shall affix the duplicate original of the application.</para><para>The certificate of authority, together with the duplicate original of the application affixed thereto by the Secretary of State, shall be returned to the principal office of the foreign limited liability company or its representative.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 16, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 647, &#167; 17. </para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc>