<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2933"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2933</statuteno><catchline>Right of member and former member to information.</catchline><para>(1) On ten days' demand, made in a record received by the limited cooperative association, a member may inspect and copy required information under subdivisions (1) through (7) of section 21-2910 during regular business hours in the limited cooperative association's principal office. A demand to inspect and copy records shall be in good faith and for a proper purpose. A member may demand the same information under subdivisions (1) through (7) of section 21-2910 no more than once during a twelve-month period.</para><para>(2) On demand, made in a record received by the limited cooperative association, a member may obtain from the limited cooperative association and inspect and copy required information if the demand is just and reasonable. A demand to inspect and copy records is just and reasonable if:</para><para>(a) The member seeks the information for a proper purpose reasonably related to the member's interest as a member;</para><para>(b) The demand includes a description, with reasonable particularity, of the information sought and the purpose for seeking the information; and</para><para>(c) The information sought is directly connected to the member's purpose.</para><para>(3) Within ten days after receiving a demand pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section, the limited cooperative association shall inform, in a record, the member that made the demand:</para><para>(a) Of what information the limited cooperative association will provide in response to the demand;</para><para>(b) Of the reasonable time and place that the limited cooperative association will provide the information; and</para><para>(c) That the limited cooperative association will decline to provide any demanded information and the limited cooperative association's reasons for declining.</para><para>(4) A person dissociated as a member pursuant to section 21-2982 may inspect and copy required information during regular business hours in the limited cooperative association's principal office if:</para><para>(a) The information pertains to the period during which the person was a member;</para><para>(b) The person seeks the information in good faith; and</para><para>(c) The person complies with this section.</para><para>(5) The limited cooperative association shall respond to a demand made pursuant to subsection (4) of this section in the same manner as otherwise provided in this section.</para><para>(6) The limited cooperative association may impose reasonable restrictions, including nondisclosure restrictions, on the use of information obtained under this section. In a dispute concerning the reasonableness of a restriction, the limited cooperative association has the burden of proving reasonableness.</para><para>(7) A limited cooperative association may charge a person that makes a demand under this section reasonable costs of copying, limited to the costs of labor and material.</para><para>(8) A member or person dissociated as a member may exercise the rights under this section through an attorney or other agent. A restriction imposed under this section or by the articles of organization or bylaws on a member or person dissociated as a member applies both to the attorney or other agent and to the member or person dissociated as a member.</para><para>(9) The rights stated in this section do not extend to a person as transferee but may be exercised by the legal representative of an individual under legal disability who is a member or person dissociated as a member.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 33.</para></source></law></legaldoc>