<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2995"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2995</statuteno><catchline>Reinstatement following administrative dissolution.</catchline><para>(1) A limited cooperative association that has been administratively dissolved may apply to the Secretary of State for reinstatement within five years after the effective date of its administrative dissolution. The application shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing and state:</para><para>(a) The name of the limited cooperative association and the effective date of its administrative dissolution;</para><para>(b) That the grounds for dissolution either did not exist or have been eliminated; and</para><para>(c) That the limited cooperative association's name satisfies the requirements of sections 21-2906 to 21-2908.</para><para>(2) If the Secretary of State determines that (a) the application for reinstatement contains the information required by subsection (1) of this section and that the information is correct and (b) the limited cooperative association has paid to the Secretary of State all delinquent occupation taxes and has forwarded to the Secretary of State a properly executed and signed biennial report for the current year, the Secretary of State shall:</para><para>(a) Prepare a declaration of reinstatement that states this determination;</para><para>(b) Sign and file the original of the declaration of reinstatement; and</para><para>(c) Serve the limited cooperative association with a copy.</para><para>(3) A limited cooperative association that has been administratively dissolved for more than five years may apply to the Secretary of State for late reinstatement. The application shall be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing, along with the fee set forth in section 21-2924, and state:</para><para>(a) The name of the limited cooperative association and the effective date of its administrative dissolution;</para><para>(b) That the grounds for dissolution either did not exist or have been eliminated;</para><para>(c) That the limited cooperative association's name satisfies the requirements of sections 21-2906 to 21-2908;</para><para>(d) That a legitimate reason exists for reinstatement and what such legitimate reason is; and</para><para>(e) That such reinstatement does not constitute fraud on the public.</para><para>(4) If the Secretary of State determines that (a) the application for late reinstatement contains the information required by subsection (3) of this section and that the information is correct and (b) the limited cooperative association has paid to the Secretary of State all delinquent occupation taxes and has forwarded to the Secretary of State a properly executed and signed biennial report for the current year, the Secretary of State shall:</para><para>(a) Prepare a declaration of late reinstatement that states this determination;</para><para>(b) Sign and file the original of the declaration of reinstatement; and</para><para>(c) Serve the limited cooperative association with a copy.</para><para>(5) When reinstatement becomes effective it relates back to and takes effect as of the effective date of the administrative dissolution and the limited cooperative association may resume or continue its activities as if the administrative dissolution had never occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB854, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB279, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>