<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,118"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,118</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298. Operative date January 1, 2017. Articles of incorporation; amendment by board of directors and shareholders.</catchline><para>(1) A corporation's board of directors may propose one or more amendments to the articles of incorporation for submission to the shareholders.</para><para>(2) For the amendment to be adopted:</para><para>(a) The board of directors shall recommend the amendment to the shareholders unless the board of directors determines that because of a conflict of interest or other special circumstances it should make no recommendation and communicates the basis for its determination to the shareholders with the amendment; and</para><para>(b) The shareholders entitled to vote on the amendment shall approve the amendment as provided in subsection (5) of this section.</para><para>(3) The board of directors may condition its submission of the proposed amendment on any basis.</para><para>(4) The corporation shall notify each shareholder, whether or not entitled to vote, of the proposed shareholders' meeting in accordance with section 21-2055. The notice of the meeting shall also state that the purpose, or one of the purposes, of the meeting is to consider the proposed amendment and contain or be accompanied by a copy or summary of the amendment.</para><para>(5) Unless the Business Corporation Act, the articles of incorporation, or the board of directors acting pursuant to subsection (3) of this section requires a greater vote or a vote by voting groups, the amendment to be adopted shall be approved by:</para><para>(a) A two-thirds majority of the votes entitled to be cast on the amendment by any voting group with respect to which the amendment would create dissenters' rights; and</para><para>(b) The votes required by sections 21-2063 and 21-2064 by every other voting group entitled to vote on the amendment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 118. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
