<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id35">
<sectno id="id36">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" id="id37" statutenumber="21-2015"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno id="id39">21-2015</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Notice.</catchline>
<para>(1) Notice under the Business Corporation Act shall be in
writing unless oral notice is reasonable under the circumstances. Notice by electronic transmission is
written notice.</para>
<para>(2) Notice may be communicated in person, by mail or other method of delivery, or by telephone or other electronic means. If
these forms of personal notice are impracticable, notice may be communicated
by a newspaper of general circulation in the area where published or by radio,
television, or other form of public broadcast communication.</para>
<para>(3) Written notice by a domestic or foreign corporation to
its shareholder, if in a comprehensible form, shall be effective (a) when mailed, if mailed
postage prepaid and correctly addressed to the shareholder's address shown
in the corporation's current record of shareholders, or (b) when electronically transmitted to the shareholder
in a manner authorized by the shareholder. Notice by a public corporation
to its shareholder shall be effective if the notice is addressed to the shareholder
or group of shareholders in a manner permitted by rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated under the federal Securities Exchange Act of 1934 if the public
corporation has first received affirmative written consent or implied consent
required under such rules and regulations.</para>
<para>(4) Written notice to a domestic or foreign corporation authorized
to transact business in this state may be addressed to its registered agent
at its registered office or to the corporation or its secretary at its principal
office, shown in its most recent annual report or, in the case of a foreign
corporation that has not yet delivered an annual report, in its application
for a certificate of authority.</para>
<para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section,
written notice, if in a comprehensible form, shall be effective at the earliest
of the following:</para>
<para>(a) When received;</para>
<para>(b) Five days after its deposit in the United States mail,
as evidenced by the postmark, if mailed postage prepaid and correctly addressed;
or</para>
<para>(c) On the date shown on the return receipt, if sent by registered
or certified mail, return receipt requested, and the receipt is signed by
or on behalf of the addressee.</para>
<para>(6) Oral notice shall be effective when communicated if communicated
in a comprehensible manner.</para>
<para>(7) If the act prescribes notice requirements for particular
circumstances, those requirements shall govern. If articles of incorporation
or bylaws prescribe notice requirements, not inconsistent with this section
or other provisions of the act, those requirements shall govern.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB528, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
