<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations And Other Companies" statutenumber="21-20,154"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>21-20,154</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2014, LB749, &#167; 298; Laws 2015, LB157, &#167; 10. Operative date January 1, 2017. Voluntary dissolution; revocation of dissolution.</catchline><para>(1) A corporation may revoke its dissolution within one hundred twenty days of its effective date.</para><para>(2) Revocation of dissolution shall be authorized in the same manner as the dissolution was authorized unless that authorization permitted revocation by action of the board of directors alone, in which event the board of directors may revoke the dissolution without shareholder action.</para><para>(3) After the revocation of dissolution is authorized, the corporation may revoke the dissolution by delivering to the Secretary of State for filing articles of revocation of dissolution, together with a copy of its articles of dissolution, that set forth:</para><para>(a) The name of the corporation;</para><para>(b) The effective date of the dissolution that was revoked;</para><para>(c) The date that the revocation of dissolution was authorized;</para><para>(d) If the corporation's board of directors or incorporators revoked the dissolution, a statement to that effect;</para><para>(e) If the corporation's board of directors revoked a dissolution authorized by the shareholders, a statement that revocation was permitted by action by the board of directors alone pursuant to that authorization; and</para><para>(f) If shareholder action was required to revoke the dissolution, the information required by subdivision (1)(c) or (d) of section 21-20,153.</para><para>(4) Revocation of dissolution shall be effective upon the effective date of the articles of revocation of dissolution.</para><para>(5) When the revocation of dissolution is effective, it shall relate back to and take effect as of the effective date of the dissolution and the corporation shall resume carrying on its business as if dissolution had never occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 154. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
