<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2638"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2638</statuteno><catchline>Foreign limited liability company; certificate of authority; application.</catchline><para>Before doing business in this state, a foreign limited liability company shall obtain a certificate of authority from the Secretary of State. In order to obtain a certificate of authority, a foreign limited liability company shall submit to the Secretary of State, together with payment of the fee required by the Limited Liability Company Act, an original executed by a member or manager, together with a duplicate original, of an application for a certificate of authority as a foreign limited liability company, setting forth:</para><para>(1) The name of the foreign limited liability company;</para><para>(2) The state or other jurisdiction or country where organized, the date of its organization, and a statement issued by an appropriate authority in that jurisdiction that the foreign limited liability company exists in good standing under the laws of the jurisdiction of its organization;</para><para>(3) The nature of the business or purposes to be conducted or promoted in this state;</para><para>(4) The address of the registered office and the name and street address of the current resident agent for service of process required to be maintained by the act. A post office box number may be provided in addition to the street address; and</para><para>(5) Such additional information as may be necessary or appropriate in order to enable the Secretary of State to determine whether such foreign limited liability company is entitled to a certificate of authority to transact business in this state and to determine and assess the fees and taxes prescribed by the laws of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB379, &#167; 26.</para><terminationdate>January 1, 2013</terminationdate></source>  </law></legaldoc>
