<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Corporations and Other Companies" statutenumber="21-2306"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>21-2306</statuteno><catchline>Articles of incorporation; amendment; procedure.</catchline><para>The articles of incorporation may at any time be amended to make any changes or add any provisions which might have been included in the first instance. To amend the articles of incorporation, the members of the board of directors of the corporation shall file with the governing body of the local political subdivision an application in writing seeking permission to amend the articles of incorporation and specifying in the application the amendment proposed to be made. The governing body shall consider the application and if by appropriate resolution it (1) duly finds and determines that it is wise, expedient, necessary, or advisable that the proposed amendment be made, (2) authorizes the same to be made, and (3) approves the form of the proposed amendment, then the persons making the application shall execute an instrument embodying the amendment specified in the application. The instrument shall be subscribed and acknowledged before a notary public by each member of the board of directors and shall be filed with the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State shall examine the proposed amendment and, if he or she finds that the requirements of this section have been complied with and that the proposed amendment is within the scope of what might be included in the original articles of incorporation, the Secretary of State shall approve the amendment and record it in his or her office. When the amendment has been made, filed, and approved it shall become effective and the articles of incorporation shall be amended pursuant to the amendment. The articles of incorporation under the Nebraska Industrial Development Corporation Act shall be amended only as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1517, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 494, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>