<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="9-812"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>9-812</statuteno><catchline id="id9">State Lottery Operation
Trust Fund; State Lottery Operation Cash Fund; State Lottery Prize Trust Fund;
created; transfers; Education Innovation Fund; created; use; investment; unclaimed
prize money; use.</catchline><para>(1) All money received from the
operation of lottery games conducted pursuant to the State Lottery Act in
Nebraska shall be credited to the State Lottery Operation Trust Fund, which
fund is hereby created. All payments of the costs of establishing and maintaining
the lottery games shall be made from the State Lottery Operation Cash Fund.
In accordance with legislative appropriations, money for payments for expenses
of the division shall be transferred from the State Lottery Operation Trust
Fund to the State Lottery Operation Cash Fund, which fund is hereby created.
All money necessary for the payment of lottery prizes shall be transferred
from the State Lottery Operation Trust Fund to the State Lottery Prize Trust
Fund, which fund is hereby created. The amount used for the payment of lottery
prizes shall not be less than forty percent of the dollar amount of the lottery
tickets which have been sold.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning October 1, 2003, a portion of the dollar amount
of the lottery tickets which have been sold on an annualized basis shall be
transferred from the State Lottery Operation Trust Fund to the Education Innovation
Fund, the Nebraska Opportunity Grant Fund, the Nebraska Environmental Trust
Fund, the Nebraska State Fair Board, and the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance
Fund. The dollar amount transferred pursuant to this subsection shall equal
the greater of (a) the dollar amount transferred to the funds in fiscal year
2002-03 or (b) any amount which constitutes at least twenty-two percent and
no more than twenty-five percent of the dollar amount of the lottery tickets
which have been sold on an annualized basis. To the extent that funds are
available, the Tax Commissioner and director may authorize a transfer exceeding
twenty-five percent of the dollar amount of the lottery tickets sold on an
annualized basis.</para>
<para>(3) Of the money available to be transferred to the Education
Innovation Fund, the Nebraska Opportunity Grant Fund, the Nebraska Environmental
Trust Fund, the Nebraska State Fair Board, and the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance
Fund:</para>
<para>(a) The first five hundred thousand dollars shall be transferred
to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund to be used as provided in section
71-817;</para>
<para>(b) Nineteen and three-fourths percent of the money remaining
after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer
to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Education
Innovation Fund;</para>
<para>(c) Twenty-four and three-fourths percent of the money remaining
after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer
to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Nebraska
Opportunity Grant Fund;</para>
<para>(d) Forty-four and one-half percent of the money remaining
after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer
to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Nebraska
Environmental Trust Fund to be used as provided in the Nebraska Environmental
Trust Act;</para>
<para>(e) Ten percent of the money remaining after the payment of
prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers
Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Nebraska State Fair Board if the
most populous city within the county in which the fair is located provides
matching funds equivalent to ten percent of the funds available for transfer.
Such matching funds may be obtained from the city and any other private or
public entity, except that no portion of such matching funds shall be provided
by the state. If the Nebraska State Fair ceases operations, ten percent of
the money remaining after the payment of prizes and operating expenses and
the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be transferred
to the General Fund; and</para>
<para>(f) One percent of the money remaining after the payment of
prizes and operating expenses and the initial transfer to the Compulsive Gamblers
Assistance Fund shall be transferred to the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance
Fund to be used as provided in section 71-817.</para>
<para>(4)(a) The Education Innovation Fund is created. At least
seventy-five percent of the lottery proceeds allocated to the Education Innovation
Fund shall be available for disbursement.</para>
<para>(b) For fiscal year 2010-11, the Education Innovation Fund
shall be allocated as follows: The first one million dollars shall be transferred
to the Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund to fund the Excellence in Teaching
Act, and the amount remaining in the Education Innovation Fund shall be allocated,
after administrative expenses, for distance education equipment and incentives
pursuant to sections 79-1336 and 79-1337.</para>
<para>(c) For fiscal year 2011-12, the Education Innovation Fund
shall be allocated as follows: (i) The first two hundred twenty-five thousand
dollars shall be transferred to the Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund to fund
the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program; (ii) the next three million
three hundred sixty-five thousand nine hundred sixty-two dollars shall be
distributed to school districts as grants pursuant to the Early Childhood
Education Grant Program; (iii) the next two million one hundred seventy-five
thousand six hundred seventy-three dollars shall be distributed to local systems
as grants for approved accelerated or differentiated curriculum programs for
students identified as learners with high ability pursuant to section 79-1108.02;
(iv) the next four hundred ninety-one thousand five hundred forty-one dollars
shall be used by the State Department of Education for the development of
an integrated early childhood, elementary, secondary, and postsecondary student
information system; (v) the next four hundred fifty thousand dollars shall
fund the Center for Student Leadership and Extended Learning Act; (vi) the
next one hundred fourteen thousand six hundred twenty-nine dollars shall fund
the multicultural education program created under section 79-720; (vii) the
next one hundred twenty-three thousand four hundred sixty-eight dollars shall
be used by the department to employ persons to investigate and prosecute alleged
violations as provided in section 79-868; (viii) up to the next one hundred sixty thousand
dollars shall be used by the department to implement section 79-759; and (ix) the
amount remaining shall be allocated, after administrative expenses, for distance
education equipment and incentives pursuant to sections 79-1336 and 79-1337.</para>
<para>(d) For fiscal year 2012-13, the Education Innovation Fund
shall be allocated as follows: (i) The first forty-five thousand dollars shall
be transferred to the Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund to fund the Attracting
Excellence to Teaching Program; (ii) the next three million three hundred
sixty-five thousand nine hundred sixty-two dollars shall be distributed to
school districts as grants pursuant to the Early Childhood Education Grant
Program; (iii) the next two million one hundred seventy-five thousand six
hundred seventy-three dollars shall be distributed to local systems as grants
for approved accelerated or differentiated curriculum programs for students
identified as learners with high ability pursuant to section 79-1108.02; (iv)
the next one hundred eight thousand one hundred thirty-six dollars shall be
used by the department for the development of an integrated early childhood,
elementary, secondary, and postsecondary student information system; (v) the
next four hundred fifty thousand dollars shall fund the Center for Student
Leadership and Extended Learning Act; (vi) the next one hundred fourteen thousand
six hundred twenty-nine dollars shall be used by the department to fund the
multicultural education program created under section 79-720; (vii) the next
one hundred twenty-three thousand four hundred sixty-eight dollars shall be
used by the department to employ persons to investigate and prosecute alleged
violations as provided in section 79-868; (viii) up to the next one hundred sixty thousand
dollars shall be used by the department to implement section 79-759; (ix)
the next twenty-seven thousand two hundred dollars shall be used to fund the
Interstate Compact on Educational Opportunity for Military Children; and (x) the
amount remaining shall be allocated, after administrative expenses, for distance
education equipment and incentives pursuant to sections 79-1336 and 79-1337.</para>
<para>(e) For fiscal year 2013-14, the Education Innovation Fund shall be allocated as follows:
(i) The first one million dollars shall be transferred to the Excellence in
Teaching Cash Fund to fund the Excellence in Teaching Act; (ii) the next allocation
shall be distributed to local systems as grants for approved accelerated or
differentiated curriculum programs for students identified as learners with
high ability pursuant to section 79-1108.02 in an aggregated amount up to
the amount distributed in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased
by the basic allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (iii) the
next allocation shall be used by the State Department of Education for the
integrated early childhood, elementary, secondary, and postsecondary student
information system in an aggregated amount up to the amount used in the prior
fiscal year for such purposes increased by the basic allowable growth rate
pursuant to section 79-1025; (iv) the next allocation shall fund the Center
for Student Leadership and Extended Learning Act in an aggregated amount up
to the amount used in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased by
the basic allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (v) the next
allocation shall be used by the department to fund the multicultural education
program created under section 79-720 in an aggregated amount up to the amount
used in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased by the basic allowable
growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (vi) the next allocation shall be
used by the department to employ persons to investigate and prosecute alleged
violations as provided in section 79-868 in an aggregated amount up to the
amount used in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased by the basic
allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (vii) up
to the next one hundred sixty thousand dollars shall be used by the department
to implement section 79-759; and (viii) the amount
remaining shall be allocated, after administrative expenses, for distance
education equipment and incentives pursuant to sections 79-1336 and 79-1337.</para>
<para>(f) For fiscal
years 2014-15 and 2015-16, the Education Innovation Fund shall be allocated
as follows: (i) The first one million dollars shall be transferred to the
Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund to fund the Excellence in Teaching Act; (ii)
the next allocation shall be distributed to local systems as grants for approved
accelerated or differentiated curriculum programs for students identified
as learners with high ability pursuant to section 79-1108.02 in an aggregated
amount up to the amount distributed in the prior fiscal year for such purposes
increased by the basic allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025;
(iii) the next allocation shall be used by the State Department of Education
for the integrated early childhood, elementary, secondary, and postsecondary
student information system in an aggregated amount up to the amount used in
the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased by the basic allowable growth
rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (iv) the next allocation shall fund the
Center for Student Leadership and Extended Learning Act in an aggregated amount
up to the amount used in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased
by the basic allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (v) the next
allocation shall be used by the department to fund the multicultural education
program created under section 79-720 in an aggregated amount up to the amount
used in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased by the basic allowable
growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; (vi) the next allocation shall be
used by the department to employ persons to investigate and prosecute alleged
violations as provided in section 79-868 in an aggregated amount up to the
amount used in the prior fiscal year for such purposes increased by the basic
allowable growth rate pursuant to section 79-1025; and (vii) the amount remaining
shall be allocated, after administrative expenses, for distance education
equipment and incentives pursuant to sections 79-1336 and 79-1337.</para>
<para>(g) For fiscal year 2016-17
and each fiscal year thereafter, the Education Innovation Fund shall be allocated,
after administrative expenses, for education purposes as provided by the Legislature.</para>
<para>(5) Any money in the State Lottery Operation Trust Fund, the
State Lottery Operation Cash Fund, the State Lottery Prize Trust Fund, or
the Education Innovation Fund available for investment shall be invested by
the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act
and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(6) Unclaimed prize money on a winning lottery ticket shall
be retained for a period of time prescribed by rules and regulations. If no
claim is made within such period, the prize money shall be used at the discretion
of the Tax Commissioner for any of the purposes prescribed in this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 563, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 647, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 119; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 275, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 860, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1015; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1069, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 118, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 347, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 710, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 865, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1228, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1229, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 386, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 659, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1243, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 833, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 418; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 367, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB286, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB545, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB547, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB2, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB956, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB333, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB575, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB637, &#167; 22.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB575, section 7, with LB637, section 22, and LB333, section 1, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB333 became effective March 16, 2011. Changes made by LB575 became operative July 1, 2012. Changes made by LB637 became effective May 5, 2011.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Center for Student Leadership and Extended Learning Act,</emphasis> see section 79-772.</para><para><emphasis>Excellence in Teaching Act,</emphasis> see section 79-8,132.</para><para><emphasis>Interstate Compact on Educational Opportunity for Military Children,</emphasis> see section 79-2201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Environmental Trust Act,</emphasis> see section 81-15,167.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>