<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-402</statuteno><catchline>Purpose of act.</catchline><para>(1) The purpose of the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act is to protect the health and welfare of the public, to protect the economic welfare and interest in certain lotteries with gross proceeds greater than one thousand dollars and certain raffles with gross proceeds greater than five thousand dollars, to insure that the profits derived from the operation of any such lottery or raffle are accurately reported in order that their revenue-raising potential be fully exposed, to insure that the profits are used for legitimate purposes, and to prevent the purposes for which the profits of any such lottery or raffle are to be used from being subverted by improper elements.</para><para>(2) The purpose of the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act is also to completely and fairly regulate each level of the traditional marketing scheme of tickets or stubs for such lotteries and raffles to insure fairness, quality, and compliance with the Constitution of Nebraska. To accomplish such purpose, the regulation and licensure of nonprofit organizations and any other person involved in the marketing scheme are necessary.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act shall apply to all lotteries with gross proceeds in excess of one thousand dollars, except for lotteries by the sale of pickle cards conducted in accordance with the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, lotteries conducted by a county, city, or village in accordance with the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, and lottery games conducted in accordance with the State Lottery Act, and to all raffles with gross proceeds in excess of five thousand dollars. All such lotteries and raffles shall be played and conducted only by the methods permitted in the act. No other form, means of selection, or method of play shall be allowed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 7.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska County and City Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-601.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>