<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-241.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-241.03</statuteno><catchline>Bingo occasions; additional restrictions; department; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Irrespective of the number of organizations authorized to hold bingo occasions within a premises:</para><para>(a) No more than two bingo occasions per calendar week shall be held within a premises except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this section; and</para><para>(b) No more than four limited period bingos with an aggregate of no more than twelve days per twelve-month period commencing October 1 of each year or such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation and no more than two special event bingos with an aggregate of no more than fourteen days per calendar year shall be held within a premises.</para><para>(2) Bingo occasions held as part of a limited period bingo or special event bingo, or a bingo occasion that was canceled due to an act of God and rescheduled pursuant to section 9-241.02, shall not be counted in determining whether the use of a premises is in compliance with subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding the restriction contained in subdivision (1)(a) of this section, the department may authorize more than two bingo occasions per calendar week to be held within a premises if a licensed organization or commercial lessor can demonstrate in writing to the department that utilizing the premises for the conduct of bingo more than two times per calendar week will result in a cost savings for each of the licensed organizations who would be utilizing the premises. If the department authorizes a premises to be used more than two times per calendar week, the department shall not permit more than one bingo occasion per calendar day to be held in a premises except when one of the occasions is a limited period bingo or a special event bingo.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 268, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>