<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id450"><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-651.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>9-651.01</statuteno><catchline>Lottery ticket, keno game; digital-on-premises ticket; purchase and sale; requirements; controls.</catchline><para>(1) Any purchase of a ticket for a keno game shall be made in person at the location of the lottery operator or an authorized sales outlet location.</para><para>(2) The lottery operator shall file with the department the address of each location where digital-on-premises tickets are sold. The lottery operator shall use reasonable safeguards approved by the department to ensure that digital-on-premises tickets are only accessible to individuals nineteen years of age or older.</para><para>(3) The lottery operator shall submit controls, for approval by the department, that include the following at the location of the lottery operator or the locations of its associated authorized sales outlets at which digital-on-premises tickets are sold:</para><para>(a) Any specific procedure and any technology partner used to fulfill the requirements set forth by the department;</para><para>(b) Any location detection procedure to reasonably detect and dynamically monitor the location of a player attempting to purchase a digital-on-premises ticket for a keno game. The location procedures shall be designed so that a player outside the permitted boundary is rejected and the player is notified. The permitted boundary shall be established in such a manner that access is not regularly available away from the property on which the licensed premises is situated and such boundary is as closely matching to the actual or legal boundaries of the licensed premises as reasonably possible;</para><para>(c) Any other specific controls as designated by the department;</para><para>(d) A process to prominently display and easily impose any limitation parameters relating to the purchase of a digital-on-premises ticket for a keno game; and</para><para>(e) An easy and obvious method for a player to make a complaint and to enable the player to notify the department if such complaint has not been or cannot be addressed by the lottery operator.</para><para>(4) The department shall approve or deny the controls within thirty days after submission. If denied, the department shall provide the reasons for denial and allow the lottery operator to resubmit revised controls.</para><para>(5) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations relating to digital-on-premises tickets. Such rules and regulations shall be adopted and promulgated no later than January 1, 2024.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB775, &#167; 11. </para><effectivedate>September 2, 2023</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>