<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-432"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-432</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; power to seize contraband; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, at the direction of the Tax Commissioner, or any peace officer of this state may seize, without a warrant, the following contraband goods found any place in this state: (a) Any lottery or raffle tickets or stubs that are being sold which are not properly printed as required in section 9-431 or which do not meet the other requirements of such section; (b) any lottery or raffle tickets or stubs that are being sold without the proper license or permit; or (c) any lottery or raffle tickets or stubs that have been sold in violation of the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner may, upon satisfactory proof, direct return of any confiscated lottery or raffle tickets or stubs when he or she has reason to believe that the owner has not willfully or intentionally failed to comply with the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act.</para><para>(3) The Tax Commissioner may, upon finding that an owner of contraband goods has willfully or intentionally failed to comply with the act, confiscate such goods. Any lottery or raffle tickets or stubs confiscated shall be destroyed.</para><para>(4) The seizure of lottery or raffle tickets or stubs under this section shall not relieve any person from a fine, imprisonment, or other penalty for violation of the act.</para><para>(5) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, when directed to do so by the Tax Commissioner, or any peace officer of this state shall not be responsible for negligence in any court for the seizure or confiscation of any lottery or raffle ticket or stub pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 153.</para></source></law></legaldoc>