<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-625"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-625</statuteno><catchline>Lotteries; established by political subdivision; election; approval required; joint lottery.</catchline><para>Any county, city, or village may establish and conduct a lottery if an election is first held pursuant to this section. Only one scheme or type of lottery may be conducted by a county, city, or village at one time. No county, city, or village shall establish and conduct a lottery until such course of action has been approved by a majority of the registered voters of such county, city, or village casting ballots on the issue at a regular election or a special election called by the governing board of the county, city, or village for such purpose. This section shall not be construed to prohibit any county, city, or village from conducting a lottery if such course of action was approved prior to July 17, 1986, by a majority of the registered voters of such county, city, or village casting ballots on the issue.</para><para>Any lottery established pursuant to this section which is authorized by an election held on or after October 1, 1989, pursuant to this section that is not in operation for any ten consecutive years shall no longer be authorized under this section. If the voters in a county, city, or village approve a lottery on or after October 1, 1989, pursuant to this section but the lottery does not actually begin operation within ten years of the date that the results of the election are certified, the lottery shall no longer be authorized under this section. Any lottery no longer authorized under this section because it did not operate within the ten-year period provided in this section may be reauthorized by a majority vote of the registered voters of the county, city, or village casting ballots on the issue at a subsequent election pursuant to this section.</para><para>Except for any restriction imposed pursuant to section 9-643, any county, city, or village may conduct a lottery only within the boundaries of such county, city, or village, or within a licensed racetrack enclosure which abuts the corporate limits thereof or which is within the zoning jurisdiction of a city, except that nothing in this section shall prohibit a county, city, or village from entering into an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act to conduct a joint lottery with another county, city, or village which has established a lottery in accordance with this section.</para><para>If any county, city, or village is conducting a lottery at the time it is consolidated into a municipal county and such county, city, or village is abolished as of the date of creation of the municipal county, the municipal county shall be subject to the same rights and obligations with respect to such lottery or lotteries as the counties, cities, and villages which were abolished, including any rights or obligations under lottery contracts of such counties, cities, and villages. Such lottery shall continue to be subject to all other provisions of the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, except that such lottery shall not be expanded to any new location in any area of the municipal county where such lottery was not previously authorized before the consolidation unless such expansion has been approved by a majority of the registered voters of such municipal county voting at a regular election or a special election called by the governing board of the municipal county for such purpose.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 232; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 259, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 949, &#167; 75; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1985), &#167; 28-1116; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 179; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 9-608; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 53.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>