
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" id="id6" statutenumber="9-255.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">9-255.04</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Expenses; limitations;
allocation; payment of workers; expenses; how paid.</catchline><para>(1)
No expense shall be incurred or amounts paid in connection with the conduct
of bingo by a licensed organization except those which are reasonable and
necessary.</para>
<para>(2) A licensed organization shall not spend more than fourteen
percent of its bingo gross receipts to pay the expenses of conducting bingo.
The actual cost of (a) license and local permit fees, (b) any taxes authorized
by the Nebraska Bingo Act, (c) bingo and promotional prizes, (d) the purchase,
rental, or lease of bingo equipment, and (e) the rental or lease of a premises
for the conduct of bingo and the purchase, rental, or lease of personal property
as allowed by the department in rule and regulation which is necessary for
the conduct of bingo shall not be included in determining compliance with
the expense limitation contained in this section.</para>
<para>(3) A licensed organization which is also licensed to conduct
a lottery by the sale of pickle cards pursuant to the Nebraska Pickle Card
Lottery Act may allocate a portion of the expenses associated with the conduct
of its bingo occasions to its lottery by the sale of pickle cards conducted
at such bingo occasions. Such allocation shall be based upon the percentage
that pickle card gross proceeds derived from the sale of pickle cards at the
bingo occasions represents to the total of bingo gross receipts and pickle
card gross proceeds derived from such bingo occasions for the previous annual
reporting period. An organization licensed to conduct bingo that has not been
previously licensed shall determine such allocation based upon the percentage
that pickle card gross proceeds derived from the sale of pickle cards at the
bingo occasions represents to the total of bingo gross receipts and pickle
card gross proceeds derived from such bingo occasions for the initial three
consecutive calendar months of operation.</para>
<para>(4) The total amount of expenses that may be allocated to
the organization's lottery by the sale of pickle cards shall be subject to
the limitations on bingo expenses as provided for in the Nebraska Bingo Act
with respect to the fourteen-percent expense limitation and the fair-market-value
limitation on the purchase, rental, or lease of bingo equipment and the rental
or lease of personal property or of a premises for the conduct of bingo. No
portion of the twelve percent of the definite
profit of a pickle card unit as allowed by section 9-347 to pay the allowable
expenses of operating a lottery by the sale of pickle cards shall be used
to pay any expenses associated with the sale of pickle cards at a bingo occasion.</para>
<para>(5) All persons paid for working at a bingo occasion, including
pickle card sellers but excluding concession workers, shall be paid only by
a check written from the licensed organization's bingo checking account and
shall not receive any other compensation or payment for working at a bingo
occasion from any other source. Such wages shall be at an hourly or occasion
rate and shall be included in the amount allowed by the expense limitation
provided in subsection (2) of this section. No person shall receive any compensation
or payment from a licensed organization based upon a percentage of the organization's
bingo gross receipts or profit.</para>
<para>(6) No expenses associated with the conduct of bingo may be
paid directly from the licensed organization's pickle card checking account.
A licensed organization may transfer funds from its pickle card checking account
to its bingo checking account as permitted by subsection (3) of this section
by a check drawn on the pickle card checking account or by electronic funds
transfer as provided only by section 9-347.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB286, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>