<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-233</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; classes; fees.</catchline><para>(1) The department may issue an applicant organization one of the following classes of bingo licenses:</para><para>(a) A Class I license which shall include organizations with gross receipts from the conduct of bingo which are less than one hundred thousand dollars per twelve-month period commencing October 1 of each year or such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation; or</para><para>(b) A Class II license which shall include organizations with gross receipts from the conduct of bingo equal to or greater than one hundred thousand dollars per twelve-month period commencing October 1 of each year or such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, when bingo occasions are conducted on a joint basis by two or more licensed organizations, the class of license required shall be determined based upon the combined gross receipts of all licensed organizations involved in the conduct of the bingo occasion.</para><para>(3) A biennial fee of thirty dollars shall be charged for a Class I license, and a biennial fee of one hundred dollars shall be charged for a Class II license.</para><para>(4) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish reporting requirements for each class of license issued.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 351, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 259, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 949, &#167; 22; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1984, &#167; 9-143; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 295, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>