<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-232.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-232.02</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; renewal; procedure; fee.</catchline><para>(1) All licenses to conduct bingo and licenses issued to utilization-of-funds members, gaming managers, or commercial lessors shall expire as provided in this section and may be renewed biennially. An application for license renewal shall be submitted at least forty-five days prior to the expiration date of the license. The department may prescribe a separate application form for renewal purposes for any license application required by the Nebraska Bingo Act. The renewal application may require such information as the department deems necessary for the proper administration of the act.</para><para>(2) A license to conduct bingo issued to a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) or (c)(4) of the Internal Revenue Code and any license issued to a utilization-of-funds member or gaming manager for such nonprofit organization shall expire on September 30 of each odd-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. The biennial license fee for a utilization-of-funds member shall be forty dollars and the biennial license fee for a gaming manager shall be one hundred dollars.</para><para>(3) A license to conduct bingo issued to a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(5), (c)(8), (c)(10), or (c)(19) of the Internal Revenue Code or any volunteer fire company or volunteer first-aid, rescue, ambulance, or emergency squad and any license issued to a utilization-of-funds member or gaming manager for such nonprofit organization or volunteer fire company or volunteer first-aid, rescue, ambulance, or emergency squad shall expire on September 30 of each even-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. The biennial license fee for a utilization-of-funds member shall be forty dollars and the biennial license fee for a gaming manager shall be one hundred dollars.</para><para>(4) A license issued to a commercial lessor shall expire on September 30 of each odd-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>