<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-649"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-649</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; power to seize contraband; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, at the direction of the Tax Commissioner, or any peace officer of this state may seize, without a warrant, the following contraband goods found any place in this state: (a) Any lottery equipment or supplies which do not conform in all respects to the requirements of the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act and any other specifications imposed by the department by rule and regulation; (b) any lottery equipment or supplies that are being sold without the proper license; (c) any lottery equipment or supplies that have been sold in violation of the act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act; or (d) any lottery equipment or supplies used in connection with any lottery that has been or is being conducted in violation of the act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner may, upon satisfactory proof, direct the return of any seized lottery equipment or supplies when he or she has reason to believe that the owner has not willfully or intentionally failed to comply with the act.</para><para>(3) The Tax Commissioner may, upon finding that an owner of contraband goods has willfully or intentionally failed to comply with the act, confiscate such goods. Any lottery equipment or supplies confiscated shall be destroyed.</para><para>(4) The seizure of contraband goods under this section shall not relieve any person from a fine, imprisonment, or other penalty for violation of the act.</para><para>(5) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, when directed to do so by the Tax Commissioner, or any peace officer of this state shall not be responsible for negligence in any court for the seizure or confiscation of any lottery equipment or supplies pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 66.</para></source></law></legaldoc>