<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" id="id6" statutenumber="9-701"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>9-701</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Conduct of gift enterprises;
conditions; prohibited acts; violation; penalties; venue; enforcement.</catchline>
<para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Gift enterprise means a contest, game of chance, savings promotion raffle, or
game promotion which is conducted within the state or throughout the state
and other states in connection with the sale of consumer or trade products
or services solely as business promotions and in which the elements of chance
and prize are present. Gift enterprise does not include any scheme using the
game of bingo or keno; any non-telecommunication-related, player-activated
electronic or electromechanical facsimile of any game of chance; or any slot
machine of any kind. A gift enterprise shall not utilize pickle cards as defined
in section 9-315. Promotional game tickets may be utilized subject to the
following:</para>
<para>(i) The tickets utilized shall be manufactured or imprinted
with the name of the operator on each ticket;</para>
<para>(ii) The tickets utilized shall not be manufactured with a
cost per play printed on them; and</para>
<para>(iii) The tickets utilized shall not be substantially similar
to any type of pickle card approved by the Department of Revenue pursuant
to section 9-332.01;</para>
<para>(b) Operator means any person, firm, corporation, association,
governmental entity, or agent or employee thereof who promotes, operates,
or conducts a gift enterprise. Operator does not include any nonprofit organization
or any agent or employee thereof, except that operator includes any credit
union chartered under state or federal law or any agent or employee thereof
who promotes, operates, or conducts a gift enterprise; and</para>
<para>(c) Savings
promotion raffle means a contest conducted by a credit union chartered under
state or federal law or any agent or employee thereof in which a chance of
winning a designated prize is obtained by the deposit of a specified amount
of money in a savings account or other savings program if each entry has an
equal chance of winning.</para><para>(2) Any operator
may conduct a gift enterprise within this state in accordance with this section.</para>
<para>(3) An operator shall not:</para>
<para>(a) Design, engage in, promote, or conduct a gift enterprise
in connection with the promotion or sale of consumer products or services
in which the winner may be unfairly predetermined or the game may be manipulated
or rigged;</para>
<para>(b) Arbitrarily remove, disqualify, disallow, or reject any
entry;</para>
<para>(c) Fail to award prizes offered;</para>
<para>(d) Print, publish, or circulate literature or advertising
material used in connection with such gift enterprise which is false, deceptive,
or misleading; or</para>
<para>(e) Require an entry fee, a payment or promise of payment
of any valuable consideration, or any other consideration as a condition of
entering a gift enterprise or winning a prize from the gift enterprise, except
that a contest, game of chance, or business promotion may require, as a condition
of participation, evidence of the purchase of a product or service as long
as the purchase price charged for such product or service is not greater than
it would have been without the contest, game of chance, or business promotion.
For purposes of this section, consideration shall not include (i) filling
out an entry blank, (ii) entering by mail with the purchase of postage at
a cost no greater than the cost of postage for a first-class letter weighing
one ounce or less, (iii)
entering by a telephone call to the operator of or for the gift enterprise
at a cost no greater than the cost of postage for a first-class letter weighing
one ounce or less. When the only method of entry is by telephone, the cost
to the entrant of the telephone call shall not exceed the cost of postage
for a first-class letter weighing one ounce or less for any reason, including
(A) whether any communication occurred during the call which was not related
to the gift enterprise or (B) the fact that the cost of the call to the operator
was greater than the cost to the entrant allowed under this section, or (iv) the deposit of money in a savings
account or other savings program, regardless of the interest rate earned by
such account or program.</para>
<para>(4) An operator
shall disclose to participants all terms and conditions of a gift enterprise.</para>
<para>(5)(a) The Department of Revenue
may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out the
operation of gift enterprises.</para>
<para>(b) Whenever the department has reason to believe that a gift
enterprise is being operated in violation of this section or the department's
rules and regulations, it may bring an action in the district court of Lancaster
County in the name of and on behalf of the people of the State of Nebraska
against the operator of the gift enterprise to enjoin the continued operation
of such gift enterprise anywhere in the state.</para>
<para>(6)(a) Any person, firm, corporation,
association, or agent or employee thereof who engages in any unlawful acts
or practices pursuant to this section or violates any of the rules and regulations
promulgated pursuant to this section shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(b) Any person, firm, corporation, association, or agent or
employee thereof who violates any provision of this section or any of the
rules and regulations promulgated pursuant to this section shall be liable
to pay a civil penalty of not more than one thousand dollars imposed by the
district court of Lancaster County for each such violation which shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for
distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution
of Nebraska. Each day of continued violation shall constitute
a separate offense or violation for purposes of this section.</para>
<para>(7) A credit
union may limit the number of chances that a participant in a savings promotion
raffle may obtain for making the required deposits but shall not limit the
number of deposits.</para><para>(8) In
all proceedings initiated in any court or otherwise under this section, the
Attorney General or appropriate county attorney shall prosecute and defend
all such proceedings.</para>
<para>(9) This section shall not
apply to any activity authorized and regulated under the Nebraska Bingo Act,
the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle
Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, or the Nebraska Small Lottery and
Raffle Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 38, &#167; 230; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 259, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1985), &#167; 28-1114; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 184; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 54, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 113; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB524, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska County and City Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-601.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
