<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-424"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-424</statuteno><catchline>License; application; contents; fee; duty to keep current.</catchline><para>(1) Each applicant for a license to conduct a lottery or raffle shall file with the department an application on a form prescribed by the department. Each application shall include:</para><para>(a) The name and address of the applicant and, if the applicant is an individual, his or her social security number;</para><para>(b) Sufficient facts relating to the incorporation or organization of the applicant to enable the department to determine if the applicant is eligible for a license under section 9-423;</para><para>(c) The name and address of each officer of the applicant organization;</para><para>(d) The name, address, social security number, date of birth, and years of membership of a bona fide and active member of the applicant organization to be licensed as a utilization-of-funds member. Such person shall have been an active and bona fide member of the applicant organization for at least one year preceding the date the application is filed with the department unless the applicant organization can provide evidence that the one-year requirement would impose an undue hardship on the organization. Such person shall sign a sworn statement indicating that he or she agrees to comply with all provisions of the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act and all rules and regulations adopted pursuant to the act, that no commission, fee, rent, salary, profits, compensation, or recompense will be paid to any person or organization except payments authorized by the act, and that all net profits will be spent only for lawful purposes. The department may prescribe a separate application for such license;</para><para>(e) A roster of members, if the department deems it necessary and proper;</para><para>(f) Other information which the department deems necessary; and</para><para>(g) A thirty-dollar biennial license fee for the organization and a forty-dollar biennial license fee for each utilization-of-funds member.</para><para>(2) The information required by this section shall be kept current. An organization shall notify the department within thirty days if any information in the application is no longer correct and shall supply the correct information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 13.</para></source></law></legaldoc>