<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-329.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-329.02</statuteno><catchline>Pickle card operator; license required; application; contents; fee; restrictions; authorization required; equipment requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A pickle card operator shall not be eligible to sell individual pickle cards as opportunities to participate in a lottery by the sale of pickle cards without first obtaining a license.</para><para>(2) Any sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation wishing to operate as a pickle card operator in this state shall file an application with the department for a license on a form prescribed by the department. Each application for a license shall include (a) the name, address, and state identification number of the sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation applying for the license, (b) a description of the premises on which the pickle cards will be sold or offered for sale, (c) if the applicant is an individual, the applicant's social security number, and (d) such other information which the department deems necessary. The information required by this subsection shall be kept current. A pickle card operator shall notify the department within thirty days if any information in the application is no longer correct and shall supply the correct information.</para><para>(3) A biennial fee of one hundred dollars shall be charged for each license issued pursuant to this section and shall be paid for by the applicant. A licensed organization shall not pay the required licensing fees of a pickle card operator as an inducement for the pickle card operator to sell individual pickle cards on its behalf. Such licenses shall expire on September 30 of each odd-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation and may be renewed biennially. The department shall remit the proceeds from such license fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the Charitable Gaming Operations Fund. An application for license renewal shall be submitted to the department at least sixty days prior to the expiration date of the license.</para><para>(4) One license issued to any sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation under this section as a pickle card operator shall cover the sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation and the employees of the licensed pickle card operator. Any license issued pursuant to this section shall be valid only for the sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation in the name of which it was issued and shall allow the sale of individual pickle cards only on the premises described in the pickle card operator's application for a license. A pickle card operator's license may not be transferred under any circumstances including change of ownership.</para><para>(5) The department may prescribe a separate application form for renewal purposes.</para><para>(6) A licensed pickle card operator shall not sell individual pickle cards on behalf of a licensed organization until an authorization has been obtained from the department by the licensed organization. The licensed organization shall file an application with the department for such authorization on a form prescribed by the department. Each application for an authorization shall include (a) the name, address, and state identification number of the licensed pickle card operator and (b) such other information which the department deems necessary. The application shall include a statement signed by a person licensed as a utilization-of-funds member signifying that such licensed organization approves the pickle card operator to sell individual pickle cards on behalf of such organization.</para><para>(7) A pickle card operator may sell individual pickle cards on behalf of more than one licensed organization. Each licensed organization for which the pickle card operator desires to sell individual pickle cards shall obtain the authorization described in subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(8) A pickle card operator who sells individual pickle cards through a coin-operated or currency-operated dispensing device shall purchase, lease, or rent its own equipment. If such equipment is obtained from a licensed organization or distributor, it shall be purchased, leased, or rented at a rate not less than fair market value. A licensed organization or distributor shall not provide such equipment to a pickle card operator free of charge or at a rate less than fair market value as an inducement for the pickle card operator to sell a licensed organization's individual pickle cards. The department may require a licensed organization, distributor, or pickle card operator to provide such documentation as the department deems necessary to verify that a pickle card operator has purchased, leased, or rented the equipment for a rate not less than fair market value.</para><para>(9) No pickle card operator shall generate revenue from the sale of individual pickle cards which exceeds the revenue generated from other retail sales on an annual basis. For purposes of this subsection, retail sales shall not include revenue generated from other charitable gaming activities authorized by Chapter 9.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1232, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 111; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 11.</para></source></law></legaldoc>