<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-808"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-808</statuteno><catchline>Division; personnel; investigators or security personnel; powers and duties; confidentiality; exception.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall employ or contract with such personnel as necessary to carry out the responsibilities of the division. The Tax Commissioner shall employ investigators or security personnel who shall be vested with the authority and power of a law enforcement officer to carry out the laws of this state administered by the Tax Commissioner or the Department of Revenue.</para><para>(2) Investigators or security personnel of the division may enter and search premises and seize all relevant materials pursuant to a warrant issued by a court.</para><para>(3)(a) Investigators or security personnel shall, as deemed necessary, conduct background investigations of all individuals seeking employment in the division. Such background investigations shall include, but not be limited to, police records checks, conviction records checks, national and statewide criminal records clearinghouse checks, and fingerprint checks.</para><para>(b) It shall be a condition of employment in the division that an individual supply investigators or security personnel with his or her fingerprints for the purpose of conducting a background investigation for employment purposes.</para><para>(c) Any individual convicted of any crime involving moral turpitude, fraud, theft, theft of services, and theft by deception and any individual whose constitutional rights have been forfeited and not restored shall not be eligible for employment in the division.</para><para>(d) All information obtained through a background investigation performed by the division shall be confidential, except that the Tax Commissioner may exchange such confidential information with state, federal, and local law enforcement agencies.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 24.</para></source></law></legaldoc>