<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-241.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-241.08</statuteno><catchline>Bingo game; participation; conduct of bingo; restrictions.</catchline><para>(1) No person under eighteen years of age shall play or participate in any bingo game, except that any person may play bingo at a limited period bingo or special event bingo if (a) no alcoholic beverages are served and (b) no prize or prizes to be awarded exceed twenty-five dollars in value per game.</para><para>(2) All persons involved in the conduct of bingo must be at least eighteen years of age.</para><para>(3) No person who is conducting or assisting in the conduct of a bingo occasion shall be permitted to participate as a player at that bingo occasion.</para><para>(4) No licensed commercial lessor, distributor, or manufacturer, person having a substantial interest in a licensed commercial lessor, distributor, or manufacturer, or employee or agent of a licensed commercial lessor, distributor, or manufacturer shall operate, manage, conduct, advise, or assist in the operating, managing, conducting, promoting, or administering of any bingo game or occasion. For purposes of this subsection, the term assist shall include, but not be limited to, the payment of any expense of a licensed organization, whether such payment is by loan or otherwise.</para><para>(5) No person, licensee, or permittee or employee or agent thereof shall knowingly permit an individual under eighteen years of age to play or participate in any way in a bingo game conducted pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act, excluding those individuals allowed by law to play at a limited period bingo or special event bingo when (a) no alcoholic beverages are served and (b) no prize or prizes that will be awarded exceed twenty-five dollars in value per game.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 5.</para></source></law></legaldoc>