<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-241.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-241.05</statuteno><catchline>Bingo equipment; obtain from licensed distributor; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) A licensed organization shall purchase or otherwise obtain bingo equipment only from a licensed distributor, except that a licensed organization may rent or lease bingo equipment, excluding disposable paper bingo cards, only from:</para><para>(a) A licensed distributor; or</para><para>(b) The licensed commercial lessor from whom the organization is leasing a premises for the conduct of bingo.</para><para>(2) All rental or lease agreements for bingo equipment shall be in writing and shall be subject to prior approval by the department.</para><para>(3) No purchase, rental, or lease of bingo equipment shall be in excess of fair market value.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section shall prohibit:</para><para>(a) Two licensed organizations which may be conducting bingo within the same premises from equally sharing the cost of purchasing bingo equipment, excluding disposable paper bingo cards, and sharing its use;</para><para>(b) A licensed organization from lending its bingo equipment, excluding disposable paper bingo cards, without charge to another licensed organization in an emergency situation or to a qualifying nonprofit organization to use at a special event bingo;</para><para>(c) A licensed organization which has purchased or intends to purchase new bingo equipment from selling or donating its old bingo equipment to another licensed organization if prior written approval has been obtained from the department;</para><para>(d) An organization which has voluntarily canceled or allowed its license to conduct bingo to lapse or an organization which has had its license to conduct bingo suspended, canceled, or revoked from selling or donating its bingo equipment to another licensed organization if prior written approval has been obtained from the department; or</para><para>(e) A licensed organization from selling or donating its disposable paper bingo cards, when authorization has been obtained from the department, to another licensed organization in an emergency situation or to a qualifying nonprofit organization to use at a special event bingo.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 15.</para></source></law></legaldoc>