<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-350"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-350</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; power to seize contraband; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, at the direction of the Tax Commissioner, or any peace officer of this state may seize, without a warrant, the following contraband goods found any place in this state: (a) Any pickle cards and pickle card units declared to be contraband goods in section 9-338; (b) any pickle cards that are not properly printed as required in section 9-346 or on which the tax has not been paid, except for pickle cards in the possession of a licensed distributor or licensed manufacturer; (c) any pickle cards or pickle card units purchased by any licensed organization from any source other than a licensed distributor; (d) any pickle cards or pickle card units that are being sold without all of the proper licenses; (e) any pickle card units or pickle cards that have been sold in violation of the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to such act; (f) any pickle cards or pickle card units in the possession of any licensee whose license has been revoked, canceled, or suspended or any pickle cards or pickle card units in the possession of any former licensee whose license has expired; or (g) any coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device which contains any pickle cards deemed to be contraband goods pursuant to this subsection or any such device which does not have permanently and conspicuously affixed to it a current registration decal required by section 9-345.03.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner may, upon satisfactory proof, direct return of any confiscated pickle cards or pickle card units when he or she has reason to believe that the entity from whom the pickle cards or pickle card units were confiscated has not willfully or intentionally evaded any tax or failed to comply with the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act. Upon receipt of an affidavit of ownership, the Tax Commissioner shall relinquish possession of a seized coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device to the lawful owners of the device if the device is not needed as evidence by the department, any county attorney, or the Attorney General at an administrative or judicial hearing, if contraband pickle cards have been removed from the device, and in the event the device was seized due to a violation of subsection (2) of section 9-345.03, if the entity who was utilizing the device has applied for and has received a current registration decal for the seized device.</para><para>(3) The Tax Commissioner may, upon finding that an entity in possession of contraband goods has willfully or intentionally evaded any tax or failed to comply with the act, confiscate such goods. Any pickle cards or pickle card units confiscated shall be destroyed.</para><para>(4) The seizure and destruction of coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing devices, pickle cards, or pickle card units shall not relieve any person from a fine, imprisonment, or other penalty for violation of the act.</para><para>(5) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, at the direction of the Tax Commissioner, may seal any pickle cards, pickle card units, or coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing devices deemed to be contraband goods pursuant to this section. Such seal shall not be broken until authorized by the Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees. If the seal on a coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device is broken prior to payment of the penalty and registration of the device required under section 9-345.03, the device shall be subject to forfeiture and sale by the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(6) The Tax Commissioner or his or her agents or employees, when directed to do so by the Tax Commissioner, or any peace officer of this state shall not be responsible for negligence in any court for the sealing, seizure, or confiscation of any coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device, pickle card, or pickle card unit pursuant to this section.</para><para>(7) Possession of pickle cards or pickle card units which are deemed to be contraband goods pursuant to this section shall be a violation of the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 408, &#167; 29; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1985, &#167; 9-187.02; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 116; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 19.</para></source></law></legaldoc>