<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-332"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-332</statuteno><catchline>Manufacturer of pickle cards; license required; application; fee; change in information; renewal.</catchline><para>A manufacturer shall obtain a license from the department prior to manufacturing or selling or supplying to any licensed distributor in this state any pickle cards or pickle card units or engaging in any interstate activities relating to such pickle cards or pickle card units, except that nothing in this section shall prohibit a manufacturer from marketing, selling, or otherwise providing pickle cards or pickle card units to a federally recognized Indian tribe for use in a Class II gaming activity authorized by the federal Indian Gaming Regulatory Act. The applicant shall include with the application form prescribed by the department a biennial license fee of three thousand fifty dollars, a sworn statement by the applicant or appropriate officer of the applicant that the applicant will comply with all provisions of the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act and all rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act, and such other information as the department deems necessary. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number.</para><para>The applicant shall notify the department within thirty days of any change in the information submitted on or with the application form. The applicant shall comply with all applicable laws of the United States and the State of Nebraska and all applicable rules and regulations of the department.</para><para>Manufacturers' licenses shall expire on September 30 of every odd-numbered year or such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. Manufacturers' licenses may be renewed biennially. An application for license renewal shall be submitted to the department at least forty-five days prior to the expiration date of the license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 408, &#167; 19; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1985, &#167; 9-143.02; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 67.</para></source></law></legaldoc>