<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-328"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-328</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; renewal; application; requirements; classes; fees.</catchline><para>(1) All licenses to conduct a lottery by the sale of pickle cards and licenses issued to utilization-of-funds members shall expire as provided in this section and may be renewed biennially. An application for license renewal shall be submitted to the department at least forty-five days prior to the expiration date of the license unless such application only pertains to the conduct of a lottery by the sale of pickle cards at a special function as provided in section 9-345.01.</para><para>(2) A license to conduct a lottery by the sale of pickle cards issued to a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) or (c)(4) of the Internal Revenue Code and any license issued to a utilization-of-funds member for such nonprofit organization shall expire on September 30 of each odd-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. </para><para>(3) A license to conduct a lottery by the sale of pickle cards issued to a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(5), (c)(7), (c)(8), (c)(10), or (c)(19) of the Internal Revenue Code or any volunteer fire company or volunteer first-aid, rescue, ambulance, or emergency squad and any license issued to a utilization-of-funds member for such nonprofit organization or volunteer fire company or volunteer first-aid, rescue, ambulance, or emergency squad shall expire on September 30 of each even-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. </para><para>(4) The department shall establish classes of licenses for licensed organizations based upon the manner in which the licensed organization intends to sell the pickle cards. The classes shall include:</para><para>(a) Class I licenses which shall include organizations which sell individual pickle cards only at the organization's designated premises and at the organization's licensed regularly scheduled bingo occasions pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act; and</para><para>(b) Class II licenses which shall include organizations which sell the pickle cards on the premises of one or more licensed pickle card operators.</para><para>A licensed organization holding a Class II license shall be required to market and deliver its pickle cards by a licensed sales agent.</para><para>(5) A biennial license fee of two hundred dollars shall be charged for each Class I license, three hundred dollars for each Class II license, and forty dollars for a license for each utilization-of-funds member.</para><para>(6) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing reporting requirements for each class of license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1232, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 9.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>