<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-255.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-255.08</statuteno><catchline>Distributor; purchase or sale of bingo equipment; restrictions; records; reporting.</catchline><para>(1) A licensed distributor shall purchase or otherwise obtain bingo equipment only from a licensed manufacturer.</para><para>(2) A licensed distributor shall sell or otherwise supply bingo equipment for use in a bingo game regulated by the Nebraska Bingo Act only to a licensed organization, a qualifying nonprofit organization, a licensed commercial lessor, or a federally recognized Indian tribe, except that a licensed distributor shall not sell disposable paper bingo cards in this state to anyone other than a licensed organization, a qualifying nonprofit organization, or a federally recognized Indian tribe. Notwithstanding the restrictions in this subsection, a licensed distributor may, with prior authorization from the department, sell disposable paper bingo cards for use in a bingo game not regulated by the Nebraska Bingo Act.</para><para>(3) A licensed distributor shall keep and maintain a complete set of records which shall include all details of all activities of the distributor related to the conduct of the licensed activity as may be required by the department, including the quantities and types of all bingo equipment purchased and sold. Such records shall be available upon request for inspection by the department. All records required by the department shall be maintained for at least three years after the last day of the distributor's fiscal year.</para><para>(4) The department may require by rule and regulation periodic reporting from the licensed distributor relative to its bingo activities in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 20.</para></source></law></legaldoc>