<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-329.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-329.03</statuteno><catchline>Pickle card operator; qualified applicant; licensee; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) Any sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation, which holds a retail license for the sale of alcoholic liquor for consumption on the premises issued by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission pursuant to the Nebraska Liquor Control Act or which holds a retail license for the sale of alcoholic liquor for consumption off the premises, may apply for a pickle card operator's license to sell individual pickle cards as opportunities to participate in a lottery by the sale of pickle cards.</para><para>(2) A pickle card operator licensed under the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act shall not be connected with or interested in, directly or indirectly, any person, partnership, limited liability company, firm, corporation, or other party licensed as a distributor or manufacturer under section 9-330 or 9-332.</para><para>(3) A sole proprietor, partner in a partnership, member in a limited liability company, or officer or director of a corporation licensed as a pickle card operator shall not be licensed as a sales agent.</para><para>(4) A sole proprietor, partner in a partnership, member in a limited liability company, or officer or director of a corporation licensed as a pickle card operator shall not be a director, manager, trustee, or member of any governing committee, board, or body of the licensed organization on behalf of which the pickle card operator sells individual pickle cards.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1232, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 795, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 485, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>