<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-631.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-631.01</statuteno><catchline>Lottery workers; application; contents; duty to keep current; investigation; probationary license; regular license.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall be a lottery worker unless a lottery worker license application has been filed with the department. The application shall be on a form prescribed by the department and shall include:</para><para>(a) The name, address, date of birth, and social security number of the applicant;</para><para>(b) The name and state identification number of the county, city, or village, lottery operator, and sales outlet location or locations for which the applicant will be performing work;</para><para>(c) A description of the applicant's duties;</para><para>(d) A statement that the applicant has not been convicted of, forfeited bond upon a charge of, or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to any felony within ten years preceding the date of the application or any felony or misdemeanor involving fraud, theft, or any gambling activity, willful failure to make required payments or reports, or filing false reports to a governmental agency at any level;</para><para>(e) The date of signing and the signature of the applicant, under penalty of perjury, verifying that the information is true and accurate;</para><para>(f) A statement signed by a governing official of the county, city, or village or the authorized representative signifying that such county, city, or village or authorized representative has examined the completed application and approved the application for submission to the department; and</para><para>(g) Any other information which the department deems necessary.</para><para>(2) The applicant shall complete and forward the application to the county, city, or village or authorized representative. Upon receipt of the completed application the governing official of the county, city, or village or the authorized representative shall examine the application and, if the governing official of the county, city, or village or the authorized representative approves the application for submission to the department, shall sign and file the application with the department. If the application is approved by an authorized representative, a copy of the application or the information contained in the application shall be filed with the county, city, or village.</para><para>(3) The department and the county, city, or village shall have the right to conduct an investigation concerning the applicant as may be necessary or appropriate to maintain the integrity of the game.</para><para>(4) The information required by this section shall be kept current, and a new application shall be filed with the department if any information on the application is no longer correct. A county, city, village, or lottery operator shall notify the department if the person to whom the license was originally issued is no longer working for such county, city, village, or lottery operator.</para><para>(5) Falsification of information on the application by the applicant shall disqualify such applicant from being a lottery worker in addition to any other penalties which may be imposed under the laws of this state.</para><para>(6) The applicant shall be granted a probationary license as a lottery worker which shall be valid for a period of one hundred twenty days after the application is filed with the department unless such application is denied by the department. An application shall be considered filed with the department upon receipt by the department or as of the date postmarked or transmitted by electronic facsimile to the department if the application is received by the department within ten days after the date postmarked or electronically transmitted. An application postmarked or electronically transmitted but not received by the department after ten days shall not be considered filed. If proceedings to deny the license application pursuant to section 9-622 have not been initiated by the department during such probationary period, the applicant shall be granted a regular lottery worker license. The license shall be valid to allow such person to perform work for the county, city, village, lottery operator, or sales outlet location or locations unless otherwise suspended, canceled, revoked, or denied by the department or unless the license otherwise becomes invalid upon notification by the county, city, village, or lottery operator that the person to whom the license was originally issued is no longer working for such county, city, village, or lottery operator.</para><para>(7) An applicant may obtain a license as a lottery worker for more than one county, city, or village conducting a lottery pursuant to the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act if a separate application has been filed for such applicant with respect to each such county, city, or village.</para><para>(8) A lottery worker license is nontransferable and shall no longer be valid if a person is no longer employed as a lottery worker by the county, city, or village for which the lottery worker license was obtained.</para><para>(9) A person holding a license as a lottery worker under the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act shall not be connected with or interested in, directly or indirectly, any individual, sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, or other party licensed as a distributor, manufacturer, or manufacturer-distributor under section 9-255.07, 9-255.09, 9-330, 9-332, or 9-632.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 563, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 55.</para></source></law></legaldoc>