<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-340.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-340.02</statuteno><catchline>Pickle card units; dispensing devices; payment; definite profit; how remitted; delivery; credit; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) All pickle card units purchased by a licensed organization from a licensed distributor shall be paid for by a check drawn on the pickle card bank account of the licensed organization either in advance of or upon delivery of the pickle card units.</para><para>(2) A licensed pickle card operator shall remit the definite profit, less not more than thirty percent of the definite profit as allowed by subsection (4) of section 9-347, of all pickle card units received to the sponsoring licensed organization by check either in advance of or upon delivery of the pickle card units from the sales agent to the pickle card operator. Upon delivery of the pickle card units, the sales agent shall issue the pickle card operator a standard receipt prescribed by the department.</para><para>(3) Unless otherwise authorized by the department, pickle card units shall be delivered to a pickle card operator only by a sales agent's personal delivery or by delivery arranged by a sales agent through the mail or by a common carrier.</para><para>(4) No licensed organization conducting a lottery by the sale of pickle cards shall extend credit in any form, including, but not limited to, the extension of any credit with regard to the receipt of the definite profit, less not more than thirty percent of the definite profit as allowed by subsection (4) of section 9-347, of a pickle card unit from a pickle card operator upon delivery of a pickle card unit to the pickle card operator and the extension of any credit with regard to the sale or lease of any equipment or coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device used in connection with a lottery by the sale of pickle cards.</para><para>(5) All payments for the purchase, lease, or rental of a coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device by a licensed organization shall be made by a check drawn on the organization's pickle card checking account.</para><para>(6) All payments for the purchase, lease, or rental of a coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device by a licensed pickle card operator from a licensed organization shall be made by a check drawn on the business checking account of the pickle card operator or a personal checking account of an owner, partner, or officer of the pickle card operator, either at the time of or before placement of the device or on or before the first day of the period of the lease, whichever comes first.</para><para>(7) All lease or rental agreements between a licensed organization and a licensed pickle card operator for coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing devices shall be subject to approval by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1232, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 33.</para></source></law></legaldoc>