<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-425"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-425</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; renewal; application; requirements; temporary license; fee.</catchline><para>(1) All licenses to conduct a lottery or raffle and licenses issued to utilization-of-funds members shall expire as provided in this section and may be renewed biennially. An application for license renewal shall be submitted to the department at least thirty days prior to the starting date of the first lottery or raffle ticket sales for the biennial licensing period. The department may issue a temporary license prior to receiving all necessary information from the applicant.</para><para>(2) A license to conduct a lottery or raffle issued to a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) or (c)(4) of the Internal Revenue Code and any license issued to a utilization-of-funds member for such nonprofit organization shall expire on September 30 of each odd-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. A license to conduct a lottery or raffle issued to a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501 of the Internal Revenue Code, other than a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) or (c)(4) of the code, or any volunteer fire company or volunteer first-aid, rescue, ambulance, or emergency squad, and any license issued to a utilization-of-funds member for such nonprofit organization or volunteer fire company or volunteer first-aid, rescue, ambulance, or emergency squad shall expire on September 30 of each even-numbered year or on such other date as the department may prescribe by rule and regulation. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 146; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 105; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 14.</para></source></law></legaldoc>