<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-348"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-348</statuteno><catchline>Segregation of definite profit; manner of payment; records; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The definite profit, less not more than thirty percent of the definite profit as allowed by subsection (4) of section 9-347, of any lottery by the sale of pickle cards and all amounts received by any licensed organization from the sale, lease, or rental of coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing devices shall be segregated from other revenue of any licensed organization conducting the lottery and placed in a separate checking account. All lawful purpose donations and expenses relating to the licensed organization's lottery by the sale of pickle cards, including the allowable expenses, any license fees paid to the department to license the organization, each utilization-of-funds member, and any sales agent, coin-operated or currency-operated pickle card dispensing device registration fees, and the unit cost but excluding the payment of prizes for winning pickle cards, shall be paid by check from such account and shall be made payable to the ultimate use of such lawful purpose donations or expenses.</para><para>(2) Separate records shall be maintained by any licensed organization conducting a lottery by the sale of pickle cards. Each nonprofit organization conducting a lottery by the sale of pickle cards shall keep a record of all locations or persons who are paid to sell pickle cards. Records and lists required by the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act shall be preserved for at least three years. Any law enforcement agency or other agency of government shall have the authority to investigate the records relating to lotteries by the sale of pickle cards and gross proceeds from such lotteries at any time. Organizations shall, upon proper written request, deliver all such records to the department, law enforcement agency, or other agency of government for investigation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 259, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 949, &#167; 52; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1984, &#167; 9-181; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1232, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 20.</para></source></law></legaldoc>