<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id16">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" id="id18" statutenumber="9-347"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id20">9-347</statuteno><catchline id="id21">Gross proceeds;
definite profit; use; restrictions; allocation of expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The gross proceeds of any lottery by the sale of pickle cards
shall be used solely for lawful purposes, awarding of prizes, payment of the
unit cost, any commission paid to a pickle card operator, allowable expenses,
and allocations for bingo expenses as provided by subsection (5) of this section.</para>
<para>(2) Not less than sixty-five percent or more than eighty percent
of the gross proceeds of any lottery by the sale of pickle cards shall be
used for the awarding of prizes.</para>
<para>(3) Not more than twelve percent of the definite
profit of a pickle card unit shall be used by the licensed organization to
pay the allowable expenses of operating a lottery by the sale of pickle cards,
except that license fees paid to the department to license the organization,
each utilization-of-funds member, and any sales agent and pickle card dispensing
device registration fees shall not be included in determining the twelve-percent limitation on expenses and no
portion of such twelve percent shall be used
to pay any expenses associated with the sale of pickle cards at a bingo occasion
conducted pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act, and of such twelve percent
not more than six percent of the definite
profit may be used by the licensed organization for the payment of any commission,
salary, or fee to a sales agent in connection with the marketing, sale, and
delivery of a pickle card unit. When determining the twelve percent
of definite profit that is permitted to pay the allowable expenses of operating
a lottery by the sale of pickle cards, the definite profit from the sale of
pickle cards at the organization's bingo occasions shall not be included.</para>
<para>(4) Not more than thirty percent of the definite profit of
a pickle card unit shall be used by a licensed organization to pay a pickle
card operator a commission, fee, or salary for selling individual pickle cards
as opportunities for participation in a lottery by the sale of pickle cards
on behalf of the licensed organization.</para>
<para>(5) An organization licensed to conduct bingo pursuant to
the Nebraska Bingo Act may allocate a portion of the expenses associated with
the conduct of its bingo occasions to its lottery by the sale of pickle cards
conducted at such bingo occasions. Such allocation shall be based upon the
percentage that pickle card gross proceeds derived from the sale of pickle
cards at the bingo occasions represents to the total of bingo gross receipts
and pickle card gross proceeds derived from such bingo occasions for the previous
annual reporting period. An organization licensed to conduct bingo that has
not been previously licensed shall determine such allocation based upon the
percentage that pickle card gross proceeds derived from the sale of pickle
cards at the bingo occasions represents to the total of bingo gross receipts
and pickle card gross proceeds derived from such bingo occasions for the initial
three consecutive calendar months of operation. The total amount of expenses
that may be allocated to the organization's lottery by the sale of pickle
cards shall be subject to the limitations on bingo expenses as provided for
in the Nebraska Bingo Act with respect to the fourteen-percent expense limitation
and the fair-market-value limitation on the purchase, rental, or lease of
bingo equipment and the rental or lease of personal property or of a premises
for the conduct of bingo. No expenses associated with the conduct of bingo
may be paid directly from the pickle card checking account. A licensed organization
which needs to allocate a portion of the expenses associated with the conduct
of its bingo occasions to its lottery by the sale of pickle cards conducted
at such bingo occasions to pay bingo expenses as provided by this section
shall transfer funds from the pickle card checking account to the bingo checking
account by a check drawn on the pickle card checking account or by electronic
funds transfer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 113; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1232, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB286, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>