<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-232.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-232.01</statuteno><catchline>License; application; contents; restrictions on conduct of bingo; gaming manager license; fee; utilization-of-funds member; license.</catchline><para>(1) Each organization applying for a license to conduct bingo shall file with the department an application on a form prescribed by the department. Each application shall include:</para><para>(a) The name and address of the applicant organization;</para><para>(b) Sufficient facts relating to the incorporation or organization of the applicant organization to enable the department to determine if the organization is eligible for a license pursuant to section 9-231;</para><para>(c) The name and address of each officer of the applicant organization;</para><para>(d) The name, address, social security number, years of membership, and date of birth of one bona fide and active member of the organization who will serve as the organization's bingo chairperson; and</para><para>(e) The name, address, social security number, years of membership, and date of birth of no more than three bona fide and active members of the organization who will serve as alternate bingo chairpersons.</para><para>(2) In addition, each applicant organization shall include with the application:</para><para>(a) The name, address, social security number, date of birth, and years of membership of an active and bona fide member of the applicant organization to be licensed as the utilization-of-funds member. Such person shall have been an active and bona fide member of the applicant organization for at least one year preceding the date the application is filed with the department unless the applicant organization can provide evidence that the one-year requirement would impose an undue hardship on the organization. All utilization-of-funds members shall sign a sworn statement indicating that they agree to comply with all provisions of the Nebraska Bingo Act and all rules and regulations adopted pursuant to the act, that they will insure that no commission, fee, rent, salary, profits, compensation, or recompense will be paid to any person or organization, except payments authorized by the act, and that all profits will be spent only for lawful purposes. A fee of forty dollars shall be charged for a license for each utilization-of-funds member, and the department may prescribe a separate application form for such license;</para><para>(b) For a Class II license only, the name, address, social security number, and date of birth of the individual to be licensed as the gaming manager. Such person shall sign a sworn statement indicating that he or she agrees to comply with all provisions of the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, and all rules and regulations adopted pursuant to such acts. A fee of one hundred dollars shall be charged for a license for each gaming manager, and the department may prescribe a separate application form for such license;</para><para>(c) The name and address of the owner or lessor of the premises in which bingo will be conducted; and</para><para>(d) Any other information which the department deems necessary, including, but not limited to, copies of any and all lease or rental agreements and contracts entered into by the organization relative to its bingo activities.</para><para>(3) The information required by this section shall be kept current. A licensed organization shall notify the department within thirty days if any information in the application is no longer correct and shall supply the correct information.</para><para>(4) Except for a limited period bingo, a licensed organization shall not conduct any bingo game or occasion at any time, on any day, at any location, or in any manner different from that described in its most recent filing with the department unless prior approval has been obtained from the department. A request for approval to change the day, time, or location of a bingo occasion shall be made by the bingo chairperson, in writing, at least thirty days in advance of the date the proposed change is to become effective.</para><para>(5) No bingo chairperson, alternate bingo chairperson, utilization-of-funds member, or gaming manager for an organization shall be connected with, interested in, or otherwise concerned directly or indirectly with any party licensed as a manufacturer, distributor, or commercial lessor pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act or with any party licensed as a manufacturer or distributor pursuant to the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act.</para><para>(6) No person shall act as a gaming manager until he or she has received a license from the department. A gaming manager may apply for a license to act as a gaming manager for more than one licensed organization by completing a separate application and paying the license fee for each organization for which he or she intends to act as a gaming manager. No gaming manager shall be a bingo chairperson or alternate bingo chairperson, and no gaming manager shall hold any other type of license issued under the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, or the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act.</para><para>(7) No person shall act as a utilization-of-funds member until he or she has received a license from the department. A utilization-of-funds member shall not hold any other type of license issued under the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, and the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, except that a utilization-of-funds member may also be designated as the bingo chairperson or alternate bingo chairperson for the same organization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 344, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>