<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id39">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" id="id41" statutenumber="9-607"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-607</statuteno><catchline id="id44">Lottery, defined;
manner of play; designation.</catchline><para>(1) Lottery shall
mean a gambling scheme in which:</para>
<para>(a) The players pay or agree to pay something of value for
an opportunity to win;</para>
<para>(b) Winning opportunities are represented by tickets;</para>
<para>(c) Winners are solely determined by one of the following
two methods:</para>
<para>(i) By a random drawing of tickets differentiated by sequential
enumeration from a receptacle by hand whereby each ticket has an equal chance
of being chosen in the drawing; or</para>
<para>(ii) By use of a game known as keno in which a player selects
up to twenty numbers from a total of eighty numbers on a paper ticket and
a computer, other electronic selection device, or electrically operated blower
machine which is not player-activated randomly selects up to twenty numbers
from the same pool of eighty numbers and the winning players are determined
by the correct matching of the numbers on the paper ticket selected by the
players with the numbers randomly selected by the computer, other electronic
selection device, or electrically operated blower machine, except that (A) no keno game shall permit
or require player activation
of lottery equipment and (B) the
random selection of numbers by the computer, other electronic selection device,
or electrically operated blower machine shall not occur within five minutes
of the completion of the previous selection of random numbers; and</para>
<para>(d) The holders of the winning paper tickets are to receive
cash or prizes redeemable for cash. Selection of a winner or winners shall
be predicated solely on chance.</para>
<para>(2) Lottery shall not include:</para>
<para>(a) Any gambling scheme which uses any mechanical gaming device,
computer gaming device, electronic gaming device, or video gaming device which
has the capability of awarding something of value, free games redeemable for
something of value, or tickets or stubs redeemable for something of value;</para>
<para>(b) Any activity authorized or regulated under the Nebraska
Bingo Act, the Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery
Act, the Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, the State Lottery Act, section
9-701, or Chapter 2, article 12; or</para>
<para>(c) Any activity prohibited under Chapter 28, article 11.</para>
<para>(3) Notwithstanding the requirement in subdivision (1)(c)(ii)
of this section that a player select up to twenty numbers, a player may select
more than twenty numbers on a paper ticket when a top or bottom, left or right,
edge, or way ticket is played. For a top or bottom ticket, the player shall
select all numbers from one through forty or all numbers from forty-one through
eighty. For a left or right ticket, the player shall select all numbers ending
in one through five or all numbers ending in six through zero. For an edge
ticket, the player shall select all of the numbers comprising the outside
edge of the ticket. For a way ticket, the player shall select a combination
of groups of numbers in multiple ways on a single ticket.</para>
<para>(4) A county, city, or village conducting a keno lottery shall
designate the method of winning number selection to be used in the lottery
and submit such designation in writing to the department prior to conducting
a keno lottery. Only those methods of winning number selection described in
subdivision (1)(c)(ii) of this section shall be permitted, and the method
of winning number selection initially utilized may only be changed once during
that business day as set forth in the designation. A county, city, or village
shall not change the method or methods of winning number selection filed with
the department or allow it to be changed once such initial designation has
been made unless (a) otherwise authorized in writing by the department based
upon a written request from the county, city, or village or (b) an emergency
arises in which case a ball draw method of number selection would be switched
to a number selection by a random number generator. An emergency situation
shall be reported by the county, city, or village to the department within
twenty-four hours of its occurrence.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 178; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 795, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 563, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB490, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
