<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-1,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1,104</statuteno><catchline>Contract or license applicant or holder; fingerprinting; criminal history record information check; personal history report; background investigation; facilities inspection; required; when; payment of costs; refusal to comply; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Any person applying for or holding a contract or license (a) as a distributor, gaming manager, or manufacturer pursuant to the Nebraska Bingo Act, (b) as a distributor, manufacturer, pickle card operator, or sales agent pursuant to the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, (c) as a lottery operator, lottery worker who is designated as a keno manager or who has authority over the verification of winning number selection by an electrically operated blower machine, manufacturer-distributor, or sales outlet location pursuant to the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, or (d) pursuant to the State Lottery Act shall be subject to fingerprinting and a check of his or her criminal history record information maintained by the Identification Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation through the Nebraska State Patrol for the purpose of determining whether the Department of Revenue has a basis to deny the contract or license application or to suspend, cancel, revoke, or terminate the person's contract or license. Each applicant for or party holding a license as a manufacturer, distributor, manufacturer-distributor, or lottery operator shall also submit a personal history report to the department on a form provided by the department and may be subject to a background investigation, an inspection of the applicant's or licensee's facilities, or both. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall also include the applicant's social security number.</para><para>(2)(a) If the applicant, party to the contract, or licensee is a corporation, the persons subject to such requirements shall include any officer or director of the corporation, his or her spouse, any person or entity directly or indirectly associated with such corporation in a consulting or other capacity which may impair the security, honesty, or integrity of the operation or conduct of the activities for which the application is made or contract or license is held, and, if applicable, any person or entity holding in the aggregate ten percent or more of the debt or equity of the corporation. If any person or entity holding ten percent or more of the debt or equity of the applicant, contractor, or licensee corporation is a corporation, partnership, or limited liability company, every partner of such partnership, every member of such limited liability company, every officer or director of such corporation or partnership, every person or entity holding ten percent or more of the debt or equity of such corporation, partnership, or limited liability company, and every person or entity directly or indirectly associated with such corporation, partnership, or limited liability company in a consulting or other capacity which may impair the security, honesty, or integrity of the operation or conduct of the activities for which the application is made or contract or license is held may also be subject to such requirements. If the applicant, party to the contract, or licensee is a partnership, the persons subject to such requirements shall include any partner, his or her spouse, any officer or director of the partnership, or any person or entity directly or indirectly associated with such partnership in a consulting or other capacity which may impair the security, honesty, or integrity of the operation or conduct of the activities for which the application is made or contract or license is held. If the applicant, party to the contract, or licensee is a limited liability company, the persons subject to such requirement shall include any member and his or her spouse. If the applicant, party to the contract, or licensee is a nonprofit organization or nonprofit corporation, the person subject to such requirement shall be the person designated by such nonprofit organization or nonprofit corporation as the manager.</para><para>(b) Notwithstanding the provisions of this section, background investigations shall not be required of any debt holder which is a financial institution organized or chartered under the laws of this state, any other state, or the United States relating to banks, savings institutions, trust companies, savings and loan associations, credit unions, installment loan licensees, or similar associations organized under the laws of this state and subject to supervision by the Department of Banking and Finance.</para><para>(c) Notwithstanding the provisions of this section, if an applicant for or party holding a license as a pickle card operator, sales agent, gaming manager, lottery operator, lottery worker, or sales outlet location is issued a license by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission, the Department of Revenue may waive the fingerprinting requirements for criminal history record investigation purposes.</para><para>(3)(a) The applicant, party to the contract, or licensee shall pay the actual cost of any fingerprinting or check of his or her criminal history record information.</para><para>(b) The Department of Revenue may require an applicant or licensee subjected to a background investigation, a facilities inspection, or both to pay the actual costs incurred by the department in conducting the investigation or inspection. The department may require payment of the estimated costs in advance of beginning the investigation or inspection. If an applicant does not wish to pay the estimated costs, it may withdraw its application and its application fee will be refunded. After completion of the investigation or inspection, the department shall refund any overpayment or shall charge and collect an amount sufficient to reimburse the department for any underpayment of actual costs. The department may establish by rule and regulation the conditions and procedures for payment of the costs.</para><para>(4) Refusal to comply with this section by any person contracted with, licensed, or seeking a contract or license under the Nebraska Bingo Act, the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, or the State Lottery Act shall be a violation of the act under which such person is contracted with, licensed, or seeking a contract or license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 767, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 427, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 106; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 563, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 694, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 248, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1086, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 545, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 18.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska County and City Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-601.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>