<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id50">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" id="id52" statutenumber="9-1006"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1006</statuteno><catchline id="id55">Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund is created. The fund
shall include revenue transferred from the State Lottery Operation Trust Fund
under section 9-812 and the Charitable Gaming Operations Fund under section
9-1,101 and any other revenue received by the division or commission for credit to the fund from any
other public or private source, including, but not limited to, appropriations,
grants, donations, gifts, devises, bequests, fees, or reimbursements. The commission shall administer the fund for the operation
of the Gamblers Assistance Program. The Director of Administrative
Services shall draw warrants upon the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund
upon the presentation of proper vouchers by the commission. Money
from the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund shall be used exclusively for
the purpose of providing assistance to agencies, groups, organizations, and
individuals that provide education, assistance, and counseling to individuals
and families experiencing difficulty as a result of problem gambling, to promote
the awareness of problem gamblers assistance programs, and to pay the costs
and expenses of the Gamblers
Assistance Program, including travel. Any money in the fund available for investment
shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska
Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 33; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1994, &#167; 9-804.05; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 275, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 659, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 541, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 83-162.04; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 551, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1058, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB189, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2009), &#167; 71-817; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB6, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>