<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" id="id17"  statutenumber="9-1003"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1003</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Commission on Problem Gambling;
created; members; terms; vacancies; meetings.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Commission on Problem Gambling
is created. For administrative purposes only, the commission shall be within
the division. The commission shall have nine members appointed by the Governor
as provided in this section, subject to confirmation by a majority of the
members of the Legislature. The members of the commission shall have no pecuniary
interest, either directly or indirectly, in a contract with the program providing
services to problem gamblers and shall not be employed by the commission or
the Department of Revenue.</para>
<para>(2) By July 1,
2013, the Governor shall appoint members of the commission as follows:</para>
<para>(a) One member
with medical care or mental health expertise;</para><para>(b) One member with expertise
in banking and finance;</para><para>(c) One member with legal expertise;</para><para>(d) One member with expertise
in the field of education;</para><para>(e) Two members who are consumers of problem gambling services;</para>
<para>(f) One member
with data analysis expertise; and</para><para>(g) Two members who are residents of the
state and are representative of the public at large.</para><para>(3) The terms of the members
shall be for three years, except that the Governor shall designate three of
the initial appointees to serve initial terms beginning on July 1, 2013, and
ending on March 1, 2014, three of the initial appointees to serve initial
terms beginning on July 1, 2013, and ending on March 1, 2015, and three of
the initial appointees to serve initial terms beginning on July 1, 2013, and
ending on March 1, 2016. The Governor shall appoint members to fill vacancies
in the same manner as the original appointments, and such appointees shall
serve for the remainder of the unexpired term.</para><para>(4) Beginning July 1, 2013,
the commission shall adopt bylaws governing its operation and the commission
shall meet at least four times each calendar year and may meet more often
on the call of the chairperson. Each member shall attend at least two meetings
each calendar year and shall be subject to removal for failure to attend at
least two meetings unless excused by a majority of the members of the commission.
Meetings of the commission are subject to the Open Meetings Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB6, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>