<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-1304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1304</statuteno><catchline>Collection system; development; submission of debt or outstanding state liability; setoff; authorized.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Department of Revenue, in consultation with the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Motor Vehicles, and the Department of Labor, shall develop and implement a secure, electronic collection system to carry out the purposes of the Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act.</para><para>(b) The collection system shall include access to the name of an obligor, the social security number of an obligor, and any other information that assists the operator in identifying an obligor. The collection system shall inform the operator of the total amount owed without detailing the source of any of the amounts owed.</para><para>(2) The Department of Health and Human Services may submit any certified debt of twenty-five dollars or more to the collection system except when the validity of the debt is legitimately in dispute. The submission of debts of past-due support shall be a continuous process that allows the amount of debt to fluctuate up or down depending on the actual amount owed.</para><para>(3) The Department of Revenue, the Department of Motor Vehicles, and the Department of Labor may submit to the collection system any amount of outstanding state liability owed by an obligor to the department except when the validity of the outstanding state liability is legitimately in dispute. The inclusion of outstanding state liability in the amount owed shall be a continuous process that allows the amount owed to fluctuate up or down depending on the actual amount of outstanding state liability owed.</para><para>(4) If the name of the obligor is retrieved from the collection system by the operator, the retrieval of such name shall be evidence of a valid lien upon and claim of lien against any applicable winnings of the obligor whose name is electronically retrieved from the collection system. If an obligor's applicable winnings are required to be set off pursuant to the Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act, the full amount of the debt and outstanding state liability shall be collected from any applicable winnings due the obligor.</para><para>(5) The information obtained by an operator or the State Racing and Gaming Commission from the collection system in accordance with this section shall retain its confidentiality and shall only be used by the operator or the commission for the purposes of complying with the Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act. An employee or prior employee of an operator or the commission who unlawfully discloses any such information for any other purpose, except as otherwise specifically authorized by law, shall be subject to the same penalties specified by law for unauthorized disclosure of confidential information by an agent or employee of the agency to which the debt or outstanding state liability is owed.</para><para>(6) The information obtained by the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Motor Vehicles, the Department of Labor, or the Department of Revenue from the operator in accordance with this section shall retain its confidentiality and shall only be used by the department in the pursuit of such department's debt or outstanding state liability assessment and collection duties and practices. An employee or prior employee of the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Motor Vehicles, the Department of Labor, or the Department of Revenue who unlawfully discloses any such information for any other purpose, except as specifically authorized by law, shall be subject to the penalties specified by law for unauthorized disclosure of confidential information by an agent or employee of such department.</para><para>(7) The amount of debt and outstanding state liability owed shall be prima facie evidence of the validity of the liability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1317, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB415, &#167; 9. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>