<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-1110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1110</statuteno><catchline>Sports wagering.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may permit an authorized gaming operator to conduct sports wagering. Any sports wager shall be placed in person or at a wagering kiosk in the designated sports wagering area at the licensed racetrack enclosure. A parimutuel wager in accordance with sections 2-1201 to 2-1218 may be placed in the designated sports wagering area at the licensed racetrack enclosure. An individual employed and authorized to accept a sports wager may also accept a parimutuel wager.</para><para>(2) A floor plan identifying the designated sports wagering area, including the location of any wagering kiosks, shall be filed with the commission for review and approval. Modification to a previously approved plan must be submitted for approval at least ten days prior to implementation. The area shall not be accessible to persons under twenty-one years of age and shall have a sign posted to restrict access. Exceptions to this subsection must be approved in writing by the commission.</para><para>(3) The authorized gaming operator shall submit controls for approval by the commission, that include the following for operating the designated sports wagering area:</para><para>(a) Specific procedures and technology partners to fulfill the requirements set forth by the commission;</para><para>(b) Other specific controls as designated by the commission;</para><para>(c) A process to easily and prominently impose limitations or notification for wagering parameters, including, but not limited to, deposits and wagers; and</para><para>(d) An easy and obvious method for a player to make a complaint and to enable the player to notify the commission if such complaint has not been or cannot be addressed by the sports wagering operator.</para><para>(4) The commission shall develop policies and procedures to ensure a prohibited participant is unable to place a sports wager or parimutuel wager.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB561, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB876, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB775, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>