<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" id="id34" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="9-1004"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1004</statuteno><catchline>Commission; officers; expenses; duties;
director; duties; rules and regulations; report.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall appoint one of its
members as chairperson and such other officers as it deems appropriate. Members
shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses in carrying out
their duties as members of the commission as provided in sections 81-1174
to 81-1177.</para>
<para>(2) The commission
shall develop guidelines and standards for the operation of the program and
shall direct the distribution and disbursement of money in the Compulsive
Gamblers Assistance Fund.</para><para>(3) The commission shall appoint a director of the program, provide
for office space and equipment, and support and facilitate the work of the
program. The director may hire, terminate, and supervise commission and program
staff, shall be responsible for the duties of the office and the administration
of the program, and shall electronically provide an annual report to the General
Affairs Committee of the Legislature which includes issues and policy concerns
that relate to problem gambling in Nebraska. All documents, files, equipment,
effects, and records belonging to the State Committee on Problem Gambling
on June 30, 2013, shall become the property of the commission on July 1, 2013.</para>
<para>(4) The commission
shall (a) provide for a process for the evaluation and approval of provider
applications and contracts for treatment and other services funded from the
Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund and (b) develop standards and guidelines
for training and certification of problem gambling counselors.</para>
<para>(5) The commission
shall provide for (a) the review and use of evaluation data, (b) the use and
expenditure of funds for education regarding problem gambling and prevention
of problem gambling, and (c) the creation and implementation of outreach and
educational programs regarding problem gambling for Nebraska residents.</para>
<para>(6) The commission
may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations and engage in other activities
it finds necessary to carry out its duties under sections 9-1001 to 9-1007.</para>
<para>(7) The commission
shall submit a report within sixty days after the end of each fiscal year
to the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature that provides details of
the administration of the program and distribution of funds from the Compulsive
Gamblers Assistance Fund. The report submitted to the Legislature shall be
submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB6, &#167; 4.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>