<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id824"><amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo and Other Gambling" statutenumber="9-1112"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1112</statuteno><catchline>Participation in unlawful manner; violations; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who, in playing any game of chance designed to be played with or to receive or to be operated by tokens approved by the commission or by lawful currency of the United States, knowingly uses tokens other than those approved by the commission, uses currency that is not lawful currency of the United States, or uses currency not of the same denomination as the currency intended to be used in that game is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) Any person who knowingly has in such person's possession within a gaming facility any device intended to be used to violate the Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Any person, other than a duly authorized employee of an authorized gaming operator acting in furtherance of such person's employment within a gaming facility, who knowingly has in such person's possession within a gaming facility any key or device known by such person to have been designed for the purpose of and suitable for opening, entering, or affecting the operation of any game, any dropbox, or any electronic or mechanical device connected to the game or dropbox, is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(4) Any person who knowingly and with intent to use any paraphernalia for manufacturing slugs for cheating or has such paraphernalia in such person's possession is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. Possession of more than two items of the equipment, products, or material described in subdivision (4)(a) or (b) of this section permits a rebuttable presumption that the possessor intended to use such paraphernalia for cheating. For purposes of this subsection, paraphernalia for manufacturing slugs (a) means the equipment, products, and materials that are intended for use or designed for use in manufacturing, producing, fabricating, preparing, testing, analyzing, packaging, storing, or concealing a counterfeit facsimile of tokens approved by the commission or a lawful coin of the United States, the use of which is unlawful pursuant to the Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act, and (b) includes: (i) Lead or lead alloy; (ii) molds, forms, or similar equipment capable of producing a likeness of a gaming token or coin; (iii) melting pots or other receptacles; (iv) torches; and (v) tongs, trimming tools, or other similar equipment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB561, &#167; 36. </para><effectivedate>May 26, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>