<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id57">
    <amendatorysection chaptername="Bingo And Other Gambling" id="id59"  statutenumber="9-1105"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>9-1105</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Gaming Commission; created; members; compensation.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of providing the necessary licensing and regulation of the operation of games of chance by authorized gaming operators within licensed racetrack enclosures pursuant to the Nebraska Racetrack Gaming Act, the Nebraska Gaming Commission is created.</para><para>(2) The commission shall consist of seven members. Not more than four of the seven members shall be affiliated with the same political party. No member shall have any personal financial interest in any licensed racetrack enclosure or authorized gaming operator for the duration of his or her term. The members of the commission shall elect one of the members to be chairperson.</para><para>(3) The five members of the State Racing Commission shall be ex officio members of the Nebraska Gaming Commission, serving terms and receiving appointment in the same manner as provided in sections 2-1201 and 2-1202.</para><para>(4) The Governor shall appoint two additional members to serve with the members of the State Racing Commission as members of the Nebraska Gaming Commission. The members appointed pursuant to this subsection shall serve five-year terms. One of such members shall have experience in the Nebraska gaming industry, and one shall be a member of the organization representing the majority of licensed owners and trainers of horses at racetracks in Nebraska.</para><para>(5) The compensation of the members of the Nebraska Gaming Commission shall be one thousand dollars per month, which may be adjusted every two years in an amount not to exceed the change in the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers for the period between June 30 of the first year to June 30 of the year of adjustment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Initiative Law 2020, No. 430, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>