<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-217"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>16-217</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Officers; removal; vacancies; how filled.</catchline><para>A city of the first class by ordinance may provide for the removal of elective officers of the city for misconduct. The city may create any office that it deems necessary for the good government and interest of the city. The city may provide for filling vacancies which occur in any elective office, except the mayor or member of the city council, by appointment by the mayor with the consent of the city council to hold his or her office for the unexpired term. Whenever the city council fails to consent to any appointment made under this section by the mayor by the close of the second regular city council meeting following the announcement of the appointment, the vacancy shall be filled by a special election to be held as prescribed by ordinance in the ward in which such vacancy exists. A vacancy in the office of the mayor or on the city council shall be filled as provided in section 32-568.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, XXII, p. 250; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4833; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4001; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-218; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-217; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 55, &#167; 1, p. 266; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1145, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 601, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 853, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 484; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 23. </para></source><annotation><para>Where a board has authority to remove an officer for cause, a court will not interfere by injunction, where the board has not acted. Cox v. Moores, 55 Neb. 34, 75 N.W. 35 (1898).</para><para>Where statute provides "for removing officers of the city for misconduct", the council acting without the mayor, is without power to remove the mayor and such attempted removal is null and void. Stahlhut v. Bauer, 51 Neb. 64, 70 N.W. 496 (1897).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>