<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the First Class" statutenumber="16-630"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-630</statuteno><catchline>Curbing and guttering bonds; interest rate; assessments; how levied.</catchline><para>Whenever curbing, or curbing and guttering, is done upon any street, avenue or alley in any paving, repaving, graveling or macadamizing district in which paving or other such improvement aforesaid has been ordered, and the mayor and council shall deem it expedient to do so, they shall have the power and authority, for the purpose of paying the cost of such curbing, or curbing and guttering, to cause to be issued bonds of the city, to be called Curbing and Guttering Bonds of Paving District No. ....., payable in not exceeding ten years from date, bearing interest, payable annually or semiannually, with interest coupons attached. In all cases they shall assess at one time the total cost of such curbing and guttering, or curbing, as the case may be, upon the property abutting or adjacent to the portion of the street, avenue or alley so improved, according to the special benefits. Such assessments shall become delinquent the same as the assessments of special taxes for paving, repaving, graveling or macadamizing purposes, draw the same rate of interest, be subject to the same penalties, and may be paid in the same manner, as special taxes for said purpose. The special tax so assessed shall constitute a sinking fund for the payment of such bonds and interest, and the bonds shall not be sold for less than their par value.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, LV, p. 267; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 19, &#167; 4, p. 315; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 119; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4925; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 226; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4093; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 50, &#167; 7, p. 196; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-622; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-630; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 128; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 29, p. 290. </para></source><annotation><para>Under prior act, where street had been reduced to grade, and only limited expense was necessary to complete the work, engineer's estimate, advertisement, etc., for bids was not necessary, and city was permitted to pay for such work out of proper city funds. Hilger v. City of Nebraska City, 97 Neb. 268, 149 N.W. 807 (1914).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>