<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the First Class" statutenumber="16-246"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-246</statuteno><catchline>General ordinances; authorized; jurisdiction.</catchline><para>A city of the first class may make all such ordinances, bylaws, rules, regulations, and resolutions not inconsistent with the general laws of the state as may be necessary or expedient, in addition to the special powers otherwise granted by law, for maintaining the peace, good government, and welfare of the city and its trade, commerce, and manufactures, for preserving order and securing persons or property from violence, danger, and destruction, for protecting public and private property, and for promoting the public health, safety, convenience, comfort, and morals and the general interests and welfare of the inhabitants of the city. It may impose fines, forfeitures, penalties, and imprisonment at hard labor for the violation of any ordinance; provide for the recovery, collection, and enforcement of such fines, forfeitures, or penalties; and, in default of payment, provide for confinement in the city or county prison, workhouse, or other place of confinement with or without hard labor as may be provided by ordinance. The jurisdiction of the city to enforce such ordinances, bylaws, rules, regulations, and resolutions shall extend over the city and over all places within two miles of the corporate limits of the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, LII, p. 259; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4862; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4030; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-247; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-246; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 47, &#167; 2, p. 247; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 48, &#167; 2, p. 249; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 934, &#167; 4. </para></source><annotation><para>City was authorized to enact ordinance for parking meters as a regulatory measure. School District of McCook v. City of McCook, 163 Neb. 817, 81 N.W.2d 224 (1957).</para><para>Where there is no building or other existing ordinance that prevents the building of an oil station, and where a few doors from the location where plaintiff wishes to construct such station there is a like station, the passing of an ordinance to prohibit plaintiff from building such station is so unreasonable and discriminatory as to be unconstitutional. Standard Oil Company v. City of Kearney, 106 Neb. 558, 184 N.W. 109 (1921).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>