<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the First Class" statutenumber="16-680"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-680</statuteno><catchline>Sewerage system; drainage; waterworks; bonds authorized; amount; approval of electors; sewer or water commissioner; authorized.</catchline><para>The mayor and council shall have power to borrow money and pledge the property and credit of the city upon its negotiable bonds or otherwise in an amount not exceeding in the aggregate four hundred thousand dollars for the purpose of constructing or aiding in the construction of a system of sewerage. They may borrow money and pledge the property and credit of the city upon its negotiable bonds or otherwise in any amount, not exceeding in the aggregate seven hundred fifty thousand dollars, for the purpose of constructing culverts and drains for the purpose of deepening, widening, straightening, walling, filling, covering, altering, or changing the channel of any watercourse or any natural or artificial surface waterway or any creek, branch, ravine, ditch, draw, basin, or part thereof flowing or extending through or being within the limits of the city and for the purpose of constructing artificial channels or covered drains sufficient to carry the water theretofore flowing in such watercourse and divert it from the natural channel and conduct the same through such artificial channel or covered drain and fill the old channel. They may borrow money and pledge the property and credit of the city upon its negotiable bonds or otherwise in an amount not exceeding in the aggregate two hundred fifty thousand dollars for the purpose of constructing, maintaining, and operating a system of waterworks for the city. No such bonds shall be issued by the city council until the question of issuing the same has been submitted to the electors of the city at an election called and held for that purpose, notice of which shall be given by publication in some newspaper published in the city at least thirty days before the date of the election, and a majority of the electors voting upon the proposition have voted in favor of issuing such bonds. When any such bonds have been issued by the city, they may levy annually upon all taxable property of the city such tax as may be necessary for a sinking fund for the payment of the accruing interest upon the bonds and the principal thereof at maturity. They may provide for the office of sewer commissioner or water commissioner and prescribe the duties and powers of such offices.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 56, p. 274; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 20, &#167; 1, p. 188; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 35, &#167; 1, p. 112; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4956; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 98, &#167; 1, p. 262; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4125; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 41, &#167; 1, p. 175; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-654; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-680; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 59, &#167; 1, p. 273; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 534, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 45. </para></source><annotation><para>City's authority to erect, extend or to improve and to maintain a sewer system and to issue bonds payable from taxes is independent and complete. State ex rel. City of Columbus v. Price, 127 Neb. 132, 254 N.W. 889 (1934).</para><para>City had authority, by ordinance, to contract with others, to operate and construct water system, partly within and partly without city limits for twenty years, and to provide therein that it should have right to purchase the same at a valuation determined by appraisers. Omaha Water Co. v. City of Omaha, 162 F. 225 (8th Cir. 1908).</para><para>Authority granted city to contract to build and operate a waterworks "on such terms and under such regulations as may be agreed on" constitutes authority to agree with water company on water rates for twenty-five years, and city's attempt to alter such rates may be enjoined. Omaha Water Co. v. City of Omaha, 147 F. 1 (8th Cir. 1906).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>