<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-633"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>16-633</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Improvements; assessments against public lands.</catchline><para>If, in any city of the first class, there shall be any real estate belonging to any county, school district, city, village, or other political subdivision abutting upon the street, avenue, or alley whereon paving or other improvements have been ordered, it shall be the duty of the governing body of the political subdivision to pay such special taxes. In the event of the neglect or refusal of such governing body to pay such taxes, or to levy and collect the taxes necessary to pay for such improvements, the city may recover the amount of such special taxes in a proper action. The judgment thus obtained may be enforced in the usual manner, and the signatures of such political subdivisions to all petitions shall have like force and effect as that of other property owners.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, LV, p. 259; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 19, &#167; 4, p. 307; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 111; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4927; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4095; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-624; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-633; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 99. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Though church property, used exclusively for church purposes, is exempt from general taxation under the Constitution, such property is not exempt from special assessments for local improvements. City of Beatrice v. Brethren Church of Beatrice, 41 Neb. 358, 59 N.W. 932 (1894).</para><para>Officers representing state, county, or school districts, may not sign petition for paving on behalf of the property of the district they represent. Von Steen v. City of Beatrice, 36 Neb. 421, 54 N.W. 677 (1893).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>