<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-103</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Reorganization as city of the first class; transitional provisions.</catchline><para>(1) After the proclamation under section 16-102, the city shall be governed by the laws of this state applicable to cities of the first class, except that the government of such city shall continue as organized at the date of such proclamation until the reorganization as a city of the first class.</para><para>(2) The mayor and city council members of the city of the second class shall be deemed to be the mayor and city council members of the city of the first class on the date the proclamation is issued. All ordinances, bylaws, acts, rules, regulations, obligations, and proclamations existing and in force in or with respect to the city of the second class at the time of its incorporation as a city of the first class shall remain in full force and effect after such incorporation until repealed or modified by the city within one year after the date of the filing of the certificate pursuant to section 16-102.</para><para>(3) For the purpose of electing city officials under the provisions of law relating to cities of the first class, the terms of office for such officials shall be established by the city council so as to conform with the intent and purpose of section 32-534.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 3, p. 227; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4806; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3974; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-103; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-103; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1119, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 957, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 482; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>