<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-207" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>16-207</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Streets and sidewalks; regulation; declaration of nuisance; procedure; special assessment.</catchline><para>(1) A city of the first class may by ordinance provide for the removal of all obstructions from the sidewalks, curbstones, gutters, and crosswalks at the expense of the owners or occupants of the grounds fronting thereon or at the expense of the person placing the obstruction and may require and regulate the planting and protection of shade trees in and along the streets and the trimming and removing of the trees.</para><para>(2) A city of the first class may by ordinance declare it to be a nuisance for a property owner to permit, allow, or maintain any dead or diseased trees within the right-of-way of streets within the corporate limits of the city or within its two-mile zoning jurisdiction. Notice to abate and remove such nuisance and notice of the right to a hearing and the manner in which it may be requested shall be given to each owner or owner's duly authorized agent and to the occupant, if any, by personal service or certified mail. Within thirty days after the receipt of such notice, if the owner or occupant of the lot or piece of ground does not request a hearing or fails to comply with the order to abate and remove the nuisance, the city may have such work done and may levy and assess all or any portion of the costs and expenses of the work upon the lot or piece of ground so benefited as a special assessment.</para><para>(3) The city may also regulate the building of bulkheads, cellars, basements, ways, stairways, railways, windows, doorways, awnings, hitching posts and rails, lampposts, awning posts, and all other structures projecting upon or over any adjoining excavation through and under the sidewalks in the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, XI, p. 247; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4823; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3991; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-208; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-207; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 695, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB266, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 17. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB266, section 5, with LB361, section 17, to reflect all amendments.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>