<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-622"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>16-622</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Improvement districts; assessments; how levied; when delinquent; interest; collection; procedure.</catchline><para>The cost of making improvements of the streets and alleys within any improvement district created pursuant to section 16-619 or 16-624 shall be assessed upon the lots and lands in such districts specially benefited thereby in proportion to such benefits. The amounts thereof shall, except as provided in sections 19-2428 to 19-2431, be determined by the mayor and city council under section 16-615. The assessment of the special tax for the cost of such improvements, except as provided in this section, shall be levied at one time and shall become delinquent in equal annual installments over such period of years, not to exceed twenty, as the mayor and city council may determine at the time of making the levy, the first such installment to become delinquent in fifty days after the date of such levy. Each installment, including those for graveling and the construction and replacement of pedestrian walks, plazas, malls, landscaping, lighting systems, and permanent facilities used in connection therewith as provided in this section, except the first, shall draw interest at a rate established by the mayor and city council not exceeding the rate of interest specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, from the time of levy until the levy becomes delinquent. After the levy becomes delinquent, interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, shall be paid thereon. Should there be three or more installments delinquent and unpaid on the same property the mayor and city council may by resolution declare all future installments on such delinquent property to be due on a future fixed date. The resolution shall set forth the description of the property and the names of its record title owners and shall provide that all future installments shall become delinquent upon the date fixed. A copy of such resolution shall be published one time each week for not less than twenty days in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city and after the fixed date such future installments shall be deemed to be delinquent and the city may proceed to enforce and collect the total amount due and all future installments. For assessments for graveling alone and without guttering or curbing, one-third of the total amount assessed against each lot or parcel of land shall become delinquent in fifty days after the date of the levy of the same, one-third in one year, and one-third in two years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, LV, p. 259; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 19, &#167; 4, p. 307; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 111; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4917; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4085; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 50, &#167; 2, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-614; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 136, &#167; 18, p. 527; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 16-614; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-622; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 28, &#167; 1, p. 115; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 32, &#167; 1, p. 139; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 64, &#167; 1, p. 285; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 47, &#167; 1, p. 233; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 67, &#167; 5, p. 220; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1213, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 541, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 933, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 94, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB132, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>This section and section 16-669 require that three payments be delinquent before the city may foreclose, and the city is required to pass and publish an acceleration resolution declaring the entire amount due and owing. City of Kearney v. Johnson, 222 Neb. 541, 385 N.W.2d 427 (1986).</para><para>Rate of interest on paving assessment was governed by home rule charter and not by this section. State ex rel. Martin v. Cunningham, 158 Neb. 708, 64 N.W.2d 465 (1954).</para><para>An unplatted and nonsubdivided tract of land in a city of the first class may be subjected to assessment for special benefits. City of Scottsbluff v. Kennedy, 141 Neb. 728, 4 N.W.2d 878 (1942).</para><para>Cities of the first class that adopt a "home rule" charter possess no power to remit or cancel interest or penalties on special taxes. Falldorf v. City of Grand Island, 138 Neb. 212, 292 N.W. 598 (1940).</para><para>In absence of a limitation in the act granting it authority to issue bonds, the city had power to levy sufficient taxes to pay the same. United States ex rel. Masslich v. Saunders, 124 F. 124 (8th Cir. 1903).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>