<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-101</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Cities of the first class, defined; population required.</catchline><para id="id00">All cities having more than five thousand and not more than one hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census shall be known as cities of the first class. The population of a city of the first class shall consist of the people residing within the territorial boundaries of such city and the residents of any territory duly and properly annexed to such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 1, p. 226; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4804; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3972; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-101; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 85, &#167; 3, p. 328; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 726, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 9. </para></source><annotation><para>Where the population of city of first class as shown by the last ten-year United States census drops below population of a city of such classification, it becomes automatically a city of second class. State ex rel. Cashman v. Carmean, 138 Neb. 819, 295 N.W. 801 (1941).</para><para>A city of the first class that adopts a "home rule" charter is a creature of law, and its corporate acts are governed by this chapter. Falldorf v. City of Grand Island, 138 Neb. 212, 292 N.W. 598 (1940).</para><para>Provisions of the charter for a city of the first class appear in this chapter. City of Fremont v. Lea, 115 Neb. 565, 213 N.W. 820 (1927).</para><para>Classification of cities is constitutional. State ex rel. Jones v. Graham, 16 Neb. 74, 19 N.W. 470 (1884).</para><para>City is estopped to defend against waterworks bonds in hands of innocent purchasers where such bonds reflect city certified in bond that they were legally issued, it having plenary power so to do, though the bonds cited the wrong statutory section as authority therefor. City of Beatrice v. Edminson, 117 F. 427 (8th Cir. 1902).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>