<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-233"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>16-233</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Public buildings; safety regulations; licensing; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>A city of the first class may regulate, license, or suppress halls, opera houses, places of amusement, entertainment, or instruction, or other buildings except churches and schools used for the assembly of citizens, and cause them to be provided with sufficient and ample means of exit and entrance, and to be supplied with necessary and appropriate appliances for the extinguishment of fire and for escape from such places in case of fire, and prevent overcrowding and regulate the placing and use of seats, chairs, benches, scenery, curtains, blinds, screens, or other appliances therein. A city of the first class may provide that for any violation of any such regulation a penalty of two hundred dollars shall be imposed, and upon conviction of any such licensees of any violation of any ordinance regulating such places, the license of any such place shall be revoked by the mayor and city council. Whenever the mayor and city council shall by resolution declare any such place to be unsafe, the license thereof shall be deemed revoked by adoption of such resolution. The city council may provide that in any case where it has so revoked a license, any owner, proprietor, manager, lessee or person opening, using, or permitting such place to be opened or used for any purpose involving the assemblage of more than twelve persons shall upon conviction thereof be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor and fined in any sum not exceeding two hundred dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, XXXIX, p. 256; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4849; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4017; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-234; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-233; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 36. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>