<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the First Class" statutenumber="16-672.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-672.06</statuteno><catchline>Construction; acceptance; notice of assessments.</catchline><para>After the completion of any such work in the construction of said public improvements, the city engineer shall file with the municipal clerk a certificate of acceptance, which acceptance shall be approved by the mayor and city council by ordinance. The mayor and city council shall then require the city engineer to make a complete statement of all the costs of such improvement and a plat of the property in the storm water sewer district and a schedule of the amount proposed to be assessed against each separate parcel of real property in such district, which shall be filed with the municipal clerk within ten days from the date of the acceptance of the work. The mayor and city council shall then order the clerk to give notice that said plat and schedules are on file in his office and that all objections thereto, or to prior proceedings on account of errors, irregularities, or inequalities, not made in writing and filed with the municipal clerk within twenty days after the first publication of said notice shall be deemed to have been waived. Such notice shall be given by two publications in a newspaper published in said city or if there be no newspaper published in said city then in some newspaper of general circulation published in the county wherein the city is located, and by notices posted in three conspicuous places in said storm water sewer district. Said notice shall state the time and place where objections, filed as herein provided, shall be considered by the mayor and city council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 46, &#167; 6, p. 180. </para></source></law></legaldoc>