<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities of the First Class" id="id63" statutenumber="16-230"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>16-230</statuteno><catchline id="id66">Drainage; nuisance;
weeds; litter; removal; notice; action by city council; hearing; violation; penalty; civil action.</catchline><para>(1) A city of the first class by ordinance may require lots or pieces
of ground within the city or within the city's extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction
to be drained or filled so as to prevent stagnant water or any other nuisance
accumulating thereon. The city may require the owner
or occupant of all lots and pieces of ground within the city to keep the lots
and pieces of ground and the adjoining streets and alleys free of excessive growth of weeds, grasses,
or worthless vegetation, and it may prohibit and control the throwing, depositing,
or accumulation of litter on any lot or piece of ground within the city.</para>
<para>(2) Any city of the first class may by ordinance
declare it to be a nuisance to permit or maintain excessive growth
of weeds, grasses, or worthless vegetation or to litter
or cause litter to be deposited or remain thereon except in proper receptacles. The city shall establish by ordinance
the height at which weeds, grasses, or worthless vegetation are a nuisance.</para>
<para>(3) Any owner or occupant of a lot or piece of ground shall, upon conviction
of violating any ordinance authorized under this section, be guilty of a Class
V misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(4) Notice to abate and remove such nuisance shall be given to each
owner or owner's duly authorized agent and to the occupant, if any. The city
shall establish the method of notice by ordinance. If notice is given by first-class
mail, such mail shall be conspicuously marked as to its importance. Within
five days after receipt of such notice, the owner or occupant of the lot or
piece of ground may request a hearing with the city to appeal the decision
to abate or remove a nuisance by filing a written appeal with the office of
the city clerk. A hearing on the appeal shall be held within fourteen days
after the filing of the appeal and shall be conducted by an elected or appointed
officer as designated in the ordinance. The hearing officer shall render a
decision on the appeal within five business days after the conclusion of the
hearing. If the appeal fails, the city may have such work done. Within
five days after receipt of such notice, if the owner or occupant of the lot or piece of ground
does not request a hearing with the city or fails to comply with the order
to abate and remove the nuisance, the city may have such work done. The costs
and expenses of any such work shall be paid by the owner. If unpaid for two
months after such work is done, the city may either (a) levy and assess the
costs and expenses of the work upon the lot or piece of ground so benefited
in the same manner as other special taxes for improvements are levied and
assessed or (b) recover in a civil action the costs and expenses of the work
upon the lot or piece of ground and the adjoining streets and alleys.</para>
<para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Litter includes, but is not limited to: (i) Trash, rubbish, refuse,
garbage, paper, rags, and ashes; (ii) wood, plaster, cement, brick, or stone
building rubble; (iii) grass, leaves, and worthless vegetation; (iv) offal
and dead animals; and (v) any machine or machines, vehicle or vehicles, or
parts of a machine or vehicle which have lost their identity, character, utility,
or serviceability as such through deterioration, dismantling, or the ravages
of time, are inoperative or unable to perform their intended functions, or
are cast off, discarded, or thrown away or left as waste, wreckage, or junk;</para>
<para>(b) Weeds includes, but is not limited to, bindweed (Convolvulus arvensis),
puncture vine (Tribulus terrestris), leafy spurge (Euphorbia esula), Canada
thistle (Cirsium arvense), perennial peppergrass (Lepidium draba), Russian
knapweed (Centaurea picris), Johnson grass (Sorghum halepense), nodding or
musk thistle, quack grass (Agropyron repens), perennial sow thistle (Sonchus
arvensis), horse nettle (Solanum carolinense), bull thistle (Cirsium lanceolatum),
buckthorn (Rhamnus sp.) (tourn), hemp plant (Cannabis sativa), and ragweed
(Ambrosiaceae); and</para>
<para>(c) Weeds, grasses, and worthless vegetation does not include vegetation
applied or grown on a lot or piece of ground outside the corporate limits
of the city but inside the city's extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction expressly
for the purpose of weed or erosion control.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, XXXVII, p. 255; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4846; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 84, &#167; 1, p. 222; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4014; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-231; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-230; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 117, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 934, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 330, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 42, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 997, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB495, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB643, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>City owes no duty to provide drainage for property within its limits, where another due to a change in street grade caused inundation of plaintiff's premises. City of Beatrice v. Knight, 45 Neb. 546, 63 N.W. 838 (1895).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>