<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id96">
<sectno id="id97">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id98" statutenumber="16-227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id100">16-227</statuteno><catchline id="id101">Riots; disorderly
conduct; use of explosives; weapons; vagabonds; lights; bonfires; regulation.</catchline>
<para>A city of the first class may prevent and restrain riots,
routs, noises, disturbances, breach of the peace, or disorderly assemblies in any street, house, or place in the city; regulate,
punish, and prevent the discharge of firearms, rockets, powder, fireworks, or any other dangerous combustible
material in the streets, lots, grounds, and alleys or about or in the vicinity
of any buildings; regulate, prevent, and punish the carrying of concealed
weapons, except the carrying
of a concealed handgun in compliance with the Concealed Handgun Permit Act;
arrest, regulate, punish, fine, or
set at work on the streets or
elsewhere all
vagabonds and persons found in the city without visible means
of support or some legitimate business; regulate and prevent the transportation
or storage of gunpowder or other explosive or combustible articles, tar, pitch,
resin, coal oil, benzine, turpentine, hemp, cotton, nitroglycerine, dynamite,
petroleum or any other productions thereof, and other materials of like nature,
the use of lights in stables, shops, or
other places, and the building of bonfires; and regulate and prohibit the
piling of building material or any excavation or obstruction in the street.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, XXXIV, p. 255; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4843; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4011; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-228; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-227; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB430, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Concealed Handgun Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 69-2427.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>City's delegated power hereunder to control storage of petroleum products must be exercised by ordinance. State ex rel. Andruss v. Mayor &amp; Council of City of North Platte, 120 Neb. 413, 233 N.W. 4 (1930).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>