<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the First Class" statutenumber="16-313"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-313</statuteno><catchline>Mayor; veto power; passage over veto.</catchline><para>The mayor shall have the power to approve or veto any ordinance passed by the city council, and to approve or veto any order, bylaw, resolution, award of or vote to enter into any contract, or the allowance of any claim; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> any ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution, award or vote to enter into any contract, or the allowance of any claim vetoed by the mayor, may be passed over his veto by a vote of two-thirds of all the members elected to the council, notwithstanding his veto. If the mayor neglects or refuses to sign any ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution, award or vote to enter into any contract, or the allowance of any claim, and returns the same with his objection in writing at the next regular meeting of the council, the same shall become a law without his signature. The mayor may veto any item or items of any appropriation bill, and approve the remainder thereof, and the item or items so vetoed may be passed by the council over the veto as in other cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 20, p. 234; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4879; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4047; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-309; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-313.</para></source><annotation><para>Under a similar section where four councilmen voted for, and four councilmen against, the issuance of a liquor license, and the mayor voted for its issuance, such vote of the mayor does not come within any exceptions direct or implied, and such mayor has the authority to cast the deciding vote. Rohrer v. Hastings Brewing Company, 83 Neb. 111, 119 N.W. 27 (1908).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>