<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-806"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>16-806</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Ordinance; publication; objections; submission to electors; election; notice.</catchline><para>The mayor and city council of a city of the first class may adopt by ordinance the proposition to make such purchase or to erect such facility or facilities as set forth in section 16-802, and before the purchase can be made or facility created, the city council shall publish in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city the location of the proposed offstreet motor vehicle parking facility or facilities, the proposed cost, and the total amount of the bonds to be issued. If the electors of such city, equal in number to five percent of the electors of such city voting at the last preceding general municipal election, file a written objection or objections to the proposed issuance of revenue bonds within sixty days after the adoption of such ordinance, the city council must submit the question to the electors of such city at a general municipal election or at a special election called for that purpose and be approved by a majority of the electors voting on such question. If the question is submitted at a special election, the vote for the purchase or acquisition of such real estate or the purchase or erection of such facility or facilities shall equal at least a majority of the votes cast at the last preceding general election. Notice of the time and place of the election shall be given by publication in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in such city three successive weeks prior thereto.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 35, &#167; 6, p. 146; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 181; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 199. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>