<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-611" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>16-611</statuteno><catchline>Vacation of street or alley; abutting property; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the vacation of any street or alley by a city of the first class, the title to such property shall vest in the owners of the abutting property and become a part of such property, one-half on each side thereof, unless the city reserves title in the ordinance vacating such street or alley. If title is retained by the city, such property may be sold, conveyed, exchanged, or leased upon such terms and conditions as shall be deemed in the best interests of the city.</para><para>(2) When a portion of a street or alley is vacated only on one side of the center thereof, the title to such property shall vest in the owner of the abutting property and become part of such property unless the city reserves title in the ordinance vacating a portion of such street or alley. If title is retained by the city, such property may be sold, conveyed, exchanged, or leased upon such terms and conditions as shall be deemed in the best interests of the city.</para><para>(3) When the city vacates all or any portion of a street or alley, the city shall, within thirty days after the effective date of the vacation, file a certified copy of the vacating ordinance with the register of deeds for the county in which the vacated property is located to be indexed against all affected lots.</para><para>(4) The title to property vacated pursuant to this section shall be subject to the following:</para><para>(a) There is reserved to the city the right to maintain, operate, repair, and renew public utilities existing at the time title to the property is vacated there; and</para><para>(b) There is reserved to the city, any public utilities, and any cable television systems the right to maintain, repair, renew, and operate water mains, gas mains, pole lines, conduits, electrical transmission lines, sound and signal transmission lines, and other similar services and equipment and appurtenances, including lateral connections or branch lines, above, on, or below the surface of the ground that are existing as valid easements at the time title to the property is vacated for the purposes of serving the general public or the abutting properties and to enter upon the premises to accomplish such purposes at any and all reasonable times.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 48, IV, p. 145; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 19, &#167; 7, p. 237; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4910; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4078; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-607; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-611; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 58, &#167; 2, p. 363; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 483, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 161, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB194, &#167; 34. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Where conveyance describes lot by block and number, contains no reservation of rights in alley, conveyance transfers fee to center line of abutting portion of vacated alley even though conveyance also describes lots by metes and bounds which did not include any part of alley and used edge of alley as boundary. Seefus v. Briley, 185 Neb. 202, 174 N.W.2d 339 (1970).</para><para>This section is not applicable to vacation of a nominal street of a platted addition. Trahan v. Council Bluffs Steel Erection Co., 183 Neb. 170, 159 N.W.2d 207 (1968).</para><para>This section has no relation to streets which have been platted and dedicated. Dell v. City of Lincoln, 170 Neb. 176, 102 N.W.2d 62 (1960).</para><para>Cities own in fee simple, the streets, alleys, etc., and may maintain ejectment, may vacate them, or even sell and dispose of them. Krueger v. Jenkins, 59 Neb. 641, 81 N.W. 844 (1900).</para><para>There is no constitutional restraint of the Legislature's plenary power, to vacate or discontinue the public easement on streets. City of Columbus v. Union Pacific R. R. Co., 137 F. 869 (8th Cir. 1905).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>