<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-664" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>16-664</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Construction; cost; special assessment; levy; when delinquent; payment.</catchline><para>The mayor and city council may provide for the laying of permanent sidewalks. Upon the petition of any freeholder who desires to build such a permanent sidewalk, the mayor and council may order the sidewalk to be built, the cost of the sidewalk until paid shall be a perpetual lien upon the real estate along which the freeholder desires such sidewalk to be constructed, and the city council may assess and levy the costs of the sidewalk against such real estate as a special assessment. The total cost of the building of the permanent sidewalk shall be levied at one time upon the property along which such permanent sidewalk is to be built, and become delinquent as follows: One-seventh of the total cost shall become delinquent in ten days after such levy; one-seventh in one year; one-seventh in two years; one-seventh in three years; one-seventh in four years; one-seventh in five years; and one-seventh in six years. Each of such installments, except the first, shall draw interest at a rate of not exceeding the rate of interest specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, from the time of the levy, until the installment becomes delinquent. If the installment becomes delinquent, interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, shall be paid thereon as in the case of other special assessments. The council shall pay for the building of such permanent sidewalk out of the general fund. The mayor and council may pass an ordinance to carry into effect this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 121, p. 303; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4948; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4117; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-646; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-664; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 65, &#167; 1, p. 264; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 57, &#167; 1, p. 264; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 933, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 24. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Cities of the first class that adopt a "home rule" charter possess no power to remit or cancel interest or penalties on special taxes. Falldorf v. City of Grand Island, 138 Neb. 212, 292 N.W. 598 (1940).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>