<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-305</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Officers and employees; merger of offices or employment; salaries.</catchline><para>All officers and employees of a city of the first class shall receive such compensation as the mayor and city council may fix at the time of their appointment or employment, subject to the limitations set forth in this section. The city council may at its discretion by ordinance combine and merge any elective or appointive office or employment or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments, except mayor and city council member, with any other elective or appointive office or employment so that one or more of such offices or employments or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments may be held by the same officer or employee at the same time. The city manager in a city under the city manager plan of government as provided in the City Manager Plan of Government Act may in his or her discretion combine and merge any elective or appointive office or employment or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments, except mayor and city council member, with any other elective or appointive office or employment so that one or more of such offices or employments or any combination of duties of any such offices or employments may be held by the same officer or employee at the same time. The offices or employments so merged and combined shall always be construed to be separate, and the effect of the combination or merger shall be limited to a consolidation of official duties only. The salary or compensation of the officer or employee holding the merged and combined offices or employments or offices and employments shall not be in excess of the maximum amount provided by law for the salary or compensation of the office, offices, employment, or employments so merged and combined.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1907, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 107; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4872; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 85, &#167; 1, p. 224; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4040; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 67, &#167; 2, p. 203; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-302; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-305; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 368, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 756, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 931, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 12, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 486; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB193, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB194, &#167; 5.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>City Manager Plan of Government Act,</emphasis> see section 19-601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The city clerk is an elective officer, and cannot be appointed as a disbursing officer or to any other office by the council. City of Scottsbluff v. Southern Surety Co., 124 Neb. 260, 246 N.W. 346 (1933).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>