<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-902"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>16-902</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Designation of jurisdiction; subdivision; platting; consent required; review by county planning commission; when required.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, a city of the first class may designate by ordinance the portion of the territory located within its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction and outside of any other organized city or village within which the designating city will exercise the powers and duties granted by sections 16-902 to 16-904 or section 19-2402.</para><para>(2) No owner of any real property located within the area designated by a city pursuant to subsection (1) or (4) of this section may subdivide, plat, or lay out such real property in building lots, streets, or other portions of the same intended to be dedicated for public use or for the use of the purchasers or owners of lots fronting thereon or adjacent thereto without first having obtained the approval of the city council of such city or its agent designated pursuant to section 19-916 and, when applicable, having complied with sections 39-1311 to 39-1311.05. The fact that such real property is located in a different county or counties than some or all portions of the city shall not be construed as affecting the necessity of obtaining the approval of the city council of such city or its designated agent.</para><para>(3) In counties that (a) have adopted a comprehensive development plan which meets the requirements of section 23-114.02 and (b) are enforcing subdivision regulations, the county planning commission shall be provided with all available materials on any proposed subdivision plat, contemplating public streets or improvements, which is filed with a city of the first class in that county, when such proposed plat lies partially or totally within the portion of that city's extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction where the powers and duties granted by sections 16-902 to 16-904 are being exercised by that city in such county. The commission shall be given four weeks to officially comment on the appropriateness of the design and improvements proposed in the plat. The review period for the commission shall run concurrently with subdivision review activities of the city after the commission receives all available material for a proposed subdivision plat.</para><para>(4) If a city of the first class receives approval for the cession and transfer of additional extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction under section 13-327, such city may designate by ordinance the portion of the territory located within its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction and outside of any other organized city or village within which the designating city will exercise the powers and duties granted by sections 16-902 to 16-904 or section 19-2402 and shall include territory ceded under section 13-327 within such designation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 28, &#167; 2(1), p. 183; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 70, &#167; 2, p. 232; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 75, &#167; 2, p. 243; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 186, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 71, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 208, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 222, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 204; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB864, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB132, &#167; 4. </para></source><annotation><para>Act, of which this section was a part, sustained as constitutional. Schlientz v. City of North Platte, 172 Neb. 477, 110 N.W.2d 58 (1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>