
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-403"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-403</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City council; ordinances; passage; proof; publication.</catchline><para>All ordinances of a city of the first class shall be passed pursuant to such rules and regulations as the city council may provide, and all such ordinances may be proved by the certificate of the city clerk under the seal of the city. When printed or published in book, pamphlet, or electronic form and purporting to be published by authority of the city, such ordinances shall be read and received in evidence in all courts and places without further proof. The passage, approval, and publication or posting of such ordinance shall be sufficiently proved by a certificate under the seal of the city from the city clerk showing that such ordinance was passed and approved, and when and in what paper the same was published, and when and by whom and where the same was posted. When ordinances are published in book, pamphlet, or electronic form, purporting to be published by authority of the city council, the same need not be otherwise published and such book, pamphlet, or electronic form shall be received as evidence of the passage and legal publication of such ordinances, as of the dates mentioned in such book, pamphlet, or electronic form, in all courts without further proof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 46, p. 244; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4896; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4064; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-403; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-403; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB194, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB159, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Ordinances as published in book form are not competent evidence unless "purported to be published by authority of the city". Christensen v. Tate, 87 Neb. 848, 128 N.W. 622 (1910).</para><para>An ordinance that is duly approved and published is in full force and effect. In re Langston, 55 Neb. 310, 75 N.W. 828 (1898).</para><para>Where certificate shows ordinance was not properly published, ordinance is not admissible without further proof. Union P. Ry. Co. v. Montgomery, 49 Neb. 429, 68 N.W. 619 (1896).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>