<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-405"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-405</statuteno><catchline>Council; ordinances; style; publication; emergency ordinances.</catchline><para>The style of ordinances shall be: "Be it ordained by the mayor and council of the city of ................," and all ordinances of a general nature shall, within fifteen days after they are passed, be published in some newspaper published within the city, or in pamphlet form, to be distributed or sold, as may be provided by ordinance; and every ordinance fixing a penalty or forfeiture for its violation shall, before the same takes effect, be published for at least one week in some manner above prescribed; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> in cases of riots, infectious diseases or other impending danger, or any other emergency requiring its immediate operation, such ordinance shall take effect upon the proclamation of the mayor immediately upon its first publication as above provided.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 47, p. 245; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4898; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4066; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-405; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 282, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Publication in one regular issue of a legal newspaper in any week was sufficient notwithstanding this section and home rule charter. Skag-Way Department Stores, Inc. v. City of Grand Island, 176 Neb. 169, 125 N.W.2d 529 (1964).</para><para>One insertion in a daily paper does not meet the requirement of statute, since a publication must be continued in each issue thereof for a week. Union Pacific Railway Co. v. McNally, 54 Neb. 112, 74 N.W. 390 (1898); Union Pacific Railway Co. v. Montgomery, 49 Neb. 429, 68 N.W. 619 (1896).</para><para>One publication is sufficient if in weekly paper. State ex rel. Hahn v. Hardy, 7 Neb. 377 (1878).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>