
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id49"  statutenumber="16-130" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-130</statuteno><catchline>Annexation by city within county between 100,000 and 250,000 inhabitants; mayor and city council; powers; notice; contents; liability; limitation on action.</catchline><para>(1) The provisions of this section shall govern annexation by a city of the first class located in whole or in part within the boundaries of a county having a population in excess of one hundred thousand inhabitants but less than two hundred fifty thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in sections 13-1111 to 13-1120 and subject to this section, the mayor and city council of a city of the first class described in subsection (1) of this section may by ordinance at any time include within the corporate limits of such city any contiguous or adjacent lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways as are urban or suburban in character and in such direction as may be deemed proper. Such grant of power shall not be construed as conferring power upon the mayor and city council to extend the limits of such a city over any agricultural lands which are rural in character.</para><para>(3) The invalidity of the annexation of any tract of land in one ordinance shall not affect the validity of the remaining tracts of land which are annexed by the ordinance and which otherwise conform to state law.</para><para>(4) Any owner of property contiguous or adjacent to such a city may by petition request that such property be included within the corporate limits of such city.</para><para>(5) Notwithstanding the requirements of this section, the mayor and city council are not required to approve any petition requesting annexation or any resolution or ordinance proposing to annex land pursuant to this section.</para><para>(6) Not later than fourteen days prior to the public hearing before the planning commission on a proposed annexation by the city, the city clerk shall send notice of the proposed annexation by certified mail, return receipt requested, to any of the following entities serving customers in such city or in the area proposed for annexation: Any natural gas public utility as defined in section 66-1802; any natural gas utility owned or operated by the city; any metropolitan utilities district; any public power district; any public power and irrigation district; any municipality; any electric cooperative; and any other governmental entity providing electric service. Such notice shall include a copy of the proposed annexation ordinance, the date, time, and place of the public hearing before the planning commission on the proposed annexation ordinance, and a map showing the boundaries of the area proposed for annexation.</para><para>(7) Prior to the final adoption of the annexation ordinance, the minutes of the city council meeting at which such final adoption was considered shall reflect formal compliance with the provisions of subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(8) No additional or further notice beyond that required by subsection (6) of this section shall be necessary in the event (a) that the scheduled city council public hearing on the proposed annexation is adjourned, continued, or postponed until a later date or (b) that subsequent to providing such notice the ordinance regarding such proposed annexation was amended, changed, or rejected by action of the city council prior to formal passage of the annexation ordinance.</para><para>(9) Except for a willful or deliberate failure to cause notice to be given, no annexation decision made by a city either to accept or reject a proposed annexation, either in whole or in part, shall be void, invalidated, or affected in any way because of any irregularity, defect, error, or failure on the part of the city or its employees to cause notice to be given as required by this section if a reasonable attempt to comply with this section was made.</para><para>(10) Except for a willful or deliberate failure to cause notice to be given, the city and its employees shall not be liable for any damage to any person resulting from any failure to cause notice to be given as required by this section when a reasonable attempt was made to provide such notice. No action for damages resulting from the failure to cause notice to be provided as required by this section shall be filed more than one year following the date of the formal acceptance or rejection of the proposed annexation, either in whole or in part, by the city council.</para><para>(11) No action to challenge the validity of the acceptance or rejection of a proposed annexation on the basis of this section shall be filed more than one year following the date of the formal acceptance or rejection of the annexation by the city council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB495, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB74, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>