<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-6,100"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>16-6,100</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Public buildings; construction; bonds authorized; approval of electors required, when.</catchline><para>The mayor and city council shall have the power to borrow money and pledge the property and credit of the city upon its negotiable bonds or otherwise for the purpose of acquiring, by purchasing or constructing, including site acquisition, or aiding in the acquiring of a city hall, jail, auditorium, buildings for the fire department, and other public buildings, including the acquisition of buildings authorized to be acquired by Chapter 72, article 14, and including acquisition of buildings to be leased in whole or in part by the city to any other political or governmental subdivision of the State of Nebraska authorized by law to lease such buildings. No such bonds shall be issued until after the same have been authorized by a majority vote of the electors of the city voting on the proposition of their issuance at an election called for the submission of such proposition and of which election notice of the time and place thereof shall have been given by publication in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city three successive weeks prior thereto. If the building to be acquired is to be used by the State of Nebraska or its agency or agencies under a lease authorized by Chapter 72, article 14, or the building is to be leased by any other political or governmental subdivision of the State of Nebraska or other governmental agencies and if the combined area of the building to be leased by the state or its agency or agencies and the political or governmental subdivision of the State of Nebraska is more than fifty percent of the area of the building and if the cost of acquisition does not exceed two million dollars, no such vote of the electors will be required.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 15, &#167; 1, p. 132; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4971; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 89, &#167; 1, p. 229; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 39, &#167; 1, p. 122; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4140; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-670; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 23, &#167; 1, p. 116; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 16-670; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-6,100; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 23, &#167; 1, p. 131; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 30, &#167; 1, p. 138; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 28, &#167; 2, p. 135; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 436; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 876, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 161. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>