
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-716"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-716</statuteno><catchline>City funds; depositories; maximum deposits; liability of treasurer.</catchline><para>The city treasurer of a city of the first class shall not have on deposit in any bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution at any time more than the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation plus the maximum amount of the bond given by the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution if the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution gives a surety bond, nor in any bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution giving a personal bond, more than the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation plus one-half of the amount of the bond of such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution, and the amount so on deposit any time with any such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution shall not in either case exceed the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation plus the paid-up capital stock and surplus of such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution.</para><para>The city treasurer shall not be liable for any loss sustained by reason of the failure of any such bonded depository whose bond has been duly approved by the mayor as provided in section 16-714 or which has, in lieu of a surety bond, given security as provided in section 16-715.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 86, p. 294; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4982; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4151; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-713; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 28, &#167; 1, p. 116; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 135; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 16-713; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-716; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 491, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 157, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1274, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 860, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 183; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB194, &#167; 82. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>