<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-313"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>16-313</statuteno><catchline>Mayor; veto power; passage over veto.</catchline>
<para>The mayor shall have the power to approve or veto any ordinance passed
by the city council and
to approve or veto any order, bylaw, resolution, award of or vote to enter
into any contract, or the allowance of any claim. If the mayor approves the ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution,
contract, or claim, he or she shall sign it, and it shall become effective.
If the mayor vetoes the ordinance, order, bylaw, resolution, contract, or
any item or items of appropriations or claims, he or she shall return it to
the city council stating that the measure is vetoed. The mayor may issue the
veto at the meeting at which the measure passed or within seven calendar days
after the meeting. If the mayor issues the veto after the meeting, the mayor
shall notify the city clerk of the veto in writing. The clerk shall notify
the city council in writing of the mayor's veto. Any ordinance,
order, bylaw, resolution, award of or
vote to enter into any contract, or the allowance of any claim vetoed by the
mayor, may be passed over his or
her veto by a vote of two-thirds of all the members elected to
the council, notwithstanding his or
her veto. If the mayor neglects or refuses to sign any ordinance,
order, bylaw, resolution, award of or
vote to enter into any contract, or the allowance of any claim, but fails to veto the measure within the
time required by this section, the measure shall
become effective without his or her signature. The mayor
may veto any item or items of any appropriation bill or
any claims bill, and approve the remainder thereof, and the item
or items so vetoed may be passed by the council over the veto as in other
cases.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 18, &#167; 20, p. 234; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4879; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4047; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-309; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-313; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB803, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Under a similar section where four councilmen voted for, and four councilmen against, the issuance of a liquor license, and the mayor voted for its issuance, such vote of the mayor does not come within any exceptions direct or implied, and such mayor has the authority to cast the deciding vote. Rohrer v. Hastings Brewing Company, 83 Neb. 111, 119 N.W. 27 (1908).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>