<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>16-901</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Zoning regulations; building ordinances; public utility codes; extension; notice to county board.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in section 13-327 and subsection (2) of this section, the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of a city of the first class shall consist of the unincorporated area two miles beyond and adjacent to its corporate boundaries.</para><para>(2) For purposes of sections 70-1001 to 70-1020, the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of a city of the first class shall consist of the unincorporated area one mile beyond and adjacent to its corporate boundaries.</para><para>(3) Any city of the first class may apply by ordinance any existing or future zoning regulations, property use regulations, building ordinances, electrical ordinances, plumbing ordinances, and ordinances authorized by section 16-240 within its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction with the same force and effect as if such area were within the corporate limits of the city, except that no such ordinance shall be extended or applied so as to prohibit, prevent, or interfere with the conduct of existing farming, livestock operations, businesses, or industry. The fact that the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction is located in a different county or counties than some or all portions of the municipality shall not be construed as affecting the powers of the city to apply such ordinances.</para><para>(4)(a) A city of the first class shall provide written notice to the county board of the county in which the city’s two-mile extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction is located when proposing to adopt or amend a zoning ordinance which affects the city’s two-mile extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction within such county. The written notice of the proposed change to the zoning ordinance shall be sent to the county board or its designee at least thirty days prior to the final decision by the city. The county board may submit comments or recommendations regarding the change in the zoning ordinance at the public hearings on the proposed change or directly to the city within thirty days after receiving such notice. The city may make its final decision (i) upon the expiration of the thirty days following the notice or (ii) when the county board submits comments or recommendations, if any, to the city prior to the expiration of the thirty days following the notice.</para><para>(b) Subdivision (4)(a) of this section does not apply to a city of the first class (i) located in a county with a population in excess of one hundred thousand inhabitants or (ii) if the city and the county have a joint planning commission or joint planning department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 28, &#167; 1, p. 183; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 70, &#167; 1, p. 232; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 75, &#167; 1, p. 242; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 934, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB295, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 203. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB295, section 1, with LB704, section 203, to reflect all amendments.</note></source><annotation><para>A city is exercising control and county zoning regulations are superseded if the city adopts an ordinance with respect to territory within the extraterritorial jurisdiction, and it is not necessary that the city designate each particular piece of property within that jurisdiction. County of Dakota v. Worldwide Truck Parts &amp; Metals, 245 Neb. 196, 511 N.W.2d 769 (1994).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>