<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id00" statutenumber="16-620"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>16-620</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Improvement districts; objections of property owners; effect.</catchline><para>After publication of a notice required by section 16-619, if the owners of the record title at the time of such publication representing more than fifty percent of the front footage of the property abutting, intersecting, or adjoining any continuous or extended street, cul de sac, or alley of an improvement district, or portion thereof which is closed at one end, shall file with the city clerk, within twenty days from the first publication of such notice, written objections to the creation of such district, such work shall not be done in such district under such ordinance, but such ordinance shall be repealed by the mayor and city council. If objections are not filed against any district in the time and manner provided in this section, the mayor and city council shall forthwith proceed to construct improvements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 254; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4084; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 192; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 16-613; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 27, &#167; 1, p. 202; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 16-613; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 16-620; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 20, &#167; 1, p. 90; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 67, &#167; 4, p. 219; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 654, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB704, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB90, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>In passing on sufficiency of paving petition, city council exercises a judicial function. Elliott v. City of Auburn, 172 Neb. 1, 108 N.W.2d 328 (1961).</para><para>Property owners are given right to object to kind of materials used in improving street. Danielson v. City of Bellevue, 167 Neb. 809, 95 N.W.2d 57 (1959).</para><para>Ordinance creating special improvement district may be repealed before additional steps have been taken. Brasier v. City of Lincoln, 159 Neb. 12, 65 N.W.2d 213 (1954).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>