<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-118" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>16-118</statuteno><catchline>Annexation of land; deemed contiguous; when.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 16-117 and 16-130, lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways shall be deemed contiguous although a stream, embankment, strip, or parcel of land not more than two hundred feet wide lies between the same and the corporate limits.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 64, &#167; 2, p. 214; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB194, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Although this section states that lands, lots, tracts, streets, or highways shall be deemed contiguous although a stream, embankment, strip, or parcel of land not more than 200 feet wide lies between the same and corporate limits, this section implies a situation where a strip of land is located parallel to the city limits. Johnson v. City of Hastings, 241 Neb. 291, 488 N.W.2d 20 (1992).</para><para>A city of the first class may annex land contiguous to its corporate limits which is urban or suburban, including segments of highway, as determined by the characteristic of the land adjacent to that being annexed. Piester v. City of North Platte, 198 Neb. 220, 252 N.W.2d 159 (1977).</para><para>An action to enjoin a school district or part thereof, consequent upon annexation of territory by a city of the first class, is barred by the statute of limitations unless brought within one year from effective date of annexation ordinance. School Dist. No. 127 of Lincoln County v. Simpson, 191 Neb. 164, 214 N.W.2d 251 (1974).</para><para>Territory purportedly annexed was not contiguous or adjacent as it was separated from city boundary by river over two hundred feet wide. Doolittle v. County of Lincoln, 191 Neb. 159, 214 N.W.2d 248 (1974).</para><para>The character of a segment of an interstate highway sought to be annexed by a city of the first class is determined by the characteristic of the land immediately adjacent to the segment sought to be annexed. Adam v. City of Hastings, 12 Neb. App. 98, 668 N.W.2d 272 (2003).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>