<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id205">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id207" statutenumber="16-1027"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1027</statuteno><catchline id="id210">Retiring firefighter;
annuity options; how determined; lump-sum payment.</catchline><para>(1)
At any time before the retirement date, the retiring firefighter may elect
to receive his or her pension benefit at retirement either in the form of
a straight life annuity or any optional form of annuity benefit established
by the retirement committee and provided under a purchased annuity contract.
Such optional annuity benefit shall be specified in the funding medium for
the retirement system and shall include a straight life annuity with a guarantee
of at least sixty monthly payments or an annuity payable for the life of the
retiring firefighter and, after the death of the retiree, monthly payments,
as elected by the retiring firefighter, of one hundred percent, seventy-five
percent, or fifty percent of the amount of annuity payable to the retiring
firefighter during his or her life, to the beneficiary selected by the retiring
firefighter at the time of the original application for an annuity. For any
firefighter whose retirement date is on or after January 1, 1997, the optional
benefit forms for the retirement system shall include a single lump-sum payment
of the firefighter's retirement value. For firefighters whose retirement date
is prior to January 1, 1997, a single lump-sum payment shall be available
only if the city has adopted such distribution option in the funding medium
established for the retirement system. The retiring firefighter may further
elect to defer the date of the first payment or lump-sum distribution to the
first day of any specified month prior to age seventy. In the event the retiring
firefighter elects to receive his or her pension benefit in the form of an
annuity, the amount of such annuity benefit shall be the amount provided by
the annuity contract purchased or otherwise provided by the firefighter's
retirement value as of the date of the first payment. Any such annuity contract
purchased by the retirement system may be distributed to the retiring firefighter.
Upon the payment of a lump sum or the distribution of a paid-up annuity contract,
all obligations of the retirement system to pay retirement benefits to the
firefighter and his or her beneficiaries shall terminate, without exception.</para>
<para>(2) For all firefighters employed on January 1, 1984, the
amount of the pension benefit at the retirement date shall not be less than
the following amounts:</para>
<para>(a) If retirement from the city occurs following age fifty-five
with twenty-one years of service with the city, fifty percent of regular pay;</para>
<para>(b) If retirement from the city occurs following age fifty
but before age fifty-five with at least twenty-one years of service with the
city, such firefighter shall receive the actuarial equivalent of the benefit
which would otherwise be provided at age fifty-five;</para>
<para>(c) If retirement from the city occurs on or after age fifty-five
with less than twenty-one years of service with the city, such firefighter
shall receive a pension of at least fifty percent of the salary he or she
was receiving at the time of retirement multiplied by the ratio of the years
of service to twenty-one;</para>
<para>(d) For terminations of employment from the city on or after
September 9, 1993, if such termination of employment as a firefighter occurs
before age fifty-five but after completion of twenty-one years of service
with the city, such firefighter shall receive upon the attainment of age fifty-five
a pension benefit of fifty percent of regular pay;</para>
<para>(e) Unless an optional annuity benefit is selected by the
retired firefighter, at the death of any such retired firefighter the same
rate of pension as is provided for in this section shall be paid to the surviving
spouse of such deceased firefighter during such time as the surviving spouse
remains unmarried and, in case there is no surviving spouse, then the minor
children, if any, of such deceased firefighter shall equally share such pension
benefit during their minority, except that as soon as a child of such deceased
firefighter ceases to be a minor, such pension as to such child shall cease;
or</para>
<para>(f) In the event a retired firefighter or his or her surviving
beneficiaries die before the aggregate amount of pension payments received
by the firefighter and his or her survivor beneficiaries, if any, equals the
total amount in the firefighter's employee account, at the time of the first
benefit payment the difference between the total amount in the employee's
account and the aggregate amount of pension payments received by the retired
firefighter and his or her surviving beneficiaries, if any, shall be paid
in a single sum to the firefighter's estate.</para>
<para>A firefighter entitled to a minimum pension benefit under
this subsection may elect to receive such pension benefit in any form permitted
by subsection (1) of this section, including a single lump-sum payment, if
the firefighter retires on or after January 1, 1997, or if the city has adopted
a lump-sum distribution option for firefighters retiring before January 1,
1997, in the funding medium for the retirement system. If the minimum pension
benefit is paid in the form of an optional annuity benefit or a single lump-sum
payment, such benefit or payment shall be the actuarial equivalent of the
annuity that would otherwise be paid to the firefighter pursuant to this subsection.</para>
<para>If the firefighter chooses the single lump-sum payment option,
the firefighter may request that the actuarial equivalent be equal to the
average of the cost of two annuity contracts based on products available for purchase in Nebraska, if
the difference between the cost of the two annuity contracts does not exceed
five percent. Of the two annuity contracts used for comparison, one shall
be chosen by the firefighter and one shall be chosen by the city. If the difference
between the two annuity contracts exceeds five percent, the retirement committee
shall review the costs of the two annuity contracts and make a recommendation
to the city council as to the amount of the lump-sum payment to be made to
the firefighter. The city council shall, after a hearing, determine the amount
of the single lump-sum payment due the firefighter. The annuity contracts used for comparison shall all use
the same type of sex-neutral basis benefit calculation.</para>
<para>(3) If the retirement value of a firefighter entitled to
a minimum pension benefit under subsection (2) of this section is not sufficient
at the time of the first payment to purchase or provide the required pension
benefit, the city shall utilize such funds as may be necessary from the unallocated
employer account of the retirement system to purchase or provide for the required
pension benefit.</para>
<para>(4) Any retiring firefighter whose pension benefit is less
than twenty-five dollars per month on the straight life annuity option shall
be paid a lump-sum settlement equal to the retirement value in lieu of annuity
and shall not be entitled to elect to receive annuity benefits.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 531, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 672, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 724, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1068, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB759, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>