<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id6" statutenumber="16-1011"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1011</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Police officer;
disability in the line of duty; benefit; requirements.</catchline><para>(1)
If any police officer becomes disabled, such police officer shall be placed
upon the roll of pensioned police officers at the regular retirement pension
of fifty percent of regular pay for the period of such disability. For purposes
of this section, disability shall mean the complete inability of the police
officer, for reasons of accident or other cause while in the line of duty,
to perform the duties of a police officer.</para>
<para>(2) No disability benefit payment shall be made except upon
adequate proof furnished to the city, such proof to consist of a medical examination
conducted by a competent, disinterested physician who is duly licensed to
practice medicine and surgery in this state and who certifies to the city
that the police officer is unable to perform the duties of a police officer.
The city, during the first three years of the payment of such benefits, shall
have the right, at reasonable times, to require the disabled police officer
to undergo a medical examination at the city's expense to determine the continuance
of the disability claimed. After such three-year period, the city may request
the district court to order the police officer to submit proof of the continuance
of the disability claimed if the city has reasonable grounds to believe the
police officer is fraudulently receiving disability payments. The city shall
have the right to demand a physical examination of the police officer by a
competent, disinterested physician who is duly licensed to practice medicine
and surgery in this state, and who is chosen by the city. The expense of such
examination shall be borne by the city.</para>
<para>(3) In case of temporary disability of a police officer received
while in the line of duty, he or she shall receive his or her salary during
the continuance of such disability for a period not to exceed twelve months,
except that if it is ascertained by the city council or other proper municipal
authorities within twelve months that such temporary disability has become
a disability as defined in this section, then the salary shall cease and he
or she shall be entitled to the benefits for pensions in case of disability
as provided in this section.</para>
<para>(4) All payments of pension or salary provided by this section
shall be subject to deduction of amounts paid under the Nebraska Workers'
Compensation Act. In case of a permanent disability of a
police officer, such payments shall not commence until all credit
for unused annual or sick leave and other similar credits have been fully
utilized by the disabled police officer if there will be no impairment to
his or her salary during the period of disability. Total payments to a disabled
police officer, in excess of amounts paid as workers' compensation benefits,
shall not be less than the retirement value at the date of disability. If
the actuarial equivalent of the disability pension payable under this section
exceeds the police officer's retirement value at the time of the first payment,
the city shall contribute such additional amounts as may be necessary, from
time to time, to provide for the required disability pension.</para>
<para>(5) If a police officer who was pensioned under this section
is later determined to be no longer disabled, the pension provided for under
this section shall terminate and the police officer's vested retirement value,
as reduced by any disability payments made from the retirement system, shall
thereafter be held and administered in the same manner as for any nondisabled
police officer or former police officer.</para>
<para>(6) If a police officer who has pensioned under this section
is later determined to be no longer disabled during the first three years
when disability benefit payments are being paid the police officer may return
to duty with the police force under the following conditions:</para>
<para>(a) If a vacancy exists on the police force for which the
police officer is qualified and the police officer wishes to return to the
police force, the city shall hire the police officer to fill the vacancy at
a pay grade of not less than his or her previous pay grade; or</para>
<para>(b) If no vacancy exists on the police force and the police
officer wishes to return to the police force, the city may create a vacancy
under the city's reduction in force policy adopted under the Civil Service
Act and rehire the officer at a pay grade of not less than his or her previous
pay grade.</para>
<para>The provisions of this subsection shall not apply to a police
officer whose disability benefit payments are terminated because of fraud
on the part of the police officer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 237, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 811, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 672, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Civil Service Act,</emphasis> see section 19-1825.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Workers' Compensation Act,</emphasis> see section 48-1,110.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>