<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities of the First Class" statutenumber="16-1037"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1037</statuteno><catchline>Retirement committee; officers; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) It shall be the duty of the retirement committee to:</para>
<para>(a) Elect a chairperson, a vice-chairperson, and such other officers
as the committee deems appropriate;</para>
<para>(b) Hold regular quarterly meetings and special meetings upon the call
of the chairperson;</para>
<para>(c) Conduct meetings pursuant to the Open Meetings Act;</para>
<para>(d) Provide each employee a summary of plan eligibility requirements,
benefit provisions, and investment options available to such employee;</para>
<para>(e) Provide, within thirty days after a request is made by a participant,
a statement describing the amount of benefits such participant is eligible
to receive; and</para>
<para>(f) Make available for review an annual report of the system's operations
describing both (i) the amount of contributions to the system from both employee
and employer sources and (ii) an identification of the total assets of the
retirement system.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Beginning December 31, 1998, and each December 31 thereafter,
the chairperson of the retirement committee shall file with the Public Employees
Retirement Board an annual report on each retirement plan established pursuant
to section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code and administered by a retirement
system established pursuant to sections 16-1020 to 16-1042 and shall submit
copies of such report to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The Auditor
of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section
84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The annual report shall
be in a form prescribed by the Public Employees Retirement Board and shall
contain the following information for each such retirement plan:</para>
<para>(i) The number of persons participating in the retirement plan;</para>
<para>(ii) The contribution rates of participants in the plan;</para>
<para>(iii) Plan assets and liabilities;</para>
<para>(iv) The names and positions of persons administering the plan;</para>
<para>(v) The names and positions of persons investing plan assets;</para>
<para>(vi) The form and nature of investments;</para>
<para>(vii) For each defined contribution plan, a full description of investment
policies and options available to plan participants; and</para>
<para>(viii) For each defined benefit plan, the levels of benefits of participants
in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a benefit, and the
total present value of such members' benefits, as well as the funding sources
which will pay for such benefits.</para>
<para>If a plan contains no current active participants, the chairperson may
file in place of such report a statement with the Public Employees Retirement
Board indicating the number of retirees still drawing benefits, and the sources
and amount of funding for such benefits.</para>
<para>(b) Beginning December 31, 1998, and every four years thereafter, if
such retirement plan is a defined benefit plan, the retirement committee shall
cause to be prepared a quadrennial report and the chairperson shall file the
same with the Public Employees Retirement Board and submit to the Auditor
of Public Accounts a copy of such report. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such
report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The
report shall consist of a full actuarial analysis of each such retirement
plan administered by a system established pursuant to sections 16-1020 to
16-1042. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization
or public entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the
American Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated
expertise to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization
offering investment advice or which provides investment management services
to the retirement plan.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 531, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 672, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 8.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>