<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-1028"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1028</statuteno><catchline>Retirement options; retirement date.</catchline><para>(1) A firefighter of a city of the first class may:</para><para>(a) Retire or be retired and receive the applicable retirement pension benefit upon the attainment of age fifty-five while employed by the city as a firefighter;</para><para>(b) Elect to retire after he or she has attained the age of fifty and has completed at least twenty-one years of service with the city and receive the actuarial equivalent of the pension benefit he or she would otherwise receive upon the attainment of age fifty-five;</para><para>(c) After twenty-one years of service with the city, terminate employment with the city and, upon the attainment of age fifty-five, receive the applicable retirement pension benefit; or</para><para>(d) Retire or be retired as a result of disability while in the line of duty, as determined under section 16-1031, at any age and receive the applicable pension benefit provided in such section.</para><para>(2) A firefighter who is eligible to retire pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section but does not shall continue to contribute to his or her employee account and the city shall continue to contribute to its employer account.</para><para>(3) For purposes of subdivisions (1)(a), (b), and (d) of this section, the first of the month immediately following the last day of work shall be the retirement date. For purposes of subdivision (1)(c) of this section, the first of the month immediately following the attainment of age fifty-five shall be the retirement date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 531, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 724, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1068, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>