<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id165">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id167" statutenumber="16-1017"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1017</statuteno><catchline id="id170">Retirement
committee; duties.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be the duty of
the retirement committee to:</para>
<para>(a) Provide each employee a summary of plan eligibility requirements
and benefit provisions;</para>
<para>(b) Provide, within thirty days after a request is made by
a participant, a statement describing the amount of benefits such participant
is eligible to receive; and</para>
<para>(c) Make available for review an annual report of the retirement
system's operations describing both (i) the amount of contributions to the
retirement system from both employee and employer sources and (ii) an identification
of the total assets of the retirement system.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Beginning December 31, 1998, and each December 31
thereafter, the chairperson of the retirement committee shall file with the
Public Employees Retirement Board a report on each retirement plan established
pursuant to section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code and administered by
a retirement system established pursuant to the Police Officers Retirement
Act and shall submit copies of such report to the Auditor of Public Accounts.
The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant
to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The annual report shall
be in a form prescribed by the Public Employees Retirement Board and shall
contain the following information for each such retirement plan:</para>
<para>(i) The number of persons participating in the retirement
plan;</para>
<para>(ii) The contribution rates of participants in the plan;</para>
<para>(iii) Plan assets and liabilities;</para>
<para>(iv) The names and positions of persons administering the
plan;</para>
<para>(v) The names and positions of persons investing plan assets;</para>
<para>(vi) The form and nature of investments;</para>
<para>(vii) For each defined contribution plan, a full description
of investment policies and options available to plan participants; and</para>
<para>(viii) For each defined benefit plan, the levels of benefits
of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a
benefit, and the total present value of such members' benefits, as well as
the funding sources which will pay for such benefits.</para>
<para>If a plan contains no current active participants, the chairperson
may file in place of such report a statement with the Public Employees Retirement
Board indicating the number of retirees still drawing benefits and the sources
and amount of funding for such benefits.</para>
<para>(b) If such retirement plan is
a defined benefit plan which
was open to new members on January 1, 2004, in addition to the reports required by section 13-2402, the
retirement committee shall cause to be prepared an
annual report and the chairperson shall file the same with the
Public Employees Retirement Board and
the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and
submit to the Auditor of Public Accounts a copy of such report. The Auditor
of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section
84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If
the retirement committee does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor
of Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor
of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the city. All costs
of the audit shall be paid by the city. The report shall consist
of a full actuarial analysis of each such retirement plan administered by
a retirement system established pursuant to the act. The analysis shall be
prepared by an independent private organization or public entity employing
actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy of Actuaries,
and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise to perform this
type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization offering investment
advice or which provides investment management services to the retirement
plan. The report to the Nebraska
Retirement Systems Committee shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 237, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1082, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB759, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>