<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id152">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities of the First Class" id="id154" statutenumber="16-1019"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1019</statuteno><catchline id="id157">Exemption from
legal process; administration; requirements; retirement committee; powers
and duties; review of adjustment; tax levy authorized; payment for civil damages; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (6) of
this section, the right to any benefits under the retirement system
and the assets of any fund of the retirement system shall not be assignable
or subject to execution, garnishment, attachment, or the operation of any
bankruptcy or insolvency laws, except that the retirement system may comply
with the directions set forth in a qualified domestic relations order meeting
the requirements of section 414(p) of the Internal Revenue Code. Any payment of benefits subject to such
order shall take priority over any payment made pursuant to subsection (6)
of this section. The city or retirement committee may require
appropriate releases from any person as a condition to complying with any
such order. The retirement system shall not recognize any domestic relations
order which alters or changes benefits, provides for a form of benefit not
otherwise provided for by the retirement system, increases benefits not otherwise
provided by the retirement system, or accelerates or defers the time of payment
of benefits. No participant or beneficiary shall have any right to any specific
portion of the assets of the retirement system.</para>
<para>(2) The retirement system shall be administered in a manner
necessary to comply with the tax-qualification requirements applicable to
government retirement plans under section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code,
including section 401(a)(9) relating to the time and manner in which benefits
are required to be distributed and
section 401(a)(9)(G) relating to incidental death benefit requirements,
section 401(a)(16) relating to compliance with the maximum limitation on the
plan benefits or contributions under section 415, section 401(a)(17) which
limits the amount of compensation which can be taken into account under a
retirement plan, section
401(a)(25) relating to the specification of actuarial assumptions, section 401(a)(31) relating to direct
rollover distributions from eligible retirement plans, and section 401(a)(37)
relating to the death benefit of a police officer who dies while performing
qualified military service. Any requirements for compliance with
section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code may be set forth in any trust
or funding medium for the retirement system. This subsection shall be in full
force and effect only so long as conformity with section 401(a) of the Internal
Revenue Code is required for public retirement systems in order to secure
the favorable income tax treatment extended to sponsors and beneficiaries
of tax-qualified retirement plans.</para>
<para>(3) If the retirement committee determines that the retirement
system has previously overpaid or underpaid a benefit payable under the Police Officers Retirement Act, it
shall have the power to correct such error. In the event of an overpayment,
the retirement system may, in addition to any other remedy that the retirement
system may possess, offset future benefit payments by the amount of the prior
overpayment, together with regular interest thereon.</para>
<para>(4) A police officer whose benefit payment is adjusted by
the retirement committee pursuant to subsection (3) of this section may request
a review by the city council of the adjustment made by the retirement committee.</para>
<para>(5) In order to provide the necessary amounts to pay for
or fund a pension plan established under the
act, the mayor and council may make a levy which is within the
levy restrictions of section 77-3442.</para>
<para>(6) If a member of the
retirement system is convicted of or pleads no contest to a felony that is
defined as assault, sexual assault, kidnapping, child abuse, false imprisonment,
or theft by embezzlement and is found liable for civil damages as a result
of such felony, following distribution of the member's benefits or the assets
of any fund of the member from the retirement system, the court may order
the payment of the member's benefits or the assets of any fund of the member
under the retirement system for such civil damages, except that the benefits
or assets to the extent reasonably necessary for the support of the member
or any of his or her beneficiaries shall be exempt from such payment. Any
order for payment of benefits or assets shall not be stayed on the filing
of any appeal of the conviction. If the conviction is reversed on final judgment,
all benefits or assets paid as civil damages shall be forfeited and returned
to the member. The changes made to this section by Laws 2012, LB916, shall
apply to persons convicted of or who have pled no contest to such a felony
and who have been found liable for civil damages as a result of such felony
prior to, on, or after April 7, 2012.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 237, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 672, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1082, &#167; 15.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>