<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" statutenumber="16-1036"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1036</statuteno><catchline>Firefighters Retirement System Fund; authorized investments; retirement committee; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The funds in the Firefighters Retirement System Fund shall be invested by the retirement committee. The city, subject to the approval of the retirement committee, shall contract with a funding agent or agents to hold or invest the assets of the retirement system and to provide for the benefits provided by sections 16-1020 to 16-1042. The retirement committee, subject to the approval of the city, may also select an investment manager. The city, subject to approval of the retirement committee, may contract with investment managers registered under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 to invest, reinvest, and otherwise manage such portion of the assets of the retirement system as may be assigned by the city or retirement committee.</para><para>(2) The retirement committee shall establish an investment plan which allows each member of the retirement system to allocate all contributions to his or her employee account and, if he or she commenced his or her employment after January 1, 1984, his or her employer account to the various investment options or combinations of investment options described in such plan. Each firefighter shall have the option of investing his or her employee account and, if he or she commenced his or her employment after January 1, 1984, his or her employer account in any proportion, including full allocation, in any investment option offered by the plan. Upon the direction of the city, firefighters employed on January 1, 1984, may have the option to allocate their employer account to various investment options or combinations of investment options in any proportion, including full allocation, in any investment option offered by the plan. Each firefighter shall be given a summary of the investment plan and a detailed current description of each investment option prior to making or revising his or her allocation.</para><para>(3) The funds in the Firefighters Retirement System Fund shall be invested pursuant to the policies established by the Nebraska Investment Council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 531, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 2, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 672, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 724, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1097, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>