<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The First Class" id="id38" statutenumber="16-1038"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>16-1038</statuteno><catchline id="id41">Retirement benefits; exemption from legal process; exception; tax-qualification requirements; benefit error; correction; appeal; tax levy authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The right to any benefits under the retirement system and the assets of any fund of the retirement system shall not be assignable or subject to execution, garnishment, attachment, or the operation of any bankruptcy or insolvency laws, except that the retirement system may comply with the directions set forth in a qualified domestic relations order meeting the requirements of section 414(p) of the Internal Revenue Code. The city or retirement committee may require appropriate releases from any person as a condition to complying with any such order. The retirement system shall not recognize any domestic relations order which alters or changes benefits, provides for a form of benefit not otherwise provided for by the retirement system, increases benefits not otherwise provided by the retirement system, or accelerates or defers the time of payment of benefits. No participant or beneficiary shall have any right to any specific portion of the assets of the retirement system.</para><para>(2) The retirement system shall be administered in a manner necessary to comply with the tax-qualification requirements applicable to government retirement plans under section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code, including section 401(a)(9) relating to the time and manner in which benefits are required to be distributed and section 401(a)(9)(G) relating to incidental death benefit requirements, section 401(a)(16) relating to compliance with the maximum limitation on the plan benefits or contributions under section 415, section 401(a)(17) which limits the amount of compensation which can be taken into account under a retirement plan, section 401(a)(25) relating to the specification of actuarial assumptions, section 401(a)(31) relating to direct rollover distribution from eligible retirement plans, and section 401(a)(37) relating to the death benefit of a firefighter who dies while performing qualified military service. Any requirements for compliance with section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code may be set forth in any trust or funding medium for the retirement system. This subsection shall be in full force and effect only so long as conformity with section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code is required for public retirement systems in order to secure the favorable income tax treatment extended to sponsors and beneficiaries of tax-qualified retirement plans.</para><para>(3) If the retirement committee determines that the retirement system has previously overpaid or underpaid a benefit payable under sections 16-1020 to 16-1042, it shall have the power to correct such error. In the event of an overpayment, the retirement system may, in addition to any other remedy that the retirement system may possess, offset future benefit payments by the amount of the prior overpayment, together with regular interest thereon.</para><para>(4) A firefighter whose benefit payment is adjusted by the retirement committee pursuant to subsection (3) of this section may request a review by the city council of the adjustment made by the retirement committee.</para><para>(5) In order to provide the necessary amounts to pay for or fund a pension plan established under sections 16-1020 to 16-1042, the mayor and council may make a levy which is within the levy restrictions of section 77-3442.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 531, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 724, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB916, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1082, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB40, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>