<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id257">
<sectno id="id258" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 23.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id259" statutenumber="71-516.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id261">71-516.04</statuteno><catchline id="id262">Facility;
disclosures required; department; duties.</catchline><para>Any
facility which offers to provide or provides care for persons with Alzheimer's
disease, dementia, or a related disorder by means of an Alzheimer's special
care unit shall disclose the form of care or treatment provided that distinguishes
such form as being especially applicable to or suitable for such persons.
The disclosure shall be made to the Department of Health and Human Services
and to any person seeking placement within an Alzheimer's special care unit.
The department shall examine all such disclosures in the records of the department
as part of the facility's license renewal procedure at the time of licensure
or relicensure.</para>
<para>The information disclosed shall explain the additional care
provided in each of the following areas:</para>
<para>(1) The Alzheimer's special care unit's written statement
of its overall philosophy and mission which reflects the needs of residents
afflicted with Alzheimer's disease, dementia, or a related disorder;</para>
<para>(2) The process and criteria for placement in, transfer to,
or discharge from the unit;</para>
<para>(3) The process used for assessment and establishment of
the plan of care and its implementation, including the method by which the
plan of care evolves and is responsive to changes in condition;</para>
<para>(4) Staff training and continuing education practices which shall include, but not be limited
to, four hours annually for direct care staff. Such training shall include
topics pertaining to the form of care or treatment set forth in the disclosure
described in this section. The requirement in this subdivision shall not be
construed to increase the aggregate hourly training requirements of the Alzheimer's
special care unit;</para>
<para>(5) The physical environment and design features appropriate
to support the functioning of cognitively impaired adult residents;</para>
<para>(6) The frequency and types of resident activities;</para>
<para>(7) The involvement of families and the availability of family
support programs; and</para>
<para>(8) The costs of care and any additional fees.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 165; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 501; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 389; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 23.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>