<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-919"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-919</statuteno><catchline>Mentally ill and dangerous person; dangerous sex offender; emergency protective custody; evaluation by mental health professional.</catchline><para>(1) A law enforcement officer who has probable cause to believe that a person is mentally ill and dangerous or a dangerous sex offender and that the harm described in section 71-908 or subdivision (1) of section 83-174.01 is likely to occur before mental health board proceedings under the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act or the Sex Offender Commitment Act may be initiated to obtain custody of the person may take such person into emergency protective custody, cause him or her to be taken into emergency protective custody, or continue his or her custody if he or she is already in custody. Such person shall be admitted to an appropriate and available medical facility, jail, or Department of Correctional Services facility as provided in subsection (2) of this section. Each county shall make arrangements with appropriate facilities inside or outside the county for such purpose and shall pay the cost of the emergency protective custody of persons from such county in such facilities. A mental health professional who has probable cause to believe that a person is mentally ill and dangerous or a dangerous sex offender may cause such person to be taken into custody and shall have a limited privilege to hold such person until a law enforcement officer or other authorized person arrives to take custody of such person.</para><para>(2)(a) A person taken into emergency protective custody under this section shall be admitted to an appropriate and available medical facility unless such person has a prior conviction for a sex offense listed in section 29-4003.</para><para>(b) A person taken into emergency protective custody under this section who has a prior conviction for a sex offense listed in section 29-4003 shall be admitted to a jail or Department of Correctional Services facility unless a medical or psychiatric emergency exists for which treatment at a medical facility is required. The person in emergency protective custody shall remain at the medical facility until the medical or psychiatric emergency has passed and it is safe to transport such person, at which time the person shall be transferred to an available jail or Department of Correctional Services facility.</para><para>(3) Upon admission to a facility of a person taken into emergency protective custody by a law enforcement officer under this section, such officer shall execute a written certificate prescribed and provided by the Department of Health and Human Services. The certificate shall allege the officer's belief that the person in custody is mentally ill and dangerous or a dangerous sex offender and shall contain a summary of the person's behavior supporting such allegations. A copy of such certificate shall be immediately forwarded to the county attorney.</para><para>(4) The administrator of the facility shall have such person evaluated by a mental health professional as soon as reasonably possible but not later than thirty-six hours after admission. The mental health professional shall not be the mental health professional who causes such person to be taken into custody under this section and shall not be a member or alternate member of the mental health board that will preside over any hearing under the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act or the Sex Offender Commitment Act with respect to such person. A person shall be released from emergency protective custody after completion of such evaluation unless the mental health professional determines, in his or her clinical opinion, that such person is mentally ill and dangerous or a dangerous sex offender.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 806, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 501, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 257, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 964; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 95; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 83-1020; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 462.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>