<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-640.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-640.01</statuteno><catchline>Birth certificates; identification of father.</catchline><para>The information pertaining to the identification of the father at the time of birth of an infant born in this state and reported on a birth certificate, filled out and filed pursuant to the Vital Statistics Act, shall comply with the following:</para><para>(1) If the mother was married at the time of either conception or birth or at any time between conception and birth, the name of the husband shall be entered on the certificate as the father of the child unless (a) paternity has been determined otherwise by a court of competent jurisdiction, (b) the mother and the mother's husband execute affidavits attesting that the husband is not the father of the child, in which case information about the father shall be omitted from the certificate, or (c) the mother executes an affidavit attesting that the husband is not the father and that the putative father is the father, the putative father executes an affidavit attesting that he is the father, and the husband executes an affidavit attesting that he is not the father. In such event, the putative father shall be shown as the father on the certificate. For affidavits executed under subdivision (b) or (c) of this subdivision, each signature shall be individually notarized;</para><para>(2) If the mother was not married at the time of either conception or birth or at any time between conception and birth, the name of the father shall not be entered on the certificate without the written consent of the mother and the person named as the father;</para><para>(3) In any case in which paternity of a child is determined by a court of competent jurisdiction, the name of the father shall be entered on the certificate in accordance with the finding of the court; and</para><para>(4) If the father is not named on the certificate, no other information about the father shall be entered thereon.</para><para>The identification of the father as provided in this section shall not be deemed to affect the legitimacy of the child or duty to support as set forth in sections 42-377 and 43-1401.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 72, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 886, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 301, &#167; 27. </para></source></law></legaldoc>