<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-514.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-514.03</statuteno><catchline>Health care providers; significant exposure to blood or body fluid; procedure; cost; restriction.</catchline><para>(1) If a health care provider has a significant exposure to the blood or body fluid of a patient as determined and documented by a designated representative of the provider agency according to a written protocol:</para><para>(a) The patient shall be informed that he or she has the right to consent to the diagnostic testing of his or her body fluid for presence of an infectious disease or condition and that if the patient refuses to grant consent, such refusal shall be communicated to the health care provider;</para><para>(b) If the patient is unconscious or incapable of signing an informed consent form, the consent may be obtained from the patient's next of kin or legal guardian;</para><para>(c) If the patient or patient's next of kin or legal guardian refuses to grant consent for such testing and a sample of the patient's blood or other body fluid is available, the sample shall be tested for the presence of infectious disease or condition. If an available sample of blood or other body fluid is tested without consent, the patient or patient's next of kin or legal guardian shall be notified that the available sample is being tested and informed of the purpose of the test and test results. If the human immunodeficiency virus test result is positive, the health care provider or provider agency shall refer the patient for posttest counseling. If the patient or patient's guardian refuses to grant consent and a sample of the patient's blood or other body fluid is not available, the health care provider or provider agency may petition the district court for an order mandating that the testing be performed; or</para><para>(d) If a patient dies without the opportunity to consent to such testing, testing for the presence of an infectious disease or condition shall be conducted.</para><para>(2) The provider agency shall be responsible for the cost of such diagnostic testing.</para><para>(3) Routine drawing of a sample of blood or other body fluid for the purpose of testing for infectious disease or conditions without obtaining consent shall be prohibited.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 819, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 