<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id969"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-252"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>71-252</statuteno><catchline>Mobile barber shop; operating requirements.</catchline><para>In order to maintain its license in good standing, each mobile barber shop shall operate in accordance with the following requirements:</para><para>(1) The barber shop shall at all times comply with all applicable provisions of the Barber Act and all rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act;</para><para>(2) The barber shop owner or his or her agent shall notify the board of any change of ownership, name, or office address and if a barber shop is permanently closed;</para><para>(3) No barber shop shall permit any unlicensed person to perform any of the practices of barbering within its confines or employment;</para><para>(4) The barber shop shall display a name upon, over, or near the entrance door distinguishing it as a barber shop;</para><para>(5) The barber shop shall permit any duly authorized agent of the board to conduct an operation inspection or investigation at any time during the normal operating hours of the barber shop, without prior notice, and the owner and manager shall assist the inspector by providing access to all areas of the barber shop, all personnel, and all records requested by the inspector;</para><para>(6) The barber shop shall display in a conspicuous place the following records:</para><para>(a) The current license or certificate of consideration to operate a barber shop; and</para><para>(b) The current licenses of all persons licensed under the act who are employed by or working in the barber shop;</para><para>(7) No barbering practices may be performed in a barber shop while the barber shop is moving. The barber shop must be safely and legally parked in a legal parking space at all times while clients are present inside the barber shop. A barber shop shall not park or conduct business within three hundred feet of another licensed barber shop. The board is not responsible for monitoring for enforcement of this subdivision but may discipline a license for a reported and verified violation; and</para><para>(8) The owner of the barber shop shall maintain a permanent business address at which correspondence from the board may be received and records of appointments, license numbers, and vehicle identification numbers shall be kept for each barber shop being operated by the owner. The owner shall make such records available for verification and inspection by the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 87. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>