<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id60"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-607"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-607</statuteno><catchline>Nonviable birth; commemorative certificate; department; duties; fee.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A health care practitioner licensed pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act who attends or diagnoses a nonviable birth or a health care facility licensed pursuant to the Health Care Facility Licensure Act at which a nonviable birth occurs shall advise a patient who experiences a nonviable birth that the patient may request a commemorative certificate as provided in this section and, upon request by the patient, shall provide a letter verifying the nonviable birth to the patient. The health care practitioner may delegate this duty to his or her designee. In lieu of a letter, the health care practitioner or his or her designee may provide the patient with a form provided by the department pursuant to subdivision (b) of this subsection and executed by the health care practitioner or his or her designee.</para><para>(b) The department shall provide on its web site a form to be executed by a health care practitioner or his or her designee affirming that a patient experienced a nonviable birth that the health care practitioner attended or diagnosed.</para><para>(2) Upon the request of the patient and submission of the letter or executed form, the department shall issue a commemorative certificate within sixty days after receipt of such request. The department shall charge a fee not to exceed its actual cost for issuing the commemorative certificate.</para><para>(3)(a) The commemorative certificate shall contain the name of the fetus and the gender, if known. If the name is not furnished by the patient, the department shall fill in the commemorative certificate with the name Baby Boy or Baby Girl and the last name of the patient, and if the gender of the child is also unknown, the department shall fill in the commemorative certificate with the name Baby and the last name of the patient.</para><para>(b) The following statement shall appear on the front of the commemorative certificate: This commemorative certificate is not proof of a live birth.</para><para>(4) The department shall not register the birth associated with a commemorative certificate issued under this section or use it to calculate live birth statistics. The commemorative certificate is commemorative in nature and has no legal effect.</para><para>(5) A commemorative certificate issued under this section shall not be used to establish, bring, or support a civil cause of action seeking damages against any person or entity for bodily injury, personal injury, or wrongful death for a nonviable birth.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB1040, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>