<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id850"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-475"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>71-475</statuteno><catchline>Drug; provided to patient upon discharge; records; label; documentation.</catchline><para>(1)(a) When administration of a drug occurs in a hospital pursuant to a chart order, hospital personnel may provide the unused portion of the drug to the patient upon discharge from the hospital for continued use in treatment of the patient if:</para><para>(i) The drug has been opened and used for treatment of the patient at the hospital and is necessary for the continued treatment of the patient and would be wasted if not used by the patient; and</para><para>(ii) The drug is:</para><para>(A) In a multidose device or a multidose container; or</para><para>(B) In the form of a liquid reconstituted from a dry stable state to a liquid resulting in a limited stability.</para><para>(b) A drug provided to a patient in accordance with this subsection shall be labeled with the name of the patient, the name of the drug including the quantity if appropriate, the date the drug was provided, and the directions for use.</para><para>(2)(a) A licensed health care practitioner authorized to prescribe controlled substances may provide to his or her patients being discharged from a hospital a sufficient quantity of drugs adequate, in the judgment of the practitioner, to continue treatment, which began in the hospital, until the patient is reasonably able to access a pharmacy.</para><para>(b) The pharmacist-in-charge at the hospital shall maintain records of the drugs provided to patients in accordance with this subsection which shall include the name of the patient, the name of the drug including the quantity if appropriate, the date the drug was provided, and the directions for use.</para><para>(3) If a drug is provided to a patient in accordance with this section:</para><para>(a) The drug shall be kept in a locked cabinet or automated medication system with access only by a licensed health care practitioner authorized to prescribe, dispense, or administer controlled substances;</para><para>(b) Prior to providing the drug to the patient, a written or electronic order shall be in the patient’s record;</para><para>(c) The process at the hospital shall be under the direct supervision of the prescriber;</para><para>(d) If the label is prepared by a nurse, the prescriber shall verify the drug and the directions for the patient;</para><para>(e) When possible, the directions for the patient shall be preprinted on the label by the pharmacist;</para><para>(f) The label shall include the name of the patient, the name of the drug including the quantity if appropriate, the date the drug was provided, and the directions for use;</para><para>(g) A written information sheet shall be given to the patient for each drug provided; and</para><para>(h) Documentation in a readily retrievable format shall be maintained each time a drug is provided to a patient from the hospital pharmacy’s inventory which shall include the date, the patient, the drug, and the prescriber.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB166, &#167; 20. </para><effectivedate>April 28, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>