<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-217"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-217</statuteno><catchline>Barbering; certificate; denial, suspension, or revocation; grounds.</catchline><para>The board may either refuse to issue or renew or may suspend or revoke any certificate of registration or approval for any one or a combination of the following causes: (1) Conviction of a felony shown by a certified copy of the record of the court of conviction; (2) gross malpractice or gross incompetency; (3) continued practice by a person knowingly having an infectious or contagious disease; (4) advertising by means of knowingly false or deceptive statements or in violation of section 71-223.02; (5) advertising, practicing, or attempting to practice under a trade name or any name other than one's own; (6) habitual drunkenness or habitual addiction to the use of morphine, cocaine, or other habit-forming drugs; (7) immoral or unprofessional conduct; (8) violation of any of the provisions of sections 71-201 to 71-237 or of any valid regulation promulgated by the board pertaining to service charges, sanitation, and the elimination of unfair practices; and (9) any check presented to the board as a fee for either an original license or renewal license or for examination for license or any other fee authorized in sections 71-201 to 71-237 which is returned to the State Treasurer unpaid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 163, &#167; 14, p. 432; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2018; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-217; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 166, &#167; 2, p. 533; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 388, &#167; 3, p. 1060; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 409, &#167; 21, p. 1323; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 87, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 482; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 90. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 