<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id917"> <amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id919"  statutenumber="71-239.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-239.01</statuteno><catchline>Foreign licenses; recognition; licensure without examination; application; form; contents; issuance; appeal.</catchline> <para>(1) The board may issue a license without examination to a person licensed in a state, territory, or country with which the board has not entered into a reciprocal agreement under section 71-239 as provided in this section.</para> <para>(2) An applicant for licensure without examination under subsection (1) of this section shall file with the board (a) an application on a form provided by the board, (b) a copy of the license issued by the state, territory, or country in which the applicant is licensed, (c) the applicant's social security number, (d) documents demonstrating that the requirements for licensure in such state, territory, or country are substantially equivalent to the requirements for licensure under the Barber Act, and (e) the fee required pursuant to section 71-219.</para><para>(3) The board shall review each application and the documents submitted under this section and determine within sixty days after receiving such application and documentation whether to issue a license without examination to the applicant. The board shall notify the applicant of its decision within ten days after the date of making the decision. If the board determines not to issue a license without examination to the applicant, he or she may appeal the decision of the board and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(4) The board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 64.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>