<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id803"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-915"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-915</statuteno><catchline>Mental health boards; created; powers; duties; compensation.</catchline><para>(1) The presiding judge in each district court judicial district shall create at least one but not more than three mental health boards in such district and shall appoint sufficient members and alternate members to such boards. Members and alternate members of a mental health board shall be appointed for four-year terms. The presiding judge may remove members and alternate members of the board at his or her discretion. Vacancies shall be filled for the unexpired term in the same manner as provided for the original appointment. Members of the mental health board shall have the same immunity as judges of the district court.</para><para>(2) Each mental health board shall consist of an attorney licensed to practice law in this state and any two of the following but not more than one from each category: A physician, a psychologist, a psychiatric nurse, a licensed clinical social worker or a licensed independent clinical social worker, a licensed independent mental health practitioner who is not a social worker, or a layperson with a demonstrated interest in mental health and substance dependency issues. The attorney shall be chairperson of the board. Members and alternate members of a mental health board shall take and subscribe an oath to support the United States Constitution and the Constitution of Nebraska and to faithfully discharge the duties of the office according to law.</para><para>(3) The mental health board shall have the power to issue subpoenas, to administer oaths, and to do any act necessary and proper for the board to carry out its duties. No mental health board hearing shall be conducted unless three members or alternate members are present and able to vote. Any action taken at any mental health board hearing shall be by majority vote. Upon the agreement of all parties, any hearing before the mental health board may be conducted by videoconferencing.</para><para>(4) The mental health board shall prepare and file an annual inventory statement with the county board of its county of all county personal property in its custody or possession. Members of the mental health board shall be compensated and shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses by the county or counties being served by such board. Compensation shall be at an hourly rate to be determined by the presiding judge of the district court, except that such compensation shall not be less than fifty dollars for each hearing of the board. Members shall also be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses, not including charges for meals. Mileage shall be determined pursuant to section 23-1112.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 806, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 95, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 498, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 83-1017; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 108. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source><annotation><para>A mental health board may assign an alternate member to serve so that the board has the required three members. In re Interest of A.M., 281 Neb. 482, 797 N.W.2d 233 (2011).</para><para>A person who is not a lawyer, a physician, a psychologist, a psychiatric social worker, a psychiatric nurse, or a clinical social worker is a "layman" within the meaning of this section. In re Interest of A.M., 281 Neb. 482, 797 N.W.2d 233 (2011).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>