<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-564" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-564</statuteno><catchline>Alzheimer's Disease and Other Dementia Advisory Council; members; terms; duties; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Alzheimer's Disease and Other Dementia Advisory Council is created and shall include:</para><para>(a) Twelve voting members appointed by the Governor. The voting members shall consist of: (i) An individual living with Alzheimer's disease or another dementia or a family member of such an individual; (ii) an individual who is the family caregiver of an individual living with Alzheimer's disease or another dementia; (iii) an individual who represents nursing homes; (iv) an individual who represents assisted-living facilities; (v) an individual who represents providers of adult day care services; (vi) an individual who represents home care providers; (vii) a medical professional who has experience diagnosing and treating Alzheimer's disease; (viii) an individual who conducts research regarding Alzheimer's disease or other dementia; (ix) an individual who represents a leading, nationwide organization that advocates on behalf of individuals living with Alzheimer's disease or other dementia; (x) an individual who represents an area agency on aging; (xi) an individual representing an organization that advocates for older adults; and (xii) an individual with experience or expertise in the area of the specific needs of individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities and Alzheimer's disease or other dementia; and</para><para>(b) Five nonvoting members. The nonvoting members shall consist of: (i) The Director of Public Health or the director's designee; (ii) the Director of Medicaid and Long-Term Care or the director's designee; (iii) a representative of the State Unit on Aging of the Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care designated by the Director of Medicaid and Long-Term Care; (iv) a representative of the Nebraska Workforce Development Board designated by the board; and (v) the state long-term care ombudsman or the ombudsman's designee.</para><para>(2) The terms of the initial members shall begin on the date of the first meeting as called by the Director of Public Health and (a) one-third shall serve for two-year terms, (b) one-third shall serve for three-year terms, and (c) one-third shall serve for four-year terms, including the chairperson and vice-chairperson. Thereafter all members shall serve four-year terms. Members may not serve more than two consecutive four-year terms. Vacancies shall be appointed by the Governor in the same manner as described in subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(3) Members of the council shall select the chairperson and vice-chairperson who shall not be employees of the state and may serve in such role for up to four consecutive years. The Director of Public Health or the director's designee shall call and preside over the first meeting until a chairperson is selected. Thereafter, the council shall meet at least quarterly at the call of the chairperson. A majority of the voting members shall constitute a quorum for the conduct of meetings.</para><para>(4) The council shall hold meetings at least once every calendar quarter.</para><para>(5) Members shall serve on the council without compensation but shall be compensated for expenses incurred for such service.</para><para>(6) The department shall provide staff and support to the council as necessary to assist the council in the performance of its duties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB752, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB903, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>