<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-944" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-944</statuteno><catchline>Subject's rights; written notice of the time and place of hearing; reasons alleged for treatment; procedure.</catchline><para>A subject shall, in advance of the mental health board hearing conducted under section 71-924 or 71-1208, be entitled to written notice of the time and place of such hearing, the reasons alleged for believing that he or she is mentally ill and dangerous or a dangerous sex offender requiring inpatient or outpatient treatment ordered by the mental health board, and all rights to which such subject is entitled under the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act or the Sex Offender Commitment Act. The notice requirements shall be deemed satisfied by personal service upon the subject of the summons or notice of time and place of the hearing and copies of the petition and list of rights required by sections 71-923 and 71-924 or sections 71-1207 and 71-1208. If the subject has counsel and if the physician or mental health professional on the board determines that the nature of the alleged mental disorder or personality disorder, if true, is such that it is not prudent to disclose the label of the mental disorder or personality disorder to the subject, then notice of this label may be disclosed to the subject's counsel rather than to the subject. When the subject does not have counsel, the subject has a right to the information about his or her mental illness or personality disorder, including its label. The clerk shall issue the summons by order of the mental health board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 806, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 95, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 884, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 83-1048; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 40. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Sex Offender Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>