<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare"  statutenumber="71-612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-612</statuteno><catchline>Department; certificates; copies;
fees; waiver of fees, when; search of death certificates; fee; access; petty
cash fund; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The department, as the State Registrar,
shall preserve permanently and index all certificates received. The department
shall supply to any applicant for any proper purpose, as defined by rules
and regulations of the department, a certified copy of the record of any birth,
death, marriage, annulment, or dissolution of marriage or an abstract of marriage.
The department shall supply a copy of a public vital record for viewing purposes
at its office upon an application signed by the applicant and upon proof of
the identity of the applicant. The application may include the name, address,
and telephone number of the applicant, purpose for viewing each record, and
other information as may be prescribed by the department by rules and regulations
to protect the integrity of vital records and preven<?Pub Caret?>t their fraudulent
use. Except as provided in subsections (2), (3), (5), (6), and (7) of this
section, the department shall be entitled to charge and collect in advance
a fee of sixteen dollars to be paid
by the applicant for each certified copy or abstract of marriage supplied
to the applicant or for any search made at the applicant's request for access
to or a certified copy of any record or abstract of marriage, whether or not
the record or abstract is found on file with the department.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall, free of charge, search for and furnish a certified
copy of any record or abstract of marriage on file with the department upon
the request of (a) the United States Department of Veterans Affairs or any
lawful service organization empowered to represent veterans if the copy of
the record or abstract of marriage is to be issued, for the welfare of any
member or veteran of the armed forces of the United States or in the interests
of any member of his or her family, in connection with a claim growing out
of service in the armed forces of the nation or (b) the Military Department.</para>
<para>(3) The department may, free of charge, search for and furnish a certified
copy of any record or abstract of marriage on file with the department when
in the opinion of the department it would be a hardship for the claimant of
old age, survivors, or disability benefits under the federal Social Security
Act to pay the fee provided in this section.</para>
<para>(4) A strict account shall be kept of all funds received by the department.
Funds received pursuant to subsections (1), (5), (6), and (8) of this section
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Health and Human
Services Cash Fund. Money credited to the fund pursuant to this section shall
be used for the purpose of administering the laws relating to vital statistics
and may be used to create a petty cash fund administered by the department
to facilitate the payment of refunds to individuals who apply for copies or
abstracts of records. The petty cash fund shall be subject to section 81-104.01,
except that the amount in the petty cash fund shall not be less than twenty-five
dollars nor more than one thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(5) The department shall, upon request, conduct a search of death certificates
for stated individuals for the Nebraska Medical Association or any of its
allied medical societies or any inhospital staff committee pursuant to sections
71-3401 to 71-3403. If such death certificate is found, the department shall
provide a noncertified copy. The department shall charge a fee for each search
or copy sufficient to cover its actual direct costs, except that the fee shall
not exceed three dollars per individual
search or copy requested.</para>
<para>(6) The department may permit use of data from vital records for statistical
or research purposes under section 71-602 or disclose data from certificates
or records to federal, state, county, or municipal agencies of government
for use in administration of their official duties and charge and collect
a fee that will recover the department's cost of production of the data. The
department may provide access to public vital records for viewing purposes
by electronic means, if available, under security provisions which shall assure
the integrity and security of the records and database and shall charge and
collect a fee that shall recover the department's costs.</para>
<para>(7) In addition to the fees charged under subsection (1) of this section,
the department shall charge and collect an additional fee of one dollar for
any certified copy of the record of any birth or for any search made at the
applicant's request for access to or a certified copy of any such record,
whether or not the record is found on file with the department. Any county
containing a city of the metropolitan class which has an established city-county
or county health department pursuant to sections 71-1626 to 71-1636 which
has an established system of registering births and deaths shall charge and
collect in advance a fee of one dollar for any certified copy of the record
of any birth or for any search made at the applicant's request for such record,
whether or not the record is found on file with the county. All fees collected
under this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Nebraska Child Abuse Prevention Fund.</para>
<para>(8) The department shall not charge other state agencies the fees authorized
under subsections (1) and (7) of this section for automated review of any
certificates or abstracts of marriage. The department shall charge and collect
a fee from other state agencies for such automated review that will recover
the department's cost.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. VI, art. II, div. IX, &#167; 14, p. 784; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 73, &#167; 1, p. 272; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8244; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 166, &#167; 9, p. 451; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2416; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 140, &#167; 10, p. 554; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 71-2416; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 147, &#167; 1, p. 532; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-612; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 229, &#167; 1, p. 830; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 323, &#167; 1, p. 1180; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 410, &#167; 1, p. 1330; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 418, &#167; 6, p. 1338; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 419, &#167; 2, p. 1342; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 583, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 42, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 333, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 344, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 524; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 140; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 48, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1115, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 413; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB994, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>