<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-416"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-416</statuteno><catchline>Health clinic, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Health clinic means a facility where advice, counseling, diagnosis, treatment, surgery, care, or services relating to the preservation or maintenance of health are provided on an outpatient basis for a period of less than twenty-four consecutive hours to persons not residing or confined at such facility. Health clinic includes, but is not limited to, an ambulatory surgical center or a public health clinic.</para><para>(2) Health clinic does not include (a) a health care practitioner facility (i) unless such facility is an ambulatory surgical center, (ii) unless ten or more abortions, as defined in subdivision (1) of section 28-326, are performed during any one calendar week at such facility, or (iii) unless hemodialysis or labor and delivery services are provided at such facility, or (b) a facility which provides only routine health screenings, health education, or immunizations.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Public health clinic means the department, any county, city-county, or multicounty health department, or any private not-for-profit family planning clinic licensed as a health clinic;</para><para>(b) Routine health screenings means the collection of health data through the administration of a screening tool designed for a specific health problem, evaluation and comparison of results to referral criteria, and referral to appropriate sources of care, if indicated; and</para><para>(c) Screening tool means a simple interview or testing procedure to collect basic information on health status.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 16. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 