<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id137" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="71-830"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>71-830</statuteno><catchline>Behavioral Health Education Center;
created; administration; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Behavioral
Health Education Center is created beginning July 1, 2009, and shall be administered
by the University of Nebraska Medical Center.</para>
<para>(2) The center shall:</para>
<para>(a) Provide funds for two additional medical residents in a Nebraska-based
psychiatry program each year starting in 2010 until a total of eight additional
psychiatry residents are added in 2013. Beginning in 2011 and every year thereafter,
the center shall provide psychiatric residency training experiences that serve
rural Nebraska and other underserved areas. As part of his or her residency
training experiences, each center-funded resident shall participate in the
rural training for a minimum of one year. Beginning in 2012, a minimum of
two of the eight center-funded residents shall be active in the rural training
each year;</para>
<para>(b) Focus on the training of behavioral health professionals in telehealth
techniques, including taking advantage of a telehealth network that exists,
and other innovative means of care delivery in order to increase access to
behavioral health services for all Nebraskans;</para>
<para>(c) Analyze the geographic and demographic availability of Nebraska
behavioral health professionals, including psychiatrists, social workers,
community rehabilitation workers, psychologists, substance abuse counselors,
licensed mental health practitioners, behavioral analysts, peer support providers,
primary care physicians, nurses, nurse practitioners, and pharmacists;</para>
<para>(d) Prioritize the need for additional professionals by type and location;</para>
<para>(e) Establish learning collaborative partnerships with other higher
education institutions in the state, hospitals, law enforcement, community-based
agencies, and consumers and their families in order to develop evidence-based,
recovery-focused, interdisciplinary curriculum and training for behavioral
health professionals delivering behavioral health services in community-based
agencies, hospitals, and law enforcement. Development and dissemination of
such curriculum and training shall address the identified priority needs for
behavioral health professionals; and</para>
<para>(f) Beginning in 2011, develop two interdisciplinary behavioral health
training sites each year until a total of six sites have been developed. Four
of the six sites shall be in counties with a population of fewer than fifty
thousand inhabitants. Each site shall provide annual interdisciplinary training
opportunities for a minimum of three behavioral health professionals.</para>
<para>(3) No later than December 1, 2011, and no later than December 1 of
every odd-numbered year thereafter, the center shall prepare a report of its
activities under the Behavioral Health Workforce Act. The report shall be
filed electronically with
the Clerk of the Legislature and shall be provided electronically to any member of the Legislature
upon request.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB603, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 109.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>