<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-443"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-443</statuteno><catchline>Findings of noncompliance; review, notice; statement of compliance; procedure.</catchline><para>If the inspection report issued under section 71-440 contains findings of noncompliance by a health care facility or health care service with any applicable provisions of the Health Care Facility Licensure Act or rules and regulations adopted under the act, the department shall review such findings within twenty working days after such inspection. If the findings are supported by the evidence, the department shall proceed pursuant to sections 71-446 to 71-455, except that if the findings indicate one or more violations that create no imminent danger of death or serious physical harm and no direct or immediate adverse relationship to the health, safety, or security of the persons residing in or served by the facility or service, the department may send a letter to the facility or service requesting a statement of compliance. The letter shall include a description of each such violation, a request that the facility or service submit a statement of compliance within ten working days, and a notice that the department may take further steps if the statement of compliance is not submitted. The statement of compliance shall indicate any steps which have been or will be taken to correct each violation and the period of time estimated to be necessary to correct each violation. If the facility or service fails to submit and implement a statement of compliance which indicates a good faith effort to correct the violations, the department may proceed pursuant to sections 71-446 to 71-455.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 43. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 