<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-920" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-920</statuteno><catchline>Mentally ill and dangerous person; certificate of mental health professional; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, a mental health professional who, upon evaluation of a person admitted for emergency protective custody under section 71-919, determines that such person is mentally ill and dangerous shall execute a written certificate as provided in subsection (2) of this section not later than twenty-four hours after the completion of such evaluation. A copy of such certificate shall be immediately forwarded to the county attorney.</para><para>(2) The certificate shall be in writing and shall include the following information:</para><para>(a) The subject's name and address, if known;</para><para>(b) The name and address of the subject's spouse, legal counsel, guardian or conservator, and next-of-kin, if known;</para><para>(c) The name and address of anyone providing psychiatric or other care or treatment to the subject, if known;</para><para>(d) The name and address of any other person who may have knowledge of the subject's mental illness or substance dependence who may be called as a witness at a mental health board hearing with respect to the subject, if known;</para><para>(e) The name and address of the medical facility in which the subject is being held for emergency protective custody and evaluation;</para><para>(f) The name and work address of the certifying mental health professional;</para><para>(g) A statement by the certifying mental health professional that he or she has evaluated the subject since the subject was admitted for emergency protective custody and evaluation; and</para><para>(h) A statement by the certifying mental health professional that, in his or her clinical opinion, the subject is mentally ill and dangerous and the clinical basis for such opinion.</para><para>(3) In the case of a subject domiciled within Indian country who is taken into emergency protective custody by a law enforcement officer under tribal law, a mental health professional who, upon evaluation of such person, determines that such person is mentally ill and dangerous shall execute appropriate written documentation in a format provided by the tribe not later than twenty-four hours after the completion of such evaluation. A copy of such certificate shall be immediately forwarded to the person designated by the tribe.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1288, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>