<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-925"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-925</statuteno><catchline>Burden of proof; mental health board; hearing; orders authorized; conditions; rehearing.</catchline><para>(1) The state has the burden to prove by clear and convincing evidence that (a) the subject is mentally ill and dangerous and (b) neither voluntary hospitalization nor other treatment alternatives less restrictive of the subject's liberty than inpatient or outpatient treatment ordered by the mental health board are available or would suffice to prevent the harm described in section 71-908.</para><para>(2) If the mental health board finds that the subject is not mentally ill and dangerous, the board shall dismiss the petition and order the unconditional discharge of the subject.</para><para>(3) If the mental health board finds that the subject is mentally ill and dangerous but that voluntary hospitalization or other treatment alternatives less restrictive of the subject's liberty than treatment ordered by the mental health board are available and would suffice to prevent the harm described in section 71-908, the board shall (a) dismiss the petition and order the unconditional discharge of the subject or (b) suspend further proceedings for a period of up to ninety days to permit the subject to obtain voluntary treatment. At any time during such ninety-day period, the county attorney may apply to the board for reinstatement of proceedings with respect to the subject, and after notice to the subject, the subject's counsel, and the subject's legal guardian or conservator, if any, the board shall hear the application. If no such application is filed or pending at the conclusion of such ninety-day period, the board shall dismiss the petition and order the unconditional discharge of the subject.</para><para>(4) If the subject admits the allegations of the petition or the mental health board finds that the subject is mentally ill and dangerous and that neither voluntary hospitalization nor other treatment alternatives less restrictive of the subject's liberty than inpatient or outpatient treatment ordered by the board are available or would suffice to prevent the harm described in section 71-908, the board shall, within forty-eight hours, (a) order the subject to receive outpatient treatment or (b) order the subject to receive inpatient treatment. If the subject is ordered by the board to receive inpatient treatment, the order shall commit the subject to the custody of the Department of Health and Human Services for such treatment.</para><para>(5) A subject who (a) is ordered by the mental health board to receive inpatient treatment and (b) has not yet been admitted for such treatment pursuant to such order may petition for a rehearing by the mental health board based on improvement in the subject's condition such that inpatient treatment ordered by the board would no longer be necessary or appropriate.</para><para>(6) A treatment order by the mental health board under this section shall represent the appropriate available treatment alternative that imposes the least possible restraint upon the liberty of the subject. The board shall consider all treatment alternatives, including any treatment program or conditions suggested by the subject, the subject's counsel, or other interested person. Inpatient hospitalization or custody shall only be considered as a treatment alternative of last resort. The county attorney and the subject may jointly offer a proposed treatment order for adoption by the board. The board may enter the proposed order without a full hearing.</para><para>(7) The mental health board may request the assistance of the Department of Health and Human Services or any other person or public or private entity to advise the board prior to the entry of a treatment order pursuant to this section and may require the subject to submit to reasonable psychiatric and psychological evaluation to assist the board in preparing such order. Any mental health professional conducting such evaluation at the request of the mental health board shall be compensated by the county or counties served by such board at a rate determined by the district judge and reimbursed for mileage at the rate provided in section 81-1176.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 806, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 501, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 95, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 102; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 83-1037; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 45. </para></source><annotation><para>The board of mental health's conclusion that a person before it is a mentally ill dangerous person and that a less restrictive alternative is not available or would not suffice to prevent the harm described in section 83-1009 must be supported by clear and convincing evidence. In re Interest of Vance, 242 Neb. 109, 493 N.W.2d 620 (1992).</para><para>In determining whether a person is dangerous, the focus must be on the subject's condition at the time of the hearing, not the date the subject of the commitment hearing was initially taken into custody. In re Interest of Rasmussen, 236 Neb. 572, 462 N.W.2d 621 (1990).</para><para>Statute requires proof that person is dangerous before he will be subject to involuntary confinement. Richards v. Douglas County, 213 Neb. 313, 328 N.W.2d 783 (1983).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (6) of this section, a mental health board, after considering all treatment alternatives including any treatment program or conditions suggested by the subject, the subject's counsel, or other interested person, can commit a person for inpatient treatment; such a treatment order shall represent the appropriate available treatment alternative that imposes the least possible restraint upon the liberty of the subject. Inpatient hospitalization or custody shall only be considered as a treatment alternative of last resort. In re Interest of Dennis W., 14 Neb. App. 827, 717 N.W.2d 488 (2006).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>