<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id119" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="71-827"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-827</statuteno><catchline>Children's Behavioral Health Oversight
Committee of the Legislature; created; members; duties; meetings; report.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Children's Behavioral Health Oversight Committee of the Legislature
is created as a special legislative committee. The committee shall consist
of nine members of the Legislature appointed by the Executive Board of the
Legislative Council as follows: (a) Two members of the Appropriations Committee
of the Legislature, (b) two members of the Health and Human Services Committee
of the Legislature, (c) two members of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature,
and (d) three members of the Legislature who are not members of such committees.
The Children's Behavioral Health Oversight Committee shall elect a chairperson
and vice-chairperson from among its members. The executive board shall appoint
members of the committee no later than thirty days after May 23, 2009, and
within the first six legislative days of the regular legislative session in
2011. The committee and this section terminate on December 31, 2012.</para>
<para>(2) The committee shall monitor the effect of implementation of the
Children and Family Behavioral Health Support Act and other child welfare
and juvenile justice initiatives by the department related to the provision
of behavioral health services to children and their families.</para>
<para>(3) The committee shall meet at least quarterly with representatives
of the Division of Behavioral Health and the Division of Children and Family
Services of the Department of Health and Human Services and with other interested
parties and may meet at other times at the call of the chairperson.</para>
<para>(4) Staff support for the committee shall be provided by existing legislative
staff as directed by the executive board. The committee may request the executive
board to hire consultants that the committee deems necessary to carry out
the purposes of the committee under this section.</para>
<para>(5) The committee shall provide a report to the Governor and the Legislature
no later than December 1 of each year. The
report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically. The
report shall include, but not be limited to, findings and recommendations
relating to the provision of behavioral health services to children and their
families. The final report
of the committee shall be provided to the Health and Human Services Committee
of the Legislature on or before September 15, 2012.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB603, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 16.</para><terminationdate>December 31, 2012</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>