<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id43">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id45" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="71-963"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-963</statuteno><catchline>Firearm-related disabilities; petition
to remove; mental health board; review hearing; evidence; decision; appeal;
petition granted; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Upon release from commitment or treatment, a person
who, because of a mental health-related commitment or adjudication occurring
under the laws of this state, is subject to the disability provisions of 18
U.S.C. 922(d)(4) and (g)(4) or is disqualified from obtaining a certificate
to purchase, lease, rent, or receive transfer of a handgun under section 69-2404
or a permit to carry a concealed handgun under the Concealed Handgun Permit
Act may petition the mental health board to remove such disabilities.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Upon
the filing of the petition, the subject may request and, if the request is
made, shall be entitled to, a review hearing by the mental health board. The
mental health board shall grant a petition filed under subsection (1) of this
section if the mental health board determines that:</para><para>(i) The subject will
not be likely to act in a manner dangerous to public safety; and</para>
<para>(ii) The
granting of the relief would not be contrary to the public interest.</para>
<para>(b) In determining
whether to remove the subject's firearm-related disabilities, the mental health
board shall receive and consider evidence upon the following:</para>
<para>(i) The circumstances
surrounding the subject's mental health commitment or adjudication;</para>
<para>(ii) The
subject's record, which shall include, at a minimum, the subject's mental
health and criminal history records;</para><para>(iii) The subject's reputation, developed,
at a minimum, through character witness statements, testimony, or other character
evidence; and</para><para>(iv) Changes in the subject's condition, treatment, treatment history,
or circumstances relevant to the relief sought.</para><para>(3) If a decision is
made by the mental health board to remove the subject's firearm-related disabilities,
the clerks of the various courts shall immediately send as soon as practicable
but within thirty days an order to the Nebraska State Patrol and the Department
of Health and Human Services, in a form and in a manner prescribed by the
Department of Health and Human Services and the Nebraska State Patrol, stating
its findings, which shall include a statement that, in the opinion of the
mental health board, (a) the subject is not likely to act in a manner that
is dangerous to public safety and (b) removing the subject's firearm-related
disabilities will not be contrary to the public interest.</para>
<para>(4) The subject
may appeal a denial of the requested relief to the district court, and review
on appeal shall be de novo.</para><para>(5) If a petition is granted under this
section, the commitment or adjudication for which relief is granted shall
be deemed not to have occurred for purposes of section 69-2404 and the Concealed
Handgun Permit Act and, pursuant to section 105(b) of Public Law 110-180,
for purposes of 18 U.S.C. 922(d)(4) and (g)(4).</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB512, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Concealed Handgun Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 69-2427.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>