<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id274">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id276" statutenumber="71-434"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-434</statuteno><catchline id="id279">License fees.</catchline><para>(1) Licensure activities under the Health Care Facility Licensure
Act shall be funded by license fees. An applicant for an initial or renewal
license under section 71-433 shall pay a license fee as provided in this section.</para>
<para>(2) License fees shall include a base fee of fifty dollars
and an additional fee based on:</para>
<para>(a) Variable costs to the department of inspections, architectural
plan reviews, and receiving and investigating complaints, including staff
salaries, travel, and other similar direct and indirect costs;</para>
<para>(b) The number of beds available to persons residing at the
health care facility;</para>
<para>(c) The program capacity of the health care facility or health
care service; or</para>
<para>(d) Other relevant factors as determined by the department.</para>
<para>Such additional fee shall be no more than two thousand six
hundred dollars for a hospital or a health clinic operating as an ambulatory
surgical center, no more than two thousand dollars for an assisted-living
facility, a health clinic providing hemodialysis or labor and delivery services,
an intermediate care facility, an intermediate care facility for persons with developmental disabilities, a
nursing facility, or a skilled nursing facility, no more than one thousand
dollars for home health agencies, hospice services, and centers for the developmentally
disabled, and no more than seven hundred dollars for all other health care
facilities and health care services.</para>
<para>(3) If the licensure application is denied, the license fee
shall be returned to the applicant, except that the department may retain
up to twenty-five dollars as an administrative fee and may retain the entire
license fee if an inspection has been completed prior to such denial.</para>
<para>(4) The department shall also collect the fee provided in
subsection (1) of this section for reinstatement of a license that has lapsed
or has been suspended or revoked. The department shall collect a fee of ten
dollars for a duplicate original license.</para>
<para>(5) The department shall collect a fee from any applicant
or licensee requesting an informal conference with a representative peer review
organization under section 71-452 to cover all costs and expenses associated
with such conference.</para>
<para>(6) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
for the establishment of license fees under this section.</para>
<para>(7) The department shall remit all license fees collected
under this section to the State Treasurer for credit to the Health and Human
Services Cash Fund. License fees collected under this section shall only be
used for activities related to the licensure of health care facilities and
health care services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 415, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 246, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB203, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 371; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 28.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>