<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id00" statutenumber="71-208"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-208</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Barber school or college; requirements for approval; course of instruction; standards set by rules and regulations.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that, through licensing of barber schools, the Board of Barber Examiners approves barbering programs which lead to a certificate or diploma in Nebraska. No barber school or college shall be approved by the board unless (1)(a) a barber school or college that operates as a postsecondary barber school or college requires, as a prerequisite to admission, high school graduation or its equivalent as determined by successfully passing a general educational development test or (b) a barber school or college that does not operate as a postsecondary barber school or college requires, as a prerequisite to graduation from such school or college, high school graduation or its equivalent as determined by successfully passing a general educational development test, (2) as a prerequisite to graduation it requires a course of instruction of not less than one thousand eight hundred hours, to be completed in not more than ten hours in any one working day, and (3) the barber school or college meets the standards of the Barber Act and any rules and regulations of the board. Such course of instruction shall include scientific fundamentals for barbering, hygiene, massaging, sterilization, haircutting, and shaving, except that when a barber school or college is a part of a high school accredited by the State Board of Education or the University of Nebraska, the Board of Barber Examiners shall provide in its rules and regulations that credit in the barber school or college shall be given for hours spent and courses pursued in the high school and that credit shall be given for courses in barbering taken in high school prior to formal enrollment in such barber school or college.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 163, &#167; 6, p. 429; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 154, &#167; 5, p. 536; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2008; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-208; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 166, &#167; 1(1), p. 532; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 294, &#167; 3, p. 1054; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 409, &#167; 10, p. 1319; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1020, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 722, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB842, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB731, &#167; 82. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>