<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-223.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-223.04</statuteno><catchline>Class of instruction; temporary permit; issuance; requirements; fee; period valid; bond.</catchline><para>Any person who desires to conduct any class or classes of instruction, other than a free demonstration, shall, before engaging in such instruction, make application to the Board of Barber Examiners for a temporary permit authorizing the applicant to conduct such class or classes. In order to be qualified for such temporary license, the applicant must (1) hold a valid license as a registered barber in some state in the United States; (2) have filed with the Board of Barber Examiners an application setting forth the type of classes to be conducted, the period of time the classes will be conducted, the place in which such classes are to be conducted, and the amount of tuition, if any, to be charged; and (3) pay the fee set by the board for issuance of a temporary permit. Upon being satisfied that the applicant does hold a valid license as a barber in some state in the United States, is qualified to conduct such classes, and has made arrangements to conduct such classes in facilities which otherwise meet the requirements as to health and sanitation required of a barber school in the State of Nebraska, the board shall issue a temporary license to such applicant to permit the conducting of such classes. The license shall be valid only for the classes and times set forth in the application. Before such application is delivered to an applicant other than a barber or barber school or college currently licensed in Nebraska, the applicant must post with the Board of Barber Examiners a good and sufficient surety bond, issued by a reputable bonding company licensed to do business in the State of Nebraska, for the benefit of the persons taking such class or classes in a sufficient amount to assure to such students a refund of any portion of their tuition paid but not used, in the event that such class or classes shall discontinue operation for any reason prior to the time that all of such classes have been conducted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 1020, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 722, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 