<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id800"> <sectno id="id801" opdate=" ">Sec. 53.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id802" statutenumber="71-201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id804">71-201</statuteno><catchline id="id805">Practice of barbering; barber shop; barber school; license required; renewal; disciplinary actions; prohibited acts.</catchline> <para>No person shall practice or attempt to practice barbering without a license issued pursuant to the Barber Act by the board. It shall be unlawful to operate a barber shop unless it is at all times under the direct supervision and management of a licensed barber.</para> <para>No person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation shall operate a barber shop or barber school until a license has been obtained for that purpose from the board. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. No person shall lease space on the premises of a barber shop to engage in the practice of barbering as an independent contractor or a self-employed person without obtaining a booth rental permit as provided in section 71-219.05. All barber shop licenses and booth rental permits shall be issued on or before June 30 of each even-numbered year, shall be effective as of July 1 of each even-numbered year, shall be valid for two years, and shall expire on June 30 of the next succeeding even-numbered year.</para> <para>Any barber shop which fails to renew its license or any person who fails to renew his or her booth rental permit on or before the expiration date may renew such license or booth rental permit by payment of the renewal fee and a late renewal fee established by the board within sixty days after such date or such other time period as the board establishes.</para> <para>Any barber shop or barber school license and any booth rental permit may be suspended, revoked, or denied renewal by the board for violation of any provision of the statutes or any rule or regulation of the board pertaining to the operation or sanitation of barber shops, barber schools, or booths under a booth rental permit after due notice and hearing before the board.</para> <para>No person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation shall use the title of barber or barber shop or indicate in any way that such person or entity offers barbering services unless such person or entity is licensed pursuant to the act. No person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation shall hold itself out as a barber shop or indicate in any way that such person or entity offers barbering services unless such person or entity and the personnel who purport to offer barbering services in association with such person or entity are licensed pursuant to the act.</para><para>No person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation shall display a barber pole or use a barber pole or the image of a barber pole in its advertising unless such person or entity is licensed to provide barbering services pursuant to the act and the display or use of such barber pole or barber pole image is to indicate that the person or entity is offering barbering services.</para></amendatorysection> </section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 163, &#167; 1, p. 427; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 154, &#167; 1, p. 533; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2001; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-201; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 294, &#167; 1, p. 1053; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 409, &#167; 2, p. 1315; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 417, &#167; 1, p. 1329; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1020, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 722, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 87, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 421; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 226, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 481; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 164; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167;  53.</para><effectivedate>August 30, 2009</effectivedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc> 