<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id78" statutenumber="71-808"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>71-808</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Regional behavioral health authority; established; regional governing board; matching funds; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A regional behavioral health authority shall be established in each behavioral health region by counties acting under provisions of the Interlocal Cooperation Act. Each regional behavioral health authority shall be governed by a regional governing board consisting of one county board member from each county in the region. Board members shall serve for staggered terms of three years and until their successors are appointed and qualified. Board members shall serve without compensation but shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(2) The regional governing board shall appoint a regional administrator who shall be responsible for the administration and management of the regional behavioral health authority. Each regional behavioral health authority shall encourage and facilitate the involvement of consumers in all aspects of service planning and delivery within the region and shall coordinate such activities with the office of consumer affairs within the division. Each regional behavioral health authority shall establish and utilize a regional advisory committee consisting of consumers, providers, and other interested parties and may establish and utilize such other task forces, subcommittees, or other committees as it deems necessary and appropriate to carry out its duties under this section.</para><para>(3) Each county in a behavioral health region shall provide funding for the operation of the behavioral health authority and for the provision of behavioral health services in the region. The total amount of funding provided by counties under this subsection shall be equal to one dollar for every three dollars from the General Fund. The division shall annually certify the total amount of county matching funds to be provided. At least forty percent of such amount shall consist of local and county tax revenue, and the remainder shall consist of other nonfederal sources. The regional governing board of each behavioral health authority, in consultation with all counties in the region, shall determine the amount of funding to be provided by each county under this subsection. For purposes of calculating the amount of county matching funds under this subsection, the amount of General Funds shall exclude:</para><para>(a) An amount equal to two million five hundred ninety-nine thousand six hundred sixty dollars from the General Fund each year, beginning on July 1, 2021;</para><para>(b) Any General Funds transferred from regional centers for the provision of community-based behavioral health services after July 1, 2004; and</para><para>(c) Funds received by a regional behavioral health authority for the provision of behavioral health services to children under section 71-826.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB603, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB384, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>April 27, 2021</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>