<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id942"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id944" statutenumber="71-604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id946">71-604</statuteno><catchline id="id947">Birth certificate; preparation and filing.</catchline><para>(1) A certificate for each live birth which occurs in the State of Nebraska shall be filed on a standard Nebraska certificate form. Such certificate shall be filed with the department within five business days after the birth.</para> <para>(2) When a birth occurs in an institution or en route thereto, the person in charge of the institution or his or her authorized designee shall obtain the personal data, prepare the certificate which shall include the name, title, and address of the attendant, certify that the child was born alive at the place and time and on the date stated either by standard procedure or by an approved electronic process, and file the certificate. The physician, physician assistant, or other person in attendance shall provide the medical information required for the certificate within seventy-two hours after the birth.</para> <para>(3) When a birth occurs outside an institution, the certificate of birth shall be prepared and filed by one of the following:</para> <para>(a) The physician or physician assistant in attendance at or immediately after the birth;</para> <para>(b) The father, the mother, or, in the absence of the father and the inability of the mother, the person in charge of the premises where the birth occurred; or</para> <para>(c) Any other person in attendance at or immediately after the birth.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. VI, art. II, div. IX, &#167; 5, p. 781; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 253, &#167; 1, p. 863; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8232; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 166, &#167; 2, p. 448; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2404; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-604; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 418, &#167; 2, p. 1335; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 42, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 344, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 886, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 135; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 403; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 67.</para></source><annotation><para>In the light of the legislative history of laws pertaining to osteopathy the term physician, used in this section, was intended to include regularly licensed osteopathic physicians. State ex rel. Johnson v. Wagner, 139 Neb. 471, 297 N.W. 906 (1941).</para></annotation>  </law> </legaldoc> 