<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id6"  statutenumber="71-503.02" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>71-503.02</statuteno><catchline>Chlamydia, gonorrhea, or trichomoniasis; prescription oral antibiotic drugs; powers of medical professionals; restrictions.</catchline><para>If a physician, a physician assistant, a nurse practitioner, or a certified nurse midwife licensed under the Uniform Credentialing Act diagnoses a patient as having chlamydia, gonorrhea, or trichomoniasis, the physician may prescribe, provide drug samples of, or dispense pursuant to section 38-2850, and the physician assistant, nurse practitioner, or certified nurse midwife may prescribe or provide drug samples of, prescription oral antibiotic drugs to that patient's sexual partner or partners without examination of that patient's partner or partners. Adequate directions for use and medication guides, where applicable, shall be provided along with additional prescription oral antibiotic drugs for any additional partner. The physician, physician assistant, nurse practitioner, or certified nurse midwife shall at the same time provide written information about chlamydia, gonorrhea, and trichomoniasis to the patient for the patient to provide to the partner or partners. The oral antibiotic drugs prescribed, provided, or dispensed pursuant to this section must be stored, dispensed, and labeled in accordance with federal and state pharmacy laws and regulations. Prescriptions for the patient's sexual partner or partners must include the partner's name. If the infected patient is unwilling or unable to deliver such prescription oral antibiotic drugs to his or her sexual partner or partners, such physician may prescribe, provide, or dispense pursuant to section 38-2850 and such physician assistant, nurse practitioner, or certified nurse midwife may prescribe or provide samples of the prescription oral antibiotic drugs for delivery to such partner, if such practitioner has sufficient locating information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB528, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB62, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>