<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-504</statuteno><catchline>Sexually transmitted diseases; minors; treatment without consent of parent; expenses.</catchline><para>The chief medical officer as designated in section 81-3115, or local director of health, if a physician, or his or her agent, or any physician, upon consultation by any person as a patient, shall, with the consent of such person who is hereby granted the right of giving such consent, make or cause to be made a diagnostic examination for sexually transmitted diseases and prescribe for and treat such person for sexually transmitted diseases including prophylactic treatment for exposure to sexually transmitted diseases whenever such person is suspected of having a sexually transmitted disease or contact with anyone having a sexually transmitted disease. All such examinations and treatment may be performed without the consent of or notification to the parent, parents, guardian, or any other person having custody of such person. In any such case, the chief medical officer, or local director of health, if a physician, or his or her agent, or the physician shall incur no civil or criminal liability by reason of having made such diagnostic examination or rendered such treatment, but such immunity shall not apply to any negligent acts or omissions. The chief medical officer or local director of health, if a physician, or his or her agent, or the physician shall incur no civil or criminal liability by reason of any adverse reaction to medication administered if reasonable care is taken to elicit from any such person who is under twenty years of age any history of sensitivity or previous adverse reaction to medication. Parents shall be liable for expenses of such treatment to minors under their custody. In the event such person is affected with a sexually transmitted disease, the chief medical officer or local director of health may cause an interview of the person by a sexually transmitted disease investigator to secure the names of sexual contacts so that appropriate investigation can be made in an effort to locate and eliminate sources of infection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1096, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1986), &#167; 71-1121; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1012, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 495; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 197, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 383.</para></source></law></legaldoc>