<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-934"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-934</statuteno><catchline>Outpatient treatment; hearing by board; warrant for custody of subject; subject's rights; board determination.</catchline><para>The mental health board shall, upon motion of the county attorney, or may, upon its own motion, hold a hearing to determine whether a subject ordered by the board to receive outpatient treatment can be adequately and safely served by the individualized treatment plan for such subject on file with the board. The mental health board may issue a warrant directing any law enforcement officer in the state to take custody of the subject and directing the sheriff or other suitable person to transport the subject to a treatment facility or public or private hospital with available capacity specified by the board where he or she will be held pending such hearing. No person may be held in custody under this section for more than seven days except upon a continuance granted by the board. At the time of execution of the warrant, the sheriff or other suitable person designated by the board shall personally serve upon the subject, the subject's counsel, and the subject's legal guardian or conservator, if any, a notice of the time and place fixed for the hearing, a copy of the motion for hearing, and a list of the rights provided by the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act. The subject shall be accorded all the rights guaranteed to a subject by the act. Following the hearing, the board shall determine whether outpatient treatment will be continued, modified, or ended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 498, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 107; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 83-1045.02; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 54. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former law, language in this section providing that no person may be held in custody pending a hearing for a period exceeding 7 days is directory, not mandatory, because of the purposes of this section and the lack of a remedy for violation of this section. In re Interest of E.M., 13 Neb. App. 287, 691 N.W.2d 550 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>