<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-510" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-510</statuteno><catchline>Emergency services provider; public safety official; significant exposure; testing; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) The patient or individual shall be informed that he or she has the right to consent to the test for presence of an infectious disease or condition and that if the patient or individual refuses the test, such refusal will be communicated to the emergency services provider or public safety official.</para><para>(2) If the patient or individual is unconscious or incapable of signing an informed consent form, the consent may be obtained from the patient's or individual's next of kin or legal guardian.</para><para>(3) If an emergency services provider has a significant exposure which, in the opinion of the designated physician, could involve the transmission of hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency virus, the patient's attending physician shall initiate the necessary diagnostic blood tests of the patient. If the patient or patient's representative refuses to grant consent for such test and a sample of the patient's blood is available, the blood shall be tested for hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency virus. If the patient or patient's guardian refuses to grant consent and a sample of the patient's blood is not available, the patient's refusal shall be communicated to the designated physician who shall inform the emergency services provider. The emergency services provider may petition the district court for an order mandating that the test be performed.</para><para>(4) If a public safety official believes he or she has had a significant exposure while performing his or her duties, other than those as an emergency services provider, which, in the opinion of a physician, could involve exposure to an infectious disease or condition, the public safety official or the provider agency which employs or directs him or her may (a) request the individual who may have transmitted the infectious disease or condition to consent to having the necessary diagnostic blood tests performed or (b) if the individual refuses to consent to such tests, petition the district court for an order mandating that the necessary diagnostic blood tests of such individual be performed.</para><para>(5) If a patient or individual is deceased, no consent shall be required to test for the presence of an infectious disease or condition.</para><para>(6) If the State of Nebraska serves as guardian for the patient or individual and refuses to grant consent to test for the presence of an infectious disease or condition, the state as guardian (a) shall be subject to the jurisdiction of the district court upon the filing of a petition for an order mandating that the test be performed and (b) shall not have sovereign immunity in such suit or proceeding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 157, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 55, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1115, &#167; 37. </para></source></law></legaldoc>