
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-468"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-468</statuteno><catchline>Onsite vaccinations for influenza and pneumococcal disease.</catchline><para>In order to prevent, detect, and control pneumonia and influenza outbreaks in Nebraska:</para><para>(1) Each general acute hospital and intermediate care facility shall annually, beginning no later than October 1 and ending on the following April 1, offer onsite vaccinations for influenza and pneumococcal disease to all residents and to all inpatients prior to discharge, pursuant to procedures of the facility and in accordance with the recommendations of the advisory committee on immunization practices of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention of the United States Public Health Service of the United States Department of Health and Human Services as the recommendations existed on January 1, 2017; and</para><para>(2) Each nursing facility and skilled nursing facility shall annually, beginning no later than October 1 and ending on the following April 1, offer onsite vaccinations for (a) influenza and pneumococcal disease to all residents and (b) influenza to all employees, pursuant to procedures of the facility and in accordance with the recommendations of the advisory committee on immunization practices of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention of the United States Public Health Service of the United States Department of Health and Human Services as the recommendations existed on January 1, 2017. This section shall not apply in individual cases when contraindicated or if a national shortage of the vaccine exists. Nothing in this section shall be construed to require any facility listed in this section to cover the cost of a vaccination provided pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1077, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB859, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB267, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>