<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id660"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-477"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-477</statuteno><catchline>Rural emergency hospital; license; eligibility; application; operation; requirements; original license; inactive.</catchline><para>(1) A facility shall be eligible to apply for a license as a rural emergency hospital if such facility is:</para><para>(a) Licensed as a critical access hospital;</para><para>(b) Licensed as a general hospital with not more than fifty licensed beds located in a county in a rural area as defined in section 1886(d)(2)(D) of the federal Social Security Act; or</para><para>(c) Licensed as a general hospital with not more than fifty licensed beds that is deemed as being located in a rural area pursuant to section 1886(d)(8)(E) of the federal Social Security Act.</para><para>(2) A facility applying for licensure as a rural emergency hospital shall include with the application:</para><para>(a) An action plan for initiating rural emergency hospital services, including a detailed transition plan that lists the specific services that the facility will retain, modify, add, and discontinue;</para><para>(b) A description of services that the facility intends to provide on an outpatient basis; and</para><para>(c) Such other information as required by rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department.</para><para>(3) A rural emergency hospital shall not have inpatient beds, except that such hospital may have a unit that is a distinct part of such hospital and that is licensed as a skilled nursing facility to provide post-hospital extended care services.</para><para>(4) A rural emergency hospital may own and operate an entity that provides ambulance services.</para><para>(5) A licensed general hospital or critical access hospital that applies for and receives licensure as a rural emergency hospital and elects to operate as a rural emergency hospital shall retain its original license as a general hospital or critical access hospital. Such original license shall remain inactive while the rural emergency hospital license is in effect.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB697, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>