<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id479"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-814"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-814</statuteno><catchline>State Advisory Committee on Mental Health Services; created; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The State Advisory Committee on Mental Health Services is created. Members of the committee shall have a demonstrated interest and commitment and specialized knowledge, experience, or expertise relating to the provision of mental health services in the State of Nebraska. The committee shall consist of twenty-three members appointed by the Governor as follows: (a) One regional governing board member, (b) one regional administrator, (c) twelve consumers of behavioral health services or their family members, (d) two providers of behavioral health services, (e) two representatives from the State Department of Education, including one representative from the Division of Vocational Rehabilitation of the State Department of Education, (f) three representatives from the Department of Health and Human Services representing mental health, social services, and medicaid, (g) one representative from the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice, and (h) one representative from the Housing Office of the Community and Rural Development Division of the Department of Economic Development.</para><para>(2) The committee shall be responsible to the division and shall (a) serve as the state's mental health planning council as required by Public Law 102-321, (b) conduct regular meetings, (c) provide advice and assistance to the division relating to the provision of mental health services and, beginning July 1, 2026, substance use disorder services in the State of Nebraska, including, but not limited to, the development, implementation, provision, and funding of organized peer support services, (d) promote the interests of consumers and their families, including, but not limited to, their inclusion and involvement in all aspects of services design, planning, implementation, provision, education, evaluation, and research, (e) provide reports as requested by the division, and (f) engage in such other activities as directed or authorized by the division.</para><para>(3) Beginning July 1, 2026, the State Advisory Committee on Mental Health Services shall also perform the duties of the State Advisory Committee on Substance Abuse Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 460; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB346, &#167; 35. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>