 <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id851"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id853" statutenumber="71-219"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id855">71-219</statuteno><catchline id="id856">Barbering fees; set by board; enumerated.</catchline><para>The board shall set the fees to be paid:</para> <para>(1) By an applicant for an examination to determine his or her fitness to receive a license to practice barbering or a registration as a barber instructor and for the issuance of the license or registration;</para> <para>(2) By an applicant for registration as an assistant barber instructor;</para> <para>(3) For the renewal of a license to practice barbering and for restoration of an inactive license;</para> <para>(4) For the renewal of a registration to practice as a barber instructor and for the restoration of an inactive registration;</para> <para>(5) For renewal of a registration to practice as an assistant barber instructor;</para> <para>(6) For late renewal of a license issued under the Barber Act;</para> <para>(7) For an application for a license to establish a barber shop or barber school and for the issuance of a license;</para> <para>(8) For the transfer of license or change of ownership of a barber shop or barber school;</para> <para>(9) For renewal of a barber license, barber instructor registration, barber shop license, or barber school license;</para> <para>(10) For an application for a temporary license to conduct classes of instruction in barbering;</para> <para>(11) For an affidavit for purposes of reciprocity or for issuance of a certification of licensure for purposes of reciprocity;</para> <para>(12) For an application for licensure without examination pursuant to section 71-239.01 and for the issuance of a license pursuant to such section;</para> <para>(13) For issuance of a booth rental permit under section 71-219.05;</para><para>(14) For the sale of listings or labels; and</para> <para>(15) For a returned check because of insufficient funds or no funds.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 163, &#167; 16, p. 433; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 154, &#167; 8, p. 537; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2020; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 490; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 71-2020; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-219; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 238, &#167; 6, p. 827; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 294, &#167; 7, p. 1056; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 409, &#167; 23, p. 1324; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 417, &#167; 6, p. 1332; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1020, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1183, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 66, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 722, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 87, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 226, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 57.</para></source><annotation><para>Repeal of former act was valid. Day v. Walker, 124 Neb. 500, 247 N.W. 350 (1933).</para></annotation>  </law> </legaldoc> 