<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-465"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>71-465</statuteno><catchline>Moratorium on new hospital licenses;
health care in Nebraska; Health and Human Services Committee of Legislature;
study; report.</catchline><para>(1)
The Legislature finds that Nebraska's general acute and critical access hospitals
provide a foundation of health care throughout the state. This long-established
means of providing health care is changing. Because health care delivery is
evolving, it is important to assess needs in Nebraska and determine whether
licensure and regulation should be changed to reflect current and future practices.</para>
<para>(2) The department
shall not accept an application for or issue a license for a new hospital
beginning on April 15, 2010, and continuing through September 15, 2011, except
that this prohibition shall not apply to an application for or issuance of
a license as a critical access hospital or an application for or issuance
of a license for any hospital which has begun construction prior to May 1,
2010.</para><para>(3) The Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature shall
study health care in Nebraska. The study shall include, but not be limited
to:</para><para>(a) A comparison of the roles of Nebraska's general acute hospitals,
critical access hospitals, ambulatory surgical centers, and other limited
service facilities, such as physician-owned hospitals and investor-owned hospitals,
and the impact of such hospitals, centers, and facilities on access to services,
quality of health care, and cost, including medicaid costs and insurance premiums;</para>
<para>(b) Compliance
with the federal Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act, 42 U.S.C.
1395dd, as such act existed on January 1, 2010;</para><para>(c) Referral practices;</para>
<para>(d) Ownership
disclosure;</para><para>(e) Uncompensated and under-compensated patient care;</para>
<para>(f) Joint ventures
among or between hospitals, physicians, and investors;</para>
<para>(g) Reinvestment
in facilities;</para><para>(h) Examination and definition of community benefits;</para>
<para>(i) Clarification
and definition of limited service facilities, such as physician-owned hospitals
and investor-owned hospitals, and other definitions as needed; and</para>
<para>(j) The impact
of federal health care reform on the items in subdivisions (a) through (i)
of this subsection.</para><para>(4) The committee shall seek information from resources, including,
but not limited to, physicians; representatives of hospitals, ambulatory surgical
centers, physician-owned hospitals, investor-owned hospitals, public health
agencies, the department, and allied professions such as behavioral health
service providers, nurses, pharmacists, and emergency care providers; businesses;
consumers; insurers; communities; the Legislative Fiscal Analyst; and the
office of Legislative Research.</para><para>(5) The committee shall report its findings
to the Legislature by December 31, 2010.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB999, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>