<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-806"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>71-806</statuteno><catchline>Division; powers and duties; rules
and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The division shall act as the chief
behavioral health authority for the State of Nebraska and shall direct the
administration and coordination of the public behavioral health system, including,
but not limited to: (a) Administration and management of the division, regional
centers, and any other facilities and programs operated by the division; (b)
integration and coordination of the public behavioral health system; (c) comprehensive
statewide planning for the provision of an appropriate array of community-based
behavioral health services and continuum of care; (d) coordination and oversight
of regional behavioral health authorities, including approval of regional
budgets and audits of regional behavioral health authorities; (e) development
and management of data and information systems; (f) prioritization and approval
of all expenditures of funds received and administered by the division, including: The establishment of rates to be paid; reimbursement methodologies for behavioral
health services; methodologies
to be used by regional behavioral health authorities in determining a consumer's
financial eligibility as provided in subsection (2) of section 71-809; and
fees and copays to
be paid by consumers of such services; (g) cooperation with the department
in the licensure and regulation of behavioral health professionals, programs,
and facilities; (h) cooperation with the department in the provision of behavioral
health services under the medical assistance program; (i) audits of behavioral
health programs and services; and (j) promotion of activities in research
and education to improve the quality of behavioral health services, recruitment
and retention of behavioral health professionals, and access to behavioral
health programs and services.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to carry out the Nebraska Behavioral Health Services Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 456; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB871, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>