<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-816"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">71-816</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Legislative findings; State Committee on Problem Gambling; created; members; duties; division; duties; joint report.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that the main sources of funding for the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund are the Charitable Gaming Operations Fund as provided in section 9-1,101 and the State Lottery Operation Trust Fund as provided in section 9-812 and Article III, section 24, of the Constitution of Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund be used primarily for counseling and treatment services for problem gamblers and their families who are residents of Nebraska.</para> <para>(2) The State Committee on Problem Gambling is created. Members of the committee shall have a demonstrated interest and commitment and specialized knowledge, experience, or expertise relating to problem gambling in the State of Nebraska. The committee shall consist of twelve members appointed by the Governor and shall include at least three consumers of problem gambling services. The committee shall appoint one of its members as chairperson of the committee and other officers as it deems appropriate. The committee shall conduct regular meetings and shall meet upon the call of the chairperson or a majority of its members to conduct its official business.</para> <para>(3) The committee shall develop and recommend to the division guidelines and standards for the distribution and disbursement of money in the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund. Such guidelines and standards shall be based on nationally recognized standards for problem gamblers assistance programs.</para> <para>(4) In addition, the committee shall develop recommendations regarding (a) the evaluation and approval process for provider applications and contracts for treatment funding from the Compulsive Gamblers Assistance Fund, (b) the review and use of evaluation data, (c) the use and expenditure of funds for education regarding problem gambling and prevention of problem gambling, and (d) the creation and implementation of outreach and educational programs regarding problem gambling for Nebraska residents. The committee may engage in other activities it finds necessary to carry out its duties under this section.</para> <para>(5) Based on the recommendations of the committee, the division shall adopt guidelines and standards for the distribution and disbursement of money in the fund and for administration of problem gambling services in Nebraska.</para> <para>(6) The division and the committee shall jointly submit a report within sixty days after the end of each fiscal year to the Legislature and the Governor that provides details of the administration of services and distribution of funds.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 551, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1058, &#167;  1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB189, &#167;  1.</para><effectivedate>August 30, 2009</effectivedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>