<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-15,141" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-15,141</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Report; false report; penalty; audits.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Within nine months after the end of each fiscal year, each local housing agency shall prepare a report summarizing such agency's activities for the year then ended. The report shall contain financial statements depicting the financial condition of the agency, its assets and liabilities, including contingent liabilities, and the results of its operations for the year then ended. The report shall be approved by the agency's board of commissioners and signed by its chairperson.</para><para id="id00">(2) The annual report of a local housing agency shall be a public record that is available for inspection and copying by members of the general public at the offices of the local housing agency. A local housing agency shall also file its annual report with the city or county clerk promptly upon completion thereof. Regional housing agencies shall file annual reports with the appropriate officials of all participating political subdivisions.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any employee or member of the board of commissioners of a local housing agency who approves, signs, or files an annual report of an agency knowing it is materially false or misleading shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para id="id00">(4) The financial statements contained in annual reports of local housing agencies with gross revenue of two hundred fifty thousand dollars or more shall be audited annually. The financial statements of agencies with gross revenue of less than two hundred fifty thousand dollars shall be audited at least biennially. A copy of each audit report shall be filed with the Auditor of Public Accounts within nine months after the end of each fiscal year in which such agency is required to file an audit report or in which an audit report of such agency is prepared. Each local housing agency audit shall be conducted in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles, except that if the agency is a recipient of federal assistance, the audit shall be conducted in accordance with any accounting principles required by the federal government.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 105, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 150, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB304, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>