<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1003"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1003</statuteno><catchline>Board; dead human bodies; distribution.</catchline><para>The State Anatomical Board, or its duly authorized officers or agents, may take and receive such dead bodies, and shall hold the same for a period of thirty days from the date of delivery, during which time any such body may be claimed, as provided in section 71-1002. The board shall distribute the bodies among the medical, chiropractic, osteopathic and dental schools and colleges, and physicians and surgeons designated by the board, under such rules and regulations as may be adopted by it. The number of bodies so distributed to the schools and colleges aforesaid shall be in proportion to the number of students matriculated in the first-year work of such schools and colleges. If there shall be more bodies than are required by such schools and colleges, the board, or its duly authorized officers, may, from time to time, designate physicians and surgeons to receive such bodies, and the number of bodies they may receive; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that such physicians and surgeons have complied with all rules and regulations which the board may adopt for such disposition. All expenses incurred by the board in receiving, caring for and delivering any such body shall be paid by those receiving such body.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 158, &#167; 3, p. 552; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2803; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1003; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 268, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Board of Funeral Directing and Embalming,</emphasis> distribution to and use by, see section 38-1417.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 