<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id211"><sectno id="id212" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 19.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id213" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-1910"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id215">71-1910</statuteno><catchline id="id216">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Child Care Licensing Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services; and</para><para>(2)(a) Program means the provision of services in lieu of parental supervision for children under thirteen years of age for compensation, either directly or indirectly, on the average of less than twelve hours per day, but more than two hours per week, and includes any employer-sponsored child care, family child care home, child care center, school-age child care program, school-age services pursuant to section 79-1104, or preschool or nursery school.</para><para>(b) Program does not include casual care at irregular intervals, a recreation camp as defined in section 71-3101, a recreation facility, center, or program operated by a political or governmental subdivision pursuant to the authority provided in section 13-304, classes or services provided by a religious organization other than child care or a preschool or nursery school, a preschool program conducted in a school approved pursuant to section 79-318, services provided only to school-age children during the summer and other extended breaks in the school year, or foster care as defined in section 71-1901.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 130, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 68, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 472, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 836, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 451, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1058; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 588; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 176; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 310, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 97; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 499; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 19.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2008</operativedate></source>  </law></legaldoc> 