<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1628.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1628.04</statuteno><catchline>Core public health functions; contract authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Each local public health department shall carry out the core public health functions within its geographically defined community.</para><para>(2) Each local public health department shall include the essential elements in carrying out the core public health functions to the extent applicable within its geographically defined community and to the extent funds are available. The essential elements include, but are not limited to, (a) monitoring health status to identify community health problems, (b) diagnosing and investigating health problems and health hazards in the community, (c) informing, educating, and empowering people about health issues, (d) mobilizing community partnerships to identify and solve health problems, (e) developing policies and rules that support individual and community health efforts, (f) enforcing laws, rules, and regulations that protect public health and the environment and ensure safety, (g) linking people to needed medical and mental health services and assuring the provision of health care when not otherwise available, (h) assuring a competent workforce within the health care industry and the public health departments, (i) evaluating effectiveness, accessibility, and quality of services within the health care industry and the public health departments, and (j) researching to gain new insights and innovative solutions to health problems.</para><para>(3) Any department or agency of the State of Nebraska may contract with a local public health department for the performance of public health administration or other functions at the discretion of and under the direction of such state department or agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 692, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 63. </para></source></law></legaldoc>