<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id71">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id73" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-1935"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1935</statuteno><catchline>Inspection report; findings of noncompliance;
department; proceedings; letter requesting statement of compliance; contents;
failure to correct; additional proceedings.</catchline><para>If the inspection report issued under section
71-1933 contains findings of noncompliance by a licensed residential child-caring
agency or child-placing agency with any applicable provisions of the Children's
Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act or rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated under the act, the department shall review such findings
within twenty working days after such inspection. If the findings are supported
by the evidence, the department shall proceed under sections 71-1939 to 71-1946,
except that if the findings indicate one or more violations that create no
imminent danger of death or serious physical harm and no direct or immediate
adverse relationship to the health, safety, or welfare of the children residing
in or served by the residential child-caring agency or child-placing agency,
the department may send a letter to the agency requesting a statement of compliance.
The letter shall include a description of each violation, a request that the
residential child-caring agency or child-placing agency submit a statement
of compliance within ten working days, and a notice that the department may
take further steps if the statement of compliance is not submitted. The statement
of compliance shall indicate any steps which have been or will be taken to
correct each violation and the period of time estimated to be necessary to
correct each violation. If the residential child-caring agency or child-placing
agency fails to submit and implement a statement of compliance which indicates
a good faith effort to correct the violations, the department may proceed
under sections 71-1939 to 71-1946.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>