<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id46">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id48" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-1958"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1958</statuteno><catchline>Quality scale rating; application;
assignment of rating.</catchline><para>(1) Quality rating criteria shall be used as provided in
this section to assign a quality scale rating to each applicable child care
or early childhood education program if the program applies under section
71-1957 to participate in the quality rating and improvement system developed
pursuant to section 71-1955.</para>
<para>(2) Licensure
under the Child Care Licensing Act for a program which serves children from
birth to kindergarten-entrance age shall be sufficient criteria to be rated
at step one.</para><para>(3) Meeting criteria established by the State Department of Education
for a prekindergarten service or prekindergarten program established pursuant
to section 79-1104 and reporting to the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional
Record System created under section 71-1962 shall be sufficient criteria to
be rated at step three.</para><para>(4) Meeting performance standards required by the federal government
for a federal Head Start program or Early Head Start program and reporting
to the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System created under section
71-1962 shall be sufficient criteria to be rated at step three.</para>
<para>(5) Accreditation
by a nationally recognized accrediting body approved by the State Department
of Education and reporting to the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record
System created under section 71-1962 shall be sufficient criteria to be rated
at step three.</para><para>(6) A participating applicable child care or early childhood education
program operating under a provisional license shall have a quality scale rating
at step one even if it meets other quality rating criteria. If a participating
applicable child care or early childhood education program is at a quality
scale rating higher than step one and the program's license is placed on corrective
action status, disciplinary limitation, probation, or suspension, such program
shall have its quality scale rating changed to step one. If an applicable
child care or early childhood education program's license is revoked, the
program is not eligible to participate in or receive a quality scale rating
under the quality rating and improvement system until the program has an operating
license which is in full force and effect.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB507, &#167; 7.</para><operativedate>September 6, 2013</operativedate></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Child Care Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1908.</para></crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>