<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id336">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id338" statutenumber="71-1631.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1631.02</statuteno><catchline id="id341">Local boards
of health; retirement plan; reports.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning
December 31, 1998, and each year thereafter, the health director of a board
of health with an independent retirement plan established pursuant to section
71-1631 and section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code shall file with the
Public Employees Retirement Board an annual report on such plan and shall
submit copies of such report to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The Auditor
of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section
84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The annual report shall be in a form
prescribed by the Public Employees Retirement Board and shall contain the
following information for each such retirement plan:</para>
<para>(a) The number of persons participating in the retirement
plan;</para>
<para>(b) The contribution rates of participants in the plan;</para>
<para>(c) Plan assets and liabilities;</para>
<para>(d) The names and positions of persons administering the
plan;</para>
<para>(e) The names and positions of persons investing plan assets;</para>
<para>(f) The form and nature of investments;</para>
<para>(g) For each independent defined contribution plan, a full
description of investment policies and options available to plan participants;
and</para>
<para>(h) For each independent defined benefit plan, the levels
of benefits of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible
for a benefit, and the total present value of such members' benefits, as well
as the funding sources which will pay for such benefits.</para>
<para>If an independent plan contains no current active participants,
the health director may file in place of such report a statement with the
Public Employees Retirement Board indicating the number of retirees still
drawing benefits, and the sources and amount of funding for such benefits.</para>
<para>(2) If such retirement plan is
a defined benefit plan which
was open to new members on January 1, 2004, in addition to the reports required by section 13-2402, a
board of health with an independent retirement plan established pursuant to
section 71-1631 shall cause to be prepared an
annual report and the health director shall file the same with
the Public Employees Retirement Board and
the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and
submit to the Auditor of Public Accounts a copy of such report. The Auditor
of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section
84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If
the board of health does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor of
Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor
of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the local public health
department. All costs of the audit shall be paid by the local public health
department. The report shall consist of a full actuarial analysis
of each such independent retirement plan established pursuant to section 71-1631.
The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public
entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American
Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise
to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization offering
investment advice or which provides investment management services to the
retirement plan. The report
to the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB759, &#167; 19.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>