<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id167">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id169" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-1947"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1947</statuteno><catchline>Lapsed license; reinstatement; suspension;
probation; reinstatement; procedure; hearing; revoked license; revocation
period.</catchline><para>(1)
A license issued under the Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure
Act that has lapsed for nonpayment of fees is eligible for reinstatement at
any time by applying to the department and paying the fees as provided in
section 71-1929.</para>
<para>(2) A license
that has been disciplined by being placed on suspension is eligible for reinstatement
at the end of the period of suspension upon successful completion of an inspection
and payment of the fees as provided in section 71-1929.</para>
<para>(3) A license
that has been disciplined by being placed on probation is eligible for reinstatement
at the end of the period of probation upon successful completion of an inspection
if the department determines an inspection is warranted.</para>
<para>(4) A license
that has been disciplined by being placed on probation or suspension may be
reinstated prior to the completion of the term of such probation or suspension
as provided in this subsection. Upon petition from a licensee and after consideration
of materials submitted with such petition, the director may order an inspection
or other investigation of the licensee. On the basis of material submitted
by the licensee and the results of any inspection or investigation by the
department, the director shall determine whether to grant full reinstatement
of the license, to modify the probation or suspension, or to deny the petition
for reinstatement. The director's decision shall become final fifteen days
after mailing the decision to the licensee unless the licensee requests a
hearing within such fifteen-day period. Any requested hearing shall be held
according to rules and regulations of the department for administrative hearings
in contested cases. Any party to the decision shall have a right to judicial
review under the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(5) A license that has been
disciplined by being revoked is not eligible for relicensure until two years
after the date of such revocation. An application for an initial license may
be made at the end of such two-year period.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 24.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>