<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1364"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1364</statuteno><catchline>Department; inspection; report; duties; noncompliance; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The department may inspect or provide for the inspection of any crematory operated by a crematory authority licensed under the Cremation of Human Remains Act in such manner and at such times as provided in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department.</para><para>(2) The department shall issue an inspection report and provide a copy of the report to the crematory authority within ten working days after the completion of an inspection. The department shall review any findings of noncompliance contained in such report within twenty working days after such inspection.</para><para>(3) If the department determines, after such review, that the evidence supports a finding of noncompliance by a crematory authority with any applicable provisions of the Cremation of Human Remains Act or rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, the department may send a letter to the crematory authority requesting a statement of compliance. The letter shall include a description of each alleged violation, a request that the crematory authority submit a statement of compliance within ten working days, and a notice that the department may take further action if the statement of compliance is not submitted. The statement of compliance shall indicate any actions by the crematory authority which have been or will be taken and the period of time estimated to be necessary to correct each alleged violation. If the crematory authority fails to submit such statement of compliance or fails to make a good faith effort to correct the alleged violations, the department may take further action as provided in sections 71-1366 to 71-1369.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 95, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 