<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id23">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id25"  statutenumber="71-1927"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1927</statuteno><catchline>Residential child-caring agency or
child-placing agency; license required; current license holders; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) Except as
provided in subsection (2) of this section, a residential child-caring agency
or child-placing agency shall not be established, operated, or maintained
in this state without first obtaining a license issued by the department under
the Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act. No person
shall hold itself out as a residential child-caring agency or child-placing
agency or as providing such services unless licensed under the act. The department
shall issue a license to a residential child-caring agency or a child-placing
agency that satisfies the requirements for licensing under the act.</para>
<para>(2) A group home,
child-caring agency, or child-placing agency licensed under sections 71-1901
to 71-1906.01 on May 26, 2013, shall be deemed licensed under the Children's
Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act until the license under such
sections expires, and renewal shall be under the act.</para><para>(3) For purposes of requiring
licensure, a residential child-caring agency or child-placing agency does
not include an individual licensed as a foster family home under sections
71-1901 to 71-1906.01, a person licensed under the Health Care Facility Licensure
Act, a person operating a juvenile detention facility as defined in section
83-4,125, a staff secure youth confinement facility operated by a county,
or a person providing only casual care for children at irregular intervals.
Such persons may voluntarily apply for a license.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>