<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1219" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1219</statuteno><catchline>Mental health board; review hearing; order discharge or change treatment disposition; when.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the filing of a periodic report under section 71-1216, the subject, the subject's counsel, or the subject's legal guardian or conservator, if any, may request and shall be entitled to a review hearing by the mental health board and to seek from the board an order of discharge from commitment or a change in treatment ordered by the board. The mental health board shall schedule the review hearing no later than fourteen calendar days after receipt of such request. The mental health board may schedule a review hearing (a) at any time pursuant to section 71-1221 or 71-1222, (b) upon the request of the subject, the subject's counsel, the subject's legal guardian or conservator, if any, the county attorney, the official, agency, or other person or entity designated by the mental health board under section 71-1215 to prepare and oversee the subject's individualized treatment plan, or the mental health professional directly involved in implementing such plan, or (c) upon the board's own motion.</para><para>(2) The board shall immediately discharge the subject or enter a new treatment order with respect to the subject whenever it is shown by any person or it appears upon the record of the periodic reports filed under section 71-1216 to the satisfaction of the board that (a) the subject's mental illness or personality disorder has been successfully treated or managed to the extent that the subject no longer poses a threat to the public or (b) a less restrictive treatment alternative exists for the subject which does not increase the risk that the subject will commit another sex offense. When discharge or a change in disposition is in issue, due process protections afforded under the Sex Offender Commitment Act shall attach to the subject.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 75.</para></source>
<annotation>
<para>A hearing under subsection (1) of this section is a special proceeding within the ordinary meaning of the term. In re Interest of D.I., 281 Neb. 917, 799 N.W.2d 664 (2011).</para>
<para>Denial of a motion for reconsideration under subsection (1) of this section is a final, appealable order. In re Interest of D.I., 281 Neb. 917, 799 N.W.2d 664 (2011).</para>
<para>Once the subject of a petition has exercised his or her right to a review hearing, and asserted that there are less restrictive treatment alternatives available, the State is required to present clear and convincing evidence that a less restrictive treatment alternative is inappropriate. At that point, the subject may further rebut the State's evidence. In re Interest of D.I., 281 Neb. 917, 799 N.W.2d 664 (2011).</para>
<para>The State bears the burden to show by clear and convincing evidence that the subject remains mentally ill and dangerous. Under the plain language of this section, a mental health board must determine whether the subject's mental illness or personality disorder has been "successfully treated or managed," which necessarily requires the board to review and rely upon the original reason for commitment. In re Interest of D.I., 281 Neb. 917, 799 N.W.2d 664 (2011).</para>
</annotation>
</law></legaldoc>