<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1001"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1001</statuteno><catchline>State Anatomical Board; members; powers and duties.</catchline><para>The heads of the anatomy departments of the medical schools and colleges of this state, one professor of anatomy appointed by the head of the anatomy department from each medical school or college of this state, one professor of anatomy appointed from each dental school or college of this state, and one layperson appointed by the Department of Health and Human Services shall constitute the State Anatomical Board of the State of Nebraska for the distribution, delivery, and use of certain dead human bodies, described in section 71-1002, to and among such schools, colleges, and persons as are entitled thereto under the provisions of such section. The board shall have power to establish rules and regulations for its government and for the collection, storage, and distribution of dead human bodies for anatomical purposes. It shall have power to appoint and remove its officers and agents. It shall keep minutes of its meetings. It shall cause a record to be kept of all of its transactions, of bodies received and distributed by it, and of the school, college, or person receiving every such body, and its records shall be open at all times to the inspection of each member of the board and to every county attorney within this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 158, &#167; 1, p. 551; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2801; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1001; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 570, &#167; 1, p. 2314; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 583, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 98, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 860, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 556; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 464.</para></source></law></legaldoc>