<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id424"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1912.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1912.02</statuteno><catchline>Child care program; volunteer; permitted, when; section; termination.</catchline><para>(1) No child care program licensed under the Child Care Licensing Act shall be prohibited from including a volunteer in the supervised staff-to-child ratio if the volunteer (a) receives qualifying results for either (i) a Federal Bureau of Investigation fingerprint check or (ii) a state criminal registry or repository check with the use of fingerprints, for the state where the staff member resides, and submits to all other background checks as required in section 71-1912 and (b) is supervised at all times by an individual who received a qualifying result on a background check.</para><para>(2) No child care program licensed under the Child Care Licensing Act shall be prohibited from including a volunteer in the unsupervised staff-to-child ratio if the volunteer (a) receives qualifying results for either (i) a Federal Bureau of Investigation fingerprint check or (ii) a state criminal registry or repository check with the use of fingerprints, for the state where the staff member resides, (b) submits to all other background checks as required by section 71-1912, and (c) meets staff qualifications and training requirements.</para><para>(3) No volunteer shall be included in the staff-to-child ratio for more than ten hours per week.</para><para>(4) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to include volunteer staff who provide direct care to children and any other individual who counts in the staff-to-child ratio in the definition of staff in all licensed settings under the Child Care Licensing Act.</para><para>(5) This section terminates on December 31, 2028.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB912, &#167; 28. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>