<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1799"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1799</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Center for Nursing Board; created; members; terms; powers and duties; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Center for Nursing Board is created. The board shall be a policy-setting board for the Nebraska Center for Nursing. The board shall be appointed by the Governor as follows:</para><para>(a) Ten members, at least three of whom shall be registered nurses, one of whom shall be a licensed practical nurse, one of whom shall be a representative of the hospital industry, and one of whom shall be a representative of the long-term care industry;</para><para>(b) One nurse educator recommended by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska;</para><para>(c) One nurse educator recommended by the Nebraska Community College Association;</para><para>(d) One nurse educator recommended by the Nebraska Association of Independent Colleges and Universities; and</para><para>(e) Three members recommended by the State Board of Health.</para><para>(2) The initial terms of the members of the Nebraska Center for Nursing Board shall be:</para><para>(a) Five of the ten members appointed under subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall serve for one year and five shall serve for two years;</para><para>(b) The member recommended by the Board of Regents shall serve for three years;</para><para>(c) The member recommended by the Nebraska Community College Association shall serve for two years;</para><para>(d) The member recommended by the Nebraska Association of Independent Colleges and Universities shall serve for one year; and</para><para>(e) The members recommended by the State Board of Health shall serve for three years.</para><para>The initial appointments shall be made within sixty days after July 13, 2000. After the initial terms expire, the terms of all of the members shall be three years with no member serving more than two consecutive terms.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska Center for Nursing Board shall have the following powers and duties:</para><para>(a) To determine operational policy;</para><para>(b) To elect a chairperson and officers to serve two-year terms. The chairperson and officers may not succeed themselves;</para><para>(c) To establish committees of the board as needed;</para><para>(d) To appoint a multidisciplinary advisory council for input and advice on policy matters;</para><para>(e) To implement the major functions of the Nebraska Center for Nursing; and</para><para>(f) To seek and accept nonstate funds for carrying out center policy.</para><para>(4) The board members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(5) The Department of Health and Human Services shall provide administrative support for the board. The board may contract for additional support not provided by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1025, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 489.</para></source></law></legaldoc>