  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1379"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1379</statuteno><catchline>Potentially hazardous implant or condition; jewelry or other valuables; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) No human remains shall be cremated with the knowledge that the human remains contain a pacemaker or defibrillator or other potentially hazardous implant or condition. The authorizing agent shall take all necessary steps to ensure that any such hazardous implant or condition is removed or corrected prior to cremation. If an authorizing agent informs the funeral director and the crematory authority on the cremation authorization form of the presence of such potentially hazardous implant or condition in the human remains, the funeral director shall ensure that all necessary steps have been taken to remove or correct the implant or condition before delivering the human remains to the crematory. A funeral director who knowingly fails to ensure the removal or correction of the hazardous implant or condition prior to delivery and who knowingly delivers such human remains shall be liable for any damages resulting from such failure. If human remains with hazardous implants or conditions are in the custody of a crematory authority, such authority shall have the hazardous implants or conditions removed or corrected by a licensed funeral director and embalmer or a licensed embalmer at a funeral establishment within an embalming preparation room or at a medical facility by appropriate medical personnel.</para><para>(2) No human remains shall be cremated with the knowledge that the human remains contain jewelry or other valuables. The authorizing agent shall take all necessary steps to ensure that any jewelry or other valuables are removed prior to cremation. If an authorizing agent informs the funeral director and the crematory authority on the cremation authorization form of the presence of jewelry or other valuables on the human remains, the funeral director shall ensure that all necessary steps have been taken to remove the jewelry or other valuables before delivering the human remains to the crematory. A funeral director who knowingly fails to ensure the removal of the jewelry or other valuables prior to delivery and who knowingly delivers such human remains shall be liable for any damages resulting from such failure. If human remains with jewelry or other valuables are in the custody of a crematory authority, such authority shall provide for the removal of such jewelry or other valuables by a licensed funeral director and embalmer or his or her agent.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 95, &#167; 25. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 