<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id125">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id127" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-1941"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1941</statuteno><catchline>License; department;
impose disciplinary actions; fine; how treated; recovery.</catchline><para>(1) The department
may impose any one or a combination of the following types of disciplinary
actions against the license of a residential child-caring agency or child-placing
agency:</para>
<para>(a) A fine not
to exceed ten thousand dollars per violation;</para><para>(b) A period of probation
not to exceed two years, during which time the residential child-caring agency
or child-placing agency may continue to operate under terms and conditions
fixed by the order of probation;</para><para>(c) Restrictions on new admissions to a
residential child-caring agency or acceptance of new referrals by a child-placing
agency;</para><para>(d) Restrictions or other limitations on the number, gender, or
age of children served by the residential child-caring agency or child-placing
agency;</para><para>(e) Other restrictions or limitations on the type of service provided
by the residential child-caring agency or child-placing agency;</para>
<para>(f) Suspension
of the license for a period not to exceed three years, during which time the
licensee shall not operate a residential child-caring agency or child-placing
agency; or</para><para>(g) Revocation of the license. A former licensee whose license
has been revoked shall not apply for a license for a minimum of two years
after the date of revocation.</para><para>(2) Any fine imposed and unpaid under the
Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act shall constitute
a debt to the State of Nebraska which may be collected in the manner of a
lien foreclosure or sued for and recovered in any proper form of action in
the name of the State of Nebraska in the district court of the county in which
the residential child-caring agency or child-placing agency is located. The
department shall, within thirty days after receipt, remit fines to the State
Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the
Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>