
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id422" statutenumber="71-1907"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1907</statuteno><catchline id="id425">Child passenger restraint; requirements; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>Any person furnishing foster care who is subject to licensure under section 71-1902 or the Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act, when transporting in a motor vehicle any children for whom care is being furnished, shall use an approved child passenger restraint system for each child, except that an occupant protection system or a three-point safety belt system as defined in section 60-6,265 may be used for any child as prescribed in section 60-6,267.</para><para>Any person violating this section shall be guilty of an infraction as defined in section 29-431 and shall have his or her license to furnish foster care revoked or suspended by the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>For purposes of this section, approved child passenger restraint system shall mean a restraint system which meets Federal Motor Vehicle Safety Standard 213 as developed by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, as such standard existed on July 20, 2002.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 69, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 386, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 958, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 475; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 586; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 410, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1073, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB231, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB42, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child passenger restraint system violation,</emphasis> see sections 60-6,267 and 60-6,268.</para><para><emphasis>Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1924.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>