<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-15,106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-15,106</statuteno><catchline>Officers; executive director; employees; city of the metropolitan class; information; meetings; requirements.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The commissioners of each housing agency shall elect a chairperson and vice-chairperson from among the commissioners and shall have power to employ an executive director who shall serve as ex officio secretary of the local housing agency.</para><para>(b) Each agency may employ legal counsel or engage the attorney of the city or county served by the agency for such legal services as the agency may require unless such employment or engagement will result in an ethical or legal violation. Each agency may employ accountants, appraisers, technical experts, and such other officers, agents, and employees as the agency may require and shall determine their qualifications, duties, compensation, and terms of office. A local housing agency may delegate to one or more of its agents or employees such powers and duties as it deems proper.</para><para>(2) A housing agency for a city of the metropolitan class shall make all contact information for senior leadership and commissioners publicly available at the agency's offices and on the agency's website. Such contact information shall include telephone numbers and email addresses for each person covered under this subsection.</para><para>(3) Prior to any agency board meeting, a housing agency for a city of the metropolitan class shall post all meeting notices and agendas in common spaces at all agency public locations. Such notices and agendas may be posted as printed material or by means of video display on a television or video monitor located in such common spaces. Prior notice of any board meeting shall also be made available at the agency's offices and on the agency's website. Opportunity for public comment shall be made at all board meetings, and such public comment shall not be limited only to agenda items.</para><para>(4) All commissioners of a housing agency in a city of the metropolitan class shall hold one regular board meeting at least once every ninety days at a public housing facility that has at least one hundred units.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 105, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB840, &#167; 10. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>