<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1637"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1637</statuteno><catchline>Political subdivision; employment and contracts authorized; duties; tax to support; limitation; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) Any city by its mayor and council or by its commission, any village by its village board, any county by its board of supervisors or commissioners, or any township by its electors shall have power to employ a visiting community nurse, a home health nurse, or a home health agency defined in section 71-417 and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the Health Care Facility Licensure Act. Such nurses or home health agency shall do and perform such duties as the city, village, county, or township, by their officials and electors, shall prescribe and direct. The city, village, county, or township shall have the power to levy a tax, not exceeding three and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation of the taxable property of such city, village, county, or township, for the purpose of paying the salary and expenses of such nurses or home health agency. The levy shall be subject to sections 77-3442 and 77-3443. The city, village, county, or township shall have the power to constitute and empower such nurses or home health agency with police power to carry out the order of such city, village, county, or township.</para><para>(2) The governing body of any city, village, county, or township may contract with any visiting nurses association, licensed hospital home health agency, or other licensed home health agency, including those operated by the Department of Health and Human Services, to perform the duties contemplated in subsection (1) of this section, subject to the supervision of the governing body, and may pay the expense of such contract out of the general funds of the city, village, county, or township.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section shall be construed to allow any city, village, county, township, nurse, or home health agency to (a) avoid the requirements of individual licensure, (b) perform any service beyond the scope of practice of licensure or beyond the limits of licensure prescribed by the Health Care Facility Licensure Act, or (c) violate any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the Department of Health and Human Services. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 209, &#167; 1, p. 514; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8234; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 71-2406; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1701; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 483, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 186; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1986), &#167; 71-1701; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 389, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 429, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 160; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 573; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 608, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 483.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>