
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id301" statutenumber="71-1107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1107</statuteno><catchline id="id304">Developmental disability, defined.</catchline><para>Developmental disability means a severe, chronic disability, including an intellectual disability, other than mental illness, which:</para><para>(1) Is attributable to a mental or physical impairment unless the impairment is solely attributable to a severe emotional disturbance or persistent mental illness;</para><para>(2) Is manifested before the age of twenty-two years;</para><para>(3) Is likely to continue indefinitely;</para><para>(4) Results in substantial functional limitations in one of each of the following areas of adaptive functioning:</para><para>(a) Conceptual skills, including language, literacy, money, time, number concepts, and self-direction;</para><para>(b) Social skills, including interpersonal skills, social responsibility, self-esteem, gullibility, wariness, social problem solving, and the ability to follow laws and rules and to avoid being victimized; and</para><para>(c) Practical skills, including activities of daily living, personal care, occupational skills, health care, mobility, and the capacity for independent living; and</para><para>(5) Reflects the individual’s need for a combination and sequence of special, interdisciplinary, or generic services, individualized support, or other forms of assistance that are of lifelong or extended duration and are individually planned and coordinated.</para><para>An individual from birth through the age of nine years who has a substantial developmental delay or specific congenital or acquired condition may be considered to have a developmental disability without manifesting substantial functional limitations in three or more of the areas of adaptive functioning described in subdivision (4) of this section if the individual, without services and support, has a high probability of manifesting such limitations in such areas later in life.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 206, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB333, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>