<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id29">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id31" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-1928"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1928</statuteno><catchline>Applicant for license or renewal;
application; requirements; contents.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for an initial or renewal
license to operate a residential child-caring agency or a child-placing agency
shall file a written application with the department. To be licensed as a
child-placing agency, an applicant must be a corporation, nonprofit corporation,
or limited liability company. The application shall be accompanied by the
applicable fees under section 71-1929 and shall set forth the full name and
address of the agency to be licensed, the full name and address of the owner
of the agency, the names of all persons in control of the agency, and additional
information as required by the department, including sufficient affirmative
evidence of the applicant's ability to comply with rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated under the Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure
Act and evidence of adequate liability insurance or, if self-insured, of sufficient
funds to pay liability claims. The application shall include the applicant's
social security number if the applicant is an individual. The social security
number shall not be public record and may only be used for administrative
purposes.</para>
<para>(2) The application
shall be signed by:</para><para>(a) The owner, if the applicant for licensure as a residential child-caring
agency is an individual or partnership;</para><para>(b) Two of its members, if the applicant
for licensure as a residential child-caring agency or as a child-placing agency
is a limited liability company;</para><para>(c) Two of its officers who have the authority
to bind the corporation to the terms of the application, if the applicant
for licensure as a residential child-caring agency or as a child-placing agency
is a corporation or a nonprofit corporation; or</para><para>(d) The head of the governmental
unit having jurisdiction over the residential child-caring agency or child-placing
agency to be licensed, if the applicant is a governmental unit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>