<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-15,139"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-15,139</statuteno><catchline>Termination of tenancy; procedure; recovery of possession of premises; when.</catchline><para>(1) A housing agency may adopt and promulgate reasonable rules and regulations consistent with federal and state laws, rules, and regulations and the purposes of the Nebraska Housing Agency Act concerning the termination of tenancy. Any resident so terminated shall be sent a written notice of termination setting out the reasons for such termination, and any resident served with a notice shall be given the opportunity to contest the termination in an appropriate hearing by the housing agency. A resident may contest the termination in any suit filed by the housing agency in any court for recovery of possession of the premises.</para><para>(2) Such notice may provide that if the resident fails to (a) pay his or her rent or comply with any covenant or condition of his or her lease or the rules and regulations of such housing agency, (b) cure a violation or default thereof as specified in such notice, or (c) follow the procedure for a hearing as set forth in the notice, all within the time or times set forth in such notice, the tenancy shall then be automatically terminated and no other notice or notices need be given of such termination or the intent to terminate the tenancy, and upon such termination, and without any notice other than as provided for in this section, a housing agency may file suit against any resident for recovery of possession of the premises and may recover the same as provided by law.</para><para>(3) A housing agency may, after three days' written notice of termination and without an administrative hearing, file suit and have judgment against any resident for recovery of possession of the premises if the resident, any member of the resident's household, any guest, or any other person who is under the resident's control or who is present upon the premises with the resident's consent, engages in any drug-related or violent criminal activity on the premises, or engages in any activity that threatens the health, safety, or peaceful enjoyment of other residents or housing agency employees. Such activity shall include, but not be limited to, any of the following activities of the resident, or the activities of any other person on the premises with the consent of the resident: (a) Physical assault or the threat of physical assault; (b) illegal use of a firearm or other weapon or the threat to use an illegal firearm or other weapon; or (c) possession of a controlled substance by the resident or any other person on the premises with the consent of the resident if the resident knew or should have known of the possession by such other person of a controlled substance, unless such controlled substance was obtained directly from or pursuant to a medical order issued by a practitioner authorized to prescribe as defined in section 28-401 while acting in the course of his or her professional practice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 105, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 68. </para></source>
<annotation><para>Under this section, a public housing agency has the authority to file suit for recovery of the premises if the resident engages in violent criminal activity. Banks v. Housing Auth. of City of Omaha, 281 Neb. 67, 795 N.W.2d 632 (2011).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc> 