<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1210" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1210</statuteno><catchline>Subject; custody pending entry of treatment order.</catchline><para>(1) At the conclusion of a mental health board hearing under section 71-1208 and prior to the entry of a treatment order by the board under section 71-1209, the board may (a) order that the subject be retained in custody until the entry of such order and the subject may be admitted for treatment pursuant to such order or (b) order the subject released from custody under such conditions as the board deems necessary and appropriate to prevent the harm described in subdivision (1) of section 83-174.01 and to assure the subject's appearance at a later disposition hearing by the board. A subject shall be retained in custody under this section at an appropriate and available medical facility, jail, or Department of Correctional Services facility. A dangerous sex offender shall not be admitted to a medical facility for emergency protective custody unless a medical or psychiatric emergency exists requiring treatment not available at a jail or correctional facility. Each county shall make arrangements with appropriate facilities inside or outside the county for such purpose and shall pay the cost of the emergency protective custody of persons from such county in such facilities.</para><para>(2) A subject who has been ordered to receive inpatient or outpatient treatment by a mental health board may be provided treatment while being retained in emergency protective custody and pending admission of the subject for treatment pursuant to such order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 66.</para></source></law></legaldoc>