<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1913.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1913.01</statuteno><catchline>Immunization requirements; record; report.</catchline><para>(1) Each program shall require the parent or guardian of each child enrolled in such program to present within thirty days after enrollment and periodically thereafter (a) proof that the child is protected by age-appropriate immunization against measles, mumps, rubella, poliomyelitis, diphtheria, pertussis, tetanus, haemophilus influenzae type B, and invasive pneumococcal disease and such other diseases as the department may from time to time specify based on then current medical and scientific knowledge, (b) certification by a physician, an advanced practice registered nurse practicing under and in accordance with his or her respective certification act, or a physician assistant that immunization is not appropriate for a stated medical reason, or (c) a written statement that the parent or guardian does not wish to have such child so immunized and the reasons therefor. The program shall exclude a child from attendance until such proof, certification, or written statement is provided. At the time the parent or guardian is notified that such information is required, he or she shall be notified in writing of his or her right to submit a certification or written statement pursuant to subdivision (b) or (c) of this subsection.</para><para>(2) Each program shall keep the written record of immunization, the certification, or the written statement of the parent or guardian. Such record, certification, or statement shall be kept by the program as part of the child's file, shall be available onsite to the department, and shall be filed with the department for review and inspection. Each program shall report to the department by November 1 of each year the status of immunization for children enrolled as of September 30 of that year, and children who have reached kindergarten age and who are enrolled in public or private school need not be included in the report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 472, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 431, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 414, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 590; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 301, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 500.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Childhood Vaccine Act,</emphasis> see section 71-526.</para><para><emphasis>School-age children,</emphasis> immunization requirements, see section 79-217 et seq.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>