<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1382" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1382</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Cremated remains; final disposition.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of the Cremation of Human Remains Act, the delivery of the cremated remains to the authorizing agent or his or her representative shall constitute final disposition. If, after a period of sixty days after the date of cremation, the authorizing agent or his or her representative has not directed or otherwise arranged for the final disposition of the cremated remains or claimed the cremated remains for final disposition as provided in this section, the crematory authority or the funeral establishment in possession of the cremated remains may dispose of the cremated remains after making a reasonable attempt to contact the authorizing agent or his or her representative. This method of disposition may be used by any crematory authority or funeral establishment to dispose of all cremated remains in the possession of a crematory authority or funeral establishment on or after August 31, 2003.</para><para>(2)(a) Cremated remains shall be delivered or released by the crematory authority or funeral establishment to the representative specified by the authorizing agent on the cremation authorization form.</para><para>(b) If the crematory authority or funeral establishment has documentation that the cremated remains are those of a veteran or the spouse or dependent of a veteran who did not desire any funeral or burial-related services or ceremonies recognizing his or her service as a veteran and the authorizing agent or his or her representative has not directed or otherwise arranged for the final disposition or claimed the remains after such sixty-day period, the crematory authority or funeral establishment may dispose of the remains.</para><para>(c) If the crematory authority or funeral establishment (i) has no information whether the cremated remains are those of a veteran or the spouse or dependent of a veteran or (ii) has information that the cremated remains are those of a veteran or the spouse or dependent of a veteran but no information on whether such veteran desired a service recognizing his or her service as a veteran, the crematory authority or funeral establishment may use the process provided in section 71-1382.01 to relinquish control of such cremated remains.</para><para>(d) The owner of the crematory authority or his or her representative and the party receiving the cremated remains shall sign a cremated remains receipt form. The form shall include the name of the deceased, the date, time, and place of receipt of the cremated remains, and the signatures of the owner of the crematory or his or her representative and the authorizing agent or his or her representative. If the cremated remains are shipped, a form used by the shipper under subsection (4) of section 71-1381 may be used in lieu of a completed cremated remains receipt form if the shipper's form contains the information required for a cremated remains receipt form. Both the party delivering such remains and the party receiving such remains shall retain a copy of the cremated remains receipt form or shipper's form. Upon delivery, the cremated remains may be further transported within this state in any manner without a permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 95, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB146, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>