<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id77"  statutenumber="71-1936" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1936</statuteno><catchline>Alleged violation of act; complaint; investigation; department; duties; confidentiality; immunity; report.</catchline><para>(1) Any person may submit a complaint to the department and request investigation of an alleged violation of the Children's Residential Facilities and Placing Licensure Act or rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act. The department shall review all complaints, including complaints of such violations received pursuant to section 28-711, and determine whether to conduct an investigation within five working days after receiving the complaint. In making such determination, the department may consider factors such as:</para><para>(a) Whether the complaint pertains to a matter within the authority of the department to enforce;</para><para>(b) Whether the circumstances indicate that a complaint is made in good faith;</para><para>(c) Whether the complaint is timely or has been delayed too long to justify present evaluation of its merit;</para><para>(d) Whether the complainant may be a necessary witness if action is taken and is willing to identify himself or herself and come forward to testify if action is taken; or</para><para>(e) Whether the information provided or within the knowledge of the complainant is sufficient to provide a reasonable basis to believe that a violation has occurred or to secure necessary evidence from other sources.</para><para>(2) A complaint submitted to the department shall be confidential. An individual submitting a complaint shall be immune from criminal or civil liability of any nature, whether direct or derivative, for submitting a complaint or for disclosure of documents, records, or other information to the department.</para><para>(3) If an investigation is conducted under this section, an investigation report shall be issued within sixty days after the determination is made to conduct the investigation, except that the final investigation report may be issued within ninety days after such determination if an interim report is issued within sixty days after such determination.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB59, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>