<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1128" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1128</statuteno><catchline>Review hearing; when authorized; notice.</catchline><para>(1) If at any time it appears that the subject no longer poses a threat of harm to others, any party may file a motion for a review hearing to be held as soon as practicable. The party filing the motion under this subsection shall have the burden of showing by a preponderance of the evidence that the subject no longer poses a threat of harm to others. If it is shown that the subject no longer poses a threat of harm to others, the court shall enter an order dismissing the case and immediately release the subject.</para><para>(2) If at any time it appears that (a) the plan submitted under section 71-1124 or 71-1127 is not sufficient to protect society or the subject or (b) the circumstances upon which the plan was based have changed significantly, any party may file a motion, to be granted for good cause shown, for a review hearing to be held as soon as practicable. The party filing the motion under this subsection shall have the burden of showing by clear and convincing evidence that the court-ordered custody and treatment of the subject should be modified or vacated.</para><para>(3) Upon the filing of a motion for a review hearing pursuant to this section, the department shall immediately provide notice to the Attorney General and the county attorney who filed a petition under section 71-1117 if the proceeding by which the subject is placed in court-ordered custody included evidence of a sex offense as defined in section 83-174.01 or if any prior proceedings resulting in a civil commitment or court-ordered custody included evidence of a sex offense as defined in section 83-174.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 206, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 54. </para></source></law></legaldoc>