<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id80" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-1962"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1962</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System; creation and operation; State Department of Education; duties; develop classification system for employees; use.</catchline><para>(1) Not later than March 1, 2014, the State Department of Education shall create and operate the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System. The system shall be designed in order to:</para><para>(a) Establish a data base of Nebraska's early childhood education workforce;</para><para>(b) Verify educational degrees and professional credentials held and relevant training completed by employees of participating applicable child care and early childhood education programs; and</para><para>(c) Provide such information to the Department of Health and Human Services for use in evaluating applications to be rated at a step above step one under section 71-1959.</para><para>(2) When an applicable child care or early childhood education program participating in the quality rating and improvement system developed pursuant to section 71-1955 applies under section 71-1959 to be rated at a step above step one, the child care or early childhood education program shall report the educational degrees and professional credentials held and relevant training completed by its child care and early childhood education employees to the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System for the program to be eligible for a quality scale rating above step one.</para><para>(3) Any child care or early childhood education provider residing or working in Nebraska may report his or her educational degrees and professional credentials held, relevant training completed, and work history to the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System.</para><para>(4) The State Department of Education shall develop a classification system for all employees of applicable child care and early childhood education programs listed in the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System. The classification system shall be based on the employees' educational degrees and professional credentials held, relevant training completed, and work history and shall be made up of four levels, with level one being the least qualified and level four being the most qualified. The minimum qualification for an employee to be classified as level one shall be a Child Development Associate Credential or a one-year certificate or diploma in early childhood education or child development. The classification system shall be used for purposes of the tax credit granted in section 77-3605.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB507, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB525, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB889, &#167; 9. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>