<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id6" statutenumber="71-1902"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1902</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Foster care; license
required; training required; license renewal; fees; license revocation; procedure.</catchline>
<para>Except as otherwise provided in this section, no person shall
furnish or offer to furnish foster care for two or more children from different
families without having in full force and effect a written license issued
by the department upon such terms and conditions as may be prescribed by general
rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department. The department
may issue a time-limited, nonrenewable provisional license to an applicant
who is unable to comply with all licensure requirements and standards, is
making a good faith effort to comply, and is capable of compliance within
the time period stated in the license. The department may issue a time-limited,
nonrenewable probationary license to a licensee who agrees to establish compliance
with rules and regulations that, when violated, do not present an unreasonable
risk to the health, safety, or well-being of the foster children in the care
of the applicant. No license shall be issued pursuant to this section unless
the applicant has completed the required hours of training in foster care
as prescribed by the department.</para>
<para>All nonprovisional and nonprobationary licenses issued under
sections 71-1901 to 71-1906.01 shall expire two years from the date of issuance
and shall be subject to renewal under the same terms and conditions as the
original license, except that if a licensee submits a completed renewal application
thirty days or more before the license's expiration date, the license shall
remain in effect until the department either renews the license or denies
the renewal application. No license issued pursuant to this section shall
be renewed unless the licensee has completed the required hours of training
in foster care in the preceding twelve months as prescribed by the department.
For the issuance or renewal of each nonprovisional and nonprobationary license,
the department shall charge a fee of fifty dollars for a group home, fifty
dollars for a child-caring agency, and fifty dollars for a child-placing agency.
For the issuance of each provisional license and each probationary license,
the department shall charge a fee of twenty-five dollars for a group home,
twenty-five dollars for a child-caring agency, and twenty-five dollars for
a child-placing agency. A license may be revoked for cause, after notice and
hearing, in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated
by the department.</para>
<para>For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(1) Foster family home means any home which provides twenty-four-hour
care to children who are not related to the foster parent by blood or adoption;</para>
<para>(2) Group home means a home which is operated under the auspices
of an organization which is responsible for providing social services, administration,
direction, and control for the home and which is designed to provide twenty-four-hour
care for children and youth in a residential setting;</para>
<para>(3) Child-caring agency means an organization which is organized as a corporation or a limited liability company for
the purpose of providing care for children in buildings maintained by the
organization for that purpose; and</para>
<para>(4) Child-placing agency means an organization which is authorized
by its articles of incorporation and by its license to place children in foster
family homes.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 154, &#167; 2, p. 564; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1902; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 171, &#167; 2, p. 549; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 207, &#167; 1, p. 595; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 415, &#167; 26, p. 1258; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 130, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 386, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 930, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1222, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 402, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 451, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 209, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 93, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB648, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
