<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1628.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1628.08</statuteno><catchline>County Public Health Aid Program; created; funds; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) The County Public Health Aid Program is created. Aid as appropriated by the Legislature from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund shall be distributed in each fiscal year as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) Of funds appropriated by the Legislature under subsection (1) of this section, the following amounts shall be distributed to local public health departments established under sections 71-1626 to 71-1636:</para><para>(a) One hundred thousand dollars to each local public health department established by at least three contiguous counties with a total population of at least thirty thousand and not more than fifty thousand persons;</para><para>(b) One hundred twenty-five thousand dollars to each local public health department established by a single county with a total population of more than fifty thousand and not more than one hundred thousand persons, with or without additional counties as part of the department, or by at least three contiguous counties with a total population of more than fifty thousand and not more than one hundred thousand persons; and</para><para>(c) One hundred fifty thousand dollars to each local public health department established by one or more counties with a total population of more than one hundred thousand persons.</para><para>(3) Any appropriated funds not distributed under subsection (2) of this section shall be allocated among all counties on a per capita basis as determined by the most recent federal decennial census. The funds allocated for each county shall be distributed to the local public health department which is established by such county and receiving funding under subsection (2) of this section. Any funds not distributed under this subsection shall be equally distributed among all local public health departments receiving funding under subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) Funds appropriated under this section shall not be used to replace existing county funding to any local public health department. Funding for any local public health department under this section shall be reduced to offset any such replacement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 692, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 412, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 64. </para></source></law></legaldoc>