<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-17,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-17,104</statuteno><catchline>Student loan; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) To qualify for a loan under the Nursing Student Loan Act, a student shall be a resident of Nebraska, intend to practice in Nebraska, be motivated to practice in Nebraska, and have substantial financial need. For purposes of this section, substantial financial need means the difference between the student's financial resources available, including those available from parents, a parent, a guardian, or a spouse, and the student's anticipated educational expenses while attending the approved nursing program, taking into account that:</para><para>(a) In determining whether a dependent student has substantial financial need, the following factors shall be considered: (i) Serious family illness; (ii) the number of dependent children of the student's parents; (iii) the number of such dependent children attending institutions of higher education; and (iv) such other circumstances as may affect the ability of the student and student's parents to contribute toward the cost of the student's education; and</para><para>(b) In determining whether an independent or self-supporting student has substantial financial need, the following factors shall be considered: (i) Any serious illness in the student's family; (ii) the number of dependent children of the student; (iii) the number of such dependent children attending institutions of higher education; and (iv) such other circumstances as may affect the ability of the student or spouse to contribute toward the cost of the student's education.</para><para>(2) Each recipient of a loan under the act shall agree to engage in the practice of nursing in the State of Nebraska for the equivalent of one year of full-time practice for each year a loan is received.</para><para>(3) Each approved nursing program shall forward to the department the names of the qualified students recommended to receive loans under the act, based on the criteria specified in subsections (1) and (2) of this section, and any other information and documentation the department deems necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 468, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc>