<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id350"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1965"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1965</statuteno><catchline>Model anaphylaxis policies; school districts; licensed child care programs; Department of Health and Human Services; State Department of Education; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall in consultation with the State Department of Education develop model anaphylaxis policies available for use in school districts and licensed child care programs setting forth guidelines and procedures to be followed for the prevention of anaphylaxis and during a medical emergency resulting from anaphylaxis. Such policies may be developed with input from representatives of allergy medicine, pediatric physicians, school nurses and other health care providers with expertise in treating children with anaphylaxis, parents of children with severe allergies, school administrators, teachers, school food service directors, and other appropriate entities.</para><para>(2) Such policies shall include as applicable:</para><para>(a) A procedure and treatment plan, including emergency protocols and responsibilities for staff members of licensed child care programs, school nurses, and other appropriate school personnel, for responding to anaphylaxis;</para><para>(b) A procedure and appropriate guidelines for the development and implementation of an individualized health care plan for children with a food or other allergy which could result in anaphylaxis;</para><para>(c) A communication plan for the intake and dissemination of information provided by the state regarding children with a food or other allergy which could result in anaphylaxis, including a discussion of methods, treatments, and therapies to reduce the risk of allergic reactions, including anaphylaxis;</para><para>(d) Strategies for the reduction of the risk of exposure to anaphylactic causative agents, including food and other allergens; and</para><para>(e) A communication plan for discussion with children that have developed adequate verbal communication and comprehension skills and with the parents, guardians, and educational decisionmakers of all children attending the school district or licensed child care program about foods that are safe and unsafe and about strategies to avoid exposure to unsafe food.</para><para>(3) The policies developed pursuant to this section shall be reexamined and updated as needed at least once every three years to be consistent with best practices relating to anaphylaxis prevention, treatment, and emergency response methods.</para><para>(4) A model policy developed or updated pursuant to this section shall be made available on the applicable department's website.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Licensed child care program means a facility or program licensed under the Child Care Licensing Act; and</para><para>(b) School district has the same meaning as in section 79-101.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB457, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child Care Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1908.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>