<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1626"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1626</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 71-1626 to 71-1636:</para><para>(1) Core public health functions means assessment, policy development, and assurance designed to protect and improve the health of persons within a geographically defined community by (a) emphasizing services to prevent illness, disease, and disability, (b) promoting effective coordination and use of community resources, and (c) extending health services into the community, including public health nursing, disease prevention and control, public health education, and environmental health services;</para><para>(2) County, district, or city-county health department means a governmental entity approved by the Department of Health and Human Services as a local full-time public health service which (a) utilizes local, state, federal, and other funds or any combination thereof, (b) employs qualified public health medical, nursing, environmental health, health education, and other essential personnel who work under the direction and supervision of a full-time qualified medical director or of a full-time qualified lay administrator and are assisted at least part time by at least one medical consultant who shall be a licensed physician, and (c) is operated in conformity with the rules, regulations, and policies of the Department of Health and Human Services. The medical director or lay administrator shall be called the health director; and</para><para>(3) Local public health department means a county, district, or city-county health department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 152, &#167; 1, p. 554; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 71-1626; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1497, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 568; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 692, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 475.</para></source></law></legaldoc>