<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-1912"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1912</statuteno><catchline>Department; investigation; inspections.</catchline>
<para>(1) Before issuance of a license, the department shall investigate or
cause an investigation to be made, when it deems necessary, to determine if
the applicant or person in charge of the program meets or is capable of meeting
the physical well-being, safety, and protection standards and the other rules
and regulations of the department adopted and promulgated under the Child
Care Licensing Act. The department may investigate the character of applicants
and licensees, any member of the applicant's or licensee's household, and
the staff and employees of programs by making a national criminal history
record information check. The department may at any time inspect or cause
an inspection to be made of any place where a program is operating to determine
if such program is being properly conducted.</para>
<para>(2) All inspections by the department shall be unannounced except for
initial licensure visits and consultation visits. Initial licensure visits
are announced visits necessary for a provisional license to be issued to a
family child care home I, family
child care home II, child care center, or school-age-only or preschool program. Consultation
visits are announced visits made at the request of a licensee for the purpose
of consulting with a department specialist on ways of improving the program.</para>
<para>(3) An unannounced inspection of any place where a program is operating
shall be conducted by the department or the city, village, or county pursuant
to subsection (2) of section 71-1914 at least annually for a program licensed
to provide child care for fewer than thirty children and at least twice every
year for a program licensed to provide child care for thirty or more children.</para>
<para>(4) Whenever an inspection is made, the findings shall be recorded in
a report designated by the department. The public shall have access to the
results of these inspections upon a written or oral request to the department.
The request must include the name and address of the program. Additional unannounced
inspections shall be performed as often as is necessary for the efficient
and effective enforcement of the Child Care Licensing Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 130, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 447, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 386, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1013, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 310, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1050, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>