<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-15,150"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-15,150</statuteno><catchline>Conflict of interest; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise permitted under the provisions of sections 71-15,149 to 71-15,157, no housing agency official shall own or hold an interest in any contract or property or engage in any business, transaction, or professional or personal activity that would:</para><para>(a) Be or appear to be in conflict with such official's duties relating to the housing agency served by or subject to the authority of such official;</para><para>(b) Secure or appear to secure unwarranted privileges or advantages for such official or others; or</para><para>(c) Prejudice or appear to prejudice such official's independence of judgment in the exercise of his or her official duties relating to the housing agency served by or subject to the authority of such official.</para><para>(2) No housing agency official shall act in an official capacity in any matter in which such official has a direct or indirect financial or personal involvement. The ownership of less than five percent of the outstanding shares of a corporation shall not constitute an interest within the meaning of this section. No housing agency official shall use his or her public office or employment to secure financial gain to such official.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise permitted by the provisions of sections 71-15,149 to 71-15,157, a housing agency shall not, with respect to any housing agency official, during his or her tenure or for a period of one year thereafter, either:</para><para>(a) Award or agree to award any contract to such housing agency official or other local government official;</para><para>(b) Purchase or agree to purchase any real property from such housing agency official or other local government official, or sell or agree to sell any real property to such housing agency official or other local government official;</para><para>(c) Permit any housing agency official to represent, appear, or negotiate on behalf of any other party before the housing agency's board of commissioners or with its other officials or employees;</para><para>(d) Employ any commissioner for compensation or otherwise;</para><para>(e) Employ any local government official, or any member of such official's immediate family, if such official's duties involve the exercise of authority relating to the housing agency; or</para><para>(f) Employ for compensation any member of the immediate family of a housing agency official, if such employment creates the relationship of direct supervisor or subordinate between family members or otherwise creates a real or apparent conflict of interest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 105, &#167; 79. </para></source></law></legaldoc>