<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id00" statutenumber="71-1913"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1913</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Fire inspections; sanitation and physical well-being standards; liability insurance; investigations.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The department may request the State Fire Marshal to inspect any program for fire safety pursuant to section 81-502. The State Fire Marshal shall immediately notify the department whenever he or she delegates authority for such inspections under such section.</para><para id="id00">(2) The department may investigate all facilities and programs of licensed providers of child care programs as defined in section 71-1910 or applicants for licenses to provide such programs to determine if the place or places to be covered by such licenses meet standards of sanitation and physical well-being set by the department for the care and protection of the child or children who may be placed in such facilities and programs. The department may delegate this authority to qualified local environmental health personnel.</para><para>(3) At each investigation, the inspector shall request from the licensee, and verify, current proof of liability insurance pursuant to section 71-1911.03.</para><para>(4) This section does not apply to school-age child care programs which are licensed pursuant to section 71-1917.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 130, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 836, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 589; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1034, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB257, &#167; 26. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>