<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1928.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1928.01</statuteno><catchline>National criminal history record information check; procedure; cost; background checks.</catchline><para>(1) Any individual eighteen years of age or older working in a residential child-caring agency shall be required to undergo a national criminal history record information check not less than once during each five-year period that he or she is working in such an agency. The individual shall submit a complete set of his or her fingerprints to the Nebraska State Patrol. The Nebraska State Patrol shall transmit a copy of the individual's fingerprints to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history record information check. The national criminal history record information check shall include information concerning the individual from federal repositories of such information and repositories of such information in other states, if authorized by federal law for use by the Nebraska State Patrol. The Nebraska State Patrol shall issue a report to the department that includes the information collected from the national criminal history record information check concerning the individual. The department shall seek federal funds, if available, to assist residential child-caring agencies and individuals working in a residential child-caring agency with the costs of the fingerprinting and national criminal history record information check. If the department does not receive sufficient federal funds to assist residential child-caring agencies and individuals working in a residential child-caring agency with such costs, then the individual being screened or the residential child-caring agency shall pay the actual cost of the fingerprinting and national criminal history record information check, except that the department may pay all or part of the cost if funding becomes available. The department and the Nebraska State Patrol may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations concerning the costs associated with the fingerprinting and the national criminal history record information check. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations implementing national criminal history record information check requirements for residential child-caring agencies.</para><para>(2) An individual eighteen years of age or older working in a residential child-caring agency shall also submit to the following background checks not less than once during each five-year period: A search of the following registries, repositories, or data bases in the state where the individual resides and each state where the individual resided during the preceding five years:</para><para>(a) State criminal registries or repositories;</para><para>(b) State sex offender registries or repositories; and</para><para>(c) State-based child abuse and neglect registries and data bases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB460, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1185, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>