<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-1370"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-1370</statuteno><catchline>License; reinstatement or relicensure.</catchline><para>(1) If the license of a crematory authority has lapsed for nonpayment of fees, such license shall be eligible for reinstatement at any time upon application to the department and payment of the applicable fee as provided in section 71-1363.</para><para>(2) If the license of a crematory authority has been placed on probation, such license shall be eligible for reinstatement at the end of the period of probation upon successful completion of an inspection if the department determines an inspection is warranted.</para><para>(3) If the license of a crematory authority has been suspended, such license shall be eligible for reinstatement at the end of the period of suspension upon successful completion of an inspection and payment of the applicable fee as provided in section 71-1363.</para><para>(4) If the license of a crematory authority has been suspended, such license may be reinstated by the department prior to the completion of the term of suspension upon petition by the licensee. After reviewing such petition and any material submitted by the licensee with such petition, the department may order an inspection or investigation of the licensee. Based on such review and such inspection or investigation, if any, the director shall (a) grant full reinstatement of the license, (b) modify the suspension, or (c) deny the petition for reinstatement. The director's decision shall become final thirty days after mailing the decision to the licensee unless the licensee requests a hearing within such period. Any requested hearing shall be held according to rules and regulations of the department for administrative hearings in contested cases.</para><para>(5) If the license of a crematory authority has been revoked, such crematory authority shall not be eligible for relicensure until five years after the date of such revocation. A reapplication for an initial license may be made by the crematory authority at the end of such five-year period.</para><para>(6) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 95, &#167; 16. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 