<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id6" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="71-2453"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2453</statuteno><catchline>Department of Correctional Services facilities, detention facilities, or jails; prescription drug or device; return for credit or relabeling and redispensing; requirements; liability; professional disciplinary action.</catchline><para>(1) Prescription drugs or devices which have been dispensed pursuant to a valid prescription and delivered to a Department of Correctional Services facility, a criminal detention facility, a juvenile detention facility, or a jail for administration to a prisoner or detainee held at such facility or jail, but which are not administered to such prisoner or detainee, may be returned to the pharmacy from which they were dispensed under contract with the facility or jail for credit or for relabeling and redispensing and administration to another prisoner or detainee held at such facility or jail pursuant to a valid prescription as provided in this section.</para><para>(2)(a) The decision to accept return of a dispensed prescription drug or device for credit or for relabeling and redispensing rests solely with the pharmacist at the contracting pharmacy.</para><para>(b) A dispensed prescription drug or device shall be properly stored and in the control of the facility or jail at all times prior to the return of the drug or device for credit or for relabeling and redispensing. The drug or device shall be returned in the original and unopened labeled container dispensed by the pharmacist with the tamper-evident seal intact, and the container shall bear the expiration date or calculated expiration date and lot number of the drug or device.</para><para>(c) A prescription drug or device shall not be returned or relabeled and redispensed under this section if the drug or device is a controlled substance, if the drug has restricted distribution by the federal Food and Drug Administration, or if the relabeling and redispensing is otherwise prohibited by law.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Administration has the definition found in section 38-2807;</para><para>(b) Calculated expiration date has the definition found in section 38-2808.01;</para><para>(c) Criminal detention facility has the definition found in section 83-4,125;</para><para>(d) Department of Correctional Services facility has the definition of facility found in section 83-170;</para><para>(e) Dispense or dispensing has the definition found in section 38-2817;</para><para>(f) Jail has the definition found in section 47-117;</para><para>(g) Juvenile detention facility has the definition found in section 83-4,125;</para><para>(h) Prescription has the definition found in section 38-2840; and</para><para>(i) Prescription drug or device has the definition found in section 38-2841.</para><para>(4) The Jail Standards Board, in consultation with the Board of Pharmacy, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations relating to the return of dispensed prescription drugs or devices for credit, relabeling, or redispensing under this section, including, but not limited to, rules and regulations relating to (a) education and training of persons authorized to administer the prescription drug or device to a prisoner or detainee, (b) the proper storage and protection of the drug or device consistent with the directions contained on the label or written drug information provided by the pharmacist for the drug or device, (c) limits on quantity to be dispensed, (d) transferability of drugs or devices for prisoners or detainees between facilities, (e) container requirements, (f) establishment of a drug formulary, and (g) fees for the pharmacy to accept the returned drug or device.</para><para>(5) Any person or entity which exercises reasonable care in accepting, distributing, or dispensing prescription drugs or devices under this section or rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under this section shall be immune from civil or criminal liability or professional disciplinary action of any kind for any injury, death, or loss to person or property relating to such activities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB274, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB37, &#167; 78. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>
