<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-20,100"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-20,100</statuteno><catchline>Nursing Facility Penalty Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Nursing Facility Penalty Cash Fund is created. Any civil money penalty collected by the department as part of any civil penalty imposed pursuant to section 71-2098 or in accordance with the federal Social Security Act, as amended, and imposed by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services pursuant to 42 C.F.R. 488.431 and disbursed to the department in accordance with 42 C.F.R. 488.433 or imposed by the department pursuant to 42 C.F.R. 488.432 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to such fund. The state investment officer shall invest any money in the fund available for investment pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations which establish circumstances under which the department may distribute funds from the Nursing Facility Penalty Cash Fund. Funds collected as part of a civil money penalty imposed by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services of the United States Department of Health and Human Services as described in subsection (1) of this section shall be distributed in accordance with the federal Social Security Act, as amended, and the federal regulations for participation in the medicaid program, to support activities that benefit nursing home residents as provided in 42 C.F.R. 488.433.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 183; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 526; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB22, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>