<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-2421"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2421</statuteno><catchline>Return of dispensed drugs and devices; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) To protect the public safety, dispensed drugs or devices may be returned to the dispensing pharmacy only under the following conditions:</para><para>(a) For immediate destruction by a pharmacist, except that drugs and devices dispensed to residents of a long-term care facility shall be destroyed on the site of the long-term care facility;</para><para>(b) In response to a recall by the manufacturer, packager, or distributor;</para><para>(c) If a device is defective or malfunctioning; or</para><para>(d) Return from a long-term care facility for credit, except that:</para><para>(i) No controlled substance may be returned;</para><para>(ii) The decision to accept the return of the dispensed drug or device shall rest solely with the pharmacist;</para><para>(iii) The dispensed drug or device shall have been in the control of the long-term care facility at all times;</para><para>(iv) The dispensed drug or device shall be in the original and unopened labeled container with a tamper-evident seal intact, as dispensed by the pharmacy. Such container shall bear the expiration date or calculated expiration date and lot number; and</para><para>(v) Tablets or capsules shall have been dispensed in a unit dose with a tamper-evident container which is impermeable to moisture and approved by the Board of Pharmacy.</para><para>(2) Returned dispensed drugs or devices shall not be retained in inventory nor made available for subsequent dispensing, except as provided in subdivision (1)(d) of this section.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Calculated expiration date means an expiration date on the prepackaged product which is not greater than twenty-five percent of the time between the date of repackaging and the expiration date of the bulk container nor greater than six months from the date of repackaging;</para><para>(b) Dispense, drugs, and devices are defined in the Pharmacy Practice Act; and</para><para>(c) Long-term care facility does not include an assisted-living facility as defined in section 71-406.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 333, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB247, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1199.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Pharmacy Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>