<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-2431"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2431</statuteno><catchline>Community health center; relabeling and redispensing prescription drugs; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Prescription drugs or devices which have been delivered to a community health center for dispensing to a patient of such health center pursuant to a valid prescription, but which are not dispensed or administered to such patient, may be delivered to a pharmacist or pharmacy under contract with the community health center for relabeling and redispensing to another patient of such health center pursuant to a valid prescription if:</para><para>(a) The decision to accept delivery of the drug or device for relabeling and redispensing rests solely with the contracting pharmacist or pharmacy;</para><para>(b) The drug or device has been in the control of the community health center at all times;</para><para>(c) The drug or device is in the original and unopened labeled container with a tamper-evident seal intact. Such container shall bear the expiration date or calculated expiration date and lot number; and</para><para>(d) The relabeling and redispensing is not otherwise prohibited by law.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Administer has the definition found in section 38-2806;</para><para>(b) Calculated expiration date has the definition found in section 38-2884;</para><para>(c) Community health center means a community health center established pursuant to the Health Centers Consolidation Act of 1996, 42 U.S.C. 201 et seq., as such act existed on May 7, 2005;</para><para>(d) Deliver or delivery has the definition found in section 38-2813;</para><para>(e) Dispense or dispensing has the definition found in section 38-2817;</para><para>(f) Prescription has the definition found in section 38-2840; and</para><para>(g) Prescription drug or device has the definition found in section 38-2841.</para><para>(3) The Department of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Board of Pharmacy, may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 382, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 542; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1201.</para></source></law></legaldoc>