<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-20,105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-20,105</statuteno><catchline>Application; department; Attorney General; duties; single unified review process; when.</catchline><para>(1) Within five working days after receipt of an application under section 71-20,104, the department shall publish notice of the application in a newspaper of general circulation in the county or counties where the hospital is located and shall notify by first-class United States mail any person who has requested notice of the filing of such applications. The notice shall state that an application has been received, state the names of the parties to the agreement, describe the contents of the application, and state the date by which a person may submit written comments about the application to the department.</para><para>(2) Within sixty days after receiving an application, the department shall review the application in accordance with the standards set forth in the Nonprofit Hospital Sale Act and approve or disapprove the acquisition pursuant to the act.</para><para>Within twenty days after receiving an application, the Attorney General shall determine whether to review the application in accordance with section 71-20,108 and shall so notify the applicant. If the Attorney General determines to review the application in accordance with the act, the Attorney General shall, within sixty days after receiving the application, review the application in accordance with the standards set forth in section 71-20,108 and approve or disapprove the acquisition. If the Attorney General determines not to review the application in accordance with the act, then none of the other provisions of the act applicable to review by the Attorney General shall apply.</para><para>(3) For acquisitions which require approval from the department under the Nonprofit Hospital Sale Act and a certificate of need under the Nebraska Health Care Certificate of Need Act, the applicant shall submit a single application for both purposes and such application shall be reviewed under a single unified review process by the department. Following the single unified review process, the department shall simultaneously issue (a) its decision for purposes of the Nebraska Health Care Certificate of Need Act and (b) its decision for purposes of the Nonprofit Hospital Sale Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1188, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Health Care Certificate of Need Act,</emphasis> see section 71-5801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>