<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-2516"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2516</statuteno><catchline>Department of Health and Human Services;
statewide environmental lead hazard awareness action plan; powers.</catchline>
<para>The Department of Health and Human Services may participate in national
efforts and may develop a statewide environmental lead hazard awareness action
plan which is comprehensive in scope and reflects contributions from a broad
base of providers and consumers. In order to implement the statewide environmental
lead hazard awareness action plan, the department may:</para>
<para>(1) Actively seek the participation and commitment of the public, health
care professionals and facilities, the educational community, and community
organizations in a comprehensive program to ensure that the state's children
are appropriately protected from environmental lead hazards;</para>
<para>(2) Apply for and receive public and private awards to develop and administer
a statewide comprehensive environmental lead hazard awareness action plan
program;</para>
<para>(3) Provide environmental lead hazard information and education to the
public, parents, health care providers, and educators to establish and maintain
a high level of awareness;</para>
<para>(4) Assist parents, health care providers, and communities in developing
systems, including demonstration and pilot projects, which emphasize the protection
of children from environmental lead poisoning and the use of private practitioners;
and</para>
<para>(5) Evaluate the effectiveness of these statewide efforts, identify
children at special risk for environmental lead hazard exposure, and report electronically on the activities
of the statewide program annually to the Legislature and the citizens of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 630; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 115.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>