<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id988" statutenumber="71-2412"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2412</statuteno><catchline id="id991">Long-term care facility; emergency boxes; use; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Drugs may be administered to residents of a long-term care facility by authorized personnel of the long-term care facility from the contents of emergency boxes located within such long-term care facility if such drugs and boxes meet the requirements of this section.</para><para>(2) When electronic or automated emergency boxes are in use in a long-term care facility, the supplying pharmacy shall have policies and procedures to ensure proper utilization of the drugs in the emergency boxes. Policies and procedures shall include who is allowed to retrieve drugs from the emergency boxes, security for the location of the emergency boxes within the long-term care facility, and other necessary provisions as determined by the pharmacist-in-charge of the supplying pharmacy.</para><para>(3) For emergency boxes that are not electronic or automated:</para><para>(a) All emergency box drugs shall be provided by and all emergency boxes containing such drugs shall be sealed by a supplying pharmacy with the seal on such emergency box to be of such a nature that it can be easily identified if it has been broken;</para><para>(b) Emergency boxes shall be stored in a medication room or other secured area within the long-term care facility. Only authorized personnel of the long-term care facility or the supplying pharmacy shall obtain access to such room or secured area, by key or combination, in order to prevent unauthorized access and to ensure a proper environment for preservation of the emergency box drugs;</para><para>(c) The exterior of each emergency box shall be labeled so as to clearly indicate that it is an emergency box for use in emergencies only. The label shall contain a listing of the drugs contained in the box, including the name, strength, route of administration, quantity, and expiration date of each drug, and the name, address, and telephone number of the supplying pharmacy; and</para><para>(d) Emergency boxes shall be inspected by a pharmacist designated by the supplying pharmacy at least once a month or after a reported usage of any drug to determine the expiration date and quantity of the drugs in the box. Every inspection shall be documented and the record retained by the long-term care facility for a period of five years.</para><para>(4) All drugs in emergency boxes shall be in the original manufacturer's or distributor's containers or shall be repackaged by the supplying pharmacy in a tight, light-resistant container and shall include the manufacturer's or distributor's name, lot number, drug name, strength, dosage form, NDC number, route of administration, and expiration date on a typewritten label. Any drug which is repackaged shall contain on the label the calculated expiration date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 184; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1195; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB166, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1052, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>