<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id944"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-2484"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2484</statuteno><catchline>Repealed. Laws 2022, LB767, &#167; 15. Operative date January 1, 2023. Information regarding cost, price, or copayment of a prescription drug; pharmacist or contracted pharmacy; authorized activities; pharmacy benefit manager; insurer; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Contracted pharmacy means a pharmacy located in this state that participates either in the network of a pharmacy benefit manager or in a health care or pharmacy benefits management plan through a direct contract or through a contract with a pharmacy services administration organization, a group purchasing organization, or another contracting agent;</para><para>(b) Covered entity means (i) a nonprofit hospital or medical services corporation, an insurer, a third-party payor, a managed care company, or a health maintenance organization, (ii) a health program administered by the state in the capacity of provider of health insurance coverage, or (iii) an employer, a labor union, or any other group of persons organized in the state that provides health insurance coverage;</para><para>(c) Covered individual means a member, participant, enrollee, contract holder, policyholder, or beneficiary of a covered entity who is provided health insurance coverage by the covered entity and includes a dependent or other person provided health insurance coverage through a policy, contract, or plan for a covered individual;</para><para>(d)(i) Insurer means any person providing life insurance, sickness and accident insurance, workers' compensation insurance, or annuities in this state.</para><para>(ii) Insurer includes an authorized insurance company, a prepaid hospital or medical care plan, a managed care plan, a health maintenance organization, any other person providing a plan of insurance subject to state insurance regulation, and an employer who is approved by the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court as a self-covered entity;</para><para>(e) Pharmacist has the same meaning as in section 38-2832;</para><para>(f) Pharmacy has the same meaning as in section 71-425;</para><para>(g) Pharmacy benefit manager means a person or an entity that performs pharmacy benefits management services for a covered entity and includes any other person or entity acting on behalf of a pharmacy benefit manager pursuant to a contractual or employment relationship;</para><para>(h) Pharmacy benefits management means the administration or management of prescription drug benefits provided by a covered entity under the terms and conditions of the contract between the pharmacy benefit manager and the covered entity; and</para><para>(i) Prescription drug means a prescription drug or device or legend drug or device as defined in section 38-2841.</para><para>(2) A pharmacist or contracted pharmacy shall not be prohibited from or subject to penalties or removal from a network or plan for sharing information regarding the cost, price, or copayment of a prescription drug with a covered individual or a covered individual's caregiver. A pharmacy benefit manager shall not prohibit or inhibit a pharmacist or contracted pharmacy from discussing any such information or selling a more affordable alternative to a covered individual or a covered individual's caregiver.</para><para>(3) An insurer that offers a health plan which covers prescription drugs shall not require a covered individual to make a payment for a prescription drug at the point of sale in an amount that exceeds the lesser of:</para><para>(a) The covered individual's copayment, deductible, or coinsurance for such prescription drug; or</para><para>(b) The amount any individual would pay for such prescription drug if that individual paid in cash.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB316, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>