<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id867"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-2491"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2491</statuteno><catchline>Opioid Prevention and Treatment Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Opioid Prevention and Treatment Cash Fund is created. The fund shall consist of transfers from the Nebraska Opioid Recovery Trust Fund. No more than the amounts specified in this section may be appropriated or transferred from the Opioid Prevention and Treatment Cash Fund in any fiscal year.</para><para>(2) Any money in the Opioid Prevention and Treatment Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature to annually appropriate from the Opioid Prevention and Treatment Cash Fund beginning in FY2024-25 three million dollars to the Department of Health and Human Services for disbursement by the division to regional behavioral health authorities for behavioral health regions established pursuant to section 71-807 for opioid use prevention and opioid remediation under the Opioid Prevention and Treatment Act as follows:</para><para>(a) Five and four-hundred-seventy-six thousandths percent to region 1;</para><para>(b) Five and one-hundred-twelve thousandths percent to region 2;</para><para>(c) Ten and eight thousand nine hundred eighty-two ten-thousandths percent to region 3;</para><para>(d) Eight and five thousand eight hundred thirty-three ten-thousandths percent to region 4;</para><para>(e) Twenty-five and seven thousand four hundred twenty-one ten-thousandths percent to region 5; and</para><para>(f) Forty-four and one thousand eight hundred sixty-nine ten-thousandths percent to region 6.</para><para>(4) The regional behavioral health authorities shall only spend such disbursements for purposes identified in section 71-2494.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1355, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>