<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id13" statutenumber="71-2455"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2455</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Prescription drug monitoring; Department of Health and Human Services; powers and duties; Health Information Technology Board; administration.</catchline><para>Subject to sections 81-6,127 and 81-6,128, the Department of Health and Human Services, in collaboration with the Nebraska Health Information Initiative or any successor public-private statewide health information exchange, shall enhance or establish technology for prescription drug monitoring to carry out the purposes of section 71-2454. The department may use state funds and accept grants, gifts, or other funds in order to implement and operate the technology. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to authorize use of electronic health information, if necessary to carry out the purposes of sections 71-2454 and 71-2455. The department shall contract with the statewide health information exchange for the administration of the Health Information Technology Board, and such contract shall specify that the health information exchange is responsible for the administration of the Health Information Technology Board, including, but not limited to, providing meeting notices, recording and distributing meeting minutes, administrative tasks related to the same, and funding such activities. The contract shall also include provisions for the statewide health information exchange to reimburse the expenses of the members of the board pursuant to subsection (5) of section 81-6,127. Such reimbursement shall be paid using a process essentially similar to sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. No state funds, including General Funds, cash funds, and federal funds, shall be used to carry out the administrative duties of the Health Information Technology Board nor for reimbursement of the expenses of the board members.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB237, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1072, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1183, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>