<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id257"><amendatorysection chaptername="PUBLIC HEALTH AND WELFARE" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="71-2478"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2478</statuteno><catchline>Legend drug not a controlled substance; written, oral, or electronic prescription; information required; controlled substance; requirements; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in this section or the Uniform Controlled Substances Act or except when administered directly by a practitioner to an ultimate user, a legend drug which is not a controlled substance shall not be dispensed without a written, oral, or electronic prescription. Such prescription shall be valid for twelve months after the date of issuance.</para><para>(2) A prescription for a legend drug which is not a controlled substance shall contain the following information prior to being filled by a pharmacist or practitioner who holds a pharmacy license under subdivision (1) of section 38-2850: (a) Patient's name, (b) name of the drug, device, or biological, (c) strength of the drug or biological, if applicable, (d) dosage form of the drug or biological, (e) quantity of the drug, device, or biological prescribed, (f) directions for use, (g) date of issuance, (h) number of authorized refills, (i) prescribing practitioner's name, and (j) if the prescription is written, prescribing practitioner's signature. Prescriptions for controlled substances must meet the requirements of sections 28-414 and 28-414.01.</para><para>(3) A written, signed paper prescription may be transmitted to the pharmacy via facsimile which shall serve as the original written prescription. An electronic prescription may be electronically or digitally signed and transmitted to the pharmacy and may serve as the original prescription.</para><para>(4) It shall be unlawful for any person knowingly or intentionally to possess or to acquire or obtain or to attempt to acquire or obtain, by means of misrepresentation, fraud, forgery, deception, or subterfuge, possession of any drug substance not classified as a controlled substance under the Uniform Controlled Substances Act which can only be lawfully dispensed, under federal statutes in effect on January 1, 2015, upon the written or oral prescription of a practitioner authorized to prescribe such substances.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB37, &#167; 22. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>