<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id60"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-24,107"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-24,107</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Medical Cannabis Regulation Act:</para><para>(1)(a) Cannabis means all parts of the plant of the genus cannabis whether growing or not, the seeds thereof, the resin extracted from any part of the plant, and every compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture, or preparation of the plant, its seeds, or its resin.</para><para>(b) Cannabis includes marijuana, hashish, and concentrated cannabis.</para><para>(c) Cannabis does not include hemp, as defined in Section 2-503(13) of the Nebraska Hemp Farming Act, nor does it include the mature stalks of the plant, fiber produced from such stalks, oil or cake made from the seeds of the plant, the sterilized seed of the plant which is incapable of germination, or cannabidiol contained in a drug product approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration;</para><para>(2) Cannabis accessories means any equipment, products, or materials of any kind that are used, intended for use, or designed for use in planting, propagating, cultivating, growing, harvesting, composting, manufacturing, compounding, converting, producing, processing, preparing, testing, analyzing, packaging, repackaging, storing, vaporizing, or containing cannabis, or for ingesting, inhaling, or otherwise introducing cannabis into the human body;</para><para>(3) Cannabis for medical purposes means cannabis, cannabis products, and cannabis accessories intended for qualified patients pursuant to any law enacted contemporaneously with the adoption of the Nebraska Medical Cannabis Regulation Act or at any time thereafter and which makes penalties inapplicable to the use of cannabis by qualified patients for the alleviation of a medical condition, its symptoms, or side effects of the condition's treatment;</para><para>(4) Cannabis products means products that are comprised of cannabis, cannabis concentrate, or cannabis extract, and other ingredients, and that are intended for use or consumption, such as, but not limited to, edible products, ointments, and tinctures;</para><para>(5) Commission means the Nebraska Medical Cannabis Commission;</para><para>(6) Registered cannabis establishment means a private entity registered pursuant to the Nebraska Medical Cannabis Regulation Act that possesses, manufactures, distributes, delivers, or dispenses cannabis for medical purposes; and</para><para>(7) Registration means a registration granted by the commission to a private entity that processes, manufactures, distributes, delivers, or dispenses cannabis for medical purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Initiative Law 2024, No. 438, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>