<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-2501" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2501</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Poison, defined; exceptions.</catchline><para> For purposes of the Poison Control Act:</para><para>(1) Poison includes: Arsenic, metallic or elemental, and all poisonous compounds and preparations thereof; corrosive sublimate; white precipitate; red precipitate, mercuric iodide; nitrate of mercury; hydrocyanic acid and all its salts and poisonous compounds; aconitine, arecoline, atropine, brucine, colchicine, coniine, daturine, delphinine, gelsemine, gelseminine, homatropine, hyoscine, hyoscyamine, lobeline, pelletierine, physostigmine, pilocarpine, sparteine, strychnine, veratrine, and all other poisonous alkaloids and their salts, poisonous compounds, and preparations; volatile or essential oil of bitter almonds, natural and artificial; aconite, belladonna, calabar bean, cantharides, colchicum, conium cotton root, cocculus indicum, datura, ergot, gelsemium, henbane, ignatia, lobelia, nux vomica, savin, scopolamine, solanum, stramonium, staphisagra, strophanthus, veratrum viride, and their pharmaceutical preparations and compounds; cantharidin, picrotoxin, elaterin, santonin, their poisonous chemical compounds and derivatives and preparations; ascaridol; volatile oil of mustard, natural and synthetic; oil of tansy; oil of savin, glacial acetic acid; trichloracetic acid; aniline oil; benzaldehyde; bromoform; carbolic acid; cresylic acid; chloral hydrate; chromic acid; croton oil; dinitrophenol; mineral acids; oxalic acid; nitrobenzene; phosphorous; paraldehyde; picric acid; salts of antimony; salts of barium, except the sulphate, salts of cobalt, salts of chromium; salts of lead; salts of thallium; salts of zinc; carbon tetrachloride, and silver nitrate; and</para><para>(2) Poison does not include:</para><para>(a) Agricultural or garden spray, insecticides, concentrated lye, fungicides, rodent destroyers, and other preparations of whatever ingredients, preservative or otherwise for animal or poultry use, for commercial, industrial, manufacturing, or fire protection purposes or any combination of such purposes, and not for human use, when the same are properly packaged, prepared, and labeled with official poison labels in conformity with the terms and provisions of section 71-2502 or the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, as such act existed on May 1, 2001, or the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act, as such act existed on May 1, 2001;</para><para>(b) Preparations prepared by or under the supervision of a governmental agency for use by it or under its direction in the suppression of injurious insect pests and plant diseases destructive to the agricultural and horticultural interests of the state; and</para><para>(c) Preparations for the destruction of rodents, predatory animals, or noxious weeds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 141, &#167; 13, p. 562; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 81-932; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-625; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 296, &#167; 1, p. 1068; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB37, &#167; 80. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>
