<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-2086"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2086</statuteno><catchline>Appointment of receiver; procedure; temporary receiver; purpose of receivership.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall file the petition for the appointment of a receiver provided for in section 71-2085 in the district court of Lancaster County or the county where the health care facility is located and shall request that a receiver be appointed for the health care facility. Unless otherwise approved by the court, no person shall be appointed as a receiver for more than six health care facilities at the same time.</para><para>(2) The court shall expeditiously hold a hearing on the petition within seven days after the filing of the petition. The department shall present evidence at the hearing in support of the petition. The licensee, owner, or operator may also present evidence, and both parties may subpoena witnesses. The court may appoint a temporary receiver for the health care facility ex parte if the department, by affidavit, states that an emergency exists which presents an imminent danger of death or physical harm to the residents or patients of the health care facility. If a temporary receiver is appointed, notice of the petition and order shall be served on the licensee, owner, operator, or administrator of the health care facility within seventy-two hours after the entry of the order. The petition and order may be served by any method specified in section 25-505.01 or the court may permit substitute or constructive service as provided in section 25-517.02 when service cannot be made with reasonable diligence by any of the methods specified in section 25-505.01. A hearing on the petition and temporary order shall be held within seventy-two hours after notice has been served unless the licensee, owner, or operator consents to a later date. After the hearing the court may terminate, continue, or modify the temporary order. If the court determines that the department did not have probable cause to submit the affidavit in support of the appointment of the temporary receiver, the court shall have the jurisdiction to determine and award compensatory damages against the state to the owner or operator. If the licensee, owner, or operator informs the court at or before the time set for hearing that the licensee, owner, or operator does not object to the petition, the court shall waive the hearing and at once appoint a receiver for the health care facility.</para><para>(3) The purpose of a receivership created under this section is to safeguard the health, safety, and continuity of care of residents and patients and to protect them from adverse health effects. A receiver shall not take any actions or assume any responsibilities inconsistent with this purpose. No person shall impede the operation of a receivership created under this section. After the appointment of a receiver, there shall be an automatic stay of any action that would interfere with the functioning of the health care facility, including, but not limited to, cancellation of insurance policies executed by the licensee, owner, or operator, termination of utility services, attachments or setoffs of resident trust funds or working capital accounts, and repossession of equipment used in the health care facility. The stay shall not apply to any licensure, certification, or injunctive action taken by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 274, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 71-6003; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 521; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1053, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>