<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare"  statutenumber="71-2437"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2437</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Immunosuppressant Drug Repository Program Act:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(2) Immunosuppressant drug means anti-rejection drugs that are used to reduce the body's immune system response to foreign material and inhibit a transplant recipient's immune system from rejecting a transplanted organ. Immunosuppressant drugs are available only as prescription drugs and come in tablet, capsule, and liquid forms. The recommended dosage depends on the type and form of immunosuppressant drug and the purpose for which it is being used. Immunosuppressant drug does not include drugs prescribed for inpatient use;</para><para>(3) Participant means a transplant center that has elected to voluntarily participate in the program, that has submitted written notification to the department of its intent to participate in the program, and that accepts donated immunosuppressant drugs under the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department for the program;</para><para>(4) Prescribing practitioner means a health care practitioner licensed under the Uniform Credentialing Act who is authorized to prescribe immunosuppressant drugs;</para><para>(5) Prescription drug has the definition found in section 38-2841;</para><para>(6) Program means the immunosuppressant drug repository program established pursuant to section 71-2438;</para><para>(7) Transplant center means a hospital that operates an organ transplant program, including qualifying patients for transplant, registering patients on the national waiting list, performing transplant surgery, and providing care before and after transplant; and</para><para>(8) Transplant program means the organ-specific facility within a transplant center. A transplant center may have transplant programs for the transplantation of hearts, lungs, livers, kidneys, pancreata, or intestines.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 544; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1202.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>