<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id1001" statutenumber="71-2413"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2413</statuteno><catchline id="id1004">Drugs to be included in emergency boxes; requirements; removal; conditions; notification of supplying pharmacy; expired drugs; treatment; examination of emergency boxes; written procedures; establishment.</catchline><para>(1) The supplying pharmacy and the medical director and quality assurance committee of the long-term care facility shall jointly determine the drugs, by identity and quantity, to be included in the emergency boxes. The supplying pharmacy shall maintain a list of emergency box drugs which is identical to the list on the exterior of the emergency box or the electronic inventory record of the emergency box and shall make such list available to the department upon request. The supplying pharmacy shall obtain a receipt upon delivery of the emergency box to the long-term care facility signed by the director of nursing of the long-term care facility or his or her designee which acknowledges that the drugs initially placed in the emergency box are identical to the initial list on the exterior of the emergency box or the electronic inventory record of the emergency box. The receipt shall be retained by the supplying pharmacy for a period of five years.</para><para>(2) Except for the removal of expired drugs as provided in subsection (4) of this section, drugs shall be removed from emergency boxes only pursuant to a prescription. Whenever access to the emergency box occurs, the prescription and proof of use shall be provided to the supplying pharmacy and shall be recorded on the resident's medical record by authorized personnel of the long-term care facility. Removal of any drug from an emergency box by authorized personnel of the long-term care facility shall be recorded on a form showing the name of the resident who received the drug, his or her room number, the name of the drug, the strength of the drug, the quantity used, the dose administered, the route of administration, the date the drug was used, the time of usage, the disposal of waste, if any, and the signature or signatures of authorized personnel. The form shall be maintained at the long-term care facility for a period of five years from the date of removal with a copy of the form to be provided to the supplying pharmacy.</para><para>(3) Whenever an emergency box is opened or otherwise accessed, the supplying pharmacy shall be notified by the charge nurse or the director of nursing of the long-term care facility within twenty-four hours and a pharmacist designated by the supplying pharmacy shall restock and refill the box, reseal the box if it is not an electronic or automated emergency box, and update the drug listing on the exterior of the emergency box or update the electronic inventory record of the emergency box as outlined in the policies and procedures of the supplying pharmacy required by section 71-2412 for an electronic or automated emergency box.</para><para>(4) Upon the expiration of any drug in the emergency box, the supplying pharmacy shall replace the expired drug, reseal the box if it is not an electronic or automated emergency box, and update the drug listing on the exterior of the emergency box or update the electronic inventory record of the emergency box as outlined in the policies and procedures of the supplying pharmacy required by section 71-2412 for an electronic or automated emergency box. Emergency box drugs shall be considered inventory of the supplying pharmacy until such time as they are removed for administration.</para><para>(5) Authorized personnel of the long-term care facility shall examine the emergency boxes once every twenty-four hours and shall immediately notify the supplying pharmacy upon discovering evidence of tampering with any emergency box. Proof of examination by authorized personnel of the long-term care facility shall be recorded and maintained at the long-term care facility for a period of five years from the date of examination.</para><para>(6) The supplying pharmacy and the medical director and quality assurance committee of the long-term care facility shall jointly establish written procedures for the safe and efficient distribution of emergency box drugs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 185; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 166; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 398, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB166, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1052, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>