<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id1018"> <sectno id="id1019" opdate=" ">Sec. 73.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id1020" statutenumber="71-2416"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id1022">71-2416</statuteno><catchline id="id1023">Violations; department; powers; prohibited acts; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The department may limit, suspend, or revoke the authority of a supplying pharmacy to maintain emergency boxes in a long-term care facility for any violation of the Emergency Box Drug Act. The department may limit, suspend, or revoke the authority of a long-term care facility to maintain an emergency box for any violation of the act. The taking of such action against the supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility or both shall not prohibit the department from taking other disciplinary actions against the supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility.</para> <para>(2) If the department determines to limit, suspend, or revoke the authority of a supplying pharmacy to maintain emergency boxes in a long-term care facility or to limit, suspend, or revoke the authority of a long-term care facility to maintain an emergency box, it shall send to the supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility a notice of such determination. The notice may be served by any method specified in section 25-505.01, or the department may permit substitute or constructive service as provided in section 25-517.02 when service cannot be made with reasonable diligence by any of the methods specified in section 25-505.01. The limitation, suspension, or revocation shall become final thirty days after receipt of the notice unless the supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility, within such thirty-day period, requests a hearing in writing. The supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility shall be given a fair hearing before the department and may present such evidence as may be proper. On the basis of such evidence, the determination involved shall be affirmed, set aside, or modified, and a copy of such decision setting forth the findings of facts and the particular reasons on which it is based shall be sent to the supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility. The parties may appeal the final decision in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. Witnesses may be subpoenaed by either party and shall be allowed a fee at the statutory rate.</para> <para>(3) The procedure governing hearings authorized by the Emergency Box Drug Act shall be in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department.</para> <para>(4) The supplying pharmacy or the long-term care facility shall not maintain an emergency box after its authority to maintain such box has been revoked or during the time such authority has been suspended. If the authority is suspended, the suspension shall be for a definite period of time. Such authority shall be automatically reinstated on the expiration of such period. If such authority has been revoked, such revocation shall be permanent, except that at any time after the expiration of two years, application for reinstatement of authority may be made to the department.</para> <para>(5) Any person who commits any of the acts prohibited by the Emergency Box Drug Act shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor. The department may maintain an action in the name of the state against any person for maintaining an emergency box in violation of the act. Each day a violation continues shall constitute a separate violation.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 188; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 828, &#167; 167; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 73.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>