<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-2304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2304</statuteno><catchline>Coordinated program of education and treatment; regional behavioral health funding; Department of Health and Human Services; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature shall appropriate funds to create a coordinated program of education and treatment for individuals that participate in prostitution-related activities as described in section 28-801.</para><para>(2) The Department of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the regional behavioral health authorities, shall distribute funds to regional behavioral health authorities that can demonstrate to the department a high incidence of prostitution within the behavioral health region. The department may consider the following criteria for regional behavioral health funding under this section:</para><para>(a) The number of criminal convictions for prostitution-related activities within the counties that comprise the regional behavioral health authority;</para><para>(b) Evidence that prostitution-related activities are impacting residential areas and businesses and the quality of life of residents in such areas and businesses is negatively impacted;</para><para>(c) The amount of local law enforcement resources devoted specifically to curtailing prostitution-related activity;</para><para>(d) Evidence that the regional behavioral health authorities consulted with recognized neighborhood and business associations within geographic proximity to concentrated areas of prostitution; and</para><para>(e) The amount of local subdivision treatment funding.</para><para>Each regional behavioral health authority may contract with qualifying public, private, or nonprofit entities for the provision of such education and treatment. Such qualifying entities may obtain additional funding from cities and counties to provide a coordinated program of treatment and education for individuals that participate in prostitution-related activities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1086, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 535.</para></source></law></legaldoc>