<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-20,112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-20,112</statuteno><catchline>Licensure; issuance, renewal, revocation, or suspension; when; section, how construed.</catchline><para>No license to operate a hospital may be issued or renewed by the department pursuant to the Health Care Facility Licensure Act or any other state statute, and a license which has been issued shall be subject to revocation or suspension, if:</para><para>(1) There is an acquisition of a hospital without first having received the approval of the department under the Nonprofit Hospital Sale Act;</para><para>(2) There is an acquisition of a hospital without the approval of the Attorney General, if the Attorney General determines to review the application under the act;</para><para>(3) There is an acquisition of a hospital and the Attorney General disapproves the acquisition and there is a judicial determination under the Uniform Declaratory Judgments Act that the acquisition is not in the public interest; or</para><para>(4) The hospital is not fulfilling its commitment under section 71-20,109 or is not following procedures of safeguards committed to under subdivision (3) of such section.</para><para>This section does not limit the right to a hearing under section 71-454 or the right of appeal for a hospital from such decision as provided in section 71-455.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1188, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 105. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Declaratory Judgments Act,</emphasis> see section 25-21,164.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 