<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-2059"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2059</statuteno><catchline>Governmental body; powers.</catchline><para>A political subdivision, state agency, or other governmental entity which owns or operates a hospital or hospital health service shall, relative to the delivery of health care services, have the authority to:</para><para>(1) Enter into agreements with other health care providers to share services or provide a tangible benefit to the hospital and into other cooperative ventures;</para><para>(2) Join or sponsor membership in organizations or associations intended to benefit the hospital or hospitals in general;</para><para>(3) Enter into partnerships;</para><para>(4) Create or merge with other corporations;</para><para>(5) Create or merge with other limited liability companies;</para><para>(6) Have members of its governing authority or its officers or administrators serve without pay as directors or officers of any such venture, organization, association, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation;</para><para>(7) Offer, directly or indirectly, products and services of the hospital or any such venture, organization, association, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation to the general public; and</para><para>(8) Acquire, erect, staff, equip, or operate one or more medical office buildings, clinic buildings, or other buildings or parts thereof for medical services. Such buildings or parts may be freestanding facilities or additions to or parts of an existing hospital or health care facility. Unless the governmental entity declares otherwise, the building or parts shall be considered an addition or improvement to the existing facilities. The governmental entity may lease all or part of such building to one or more health care practitioners or groups of health care practitioners or otherwise allow health care practitioners the use thereof on such terms as the governmental entity deems appropriate. Such lease or other use shall not be required to comply with public bidding requirements or approval of the electorate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 61, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1019, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 430. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 