<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id168">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id170" statutenumber="71-20,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-20,104</statuteno><catchline id="id173">Acquisition
of hospital; approval required; exception; notice; application; procedure.</catchline>
<para>(1) No
person shall engage in the acquisition of a hospital owned by a nonprofit
corporation without first having applied for and received the approval of
the department and without first having notified the Attorney General and,
if applicable, received approval from the Attorney General pursuant to the
Nonprofit Hospital Sale Act. No person shall engage in the acquisition of
a hospital not owned by a nonprofit corporation without first having applied
for and received the approval of the department pursuant to the act unless
such acquiring person is a nonprofit corporation exempt from federal income
tax under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code or is a governmental
entity. For purposes of the act, approval of the department and the Attorney
General shall not be required for the acquisition of a hospital not owned
by a nonprofit corporation as follows: (a) The lease or sale of a county hospital approved under subdivision (3) of section
23-3504; or (b) the dissolution of a hospital
district approved under sections 23-3544 to 23-3546 or the merger of hospital
districts approved under sections 23-3573 to 23-3578.</para>
<para>(2) Any
person not required to obtain the approval of the department under the Nonprofit
Hospital Sale Act shall give the Attorney General at least thirty days' notice
of an impending acquisition, during which time the Attorney General may take
any necessary and appropriate action consistent with his or her general duties
of oversight with regard to the conduct of charities. The notice shall briefly
describe the impending acquisition, including any change in ownership of tangible
or intangible assets.</para>
<para>(3) The
application shall be submitted to the department and the Attorney General
on forms provided by the department and shall include the name of the seller,
the name of the purchaser or other parties to an acquisition, the terms of
the proposed agreement, the sale price, a copy of the acquisition agreement,
a financial and economic analysis and report from an independent expert or
consultant of the effect of the acquisition under the criteria set forth in
section 71-20,108, and all other related documents. A copy of the application
and copies of all additional related materials shall be submitted to the department
and to the Attorney General at the same time. The applications and all related
documents shall be considered public records for purposes of sections 84-712
to 84-712.09.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1188, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB995, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>