<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-2434" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-2434</statuteno><catchline>Local public health department; powers and duties; fees; release of property for human habitation; civil penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The local public health department serving the municipality or county where a clandestine drug lab has been discovered shall monitor the rehabilitation of any contaminated property at such location in accordance with standards and procedures established or approved by the department. The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish such standards and procedures no later than July 15, 2007. Such procedures shall include deadlines for completion of the various stages of rehabilitation and proper disposal of the contaminated property.</para><para>(2) A local public health department may charge and collect fees from the owner or owners of contaminated property to cover the costs directly associated with monitoring the rehabilitation of such property under this section as provided in rules and regulations of the department. A local public health department may contract with other local public health departments or other appropriate entities to assist in the monitoring of such rehabilitation. Upon the completion of such rehabilitation, the local public health department shall release the property for human habitation and commercial or other use in a timely manner.</para><para>(3) The owner or owners of contaminated property shall not permit the human habitation or use of such property until the rehabilitation of such property has been completed and the property has been released for such habitation or use under this section. An owner who knowingly violates this subsection may be subject to a civil penalty not to exceed one thousand dollars. The department shall enforce this subsection. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 915, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>