<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id6" statutenumber="71-3305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3305</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Political subdivision; fluoride added to water supply; exception; ordinance to prohibit addition of fluoride; ballot; vote.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) or (3) of this section, any city or village having a population of one thousand or more inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census shall add fluoride to the water supply for human consumption for such city or village as provided in the rules and regulations of the Department of Health and Human Services unless such water supply has sufficient amounts of naturally occurring fluoride as provided in such rules and regulations.</para><para>(2) Subsection (1) of this section does not apply if the voters of the city or village adopted an ordinance, after April 18, 2008, but before June 1, 2010, to prohibit the addition of fluoride to such water supply.</para><para>(3) If any city or village reaches a population of one thousand or more inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census after June 1, 2010, and is required to add fluoride to its water supply under subsection (1) of this section, the city or village may adopt an ordinance to prohibit the addition of fluoride to such water supply. The ordinance may be placed on the ballot by a majority vote of the governing body of the city or village or by initiative pursuant to sections 18-2501 to 18-2538. Such proposed ordinance shall be voted upon at the next statewide general election after the population of the city or village reaches one thousand or more inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census.</para><para>(4) Any rural water district organized under sections 46-1001 to 46-1020 that supplies water for human consumption to any city or village which is required to add fluoride to such water supply under this section shall not be responsible for any costs, equipment, testing, or maintenance related to such fluoridation unless such district has agreed with the city or village to assume such responsibilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 449, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 245, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 807, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 644; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 559; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB245, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB36, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 53. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>