<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id21" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-3004"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3004</statuteno><catchline>Mental health first aid training
program; Division of Behavioral Health of Department of Health and Human Services;
duties.</catchline><para>(1)
The Division of Behavioral Health of the Department of Health and Human Services
shall establish a mental health first aid training program, using contracts
through the behavioral health regions, to help the public identify and understand
the signs of a mental illness or substance abuse problem or a mental health
crisis and to provide the public with skills to help a person who is developing
or experiencing a mental health or substance abuse problem or a mental health
crisis and to de-escalate crisis situations if needed. The training program
shall provide an interactive mental health first aid training course administered
by the state's regional behavioral health authorities. Instructors in the
training program shall be certified by a national authority for Mental Health
First Aid USA or a similar organization. The training program shall work cooperatively
with local entities to provide training for individuals to become instructors.</para>
<para>(2) The mental
health first aid training program shall be designed to train individuals to
accomplish the following objectives as deemed appropriate considering the
trainee's age:</para><para>(a) Help the public identify, understand, and respond to the signs
of mental illness and substance abuse;</para><para>(b) Emphasize the need to reduce the stigma
of mental illness; and</para><para>(c) Assist a person who is believed to be developing or has developed
a mental health or substance abuse problem or who is believed to be experiencing
a mental health crisis.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB901, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>