<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3612</statuteno><catchline>Communicable tuberculosis; examination required; expense; payment.</catchline><para>The state health officer and each local health officer shall use all available means to detect persons with communicable tuberculosis in his or her jurisdiction. If he or she has reasonable grounds based upon medical science for believing that a person has communicable tuberculosis and if this person refuses to submit to the examination necessary for determining the existence of communicable tuberculosis, the state health officer or local health officer shall issue an order to the person to obtain the appropriate examination. Thereafter, if the person does not comply within seven days, the state health officer or local health officer may institute commitment procedures as described in sections 71-3601 to 71-3604, the purpose of commitment under this section being to determine whether or not the person has communicable tuberculosis.</para><para>The costs of voluntary examination made upon request of the state health officer or local health officer and the cost of examination made upon order of the state health officer or local health officer shall be paid from county general funds of the person's county of residence. If the person is a nonresident or has no permanent residence, the costs shall be paid from the county general funds of the county of commitment. The costs of examination and maintenance while under commitment shall be paid from state funds appropriated to the department therefor. The costs of transportation under the commitment procedure for examination shall be paid from county general funds of the county of residence. If the person is not a resident of Nebraska or has no permanent residence, they shall be paid from the county general funds of the county of commitment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 399, &#167; 12, p. 1277; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1492, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 663; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 95. </para></source></law></legaldoc>