<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3705" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3705</statuteno><catchline>Brain Injury Assistance Program; created; administration.</catchline><para>(1) The Brain Injury Assistance Program is created. The program shall be administered by the Department of Health and Human Services through a contract with the University of Nebraska Medical Center. The program shall provide assistance for individuals with a brain injury by paying for contracts with outside sources that specialize in the area of brain injury. Such outside sources shall operate, at a minimum, statewide, and also in targeted areas as defined and determined in the contract, with individuals with a brain injury; work to secure and develop community-based services for individuals with a brain injury; provide support groups and access to pertinent information, medical resources, and service referrals for individuals with a brain injury; and educate professionals who work with individuals with a brain injury.</para><para>(2) The program may provide assistance with the following activities, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(a) Resource facilitation. Resource facilitation shall be given priority and made available to provide ongoing support for individuals with a brain injury and their families for coping with brain injuries. Resource facilitation may provide a linkage to existing services and increase the capacity of the state's providers of services to individuals with a brain injury by providing brain-injury-specific information, support, and resources and enhancing the usage of support commonly available in a community. Agencies providing resource facilitation shall specialize in providing services to individuals with a brain injury and their families;</para><para>(b) Voluntary training for service providers in the appropriate provision of services to individuals with a brain injury;</para><para>(c) Followup contact to provide information on brain injuries for individuals on the brain injury registry established in the Brain Injury Registry Act;</para><para>(d) Activities to promote public awareness of brain injury and prevention methods;</para><para>(e) Supporting research in the field of brain injury;</para><para>(f) Providing and monitoring quality improvement processes with standards of care among brain injury service providers; and</para><para>(g) Collecting data and evaluating how the needs of individuals with a brain injury and their families are being met in this state.</para><para>(3) Administration costs of the program shall not be more than ten percent of the total expenditures of the program.</para><para>(4) Data collection and evaluation conducted pursuant to this section shall not be a burden or unnecessary hardship to individuals with a brain injury or service providers.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall require a professional, provider, caregiver, or individual to receive training as a condition of receiving or providing nonmedical services to individuals with a brain injury.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB481, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB971, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Brain Injury Registry Act,</emphasis> see section 81-653.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>