<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3508.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3508.01</statuteno><catchline>Radioactive materials license; terms and conditions; termination of license; transfer of land; effect; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any radioactive materials license issued or renewed after August 30, 1987, for any activity which results in the production of byproduct material as defined in subdivision (12)(b) of section 71-3503 shall contain such terms and conditions as the department determines to be necessary to assure that prior to termination of such license:</para><para>(a) The licensee shall comply with decontamination, decommissioning, and reclamation standards prescribed by the department which shall be equivalent, to the extent practicable, or more stringent than those of the federal Nuclear Regulatory Commission for sites (i) at which ores are processed primarily for their source material content and (ii) at which such byproduct material or mill tailings are deposited; and</para><para>(b) Ownership of any disposal site and such byproduct material or mill tailings which resulted from the licensed activity will, subject to subsection (2) of this section, be transferred to (i) the United States or (ii) this state if the state exercises the option to acquire land used for the disposal of such byproduct material or mill tailings. Any license which is in effect on August 30, 1987, and which is subsequently terminated without renewal shall comply with subdivisions (1)(a) and (b) of this section upon termination.</para><para>(2)(a) The department shall require by rule, regulation, or order that prior to the termination of any license which is issued after August 30, 1987, title to the land, including any interests therein, other than land held in trust by the United States for any Indian tribe or owned by an Indian tribe subject to a restriction against alienation imposed by the United States or land already owned by the United States or by the state, which is used pursuant to such license for the disposal of byproduct material or source material mill tailings will be transferred to (i) the United States or (ii) this state, unless the federal Nuclear Regulatory Commission determines prior to such termination that transfer of title to such land and such byproduct material or mill tailings is not necessary or desirable to protect the occupational and public health and safety and the environment or to minimize danger to life or property.</para><para>(b) If transfer to the state of title to such byproduct material or mill tailings and land is required, the state may assume title, following the federal Nuclear Regulatory Commission's determination that the licensee has complied with applicable standards and requirements under the license, and the department shall maintain the byproduct material or mill tailings and land in such manner as will protect the occupational and public health and safety and the environment.</para><para>(c) The department may undertake such monitoring, maintenance, and emergency measures as are necessary to protect the occupational and public health and safety and the environment for those materials and property to which the state has assumed title pursuant to this section.</para><para>(d) The transfer of title to the United States or this state shall not relieve any licensee of liability for any fraudulent or negligent acts done prior to such transfer.</para><para>(e) Title transferred pursuant to this section shall be transferred without cost to the United States or this state other than the administrative and legal costs incurred in carrying out such transfer.</para><para>(3) In the licensing and regulation of byproduct material and source material mill tailings or of any activity which results in the production of byproduct material or mill tailings, the department shall require compliance with applicable standards adopted and promulgated by the department which are equivalent, to the extent practicable, or more stringent than standards adopted and enforced by the federal Nuclear Regulatory Commission for the same purpose, including requirements and standards promulgated by the federal Environmental Protection Agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 390, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 93, &#167; 15. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 