<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id295"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3426"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3426</statuteno><catchline>Lead organization; establish a local team; membership; chairperson; duties.</catchline><para>(1) A lead organization may establish a local team for the lead organization's jurisdiction or for a group of cities, counties, or districts, pursuant to an agreement between multiple lead organizations. If multiple lead organizations decide to form a local team, only one shall fulfill the role of lead organization. The lead organization shall select the members of the local team.</para><para>(2) A local team shall consist of the core members that may include one or more members from the following backgrounds:</para><para>(a) Officials from the lead organization or from another local public health department or such officials' designees;</para><para>(b) Behavioral health providers or officials;</para><para>(c) Law enforcement personnel;</para><para>(d) Representatives of jails or detention centers;</para><para>(e) The coroner or the coroner's designee;</para><para>(f) Health care providers who specialize in the prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of substance use disorders;</para><para>(g) Mental health providers who specialize in substance use disorders;</para><para>(h) Representatives of emergency medical services providers in the county;</para><para>(i) The Director of Children and Family Services of the Division of Children and Family Services of the Department of Health and Human Services or the director's designee; and</para><para>(j) Representatives from the Board of Parole, the Office of Probation Administration, the Division of Parole Supervision, or the Community Corrections Division of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice.</para><para>(3) A local team may also include, either as permanent or temporary members:</para><para>(a) A local school superintendent or the superintendent's designee;</para><para>(b) A representative of a local hospital;</para><para>(c) A health care provider who specializes in emergency medicine;</para><para>(d) A health care provider who specializes in pain management;</para><para>(e) A pharmacist with a background in prescription drug misuse and diversion;</para><para>(f) A substance use disorder treatment provider from a licensed substance use disorder treatment program;</para><para>(g) A poison control center representative;</para><para>(h) A mental health provider who is a generalist;</para><para>(i) A prescription drug monitoring program administrator or such administrator's designee;</para><para>(j) A representative from a harm reduction provider;</para><para>(k) A recovery coach, peer support worker, or other representative of the recovery community;</para><para>(l) A representative from the local drug court; and</para><para>(m) Any other individual necessary for the work of the local team.</para><para>(4) The lead organization shall select a chairperson for the local team. The chairperson shall be an official of the lead organization or such official's designee. The chairperson shall:</para><para>(a) Solicit and recruit members and appoint replacement members to fill vacancies that may arise on the team. In carrying out this responsibility, the chairperson shall, at a minimum, attempt to appoint at least one member from each of the backgrounds or positions described in subsection (2) of this section;</para><para>(b) Facilitate local team meetings and implement the protocols and procedures of the local team;</para><para>(c) Request and collect the records and information needed for the local team's case review. The chairperson shall remove all personal identifying information from any records or information prior to providing it to the local team;</para><para>(d) Gather, store, and distribute the necessary records and information for reviews conducted by the team. The chairperson shall carry out such duties in compliance with all local, state, and federal confidentiality laws and regulations;</para><para>(e) Ensure that team members receive timely notification of upcoming meetings;</para><para>(f) Ensure the team fulfills the requirements of section 71-3427 to publish an annual report, including recommendations to prevent future drug overdose deaths;</para><para>(g) Ensure that all members of the local team and all guest observers and participants sign confidentiality forms as required under section 71-3433;</para><para>(h) Oversee compliance with the Overdose Fatality Review Teams Act and the protocols developed by the team;</para><para>(i) Serve as a liaison for the local team; and</para><para>(j) Perform such other duties as the team deems appropriate.</para><para>(5) Members of the local team shall not receive compensation for their services as team members.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 83. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>