<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id377"><sectno id="id378" opdate="December 1, 2008">Sec. 28.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id379" statutenumber="71-3517"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id381">71-3517</statuteno><catchline id="id382">Violations; civil and criminal penalties; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who violates any of the provisions of the Radiation Control Act shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) In addition to the penalty provided in subsection (1) of this section, any person who violates any provision of the Radiation Control Act or any rule, regulation, or order issued pursuant to such act or any term, condition, or limitation of any license or registration certificate issued pursuant to such act shall be subject to:</para><para>(a) License revocation, suspension, modification, condition, or limitation;</para><para>(b) The imposition of a civil penalty; or</para><para>(c) The terms of any appropriate order issued by the department.</para><para>(3) Whenever the department proposes to subject a person to the provisions of subsection (2) of this section, the department shall notify the person in writing (a) setting forth the date, facts, and nature of each act or omission with which the person is charged, (b) specifically identifying the particular provision or provisions of the section, rule, regulation, order, license, or registration certificate involved in the violation, and (c) of the sanction or order to be imposed. If a civil penalty is imposed, the notice shall include a statement that it can be collected by civil action. The notice shall be delivered to each alleged violator by personal service, by certified or registered mail to his or her last-known address, or by publication. Notice by publication shall only be made if personal service or service by mail cannot be effectuated. The sanction or order in the notice shall become final thirty days after the mailing of the notice unless the applicant, registrant, or licensee, within the thirty-day period, requests, in writing, a hearing before the department. If the notice is served by personal service or publication, the sanction or order shall become final thirty days after completion of such service unless the applicant, registrant, or licensee, within the thirty-day period, requests, in writing, a hearing before the department.</para><para>(4) Hearings held pursuant to subsection (3) of this section shall be held in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department and shall provide for the alleged violator to present such evidence as may be proper. Witnesses may be subpoenaed by either party and shall be allowed fees at a rate prescribed by the rules and regulations of the department. A full and complete record shall be kept of the proceedings.</para><para>(5) Following the hearing, the department shall determine whether the charges are true or not, and if true, the department may (a) issue a declaratory order finding the charges to be true, (b) revoke, suspend, modify, condition, or limit the license, (c) impose a civil penalty in an amount not to exceed ten thousand dollars for each violation, or (d) enter an appropriate order. If any violation is a continuing one, each day of such violation shall constitute a separate violation for the purpose of computing the applicable civil penalty and the amount of the penalty shall be based on the severity of the violation. A copy of such decision setting forth the finding of facts and the particular reasons upon which it is based shall be sent by either certified or registered mail to the alleged violator. The decision may be appealed, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(6) Any civil penalty assessed and unpaid under subsection (5) of this section shall constitute a debt to the State of Nebraska which may be collected in the manner of a lien foreclosure or sued for and recovered in any proper form of action in the name of the State of Nebraska in the district court of the county in which the violator resides or owns property. The department shall, within thirty days from receipt, remit any collected civil penalty to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(7) In addition to the provisions of this section, radon measurement specialists and radon mitigation specialists shall be subject to the reporting, investigatory, and disciplinary provisions of sections 38-176 to 38-185, 38-1,106, 38-1,109 to 38-1,126, and 38-1,137 to 38-1,139. In addition to the grounds for disciplinary action found in the Uniform Credentialing Act, a license issued to a specialist may be disciplined for any violation of the Radiation Control Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 406, &#167; 17, p. 1306; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 172; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 390, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 133; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 573; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1214; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 28.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc> 