<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id473"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3416"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3416</statuteno><catchline>State Domestic Abuse Death Review Team; members; terms; Attorney General; duties; not considered public body; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The State Domestic Abuse Death Review Team is created.</para><para>(2) The Attorney General shall appoint the following members to the State Domestic Abuse Death Review Team:</para><para>(a) At least two survivors of domestic abuse;</para><para>(b) A representative who is an employee of a statewide coalition representing nonprofit organizations that have an affiliation agreement with the Department of Health and Human Services to provide services to victims of domestic abuse under the Protection from Domestic Abuse Act;</para><para>(c) A representative who is an employee of a nonprofit organization that primarily provides services and support to victims of domestic abuse in metropolitan areas;</para><para>(d) A representative who is an employee of a nonprofit organization that primarily provides services and support to victims of domestic abuse in rural areas;</para><para>(e) A representative who is an employee of child advocacy centers;</para><para>(f) A representative who is a member of a federally recognized Indian tribe residing within the State of Nebraska with preference given to a person with experience in domestic abuse;</para><para>(g) A licensed physician or nurse with experience in forensics who is knowledgeable concerning domestic abuse injuries and deaths in Nebraska;</para><para>(h) A licensed mental health professional who is knowledgeable concerning domestic abuse in Nebraska;</para><para>(i) An officer of a law enforcement agency from a metropolitan jurisdiction with experience investigating domestic abuse in Nebraska;</para><para>(j) An officer of a law enforcement agency from a rural jurisdiction with experience investigating domestic abuse in Nebraska;</para><para>(k) An active county attorney or active deputy county attorney with experience prosecuting domestic abuse cases in Nebraska;</para><para>(l) An attorney from the office of the Attorney General; and</para><para>(m) The team coordinator pursuant to subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(3) The remaining members of the State Domestic Abuse Death Review Team shall be appointed as follows: (a) The Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety or designee shall appoint an employee representative of the Nebraska State Patrol; (b) the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services shall appoint an employee representative of the department; and (c) the probation administrator shall appoint an employee representative of the Office of Probation Administration.</para><para>(4) The Attorney General shall be responsible for the general administration of the activities of the team and shall employ or contract with a team coordinator to provide administrative support for the team.</para><para>(5) Members of the team appointed by the Attorney General shall serve four-year terms. The remaining members shall serve two-year terms.</para><para>(6) The team shall not be considered a public body for purposes of the Open Meetings Act. Members of the team shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(7) In appointing members to the team, the Attorney General shall consider persons working in and representing communities that are diverse with regard to race, ethnicity, immigration status, and English proficiency and shall include members from differing geographic regions of the state, including both rural and urban areas.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB741, &#167; 41. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para><para><emphasis>Protection from Domestic Abuse Act,</emphasis> see section 42-901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>