 <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id68"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id70" statutenumber="71-3614"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id72">71-3614</statuteno><catchline id="id73">Cost of drugs and patient care; transportation; payment.</catchline><para>(1) When any person who has communicable tuberculosis and who has relatives, friends, or a private or public agency or organization willing to undertake the obligation to support him or her or to aid in supporting him or her in any other state or country, the department may furnish him or her with the cost of transportation to such other state or country if it finds that the interest of the State of Nebraska and the welfare of such person will be promoted thereby. The expense of such transportation shall be paid by the department out of funds appropriated to it for the purpose of carrying out the Tuberculosis Detection and Prevention Act.</para> <para>(2) No funds appropriated to the department for the purpose of carrying out the act shall be used for meeting the cost of the care, maintenance, or treatment of any person who has communicable tuberculosis in a health care facility on either an inpatient or an outpatient basis, or otherwise, for directed health measures, or for transportation to another state or country, to the extent that such cost is covered by an insurer or other third-party payor or any other entity under obligation to such person by contract, policy, certificate, or any other means whatsoever. The department in no case shall expend any such funds to the extent that any such person is able to bear the cost of such care, maintenance, treatment, or transportation. To protect the health and safety of the public, the department may pay, in part or in whole, the cost of drugs and medical care used to treat any person for or to prevent the spread of communicable tuberculosis and for evaluation and diagnosis of persons who have been identified as contacts of a person with communicable tuberculosis. The department shall determine the ability of a person to pay by consideration of the following factors: (a) The person's age, (b) the number of his or her dependents and their ages and physical condition, (c) the person's length of care, maintenance, or treatment, (d) his or her liabilities, (e) the extent that such cost is covered by an insurer or other third-party payor, and (f) his or her assets. Pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act, the department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for making the determinations required by this subsection.</para> <para>Rules, regulations, and orders in effect under this section prior to July 16, 2004, shall continue to be effective until revised, amended, repealed, or nullified pursuant to law.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1492, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 665; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 97; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 82.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>