<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3411"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3411</statuteno><catchline>Information and records; confidentiality; release; conditions; disclosure; limitations.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) All information
and records acquired by the team in the exercise of its purposes and duties
pursuant to the
Child and Maternal Death Review Act shall be confidential and
exempt from disclosure and may only be disclosed as provided in this section and as provided
in section 71-3407. Statistical compilations of data made by the
team which do not contain any information that would permit the identification
of any person to be ascertained shall be public records.</para>
<para>(b) De-identified information
and records obtained by the team may be released to a researcher, upon proof
of identity and qualifications of the researcher, if the researcher is employed
by a research organization, university, institution, or government agency
and is conducting scientific, medical, or public health research and if there
is no publication or disclosure of any name or facts that could lead to the
identity of any person included in the information or records. Such release
shall provide for a written agreement with the Department of Health and Human
Services providing protection of the security of the content of the information,
including access limitations, storage of the information, destruction of the
information, and use of the information. The release of such information pursuant
to this subdivision shall not make otherwise confidential information a public
record.</para><para>(c)
De-identified information and records obtained by the team may be released
to the United States Public Health Service or its successor, a government
health agency, or a local public health department as defined in section 71-1626
if there is no publication or disclosure of any name or facts that could lead
to the identity of any person included in the information or records. Such
release shall provide for protection of the security of the content of the
information, including access limitations, storage of the information, destruction
of the information, and use of the information. The release of such information
pursuant to this subdivision shall not make otherwise confidential information
a public record.</para><para>(2) Except as necessary to carry
out a team's purposes and duties, members of a team and persons attending
a team meeting may not disclose what transpired at a meeting and shall not
disclose any information the disclosure of which is prohibited by this section.</para>
<para>(3) Members of a team and persons attending a team meeting shall not
testify in any civil, administrative, licensure, or criminal proceeding, including
depositions, regarding information reviewed in or opinions formed as a result
of a team meeting. This subsection shall not be construed to prevent a person
from testifying to information obtained independently of the team or which
is public information.</para>
<para>(4) Information, documents, and records of the team shall not be subject
to subpoena, discovery, or introduction into evidence in any civil or criminal
proceeding, except that information, documents, and records otherwise available
from other sources shall not be immune from subpoena, discovery, or introduction
into evidence through those sources solely because they were presented during
proceedings of the team or are maintained by the team.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>