<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3406</statuteno><catchline>State Child and Maternal Death Review Team; core members;
terms; chairperson; not considered public body; meetings; expenses.</catchline>
<para>(1) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human
Services shall appoint a minimum of twelve and a maximum of fifteen members to the State Child and Maternal Death Review
Team. The core members shall be (a) a physician employed by the department,
who shall be a permanent member and shall serve as the chairperson of the
team, (b) a senior staff member with child protective services of the department,
(c) a forensic pathologist, (d) a law enforcement representative, (e) the Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare, and (f) an
attorney. The remaining members appointed may be, but shall not be limited
to, the following: A county attorney; a Federal Bureau of Investigation agent
responsible for investigations on Native American reservations; a social worker;
and members of organizations which represent hospitals or physicians. The department shall be responsible for
the general administration of the activities of the team and shall employ
or contract with a team coordinator to provide administrative support for
the team.</para>
<para>(2) Members shall serve four-year terms with the exception of the chairperson.
In the absence of the chairperson, the chief executive officer may appoint
another member of the core team to serve as chairperson.</para>
<para>(3) The team shall not be considered a public body for purposes of the
Open Meetings Act. The team shall meet a minimum of four times a year. Members
of the team shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as
provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 648; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 187; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 467, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 563; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB269, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 3.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB269, section 12, with LB361, section 3, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB269 became effective June 5, 2013. Changes made by LB361 became effective September 6, 2013.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>