 <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id35"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id37" statutenumber="71-3601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id39">71-3601</statuteno><catchline id="id40">Terms, defined.</catchline> <para>For purposes of the Tuberculosis Detection and Prevention Act:</para> <para>(1) Communicable tuberculosis means tuberculosis manifested by a laboratory report of sputum or other body fluid or excretion found to contain tubercle bacilli or by chest X-ray findings interpreted as active tuberculosis by competent medical authority;</para> <para>(2) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para> <para>(3) Directed health measure means any measure, whether prophylactic or remedial, intended and directed to prevent, treat, or limit the spread of tuberculosis;</para> <para>(4) Facility means a structure in which suitable isolation for tuberculosis can be given and which is approved by the department for the detention of recalcitrant tuberculous persons;</para> <para>(5) Local health officer means (a) the health director of a local public health department as defined in section 71-1626 or (b) the medical advisor to the board of health of a county, city, or village;</para> <para>(6) Recalcitrant tuberculous person means a person affected with tuberculosis in an active stage who by his or her conduct or mode of living endangers the health and well-being of other persons, by exposing them to tuberculosis, and who refuses to accept adequate treatment; and</para> <para>(7) State health officer means the chief medical officer as described in section 81-3115.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 399, &#167; 1, p. 1273; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 566, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 657; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 576; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 79.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>