<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3407"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3407</statuteno><catchline>Team; purposes; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The purposes of the team shall be to (a) develop an understanding
of the causes and incidence of child deaths in this state, (b) develop recommendations
for changes within relevant agencies and organizations which may serve to
prevent child deaths, and (c) advise the Governor, the Legislature, and the
public on changes to law, policy, and practice which will prevent child deaths.</para>
<para>(2) The team shall:</para>
<para>(a) Undertake annual statistical studies of the causes and incidence
of child deaths in this state. The studies shall include, but not be limited
to, an analysis of the records of community, public, and private agency involvement
with the children and their families prior to and subsequent to the deaths;</para>
<para>(b) Develop a protocol for retrospective investigation of child deaths
by the team;</para>
<para>(c) Develop a protocol for collection of data regarding child deaths
by the team;</para>
<para>(d) Consider training needs, including cross-agency training, and service
gaps;</para>
<para>(e) Include in its annual report recommended changes to any law, rule,
regulation, or policy needed to decrease the incidence of preventable child
deaths;</para>
<para>(f) Educate the public regarding the incidence and causes of child deaths,
the public role in preventing child deaths, and specific steps the public
can undertake to prevent child deaths. The team may enlist the support of
civic, philanthropic, and public service organizations in the performance
of its educational duties;</para>
<para>(g) Provide the Governor, the Legislature, and the public with annual reports which shall
include the team's findings and recommendations for each of its duties. For 2012, 2013, and 2014, the team shall
also provide the report to the Health and Human Services Committee of the
Legislature on or before September 15. The reports submitted to the Legislature
shall be submitted electronically; and</para>
<para>(h) When appropriate, make referrals to those agencies as required in
section 28-711 or as otherwise required by state law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 116; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1160, &#167; 18.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB782, section 116, with LB1160, section 18, to reflect all amendments.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>