<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3406</statuteno><catchline>State Child Death Review Team and State Maternal Death Review Team; members; terms; chairpersons; not considered public body; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services shall appoint a minimum of twelve members each to the State Child Death Review Team and the State Maternal Death Review Team. A person seeking appointment shall apply using an application process developed by the chief executive officer.</para><para>(2) The core members shall serve on both teams and shall be (a) a physician employed by the department, who shall be a permanent member of the teams, (b) a forensic pathologist, (c) a law enforcement representative, (d) a mental health provider, and (e) an attorney.</para><para>(3) Additional required members appointed to the State Child Death Review Team shall include the Inspector General of Nebraska Child Welfare and a senior department staff member with child protective services, who shall be permanent members. The remaining members appointed to the State Child Death Review Team may include, but shall not be limited to, the following: (a) A county attorney; (b) a Federal Bureau of Investigation agent responsible for investigations on Native American reservations; (c) a social worker; and (d) members of organizations which represent hospitals or physicians.</para><para>(4) The remaining members appointed to the State Maternal Death Review Team may include, but shall not be limited to, the following: (a) County attorneys; (b) representatives of tribal organizations; (c) social workers; (d) medical providers, including, but not limited to, the practice areas of obstetrics, maternal-fetal medicine, and anesthesiology; (e) public health workers; (f) community birth workers; and (g) community advocates. In appointing members to the State Maternal Death Review Team, the chief executive officer of the department shall consider members working in and representing communities that are diverse with regard to race, ethnicity, immigration status, and English proficiency and include members from differing geographic regions in the state, including both rural and urban areas.</para><para>(5) The department shall be responsible for the general administration of the activities of the teams and shall employ or contract with team coordinators to provide administrative support for each team and shall provide a team data abstractor for the teams.</para><para>(6) Members shall serve four-year terms with the exception of the permanent members. Each team shall annually elect a chairperson from among its members.</para><para>(7) The teams shall not be considered a public body for purposes of the Open Meetings Act. The teams shall meet a minimum of four times a year. Members of the teams shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 648; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 187; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 467, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 563; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB269, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB741, &#167; 49. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>