<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3409"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3409</statuteno><catchline>Review of child deaths; review of maternal deaths; manner.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The
team shall review all child deaths occurring on or after January 1, 1993, and before January 1, 2014, in
three phases as provided in
this subsection.</para>
<para>(b) Phase one shall be conducted
by the core members. The core members shall review the death certificate,
birth certificate, coroner's report or autopsy report if done, and indicators
of child or family involvement with the Department of Health and Human Services.
The core members shall classify the nature of the death, whether accidental,
homicide, suicide, undetermined, or natural causes, determine the completeness
of the death certificate, and identify discrepancies and inconsistencies.
The core members may select cases from phase one for review in phase two.</para>
<para>(c) Phase two shall be completed
by the core members and shall not be conducted on any child death under active
investigation by a law enforcement agency or under criminal prosecution. The
core members may seek additional records described in section 71-3410. The
core members shall identify the preventability of death, the possibility of
child abuse or neglect, the medical care issues of access and adequacy, and
the nature and extent of interagency communication. The core members may select
cases from phase two for review by the team in phase three.</para>
<para>(d) Phase three shall be a
review by the team of those cases selected by the core members for further
discussion, review, and analysis.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The team shall
review all child deaths occurring on or after January 1, 2014, in the manner
provided in this subsection.</para><para>(b) The members shall review the death certificate,
birth certificate, coroner's report or autopsy report if done, and indicators
of child or family involvement with the department. The members shall classify
the nature of the death, whether accidental, homicide, suicide, undetermined,
or natural causes, determine the completeness of the death certificate, and
identify discrepancies and inconsistencies.</para><para>(c) A review shall not be conducted on any child death
under active investigation by a law enforcement agency or under criminal prosecution.
The members may seek records described in section 71-3410. The members shall
identify the preventability of death, the possibility of child abuse or neglect,
the medical care issues of access and adequacy, and the nature and extent
of interagency communication.</para><para>(3)(a) The team shall review all maternal deaths occurring
on or after January 1, 2014, in the manner provided in this subsection.</para>
<para>(b) The members shall
review the death certificate, coroner's report or autopsy report if done,
and indicators of the woman's involvement with the department. The members
shall classify the nature of the death, whether accidental, homicide, suicide,
undetermined, or natural causes, determine the completeness of the death certificate,
and identify discrepancies and inconsistencies.</para><para>(c) A review shall not be conducted
on any maternal death under active investigation by a law enforcement agency
or under criminal prosecution. The members may seek records described in section
71-3410. The members shall identify the preventability of death, the possibility
of domestic abuse, the medical care issues of access and adequacy, and the
nature and extent of interagency communication.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 649; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>