<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3404"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3404</statuteno><catchline>Act, how cited; child deaths; maternal deaths; legislative
findings and intent.</catchline><para>(1)
Sections 71-3404 to 71-3411 shall be known and may be cited as the Child and
Maternal Death Review Act.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds and declares that
it is in the best interests of the state, its residents, and
especially the children of this state that the number and causes of death
of children in this state be examined. There is a need for a comprehensive
integrated review of all child deaths in Nebraska and a system for statewide
retrospective review of existing records relating to each child death.</para>
<para>(3) The Legislature further
finds and declares that it is in the best interests of the state and its residents
that the number and causes of maternal death in this state be examined. There
is a need for a comprehensive integrated review of all maternal deaths in
Nebraska and a system for statewide retrospective review of existing records
relating to each maternal death.</para><para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature, by creation of the Child and Maternal Death Review Act, to:</para>
<para>(a) Identify trends from the
review of past records to prevent future child
and maternal deaths from similar causes when applicable;</para>
<para>(b) Recommend systematic changes
for the creation of a cohesive method for responding to certain child and maternal deaths; and</para>
<para>(c) When appropriate, cause
referral to be made to those agencies as required in section 28-711 or as
otherwise required by state law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>