<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3504</statuteno><catchline>Radiation control activities; Department of Health and Human Services; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall coordinate radiation control activities and may designate an administrator of radiation control. The administrator shall:</para><para>(a) Advise the Governor and agencies of the state on matters relating to radiation; and</para><para>(b) Coordinate regulatory activities of the state relating to radiation, including cooperation with other states and the federal government.</para><para>(2) The administrator shall:</para><para>(a) Review before and after the holding of any public hearing required under the Administrative Procedure Act, prior to promulgation, the proposed rules and regulations of all agencies of the state relating to use and control of radiation to assure that such rules and regulations are consistent with rules and regulations of other agencies of the state;</para><para>(b) When he or she determines that proposed rules or regulations or parts thereof are inconsistent with rules and regulations of other agencies of the state, make an effort to resolve such inconsistencies. Upon notification that such inconsistencies have not been resolved, the Governor may, after consultation with the department, find that the proposed rules and regulations or parts thereof are inconsistent with rules and regulations of other agencies of the state or the federal government and may issue an order to that effect, in which event the proposed rules and regulations or parts thereof shall not become effective. The Governor may, in the alternative, upon a similar determination, direct the appropriate agency or agencies to amend or repeal existing rules and regulations to achieve consistency with the proposed rules and regulations;</para><para>(c) Advise, consult, and cooperate with other agencies of the state, the federal government, other states, interstate agencies, political subdivisions, and other organizations concerned with control of sources of radiation; and</para><para>(d) Collect and disseminate information relating to the control of sources of radiation and maintain (i) a file of all registrants, license applications, issuances, denials, amendments, transfers, renewals, modifications, inspections, recommendations pertaining to radiation, suspensions, and revocations, (ii) a file of registrants possessing or using sources of radiation requiring registration under the Radiation Control Act and any administrative or judicial action pertaining to such registration, and (iii) a file of all rules and regulations relating to the regulation of sources of radiation, pending or promulgated, and proceedings on such rules and regulations thereon.</para><para>(3) The several agencies of the state and political subdivisions shall keep the administrator fully and currently informed as to their activities relating to development of new uses and regulation of sources of radiation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 406, &#167; 4, p. 1298; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 157, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 390, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 652; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 93, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 567.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>