<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id6" statutenumber="71-3405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3405</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Child and Maternal Death Review Act:</para>
<para>(1) Child means a person from birth to eighteen years of age;</para>
<para>(2) Investigation of child death means a review of existing
records and other information regarding the child from relevant agencies,
professionals, and providers of medical, dental, prenatal, and mental health
care. The records to be reviewed may include, but not be limited to, medical
records, coroner's reports, autopsy reports, social services records, records of alternative response cases
under alternative response demonstration projects implemented in accordance
with sections 28-710.01 to 28-712.01, educational records, emergency
and paramedic records, and law enforcement reports;</para>
<para>(3) Investigation of maternal death means a review of existing
records and other information regarding the woman from relevant agencies,
professionals, and providers of medical, dental, prenatal, and mental health
care. The records to be reviewed may include, but not be limited to, medical
records, coroner's reports, autopsy reports, social services records, educational
records, emergency and paramedic records, and law enforcement reports;</para>
<para>(4) Maternal death means the death of a woman during pregnancy
or the death of a postpartum woman;</para>
<para>(5) Postpartum woman means a woman during the period of time
beginning when the woman ceases to be pregnant and ending one year after the
woman ceases to be pregnant;</para>
<para>(6) Preventable child or maternal death means the death of
any child or pregnant or postpartum woman which reasonable medical, social,
legal, psychological, or educational intervention may have prevented. Preventable
child or maternal death includes, but is not limited to, the death of a child
or pregnant or postpartum woman from (a) intentional and unintentional injuries,
(b) medical misadventures, including untoward results, malpractice, and foreseeable
complications, (c) lack of access to medical care, (d) neglect and reckless
conduct, including failure to supervise and failure to seek medical care for
various reasons, and (e) preventable premature birth;</para>
<para>(7) Reasonable means taking into consideration the condition,
circumstances, and resources available; and</para>
<para>(8) Team means the State Child and Maternal Death Review Team.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB853, &#167; 46.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>