<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3408"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3408</statuteno><catchline>Chairperson; team coordinator; duties; team data abstractor; qualifications; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The chairperson of each team shall:</para><para>(a) Chair meetings of the teams; and</para><para>(b) Ensure identification of strategies to prevent child or maternal deaths.</para><para>(2) The team coordinator of each team provided under subsection (5) of section 71-3406 shall:</para><para>(a) Have the necessary information from investigative reports, medical records, coroner's reports, autopsy reports, educational records, and other relevant items made available to the team;</para><para>(b) Ensure timely notification of the team members of an upcoming meeting;</para><para>(c) Ensure that all team reporting and data-collection requirements are met;</para><para>(d) Oversee adherence to the review process established by the Child and Maternal Death Review Act; and</para><para>(e) Perform such other duties as the team deems appropriate.</para><para>(3) The team data abstractor provided under subsection (5) of section 71-3406 shall:</para><para>(a) Possess qualifying nursing experience, a demonstrated understanding of child and maternal outcomes, strong professional communication skills, data entry and relevant computer skills, experience in medical record review, flexibility and ability to accomplish tasks in short timeframes, appreciation of the community, knowledge of confidentiality laws, the ability to serve as an objective unbiased storyteller, and a demonstrated understanding of social determinants of health;</para><para>(b) Request records for identified cases from sources described in section 71-3410;</para><para>(c) Upon receipt of such records, review all pertinent records to complete fields in child, stillbirth, and maternal death databases;</para><para>(d) Summarize findings in a case summary; and</para><para>(e) Report all findings to the team coordinators.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 431, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB361, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB741, &#167; 51. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>