<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id344"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3432"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3432</statuteno><catchline>Local team meetings; ad hoc participation; confidential information; shared, when; lead organization; powers and duties; local team; consultation agreements.</catchline><para>(1) A chairperson may invite other individuals to participate on the local team on an ad hoc basis for a particular investigation. Such individuals may include those with expertise that would aid in the investigation and representatives from organizations or agencies that had contact with, or provided services to, the overdose victim.</para><para>(2) So long as each individual present at a local team meeting has signed the confidentiality form provided for in section 71-3433, any otherwise confidential information received by the local team may be shared at a local team meeting with any nonmember attendees.</para><para>(3) Local team meetings in which confidential information is discussed shall be closed to the public.</para><para>(4) A lead organization may enter into confidentiality agreements with third-party agencies to obtain otherwise confidential information.</para><para>(5) A lead organization shall enter into a data-use agreement with the prescription drug monitoring program created under section 71-2454.</para><para>(6) A local team may enter into consultation agreements with relevant experts to evaluate the information and records collected by the team. All of the confidentiality provisions of the Overdose Fatality Review Teams Act shall apply to the activities of a consulting expert.</para><para>(7) A lead organization may enter into written agreements with entities to provide for the secure storage of electronic data based on information and records collected in carrying out the local team's duties, including data that contains personal or incident identifiers. Such agreements shall provide for the protection of the security and confidentiality of the information, including access limitations, storage, and destruction of the information. The confidentiality provisions of the Overdose Fatality Review Teams Act shall apply to the activities of the data storage entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB227, &#167; 89. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>