<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id789"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-3420"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3420</statuteno><catchline>Provision of information and records; subpoenas; contempt.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of conducting an investigation, and as necessary to fulfill the purposes of the Domestic Abuse Death Review Act, the team shall be immediately provided the following upon request:</para><para>(a) Records, documents, or other information maintained by a health care provider, mental health provider, or other medical professional, including medical records, mental health records, therapy records, and emergency medical services records; and</para><para>(b) All information and records maintained by any state agency, county or local government, political subdivision, school district, or public or private educational institution, including birth and death certificates; protection orders; dissolution, mediation, custody, and child support agreements; court records, including juvenile cases and dismissed criminal cases; law enforcement agency investigative information and reports; autopsy reports; educational records; Department of Correctional Services information and records; parole and probation information and records; and information and records of any social services agency, including juvenile records, that provided services to the decedent victim, an associated victim, or the perpetrator.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in section 71-3415, the Attorney General shall have the authority to issue subpoenas to compel production of any of the records and information specified in this section.</para><para>(3) Any failure to respond to such subpoena shall be certified by the Attorney General to the district court of Lancaster County for enforcement or punishment for contempt of court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB741, &#167; 45. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>