<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id377"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-3703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-3703</statuteno><catchline>Brain Injury Oversight Committee; created; members; terms; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para> (1) The Brain Injury Oversight Committee is created. The committee shall consist of nine public members and the following directors, or their designees: The Commissioner of Education; the Director of Behavioral Health of the Department of Health and Human Services; and the Director of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services. The Governor shall appoint the nine public members which shall include individuals with a brain injury or family members of individuals with a brain injury, a representative of a public or private health-related organization, a representative of a developmental disability advisory or planning group within Nebraska, a representative of service providers for individuals with a brain injury, and a representative of a nonprofit brain injury advocacy organization.</para><para>(2) The Governor shall appoint the public members within ninety days after July 15, 2020. The Governor shall designate the initial terms so that three members serve one-year terms, three members serve two-year terms, and three members serve three-year terms. Their successors shall be appointed for four-year terms. Any vacancy shall be filled from the same category for the remainder of the unexpired term. Any member of the committee shall be eligible for reappointment. At least one member of the committee shall be appointed from each congressional district.</para><para>(3) The committee shall select a chairperson and such other officers as it deems necessary to perform its functions and shall establish policies to govern its procedures. The committee shall meet at least four times annually, and at any other time as the business of the committee requires, and shall meet at such place as may be established by the chairperson. The public members of the committee shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB481, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>