<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id393">
<sectno id="id394" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 39.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id395" statutenumber="71-4822">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id397">71-4822</statuteno><catchline id="id398">Donor Registry
of Nebraska; establishment; duties; restriction on information.</catchline><para>(1) The federally designated organ procurement organization for Nebraska shall use the information received
from the Department of Motor Vehicles under section 60-494 to establish and
maintain the Donor Registry of Nebraska. A procurement organization located outside of Nebraska may
obtain information from the
Donor Registry of Nebraska when a Nebraska resident is listed
as a donor on the registry and is not located in Nebraska immediately preceding
or at the time of his or her death. The federally designated organ procurement
organization for Nebraska may receive donor
information from sources other than the Department of Motor Vehicles and shall
pay all costs associated with creating and maintaining the Donor
Registry of Nebraska.</para>
<para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature that the Donor Registry of Nebraska facilitate organ
and tissue donations and not inhibit such donations. A person does not need
to be listed on the Donor Registry of Nebraska to
be an organ and tissue donor.</para>
<para>(3) No person shall obtain information from the Donor Registry of Nebraska for the purpose of
fundraising or other commercial use. Information obtained from the Donor Registry of Nebraska may only be used
to facilitate the donation process at the time of the donor's death. General
statistical information may be provided upon request to the federally designated
organ procurement organization for Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 559, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1036, &#167; 39.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>