<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id157"><sectno id="id158" opdate=" April  1, 2008">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id159" statutenumber="71-4631"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id161">71-4631</statuteno><catchline id="id162">Licenses; issuance; denial, refusal of renewal, suspension, or revocation; civil penalty; grounds; notice; hearing; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall issue licenses for the establishment, operation, and maintenance of mobile home parks which are found to comply with the Uniform Standard Code for Mobile Home Parks and such rules, regulations, and standards as are lawfully adopted and promulgated by the department pursuant thereto. </para><para>(2) The department shall deny, refuse renewal of, suspend, or revoke licenses or impose a civil penalty not to exceed two thousand dollars per day on any of the following grounds:</para><para>(a) Violation of any of the provisions of the code or the rules, regulations, and standards lawfully adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto;</para><para>(b) Permitting, aiding, or abetting the commission of any unlawful act; or</para><para>(c) Conduct or utility or sanitation practices detrimental to the health or safety of residents of a mobile home park. </para><para>(3) Should the department determine to deny, refuse renewal of, suspend, or revoke a license or impose a civil penalty, it shall send to the applicant or licensee, by either certified or registered mail, a notice setting forth the specific reasons for the determination. </para><para>(4) The denial, refusal of renewal, suspension, revocation, or imposition of a civil penalty shall become final thirty days after the mailing of the notice in all cases of failure to pay the required licensure fee if not paid by the end of such period, and in all other instances unless the applicant or licensee, within such thirty-day period, shall give written notice of a desire for a hearing. Thereupon the applicant or licensee shall be given opportunity for a formal hearing before the department and shall have the right to present evidence on his or her own behalf. </para><para>(5) The procedure governing hearings authorized by this section shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. On the basis of the evidence presented, the determination involved shall be affirmed or set aside, and a copy of such decision setting forth the findings of facts and the specific reasons upon which it is based shall be sent by either certified or registered mail to the applicant or licensee. The applicant or licensee may appeal such decision, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(6) The department shall remit any collected civil penalty to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 91, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 137; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 18.</para><operativedate>April 1, 2008</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc> 