<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id221"  statutenumber="71-4843"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4843</statuteno><catchline>Effect of anatomical gift on advance health care directive.</catchline><para>(a) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(1) Advance health care directive means a power of attorney for health care or a record signed or authorized by a prospective donor containing the prospective donor's direction concerning a health care decision for the prospective donor;</para><para>(2) Declaration means a record signed by a prospective donor specifying the circumstances under which life-sustaining treatment may be withheld or withdrawn from the prospective donor; and</para><para>(3) Health care decision means any decision regarding the health care of the prospective donor.</para><para>(b) If a prospective donor has a declaration or advance health care directive and the terms of the declaration or directive and the express or implied terms of a potential anatomical gift are in conflict with regard to the administration of measures necessary to ensure the medical suitability of a part for transplantation or therapy, the prospective donor's attending physician and prospective donor shall confer to resolve the conflict. If the prospective donor is incapable of resolving the conflict, an agent acting under the prospective donor's declaration or directive, or, if none or the agent is not reasonably available, a surrogate acting under the Health Care Surrogacy Act or another person authorized by law other than the Revised Uniform Anatomical Gift Act to make health care decisions on behalf of the prospective donor, shall act for the donor to resolve the conflict. The conflict must be resolved as expeditiously as possible. Information relevant to the resolution of the conflict may be obtained from the appropriate procurement organization and any other person authorized to make an anatomical gift for the prospective donor under section 71-4832. Before resolution of the conflict, measures necessary to ensure the medical suitability of the part from a prospective donor may not be administered if it is determined that the administration of those measures would not provide the prospective donor with appropriate end-of-life care or it can be anticipated by reasonable medical judgment that such measures would cause the prospective donor's death other than by the prospective donor's underlying pathology. If the conflict is not resolved expeditiously, the direction of the declaration or advanced directive controls.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1036, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB104, &#167; 22.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Surrogacy Act,</emphasis> see section 30-601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>