<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-4209"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4209</statuteno><catchline>Stroke system of care task force; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall establish a stroke system of care task force to address matters of triage, treatment, and transport of possible acute stroke patients. The task force shall include representation from the department, including a program created by the department to address chronic disease prevention and control issues including cardiovascular health, the Emergency Medical Services Program created by the department, and the Office of Rural Health, the American Stroke Association, the Nebraska State Stroke Association, hospitals designated as comprehensive stroke centers under the Stroke System of Care Act, hospitals designated as primary stroke centers under the act, hospitals designated as thrombectomy-capable stroke centers under the act, rural hospitals, physicians, and emergency medical services licensed pursuant to the Emergency Medical Services Practice Act.</para><para>(2) The task force shall provide advice and recommendations to the department regarding the implementation of the Stroke System of Care Act. The task force shall focus on serving both rural and urban areas. The task force shall provide advice regarding protocols for the assessment, stabilization, and appropriate routing of stroke patients by emergency medical services and for coordination and communication between hospitals, comprehensive stroke centers, primary stroke centers, and other support services necessary to assure all residents of Nebraska have access to effective and efficient stroke care.</para><para>(3) The task force shall recommend eligible essential health care services for acute stroke care provided through telehealth as defined in section 71-8503.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB722, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1034, &#167; 68. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Emergency Medical Services Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>