<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id132"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id134" statutenumber="71-4608"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id136">71-4608</statuteno><catchline id="id137">Violations; penalties; administrative fine.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who is in violation of any provision of the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles regarding a used manufactured home or recreational vehicle or who manufactures unless destined for sale outside the United States, sells, offers for sale, or leases in this state any used manufactured home or recreational vehicle manufactured more than four months after May 27, 1975, which does not bear the federal manufactured-home label or the recreational-vehicle seal issued by this state or by a state which has been placed on the reciprocity list as required by the code shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor. Nothing in the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles shall be construed to require a seal for any recreational vehicle manufactured in this state which is sold or leased outside this state.</para><para>(2) No person shall:</para><para>(a) Manufacture for sale, lease, sell, offer for sale or lease, or introduce, deliver, or import into this state any manufactured home or recreational vehicle which is manufactured on or after the effective date of any applicable standard of the commission which does not comply with such standard;</para><para>(b) Fail or refuse to permit access to or copying of records, fail to make reports or provide information, or fail or refuse to permit entry or inspection as provided in section 71-4610;</para><para>(c) Fail to furnish notification to the purchaser of any manufactured home of any defect as required by 42 U.S.C. 5414 or to the purchaser of any recreational vehicle as provided in section 71-4616;</para><para>(d) Fail to issue a certification required by 42 U.S.C. 5415 or issue a certification to the effect that a manufactured home conforms to all applicable Manufactured Home Construction and Safety Standards, 24 C.F.R. 3280, if such person in the exercise of due care has reason to know that such certification is false or misleading in a material respect;</para><para>(e) Fail to establish and maintain such records, make such reports, and provide such information as the commission may reasonably require to enable it to determine whether there is compliance with the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974, as amended, 42 U.S.C. 5401 et seq., or the standards adopted by the commission for recreational-vehicle construction or fail to permit, upon request of a person duly authorized by the commission, inspection of appropriate books, papers, records, and documents relative to determining whether a manufacturer, distributor, or dealer has acted or is acting in compliance with the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles or with the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974, as amended, 42 U.S.C. 5401 et seq.; or</para><para>(f) Issue a certification pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 5403(a) if such person in the exercise of due care has reason to know that such certification is false or misleading in a material respect.</para><para>(3) Subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall not apply to the sale or the offer for sale of any manufactured home or recreational vehicle after the first purchase of it in good faith for purposes other than resale.</para><para>(4) Subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall not apply to any person who establishes that he or she did not have reason to know in the exercise of due care that such manufactured home or recreational vehicle was not in conformity with applicable Manufactured Home Construction and Safety Standards, 24 C.F.R. 3280, or the standards adopted by the commission for recreational-vehicle construction or any person who, prior to such first purchase, holds a certificate by the manufacturer or importer of such manufactured home or recreational vehicle to the effect that such manufactured home conforms to all applicable Manufactured Home Construction and Safety Standards, 24 C.F.R. 3280, or that such recreational vehicle conforms to the standards adopted by the commission for recreational-vehicle construction unless such person knows that such manufactured home or recreational vehicle does not so conform.</para><para>(5) Any person or officer, director, or agent of a corporation who willfully or knowingly violates subsection (2) of this section in any manner which threatens the health or safety of any purchaser shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(6) The commission may administratively fine pursuant to section 75-156 any person who violates the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated under the code.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 557, &#167; 8, p. 2274; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 300, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 176; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 313, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 132; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 319, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 