<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id61">
<sectno id="id62" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id63" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-4828"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4828</statuteno><catchline>Manner of making anatomical gift
before donor's death.</catchline><para>(a) A donor may make an anatomical gift:</para>
<para>(1)
By authorizing a statement or symbol indicating that the donor has made an
anatomical gift to be imprinted on the donor's driver's license or identification
card;</para><para>(2) In a will;</para><para>(3) During a terminal illness or injury
of the donor, by any form of communication addressed to at least two adults,
at least one of whom is a disinterested witness; or</para><para>(4) As provided
in subsection (b) of this section.</para><para>(b) A donor or other person authorized to
make an anatomical gift under section 71-4827 may make a gift by a donor card
or other record signed by the donor or other person making the gift or by
authorizing that a statement or symbol indicating that the donor has made
an anatomical gift be included on a donor registry. If the donor or other
person is physically unable to sign a record, the record may be signed by
another individual at the direction of the donor or other person and must:</para>
<para>(1)
Be witnessed by at least two adults, at least one of whom is a disinterested
witness, who have signed at the request of the donor or the other person;
and</para><para>(2) State that it has been signed and witnessed as provided in subdivision
(1) of this subsection.</para><para>(c) Revocation, suspension, expiration,
or cancellation of a driver's license or identification card upon which an
anatomical gift is indicated does not invalidate the gift.</para>
<para>(d)
An anatomical gift made by will takes effect upon the donor's death whether
or not the will is probated. Invalidation of the will after the donor's death
does not invalidate the gift.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1036, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>