<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id664"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-4746"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4746</statuteno><catchline>Language assessment program; children from birth through five years of age; scope; report.</catchline><para>(1) The State Department of Education, in collaboration with the Commission for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing, shall establish and coordinate a language assessment program for children who are deaf or hard of hearing. The program shall assess, monitor, and track the language developmental milestones for children from birth through five years of age who are deaf or hard of hearing. The scope of the program shall include children who use one or more communication modes in American Sign Language, English literacy, and, if applicable, spoken English and visual supplements.</para><para>(2) Language assessments shall be given as needed to each child who is deaf or hard of hearing and who is less than six years of age in compliance with the Special Education Act and the federal Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, as such act existed on January 1, 2020. Such language assessments shall be provided in accordance with the provisions of this section and any recommendations adopted pursuant to this section.</para><para>(3) On or before December 31, 2022, and on or before each December 31 thereafter, the State Department of Education and the Commission for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing shall publish a joint report that is specific to language and literacy developmental milestones for each age from birth through five years of age of children who are deaf or hard of hearing, including children who are deaf or hard of hearing and have another disability, relative to such children's peers who are not deaf or hard of hearing. Such report shall be based on existing data annually reported by the State Department of Education in compliance with the federally required state performance plan on pupils with disabilities. The State Department of Education and the Commission for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing shall each publish the report on their respective web sites. The report shall be electronically submitted to the Education Committee of the Legislature and the Clerk of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB965, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Special Education Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1110.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>