<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-4408"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4408</statuteno><catchline>Rabies control authority; pounds; authorized; impoundment; notice; release; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The rabies control authority may authorize an animal pound or pounds or may enter into a cooperative agreement with a licensed veterinarian for the establishment and operation of a pound.</para><para>(2) Any dog or hybrid of the family Canidae found outside the owner's premises whose owner does not possess a valid certificate of rabies vaccination and valid rabies vaccination tag for such dog or hybrid of the family Canidae shall be impounded. The rabies control authority may require the impoundment of domestic or hybrid animals other than dogs or hybrids of the family Canidae. All impounded domestic or hybrid animals shall be given proper care, treatment, and maintenance. Each impounded domestic or hybrid animal shall be kept and maintained at the pound for a period of not less than seventy-two hours unless reclaimed earlier by the owner.</para><para>(3) Notice of impoundment of all animals, including any significant marks of identification, shall be posted at the pound as public notification of impoundment. Any unvaccinated domestic or hybrid animal may be reclaimed by its owner during the period of impoundment by payment of prescribed pound fees and by complying with the rabies vaccination requirement of sections 71-4401 to 71-4412 within seventy-two hours of release. Any vaccinated domestic or hybrid animal impounded because its owner has not presented a valid certificate of rabies vaccination and a valid rabies vaccination tag for such domestic or hybrid animal may be reclaimed by its owner by furnishing proof of rabies vaccination and payment of all impoundment fees prior to release.</para><para>(4) At the expiration of impoundment, a domestic or hybrid animal may be claimed by payment of established pound fees and by compliance with the rabies vaccination requirement of sections 71-4401 to 71-4412 within seventy-two hours of release. If the domestic or hybrid animal is unclaimed at the end of five days, the authorities may dispose of the domestic or hybrid animal in accordance with applicable laws or rules and regulations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 445, &#167; 8, p. 1487; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 104, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB25, &#167; 10.</para></source></law></legaldoc>