<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-4401"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4401</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 71-4401 to 71-4412, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Compendium means the Compendium of Animal Rabies Prevention and Control as published by the National Association of State Public Health Veterinarians;</para><para>(2) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(3) Domestic animal means any dog of the species Canis familiaris, cat of the species Felis domesticus, or ferret of the species Mustela putorius furo, and cat means a cat which is a household pet;</para><para>(4) Hybrid animal means any animal which is the product of the breeding of a domestic dog with a nondomestic canine species;</para><para>(5) Own, unless otherwise specified, means to possess, keep, harbor, or have control of, charge of, or custody of a domestic or hybrid animal. This term does not apply to domestic or hybrid animals owned by other persons which are temporarily maintained on the premises of a veterinarian or kennel operator for a period of not more than thirty days;</para><para>(6) Owner means any person possessing, keeping, harboring, or having charge or control of any domestic or hybrid animal or permitting any domestic or hybrid animal to habitually be or remain on or be lodged or fed within such person's house, yard, or premises. This term does not apply to veterinarians or kennel operators temporarily maintaining on their premises domestic or hybrid animals owned by other persons for a period of not more than thirty days;</para><para>(7) Rabies control authority means county, township, city, or village health and law enforcement officials who shall enforce sections 71-4401 to 71-4412 relating to the vaccination and impoundment of domestic or hybrid animals. Such public officials are not responsible for any accident or disease of a domestic or hybrid animal resulting from the enforcement of such sections; and</para><para>(8) Vaccination against rabies means the inoculation of a domestic or hybrid animal with a United States Department of Agriculture-licensed rabies vaccine administered consistent with its labeling. Such vaccination shall be performed by a veterinarian duly licensed to practice veterinary medicine in the State of Nebraska or licensed in the state where the vaccination was administered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 445, &#167; 1, p. 1484; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 104, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 674; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB25, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 585; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB61, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>