  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-4606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4606</statuteno><catchline>Standards; exception; reciprocity with other states; effect; seal of state on reciprocity list; federal manufactured-home label; validity; restrictions on sale.</catchline><para>If any other state has plumbing, heating, electrical, or body and frame design and construction codes for recreational vehicles at least equal to those established under the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles, the commission, upon determining that such standards are being enforced by such other state, shall place such other state on a reciprocity list, which list shall be available to any interested person. Any recreational vehicle which bears the seal of any state which has been placed on the reciprocity list shall not be required to bear the seal issued by this state. A manufactured home manufactured more than four months after May 27, 1975, which does not bear the federal manufactured-home label issued by this state or by a state which has been placed on the reciprocity list shall not be permitted to be manufactured, offered for sale, sold, or leased by a manufacturer, dealer, or any other person anywhere within this state nor delivered from this state into any other state or jurisdiction unless destined for sale outside the United States. A recreational vehicle manufactured in this state, which is offered for sale, sold, or leased by a manufacturer, dealer, or other person anywhere outside this state, shall not be required to bear the seal issued by this state. If a recreational vehicle has a certificate of title or other certification from a state on the reciprocity list, a dealer may sell it unless he or she has actual knowledge that the recreational vehicle does not meet the standards of the state which has issued a certificate of title or other certification for it, so long as it bears the seal issued by this state or a state on the reciprocity list. No dealer or distributor shall sell a manufactured home or recreational vehicle if it contains a defect, a serious defect, or an imminent safety hazard.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 557, &#167; 6, p. 2273; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 654, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 300, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 313, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 131. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 