<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id366">
<sectno id="id367" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 36.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id368" statutenumber="71-4813"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id370">71-4813</statuteno><catchline id="id371">Eye tissue;
pituitary gland; removal; when authorized.</catchline><para>(1) When an autopsy is performed
by the physician authorized by the county coroner to perform such autopsy,
the physician or an appropriately qualified designee with training in ophthalmologic
techniques, as provided for in subsection (2) of this section, may remove eye tissue
of the decedent for the purpose of transplantation. The physician may also
remove the pituitary gland for the purpose of research and treatment of hypopituitary
dwarfism and of other growth disorders. Removal of the eye tissue or the pituitary
gland shall only take place if the:</para>
<para>(a) Autopsy was authorized
by the county coroner;</para>
<para>(b) County coroner receives
permission from the person having control of the disposition of the decedent's
remains pursuant to section 38-1425; and</para>
<para>(c) Removal of eye tissue
or of the pituitary gland will not interfere with the course of any subsequent
investigation or alter the decedent's post mortem facial appearance.</para>
<para>(2) An appropriately
qualified designee of a physician with training in ophthalmologic techniques
or a funeral director and embalmer licensed pursuant to the Funeral Directing
and Embalming Practice Act upon (a) successfully completing a course in eye
enucleation and (b) receiving a certificate of competence from the Department
of Ophthalmology of the University of Nebraska Medical Center may enucleate
the eyes of the donor.</para><para>(3) The removed eye tissue or pituitary gland
shall be transported to the Department of Health and Human Services or any
desired institution or health facility as prescribed by section 38-1427.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 60, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 130, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 683; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 599; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1220; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1036, &#167; 36.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Funeral Directing and Embalming Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-1401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>