<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-4504"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4504</statuteno><catchline>Palliative Care and Quality of Life Advisory Council; created; duties; members; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Palliative Care and Quality of Life Advisory Council is created. The council shall consult with and advise the Department of Health and Human Services on matters relating to palliative care initiatives. The council shall:</para><para>(a) Survey palliative care providers regarding best practices and recommendations;</para><para>(b) Work with the department; and</para><para>(c) Make recommendations to the department regarding information on the website pursuant to section 71-4503 as standards of care change.</para><para>(2) The council shall be composed of nine members appointed by the Governor for three-year terms. At least two of the members shall be physicians or nurses certified under the Hospice and Palliative Medicine Certification Program administered by the American Board of Internal Medicine. One member shall be an employee of the department familiar with hospice and palliative medicine. The remaining members shall (a) have palliative care work experience, (b) have experience with palliative care delivery models in a variety of settings, such as acute care, long-term care, and hospice care, and with a variety of populations, including pediatric patients, youth patients, and adult patients, or (c) be representatives of palliative care patients and their family caregivers.</para><para>(3) The council shall meet at least twice each calendar year. The members shall elect a chairperson and vice-chairperson. The members shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 but shall not receive any other compensation for such services.</para><para>(4) The department shall provide a place and time for the council to meet and provide staffing assistance as necessary for the meetings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB323, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 65. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>