<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-4728.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4728.05</statuteno><catchline>Interpreter Review Board; members; duties; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall appoint the Interpreter Review Board as required in section 20-156. </para><para>(2) Members of the Interpreter Review Board shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) A representative of the Department of Health and Human Services and the executive director of the commission or his or her designee, both of whom shall serve continuously and without limitation;</para><para>(b) One qualified interpreter, appointed for a term to expire on June 30, 2008;</para><para>(c) One representative of local government, appointed for a term to expire on June 30, 2008;</para><para>(d) One deaf or hard of hearing person, appointed for a term to expire on June 30, 2009;</para><para>(e) One qualified interpreter, appointed for a term to expire on June 30, 2009;</para><para>(f) One deaf or hard of hearing person, appointed for a term to expire on June 30, 2010; and</para><para>(g) One representative of local government, appointed for a term to expire on June 30, 2010.</para><para>(3) Upon the expiration of the terms described in subsection (2) of this section, members other than those identified in subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall be appointed for terms of three years. No such member may serve more than two consecutive three-year terms beginning June 30, 2007, except that members whose terms have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have been appointed and qualified.</para><para>(4) The commission may remove a member of the board for inefficiency, neglect of duty, or misconduct in office after delivering to such member a copy of the charges and a public hearing in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act. If a vacancy occurs on the board, the commission shall appoint another member with the same qualifications as the vacating member to serve the remainder of the term. The members of the board shall receive no compensation but shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 in attending meetings of the commission and in carrying out their official duties as provided in this section and section 20-156.</para><para>(5) The board shall establish policies, standards, and procedures for evaluating and licensing interpreters, including, but not limited to, testing, training, issuance, renewal, and denial of licenses, continuing education and continuing competency assessment, investigation of complaints, and disciplinary actions against a license pursuant to section 20-156. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 22, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 87, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 590; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 67. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>