<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-4728"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>71-4728</statuteno><catchline>Commission; purpose; duties.</catchline><para>The commission shall serve as the principal state agency responsible for monitoring public policies and implementing programs which shall improve the quality and coordination of existing services for deaf or hard of hearing persons and promote the development of new services when necessary. To perform this function the commission shall:</para><para>(1) Inventory services available for meeting the problems of persons with a hearing loss and assist such persons in locating and securing such services;</para><para>(2) License interpreters and video remote interpreting providers under sections 20-150 to 20-159 and prepare and maintain a roster of licensed interpreters as defined in section 20-151. The roster shall include the type of employment the interpreter generally engages in, the type of license held, and the expiration date of the license. Each interpreter included on the roster shall provide the commission with his or her social security number which shall be kept confidential by the commission. The roster shall be made available to local, state, and federal agencies and shall be used for referrals to private organizations and individuals seeking interpreters and video remote interpreting providers;</para><para>(3) Promote the training of interpreters and video remote interpreting providers for deaf or hard of hearing persons;</para><para>(4) Provide counseling to deaf or hard of hearing persons or refer such persons to private or governmental agencies which provide counseling services;</para><para>(5) Conduct a voluntary census of deaf or hard of hearing persons in Nebraska and compile a current registry;</para><para>(6) Promote expanded adult educational opportunities for deaf or hard of hearing persons;</para><para>(7) Serve as an agency for the collection of information concerning deaf or hard of hearing persons and for the dispensing of such information to interested persons by collecting studies, compiling bibliographies, gathering information, and conducting research with respect to the education, training, counseling, placement, and social and economic adjustment of deaf or hard of hearing persons and with respect to the causes, diagnosis, treatment, and methods of prevention of impaired hearing;</para><para>(8) Appoint advisory or special committees when appropriate for indepth investigations and study of particular problems and receive reports of findings and recommendations;</para><para>(9) Assess and monitor programs for services to deaf or hard of hearing persons and make recommendations to those state agencies providing such services regarding changes necessary to improve the quality and coordination of the services;</para><para>(10) Make recommendations to the Governor and the Legislature with respect to modification in existing services or establishment of additional services for deaf or hard of hearing persons. The recommendations submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically;</para><para>(11) Promote awareness and understanding of the rights of deaf or hard of hearing persons;</para><para>(12) Promote statewide communication services for deaf or hard of hearing persons;</para><para>(13) Assist deaf or hard of hearing persons in accessing comprehensive mental health, alcoholism, and drug abuse services;</para><para>(14) Provide licensed interpreters in public and private settings for the benefit of deaf or hard of hearing persons, if private-practice licensed interpreters are not available, and establish and collect reasonable fees for such services; and</para><para>(15) Approve, conduct, and sponsor continuing education programs and other activities to assess continuing competence of licensees. The commission shall establish and charge reasonable fees for such activities. All fees collected pursuant to this section by the commission shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Commission for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing Fund. Such fees shall be disbursed for payment of expenses related to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 101, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 250, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 376, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 25, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 851, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 359, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 22, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 87, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB287, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Telecommunications Relay System Act,</emphasis> see section 86-301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>