<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id292">
<sectno id="id293" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 26.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id294" statutenumber="71-4604.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id296">71-4604.01</statuteno><catchline id="id297">Manufactured
home or recreational vehicle; seals certifying compliance with standards;
exemption; rules and regulations; fees; Public
Service Commission Housing and Recreational Vehicle Cash Fund.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Every manufactured home or recreational vehicle manufactured,
sold, offered for sale, or leased in this state more than four months after
May 27, 1975, and before May 1, 1998, shall comply with the seal requirements
of the state agency responsible for regulation of manufactured homes or recreational
vehicles as such requirements existed on the date of manufacture.</para>
<para>(b) Every manufactured home or recreational vehicle manufactured,
sold, offered for sale, or leased in this state on or after May 1, 1998, shall
bear a seal issued by the commission certifying that the body and frame design
and construction and the plumbing, heating, and electrical systems of such
manufactured home or recreational vehicle have been installed in compliance
with the standards adopted by the commission, applicable at the time of manufacture.
Manufactured homes destined for sale outside the United States shall be exempt
from displaying the seal issued by the state if sufficient proof of such delivery
is submitted to the commission for review. Recreational vehicles destined
for sale or lease outside this state or the United States shall be exempt
from displaying the seal issued by the state if sufficient proof of such delivery
is submitted to the commission for review. The commission shall issue the
recreational-vehicle seal upon an inspection of the plans and specifications
for the recreational vehicle or upon an actual inspection of the recreational
vehicle during or after construction if the recreational vehicle is in compliance
with state standards. The commission shall issue the manufactured-home seal
in accordance with the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety
Standards Act of 1974, 42 U.S.C. 5401 et seq., as such act existed on January
1, 2005. Each seal issued by the state shall remain the property of the commission
and may be revoked by the commission in the event of a violation of the conditions
of issuance.</para>
<para>(2) The commission shall charge a fee in
an amount determined annually by the commission after published
notice and a hearing, for seals issued by the commission. A seal shall be
placed on each manufactured home. The commission shall assess any costs of
inspections conducted outside of Nebraska to the manufacturer in control of
the inspected facility or to a manufacturer requesting such inspection. Such
costs shall include, but not be limited to, actual travel, personnel, and
inspection expenses and shall be paid prior to any issuance of seals.</para>
<para>(3) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
governing the submission of plans and specifications of manufactured homes
and recreational vehicles. A person who submits recreational-vehicle plans
and specifications to the commission for review and approval shall be assessed
an hourly rate by the commission for performing the review of the plans and
specifications and related functions. The hourly rate shall be not less than
fifteen dollars per hour and not more than seventy-five dollars per hour as
determined annually by the commission after published notice and hearing based
on the number of hours of review time as follows:</para>
<para>(a) New model, one hour;</para>
<para>(b) Quality control manual, two hours;</para>
<para>(c) Typicals, one-half hour;</para>
<para>(d) Revisions, three-fourths hour;</para>
<para>(e) Engineering calculations, three-fourths hour;</para>
<para>(f) Initial package, fifteen hours; and</para>
<para>(g) Yearly renewal, two hours plus the three-fourths hour
for revisions.</para>
<para>(4) The commission shall charge each manufacturer an inspection
fee of two hundred fifty dollars for each inspection of any new recreational
vehicle manufactured by such manufacturer and not bearing a seal issued by
the State of Nebraska or some reciprocal state.</para>
<para>(5) All fees collected pursuant to the Uniform Standard Code
for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles shall be remitted to the
State Treasurer for credit to the Public
Service Commission Housing and Recreational Vehicle Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 300, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 617, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 313, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 536, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 677; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 241, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 319, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 26.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>