<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-5311"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5311</statuteno><catchline>Advisory Council on Public Water Supply; established; duties; members; qualifications; terms; vacancy; meetings; officers; quorum; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby established the Advisory Council on Public Water Supply which shall advise and assist the department in administering the Nebraska Safe Drinking Water Act.</para><para>(2) The council shall be composed of seven members appointed by the Governor, (a) one of whom shall be a professional engineer, (b) one of whom shall be a licensed physician, (c) two of whom shall be consumers of a public water system, (d) two of whom shall be operators of a public water system who possess a license issued by the department to operate a public water system. One such operator shall represent a system serving a population of five thousand or less, and one such operator shall represent a system serving a population of more than five thousand, and (e) one of whom shall be, at the time of appointment, (i) an individual who owns a public water system, (ii) a member of the governing board of a public or private corporation which owns a public water system, or (iii) in the case of a political subdivision which owns a public water system, a member of the subdivision's governing board or board of public works or similar board which oversees the operation of a public water system.</para><para>(3) All members shall be appointed for three-year terms. No member shall serve more than three consecutive three-year terms. Each member shall hold office until the expiration of his or her term or until a successor has been appointed. Any vacancy occurring in council membership, other than by expiration of term, shall be filled within sixty days by the Governor by appointment from the appropriate category for the unexpired term.</para><para>(4) The council shall meet not less than once each year. Special meetings of the council may be called by the director or upon the written request of any two members of the council explaining the reason for such meeting. The place of the meeting shall be set by the director. Such officers as the council deems necessary shall be elected every three years beginning with the first meeting in the year 1990. A majority of the members of the council shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. Representatives of the department shall attend each meeting. Every act of the majority of the members of the council shall be deemed to be the act of the council.</para><para>(5) No member of the council shall receive any compensation, but each member shall be entitled, while serving on the business of the council, to receive his or her travel and other necessary expenses while so serving away from his or her place of residence as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 821, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 344, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 719; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 110; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 618; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1229.</para></source></law></legaldoc>