<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-5908"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5908</statuteno><catchline>Rules and regulations.</catchline><para>The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out the Assisted-Living Facility Act, including, but not limited to, rules and regulations which:</para><para>(1) Prohibit the use of chemical or physical restraints at an assisted-living facility;</para><para>(2) Require that a criminal background check be conducted on all persons employed as direct care staff at an assisted-living facility;</para><para>(3) Establish initial and ongoing training requirements for administrators and approved curriculum for such training. Such requirements shall consist of thirty hours of initial training, including, but not limited to, training in resident care and services, social services, financial management, administration, gerontology, and rules, regulations, and standards relating to the operation of an assisted-living facility. The department may waive initial training requirements established under this subdivision for persons employed as administrators of assisted-living facilities on January 1, 2005, upon application to the department and documentation of equivalent training or experience satisfactory to the department. Training requirements established under this subdivision shall not apply to an administrator who is also a nursing home administrator or a hospital administrator; and</para><para>(4) Provide for acceptance of accreditation by a recognized independent accreditation body or public agency, which has standards that are at least as stringent as those of the State of Nebraska, as evidence that the assisted-living facility complies with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the Assisted-Living Facility Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 52. </para></source></law></legaldoc>