<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-5206.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5206.01</statuteno><catchline>Family practice residents; funding
of stipends and benefits; report.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Legislature
may provide funding to the Office of Rural Health for the purpose of funding
the cost of resident stipends and benefits, which funding may include health
insurance, professional liability insurance, disability insurance, medical
education expenses, continuing competency expenses, pension benefits, moving
expenses, and meal expenses in family practice residency programs based in
Nebraska but which are not under a contract pursuant to section 71-5206. The
resident stipends and benefits funded in this section shall apply only to
residents who begin family practice residency training at a qualifying institution
in years beginning on or after January 1, 1993. The total funding provided
in the form of stipend and benefit support per resident to a family practice
residency program under this section shall not exceed the total funding provided
in the form of stipend and benefit support per resident to a family practice
residency program under section 71-5203.</para>
<para>(2) Upon
receiving an itemized statement of the cost of stipends and benefits of a
family practice residency program from a sponsoring institution and upon determining
that the sponsoring institution is not receiving funds under a contract pursuant
to section 71-5206, the office may reimburse such institution fifty percent
of such cost for each family practice resident in the program. The office
may reimburse such institution twenty-five percent of the remaining cost per
family practice resident for each year that one of the program's graduates
practices family medicine in Nebraska, up to a maximum of three years for
each graduate, and an additional twenty-five percent of the remaining cost
per resident for each of the program's graduates who practices family medicine
in an area of Nebraska classified as of January 1, 1991, by the United States
Secretary of Health and Human Services as Medicare Locale 16. The total number
of residents receiving annual financial payments made under this section shall
not exceed nine students during any school year.</para>
<para>(3) At the
end of the third year of the funding under this section, the sponsoring institutions
and the office shall report electronically to
the Legislature regarding the performance of the residency programs and the
placement of residents and physicians for training and practice.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 152, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 241, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 120.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>