
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-5663"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5663</statuteno><catchline>Amount of financial assistance; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) The amount of financial assistance provided through student loans pursuant to the Rural Health Systems and Professional Incentive Act shall be limited to thirty thousand dollars for each recipient for each academic year and shall not exceed one hundred twenty thousand dollars per medical, dental, or doctorate-level mental health student or thirty thousand dollars per master's level mental health or physician assistant student.</para><para>(2) The amount of financial assistance provided through the medical resident incentive program pursuant to the act shall be limited to forty thousand dollars for each recipient for each year of residency and shall not exceed one hundred twenty thousand dollars.</para><para>(3) The amount of financial assistance provided by the state through loan repayments pursuant to the act (a) for physicians, dentists, and psychologists shall be limited to thirty thousand dollars per recipient per year of full-time practice in a designated health profession shortage area and shall not exceed ninety thousand dollars per recipient and (b) for physician assistants, nurse practitioners, pharmacists, physical therapists, occupational therapists, and mental health practitioners shall be limited to fifteen thousand dollars per recipient per year of full-time practice in a designated health profession shortage area and shall not exceed forty-five thousand dollars per recipient.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 400, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 577, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 105; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 962, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB196, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>