<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id260"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="71-5669.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5669.01</statuteno><catchline>Medical resident incentive recipient; agreement; contents.</catchline><para>Each medical resident incentive recipient shall execute an agreement with the department. Such agreement shall be exempt from the requirements of sections 73-501 to 73-510 and shall include, at a minimum, the following terms:</para><para>(1) The medical resident incentive recipient agrees to practice an approved medical specialty the equivalent of one year of full-time practice in a designated health profession shortage area and to accept medicaid patients in his or her practice;</para><para>(2) In consideration of the agreement by the medical resident incentive recipient, the State of Nebraska will provide funding for the repayment of the recipient's qualified educational debts, in amounts up to forty thousand dollars per year for up to three years while in an approved medical specialty residency program in Nebraska. The department shall make payments directly to the medical resident incentive recipient;</para><para>(3) If the medical resident incentive recipient extends his or her residency training but not in an approved specialty, practices an approved specialty in Nebraska but not in a designated health profession shortage area, practices a specialty other than an approved specialty in Nebraska, does not practice the profession for which the loan was given, discontinues practice of the profession for which the loan was given, or practices outside Nebraska, the medical resident incentive recipient shall repay to the state one hundred fifty percent of the outstanding loan principal with interest at a rate of eight percent simple interest per year from the date of default. Such repayment shall commence within six months of the completion or discontinuation of an approved specialty residency training in Nebraska and shall be completed within a period not to exceed twice the number of years for which the medical resident incentive recipient received awards; and</para><para>(4) Any practice or payment obligation incurred by the medical resident incentive recipient under the medical resident incentive program is canceled in the event of the medical resident incentive recipient's total and permanent disability or death.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB196, &#167; 10. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>