<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-5322"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5322</statuteno><catchline>Department; powers and duties.</catchline>
<para>The department shall have the following powers and duties:</para>
<para>(1) The power to establish a program to make loans to owners of public
water systems, individually or jointly, for construction or modification of
safe drinking water projects in accordance with the Drinking Water State Revolving
Fund Act and the rules and regulations of the council adopted and promulgated
pursuant to such act;</para>
<para>(2) The power, if so authorized by the council pursuant to section 71-5321,
to execute and deliver documents obligating the Drinking Water Facilities
Loan Fund or the Land Acquisition and Source Water Loan Fund and the assets
thereof to the extent permitted by section 71-5318 to repay, with interest,
loans to or credits into such funds and to execute and deliver documents pledging
to the extent permitted by section 71-5318 all or part of such funds and assets
to secure, directly or indirectly, the loans or credits;</para>
<para>(3) The duty to prepare an annual report for the Governor and the Legislature. The report submitted to the Legislature
shall be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(4) The duty to establish fiscal controls and accounting procedures
sufficient to assure proper accounting during appropriate accounting periods,
including the following:</para>
<para>(a) Accounting from the Nebraska Investment Finance Authority for the
costs associated with the issuance of bonds pursuant to the act;</para>
<para>(b) Accounting for payments or deposits received by the funds;</para>
<para>(c) Accounting for disbursements made by the funds; and</para>
<para>(d) Balancing the funds at the beginning and end of the accounting period;</para>
<para>(5) The duty to establish financial capability requirements that assure
sufficient revenue to operate and maintain a facility for its useful life
and to repay the loan for such facility;</para>
<para>(6) The power to determine the rate of interest to be charged on a loan
in accordance with the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the
council;</para>
<para>(7) The power to develop an intended use plan, in consultation with
the Director of Public Health of the Division of Public Health, for adoption
by the council;</para>
<para>(8) The power to enter into required agreements with the United States
Environmental Protection Agency pursuant to the Safe Drinking Water Act;</para>
<para>(9) The power to enter into agreements for the purpose of providing
loan forgiveness concurrent with loans to public water systems operated by
political subdivisions with populations of ten thousand inhabitants or less
which demonstrate serious financial hardships. The department may enter into
agreements for up to one-half of the eligible project cost. Such agreements
shall contain a provision that payment of the amount allocated is conditional
upon the availability of appropriated funds;</para>
<para>(10) The power to provide emergency funding to public water systems
operated by political subdivisions with drinking water facilities which have
been damaged or destroyed by natural disaster or other unanticipated actions
or circumstances. Such funding shall not be used for routine repair or maintenance
of facilities;</para>
<para>(11) The power to provide financial assistance consistent with the intended
use plan, described in subdivision (7) of this section, for completion of
engineering studies, research projects to investigate low-cost options for
achieving compliance with safe drinking water standards, preliminary engineering
reports, regional water system planning, source water protection, and other
studies for the purpose of enhancing the ability of communities to meet the
requirements of the Safe Drinking Water Act, to public water systems operated
by political subdivisions with populations of ten thousand inhabitants or
less which demonstrate serious financial hardships. The department may enter
into agreements for up to ninety percent of the eligible project cost. Such
agreements shall contain a provision that payment of the amount obligated
is conditional upon the availability of appropriated funds; and</para>
<para>(12) Such other powers as may be necessary and appropriate for the exercise
of the duties created under the Drinking Water State Revolving Fund Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 517, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB80, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 621; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 122.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>