<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-5303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5303</statuteno><catchline>Public water system; permit; director; powers; hearing; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall operate or maintain a public water system without first obtaining a permit to operate such system from the director. No fee shall be charged for the issuance of such permit.</para><para>(2) The director shall inspect public water systems and report findings to the owner, publish a list of those systems not in compliance, and promote the training of operators. The director may deny or revoke a permit, issue administrative orders scheduling action to be taken, take emergency action as provided in section 71-5304.01, and seek a temporary or permanent injunction or such other legal process as is deemed necessary to obtain compliance with the Nebraska Safe Drinking Water Act.</para><para>(3) A permit may be denied or revoked for noncompliance with the act, the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, or the terms of a variance or exemption issued pursuant to section 71-5310.</para><para>(4) Any person shall be granted, upon request, an opportunity for a hearing before the department under the Administrative Procedure Act prior to the denial or revocation of a permit. The denial or revocation may be appealed, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 821, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 383, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 139; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 713; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 31, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 610; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1224.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>