<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id1112" statutenumber="71-5829.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5829.04</statuteno><catchline id="id1115">Long-term
care beds; moratorium; exceptions; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1)
All long-term care beds which require a certificate of need under section
71-5829.03 are subject to a moratorium unless one of the following exceptions
applies:</para>
<para>(a) An exception to the moratorium may be granted if the department
establishes that the needs of individuals whose medical and nursing needs
are complex or intensive and are above the level of capabilities of staff
and above the services ordinarily provided in a long-term care bed are not
currently being met by the long-term care beds licensed in the health planning
region; or</para>
<para>(b) If the average occupancy for all licensed long-term care beds located
in a twenty-five-mile radius of
the proposed site has exceeded ninety percent
occupancy during the most recent three consecutive calendar quarters as reported
at the time of the application filing and there is a long-term care bed need
as determined under this section, the department may grant an exception to
the moratorium and issue a certificate of need. If the department determines
average occupancy for all licensed long-term care beds located in a twenty-five-mile radius of
the proposed site has not exceeded ninety percent occupancy during the most
recent three consecutive calendar quarters as reported at the time of the
application filing, the department shall deny the application unless the department determines that all long-term care
beds in a licensed facility located in a city of the second class or village
have been sold or transferred to another facility or facilities located outside
of the twenty-five-mile radius of the city or village resulting in no licensed
long-term care beds within the corporate limits of the city of the second
class or village. In such case, the department shall waive the certificate
of need limitations of this subdivision for development and licensure of a
long-term care facility by a political subdivision or a nonprofit organization
in such a city of the second class or village if the political subdivision
or nonprofit organization agrees not to sell long-term care beds licensed
under such waiver or increase the number of long-term care beds as allowed
under subdivision (2) of section 71-5829.03 until five years have passed after
such beds are first occupied. The number of licensed long-term care beds in
the facility shall be limited to the number of long-term care beds sold or
transferred as described in this subdivision.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall review applications which require a certificate
of need under section 71-5829.03 and determine if there is a need for additional
long-term care beds as provided in this section. No such application shall
be approved if the current supply of licensed long-term care beds in the health
planning region of the proposed site exceeds the long-term care bed need for
that health planning region. For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Long-term care bed need is equal to the population of the health
planning region, multiplied by the utilization rate of long-term care beds
within the health planning region, and the result divided by the minimum occupancy
rate of long-term care beds within the health planning region;</para>
<para>(b) Population is the most recent projection of population for the health
planning region for the year which is closest to the fifth year immediately
following the date of the application. The applicant shall provide such projection
as part of the application using data from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln
Bureau of Business Research or other source approved by the department;</para>
<para>(c) The utilization rate is the number of people using long-term care
beds living in the health planning region in which the proposed project is
located divided by the population of the health planning region; and</para>
<para>(d) The minimum occupancy rate is ninety-five percent for health planning
regions which are part of or contain a Metropolitan Statistical Area as defined
by the United States Bureau of the Census. For all other health planning regions
in the state, the minimum occupancy rate is ninety percent.</para>
<para>(3) To facilitate the review and determination required by this section,
each health care facility with long-term care beds shall report on a quarterly
basis to the department the number of residents at such facility on the last
day of the immediately preceding quarter on a form provided by the department.
Such report shall be provided to the department no later than ninety days
after the last day of the immediately preceding quarter. The department shall
provide the occupancy data collected from such reports upon request. Any facility
failing to timely report such information shall be ineligible for any exception
to the requirement for a certificate of need under section 71-5830.01 and
any exception to the moratorium imposed under this section and may not receive,
transfer, or relocate long-term care beds.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 798, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB344, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>