<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id5" statutenumber="71-5905"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5905</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Admission or retention;
conditions; health maintenance activities; requirements; written information provided to applicant for admission.</catchline>
<para>(1) An assisted-living facility shall not admit or retain a
resident who requires complex nursing interventions or whose condition is
not stable or predictable unless:</para>
<para>(a) The resident, if he or she is not a minor and is competent
to make a rational decision as to his or her needs or care, or his or her
authorized representative, and his or her physician or a registered nurse
agree that admission or retention of the resident is appropriate;</para>
<para>(b) The resident or his or her authorized representative agrees
to arrange for the care of the resident through appropriate private duty personnel,
a licensed home health agency, or a licensed hospice; and</para>
<para>(c) The resident's care does not compromise the facility operations
or create a danger to others in the facility.</para>
<para>(2) Health maintenance activities at an assisted-living facility
shall be performed in accordance with the Nurse Practice Act and the rules
and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.</para>
<para>(3) Each assisted-living
facility shall provide written information about the practices of the assisted-living
facility to each applicant for admission to the facility or his or her authorized
representative. The information shall include:</para><para>(a) A description of the
services provided by the assisted-living facility and the staff available
to provide the services;</para><para>(b) The charges for services provided by the assisted-living facility;</para>
<para>(c) Whether
or not the assisted-living facility accepts residents who are eligible for
the medical assistance program under the Medical Assistance Act and, if applicable,
the policies or limitations on access to services provided by the assisted-living
facility for residents who seek care paid by the medical assistance program;</para>
<para>(d) The circumstance
under which a resident would be required to leave an assisted-living facility;</para>
<para>(e) The process
for developing and updating the resident services agreement; and</para>
<para>(f) For facilities
that have special care units for dementia, the additional services provided
to meet the special needs of persons with dementia.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB401, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Medical Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 68-901.</para><para><emphasis>Nurse Practice Act,</emphasis> see section 38-2201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
