<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id458" statutenumber="71-5661"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5661</statuteno><catchline id="id461">Financial incentives; funding; Rural Health Professional Incentive Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The financial incentives provided by the Rural Health Systems and Professional Incentive Act shall consist of (a) student loans to eligible students for attendance at an eligible school as determined pursuant to section 71-5662, (b) the repayment of qualified educational debts owed by physicians in an approved medical specialty residency program in Nebraska as determined pursuant to section 71-5662, and (c) the repayment of qualified educational debts owed by eligible health professionals as determined pursuant to section 71-5662. Funds for such incentives shall be appropriated from the General Fund to the department for such purposes.</para><para>(2) The Rural Health Professional Incentive Fund is created. The fund shall be used to carry out the purposes of the act, except that transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Money credited pursuant to section 71-5670.01 and payments received pursuant to sections 71-5666, 71-5668, and 71-5669.01 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Rural Health Professional Incentive Fund. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 400, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 242, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 214, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB196, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>