<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-5654"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5654</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Rural Health Advisory Commission; created; members; appointment; terms.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Rural Health Advisory Commission is hereby created as the direct and only successor to the Commission on Rural Health Manpower. The Nebraska Rural Health Advisory Commission shall consist of thirteen members as follows:</para><para>(1) The Director of Public Health of the Division of Public Health or his or her designee and another representative of the Department of Health and Human Services; and</para><para>(2) Eleven members to be appointed by the Governor with the advice and consent of the Legislature as follows:</para><para>(a) One representative of each medical school located in the state involved in training family physicians and one physician in family practice residency training; and</para><para>(b) From rural areas one physician, one consumer representative, one hospital administrator, one nursing home administrator, one nurse, one physician assistant, one mental health practitioner or psychologist licensed under the requirements of section 38-3114 or the equivalent thereof, and one dentist.</para><para>Members shall serve for terms of three years. When a vacancy occurs, appointment to fill the vacancy shall be made for the balance of the term. All appointed members shall be citizens and residents of Nebraska. The appointed membership of the commission shall, to the extent possible, represent the three congressional districts equally.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 400, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 728; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1155, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 577, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 411, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 626; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1233.</para></source></law></legaldoc>