<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-5308"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-5308</statuteno><catchline>License; application; issuance; disciplinary actions; grounds; existing certificate holder; how treated.</catchline><para>Application for a license to act as a licensed operator of a public water system shall be made as provided in the Uniform Credentialing Act. The department shall establish and collect fees for licenses as provided in sections 38-151 to 38-157. An operator shall be licensed in the same manner as an individual under subsection (1) of section 38-121 and shall be subject to the reporting, investigatory, and disciplinary provisions of sections 38-176 to 38-185, 38-1,106, 38-1,109 to 38-1,126, and 38-1,137 to 38-1,139. In addition to the grounds for disciplinary action found in the Uniform Credentialing Act, a license issued under the Nebraska Safe Drinking Water Act may be disciplined for any violation of the act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.</para><para>An individual holding a certificate as a certified operator of a public water system under the Nebraska Safe Drinking Water Act on December 1, 2008, shall be deemed to be holding a license under the Uniform Credentialing Act and the Nebraska Safe Drinking Water Act on such date. The certificate holder may continue to practice under such certificate as a license in accordance with such acts until the certificate would have expired under its terms.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 821, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 190; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1021, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1227.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>