<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6310.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6310.03</statuteno><catchline>Project designer or project monitor; duties.</catchline><para>If a project designer or a project monitor is selected by the structure's owner or operator for an asbestos project, the project designer and project monitor shall be responsible for the following:</para><para>(1) Project designers shall prepare plans and specifications for business entities conducting asbestos projects. The plans and specifications shall be consistent with the criteria, requirements, and best interests of the structure's owner or operator and the requirements of the Asbestos Control Act. The project designer shall represent the owner or operator and ensure that these objectives are achieved by the business entity conducting the project throughout the project;</para><para>(2) Prior to preparing plans and specifications for any renovation project, a project designer shall ensure that any equipment items and any structural items of a structure affected by the renovation were inspected and assessed by a licensed inspector. Prior to preparing plans and specifications for any demolition, a project designer shall ensure that the entire structure was inspected and assessed by a licensed inspector. No dismantling or salvage operation shall begin before the inspection and assessment is completed;</para><para>(3) If a project designer or project monitor is selected by the owner or operator of the structure on or in which the asbestos project is conducted, he or she shall be independent of the business entity selected to perform the asbestos project. A private or public business entity which uses its own trained and licensed employees to perform asbestos projects may also use its own employees who are trained and licensed as project designers or project monitors to design and monitor projects conducted on or in its own structures; and</para><para>(4) If a project designer or project monitor is selected by the structure's owner or operator for an asbestos project, the project designer or project monitor shall oversee the activities of a business entity conducting an asbestos project to ensure that the requirements of the Asbestos Control Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act are met. Prior to allowing an asbestos project site to be returned to normal occupancy or function, a project designer or project monitor shall ensure that all waste, debris, and residue have been removed from the site in compliance with the act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 78; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1253.</para></source></law></legaldoc>