<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6723"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6723</statuteno><catchline>Administration of medication; methods authorized; conditions; additional methods; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A medication aide, a person licensed to operate a child care facility or a staff member of a child care facility, or a staff member of a school may provide routine medications by the following routes: (a) Oral; (b) inhalation; (c) topical; and (d) instillation into the eyes, ears, and nose.</para><para>(2) A medication aide, a person licensed to operate a child care facility or a staff member of a child care facility, or staff member of a school may provide medication by additional routes not listed in subsection (1) of this section, provide PRN medication, or participate in observing and reporting for monitoring medications only under the following conditions:</para><para>(a) A determination has been made by a competent individual, a caretaker, or a licensed health care professional and placed in writing that the medication aide, person licensed to operate a child care facility or staff member of a child care facility, or staff member of a school is competent to perform these activities; and</para><para>(b) It has been determined by a licensed health care professional and placed in writing that these activities can be done safely for a specified recipient.</para><para>Direction for additional routes not listed in subsection (1) of this section must be for recipient-specific procedures and must be in writing. Direction for PRN medication must be in writing and include the parameters for provision of the PRN medication. Direction for observing and reporting for monitoring medication must be in writing and include the parameters for the observation and reporting. A medication aide, a person licensed to operate a child care facility or a staff member of a child care facility, or a staff member of a school acting under this subsection shall comply with the written directions. Subdivision (b) of this subsection does not apply to nonprescription drugs when direction and monitoring is done by a competent individual for himself or herself or by a caretaker.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1354, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 