<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6602"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6602</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in sections 71-6601 to 71-6615, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Activities of daily living means assistance with ambulation, bathing, toileting, feeding, and similar activities;</para><para>(2) Basic therapeutic care means basic health care procedures, including, but not limited to, measuring vital signs, applying hot and cold applications and nonsterile dressings, and assisting with, but not administering, internal and external medications which are normally self-administered. Basic therapeutic care does not include health care procedures which require the exercise of nursing or medical judgment;</para><para>(3) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(4) Home health agency means a home health agency as defined in section 71-417;</para><para>(5) Home health aide means a person who is employed by a home health agency to provide personal care, assistance with the activities of daily living, and basic therapeutic care to patients of the home health agency;</para><para>(6) Personal care means hair care, nail care, shaving, dressing, oral care, and similar activities;</para><para>(7) Supervised practical training means training in a laboratory or other setting in which the trainee demonstrates knowledge while performing tasks on an individual under the direct supervision of a registered nurse or licensed practical nurse; and</para><para>(8) Vital signs means temperature, pulse, respiration, and blood pressure.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1100, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 765; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1354, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 662; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB824, &#167; 2.</para></source></law>
</legaldoc>