  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6608.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6608.02</statuteno><catchline>Home health aide competency evaluation; requirements.</catchline><para>If a competency evaluation is required by section 71-6603, the home health agency shall be responsible for ensuring that the individuals who furnish home health aide services on its behalf meet the competency evaluation requirements of this section. A home health aide competency evaluation shall address each of the subjects listed in subdivisions (1)(b) through (1)(m) of section 71-6608.01. The competency evaluation may be offered by any organization except as specified in subdivision (4) of such section. The competency evaluation shall be performed by a registered nurse. The subject areas listed in subdivisions (1)(c) and (1)(i) through (1)(k) of such section shall be evaluated after observation of the aide's performance of the tasks with a patient or other individual. The other subject areas in subdivision (1) of such section shall be evaluated through written examination or oral examination or after observation of a home health aide with a patient or other individual. A home health aide shall not be considered competent in any task for which he or she is evaluated as unsatisfactory, and the home health aide shall not perform that task without direct supervision by a Nebraska-licensed nurse until after he or she receives training in the task for which he or she was evaluated as unsatisfactory and subsequently is evaluated as satisfactory. A home health aide shall not be considered to have successfully passed a competency evaluation if the aide has been evaluated as unsatisfactory in more than one of the required areas. The home health agency shall maintain documentation which demonstrates that the requirements of this section are met.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 60. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 