<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id17" statutenumber="71-6405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6405</statuteno><catchline id="id20">State building code; compliance required.</catchline><para>(1) All state agencies, including all state constitutional offices, state administrative departments, and state boards and commissions, the University of Nebraska, and the Nebraska state colleges, shall comply with the state building code. The state building code shall be the legally applicable code in all buildings and structures owned by the state or any state agency regardless of whether the state, state agency, or applicable county, city, or village has provided for the administration or enforcement of the state building code.</para><para>(2) No state agency may adopt, promulgate, or enforce any rule or regulation in conflict with the state building code unless otherwise specifically authorized by statute to (a) adopt, promulgate, or enforce any rule or regulation in conflict with the state building code or (b) adopt or enforce a building or construction code other than the state building code.</para><para>(3) Nothing in the Building Construction Act shall authorize any state agency to apply such act to manufactured homes or recreational vehicles regulated by the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles or to modular housing units regulated by the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 227, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 319, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1304, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 643, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB799, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB546, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1001, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB590, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB131, &#167; 22. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1555.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles,</emphasis> see section 71-4601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>