<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id14">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id16" statutenumber="71-6901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6901</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of sections 71-6901 to 71-6911:</para>
<para>(1) Abortion means the act of using or prescribing
any instrument, medicine, drug, or any other substance, device, or means with
the intent to terminate the clinically diagnosable pregnancy of a woman with
knowledge that the termination by those means will with reasonable likelihood
cause the death of the unborn child. Such use, prescription, or means is not
an abortion if done with the intent to:</para><para>(a) Save the life or preserve the health
of an unborn child;</para><para>(b) Remove a dead unborn child caused by a spontaneous abortion;
or</para><para>(c) Remove an ectopic pregnancy;</para><para>(2) Coercion means restraining or dominating
the choice of a pregnant woman by force, threat of force, or deprivation of
food and shelter;</para><para>(3) Consent means a declaration acknowledged before a notary public
and signed by a parent or legal guardian of the pregnant woman or an alternate
person as described in section 71-6902.01 declaring that the principal has
been informed that the pregnant woman intends to undergo a procedure pursuant
to subdivision (1) of section 71-6901 and that the principal consents to the
procedure;</para><para>(4) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para>
<para>(5) Emancipated
means a situation in which a person under eighteen years of age has been married
or legally emancipated;</para><para>(6) Facsimile copy means a copy generated by a system that encodes
a document or photograph into electrical signals, transmits those signals
over telecommunications lines, and then reconstructs the signals to create
an exact duplicate of the original document at the receiving end;</para>
<para>(7) Incompetent
means any person who has been adjudged a disabled person and has had a guardian
appointed under sections 30-2617 to 30-2629;</para><para>(8) Medical emergency
means a condition that, on the basis of the physician's good-faith clinical
judgment, so complicates the medical condition of a pregnant woman as to necessitate
the immediate abortion of her pregnancy to avert her death or for which a
delay will create serious risk of substantial and irreversible impairment
of a major bodily function;</para><para>(9) Physician means any person licensed
to practice medicine in this state as provided in the Uniform Credentialing
Act. Physician includes a person who practices osteopathy; and</para>
<para>(10) Pregnant
woman means an unemancipated woman under eighteen years of age who is pregnant
or a woman for whom a guardian has been appointed pursuant to sections 30-2617
to 30-2629 because of a finding of incapacity, disability, or incompetency
who is pregnant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 425, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB690, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
