<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id340"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6409"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6409</statuteno><catchline>Building permit; inspections; how conducted.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Authorized inspector means an individual credentialed with the state agency, county, city, or village issuing permits or a third-party inspector registered or licensed with the State of Nebraska contracted as a result of project specification requirements. Authorized inspector does not include an individual performing a self-performed inspection for the individual's own permit or building; and</para><para>(b) Inspection records means the pass or fail results, including the reasons for failure or deviation from project specifications, of any inspection required by the permitting entity as a condition of construction in association with the address of the permit requested or issued.</para><para>(2)(a) Any state agency, county, city, or village that requires an inspection as part of a building permit may allow for virtual inspection by an authorized inspector if the following conditions are met:</para><para>(i) The inspection is of an area of a single-family or two-family residential building that is less than three stories in height and under ten thousand square feet;</para><para>(ii) The individual requesting or holding the building permit has provided the name of the contractor who is licensed or registered in such state, county, city, or village and who is completing the work to be virtually inspected; and</para><para>(iii) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, the virtual inspection is conducted live with both the individual requesting or holding the building permit and the authorized inspector.</para><para>(b) Inspections required for building permits of a nonstructural nature, as determined by the permitting entity, may be conducted using video or photo documentation for any reinspection.</para><para>(3) Any state agency, county, city, or village that utilizes virtual inspections shall not be required to publicize the name of the contractor who is provided in subdivision (2)(a) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB441, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>