<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id5" statutenumber="71-6403"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6403</statuteno><catchline id="id8">State building code; adopted; amendments.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the state building code. The Legislature hereby adopts by reference:</para><para>(a) The International Building Code (IBC), 2018 edition, except section 101.4.3 and chapter 29, published by the International Code Council, except that (i) section 305.2.3 applies to a facility having twelve or fewer children and (ii) section 310.4.1 applies to a care facility for twelve or fewer persons;</para><para>(b) The International Residential Code (IRC), 2018 edition, except section R313 and chapters 25 through 33, published by the International Code Council;</para><para>(c) The International Existing Building Code, 2018 edition, except section 809, published by the International Code Council; and</para><para>(d) The Uniform Plumbing Code, 2018 edition, designated by the American National Standards Institute as an American National Standard.</para><para>(2) The codes adopted by reference in subsection (1) of this section and the minimum standards for radon resistant new construction adopted under section 76-3504 shall constitute the state building code except as amended pursuant to the Building Construction Act or as otherwise authorized by state law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 227, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 319, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1304, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 643, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB799, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB546, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB540, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB590, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB130, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB348, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB405, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB131, &#167; 21. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>