<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6326"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6326</statuteno><catchline>Individuals; license required; qualifications; term; renewal; applications; current certificate holder; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) An individual shall not be eligible to work on an abatement project unless the individual holds a license issued by the department.</para><para>(2) The department shall issue the following classes of licenses: Worker, supervisor, inspector, risk assessor, visual lead-hazard advisor, elevated blood-lead level inspector, and project designer. To qualify for a license of a particular class, an individual shall have (a) successfully completed a training course approved or administered by the department, (b) passed an examination approved or administered by the department with at least the minimum score prescribed by the department, and (c) for the classes of worker and supervisor, been examined by a physician within the preceding year and declared by the physician to be physically capable of working while wearing a respirator.</para><para>(3) An individual holding such a certificate on December 1, 2008, shall be deemed to be holding a license under the Residential Lead-Based Paint Professions Practice Act and the Uniform Credentialing Act on such date. The certificate holder may continue to practice under such certificate as a license in accordance with such acts until the certificate would have expired under its terms.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 196; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 863, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1277.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>