<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id140">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id142" statutenumber="71-6223"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6223</statuteno><catchline id="id145">Letter of intent;
application; contents.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant group shall submit a letter
of intent to file an application to the director on forms prescribed by the
director. The letter of intent shall identify the applicant group, the proposed
regulation or change in scope of practice sought, and information sufficient
for the director to determine whether the application is eligible for review.</para>
<para>(2) The director shall notify
the applicant group as to whether it is eligible for review within fifteen
days after the receipt of the letter
of intent. The final application shall be submitted to the director who shall
notify the applicant group of its acceptance for review within fifteen days after receipt of the final application. If more
than one application is received in a given year, the director may establish
the order in which applications shall be reviewed.</para>
<para>(3) The application shall
include an explanation of:</para>
<para>(a) The problem created by not regulating
a health professional group not previously regulated or by not changing the
scope of practice of a regulated health profession;</para><para>(b) If the application
is for the regulation of a health professional group not previously regulated,
all feasible methods of regulation, including those methods listed in section
71-6222, and the impact of such methods on the public;</para>
<para>(c) The benefit
to the public of regulating a health professional group not previously regulated
or changing the scope of practice of a regulated health profession;</para>
<para>(d) The extent to which regulation
or the change of scope of practice might harm the public;</para>
<para>(e) The type of standards that exist to
ensure that a practitioner of a health profession would maintain competency;</para>
<para>(f) A description of the health professional group
proposed for regulation, including a list of associations, organizations,
and other groups representing the practitioners in this state, an estimate
of the number of practitioners in each group, and whether the groups represent
different levels of practice;</para>
<para>(g) The role
and availability of third-party reimbursement for the services provided by
the applicant group;</para><para>(h) The experience of other jurisdictions in regulating the practitioners
affected by the application;</para><para>(i) The expected costs of regulation, including (i) the impact registration, certification,
or licensure will have on the costs of the services to the public and (ii) the cost to the state and to the general
public of implementing the proposed legislation; and</para>
<para>(j) Other
information relevant to the requested review as determined by the division.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 407, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 384, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB834, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>