<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id186">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id188" statutenumber="71-6226"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6226</statuteno><catchline id="id191">Director; prepare
final report; recommendations.</catchline><para>(1) After receiving
and considering reports from the committee or the board, the director shall
prepare a final report for the Legislature. The final report shall include
copies of the committee report and the board report, if any, but the director
shall not be bound by the findings and recommendations of such reports. The
director in compiling his or her report shall apply the criteria established
in sections 71-6221 to 71-6223 and may consult with the board or the committee.
The recommendation of the director shall be developed in a manner consistent
with subsection (4) of section 71-6224. The
final report shall be submitted electronically to
the Speaker of the Legislature, the Chairperson of the Executive Board of
the Legislature, and the Chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee
of the Legislature no later than twelve months after the application
is submitted to the director and found
to be complete and shall be made available electronically to all other members of the Legislature
upon request.</para>
<para>(2) The director may recommend that no legislative action
be taken on an application. If the director recommends that an application
of an applicant group be approved, the director shall recommend an agency
to be responsible for the regulation and the level of regulation to be assigned
to such applicant group.</para>
<para>(3) An application which is resubmitted shall be considered
the same as a new application.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 407, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 384, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB834, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>