<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6319.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6319.02</statuteno><catchline>Abatement or abatement project, defined.</catchline><para>Abatement or abatement project means any measure or set of measures designed to permanently eliminate lead-based paint hazards. Abatement includes, but is not limited to:</para><para>(1) The removal of lead-based paint and lead-contaminated dust, the permanent enclosure or encapsulation of lead-based paint, the replacement of lead-painted surfaces or fixtures, and the removal or covering of lead-contaminated soil;</para><para>(2) All preparation, cleanup, disposal, and post-abatement clearance testing activities associated with such measures; and</para><para>(3)(a) Projects for which there is a written contract or other documentation which provides that a firm or an individual will be conducting activities in or to a residential dwelling or child-occupied facility that (i) will result in the permanent elimination of lead-based paint hazards or (ii) are designed to permanently eliminate lead-based paint hazards and are described in subdivision (1) or (2) of this section;</para><para>(b) Projects resulting in the permanent elimination of lead-based paint hazards conducted by firms or individuals licensed in accordance with the Residential Lead-Based Paint Professions Practice Act unless such projects are excluded from the definition of abatement or abatement project under this section;</para><para>(c) Projects resulting in the permanent elimination of lead-based paint hazards conducted by firms or individuals who or which, through company name or promotional literature, hold themselves out to be in the business of performing lead-based paint activities unless such projects are excluded from the definition of abatement or abatement project under this section; or</para><para>(d) Projects resulting in the permanent elimination of lead-based paint hazards that are conducted in response to state or local abatement orders.</para><para>Abatement does not include renovation, remodeling, landscaping, or other activities when such activities are not designed to permanently eliminate lead-based paint hazards but instead are designed to repair, restore, or remodel a structure or dwelling even if such activities may incidentally result in a reduction or elimination of lead-based paint hazards. Abatement does not include interim controls, operations, and maintenance activities or other measures and activities designed to temporarily but not permanently reduce lead-based paint hazards.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 863, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1263.</para></source></law></legaldoc>