<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id805"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6105"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6105</statuteno><catchline>Interior design registry; created; listing; term; eligibility; examinations.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The interior design registry is created.</para><para>(b) The State Treasurer shall list each interior designer registration in the registry. A listing in the registry shall be valid for the term of the registration and upon renewal unless such listing is refused renewal or is removed as provided in the Interior Design Voluntary Registration Act.</para><para>(c) The registry shall contain (i) the individual's full name and (ii) any other information as the State Treasurer may require by rules and regulations.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this section or section 71-6107, the following shall be considered as the minimum evidence satisfactory to the State Treasurer that an applicant is eligible for listing on the interior design registry:</para><para>(a) Education eligibility as outlined by the Council for Interior Design Qualification to sit for an examination on technical and professional subjects of interior design as required by the council;</para><para>(b) Experience eligibility as outlined by the Council for Interior Design Qualification to sit for an examination on technical and professional subjects of interior design as required by the council;</para><para>(c) Successful passage of an examination on technical and professional subjects of interior design as required by the Council for Interior Design Qualification;</para><para>(d) Passage of an examination on the statutes, rules and regulations, and other requirements unique to this state regarding the practice of registered interior design; and</para><para>(e) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the State Treasurer shall be included in the application for registration.</para><para>(3) An individual holding a credential to practice interior design issued by a proper authority of any jurisdiction, based on credentials that do not conflict with subsection (2) of this section, may, upon application, be listed on the interior design registry after:</para><para>(a) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules and regulations, and other requirements unique to this state regarding the practice of registered interior design; and</para><para>(b) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the State Treasurer shall be included in the application for registration.</para><para>(4) An individual who holds a current and valid certification issued by the Council for Interior Design Qualification and who submits satisfactory evidence of such certification to the State Treasurer may, upon application, be listed on the interior design registry after:</para><para>(a) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules and regulations, and other requirements unique to this state regarding the practice of registered interior design; and</para><para>(b) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the State Treasurer shall be included in the application for registration.</para><para>(5) An individual who has been credentialed to practice interior design for fifteen years or more in one or more jurisdictions and who has practiced interior design for fifteen years in compliance with the credentialing laws in the jurisdictions where such individual interior design practice has occurred since initial issuance of the credential may, upon application, be listed on the interior design registry after:</para><para>(a) Successful passage of an examination on the statutes, rules and regulations, and other requirements unique to this state regarding the practice of registered interior design; and</para><para>(b) Demonstration of good reputation and good ethical character by attestation of references. The names and complete addresses of references acceptable to the State Treasurer shall be included in the application for registration.</para><para>(6) None of the examination materials described in this section shall be considered public records.</para><para>(7) The State Treasurer or the State Treasurer's agent shall direct the time and place of the interior design examinations referenced in this section.</para><para>(8) The State Treasurer may adopt the examinations and grading procedures of the Council for Interior Design Qualification. The State Treasurer may also adopt guidelines published by the council.</para><para>(9) Registration shall be effective upon listing in the registry.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB16, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>