<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6323"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6323</statuteno><catchline>License; application; contents; current certificate holder; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) To apply for a license, a firm shall submit an application to the department in the form required by the department and shall pay the fee prescribed by the department.</para><para>(2) The application shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) The name, address, and nature of the firm;</para><para>(b) A statement that all individuals who will engage in any abatement project for the firm will be licensed as required by the Residential Lead-Based Paint Professions Practice Act;</para><para>(c) A description of the removal, enclosure, encapsulation, demolition, dismantling, and maintenance methods that the firm will use;</para><para>(d) A description of the procedures that the firm will use for handling lead-containing waste;</para><para>(e) A description of the procedures that the firm will use in cleaning up the abatement project;</para><para>(f) The signature of the chief executive officer of the firm or his or her designee; and</para><para>(g) Such other information as may be necessary for the efficient administration and enforcement of the act and for the protection of the health, safety, and welfare of all classes of lead-based paint professions and the general public.</para><para>(3) A firm holding a certificate on December 1, 2008, shall be deemed to be holding a license under the Residential Lead-Based Paint Professions Practice Act and the Uniform Credentialing Act on such date. The certificate holder may continue to practice under such certificate as a license in accordance with such acts until the certificate would have expired under its terms.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 171; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 863, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1276.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>