<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6314"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6314</statuteno><catchline>Violations; citation; disciplinary actions; procedures; civil penalty; lien; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) When the department determines that a business entity that holds a license has violated the Asbestos Control Act or any rule and regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act, the department may, rather than initially instituting disciplinary proceedings pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, within seven working days after a finding of a violation is made, issue a citation to the licensee. The citation shall be served upon the licensee personally or by certified mail. Each citation shall specifically describe the nature of the violation and identify the statute, rule, or regulation violated. When a citation is served upon the licensee, the licensee shall have seven working days to remedy the violation. If such violation has not been remedied at the end of such time, the department may take such other action as is deemed appropriate pursuant to the Asbestos Control Act and the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(2) Independent of the provisions of subsection (1) of this section, a license or approval issued pursuant to the Asbestos Control Act may be denied, refused renewal, suspended, or revoked when the applicant or licensee violates any of the provisions of the act, fraudulently or deceptively obtains or attempts to obtain a license or approval, fails at any time to meet the qualifications for a license or approval, fails to comply with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act, fails to meet any applicable state standard for asbestos projects, or employs or permits an unlicensed individual to work in an asbestos occupation. An individual shall be subject to the reporting, investigatory, and disciplinary provisions of sections 38-176 to 38-185, 38-1,106, 38-1,109 to 38-1,126, and 38-1,137 to 38-1,139 for any of the grounds for disciplinary action found in the Uniform Credentialing Act and for any violation of the Asbestos Control Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the acts.</para><para>(3) In addition to the disciplinary actions provided for in subsection (2) of this section, the department may assess a civil penalty of not less than one thousand dollars nor more than twenty-five thousand dollars for each offense committed by any business entity licensed under the Asbestos Control Act or not less than one hundred dollars nor more than five thousand dollars for each offense committed by an individual licensed under the act for violation of the act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto. Each day a violation continues shall constitute a separate offense.</para><para>(4) Whenever the department determines to deny, refuse to renew, suspend, or revoke a license or approval or assess a civil penalty, it shall send to the applicant or licensee a notice setting forth the particular reasons for the determination. The denial, suspension, refusal to renew, revocation, or assessment of a civil penalty shall become final thirty days after the mailing of the notice unless the applicant or licensee gives written notice to the department of a desire for a hearing. If a hearing is requested, the applicant or licensee shall be given a hearing before the department and shall have the right to present such evidence as may be proper. On the basis of such evidence, the determination shall be affirmed, modified, or set aside, and a copy of such decision setting forth the findings of fact and the particular reasons upon which such decision was based shall be sent by certified mail to the applicant or licensee. The decision shall become a final decision of the department and may be appealed, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(5) Hearings held pursuant to this section shall be held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department under such act.</para><para>(6) Any civil penalty assessed and unpaid under the Asbestos Control Act shall constitute a debt to the State of Nebraska which may be collected in the manner of a lien foreclosure or sued for and recovered in any proper form of action in the name of the State of Nebraska in the district court of the county in which the violator resides or owns property. The department shall, within thirty days of receipt, remit any collected civil penalty to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1051, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 145; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1073, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1257.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>