<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6329"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6329</statuteno><catchline>Violations; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) A firm which engages in an abatement project without a valid license as provided in the Residential Lead-Based Paint Professions Practice Act shall be assessed a civil penalty of not less than five thousand dollars nor more than twenty-five thousand dollars for the first offense and not less than twenty-five thousand dollars nor more than one hundred thousand dollars for a second or subsequent offense. Each day a violation continues shall constitute a separate offense.</para><para>(2) An individual who engages in a lead-based paint profession without a valid license shall be assessed a civil penalty of not less than five hundred dollars nor more than five thousand dollars for the first offense and not less than one thousand dollars nor more than fifteen thousand dollars for the second or subsequent offense. Each day a violation continues shall constitute a separate offense.</para><para>(3) Any firm which knowingly engages in an abatement project but which uses employees who do not hold licenses shall be assessed a civil penalty of not less than five thousand dollars nor more than twenty-five thousand dollars for the first offense and not less than twenty-five thousand dollars nor more than one hundred thousand dollars for a second or subsequent offense. Each day a violation continues shall constitute a separate offense.</para><para>(4) Any firm conducting an accredited training program which knowingly engages in issuing fraudulent licenses or fails to conduct its training program in accordance with its accreditation shall, in addition to having its accreditation revoked, pay a civil penalty of not less than five thousand dollars nor more than twenty-five thousand dollars.</para><para>(5) The civil penalties prescribed in subsections (1), (2), (3), and (4) of this section shall be assessed in a civil action brought for such purpose by the Attorney General or the county attorney in the district court of the county in which the violation occurred.</para><para>(6) An individual or firm which has been assessed a civil penalty under this section and subsequently engages in an abatement project or a lead-based paint profession without a valid license or using employees who do not hold licenses, conducts training programs without being accredited by the department, or issues fraudulent licenses, except as otherwise provided in the act:</para><para>(a) For a first offense, shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor; and</para><para>(b) For a second or subsequent offense, shall be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1210, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 863, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1281.</para></source></law></legaldoc>