<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6021"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6021</statuteno><catchline>Administrator refuse access; hearing; procedure; access authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding the provisions of sections 71-6019 and 71-6020, the administrator of a nursing home may refuse access to the nursing home to any person if the presence of such person in the nursing home would be injurious to the health and safety of a resident or would threaten the security of the property of a resident or the nursing home or if the person seeks access to the nursing home for commercial purposes. Any person refused access to a nursing home may, within thirty days of such refusal, request a hearing by the department. The wrongful refusal of a nursing home to grant access to any person as required in sections 71-6019 and 71-6020 shall constitute a violation of the Nebraska Nursing Home Act. A nursing home may appeal any citation issued pursuant to this section in the manner provided in sections 71-452 to 71-455.</para><para>(2) Nothing in sections 71-6019 to 71-6021 shall be construed to prevent (a) an employee of the department, acting in his or her official capacity, from entering a nursing home for any inspection authorized by the act or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated pursuant thereto or (b) a state long-term care ombudsman or an ombudsman advocate, acting in his or her official capacity, from entering a nursing home to conduct an investigation authorized by any rules and regulations promulgated by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 235, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 677, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 748; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 641.</para></source></law></legaldoc>