<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id24" statutenumber="71-6406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6406</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Political subdivision;
building code; adopt; amend; enforce.</catchline><para>(1) Any political
subdivision may enact, administer, or enforce a local building or construction
code if or as long as such political subdivision adopts the state building
code. The political subdivision shall regularly update its code. For purposes
of this section, a code shall be deemed to be regularly updated if the most recently enacted state building code is
adopted by the political subdivision within two years. No political subdivision
may adopt or enforce a local building or construction code other than as provided
by this section.</para>
<para>(2) A political subdivision may amend its local building or
construction code if the amendment:</para>
<para>(a) Conforms generally with the state building code;</para>
<para>(b) Adopts a special or differing building standard by modifying or deleting any portion of
the state building code in order to reduce unnecessary costs of
construction, increase safety, durability, or efficiency, or address special
local conditions within its jurisdiction;</para>
<para>(c) Adopts any supplement, new edition, appendix, or component
or combination of components of the state building code; or</para>
<para>(d) Adopts
section R313 of the 2009 edition of the International Residential Code.</para>
<para>(3) A political subdivision may adopt and promulgate amendments
for the proper administration and enforcement of its local building or construction
code including organization of enforcement, qualifications of staff members,
examination of plans, inspections, appeals, permits, and fees. Any amendment
adopted pursuant to this section shall be published separately from the local
building or construction code. Fees, if any, for services which monitor a
builder's application of codes shall be negotiable between the political subdivisions
involved, but such fees shall not exceed the actual expenses incurred by the
political subdivision doing the monitoring.</para>
<para>(4) Notwithstanding the provisions of the Building Construction
Act, a public building of a political subdivision shall be built in accordance
with the applicable local building or construction code.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 227, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 319, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB799, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB546, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>