<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id826"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-6106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6106</statuteno><catchline>Seal; design; use.</catchline><para>(1) Each registered interior designer shall obtain a seal. The design of the seal shall be determined by the State Treasurer. The following information shall be on the seal: State of Nebraska; registrant's name; registrant's business city; and the words Registered Interior Designer.</para><para>(2) Whenever the seal is applied, the registrant's signature shall be across the seal. The seal and date of its placement shall be on all technical submissions and calculations whenever presented to a client or any public or governmental agency. It shall be unlawful for a registrant to affix such registrant's seal or to permit such seal to be affixed to any document after the expiration of the registration or for the purpose of aiding or abetting any other person to evade or attempt to evade the Interior Design Voluntary Registration Act.</para><para>(3) The seal and date shall be placed on all originals, copies, tracings, or other reproducible drawing and the first and last pages of specifications, reports, and studies in such a manner that the seal, signature, and date will be reproduced and be in compliance with the Interior Design Voluntary Registration Act. The application of the registrant's seal shall constitute certification that the work was done by the registrant or under the registrant's control.</para><para>(4) A registered interior designer shall not affix such registered interior designer's seal and signature to technical submissions that are subject to the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act unless the technical submissions were:</para><para>(a) Prepared entirely by the registered interior designer; or</para><para>(b) Prepared entirely under the direct supervision of the registered interior designer.</para><para>(5) A registered interior designer may affix such registered interior designer's seal to technical submissions not subject to the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act if the registered interior designer has reviewed or adapted in whole or in part such submissions and integrated them into such registered interior designer's work.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB16, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Engineers and Architects Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-3401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>