<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6310.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6310.01</statuteno><catchline>Asbestos occupations; training courses; approval.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall approve training courses for each classification of asbestos occupation. Applicants for course approval shall meet the requirements for each course and shall submit an application on forms provided by the department together with the prescribed fee. Approved course providers shall use only approved instructors to teach each training course. The department shall conduct onsite inspections of the training courses offered by course providers.</para><para>(2) In order to be approved by the department, an initial inspector training course shall meet the following requirements: A three-day training course including lectures, demonstrations, a field trip, at least four hours of hands-on training, individual respirator-fit testing, and a written examination; background information on asbestos and potential health effects related to exposure to asbestos; functions, qualifications, and the role of inspectors; legal liabilities and defenses; understanding building systems; public, employee, and occupant relations; preinspection planning and review of previous inspection records and inspecting for friable and nonfriable asbestos-containing material and assessing the condition of asbestos-containing material; bulk sampling and documentation of asbestos; inspector respiratory protection and personal protective equipment; and record keeping and inspection report writing, regulatory review, and course review. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department and shall be composed of questions covering subjects dealing with the course content. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para><para>(3) In order to be approved by the department, an initial management planner training course shall meet the following requirements: A three-day inspector training course as outlined in subsection (2) of this section and a two-day management planner training course including lectures, demonstrations, and a written examination; course overview; evaluation and interpretation of survey results, hazard assessment, and legal implications; evaluation and selection of control options; role of other professionals; developing an operations and maintenance plan; and regulatory review, record keeping for the management planner, assembling and submitting the management plan, financing abatement actions, and course review. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department and shall be composed of questions covering subjects dealing with the course content. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para><para>(4) In order to be approved by the department, an initial project designer training course shall meet the following requirements: A three-day training course including lectures, demonstrations, a field trip, and a written examination; background information on asbestos and potential health effects related to asbestos exposure; overview of abatement construction projects; safety system design specifications, employee personal protective equipment, and additional safety hazards; fiber aerodynamics and control, designing abatement solutions, final clearance process, and budgeting and cost estimation; writing abatement specifications and preparing abatement drawings; contract preparation and administration and legal liabilities and defenses; replacement of asbestos with asbestos-free substitutes; role of other consultants; occupied buildings; and relevant federal, state, and local regulatory requirements and course review. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department and shall be composed of questions covering subjects dealing with the course content. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para><para>(5) In order to be approved by the department, an initial project monitor training course shall meet the following requirements: A five-day asbestos training course including lectures, demonstrations, at least six hours of hands-on training, and a written examination; roles and responsibilities of the project monitor; characteristics of asbestos and asbestos-containing materials; federal and state asbestos regulation overview; understanding building construction and building systems; asbestos abatement contracts, specifications, and drawings; response actions and abatement practices; asbestos abatement equipment; personal protective equipment; air monitoring strategies; safety and health issues other than asbestos; conducting visual inspections; final clearance process; legal responsibilities and liabilities of project monitors; record keeping and report writing; and course review. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department and shall be composed of questions covering subjects dealing with the course content. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para><para>(6) In order to be approved by the department, an initial supervisor training course shall meet the following requirements: A five-day asbestos training course including lectures, demonstrations, at least fourteen hours of hands-on training, individual respirator-fit testing, and a written examination; the physical characteristics of asbestos and asbestos-containing materials and potential health effects related to asbestos exposure; employee personal protective equipment, state-of-the-art work practices, personal hygiene, additional safety hazards, medical monitoring, and air monitoring; relevant federal, state, and local regulatory requirements; respiratory protection programs, medical surveillance programs, and insurance and liability issues; record keeping for asbestos abatement projects and supervisory techniques for asbestos abatement activity; contract specifications; and course review. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department and shall be composed of questions covering subjects dealing with the course content. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para><para>(7) In order to be approved by the department, an initial worker training course shall meet the following requirements: A four-day training course including lectures, demonstrations, at least fourteen hours of hands-on training, individual respirator-fit testing, and a written examination; physical characteristics of asbestos, potential health effects related to asbestos exposure, employee personal protective equipment, state-of-the-art work practices, personal hygiene, additional safety hazards, medical monitoring, and air monitoring; relevant federal, state, and local regulatory requirements, procedures, and standards; establishment of respiratory protection programs; and course review. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department and shall be composed of questions covering subjects dealing with the course content. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para><para>(8) In order to be approved by the department, a course on Nebraska law, rules, and regulations required by subsection (3) of section 71-6310 shall consist of at least four hours of training on Nebraska law, rules, and regulations relating to asbestos. The written examination shall be approved and may be administered by the department. The passing score shall be determined by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1073, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1251.</para></source></law></legaldoc>