<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-6305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-6305</statuteno><catchline>License; application; contents.</catchline><para>(1) To apply for a license, a business entity shall submit an application to the department in the form required by the department and shall pay the fee prescribed by the department.</para><para>(2) The application shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) The name, address, and nature of the business entity;</para><para>(b) A statement that all individuals who will engage in any asbestos project for the business entity will be licensed as required by the Asbestos Control Act;</para><para>(c) A description of the protective clothing and respirators that the business entity will use;</para><para>(d) The name and address of each asbestos disposal site that the business entity will use;</para><para>(e) A description of the site decontamination procedures that the business entity will use;</para><para>(f) A description of the removal, enclosure, encapsulation, demolition, dismantling, and maintenance methods that the business entity will use;</para><para>(g) A description of the procedures that the business entity will use for handling waste containing asbestos;</para><para>(h) A description of the air monitoring procedures that the business entity will use;</para><para>(i) A description of the procedures that the business entity will use in cleaning up the asbestos project;</para><para>(j) The signature of the chief executive officer of the business entity or his or her designee; and</para><para>(k) Such other information as may be necessary for the efficient administration and enforcement of the act and for the protection of the health, safety, and welfare of the general public and all classes of asbestos occupations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1051, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1073, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1246.</para></source></law></legaldoc>