<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id212"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-7804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7804</statuteno><catchline>Primary Care Investment Council; created; members; termination.</catchline><para>(1) The Primary Care Investment Council is created. The council shall consist of fifteen voting members and two ex officio, nonvoting members.</para><para>(2) The Primary Care Investment Council shall consist of the following voting members:</para><para>(a) Three representatives of primary care physicians, one representing each congressional district;</para><para>(b) A representative of behavioral health providers;</para><para>(c) A representative of hospitals;</para><para>(d) A representative of academia with experience in health care data;</para><para>(e) Two other representatives of health providers who are not primary care physicians or hospitals;</para><para>(f) Three representatives of health insurers, one of which shall be a representative of a managed care organization;</para><para>(g) One representative of large employers that purchase health insurance for employees, which representative is not an insurer;</para><para>(h) One representative of small employers that purchase group health insurance for employees, which representative is not an insurer;</para><para>(i) One health care consumer advocate who is knowledgeable about the private health insurance market; and</para><para>(j) A representative of organizations that facilitate health information exchange in Nebraska.</para><para>(3) The following officials or their designees shall serve as ex officio, nonvoting members:</para><para>(a) The Director of Insurance; and</para><para>(b) The Director of Medicaid and Long-Term Care of the Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care of the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(4) The Governor shall appoint the voting members of the council. The Governor shall appoint the initial members by October 1, 2022. Any member who ceases to meet the requirements for his or her appointment regarding representation or practice shall cease to be a member of the council. Any vacancy shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment.</para><para>(5) The council shall select one of its members to serve as chairperson for a one-year term. The council shall conduct its organizational meeting in October 2022.</para><para>(6) The council shall terminate on July 1, 2029.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB863, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>