<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-7108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7108</statuteno><catchline>Department of Health and Human Services; Nebraska State Patrol; State Fire Marshal; Nebraska Emergency Management Agency; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall participate in the council and committee, recruit mental health workers for each critical incident stress management region, and participate in the training and continuing education activities of critical incident stress management peers and mental health professionals.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska State Patrol shall participate in the council and committee, receive all initial requests for stress management sessions, coordinate transportation requirements for critical incident stress management team members, recruit members of the law enforcement profession in each region to be trained as critical incident stress management peers, participate in the training and continuing education activities of critical incident stress management peers and mental health professionals, and appoint a member of the patrol to each regional management committee.</para><para>(3) The State Fire Marshal shall participate in the council and committee, cooperate in providing transportation for critical incident stress management teams, recruit firefighters to be trained as critical incident stress management peers in each critical incident stress management region, participate in the training and continuing education activities of critical incident stress management peers and mental health professionals, and appoint an individual who is employed by the State Fire Marshal to be on each regional management committee.</para><para>(4) The Nebraska Emergency Management Agency shall participate in the council and committee, promote stress management planning as part of emergency management preparedness, promote preincident education programs to acquaint emergency service personnel with stress management techniques, and participate in the training and continuing education activities of critical incident stress management peers and mental health professionals.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 775; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 184, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 