<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id64" statutenumber="71-7611"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7611</statuteno><catchline id="id67">Nebraska Health Care Cash
Fund; created; use; investment; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska
Health Care Cash Fund is created. The State Treasurer shall transfer (a) fifty-six
million one hundred thousand dollars no later than July 15, 2009, and (b) fifty-nine million
one hundred thousand dollars on or
before July 15, 2010, July 15, 2011, and July 15, 2012, and on or before every July 15 thereafter from
the Nebraska Medicaid Intergovernmental Trust Fund and the Nebraska Tobacco
Settlement Trust Fund to the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund, except that such
amount shall be reduced by the amount of the unobligated balance in the Nebraska
Health Care Cash Fund at the time the transfer is made. The state investment
officer upon consultation with the Nebraska Investment Council shall advise
the State Treasurer on the amounts to be transferred from the Nebraska Medicaid
Intergovernmental Trust Fund and from the Nebraska Tobacco Settlement Trust
Fund under this section in order to sustain such transfers in perpetuity.
The state investment officer shall report electronically to the Legislature
on or before October 1 of every even-numbered year on the sustainability of
such transfers. Except as otherwise provided by law, no more than the amount
specified in this subsection may be appropriated or transferred from the Nebraska
Health Care Cash Fund in any fiscal year.</para>
<para>It is the intent of the Legislature that no additional programs are
funded through the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund until funding for all programs
with an appropriation from the fund during FY2012-13 are restored to their
FY2012-13 levels.</para>
<para>(2) Any money in the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund available for investment
shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska
Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(3) The University of Nebraska and postsecondary educational institutions
having colleges of medicine in Nebraska and their affiliated research hospitals
in Nebraska, as a condition of receiving any funds appropriated or transferred
from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund, shall not discriminate against any
person on the basis of sexual orientation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1070, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1427, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 692, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 412, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB482, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB480, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB830, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB961, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB27, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB316, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB969, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 29.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>