<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 25.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id16280" statutenumber="71-7012"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id16282">71-7012</statuteno><catchline id="id16283">Breast and Cervical Cancer Advisory Committee; established; members; appointment; terms; duties; expenses.</catchline><para>The Breast and Cervical Cancer Advisory Committee is established. The committee consists of the members of the Mammography Screening Committee serving immediately prior to September 9, 1995, and eight additional members appointed by the chief executive officer of the department or his or her designee who have expertise or a personal interest in cervical cancer. The committee shall consist of not more than twenty-four volunteer members, at least eight of whom are women, appointed by the chief executive officer or his or her designee. Members of the committee shall be persons interested in health care, the promotion of breast cancer screening, and cervical cancer and shall be drawn from both the private sector and the public sector. At least one member shall be a person who has or who has had breast cancer.</para><para>Of the initial members of the committee, four shall be appointed for terms of one year and four shall be appointed for terms of two years. Thereafter all appointments shall be for terms of two years. All members shall serve until their successors are appointed. No member shall serve more than two successive two-year terms. Vacancies in the membership of the committee for any cause shall be filled by appointment by the chief executive officer or his or her designee for the unexpired term.</para><para>Duties of the committee shall include, but not be limited to, encouraging payment of public and private funds to the Breast and Cervical Cancer Cash Fund, researching and recommending to the department reimbursement limits, planning and implementing outreach and educational programs to Nebraska women, advising the department on its operation of the early detection of breast and cervical cancer grant from the United States Department of Health and Human Services, and encouraging payment of public and private funds to the fund. Members of the committee shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 256, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 68, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 406, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 772; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 668; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 25.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2008</operativedate></source>  </law></legaldoc> 