<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id64" statutenumber="71-7611"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7611</statuteno><catchline id="id67">Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund; created; use; investment; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund is created. The State Treasurer shall transfer (a) sixty million three hundred thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2014, (b) sixty million three hundred fifty thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2015, (c) sixty million three hundred fifty thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2016, (d) sixty million seven hundred thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2017, (e) five hundred thousand dollars on or before May 15, 2018, (f) sixty-one million six hundred thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2018, (g) sixty-two million dollars on or before July 15, 2019, (h) sixty-one million four hundred fifty thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2020, (i) sixty-six million two hundred thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2022, (j) fifty-six million seven hundred thousand dollars on or before July 15, 2023, (k) fifty-four million dollars on or before July 15, 2024, (l) fifty-nine million one hundred fifty thousand dollars on or before July 1, 2025, and (m) sixty million one hundred fifty thousand dollars on or before every July 15 thereafter from the Nebraska Medicaid Intergovernmental Trust Fund and the Nebraska Tobacco Settlement Trust Fund to the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund, except that such amount shall be reduced by the amount of the unobligated balance in the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund at the time the transfer is made. The state investment officer shall advise the State Treasurer on the amounts to be transferred first from the Nebraska Medicaid Intergovernmental Trust Fund until the fund balance is depleted and from the Nebraska Tobacco Settlement Trust Fund thereafter in order to sustain such transfers in perpetuity. The state investment officer shall report electronically to the Legislature on or before October 1 of every even-numbered year on the sustainability of such transfers. The Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund shall also include money received pursuant to section 77-2602. Except as otherwise provided by law, no more than the amounts specified in this subsection may be appropriated or transferred from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund in any fiscal year.</para><para>Except as otherwise provided in subsections (5) and (6) of this section, it is the intent of the Legislature that no additional programs are funded through the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund until funding for all programs with an appropriation from the fund during FY2012-13 are restored to their FY2012-13 levels.</para><para>(2) Any money in the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(3) The University of Nebraska and postsecondary educational institutions having colleges of medicine in Nebraska and their affiliated research hospitals in Nebraska, as a condition of receiving any funds appropriated or transferred from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund, shall not discriminate against any person on the basis of sexual orientation.</para><para>(4) The State Treasurer shall transfer fifteen million dollars from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund on or after July 1, 2022, but before June 30, 2023, to the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska for the University of Nebraska Medical Center for pancreatic cancer research at the University of Nebraska Medical Center. Transfers from the Nebraska Health Care Cash Fund in this subsection shall be contingent upon receipt of any matching funds from private or other sources, up to fifteen million dollars, certified by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. Upon receipt of any matching funds certified by the budget administrator, the State Treasurer shall transfer an equal amount of funds to the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1070, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1427, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 692, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 412, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1091, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB482, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB480, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB830, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB961, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB27, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB316, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB969, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB906, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB390, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB661, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB439, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB793, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB298, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB481, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB570, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB600, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB641, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB384, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1413, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 152. </para><operativedate>May 22, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>