<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id738"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-7107"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7107</statuteno><catchline>Department of Health and Human Services; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall be the lead agency for the program.</para><para>(2) Until July 1, 2026, the department shall:</para><para>(a) Provide office support to program activities;</para><para>(b) Provide necessary equipment for the program and participants;</para><para>(c) Provide staff support to the Critical Incident Stress Management Council;</para><para>(d) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to implement the program;</para><para>(e) Recruit hospital personnel and emergency medical workers to be trained as critical incident stress management peers;</para><para>(f) Participate in the training and continuing education of such peers and mental health professionals; and</para><para>(g) Appoint a director for the program who shall be an employee of the department and shall be the chairperson of the Interagency Management Committee.</para><para>(3) On and after July 1, 2026, the department shall:</para><para>(a) Coordinate program activities and emergency response;</para><para>(b) Provide necessary equipment for the program and participants;</para><para>(c) Recruit hospital personnel and emergency medical workers to be trained as critical incident stress management peers;</para><para>(d) Participate in the training and continuing education of such peers and mental health professionals;</para><para>(e) Appoint a director for the program who shall be an employee of the department;</para><para>(f) Specify the organizational and operational goals for the program and provide overall policy direction for the program;</para><para>(g) Manage planning and budget development for the program;</para><para>(h) Manage program development and evaluation;</para><para>(i) Provide a mechanism for quality assurance that may include certification of critical incident stress management team members;</para><para>(j) Identify critical incident stress management regions; and</para><para>(k) Provide backup to regional critical incident stress management teams.</para><para>(4) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to implement the program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 774; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 184, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 670; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB346, &#167; 43. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>