<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id751"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" statutenumber="71-7305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7305</statuteno><catchline>Nonsurgical gender-altering procedures; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The chief medical officer as designated in section 81-3115 shall adopt and promulgate such rules and regulations as are necessary to provide for nonsurgical gender-altering procedures for individuals younger than nineteen years of age, such as puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or both. Such rules and regulations shall be consistent with the Let Them Grow Act and, at a minimum, include the following:</para><para>(a) Specify that a health care practitioner may prescribe approved puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or both to an individual younger than nineteen years of age if such individual has a long-lasting and intense pattern of gender nonconformity or gender dysphoria which began or worsened at the start of puberty;</para><para>(b) Specific criteria, obligations, or conditions regulating the administration, prescribing, delivery, sale, or use of puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or both involving an individual younger than nineteen years of age in accordance with subdivision (1)(a) of this section, which shall, at a minimum, set forth the following:</para><para>(i) The minimum number of gender-identity-focused therapeutic hours required prior to an individual receiving puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or both;</para><para>(ii) Patient advisory requirements necessary for a health care practitioner to obtain informed patient consent;</para><para>(iii) Patient medical record documentation requirements to ensure compliance with the act; and</para><para>(iv) A minimum waiting period between the time the health care practitioner obtains informed patient consent and the administration, prescribing, or delivery of puberty-blocking drugs, cross-sex hormones, or both to such patient; and</para><para>(c) Specify that section 71-7304 does not apply to nonsurgical gender-altering procedures when such procedures are provided in compliance with the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section.</para><para>(2) The Department of Health and Human Services may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations not inconsistent with the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the chief medical officer that are necessary to carry out the Let Them Grow Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB574, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>