<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id497"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-7001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7001</statuteno><catchline>Mammography; health care facilities; notice; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) All health care facilities that perform mammography shall include in the summary of the mammography report to be provided to a patient information that identifies the patient's individual breast tissue classification based on the Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System established by the American College of Radiology. If a facility determines that a patient has heterogeneously dense or extremely dense breast tissue, the summary of the mammography report shall also include a notice substantially similar to the following:</para><para>Your mammogram indicates that you have dense breast tissue. Dense breast tissue is a normal finding that is present in about forty percent of women. Dense breast tissue can make it more difficult to detect cancer on a mammogram and may be associated with a slightly increased risk for breast cancer. This information is provided to raise your awareness of the impact of breast density on cancer detection and to encourage you to discuss this issue, as well as other breast cancer risk factors, with your health care provider as you decide together which screening options may be right for you.</para><para>(2) A facility that performs mammography may update the language in the notice to reflect advances in science and technology, as long as it continues to notify patients about the frequency of dense breast tissue and its effect on the accuracy of mammograms and encourage patients to discuss the issue with their health care provider.</para><para>(3) This section does not create a duty of care or other legal obligation beyond the duty to provide notice as set forth in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB195, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>