  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-7709"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7709</statuteno><catchline>Parties and participants; immunity; notice; act, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) Any party to a cooperative agreement which has been approved in whole or in part by the department pursuant to the Health Care Facility-Provider Cooperation Act shall be immune from any civil or criminal antitrust action if such action is based upon the cooperative agreement or arises from conduct or activity reasonably necessary and reasonably foreseeable to implement such agreement or any decision or order issued by the department.</para><para>(2) Any part to a cooperative agreement that has been filed with the department pursuant to the act shall be immune from any civil or criminal antitrust action if such action is based upon or arises from the negotiation of or entering into the cooperative agreement.</para><para>(3) All persons who participate in community planning, discussions, or negotiations intended in good faith to culminate in a cooperative agreement to be filed with the department pursuant to the provisions of the act shall be immune from any civil or criminal antitrust action if such action is based upon or arises from such conduct.</para><para>(4)(a) The immunity provided in this section shall apply only to community planning, discussions, and negotiations that occur after notice of such activities has been sent to the department in accordance with the requirements of subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para><para>(b) The notice to the department required by subdivision (a) of this subsection shall include a description of the proposed purpose of the agreement, the potential parties, and the potential nature and scope of the cooperation and joint activities contemplated. The persons filing such notice shall also notify the department if negotiations have terminated, or if negotiations are continuing they shall notify the department of progress of negotiation at least once every six months. The department may request additional information from the potential parties and may communicate with and monitor the parties in any manner the department deems necessary but shall not hinder or interfere with negotiations.</para><para>(5) The submission of a cooperative agreement for department approval pursuant to the act shall be voluntary, and the failure of the parties to any such agreement to seek approval shall not be admissible in any civil or criminal antitrust action if such action is based upon the cooperative agreement or arises from conduct or activity reasonably necessary and reasonably foreseeable to implement the cooperative agreement.</para><para>(6) Nothing in the act shall be construed to limit the application of any other statute concerning the licensure of facilities, services, or professions, and any activities undertaken pursuant to a cooperative agreement shall comply with applicable law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1223, &#167; 119. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 