<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-7439" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-7439</statuteno><catchline>Normal distribution chain, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Normal distribution chain means the transfer of a prescription drug or the co-licensed product of the original manufacturer of the finished form of a prescription drug along a chain of custody directly from the manufacturer or co-licensee of such drug to a patient or ultimate consumer of such drug.</para><para>(2) Normal distribution chain includes transfers of a prescription drug or co-licensed product:</para><para>(a) From a manufacturer or co-licensee to a wholesale drug distributor, to a pharmacy, and then to a patient or a patient's agent;</para><para>(b) From a manufacturer or co-licensee to a wholesale drug distributor, to a pharmacy, to a health care practitioner, health care practitioner facility, or hospital, and then to a patient or a patient's agent;</para><para>(c) From a manufacturer or co-licensee to a wholesale drug distributor, to a chain pharmacy warehouse, to a pharmacy affiliated with the chain pharmacy warehouse, and then to a patient or a patient's agent;</para><para>(d) From a manufacturer or co-licensee to a chain pharmacy warehouse, to a pharmacy affiliated with the chain pharmacy warehouse, and then to a patient or a patient's agent; or</para><para>(e) Recognized in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, co-licensed products means prescription drugs that have been approved by the federal Food and Drug Administration and are the subject of an arrangement by which two or more parties have the right to engage in a business activity or occupation concerning such drugs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 13.</para></source></law></legaldoc>