<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id471">
<sectno id="id472">Sec. 48.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id473" statutenumber="71-8612"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id475">71-8612</statuteno><catchline id="id476">Commission
for the Blind and Visually Impaired Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline>
<para>The Commission for the Blind and Visually Impaired Cash Fund
is created. The fund shall contain money received pursuant to the Commission
for the Blind and Visually Impaired Act and shall include a percentage of
the net proceeds derived from the operation of vending facilities. The net
proceeds from the operation of vending facilities shall accrue to the blind
vending facility operator, except for the percentage of the net proceeds that
shall revert to the cash fund. Such fund shall be used for supervision and
other administrative purposes as necessary,
except that transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the
direction of the Legislature. The commission, in consultation
with the Committee of Blind Vendors, shall determine the percentage of the
net proceeds that reverts to the Commission for the Blind and Visually
Impaired Cash Fund after an investigation to reveal the gross
proceeds, cost of operation, amount necessary to replenish the stock of merchandise,
and the business needs of the blind vending facility operator. All equipment
purchased from the fund is the property of the state and shall be disposed
of only by sale at a fair market price. Any money in the fund available for
investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the
Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 343, &#167; 1, p. 1085; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 292, &#167; 1, p. 996; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 386, &#167; 1, p. 1343; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 442, &#167; 1, p. 1362; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 561, &#167; 1, p. 1845; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 113, p. 2418; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 334, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 674, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 142; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 83-210.01; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 352, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 55, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 48.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>