  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-8604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8604</statuteno><catchline>Commission for the Blind and Visually Impaired; created; per diem; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Commission for the Blind and Visually Impaired is created. The governing board of the commission shall consist of five members appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the members of the Legislature. All board members shall have reasonable knowledge or experience in issues related to blindness which may include, but is not limited to, reasonable knowledge or experience acquired through membership in consumer organizations of the blind. No board member or his or her immediate family shall be a current employee of the commission. At least three board members shall be blind persons: One member shall be a member or designee of the National Federation of the Blind of Nebraska; one member shall be a member or designee of the American Council of the Blind of Nebraska; and one member may be a member of another consumer organization of the blind.</para><para>(2) Board members shall be appointed for staggered terms with the initial members appointed for terms as follows: Two members for terms ending on December 31, 2001, and three members for terms ending December 31, 2003. Subsequent appointments shall be for terms of four years with no board member appointed to more than two consecutive terms. Board members whose terms have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have been appointed. In the case of a vacancy, the Governor shall appoint a successor for the unexpired term. Board members may be removed for cause.</para><para>(3) A majority of the board members constitutes a quorum for the transaction of business. The board shall annually elect a chairperson from its membership.</para><para>(4) Board members shall receive a per diem of seventy dollars for each day spent in the performance of their official duties and shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. Aside from the provisions of this subsection, a board member shall not receive other compensation, perquisites, or allowances for the performance of official duties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 352, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 