<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id56"><sectno id="id57">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id58" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-8913"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8913</statuteno><catchline>Veterinary drug distributor license; application; contents; authority.</catchline><para>(1) Any person or entity that acts as a veterinary drug distributor in this state shall obtain a veterinary drug distributor license from the department prior to engaging in distribution of veterinary legend drugs in or into this state.</para><para>(2) An applicant for an initial or renewal license as a veterinary drug distributor shall file a written application with the department. The application shall be accompanied by the fee established by the department pursuant to section 71-8918 and shall include the following information:</para><para>(a) The applicant's name, business address, type of business entity, and telephone number. If the applicant is a partnership, the application shall include the name of each partner and the name of the partnership. If the applicant is a corporation, the application shall include the name and title of each corporate officer and director, all corporate names of the applicant, and the applicant's state of incorporation. If the applicant is a sole proprietorship, the application shall include the name of the sole proprietor, the name of the proprietorship, and the proprietor's social security number. The social security number shall not be a public record and may only be used by the department for administrative purposes;</para><para>(b) All trade or business names used by the applicant;</para><para>(c) The addresses and telephone numbers of all facilities to be used by the applicant for the storage, handling, and distribution of veterinary legend drugs and the names of persons to be in charge of such facilities. A separate license shall be obtained for each such facility;</para><para>(d) A listing of all licenses, permits, or other similar documentation issued to the applicant in any other state authorizing the applicant to purchase, possess, and distribute veterinary legend drugs;</para><para>(e) The names and addresses of the owner of the applicant's veterinary legend drug distribution facilities, a designated representative at each such facility, and all managerial employees at each such facility; and</para><para>(f) Other information as required by the department, including affirmative evidence of the applicant's ability to comply with the Veterinary Drug Distribution Licensing Act and the rules and regulations adopted under the act.</para><para>(3) The application shall be signed by:</para><para>(a) The owner, if the applicant is an individual or partnership;</para><para>(b) The member, if the applicant is a limited liability company with only one member, or two of its members, if the applicant is a limited liability company with two or more members; or</para><para>(c) Two of its officers, if the applicant is a corporation.</para><para>(4) A veterinary drug distributor holding a valid license issued pursuant to the Veterinary Drug Distribution Licensing Act shall have the authority to purchase, possess, or otherwise acquire veterinary legend drugs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1022, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 