<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id23"> <sectno id="id24">Sec. 20.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id25" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-8805"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id27">71-8805</statuteno><catchline id="id28">Stem Cell Research Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Stem Cell Research Cash Fund is created. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para> <para>(2) Money credited to the Stem Cell Research Cash Fund pursuant to section 71-7611 shall be used to provide a dollar-for-dollar match, up to five hundred thousand dollars per fiscal year, of funds received by institutions or researchers from sources other than funds provided by the State of Nebraska for nonembryonic stem cell research. Such matching funds shall be awarded through the grant process established pursuant to section 71-8804. No single institution or researcher shall receive more than seventy percent of the funds available for distribution under this section on an annual basis.</para> <para>(3) Up to three percent of the funds credited to the Stem Cell Research Cash Fund shall be available to the Division of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services for administrative costs, including stipends and reimbursements pursuant to section 71-8803.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB606, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB316, &#167; 20.</para><effectivedate>May 20, 2009</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>