<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id16">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id18"  statutenumber="71-8506">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8506</statuteno><catchline id="id21">Medical assistance
program; reimbursement; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) In-person
contact between a health care practitioner and a patient shall not be required
under the medical assistance program established pursuant to the Medical Assistance
Act and Title XXI of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, for health
care services delivered through telehealth that are otherwise eligible for
reimbursement under such program and federal act. Such services shall be subject
to reimbursement policies developed pursuant to such program and federal act.
This section also applies to managed care plans which contract with the department
pursuant to the Medical Assistance Act only to the extent that:</para>
<para>(a) Health care services delivered through telehealth are
covered by and reimbursed under the medicaid fee-for-service program; and</para>
<para>(b) Managed care contracts with managed care plans are amended
to add coverage of health care services delivered through telehealth and any
appropriate capitation rate adjustments are incorporated.</para>
<para>(2) The reimbursement rate for a telehealth consultation shall,
as a minimum, be set at the same rate as the medical assistance program rate
for a comparable in-person consultation,
and the rate shall not depend on the distance between the health care practitioner
and the patient.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall establish rates for transmission
cost reimbursement for telehealth consultations, considering, to the extent
applicable, reductions in travel costs by health care practitioners and patients
to deliver or to access health care services and such other factors as the
department deems relevant. Such rates shall include reimbursement for all
two-way, real-time, interactive communications, unless provided by an Internet
service provider, between the patient and the physician or health care practitioner
at the distant site which comply with the federal Health Insurance Portability
and Accountability Act of 1996 and rules and regulations adopted thereunder
and with regulations relating to encryption adopted by the federal Centers
for Medicare and Medicaid Services and which satisfy federal requirements
relating to efficiency, economy, and quality of care.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 559, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB556, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1076, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Medical Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 68-901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>