<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id443" statutenumber="71-8249"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id445">71-8249</statuteno><catchline id="id446">Statewide trauma registry; data; confidentiality.</catchline><para>(1) All data collected under section 71-8248 shall be held confidential pursuant to sections 81-663 to 81-675. Confidential patient medical record data shall only be released as (a) Class I, II, or IV medical records under sections 81-663 to 81-675, (b) aggregate or case-specific data to the regional trauma system quality assurance program and the regional trauma advisory boards, (c) protected health information to a public health authority, as such terms are defined under the federal Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, as such act existed on January 1, 2008, and (d) protected health information, as defined under the federal Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, as such act existed on January 1, 2008, to an emergency medical service, to an out-of-hospital emergency care provider, to a licensed health care facility, or to a center that will treat or has treated a specific patient.</para><para>A record may be shared with the emergency medical service, the out-of-hospital emergency provider, the licensed health care facility, or center that reported that specific record.</para><para>(2) Patient care quality assurance proceedings, records, and reports developed pursuant to this section and section 71-8248 are confidential and are not subject to discovery by subpoena or admissible as evidence in any civil action, except pursuant to a court order which provides for the protection of sensitive information of interested parties, including the department, pursuant to section 25-12,123.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 626, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB185, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 27.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 