<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id6" statutenumber="71-8611"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8611</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Vending facilities; license; priority status.</catchline><para>For the purpose of providing blind persons with remunerative employment, enlarging the economic opportunities of blind persons, and stimulating blind persons to greater efforts in striving to make themselves self-supporting, the commission shall administer and operate vending facilities programs pursuant to the federal Randolph-Sheppard Act, as the act existed on January 1, 2019, 20 U.S.C. 107 et seq. Blind persons licensed by the commission pursuant to its rules and regulations are authorized to operate vending facilities in any federally owned building or on any federally owned or controlled property, in any state-owned building or on any property owned or controlled by the state, or on any property owned or controlled by any county, city, or municipality with the approval of the local governing body, when, in the judgment of the director of the commission, such vending facilities may be properly and satisfactorily operated by blind persons. With respect to vending facilities in any state-owned building or on any property owned or controlled by the state, priority shall be given to blind persons, except that this shall not apply to the Game and Parks Commission or the University of Nebraska. If a blind person is selected to operate vending facilities in such building or on such property, he or she shall do so on a rent-free basis and offer products at prices comparable to similar products sold in similar buildings or on similar property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 443, &#167; 1, p. 1363; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 32, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 674, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 929; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 83-210.03; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 352, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 134; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB858, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB220, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>