<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id6" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="71-8509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8509</statuteno><catchline>Telehealth services for children's
behavioral health; rules and regulations; terms, defined.</catchline><para>(1) The Department
of Health and Human Services shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
providing for telehealth services for children's behavioral health. Such rules
and regulations relate specifically to children's behavioral health and are
in addition to the Nebraska Telehealth Act.</para>
<para>For purposes of
sections 71-8509 to 71-8512, child means a person under nineteen years of
age.</para><para>(2) The rules and regulations required pursuant to subsection (1)
of this section shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) An appropriately trained
staff member or employee familiar with the child's treatment plan or familiar
with the child shall be immediately available in person to the child receiving
a telehealth behavioral health service in order to attend to any urgent situation
or emergency that may occur during provision of such service. This requirement
may be waived by the child's parent or legal guardian;</para>
<para>(b) In cases in which
there is a threat that the child may harm himself or herself or others, before
an initial telehealth service the health care practitioner shall work with
the child and his or her parent or guardian to develop a safety plan. Such
plan shall document actions the child, the health care practitioner, and the
parent or guardian will take in the event of an emergency or urgent situation
occurring during or after the telehealth session. Such plan may include having
a staff member or employee familiar with the child's treatment plan immediately
available in person to the child, if such measures are deemed necessary by
the team developing the safety plan; and</para><para>(c) Services provided by means of telecommunications
technology, other than telehealth behavioral health services received by a
child, are not covered if the child has access to a comparable service within
thirty miles of his or her place of residence.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB556, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Telehealth Act,</emphasis> see section 71-8501.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>