<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-8505"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8505</statuteno><catchline>Written statement; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to an initial telehealth consultation under section 71-8506, a health care practitioner who delivers a health care service to a patient through telehealth shall ensure that the following written information is provided to the patient:</para><para>(a) A statement that the patient retains the option to refuse the telehealth consultation at any time without affecting the patient's right to future care or treatment and without risking the loss or withdrawal of any program benefits to which the patient would otherwise be entitled;</para><para>(b) A statement that all existing confidentiality protections shall apply to the telehealth consultation;</para><para>(c) A statement that the patient shall have access to all medical information resulting from the telehealth consultation as provided by law for patient access to his or her medical records; and</para><para>(d) A statement that dissemination of any patient identifiable images or information from the telehealth consultation to researchers or other entities shall not occur without the written consent of the patient.</para><para>(2) The patient shall sign a written statement prior to an initial telehealth consultation, indicating that the patient understands the written information provided pursuant to subsection (1) of this section and that this information has been discussed with the health care practitioner or his or her designee. Such signed statement shall become a part of the patient's medical record.</para><para>(3) If the patient is a minor or is incapacitated or mentally incompetent such that he or she is unable to sign the written statement required by subsection (2) of this section, such statement shall be signed by the patient's legally authorized representative.</para><para>(4) This section shall not apply in an emergency situation in which the patient is unable to sign the written statement required by subsection (2) of this section and the patient's legally authorized representative is unavailable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 559, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 