<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id22" statutenumber="71-8803"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8803</statuteno><catchline>Stem Cell Research Advisory Committee; created; qualifications; terms; meetings; stipend; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Stem Cell Research Advisory Committee is created. The committee shall consist of the dean of every medical school in Nebraska that is accredited by the Liaison Committee on Medical Education or his or her designee and additional members appointed as follows: (a) The dean of every medical school in Nebraska shall nominate three scientists from outside Nebraska conducting human stem cell research with funding from the National Institutes of Health of the United States Department of Health and Human Services; and (b) the chief medical officer as designated in section 81-3115 shall select two of such scientists from each set of nominations to serve on the committee. Appointments by the chief medical officer pursuant to this subsection shall be approved by the Legislature. Members appointed by the chief medical officer shall serve for staggered terms of three years each and until their successors are appointed and qualified. Such members may be reappointed for additional three-year terms.</para><para>(2) The committee shall meet not less than twice each year.</para><para>(3) Members of the committee not employed by medical schools in Nebraska shall receive a stipend per meeting to be determined by the Division of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services based on standard consultation fees, and all members of the committee shall be reimbursed for expenses incurred in service on the committee pursuant to sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB606, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 76. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>