<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health and Welfare" id="id22" statutenumber="71-8512"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8512</statuteno><catchline>Behavioral Health Screening and Referral
Pilot Program; created by University of Nebraska Medical Center; clinics;
selection; collection of data; evaluation; termination of section.</catchline>
<para>(1) The University
of Nebraska Medical Center shall create the Behavioral Health Screening and
Referral Pilot Program. The pilot program shall utilize a strategy of screening
and behavioral health intervention in coordination with the regional behavioral
health authorities established pursuant to section 71-808 in which the clinics
identified under subsection (2) of this section are located. It is the intent
of the Legislature that the pilot program demonstrate a method of addressing
the unmet emotional or behavioral health needs of children that can be replicated
statewide. Under the pilot program, behavioral health screening will be offered:
(a) In primary care providers' offices during examinations under the early
and periodic screening, diagnosis, and treatment services program pursuant
to 42 U.S.C. 1396d(r), as such section existed on January 1, 2013; or (b)
upon request from parents or legal guardians who have concerns about a child's
behavioral health.</para>
<para>(2) Three clinics
shall be selected to serve as sites for the pilot program, including at least
one rural and one urban clinic. Selected clinics shall have child psychologists
integrated in the pediatric practice of the clinics. Parents or legal guardians
of children participating in the pilot program shall be offered routine mental
and behavioral health screening for their child during required physical examinations
or at the request of a parent or legal guardian. Behavioral health screening
shall be administered by clinic staff and interpreted by the psychiatrist,
psychiatric nurse practitioner, psychologist, or licensed mental health practitioner
and the child's primary care physician.</para><para>(3) Children identified through such screenings
as being at risk may be referred for further evaluation and diagnosis as indicated.
If intervention is required, the primary care medical team, including the
psychologist and the primary care physician, shall develop a treatment plan
collaboratively with the parent or legal guardian and any other individuals
identified by the parent or legal guardian. If appropriate, the child shall
receive behavioral therapy, medication, or combination therapy within the
primary care practice setting.</para><para>(4) Consultation via telephone or telehealth
with faculty and staff of the departments of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry,
Psychiatric Nursing, and Developmental Pediatrics, and the Munroe-Meyer Institute
Psychology Department, of the University of Nebraska Medical Center shall
be available to the primary care practice and the children as needed to manage
the care of children with mental or behavioral health issues that require
more specialized care than can be provided by the primary care practice.</para>
<para>(5) Data on the
pilot program shall be collected and evaluated by the Interdisciplinary Center
for Program Evaluation at the Munroe-Meyer Institute of the University of
Nebraska Medical Center. Evaluation of the pilot program shall include, but
not be limited to:</para><para>(a)
The number of referrals for behavioral health screening under the pilot program;</para>
<para>(b) Whether each referral
is initiated by a parent, a school, or a physician;</para><para>(c) The number of children and
adolescents recommended for further psychological assessment after screening
for a possible behavioral health disorder;</para><para>(d) The number and type of further psychological assessments
of children and adolescents recommended and conducted;</para>
<para>(e) The number and
type of behavioral health disorders in children and adolescents diagnosed
as a result of a further psychological assessment following a behavioral health
screening under the pilot program;</para><para>(f) The number and types of referrals of children
and adolescents for behavioral health treatment from primary care medical
practitioners;</para><para>(g)
The number of children and adolescents successfully treated for a behavioral
health disorder based upon patient reports, parent ratings, and academic records;</para>
<para>(h) The number and
type of referrals of children and adolescents to psychiatric backup services
at the University of Nebraska Medical Center;</para><para>(i) The number of children and
adolescents diagnosed with a behavioral health disorder who are successfully
managed or treated through psychiatric backup services from the University
of Nebraska Medical Center;</para><para>(j) The number and types of medications, consultations,
or prescriptions ordered by psychiatric nurse practitioners for children and
adolescents;</para><para>(k)
The number of referrals of children and adolescents for severe behavioral
health disorders and consultations to child psychiatrists, developmental pediatricians,
or psychologists specializing in treatment of adolescents;</para>
<para>(l) The number of children
and adolescents referred to psychiatric hospitals or emergency departments
of acute care hospitals for treatment for dangerous or suicidal behavior;</para>
<para>(m) The number of children
and adolescents prescribed psychotropic medications and the types of such
psychotropic medications; and</para><para>(n) Data collection on program costs and financial
impact as related to capacity for replication in other primary care practices.
Primary program costs include physician and psychologist time for conducting
screenings, family interviews, further testing, and specialist consulting
costs relating to consulting services by psychiatric nurses, developmental
pediatricians, and psychologists. Treatment or medications paid by private
insurance, the medical assistance program, or the State Children's Health
Insurance Program shall not be included in program costs pursuant to this
subdivision.</para><para>(6)
This section terminates two years after September 6, 2013.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB556, &#167; 4.</para><terminationdate>September 6, 2015</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>