<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id4"> <sectno id="id5">Sec. 14.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-8922"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">71-8922</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Distribution of veterinary legend drugs; authorized; applicability of labeling provisions.</catchline> <para>A veterinary drug distributor may distribute veterinary legend drugs to:</para> <para>(1) A licensed veterinarian or to another veterinary drug distributor subject to the requirements of section 71-8921; and</para> <para>(2) A layperson responsible for the control of an animal if:</para> <para>(a) A licensed veterinarian has issued, prior to such distribution, a veterinary drug order for the veterinary legend drug in the course of an existing, valid veterinarian-client-patient relationship and the veterinary drug order is in compliance with all federal laws and regulations;</para> <para>(b) At the time the veterinary legend drug leaves the licensed location of the veterinary drug distributor, those in the employ of the veterinary drug distributor possess a copy of the veterinary drug order for the veterinary legend drug issued according to subdivision (a) of this subdivision and deliver a copy to the layperson responsible for the control of the animal at the time of the distribution;</para> <para>(c) The original veterinary drug order issued according to subdivision (a) of this subdivision is retained on the premises of the veterinary drug distributor or an authorized central location for three years after the date of the last transaction affecting the veterinary drug order;</para> <para>(d) All veterinary legend drugs distributed on the veterinary drug order issued according to subdivision (a) of this subdivision are sold in the original, unbroken manufacturer's containers; and</para> <para>(e) The veterinary legend drugs, once distributed, are not returned to the veterinary drug distributor for resale or redistribution.</para> <para>Nothing contained in Nebraska statutes governing the practice of pharmacy shall be construed to prohibit a veterinary drug distributor from selling or otherwise distributing a veterinary legend drug pursuant to a veterinary drug order by a veterinarian licensed in this state and, when a valid veterinarian-client-patient relationship exists, to the layperson responsible for the control of the animal.</para> <para>(3) If all federal labeling requirements are met, labeling provisions of Nebraska laws governing the practice of pharmacy shall not apply to veterinary legend drugs distributed pursuant to the Veterinary Drug Distribution Licensing Act.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1022, &#167;  22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB463, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>