<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" statutenumber="71-8607" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>71-8607</statuteno><catchline>Commission; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall:</para><para>(a) Apply for, receive, and administer money from any state or federal agency to be used for purposes relating to blindness, including federal funds relating to vocational rehabilitation of blind persons as provided in subsection (1) of section 71-8610;</para><para>(b) Receive on behalf of the state any gifts, donations, or bequests from any source to be used in carrying out the purposes of the Commission for the Blind and Visually Impaired Act;</para><para>(c) Promote self-support of blind persons as provided in sections 71-8608, 71-8609, and 71-8611;</para><para>(d) Provide itinerant training of alternative skills of blindness, including, but not limited to, braille, the long white cane for independent travel, adaptive technology, and lifestyle maintenance;</para><para>(e) Establish, equip, and maintain a residential training center with qualified instructors for comprehensive prevocational training of eligible blind persons. The center shall also provide comprehensive independent living training as well as orientation and adjustment counseling for blind persons;</para><para>(f) Administer and operate a vending facility program in the state, in its capacity as the designated licensing agency pursuant to the federal Randolph-Sheppard Act, as the act existed on January 1, 2019, 20 U.S.C. 107 et seq., for the benefit of blind persons;</para><para>(g) Contract for the purchase of information services for blind persons; and</para><para>(h) Perform other duties necessary to fulfill the purposes of the Commission for the Blind and Visually Impaired Act.</para><para>(2) The commission may perform educational services relating to blindness and may cooperate and consult with other public and private agencies relating to educational issues.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 352, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB220, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>