<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Health And Welfare" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="71-9203"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>71-9203</statuteno><catchline>Health Care Data Base Advisory Committee;
members.</catchline><para>(1)
The Health Care Data Base Advisory Committee shall be appointed within forty-five
business days after February 14, 2014.</para>
<para>(2) The advisory
committee members appointed by the Director of Insurance shall include, but
not be limited to:</para><para>(a)
A member of academia with experience in health care data and cost efficiency
research;</para><para>(b)
At least one representative of hospitals;</para><para>(c) At least one representative of physicians;</para>
<para>(d) At least one other
representative of health care providers;</para><para>(e) A representative of small employers that purchase
group health insurance for employees, which representative is not an insurer
or insurance producer;</para><para>(f) A representative of large employers that purchase
health insurance for employees, which representative is not an insurer or
insurance producer;</para><para>(g) At least one health care consumer advocate, knowledgeable
about private market insurance, public health insurance programs, enrollment
and access, or related areas and has background or experience in consumer
health care advocacy;</para><para>(h) At least one representative of health insurers;</para>
<para>(i) A representative
of organizations that facilitate health information exchange to improve health
care for all Nebraskans; and</para><para>(j) At least one representative of local public health
departments.</para><para>(3)
The following shall serve as ex officio members of the advisory committee:</para>
<para>(a) The Director
of Insurance or his or her designee;</para><para>(b) The Director of Medicaid and Long-Term Care of
the Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care of the Department of Health and
Human Services or his or her designee; and</para><para>(c) The Director of Public Health of the Division
of Public Health of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or
her designee.</para><para>(4)
The members of the advisory committee appointed pursuant to subsection (2)
of this section shall serve without compensation and shall not be reimbursed
for expenses incurred in the performance of their duties on the committee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB76, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>February 14, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>