<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Attorneys At Law" statutenumber="7-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>7-104</statuteno><catchline>Admission to bar; oath; form.</catchline><para>Every attorney upon being admitted to practice in the Supreme Court or district courts of this state, shall take and subscribe an oath substantially in the following form: You do solemnly swear that you will support the Constitution of the United States, and the Constitution of this state, and that you will faithfully discharge the duties of an attorney and counselor, according to the best of your ability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 3, &#167; 4, p. 14; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 5, &#167; 1, p. 55; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 268; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 263; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 7-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 7-104. </para></source>  <annotation><para><emphasis>1. Requirements of oath</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Violation of oath</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Administration of oath</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Requirements of oath</emphasis></para><para>Conduct of an attorney in a courtroom must at all times conform to his oath. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Rhodes, 177 Neb. 650, 131 N.W.2d 118 (1964).</para><para>Oath taken by an attorney requires him to faithfully discharge his duties. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Jensen, 171 Neb. 1, 105 N.W.2d 459 (1960).</para><para>Oath requires lawyers to observe canons of professional ethics. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Fitzgerald, 165 Neb. 212, 85 N.W.2d 323 (1957).</para><para>Oath requires attorney to observe established codes of professional ethics. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Richards, 165 Neb. 80, 84 N.W.2d 136 (1957).</para><para>Oath requires attorney to refrain from impeding or obstructing the administration of justice. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Palmer, 160 Neb. 786, 71 N.W.2d 491 (1955).</para><para>Oath of attorney requires him to observe standards and codes of professional ethics and honor. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Wiebusch, 153 Neb. 583, 45 N.W.2d 583 (1951).</para><para>Oath administered to attorney requires him faithfully to discharge his duties, one of which is to abstain from all offensive practices. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Goldman, 127 Neb. 340, 255 N.W. 32 (1934).</para><para><emphasis>2. Violation of oath</emphasis></para><para>An attorney who misappropriates client trust funds to cover deficits in business account violates his oath of office under this section, as well as the Code of Professional Responsibility. State ex rel. NSBA v. Veith, 238 Neb. 239, 470 N.W.2d 549 (1991).</para><para>To determine whether and to what extent discipline should be imposed in a disciplinary proceeding against an attorney, it is necessary that the Supreme Court consider the nature of the offense, the need for deterring others, the maintenance of the reputation of the bar as a whole, the protection of the public, the attitude of the offender generally, and his present or future fitness to continue in the practice of law. State ex rel. NSBA v. Miller, 225 Neb. 261, 404 N.W.2d 40 (1987).</para><para>Attorney who secured forged endorsement of his client's bond receipt and then cashed the receipt violated his oath to faithfully discharge his duties as an attorney to the best of his abilities. State ex rel. NSBA v. Kelly, 221 Neb. 8, 374 N.W.2d 833 (1985).</para><para>Cumulative acts of deception upon a client are distinguishable from isolated incidents of neglect and therefor justify more serious sanctions. State ex rel. NSBA v. Frank, 214 Neb. 825, 336 N.W.2d 557 (1983).</para><para>A party has failed to faithfully discharge his duties as an attorney and counselor when he conceals material facts from a court and presents a report known by him to be less than a true, accurate, and full account. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. McArthur, 212 Neb. 815, 326 N.W.2d 173 (1982).</para><para>Attorney's violation of a disciplinary rule and failure to act competently by neglecting a matter entrusted to him is conduct violative of an attorney's oath as a member of the bar. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Divis, 212 Neb. 699, 325 N.W.2d 652 (1982).</para><para>An attorney who fails to use a trust account for client's funds, and who fails to properly transmit client's funds to the client, is guilty of unprofessional conduct and violates the Canons of Ethics and his oath as a member of the bar of this court. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Conley, 209 Neb. 717, 310 N.W.2d 520 (1981).</para><para>Failure to use a trust account for client's funds and to promptly transmit client's funds to the client is a violation of the Canons of Ethics and oath as a member of the bar. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. James, 209 Neb. 306, 307 N.W.2d 524 (1981).</para><para>An attorney who fails to fully explain to a client the nature of the client's claim and to adequately represent the client has violated his oath of office under this section as well as the Code of Professional Responsibility. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Association v. Walsh, 206 Neb. 737, 294 N.W.2d 873 (1980).</para><para>An attorney who performs an illegal act, such as knowingly writing an insufficient funds check, may be in violation of his oath under this section as well as the Code of Professional Responsibility even if he isn't prosecuted. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Association v. Walsh, 206 Neb. 737, 294 N.W.2d 873 (1980).</para><para>Where conduct of attorneys violates the Code of Professional Responsibility and their oath as attorneys, but does not involve moral turpitude, a judgment of reprimand and censure is appropriate. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Addison &amp; Levy, 198 Neb. 61, 251 N.W.2d 717 (1977).</para><para>Misconduct of a lawyer acting as a judge may justify disbarment. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Conover, 166 Neb. 132, 88 N.W.2d 135 (1958).</para><para><emphasis>3. Administration of oath</emphasis></para><para>Under former act, for purpose of admission, either district court or Supreme Court had authority to administer the required oath. In re Robinson, 82 Neb. 172, 117 N.W. 352 (1908).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>