<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Attorneys at Law" statutenumber="7-113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>7-113</statuteno><catchline>Attorneys as guardians; duties.</catchline><para>It shall be the duty of every attorney to act as the guardian of a minor or incompetent defendant in any suit pending against him when appointed for that purpose by an order of the court. He shall prepare himself to make the proper defense, to guard the rights of such defendant, and shall be entitled to such compensation as the court shall deem reasonable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 3, &#167; 14, p. 16; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 277; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 272; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 7-113; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 7-113; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 105.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Compensation</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Compensation</emphasis></para><para>Guardian for incompetent person in proceedings under Chapter 83, article 5, who carries out functions of guardian ad litem on appeal is entitled to reasonable compensation to be taxed as costs. State v. Cavitt, 182 Neb. 712, 157 N.W.2d 171 (1968).</para><para>Attorney acting as guardian ad litem is entitled to reasonable compensation for his services. White v. Ogier, 175 Neb. 883, 125 N.W.2d 68 (1963).</para><para>Guardian ad litem of an infant defendant is entitled to such compensation as the court shall deem reasonable taxed as costs. Omey v. Stauffer, 174 Neb. 247, 117 N.W.2d 481 (1962).</para><para>Guardian ad litem is entitled to such compensation as the court shall deem reasonable. Peterson v. Skiles, 173 Neb. 470, 113 N.W.2d 628 (1962).</para><para>Fee for guardian ad litem in divorce suit may be taxed as costs. Weesner v. Weesner, 168 Neb. 346, 95 N.W.2d 682 (1959).</para><para>Courts are authorized to tax as costs a reasonable fee for services of a guardian ad litem, the litigant to whom such fee is taxed depending on the circumstances of the case and discretion of the court. Ben B. Wood Realty Co. v. Wood, 132 Neb. 817, 273 N.W. 493 (1937).</para><para>Fees for guardian ad litem are properly allowed, though appeal in will contest is dismissed by district court. Shelby v. Meikle, 62 Neb. 10, 86 N.W. 939 (1901).</para><para>Services rendered by guardian ad litem do not furnish consideration for deed by the ward, since for performing the services the attorney must look only for the amount of his compensation to the court, which taxes the compensation allowed as part of the costs. Englebert v. Troxell, 40 Neb. 195, 58 N.W. 852 (1894), 26 L.R.A. 177 (1894), 42 A.S.R. 665 (1894).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>In suit for specific performance of contract, guardian ad litem fee for representing minor defendants cannot be taxed to adult defendants, but are costs taxable to plaintiff. Hajek v. Hajek, 108 Neb. 503, 188 N.W. 181 (1922).</para><para>Guardian ad litem may take appeal. Hunter v. Buchanan, 87 Neb. 277, 127 N.W. 166 (1910), 29 L.R.A.N.S. 147 (1910), Ann. Cas. 1912A 1072 (1910).</para><para>It is the duty of an attorney acting as guardian ad litem to submit to court for its consideration every relevant fact involving the rights of his ward. In re Estate of Manning, 85 Neb. 60, 122 N.W. 711 (1909).</para><para>A guardian ad litem has no authority to make stipulations for allowances against estate of ward, and at every stage of proceedings it is his duty to insist upon strict proof of everything which affects the rights of the ward. Court has no authority to appoint guardian ad litem until ward is served with process. In re Estate of Manning, 83 Neb. 417, 119 N.W. 672 (1909).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>