<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Attorneys At Law" id="id75"  statutenumber="7-209"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>7-209</statuteno><catchline id="id78">Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>The Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Fund is created. The fund shall consist of funds appropriated or transferred by the Legislature, funds donated to the legal education for public legal service and rural practice loan repayment assistance program pursuant to section 7-208, and application fees collected under the Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Act. Any money in the Legal Education for Public Service Loan Repayment Fund on July 18, 2014, shall be transferred to the Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Fund. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>The unexpended, unobligated balance in the Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Fund existing on June 30, 2017, shall be transferred to the General Fund on or before July 30, 2017, as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB907, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 17. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>