<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id36">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Attorneys At Law" id="id38"  statutenumber="7-206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>7-206</statuteno><catchline id="id41">Legal education
for public legal service and rural practice loan repayment assistance program; rules
and regulations; contents.</catchline><para>The board shall develop
and recommend to the Commission on Public Advocacy rules and regulations that
will govern the legal education for public legal service and rural practice loan repayment assistance program. The rules
and regulations shall include:</para>
<para>(1) Recipients shall be either: (a) Full-time, salaried
attorneys working for a tax-exempt charitable organization and whose primary
duties are public legal service or
(b) full-time attorneys primarily serving in a designated legal profession
shortage area;</para>
<para>(2) Loan applicants shall pay an application fee established
by the rules and regulations at a level anticipated to cover all or most of
the administrative costs of the program. All application fees shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Fund. Every effort
shall be made to minimize administrative costs and the application fee;</para>
<para>(3) The maximum annual loan amount, which initially shall
not exceed six thousand dollars per year per recipient, shall be an amount
which is sufficient to fulfill the purposes of recruiting and retaining public
legal service attorneys in occupations and areas with unmet needs, including public legal service attorneys with
skills in languages other than English and
attorneys committed to working in designated legal profession shortage areas.
The board may recommend adjustments of the loan amount annually to the commission
to account for inflation and other relevant factors;</para>
<para>(4) Loans shall be made only to refinance existing educational
loans;</para>
<para>(5) Information on the potential tax consequences
of income from discharge of indebtedness;</para><para>(6) Recipients shall agree to practice the
equivalent of at least three years of full-time practice in public legal service
or a designated legal profession shortage area; and</para><para>(7) Other criteria for loan
eligibility, application, payment, and repayment assistance necessary
to carry out the purposes of the Legal Education for Public Service and Rural Practice Loan Repayment Assistance Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB907, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>