<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" id="id236" statutenumber="47-632"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>47-632</statuteno><catchline id="id239">Community Corrections
Uniform Data Analysis Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1)
The Community Corrections Uniform Data Analysis Cash Fund is created. Except
as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, the
fund shall be within the Nebraska Commission on
Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice, shall be administered by the division, and
shall only be used to support operations costs and analysis relating to the
implementation and coordination of the uniform analysis of crime data pursuant
to the Community Corrections Act, including associated information technology
projects. The fund shall
consist of money collected pursuant to section 47-633.</para>
<para>(2) Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction
of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(3) The State Treasurer
shall transfer the following amounts from the Community Corrections Uniform
Data Analysis Cash Fund to the Violence Prevention Cash Fund:</para>
<para>(a) Two hundred thousand
dollars on July 1, 2011, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible;
and</para><para>(b)
Two hundred thousand dollars on July 1, 2012, or as soon thereafter as administratively
possible.</para><para>(4) Any money in the Community
Corrections Uniform Data Analysis Cash Fund available for investment shall
be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB390, &#167; 13.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>