<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails And Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>47-503</statuteno><catchline>Credit against jail term.</catchline><para>(1) Credit against a jail term shall be given to any person sentenced to a city or county jail for time spent in jail as a result of the criminal charge for which the jail term is imposed or as a result of conduct upon which such charge is based. Such credit shall include, but not be limited to, time spent in jail:</para><para>(a) Prior to trial;</para><para>(b) During trial;</para><para>(c) Pending sentence;</para><para>(d) Pending resolution of an appeal; and</para><para>(e) Prior to delivery of such person to the county board of corrections or, in counties which do not have a county board of corrections, the county sheriff.</para><para>(2) Credit to any person sentenced to a city or county jail who is eligible for credit pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall be set forth as part of the sentence at the time such sentence is imposed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 113, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Invalid or erroneous sentence.</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Credit not allowed</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Invalid or erroneous sentence</emphasis></para><para>When a court grants a defendant more or less credit for time served than the defendant actually served, that portion of the pronouncement of sentence is erroneous and may be corrected to reflect the accurate amount of credit as verified objectively by the record. State v. Galvan, 305 Neb. 513, 941 N.W.2d 183 (2020); State v. Clark, 278 Neb. 557, 772 N.W.2d 559 (2009).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the court had the authority to revise the sentence when the defendant was inadvertently given 361 days' credit for time served rather than the 61 days actually served. State v. Clark, 17 Neb. App. 361, 762 N.W.2d 64 (2009).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, where a portion of a sentence is valid and a portion is invalid or erroneous, the court has the authority to modify or revise the sentence by removing the invalid or erroneous portion of the sentence if the remaining portion of the sentence constitutes a complete valid sentence. State v. Clark, 17 Neb. App. 361, 762 N.W.2d 64 (2009).</para><para><emphasis>2. Credit not allowed</emphasis></para>This section does not authorize presentence credit against a jail sentence for time spent in the Department of Correctional Services serving a separate sentence. State v. Harms, 304 Neb. 441, 934 N.W.2d 850 (2019).<para>Under subsection (1) of this section, a defendant is not entitled to credit against a jail sentence for time spent in a residential substance abuse treatment facility. State v. Anderson, 18 Neb. App. 329, 779 N.W.2d 623 (2010).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>This section and section 83-1,106(1) use similar language, so the reasoning of cases involving one of these provisions is applicable to cases involving the other. State v. Wills, 285 Neb. 260, 826 N.W.2d 581 (2013).</para><para>This section provides that a defendant is entitled to “[c]redit against” his jail term. In context, that means that a judge cannot credit a defendant with more time served than the length of his or her sentence. State v. Wills, 285 Neb. 260, 826 N.W.2d 581 (2013).</para><para>Pursuant to this section, a sentencing court is required to separately determine, state, and grant credit for time served. State v. Clark, 278 Neb. 557, 772 N.W.2d 559 (2009).</para><para>The court has no discretion to grant a defendant more or less credit than is established by the record. State v. Clark, 278 Neb. 557, 772 N.W.2d 559 (2009).</para><para>Under this section, a sentencing judge is required, at the time of sentencing, to separately determine, state, and grant the amount of credit on the defendant's sentence to which the defendant is entitled. State v. Torres, 256 Neb. 380, 590 N.W.2d 184 (1999).</para>
<para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the giving of credit for time served is part of the sentence. State v. Clark, 17 Neb. App. 361, 762 N.W.2d 64 (2009).</para>
</annotation></law></legaldoc> 