<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id24">
<sectno id="id25" opdate="July 1, 2011">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Jails And Correctional Facilities" id="id26" statutenumber="47-120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id28">47-120</statuteno><catchline id="id29">Care of prisoners;
county board or county board of corrections; sheriff; duties; payment.</catchline>
<para>The county board or county board of corrections serving pursuant
to Chapter 23, article 28, shall provide proper quarters and adequate equipment
for the preparation and serving of all meals furnished to all prisoners confined
in the county jail. The county sheriff or the county board of corrections
shall have full charge and control of such services and the county board shall
provide for all washing, fuel, lights, and clothing for prisoners, subject to the
right of the county to be paid by the city or federal government for city
or federal prisoners at actual cost to the county. Supplies of every nature
entering into the furnishing of meals, washing, fuel, lights, and clothing
to the prisoners confined in the county jail shall be purchased and provided
under the direction of the county sheriff or the county board of corrections.
Payment for all purchases shall only be made by the county board on the original
invoices submitted by the sheriff or the county board of corrections of goods,
supplies, and services, setting forth (1) that the invoice correctly describes
the goods as to quality and quantity, (2) that the same have been received
and are in the custody of the affiant, (3) that they have been or will be
devoted exclusively to the purposes authorized in this section, and (4) that
the price charged is reasonable and just. Nothing in this section shall be
construed to restrict the sheriff or the county board of corrections in employing
necessary personnel and from otherwise carrying out the duties required in
the operation of the jail.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 628, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 394, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 4, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 695, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB218, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>