<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Jails And Correctional Facilities" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="47-905"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>47-905</statuteno><catchline>Office; duties; law enforcement agencies and prosecuting attorneys; cooperation; confidentiality.</catchline><para>(1) The office shall investigate:</para><para>(a) Allegations or incidents of possible misconduct, misfeasance, malfeasance, or violations of statutes or of rules or regulations of the department by an employee of or a person under contract with the department or a private agency; and</para><para>(b) Death or serious injury in private agencies, department correctional facilities, and other programs and facilities licensed by or under contract with the department. The department shall report all cases of death or serious injury of a person in a private agency, department correctional facility or program, or other program or facility licensed by the department to the Inspector General as soon as reasonably possible after the department learns of such death or serious injury. The department shall also report all cases of the death or serious injury of an employee when acting in his or her capacity as an employee of the department as soon as reasonably possible after the department learns of such death or serious injury. The department shall also report all cases when an employee is hospitalized in response to an injury received when acting in his or her capacity as an employee of the department as soon as reasonably possible after the department learns of such hospitalization. For purposes of this subdivision, serious injury means an injury which requires urgent and immediate medical treatment and restricts the injured person’s usual activity.</para><para>(2) Any investigation conducted by the Inspector General shall be independent of and separate from an investigation pursuant to sections 23-1821 to 23-1823.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding the fact that a criminal investigation, a criminal prosecution, or both are in progress, all law enforcement agencies and prosecuting attorneys shall cooperate with any investigation conducted by the Inspector General and shall, immediately upon request by the Inspector General, provide the Inspector General with copies of all law enforcement reports which are relevant to the Inspector General's investigation. All law enforcement reports which have been provided to the Inspector General pursuant to this section are not public records for purposes of sections 84-712 to 84-712.09 and shall not be subject to discovery by any other person or entity. Except to the extent that disclosure of information is otherwise provided for in the Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System Act, the Inspector General shall maintain the confidentiality of all law enforcement reports received pursuant to its request under this section. Law enforcement agencies and prosecuting attorneys shall, when requested by the Inspector General, collaborate with the Inspector General regarding all other information relevant to the Inspector General's investigation. If the Inspector General in conjunction with the Public Counsel determines it appropriate, the Inspector General may, when requested to do so by a law enforcement agency or prosecuting attorney, suspend an investigation by the office until a criminal investigation or prosecution is completed or has proceeded to a point that, in the judgment of the Inspector General, reinstatement of the Inspector General's investigation will not impede or infringe upon the criminal investigation or prosecution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB539, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>April 28, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>