<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id969"><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails And Correctional Facilities"  statutenumber="47-902"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>47-902</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature to:</para><para>(a) Establish a full-time program of investigation and performance review to provide increased accountability and oversight of the Nebraska correctional system;</para><para>(b) Assist in improving operations of the department and the Nebraska correctional system;</para><para>(c) Provide an independent form of inquiry for concerns regarding the actions of individuals and agencies responsible for the supervision and release of persons in the Nebraska correctional system. A lack of responsibility and accountability between individuals and private agencies in the current system make it difficult to monitor and oversee the Nebraska correctional system; and</para><para>(d) Provide a process for investigation and review in order to improve policies and procedures of the correctional system.</para><para>(2) It is not the intent of the Legislature in enacting the Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System Act to interfere with the duties of the Legislative Auditor or the Legislative Fiscal Analyst or to interfere with the statutorily defined investigative responsibilities or prerogatives of any officer, agency, board, bureau, commission, association, society, or institution of the executive branch of state government, except that the act does not preclude an inquiry on the sole basis that another agency has the same responsibility. The act shall not be construed to interfere with or supplant the responsibilities or prerogatives of the Governor to investigate, monitor, and report on the activities of the agencies, boards, bureaus, commissions, associations, societies, and institutions of the executive branch under his or her administrative direction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>