<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="47-623"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>47-623</statuteno><catchline>Council; members; terms; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The council shall include the following voting members:</para><para>(a) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice;</para><para>(b) The Director of Correctional Services;</para><para>(c) The chairperson of the Board of Parole;</para><para>(d) The Parole Administrator; and</para><para>(e) Nine members appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature, consisting of: One representative from a list of persons nominated by the Nebraska Criminal Defense Attorneys Association; one representative from a list of persons nominated by the Nebraska County Attorneys Association; one full-time officer or employee of a law enforcement agency; one mental health and substance abuse professional; from each congressional district, one provider of community-based behavioral health services; and two at-large members.</para><para>(2) The council shall include the following nonvoting members:</para><para>(a) The State Court Administrator;</para><para>(b) The probation administrator;</para><para>(c) Two members of the Legislature, appointed by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council;</para><para>(d) Two judges of the district court, appointed by the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court; and</para><para>(e) The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designee.</para><para>(3) The terms of office for members initially appointed under subdivision (1)(e) of this section shall be three years. Upon completion of the initial terms of such members, the Governor shall appoint (a) a representative from law enforcement, a mental health and substance abuse professional, and one at-large member for terms of one year, (b) a representative of the Nebraska Criminal Defense Attorneys Association, one provider of community-based behavioral health services from the first congressional district, one provider of community-based behavioral health services from the third congressional district, and one at-large member for terms of two years, and (c) a representative of the Nebraska County Attorneys Association and a provider of community-based behavioral health services from the second congressional district for terms of three years. Succeeding appointees shall be appointed for terms of three years. An appointee to a vacancy occurring from an unexpired term shall serve out the term of his or her predecessor. Members whose terms have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have been appointed and qualified.</para><para>(4) The council shall by majority vote elect a chairperson from among the members of the council.</para><para>(5) The members of the council shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred while engaged in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 215.</para></source></law></legaldoc>