<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-637"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>47-637</statuteno><catchline>Study of probation and parole service delivery; legislative findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(1) Nebraska's probation and parole services function administratively under different branches of state government. Probation services are currently under the judicial branch while parole is a function of the Department of Correctional Services in the executive branch;</para><para>(2) Probation and parole offender-based services share many characteristics relative to: Community supervision of offenders; risk assessment; enforcement of probation and parole terms and conditions; offender accountability; initiation of filings relating to probation and parole violations; providing offender assistance; and appropriate referral for community-based services, including, but not limited to, substance abuse and mental health evaluation and treatment, housing assistance, and workforce development;</para><para>(3) Laws 1971, LB 680, which statutorily established probation service delivery in the judicial branch, provided the authority for parole officers to supervise probationers;</para><para>(4) Laws 2003, LB 46, provided for the establishment of community-based programs, services, and facilities for both probationers and parolees. Access to and participation in program services and facilities are shared by probationers and parolees. Probation officers and parole officers are assigned supervision of probationers and parolees that concurrently access and participate in community-based programs and services; and</para><para>(5) It is appropriate for the Legislature to commission a study of the effectiveness, efficiency, and responsiveness of Nebraska's current administrative assignment of probation and parole service delivery.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB540, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>