
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id760"><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails And Correctional Facilities"  statutenumber="47-904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>47-904</statuteno><catchline>Office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System; created; Inspector General; appointment; term; qualifications; employees; removal.</catchline><para>(1) The office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System is created within the office of Public Counsel for the purpose of conducting investigations, audits, inspections, and other reviews of the Nebraska correctional system. The Inspector General shall be appointed by the Public Counsel with approval from the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council and the chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) The Inspector General shall be appointed for a term of five years and may be reappointed. The Inspector General shall be selected without regard to political affiliation and on the basis of integrity, capability for strong leadership, and demonstrated ability in accounting, auditing, financial analysis, law, management, public administration, investigation, or criminal justice administration or other closely related fields. No former or current executive or manager of the department shall be appointed Inspector General within five years after such former or current executive's or manager's period of service with the department. Not later than two years after the date of appointment, the Inspector General shall obtain certification as a Certified Inspector General by the Association of Inspectors General, its successor, or another nationally recognized organization that provides and sponsors educational programs and establishes professional qualifications, certifications, and licensing for inspectors general. During his or her employment, the Inspector General shall not be actively involved in partisan affairs.</para><para>(3) The Inspector General shall employ such investigators and support staff as he or she deems necessary to carry out the duties of the office within the amount available by appropriation through the office of Public Counsel for the office of Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System. The Inspector General shall be subject to the control and supervision of the Public Counsel, except that removal of the Inspector General shall require approval of the chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council and the chairperson of the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>