<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id372"><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-1102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>47-1102</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings and intent; act, purpose.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that studies have shown that post-prison outcomes tend to be better for committed offenders who participate in work release programs prior to discharge from custody. Specifically, findings indicate that committed offenders who participated in work release programs had a higher likelihood of obtaining post-release employment within the first calendar quarter after release and also had a significantly lower rate of recidivism than committed offenders who did not participate in work release programs prior to discharge from custody. In addition, studies indicate that committed offenders who participated in privately operated work release programs were significantly more likely to become employed after release.</para><para>(2) In light of these findings, and in order to give the Board of Parole and the Department of Correctional Services additional options for the placement of committed offenders, it is the intent of the Legislature:</para><para>(a) To increase the number of committed offenders in the Nebraska correctional system who are exposed to work release prior to discharge from custody; and</para><para>(b) To do so in settings that also offer therapy, programming, treatment, vocational training, and educational classes.</para><para>(3) To achieve these goals, the purpose of the Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act is to empower the Division of Parole Supervision and the Department of Correctional Services to contract with private providers to establish community work release and reentry centers at various locations throughout the State of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>