<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id588"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-1116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>47-1116</statuteno><catchline>Reentry housing facilities; investigations and evaluations; cooperation; access to facilities and records; fire safety code and building or construction code inspections; notice of imminent threat; contest findings.</catchline><para>(1) Reentry housing facilities shall cooperate with investigations and evaluations conducted pursuant to the Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act and shall provide the department, board, probation administration, and the Office of Public Counsel with reasonable access to facilities and records related to the provision of reentry housing.</para><para>(2) The department or board may request the State Fire Marshal to investigate any reentry housing facility for fire safety under section 81-502. The State Fire Marshal shall assess a fee for such inspection under section 81-505.01 payable by the facility. The State Fire Marshal may delegate the authority to make such inspections to qualified local fire prevention personnel under section 81-502.</para><para>(3) The department or board may request a county, city, or village to inspect any reentry housing facility for the purpose of administering or enforcing the state building code or an applicable local building or construction code enacted pursuant to the Building Construction Act, if the county, city, or village has taken on the responsibility of code enforcement. A county, city, or village may assess fees for such an inspection under section 71-6406.</para><para>(4) The department or board shall promptly notify a reentry housing facility and relevant agencies if there is reason to believe conditions in the facility present an imminent threat to the health or safety of reentering persons residing at the facility.</para><para>(5) The department shall work with the board, probation administration, and the advisory board to establish a speedy process by which reentry housing facilities may contest the findings of any investigation or evaluation pursuant to the Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 72. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>