<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id487"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-1115"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>47-1115</statuteno><catchline>Reentry housing and services; program; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The department, with the assistance of the board, shall establish a program to encourage the development of reentry housing, coordinate the provisions of reentry services, and provide standards for reentry housing. Through this program, the department shall:</para><para>(a) Establish minimum standards for reentry housing facilities, including requirements related to health and safety, insurance, evaluations, and inspections, with input from the advisory committee;</para><para>(b) Monitor compliance with these minimum standards and investigate suspected violations;</para><para>(c) Coordinate evaluations of reentry housing facilities based on living conditions, staffing, programming, and other criteria;</para><para>(d) Communicate with relevant agencies regarding evaluation results and compliance with minimum standards;</para><para>(e) Facilitate communication between the department, board, probation administration, and reentry housing facilities regarding reentering persons in need of housing and the availability of housing to meet such needs;</para><para>(f) Engage in regular discussions with entities which organize and prioritize housing services for people experiencing homelessness or at risk of homelessness in Nebraska;</para><para>(g) Track data on costs, utilization, and outcomes for reentry housing within the state and use this data to determine trends and project future needs and costs; and</para><para>(h) Electronically submit an annual report to the Legislature, the Supreme Court, and the Governor which describes the status of housing for reentering persons in Nebraska. The report shall include details on housing-related expenditures, characteristics of reentry housing facilities and other places which provide housing for reentering persons, characteristics of the individuals receiving financial assistance for housing, and recommendations for improving the quality and availability of housing for reentering persons in the state.</para><para>(2) The department and board may use available funds to encourage development of quality, safe reentry housing and to assist existing reentry housing facilities in making improvements for the benefit of reentering persons and public safety.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 71. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>