<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id888"><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-1105"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>47-1105</statuteno><catchline>Division; department; powers and duties; agreements with private providers; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The division and the department may exercise all powers and perform all duties necessary and proper for carrying out their responsibilities under the Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act.</para><para>(2) The division and the department may use designated funds provided by the Legislature to enter into agreements with private providers for the development and operation of community work release and reentry centers to be established at various locations throughout the state. Any such agreement shall require a private provider to:</para><para>(a) Establish a contract with public or private employers to provide employment for committed offenders placed at the center;</para><para>(b) Assist any committed offender placed at the center to obtain and maintain employment in the community;</para><para>(c) Provide vocational training, education, programming, and treatment for issues related to the criminogenic needs of any committed offender placed at the center; and</para><para>(d) Otherwise direct and supervise the activities and behavior of any committed offender placed at the center as provided in the act.</para><para>(3) In an agreement under this section, the division or the department may include contractual requirements that obligate the private provider to offer to any committed offender placed at the center:</para><para>(a) Specialized educational or vocational training; and</para><para>(b) Other programming that will address the mental health, behavioral health, or substance abuse treatment needs of such committed offender.</para><para>(4) An agreement under this section shall require the community work release and reentry center to establish programs, rules, and enforcement systems:</para><para>(a) Regarding the behavior of committed offenders;</para><para>(b) To ensure that committed offenders seek and retain continuous employment;</para><para>(c) For the treatment of committed offenders for substance abuse;</para><para>(d) To ensure that committed offenders only leave the center for purposes of work or for other specified and approved activities, including, but not limited to, job interviews, medical appointments, treatment, and outings to visit family;</para><para>(e) To ensure that committed offenders consistently participate in all necessary therapy, programming, treatment, vocational training, and educational classes; and</para><para>(f) To ensure that committed offenders maintain their scheduled work hours.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>