<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id627"><amendatorysection chaptername="Jails and Correctional Facilities" statutenumber="47-1117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>47-1117</statuteno><catchline>Reentry Continuity Advisory Board; created; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Reentry Continuity Advisory Board is created. The board shall include the following members:</para><para>(a) The Inspector General of the Nebraska Correctional System;</para><para>(b) The Director of Correctional Services or his or her designee;</para><para>(c) The chairperson of the Board of Parole or his or her designee;</para><para>(d) The probation administrator or his or her designee; and</para><para>(e) Five additional members to be appointed by the Governor. Such members shall include:</para><para>(i) An individual with experience in reentry and restorative justice service delivery;</para><para>(ii) A victims' rights representative;</para><para>(iii) A formerly incarcerated individual;</para><para>(iv) An individual with expertise in mental or behavioral health; and</para><para>(v) An individual with experience in public policy.</para><para>(2) The advisory board shall select a chairperson from among its members.</para><para>(3) The advisory board shall identify areas for improving continuity and collaboration among the department, the division, the board, probation administration, and any other relevant criminal justice entities and offer advice on practices that will enhance the continuity of reentry services and reentry housing for individuals in the criminal justice system.</para><para>(4) The advisory board shall:</para><para>(a) Conduct regular meetings;</para><para>(b) Provide advice and assistance to the department and board relating to reentry housing in Nebraska;</para><para>(c) Promote the interests of reentering persons and their families;</para><para>(d) Promote public safety through effective reintegration into the community;</para><para>(e) Provide input on the process of evaluating reentry housing facilities;</para><para>(f) Engage with neighborhood groups and other stakeholders;</para><para>(g) Provide reports as requested by the department and board; and</para><para>(h) Engage in other activities as requested by the department and board.</para><para>(5) The advisory board shall convene at least quarterly. The members described in subdivisions (1)(b), (c), and (d) of this section shall attend each meeting of the advisory board and share and present information relevant to the mission of the advisory board.</para><para>(6) The department, division, board, and probation administration shall provide information requested by the advisory board related to its mission. This shall include, but is not limited to, information regarding:</para><para>(a) The use of evidence-based risk assessments and evidence-based programming;</para><para>(b) Participation in rehabilitation and education programs;</para><para>(c) Treatment and programming offered, including vocational training, substance abuse treatment, cognitive-behavioral therapy, and mental health counseling;</para><para>(d) Population and demographic data;</para><para>(e) Use of and need for transitional housing and reentry housing;</para><para>(f) Identified gaps in services;</para><para>(g) Recidivism;</para><para>(h) Institutional conduct; and</para><para>(i) Post-release and reentry planning and services;</para><para>(7) The advisory board shall conduct periodic evaluations of the effectiveness of the collaborative efforts and reentry programs offered by the department, division, board, probation administration, and other criminal justice agencies. Such evaluation shall be accomplished using an integrated reentry and rehabilitation framework, which shall include an examination of:</para><para>(a) The extent to which agencies are conducting comprehensive assessments of criminal justice-involved individuals' needs and risks, including education, employment, housing, mental health, substance abuse, and family support;</para><para>(b) Whether the agencies are providing individualized reentry planning tailored to the specific needs and circumstances of such individuals, with a focus on addressing criminogenic factors and promoting positive behavioral change;</para><para>(c) Whether such individuals have access to evidence-based interventions, programs, and services both during and following incarceration, including education, vocational training, mental health treatment, substance abuse counseling, and life skills development; and</para><para>(d) The extent of collaboration and coordination between the department, parole, probation, other criminal justice agencies, community-based organizations, and other stakeholders.</para><para>(8) The advisory board shall assist probation administration, the department, and the division in implementing performance metrics for staff as provided in sections 29-2243 and 83-171.01. The advisory board shall regularly review such agencies' implementation and use of such performance metrics and offer updated guidance to ensure that such metrics are aligned with best practices, stakeholder input, and the evolving goals and priorities of the criminal justice system.</para><para>(9) On or before October 1, 2025, and on or before each October 1 thereafter, the advisory board shall electronically submit a report to the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature. The report shall include data regarding baselines, goals, efforts undertaken to achieve such goals, and action steps outlined to meet such goals and set objectives. The report shall detail the outcomes of parole decisions, reentry efforts, recidivism rates, and any challenges encountered. The report shall provide stakeholders with a clear understanding of the progress made, challenges faced, and strategies employed throughout the reporting period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>