<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id24" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="68-959"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>68-959</statuteno><catchline>Medical home pilot program; designation;
division; duties; evaluation; report.</catchline><para>(1) No later than January
1, 2012, the division shall design and implement a medical home pilot program,
in consultation with the Medical Home Advisory Council, in one or more geographic
regions of the state to provide access to medical homes for patients. The
division shall apply for any available federal or other funds for the program.
The division shall establish necessary and appropriate reimbursement policies
and incentives under such program to accomplish the purposes of the Medical
Home Pilot Program Act. The reimbursement policies:</para>
<para>(a) Shall require the provision of a medical home for clients;</para>
<para>(b) Shall be designed to increase the availability of primary health
care services to clients;</para>
<para>(c) May provide an increased reimbursement rate to providers who provide
primary health care services to clients outside of regular business hours
or on weekends; and</para>
<para>(d) May provide a postevaluation incentive payment.</para>
<para>(2) No later than June 1, 2014, the division shall evaluate the medical
home pilot program and report the results of such evaluation to the Governor
and the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature. The report submitted to the committee
shall be submitted electronically. Such report shall include an
evaluation of health outcomes and cost savings achieved, recommendations for
improvement, recommendations regarding continuation and expansion of the program,
and such other information as deemed necessary by the division or requested
by the committee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB396, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 93.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate><terminationdate>June 30, 2014</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>