<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-621"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>68-621</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>(1)
A referendum group, as referred to in sections 68-621 to 68-630, shall consist
of the employees of the state, a single political subdivision of this state,
or any instrumentality jointly created by this state and any other state or
states, the employees of which are or may be members of a retirement system
covering such employees, except that: (a) The employees of the University
of Nebraska shall constitute a referendum group; (b) the employees of a Class
V school district shall constitute a referendum group; (c) all employees of
the State of Nebraska who are or may be members of the School Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska, including employees of institutions operated by
the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, employees of institutions
operated by the Department of Correctional Services and the Department of
Health and Human Services, and employees subordinate to the State Board of
Education, shall constitute a referendum group; and (d) all employees of school
districts of the State of Nebraska, county superintendents, and county school
administrators, who are or may be members of the School Retirement System
of the State of Nebraska, shall constitute a single referendum group.</para>
<para>(2) The managing authority of a political subdivision or educational
institution shall be the board, committee, or council having general authority
over a political subdivision, university, college, or school district whose
employees constitute or are included in a referendum group; the managing authority
of the state shall be the Governor; and insofar as sections 68-601 to 68-631 may be applicable to
county superintendents and county school administrators, managing authority
shall mean the board of county commissioners or county supervisors of the
county in which the county superintendent was elected or with which the county
school administrator contracted.</para>
<para>(3) Eligible employees, as referred to in sections 68-621 to 68-630,
shall mean those employees of the state or any political subdivision thereof
who at or during the time of voting in a referendum as herein provided are
in positions covered by a retirement system, are members of such retirement
system, and were in such positions at the time of giving of the notice of
such referendum, as herein required, except that no such employee shall be
considered an eligible employee if at the time of such voting such employee
is in a position to which the state agreement applies or if such employee
is in service in a police officer or firefighter position.</para>
<para>(4) State agreement, as referred to in sections 68-621 to 68-630, shall
mean the agreement between the State of Nebraska and the designated officer
of the United States of America entered into pursuant to section 68-603.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 264, &#167; 15, p. 821; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 537, &#167; 1, p. 2187; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 563, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 802, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 297; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1216, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB684, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>