<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id189">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id191" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-921"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>68-921</statuteno><catchline id="id194">Entitlement
of spouse; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections
68-921 to 68-925:</para>
<para>(1) Assets means property which is not exempt from consideration
in determining eligibility for medical assistance under rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated under section 68-922;</para>
<para>(2) Community spouse monthly income allowance means the amount
of income determined by the department in accordance with section 1924 of
the federal Social Security Act, as amended, Public Law 100-360, 42 U.S.C.
1396r-5;</para>
<para>(3) Community spouse resource allowance means the amount
of assets determined in accordance with section 1924 of the federal Social
Security Act, as amended, Public Law 100-360, 42 U.S.C. 1396r-5. For purposes
of 42 U.S.C. 1396r-5(f)(2)(A)(i), the amount specified by the state shall
be twelve thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(4) Home and community-based services means services furnished
under home and community-based waivers as defined in Title XIX of the federal
Social Security Act, as amended, 42 U.S.C. 1396;</para>
<para>(5) Qualified applicant means a person (a) who applies for
medical assistance on or after July 9, 1988, (b) who is under care in a state-licensed
hospital, a nursing facility, an intermediate care facility for persons with developmental disabilities, an
assisted-living facility, or a center for the developmentally disabled, as
such terms are defined in the Health Care Facility Licensure Act, or an adult
family home certified by the department or is receiving home and community-based
services, and (c) whose spouse is not under such care or receiving such services
and is not applying for or receiving medical assistance;</para>
<para>(6) Qualified recipient means a person (a) who has applied
for medical assistance before July 9, 1988, and is eligible for such assistance,
(b) who is under care in a facility certified to receive medical assistance
funds or is receiving home and community-based services, and (c) whose spouse
is not under such care or receiving such services and is not applying for
or receiving medical assistance; and</para>
<para>(7) Spouse means the spouse of a qualified applicant or qualified
recipient.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 419, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 362, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 244, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 336; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 608, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 81; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 68-1038; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB185, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 250; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 14.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>