<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-154.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-154.01</statuteno><catchline>Employable recipient; community service required; exception.</catchline><para>(1) Any individual applying for general assistance who has completed a county-approved vocational, rehabilitation, or job training program within two years prior to the date of such application or who refuses or fails to participate in such a program may be required to participate in a county-approved community service program. Any employable recipient who has completed such a vocational, rehabilitation, or job training program and continues to be unemployed for a period of three calendar months from the date of completing such program may be required to participate in such a community service program.</para><para>(2) No individual who is a single parent and has legal custody of his or her child under six years of age shall be required to perform community service. No individual shall be required to participate in a county-approved community service program unless he or she has first been given the opportunity to participate in a county-approved vocational, rehabilitation, or job training program.</para><para>(3) The maximum number of hours of community service required of each employable recipient shall be determined by dividing the amount of his or her general assistance received in the calendar month by the federal minimum hourly wage. No individual shall be required to perform community service for more than eight hours in any one day or more than sixteen hours in one week.</para><para>(4) No individual required to perform community service pursuant to this section shall be denied general assistance for failure to participate in a county-approved community service program through no fault of his or her own.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 227, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 