<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id832"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-997"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>68-997</statuteno><catchline>Job-skills programs; voluntary; departments; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning October 1, 2020, the Department of Health and Human Services shall inform each adult applicant for medical assistance about job-skills programs within the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Labor, or other skill-based programs that could assist the applicant for medical assistance in obtaining job skills or training, employment, higher-paying jobs, or related skills. The Department of Health and Human Services shall connect interested applicants to such job-skills programs. The job-skills programs may be utilized on a voluntary basis by applicants for medical assistance or recipients of medical assistance. The job-skills programs do not affect the receipt of services provided under the Medical Assistance Act.</para><para>(2) Beginning February 1, 2021, and within thirty days of the expiration of each subsequent calendar quarter within the years 2021 and 2022, the Department of Health and Human Services shall report electronically to the Clerk of the Legislature on the total number of applicants for medical assistance who were referred to job-skills programs under this section and any job-skills services received as a result of this section by applicants for medical assistance.</para><para>(3) Beginning January 1, 2021, through December 31, 2022, the Department of Labor shall report quarterly to the Department of Health and Human Services the number of applicants for medical assistance who were referred to job-skills programs under this section, the number of applicants for medical assistance who received help obtaining job skills or training, employment, higher-paying jobs, or related skills under this section, and the types of job-skills services received as a result of this section.</para><para>(4) The Department of Health and Human Services and the Department of Labor shall administer this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1158, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>