<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance"  statutenumber="68-971"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-971</statuteno><catchline>Amendment to medicaid state plan or
waiver; Nebraska Regional Poison Center; payments; use; department; duties;
University of Nebraska Medical Center; report.</catchline><para>(1) On or
before January 1, 2012, the department shall submit an application to the
federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services of the United States Department
of Health and Human Services to amend the medicaid state plan or seek a waiver
to provide for utilization of the unused administrative cap to allow for payments
to the Nebraska Regional Poison Center funded through the University of Nebraska
Medical Center Cash Fund to help offset the cost for treatment of children
who are eligible for assistance under the medical assistance program and the
Children's Health Insurance Program established pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 1397aa
et seq., pursuant to the federal Children's Health Insurance Program Reauthorization
Act of 2009, Public Law 111-3, as such act existed on January 1, 2010.</para>
<para>(2) Upon approval of the amendment to the medicaid state plan or the
granting of the waiver, the University of Nebraska Medical Center shall transfer
an amount, not to exceed two hundred fifty thousand dollars, to the Health
and Human Services Cash Fund for the Nebraska Department of Health and Human
Services to meet the state match to maximize the use of the unused administrative
cap money. At the time the department receives the transferred amount or any
portion thereof and the corollary federal funds, the department shall transfer
the combined funds to the University of Nebraska Medical Center Cash Fund
for operation of the Nebraska Regional Poison Center. If no amendment is approved
nor waiver granted or if less than two hundred fifty thousand dollars is needed
for the match, then the University of Nebraska Medical Center may use the
remaining state appropriation for the operation of the Nebraska Regional Poison
Center.</para>
<para>(3) The University of Nebraska Medical Center shall report electronically to the Legislative
Fiscal Analyst on or before October 1 of every year the amount transferred
to the department in the prior fiscal year and the amount of matching funds
received under this section for the Nebraska Regional Poison Center in the
prior fiscal year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB525, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 94.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>