<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-928"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-928</statuteno><catchline>Licensed insurer or self-funded insurer; provide coverage information.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, at the request of the department, a licensed insurer or a self-funded insurer shall provide coverage information to the department without an individual's authorization for purposes of:</para><para>(a) Determining an individual's eligibility for state benefit programs, including the medical assistance program; or</para><para>(b) Coordinating benefits with state benefit programs.</para><para>Such information shall be provided within thirty days after the date of request unless good cause is shown. Requests for coverage information shall specify individual recipients for whom information is being requested.</para><para>(2)(a) Coverage information requested pursuant to subsection (1) of this section regarding a limited benefit policy shall be limited to whether a specified individual has coverage and, if so, a description of that coverage, and such information shall be used solely for the purposes of subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this section, limited benefit policy means a policy of insurance issued by a licensed insurer that consists only of one or more, or any combination of the following:</para><para>(i) Coverage only for accident or disability income insurance, or any combination thereof;</para><para>(ii) Coverage for specified disease or illness; or</para><para>(iii) Hospital indemnity or other fixed indemnity insurance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 589, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2005, &#167; 68-10,102; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 257.</para></source></law></legaldoc>