<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id25" statutenumber="68-915"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>68-915</statuteno><catchline id="id28">Eligibility.</catchline><para>The following persons shall be eligible for medical assistance:</para><para>(1) Dependent children as defined in section 43-504;</para><para>(2) Aged, blind, and disabled persons as defined in sections 68-1002 to 68-1005;</para><para>(3) Children under nineteen years of age who are eligible under section 1905(a)(i) of the federal Social Security Act;</para><para>(4) Persons who are presumptively eligible as allowed under sections 1920 and 1920B of the federal Social Security Act;</para><para>(5) Children under nineteen years of age with a family income equal to or less than two hundred percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline, as allowed under Title XIX and Title XXI of the federal Social Security Act, without regard to resources, and pregnant women with a family income equal to or less than one hundred eighty-five percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline, as allowed under Title XIX and Title XXI of the federal Social Security Act, without regard to resources. Children described in this subdivision and subdivision (6) of this section shall remain eligible for six consecutive months from the date of initial eligibility prior to redetermination of eligibility. The department may review eligibility monthly thereafter pursuant to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the department. The department may determine upon such review that a child is ineligible for medical assistance if such child no longer meets eligibility standards established by the department;</para><para>(6) For purposes of Title XIX of the federal Social Security Act as provided in subdivision (5) of this section, children with a family income as follows:</para><para>(a) Equal to or less than one hundred fifty percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline with eligible children one year of age or younger;</para><para>(b) Equal to or less than one hundred thirty-three percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline with eligible children over one year of age and under six years of age; or</para><para>(c) Equal to or less than one hundred percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline with eligible children six years of age or older and less than nineteen years of age;</para><para>(7) Persons who are medically needy caretaker relatives as allowed under 42 U.S.C. 1396d(a)(ii);</para><para>(8) As allowed under 42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(10)(A)(ii)(XV) and (XVI), disabled persons who have a family income of less than two hundred fifty percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline. Such persons shall be subject to payment of premiums as a percentage of family income beginning at not less than two hundred percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline. Such premiums shall be graduated based on family income and shall not exceed seven and one-half percent of family income;</para><para>(9) As allowed under 42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(10)(A)(ii), persons who:</para><para>(a) Have been screened for breast and cervical cancer under the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention breast and cervical cancer early detection program established under Title XV of the federal Public Health Service Act, 42 U.S.C. 300k et seq., in accordance with the requirements of section 1504 of such act, 42 U.S.C. 300n, and who need treatment for breast or cervical cancer, including precancerous and cancerous conditions of the breast or cervix;</para><para>(b) Are not otherwise covered under creditable coverage as defined in section 2701(c) of the federal Public Health Service Act, 42 U.S.C. 300gg-3(c);</para><para>(c) Have not attained sixty-five years of age; and</para><para>(d) Are not eligible for medical assistance under any mandatory categorically needy eligibility group;</para><para>(10) Persons eligible for services described in subsection (3) of section 68-972; and</para><para>(11) Persons eligible pursuant to section 68-992.</para><para>Except as provided in subdivision (8) of this section and section 68-972, eligibility shall be determined under this section using an income budgetary methodology that determines children's eligibility at no greater than two hundred percent of the Office of Management and Budget income poverty guideline and adult eligibility using adult income standards no greater than the applicable categorical eligibility standards established pursuant to state or federal law. Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (8) of this section, the department shall determine eligibility under this section pursuant to such income budgetary methodology and subdivision (1)(q) of section 68-1713.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 397, &#167; 5, p. 1278; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1127, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 229, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 455, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 323; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1063, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 677, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 8, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 411, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 301, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2005, &#167; 68-1020; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 249; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB351, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB603, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB599, &#167; 3; </para><para>Initiative Law 2018, No. 427, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB323, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>The adoption of an act of Congress to be passed in the future would be an unconstitutional attempt on the part of the Legislature to delegate legislative authority to Congress. By adopting the provisions of federal law, this section provides that caretaker relatives are eligible for medical assistance benefits. The Legislature may lawfully adopt by reference an existing law or regulation of another jurisdiction, including the United States. Clemens v. Harvey, 247 Neb. 77, 525 N.W.2d 185 (1994).</para><para>In order for a minor or an incompetent adult without a legal guardian to qualify for assistance under this section, the applicant's parent must be a legal resident of Nebraska, the applicant's legal residence in Nebraska must be established by a court, or the applicant must have left her parents' home while the parents were legal residents of Nebraska. Gosney v. Department of Public Welfare, 206 Neb. 137, 291 N.W.2d 708 (1980).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>