<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id897"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-996"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>68-996</statuteno><catchline>Medicaid Managed Care Excess Profit Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Medicaid Managed Care Excess Profit Fund is created. The fund shall contain money returned to the State Treasurer pursuant to subdivision (1)(c) of section 68-995.</para><para>(2) The fund shall first be used to offset any losses under subdivision (1)(b) of section 68-995 and then to provide for (a) services addressing the health needs of adults and children under the Medical Assistance Act, including filling service gaps, (b) system improvements, (c) evidence-based early intervention home visitation programs, (d) medical respite services, (e) translation and interpretation services, (f) coverage for continuous glucose monitors as described in section 68-911, (g) other services sustaining access to care, (h) services under the Nebraska Prenatal Plus Program, (i) grants pursuant to the Intergenerational Care Facility Incentive Grant Program, (j) evidence-based nurse home visiting services, (k) domestic violence services, (l) reimbursement of the actual costs of providing eligible activities and services described in section 81-2222, and (m) the Family Resource and Juvenile Assessment Center Pilot Program, as determined by the Legislature. The fund shall only be used for the purposes described in this section.</para><para>(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1158, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB62, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB857, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB904, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB905, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1413, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB22, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB48, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 147; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB380, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB382, &#167; 1. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB22, section 11, LB48, section 12, with LB264, section 147, LB380, section 8, and LB382, section 1, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB22 became effective September 3, 2025. Changes made by LB48 became effective September 3, 2025. Changes made by LB264 became operative May 22, 2025. Changes made by LB380 became effective September 3, 2025. Changes made by LB382 became effective September 3, 2025.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>