<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id176">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id178" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-919">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>68-919</statuteno><catchline id="id181">Medical assistance
recipient; liability; when; claim; procedure; department; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) The recipient of medical assistance under the medical
assistance program shall be indebted to the department for the total amount
paid for medical assistance on behalf of the recipient if:</para>
<para>(a) The recipient was fifty-five years of age or older at
the time the medical assistance was provided; or</para>
<para>(b) The recipient resided in a medical institution and, at
the time of institutionalization or application for medical assistance, whichever
is later, the department determines that the recipient could not have reasonably
been expected to be discharged and resume living at home. For purposes of
this section, medical institution means a nursing facility, an intermediate
care facility for persons
with developmental disabilities, or an inpatient hospital.</para>
<para>(2) The debt accruing under subsection (1) of this section
arises during the life of the recipient but shall be held in abeyance until
the death of the recipient. Any such debt to the department that exists when
the recipient dies shall be recovered only after the death of the recipient's
spouse, if any, and only when the recipient is not survived by a child who
either is under twenty-one years of age or is blind or totally and permanently
disabled as defined by the Supplemental Security Income criteria.</para>
<para>(3) The debt shall include the total amount of medical assistance
provided when the recipient was fifty-five years of age or older or during
a period of institutionalization as described in subsection (1) of this section
and shall not include interest.</para>
<para>(4) In any probate proceedings in which the department has
filed a claim under this section, no additional evidence of foundation shall
be required for the admission of the department's payment record supporting
its claim if the payment record bears the seal of the department, is certified
as a true copy, and bears the signature of an authorized representative of
the department.</para>
<para>(5) The department may waive or compromise its claim, in
whole or in part, if the department determines that enforcement of the claim
would not be in the best interests of the state or would result in undue hardship
as provided in rules and regulations of the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1224, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 334; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 257, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1005, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2004, &#167; 68-1036.02; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB185, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 13.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The plain and unambiguous language of this section provides that reimbursement claims for medical expenses arise at or after the death of the recipient. In re Estate of Tvrz, 260 Neb. 991, 620 N.W.2d 757 (2001).</para>
<para>Subsection (4) of this section clearly dispenses with foundation for the admission of the record, if properly certified. In re Estate of Reimers, 16 Neb. App. 610, 746 N.W.2d 724 (2008).</para>
<para>This section does not create any presumption that the amounts shown on the payment record of the Department of Health and Human Services are reimbursable by the recipient's estate&#8212;such must still be proved&#8212;and if the exhibit does not do so, then additional evidence is needed. In re Estate of Reimers, 16 Neb. App. 610, 746 N.W.2d 724 (2008).</para>
<para>A claim by the Department of Health and Human Services Finance and Support for reimbursement of medical assistance benefits pursuant to this section is one that necessarily falls within the provisions of subsection (b) of section 30-2485 as arising "at or after" the death of the decedent who is a recipient of those benefits. In re Estate of Tvrz, 9 Neb. App. 98, 608 N.W.2d 226 (2000).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>