
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-608"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-608</statuteno><catchline>Coverage by political subdivisions;
plan; modification; approval by state agency.</catchline><para>Unless otherwise
provided for by sections 68-601 to 68-631, each
political subdivision of the state is hereby authorized to submit for approval
by the state agency a plan for extending the benefits of Title II of the Social
Security Act, in conformity with applicable provisions of such act, to employees
of such political subdivision and is hereby further authorized to submit for
approval by the state agency any modification or amendment to any then existing
plan if such modification or amendment is necessary or desirable to secure
the benefits and exemptions allowable to such political subdivisions thereof
or to any employee of the political subdivision in conformity with Title II
of the act. Each such plan and any amendment thereof shall be approved by
the state agency if it finds that such plan or such plan as amended is in
conformity with such requirements as are provided in regulations of the state
agency, except that no such plan shall be approved unless: (1) It is in conformity
with the requirements of the act and with the agreement entered into under
sections 68-603 and 68-604; (2) it provides that all services which constitute
employment and are performed in the employ of the political subdivision by
employees thereof will be covered by the plan; (3) it specifies the source
or sources from which the funds necessary to make the payments required by
subsection (1) of section 68-610 and by section 68-611 are expected to be
derived and contains reasonable assurance that such sources will be adequate
for such purpose; (4) it provides for such methods of administration of the
plan by the political subdivision as are found by the state agency to be necessary
for the proper and efficient administration of the plan; (5) it provides that
the political subdivision will make such reports in such form and containing
such information as the state agency may from time to time require and will
comply with such provisions as the state agency or the Secretary of Health
and Human Services may from time to time find necessary to assure the correctness
and verification of such reports; and (6) it authorizes the state agency to
terminate the plan in its entirety, in the discretion of the state agency,
if it finds that there has been a failure to comply substantially with any
provision contained in such plan, such termination to take effect at the expiration
of such notice and on such conditions as may be provided by regulations of
the state agency and may be consistent with the provisions of the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 297, &#167; 5(1), p. 981; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 264, &#167; 6, p. 817; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 536, &#167; 3, p. 2184; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 933, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 820, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1216, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB684, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>