<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id15"> <sectno id="id16" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 24.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id17" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-948"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id19">68-948</statuteno><catchline id="id20">Medicaid Reform Council; established; members; duties; expenses; terms; vacancies; department; provide information.</catchline><para>(1) The Medicaid Reform Council is established. The council shall consist of ten persons appointed by the Governor. The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature or his or her designee shall serve as a nonvoting, ex officio member of the council. The council shall include, but not be limited to, at least one representative from each of the following: Providers, recipients of medical assistance, advocates for such recipients, business representatives, insurers, and elected officials. The Governor shall appoint the chairperson of the council. Members of the council may be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para> <para>(2) The council shall (a) oversee and advise the department regarding implementation of reforms to the medical assistance program, including, but not limited to, reforms such as those contained in the Medicaid Reform Plan, (b) conduct public meetings at least quarterly and other meetings at the call of the chairperson of the council, in consultation with the department, and (c) provide comments and recommendations to the department regarding the administration of the medical assistance program and any proposed changes to such program.</para> <para>(3) The department shall provide the council with any reports, data, analysis, or other such information upon which the department relied, which provided a basis for the department's proposed reforms, or which the department otherwise intends to present to the council at least two weeks prior to the quarterly meeting.</para> <para>(4) Beginning June 30, 2010, the terms of the existing members of the council shall be extended as follows: One-half of the members shall serve for two-year terms and one-half of the members shall serve for four-year terms as determined by the Governor. Thereafter all members shall serve for four-year terms. Members may be reappointed at the discretion of the Governor. Appointments to the council occurring as a result of replacement of an existing member at the expiration of the member's term or due to resignation of an existing member shall be made by the Governor.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 262; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 24.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>