<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id485"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-976"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-976</statuteno><catchline>Provider with high categorical risk level; fingerprint-based criminal history record information check; Nebraska State Patrol; issue report; cost; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any provider with a high categorical risk level as determined by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services or the medicaid assistance program established pursuant to the Medical Assistance Act shall be subject to a fingerprint-based criminal history record information check.</para><para>(b) Such provider who is an individual, or any individual with at least a five percent direct or indirect ownership interest in any such provider, shall provide his or her fingerprints to the Nebraska State Patrol. The Nebraska State Patrol shall undertake a search for fingerprint-based criminal history record information relating to such provider, including transmittal of the fingerprints to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national fingerprint-based criminal history record information check.</para><para>(c) The fingerprint-based criminal history record information check shall include information concerning the provider from federal repositories of such information and repositories of such information in other states, if authorized by federal law.</para><para>(d) The Nebraska State Patrol shall issue a report to the department that includes the fingerprint-based criminal history record information concerning the provider.</para><para>(e) The provider or individual being screened shall pay the actual cost of the fingerprinting and fingerprint-based criminal history record information check.</para><para>(2) The department shall maintain a record of the results of the fingerprint-based criminal history record information check.</para><para>(3) The department may deny or terminate the enrollment of:</para><para>(a) Any provider who is an individual who does not pass the national fingerprint-based criminal history record information check; or</para><para>(b) Any provider in which an individual with at least a five percent direct or indirect ownership interest in the provider does not pass the national fingerprint-based criminal history record information check. Criteria for not passing the fingerprint-based criminal history record information check includes at least the following: (i) Any criminal conviction within the last ten years related to the provider's involvement with the federal Health Insurance for the Aged Act, 42 U.S.C. 1305 et seq., any program or assistance set forth in Chapter 68, or the federal Children's Health Insurance Program established pursuant to 42 U.S.C. 1397aa, as such act, laws, and section existed on January 1, 2016; or (ii) any conviction involving fraudulent activities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB698, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>