<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id172"><sectno id="id173" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 16.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id174" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-949"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id176">68-949</statuteno><catchline id="id177">Medical assistance program; legislative intent; department; duties; reports.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that the department implement reforms to the medical assistance program such as those contained in the Medicaid Reform Plan, including (a) an incremental expansion of home and community-based services for aged persons and persons with disabilities consistent with such plan, (b) an increase in care coordination or disease management initiatives to better manage medical assistance expenditures on behalf of high-cost recipients with multiple or chronic medical conditions, and (c) other reforms as deemed necessary and appropriate by the department, in consultation with the committee and the Medicaid Reform Council.</para><para>(2)(a) The department shall develop recommendations based on a comprehensive analysis of various options available to the state under applicable federal law for the provision of medical assistance to persons with disabilities who are employed, including persons with a medically improved disability, to enhance and replace current eligibility provisions contained in subdivision (8) of section 68-915.</para><para>(b) The department shall provide a draft report of such recommendations to the committee and the Medicaid Reform Council no later than October 1, 2008. The council shall conduct a public meeting no later than October 15, 2008, to discuss and receive public comment regarding such report. The council shall provide any comments and recommendations regarding such report in writing to the department and the committee no later than November 1, 2008. The department shall provide a final report of such recommendations to the Governor, the committee, and the council no later than December 1, 2008.</para><para>(3)(a) The department shall develop recommendations for further modification or replacement of the defined benefit structure of the medical assistance program. Such recommendations shall be consistent with the public policy in section 68-905 and shall consider the needs and resources of low-income Nebraska residents who are eligible or may become eligible for medical assistance, the experience and outcomes of other states that have developed and implemented such changes, and other relevant factors as determined by the department.</para><para>(b) The department shall provide a draft report of such recommendations to the committee and the Medicaid Reform Council no later than October 1, 2008. The council shall conduct a public meeting no later than October 15, 2008, to discuss and receive public comment regarding such report. The council shall provide any comments and recommendations regarding such report in writing to the department and the committee no later than November 1, 2008. The department shall provide a final report of such recommendations to the Governor, the committee, and the council no later than December 1, 2008.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 263; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 16.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 