<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-968"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>68-968</statuteno><catchline>School-based health centers; School
Health Center Advisory Council; members.</catchline><para>(1) To ensure that the interests
of the school district, community, and health care provider are reflected
within the policies, procedures, and scope of services of school-based health
centers, each school district shall establish a School Health Center Advisory
Council for each school in the district hosting a school-based health center.</para>
<para>(2) The
School Health Center Advisory Council shall include:</para><para>(a) At least one
representative of the school administration or school district administration;</para>
<para>(b)
At least one representative of the sponsoring facility; and</para>
<para>(c)
At least one parent recommended by a school administrator or school district
administrator and approved by a majority vote of the school board. Any parent
serving on a School Health Center Advisory Council shall have at least one
child enrolled in the school through which the school-based health center
is organized.</para><para>(3) If another institution or organization sponsors the school-based
health center, at least one representative of each sponsoring institution
or organization shall be included on the School Health Center Advisory Council.</para>
<para>(4)
School Health Center Advisory Councils may also include students enrolled
in the school district through which the school-based health center is organized.
Any such students must be appointed by a school administrator or school district
administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1106, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>