<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id37"> <sectno id="id38">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id39" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="68-961"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-961</statuteno><catchline>Medical Home Advisory Council; created; members; chairperson; expenses; removal; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Medical Home Advisory Council is created. The council shall consist of seven voting members appointed by the Governor as follows:</para> <para>(a) Two licensed primary care physicians actively practicing in the area of general and family medicine;</para><para>(b) Two licensed primary care physicians actively practicing in the area of pediatrics;</para><para>(c) Two licensed primary care physicians actively practicing in the area of internal medicine; and</para><para>(d) One representative from a licensed hospital in Nebraska.</para><para>(2) The chairperson of the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature or another member of the committee designated by the chairperson shall serve as an ex officio, nonvoting member of the council.</para> <para>(3) The council shall annually select one of its appointed members to serve as chairperson of the council for a one-year term. Appointed members of the council shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The division shall provide administrative support to the council.</para><para>(4) The Governor may remove appointed members of the council for good cause upon written notice and an opportunity to be heard. Any appointed member of the council who ceases to meet the requirements for appointment to the council shall cease to be a member of the council. A vacancy on the council shall be filled in the same manner as provided for the original appointment.</para> <para>(5) The Governor shall make initial appointments to the council no later than October 1, 2009. The council shall conduct its initial organizational meeting no later than October 31, 2009.</para><para>(6) The council shall (a) guide and assist the division in the design and implementation of the medical home pilot program and (b) promote the use of best practices to ensure access to medical homes for patients and accomplish the purposes of the Medical Home Pilot Program Act.</para></amendatorysection> </section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB396, &#167; 6.</para><terminationdate>June 30, 2014</terminationdate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>