<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-994"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>68-994</statuteno><catchline>Long-term care services and supports; department; limitation on addition to medicaid managed care program; long-term care clients with special needs; medicaid managed care contracts; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Until July 1, 2023, the department shall not add long-term care services and supports to the medicaid managed care program. For purposes of this section, long-term care services and supports includes services of a skilled nursing facility, a nursing facility, and an assisted-living facility and home and community-based services.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature that services provided to long-term care clients with special needs be administered in a manner that preserves continuity of care, program stability, and specialized oversight.</para><para>(3)(a) The department shall exclude skilled nursing facility and nursing facility services for long-term care clients with special needs from enrollment with medicaid managed care organizations.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this section, (i) long-term care client with special needs means a medicaid recipient whose medical or nursing needs are complex or intensive and exceed the usual level of staff expertise and services ordinarily provided in a nursing facility and (ii) provider means a medicaid-approved provider of long-term care services for long-term care clients with special needs.</para><para>(c) Skilled nursing facility and nursing facility services provided to a long-term care client with special needs shall continue to be administered and reimbursed through fee-for-service medicaid or another delivery system authorized under state or federal law and not through medicaid managed care organizations.</para><para>(d) The department shall not require a provider to enroll with a managed care organization as a condition of eligibility to serve a long-term care client with special needs.</para><para>(e) Nothing in this subsection shall prohibit the department from requiring a managed care organization to coordinate benefits other than skilled nursing facility or nursing facility services or provide wraparound services for a long-term care client with special needs if financial risk and utilization management for a provider is not administered by the managed care organizations.</para><para>(f) The department shall amend medicaid managed care contracts as necessary, including, but not limited to, revisions to enrollment processes, no later than six months after July 18, 2026.</para><para>(g) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to implement this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB468, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB101, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB1091, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>