<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id40"> <sectno id="id41">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id42" statutenumber="68-966"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id44">68-966</statuteno><catchline id="id45">Department; apply for medical assistance program waiver or amendment; legislative intent.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall apply for a waiver or an amendment to an existing waiver under the medical assistance program established in section 68-903 for the purpose of providing medical assistance for intensive early intervention services based on behavioral principles for children with a medical diagnosis of an autism spectrum disorder or an educational verification of autism. Such waiver shall not be construed to create an entitlement to services provided under such waiver.</para> <para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature that such waiver (a) require means testing for and cost-sharing by recipient families, (b) limit eligibility only to children for whom such services have been initiated prior to the age of nine years, (c) limit the number of children served according to available funding, (d) require demonstrated progress toward the attainment of treatment goals as a condition for continued receipt of medical assistance benefits for such treatment, (e) be developed in consultation with the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services and with the input of parents and families of children with autism spectrum disorders and organizations advocating on behalf of such persons, and (f) be submitted to the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services as soon as practicable, but no later than September 1, 2009.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB482, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 85-1,142; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB27, &#167; 6.</para><effectivedate>May 27, 2009</effectivedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>