<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Public Assistance"  statutenumber="68-720"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-720</statuteno><catchline>Aid to dependent children; child care subsidy program; administrative disqualification; intentional program violation; disqualification period.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall establish an administrative disqualification process for the aid to dependent children program described in section 43-512 and the child care subsidy program established pursuant to section 68-1202. The department may initiate an administrative disqualification proceeding when it has reason to believe, on the basis of sufficient documentary evidence, that an individual has committed an intentional program violation. Proceedings under this section shall be subject to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(2) If an individual is found to have committed an intentional program violation, a period of disqualification shall be imposed.  The period may be determined by the Department of Health and Human Services after an administrative disqualification hearing or without a hearing if the individual waives his or her right to such hearing.  The period of disqualification shall be: (a) For a first violation, up to one year; (b) for a second violation, up to two years; and (c) for a third violation, permanent disqualification.  The penalties described in this subsection shall also be imposed if the individual is found by a court to have violated section 68-1017.</para><para>(3) For the aid to dependent children program, only the individual found to have committed the intentional program violation shall be disqualified under this section.  For the child care subsidy program, the individual found to have committed the intentional violation shall disqualify such individual and his or her family under this section. The department shall inform each applicant in writing of the penalties described in this section for intentional program violations each time an application for benefits is made to either program.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, intentional program violation means any action by an individual to intentionally (a) make a false statement, either verbally or in writing, to obtain benefits to which the individual is not entitled, (b) conceal information to obtain benefits to which the individual is not entitled, or (c) alter one or more documents to obtain benefits to which the individual is not entitled.</para><para>(5) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 30. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>