<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-909"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>68-909</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Existing contracts,
agreements, rules, regulations, plan, and waivers; how treated; report required; exception; Medicaid Reform
Council; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) All
contracts, agreements, rules, and regulations relating to the medical assistance
program as entered into or adopted and promulgated by the department prior
to July 1, 2006, and all provisions of the medicaid state plan and waivers
adopted by the department prior to July 1, 2006, shall remain in effect until
revised, amended, repealed, or nullified pursuant to law.</para>
<para>(2) Prior to the adoption and promulgation of proposed rules
and regulations under section 68-912 or relating to the implementation of
medicaid state plan amendments or waivers, the department shall provide a
report to the Governor, the Legislature, and the Medicaid Reform Council no
later than December 1 before the next regular session of the Legislature summarizing
the purpose and content of such proposed rules and regulations and the projected
impact of such proposed rules and regulations on recipients of medical assistance
and medical assistance expenditures. Any
changes in medicaid copayments in fiscal year 2011-12 are exempt from the
reporting requirement of this subsection and the requirements of section 68-912.</para>
<para>(3) The Medicaid Reform Council, no later than thirty days
after the date of receipt of any report under subsection (2) of this section,
may conduct a public meeting to receive public comment regarding such report.
The council shall promptly provide any comments and recommendations regarding
such report in writing to the department. Such comments and recommendations
shall be advisory only and shall not be binding on the department, but the
department shall promptly provide a written response to such comments or recommendations
to the council.</para>
<para>(4) The department shall monitor and shall periodically, as
necessary, but no less than biennially, report to the Governor, the Legislature,
and the Medicaid Reform Council on the implementation of rules and regulations,
medicaid state plan amendments, and waivers adopted under the Medical Assistance
Act and the effect of such rules and regulations, amendments, or waivers on
eligible recipients of medical assistance and medical assistance expenditures.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB928, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB468, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
