<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id276"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-1530"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1530</statuteno><catchline>Family support program; Department of Health and Human Services; Advisory Committee on Developmental Disabilities; duties; funding; legislative intent; family support program; services and support; rules and regulations; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall apply for a three-year medicaid waiver under section 1915(c) of the federal Social Security Act to administer a family support program which is a home and community-based services program as provided in this section.</para><para>(2)(a) The Advisory Committee on Developmental Disabilities created in section 83-1212.01 shall assist in the development and guide the implementation of the family support program. The family support program shall be administered by the Division of Developmental Disabilities of the Department of Health and Human Services.</para><para>(b) It is the intent of the Legislature that any funds distributed to Nebraska pursuant to section 9817 of the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021, Public Law 117-2, be used to eliminate unmet needs relating to home and community-based services for persons with developmental disabilities as much as is possible.</para><para>(c) If funds are distributed to Nebraska pursuant to section 9817 of the federal American Rescue Plan Act of 2021, it is the intent of the Legislature that such funds distributed to Nebraska should at least partially fund the family support program if doing so is in accordance with federal law, rules, regulations, or guidance.</para><para>(3) The family support program shall:</para><para>(a) Offer an annual capped budget for long-term services and supports of ten thousand dollars for each eligible applicant;</para><para>(b) Offer a pathway for medicaid eligibility for disabled children by disregarding parental income and establishing eligibility based on a child's income and assets;</para><para>(c) Allow a family to self-direct services, including contracting for services and supports approved by the division; and</para><para>(d) Not exceed eight hundred fifty participants.</para><para>(4) The department, in consultation with the advisory committee, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the implementation of the family support program to be set at an intermediate care facility institutional level of care to support children with intellectual and developmental disabilities and their families. Such rules and regulations shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) Criteria for and types of long-term services and supports to be provided by the family support program;</para><para>(b) The method, as provided in section 68-1532, for allocating resources to family units participating in the family support program;</para><para>(c) Eligibility determination, including, but not limited to, a child's maximum income and assets;</para><para>(d) The enrollment process;</para><para>(e) Limits on benefits; and</para><para>(f) Processes to establish quality assurance, including, but not limited to, measures of family satisfaction.</para><para>(5) The division shall administer the family support program within the limits of the appropriations by the Legislature for such program.</para><para>(6) The division shall submit an annual report electronically to the Legislature on the family support program. The report shall include:</para><para>(a) The distribution of available funds, the total number of children and families served, and the status of the waiting list for the comprehensive waiver and other applicable waivers;</para><para>(b) A summary of any grievances filed by family units pertaining to the family support program, including any appeals and a description of how such grievances were resolved;</para><para>(c) The number and demographics of children with disabilities and their families who applied under the family support program but who were not found eligible and the reason such children and their families were not found eligible;</para><para>(d) Quality assurance activities and the results of annual measures of family satisfaction; and</para><para>(e) Recommendations to innovate the family support program, improve current programming, and maximize limited funding, including, but not limited to, the potential utilization of other medicaid pathways or medicaid waivers that could help increase access to medicaid and long-term services and supports for children with disabilities or special health care needs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB376, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>