<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-1206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1206</statuteno><catchline>Social services; administration; contracts; payments.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall administer the program of social services in this state. The department may contract with other social agencies for the purchase of social services at rates not to exceed those prevailing in the state or the cost at which the department could provide those services. The statutory maximum payments for the separate program of aid to dependent children shall apply only to public assistance grants and shall not apply to payments for social services.</para><para>(2) In determining the rate or rates to be paid by the department for child care as defined in section 43-2605, the department shall adopt a fixed-rate schedule for the state or a fixed-rate schedule for an area of the state applicable to each child care program category of provider as defined in section 71-1910 which may claim reimbursement for services provided by the federal Child Care Subsidy program, except that the department shall not pay a rate higher than that charged by an individual provider to that provider's private clients. The schedule may provide separate rates for care for infants, for children with special needs, including disabilities or technological dependence, or for other individual categories of children. The schedule shall be effective on October 1 of every year and shall be revised annually by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 511, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 522, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 836, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 401, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 347; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 279.</para></source></law></legaldoc>