<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-1101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1101</statuteno><catchline>Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care Advisory Committee on Aging; created; members; appointment; term; vacancy.</catchline><para>The Division of Medicaid and Long-Term Care Advisory Committee on Aging is created. The committee shall consist of twelve members, one from each of the planning-and-service areas as designated in the Nebraska Community Aging Services Act and the remaining members from the state at large.</para><para>Any member serving on the Department of Health and Human Services Advisory Committee on Aging on July 1, 2007, shall continue to serve until his or her term expires. As the terms of the members expire, the Governor shall, on or before March 1 of such year, appoint or reappoint a member of the committee for a term of four years. Each area agency on aging serving a designated planning-and-service area shall recommend to the Governor the names of persons qualified to represent the senior population of the planning-and-service area. Any vacancy on the committee shall be filled for the unexpired term. A vacancy shall exist when a member of the committee ceases to be a resident of the planning-and-service area from which he or she was appointed or reappointed. The members to be appointed to represent a planning-and-service area shall be residents of the planning-and-service area from which they are appointed. Members of the advisory committee shall not be elected public officials or staff of the Department of Health and Human Services or of an area agency on aging.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 409, &#167; 1, p. 1311; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 97, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 404, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 456, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 341; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 273.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Community Aging Services Act,</emphasis> see section 81-2201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>