<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id698"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="68-1110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1110</statuteno><catchline>Aging Nebraskans Task Force; state plan regarding Alzheimer's and related disorders; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Aging Nebraskans Task Force shall develop a state plan regarding individuals with Alzheimer's and related disorders. The task force shall work with the chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services, the Public Guardian, the area agencies on aging, organizations advocating for patients and caregivers for patients with Alzheimer's or related disorders, the law enforcement community, patients with Alzheimer's or related disorders, caregivers for patients with Alzheimer's or related disorders, client advocacy organizations, health care provider advocacy organizations, private health care providers, and community-based health professionals.</para><para>(2) The task force shall:</para><para>(a) Assess the current and future impact of Alzheimer's and related disorders on residents of the state;</para><para>(b) Determine the existing services and resources in the state that address the needs of individuals with Alzheimer's and related disorders and their families and caregivers; and</para><para>(c) Develop recommendations to respond to escalating needs for the services and resources described in subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para><para>(3) In fulfilling the duties described in subsection (1) of this section, the task force shall examine:</para><para>(a) Trends and needs in the state relating to populations with Alzheimer's or related disorders, including (i) the state's role in the provision of long-term care, (ii) family caregiver support, (iii) the provision of early-stage diagnoses, assistance, support, and medical services, (iv) younger onset of Alzheimer's or related disorders, (v) ethnic populations at higher risk, and (vi) risk reduction;</para><para>(b) Existing services, resources, and capacity available to individuals with Alzheimer's or related disorders, including:</para><para>(i) The type, cost, availability, and adequacy of services, including, (A) home and community-based resources, (B) respite care, (C) residential long-term care, and (D) geriatric-psychiatric units for individuals with associated behavioral disorders;</para><para>(ii) Dementia-specific training requirements for individuals who are employed to provide care to individuals with Alzheimer's or related disorders;</para><para>(iii) Quality of care measures for services delivered across the continuum of care;</para><para>(iv) The capacity of public safety and law enforcement to respond to individuals with Alzheimer's or related disorders; and</para><para>(v) State support to institutions of higher learning for research on Alzheimer's or related disorders;</para><para>(c) The need for state policy or action in order to provide clear, coordinated services and support to individuals with Alzheimer's or related disorders and their families and caregivers; and</para><para>(d) Strategies to identify gaps in services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB320, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>May 28, 2015</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>