<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id117" statutenumber="68-1017.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1017.02</statuteno><catchline id="id120">Supplemental Nutrition
Assistance Program; department; duties; state outreach plan; report; contents;
person ineligible; when.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Department of Health
and Human Services shall apply for and utilize to the maximum extent possible,
within limits established by the Legislature, any and all appropriate options
available to the state under the federal Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program and regulations adopted under such program to maximize the number
of Nebraska residents being served under such program within such limits.
The department shall seek to maximize federal funding for such program and
minimize the utilization of General Funds for such program and shall employ
the personnel necessary to determine the options available to the state and
issue the report to the Legislature required by subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para>
<para>(b) The department shall submit
electronically an annual report to
the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature by December 1 on
efforts by the department to carry out the provisions of this subsection.
Such report shall provide the committee with all necessary and appropriate
information to enable the committee to conduct a meaningful evaluation of
such efforts. Such information shall include, but not be limited to, a clear
description of various options available to the state under the federal Supplemental
Nutrition Assistance Program, the department's evaluation of and any action
taken by the department with respect to such options, the number of persons
being served under such program, and any and all costs and expenditures associated
with such program.</para>
<para>(c) The Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature, after
receipt and evaluation of the report required in subdivision (b) of this subsection,
shall issue recommendations to the department on any further action necessary
by the department to meet the requirements of this section.</para>
<para> (2)(a) The department shall develop a state outreach plan to promote
access by eligible persons to benefits of the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program. The plan shall meet the criteria established by the Food and Nutrition
Service of the United States Department of Agriculture for approval of state
outreach plans. The Department of Health and Human Services may apply for
and accept gifts, grants, and donations to develop and implement the state
outreach plan.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of developing and implementing the state outreach plan,
the department shall partner with one or more counties or nonprofit organizations.
If the department enters into a contract with a nonprofit organization relating
to the state outreach plan, the contract may specify that the nonprofit organization
is responsible for seeking sufficient gifts, grants, or donations necessary
for the development and implementation of the state outreach plan and may
additionally specify that any costs to the department associated with the
award and management of the contract or the implementation or administration
of the state outreach plan shall be paid out of private or federal funds received
for development and implementation of the state outreach plan.</para>
<para>(c) The department shall submit the state outreach plan to the Food
and Nutrition Service of the United States Department of Agriculture for approval
on or before August 1, 2011, and shall request any federal matching funds
that may be available upon approval of the state outreach plan. It is the
intent of the Legislature that the State of Nebraska and the Department of
Health and Human Services use any additional public or private funds to offset
costs associated with increased caseload resulting from the implementation
of the state outreach plan.</para>
<para>(d) The department shall be exempt from implementing or administering
a state outreach plan under this subsection, but not from developing such
a plan, if it does not receive private or federal funds sufficient to cover
the department's costs associated with the implementation and administration
of the plan, including any costs associated with increased caseload resulting
from the implementation of the plan.</para>
<para>(3)(a)(i) On or before October 1, 2011, the department shall create
a TANF-funded program or policy that, in compliance with federal law, establishes
categorical eligibility for federal food assistance benefits pursuant to the
Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program to maximize the number of Nebraska
residents being served under such program in a manner that does not increase
the current gross income eligibility limit.</para>
<para>(ii) Such TANF-funded program or policy shall eliminate all asset limits
for eligibility for federal food assistance benefits, except that the total
of liquid assets which includes cash on hand and funds in personal checking
and savings accounts, money market accounts, and share accounts shall not
exceed twenty-five thousand dollars pursuant to the Supplemental Nutrition
Assistance Program, as allowed under federal law and under 7 C.F.R. 273.2(j)(2).</para>
<para>(iii) This subsection becomes effective only if the department receives
funds pursuant to federal participation that may be used to implement this
subsection.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of this subsection:</para>
<para>(i) Federal law means the federal Food and Nutrition Act of 2008, 7
U.S.C. 2011 et seq., and regulations adopted under the act; and</para>
<para>(ii) TANF means the federal Temporary Assistance for Needy Families
program established in 42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Within the limits specified in this subsection, the State of
Nebraska opts out of the provision of the federal Personal Responsibility
and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996, as such act existed on January
1, 2009, that eliminates eligibility for the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program for any person convicted of a felony involving the possession, use,
or distribution of a controlled substance.</para>
<para>(b) A person shall be ineligible for Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program benefits under this subsection if he or she (i) has had three or more
felony convictions for the possession or use of a controlled substance or
(ii) has been convicted of a felony involving the sale or distribution of
a controlled substance or the intent to sell or distribute a controlled substance.
A person with one or two felony convictions for the possession or use of a
controlled substance shall only be eligible to receive Supplemental Nutrition
Assistance Program benefits under this subsection if he or she is participating
in or has completed a state-licensed or nationally accredited substance abuse
treatment program since the date of conviction. The determination of such
participation or completion shall be made by the treatment provider administering
the program.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 667, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 301, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB171, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB543, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 95.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>