
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id18" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-1735.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1735.01</statuteno><catchline>Creating self-sufficiency contract
and meeting work activity requirement; applicant; activities authorized.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of this section, target work rate means fifty percent less the
caseload reduction credit submitted by the Nebraska Department of Health and
Human Services to the United States Department of Health and Human Services
for the fiscal year.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of creating the self-sufficiency contract and meeting
the applicant's work activity requirement, an applicant shall be deemed
to have met the work activity requirement in a month if he or she is engaged
in education directly related to employment for an average of at least twenty
hours per week during such month. Education directly related to employment
includes, but is not limited to, Adult Basic Education, English as a Second
Language, and a general education development program.</para>
<para>(3) No state funds shall be used to carry out this section unless such
state funds meet the definition of qualified state expenditures under the
federal Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program, 42 U.S.C. 609(a)(7)(B)(i).</para>
<para>(4) If Nebraska's work participation rate under the federal Temporary
Assistance for Needy Families program, 42 U.S.C. 601 et seq., does not exceed
the target work rate by ten percentage points in any month, the Department
of Health and Human Services may suspend the requirements of subsection (2)
of this section until the work participation rate exceeds the target work
rate by ten percentage points for three consecutive months.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB507, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB240, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>