<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="68-1116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1116</statuteno><catchline>Aging and disability resource centers; services.</catchline><para>(1) The aging and disability resource centers shall be a means of promoting appropriate, effective, and efficient use of long-term care resources.</para><para>(2) Each aging and disability resource center shall provide one or more of the following services:</para><para>(a) Comprehensive information on the full range of available public and private long-term care programs, options, financing, service providers, and resources within a community, including information on the availability of integrated long-term care;</para><para>(b) Options counseling;</para><para>(c) Assistance in accessing and applying for public benefits programs;</para><para>(d) A convenient point of entry to the range of publicly supported long-term care programs for an eligible individual;</para><para>(e) A process for identifying unmet service needs in communities and developing recommendations to respond to those unmet needs;</para><para>(f) Facilitation of person-centered transition support to assure that an eligible individual is able to find the services and support that are most appropriate to his or her need;</para><para>(g) Mobility management to promote the appropriate use of public transportation services by a person who does not own or is unable to operate an automobile; and</para><para>(h) A home care provider registry that will provide a person who needs home care with the names of home care providers and information about his or her rights and responsibilities as a home care consumer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB320, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB793, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>April 24, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>