<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id13" statutenumber="68-1804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1804</statuteno><catchline id="id16">ICF/DD Reimbursement
Protection Fund; created; use; allocation;
investment; report.</catchline><para>(1) The ICF/DD Reimbursement Protection
Fund is created. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested
by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion
Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Interest and income earned
by the fund shall be credited to the fund.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning
July 1, 2014, the department shall use the ICF/DD Reimbursement Protection
Fund, including the matching federal financial participation under Title XIX
of the Social Security Act, as amended, for purposes of enhancing rates paid
under the medical assistance program to intermediate care facilities for persons
with developmental disabilities and for an annual contribution to community-based
programs for persons with developmental disabilities as specified in subsection
(4) of this section, exclusive of the reimbursement paid under the medical
assistance program and any other state appropriations to intermediate care
facilities for persons with developmental disabilities.</para>
<para>(3) For FY2011-12 through FY2013-14, proceeds
from the tax imposed pursuant to section 68-1803 shall be remitted to the
State Treasurer for credit to the ICF/DD Reimbursement Protection
Fund for allocation as follows:</para>
<para>(a) First, fifty-five thousand dollars for administration
of the fund;</para>
<para>(b) Second, the amount needed to reimburse intermediate care
facilities for persons
with developmental disabilities for the cost of the tax;</para>
<para>(c) Third, three hundred twelve thousand dollars for community-based
services for persons with developmental disabilities;</para>
<para>(d) Fourth, six hundred thousand dollars or such lesser amount
as may be available in the fund for non-state-operated intermediate care facilities
for persons with developmental disabilities, in
addition to any continuation appropriations percentage increase provided by
the Legislature to nongovernmental intermediate care facilities for persons with developmental disabilities under
the medical assistance program, subject to approval by the federal Centers
for Medicare and Medicaid Services of the department's annual application
amending the medicaid state plan reimbursement methodology for intermediate
care facilities for persons
with developmental disabilities; and</para>
<para>(e) Fifth, the remainder of the proceeds to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(4) For FY2014-15
and each fiscal year thereafter, the ICF/DD Reimbursement Protection Fund
shall be used as follows:</para><para>(a) First, fifty-five thousand dollars to the department for administration
of the fund;</para><para>(b) Second, payment to the intermediate care facilities for persons
with developmental disabilities for the cost of the tax;</para>
<para>(c) Third,
three hundred twelve thousand dollars, in addition to any federal medicaid
matching funds, for payment to providers of community-based services for persons
with developmental disabilities;</para><para>(d) Fourth, one million dollars to the General Fund;
and</para><para>(e) Fifth, rebase rates under the medical assistance program in
accordance with the medicaid state plan as defined in section 68-907. In calculating
rates, the proceeds of the tax provided for in section 68-1803 and not utilized
under subdivisions (a), (b), (c), and (d) of this subsection shall be used
to enhance rates in non-state-operated intermediate care facilities for persons
with developmental disabilities by increasing the annual inflation factor
to the extent allowed by such proceeds and any funds appropriated by the Legislature.</para>
<para>(5) The Division of Medicaid
and Long-Term Care of the Department of Health and Human Services shall report
electronically, no later than December 1 of each year, to the Health and Human
Services Committee of the Legislature and the Revenue Committee of the Legislature
the amounts collected from each payer of the tax pursuant to section 68-1803
and the amount of each disbursement from the ICF/DD Reimbursement Protection
Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 841, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB701, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 19.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>