<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id205">
<sectno id="id206" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 16.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" id="id207" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-1070"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id209">68-1070</statuteno><catchline id="id210">Non-United-States
citizens; assistance; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) If the
following non-United-States citizens meet the income and other requirements
for participation in the medical assistance program established pursuant to
the Medical Assistance Act, in the program for financial assistance pursuant
to section 43-512, in the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program administered
by the State of Nebraska pursuant to the federal Food and Nutrition Act of
2008, 7 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.,
as such sections existed on January 1, 2010, or in the program for
assistance to the aged, blind, and disabled, such persons shall be eligible
for such program or benefits:</para>
<para>(a) Non-United-States citizens lawfully admitted, regardless
of the date entry was granted, into the United States for permanent residence;</para>
<para>(b) Non-United-States
citizens described in 8 U.S.C. 1613(b)(1)(A) through (C), as such section
existed on January 1, 2010, regardless of the date of entry into
the United States; and</para>
<para>(c) Individuals for whom coverage is mandated under federal
law.</para>
<para>(2) Individuals eligible for the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program under this section shall receive any Supplemental Nutrition Assistance
Program benefits
or a state voucher which can be used only for food products authorized under
the federal Food and Nutrition Act of 2008,
7 U.S.C. 2011 et seq., as such sections existed on January 1, 2010, in the amount of the Supplemental Nutrition
Assistance Program benefit for which this individual was otherwise eligible
but for the citizenship provisions of 7 U.S.C. 2015, as such section existed on January 1, 2010.</para>
<para>(3) The income and resources of any individual who assists
a non-United-States citizen to enter the United States by signing an affidavit
of support shall be deemed available in determining the non-United-States
citizen's eligibility for assistance until the non-United-States citizen becomes
a United States citizen.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 864, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 16.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Medical Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 68-901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>