
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id350">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id352" statutenumber="68-1207"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1207</statuteno><catchline id="id355">Department
of Health and Human Services; public child welfare services; supervise; department;
pilot project; caseload requirements; case plan developed.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall supervise
all public child welfare services as described by law. The department and
the pilot project described in section 68-1212 shall maintain caseloads to
carry out child welfare services which provide for adequate, timely, and indepth
investigations and services to children and families. Caseloads shall range
between twelve and seventeen cases as determined pursuant to subsection (2)
of this section. In establishing the specific caseloads within such range,
the department and the pilot project shall (a) include the workload factors
that may differ due to geographic responsibilities, office location, and the
travel required to provide a timely response in the investigation of abuse
and neglect, the protection of children, and the provision of services to
children and families in a uniform and consistent statewide manner and (b)
utilize the workload criteria of the standards established as of January 1,
2012, by the Child Welfare League of America. The average caseload shall be
reduced by the department in all service areas as designated pursuant to section
81-3116 and by the pilot project to comply with the caseload range described
in this subsection by September 1, 2012. Beginning September 15, 2012, the
department shall include in its annual report required pursuant to section
68-1207.01 a report on the attainment of the decrease according to such caseload
standards. The department's annual report shall also include changes in the
standards of the Child Welfare League of America or its successor.</para>
<para>(2) Caseload size shall be determined in the following manner:
(a) If children are placed in the home, the family shall count as one case
regardless of how many children are placed in the home; (b) if a child is
placed out of the home, the child shall count as one case; (c) if, within
one family, one or more children are placed in the home and one or more children
are placed out of the home, the children placed in the home shall count as
one case and each child placed out of the home shall count as one case; and
(d) any child receiving services from the department or a private entity under
contract with the department shall be counted as provided in subdivisions
(a) through (c) of this subsection whether or not such child is a ward of
the state. For purposes of this subsection, a child is considered to be placed
in the home if the child is placed with his or her biological or adoptive
parent or a legal guardian and a child is considered to be placed out of the
home if the child is placed in a foster family home as defined in section 71-1901,
a residential child-caring agency as defined in section 71-1926, or
any other setting which is not the child's planned permanent home.</para>
<para>(3) To insure appropriate oversight of noncourt and voluntary
cases when any child welfare services are provided, either by the department
or by a lead agency participating in the pilot project, as a result of a child
safety assessment, the department or lead agency shall develop a case plan
that specifies the services to be provided and the actions to be taken by
the department or lead agency and the family in each such case. Such case plan shall clearly indicate,
when appropriate, that children are receiving services to prevent out-of-home
placement and that, absent preventive services, foster care is the planned
arrangement for the child.</para>
<para>(4) To carry out the provisions of this section, the Legislature
shall provide funds for additional staff.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 511, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 1, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 720, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 348; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 264, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 280; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB961, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB265, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB269, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>