<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-1804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1804</statuteno><catchline>ICF/MR Reimbursement Protection Fund;
created; allocation; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The ICF/MR Reimbursement
Protection Fund is created. Any money in the fund available for investment
shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska
Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Interest
and income earned by the fund shall be credited to the fund.</para>
<para>(2) For fiscal year 2004-05, proceeds from the tax imposed under section
68-1803 shall be allocated as follows:</para>
<para>(a) First, fifty-five thousand dollars to the department for administration
of the fund;</para>
<para>(b) Second, payment to intermediate care facilities for the mentally
retarded for the cost of the tax;</para>
<para>(c) Third, three hundred thousand dollars, in addition to any federal
medicaid matching funds, for increases in payments to non-state-operated intermediate
care facilities for the mentally retarded which shall be such facilities'
only increase in payments for such fiscal year;</para>
<para>(d) Fourth, three hundred twelve thousand dollars, in addition to any
federal medicaid matching funds, for payment to providers of community-based
services for the purpose of reducing the waiting list of persons with developmental
disabilities; and</para>
<para>(e) Fifth, any money remaining in the fund after the allocations required
by subdivisions (2)(a) through (d) of this section have been made shall be
transferred to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(3) For FY2005-06 through
FY2010-11, proceeds from the tax imposed pursuant to section 68-1803
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit as follows:</para>
<para>(a) To the ICF/MR Reimbursement Protection Fund for allocation as described
in this subdivision: (i) Fifty-five thousand dollars for administration of
the fund; (ii) the amount needed to reimburse intermediate care facilities
for the mentally retarded for the cost of the tax; (iii) three hundred thousand
dollars for payment of rates to non-state-operated intermediate care facilities;
and (iv) three hundred twelve thousand dollars for community-based services
for persons with developmental disabilities; and</para>
<para>(b) To the General Fund: The remainder of the proceeds.</para>
<para>(4) For FY2011-12 and
each fiscal year thereafter, proceeds from the tax imposed pursuant to section
68-1803 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the ICF/MR
Reimbursement Protection Fund for allocation as follows:</para>
<para>(a) First, fifty-five
thousand dollars for administration of the fund;</para><para>(b) Second, the amount needed to
reimburse intermediate care facilities for the mentally retarded for the cost
of the tax;</para><para>(c)
Third, three hundred twelve thousand dollars for community-based services
for persons with developmental disabilities;</para><para>(d) Fourth, six hundred thousand
dollars or such lesser amount as may be available in the fund for non-state-operated
intermediate care facilities for the mentally retarded, in addition to any
continuation appropriations percentage increase provided by the Legislature
to nongovernmental intermediate care facilities for the mentally retarded
under the medical assistance program, subject to approval by the federal Centers
for Medicare and Medicaid Services of the department's annual application
amending the medicaid state plan reimbursement methodology for intermediate
care facilities for the mentally retarded; and</para><para>(e) Fifth, the remainder of the
proceeds to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 841, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB701, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>