<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Paupers and Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-1723"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1723</statuteno><catchline>Cash assistance; requirements; extension of time limit; when; hearing; review.</catchline><para>(1) Cash assistance shall be provided only while recipients are actively engaged in the specific activities outlined in the self-sufficiency contract developed under section 68-1719. If the recipients are not actively engaged in these activities, no cash assistance shall be paid.</para><para>(2) Recipient families with at least one adult with the capacity to work, as determined by the comprehensive assets assessment, shall participate in the self-sufficiency contract as a condition of receiving cash assistance. If any such adult fails to cooperate in carrying out the terms of the contract, the family shall be ineligible for cash assistance.</para><para>(a) Adult members of recipient families whose youngest child is between the ages of twelve weeks and six months shall engage in an individually determined number of part-time hours in activities such as family nurturing, preemployment skills, or education.</para><para>(b) Participation in activities outlined in the self-sufficiency contract shall not be required for one parent of a recipient family whose youngest child is under the age of twelve weeks.</para><para>(c) Cash assistance under section 68-1724 shall be extended: (i) To cover the twelve-week postpartum recovery period for children born to recipient families; and (ii) to recognize special medical conditions of such children requiring the presence of at least one adult member of the recipient family, as determined by the state, which extend past the age of twelve weeks.</para><para>(d) Full participation in the activities outlined in the self-sufficiency contract shall be required for adult members of a two-parent recipient family whose youngest child is over the age of six months. Part-time participation in activities outlined in the self-sufficiency contract shall be required for an adult member of a single-parent recipient family whose youngest child is under the age of six years.</para><para>(e) In cases in which the only adults in the recipient family do not have parental responsibility which shall mean such adults are not the biological or adoptive parents or stepparents of the children in their care, and assistance is requested for all family members, including the adults, the family shall participate in the activities outlined in the self-sufficiency contract as a condition of receiving cash assistance.</para><para>(f) Unemployed or underemployed absent and able-to-work parents of children in the recipient family may participate in self-sufficiency contracts, employment, and payment of child support, and such absent parents may be required to pay all or a part of the costs of the self-sufficiency contracts.</para><para>(3) Individual recipients and recipient families shall have the right to request an administrative hearing (a) for the purpose of reviewing compliance by the state with the terms of the self-sufficiency contract or (b) for the purpose of reviewing a determination by the department that the recipient or recipient family has not complied with the terms of the self-sufficiency contract. It is the intent of the Legislature that an independent mediation appeal process be developed as an option to be considered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1224, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB351, &#167; 10.</para></source>
<annotation><para>This section does not authorize the removal of Medicaid benefits as a sanction for noncompliance with an Employment First contract. Davio v. Nebraska Dept. of Health &amp; Human Servs., 280 Neb. 263, 786 N.W.2d 655 (2010).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc>