<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="68-1212"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1212</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Department of Health
and Human Services; cases; case manager; employee of department; duties; case
management lead agency model pilot project; contract authorized; conditions,
performance outcomes, and oversight; extension of contract.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, by April 1, 2012, for
all cases in which a court has awarded a juvenile to the care of the Department
of Health and Human Services according to subsection (1) of section 43-285
and for any noncourt and voluntary cases, the case manager shall be an employee
of the department. Such case manager shall be responsible for and shall directly
oversee: Case planning; service authorization; investigation of compliance;
monitoring and evaluation of the care and services provided to children and
families; and decisionmaking regarding the determination of visitation and
the care, placement, medical services, psychiatric services, training, and
expenditures on behalf of each juvenile under subsection (1) of section 43-285.
Such case manager shall be responsible for decisionmaking and direct preparation
regarding the proposed plan for the care, placement, services, and permanency
of the juvenile filed with the court required under subsection (2) of section
43-285. The health and safety of the juvenile shall be the paramount concern
in the proposed plan in accordance with such subsection.</para>
<para>(2) The department may contract with a lead agency for a case
management lead agency model pilot project in the department's eastern service
area as designated pursuant to section 81-3116. The department shall include
in the pilot project the appropriate conditions, performance outcomes, and
oversight for the lead agency, including, but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(a) The reporting and survey requirements of lead agencies
described in sections 43-4406 and 43-4407;</para>
<para>(b) Departmental monitoring and functional capacities of lead
agencies described in section 43-4408;</para>
<para>(c) The key areas of evaluation specified in subsection (3)
of section 43-4409;</para>
<para>(d) Compliance and coordination with the development of the
statewide strategic plan for child welfare program and service reform pursuant
to Laws 2012, LB821; and</para>
<para>(e) Assurance of financial accountability and reporting by
the lead agency.</para>
<para>(3) Before June 30, 2014, the department may
extend the contract for the pilot project described in subsection (2) of this
section. The lead agency shall also comply
with the requirements of section 43-4204.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB961, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB660, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
