<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id814"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="68-1116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1116</statuteno><catchline>Aging and disability resource center demonstration project; services.</catchline><para>The aging and disability resource center demonstration projects shall be established to evaluate the feasibility of establishing aging and disability resource centers statewide as a means of promoting appropriate, effective, and efficient use of long-term care resources. The aging and disability resource center demonstration projects shall operate through June 30, 2018. Each aging and disability resource center demonstration project shall provide one or more of the following services:</para><para>(1) Comprehensive information on the full range of available public and private long-term care programs, options, financing, service providers, and resources within a community, including information on the availability of integrated long-term care;</para><para>(2) Assistance in accessing and applying for public benefits programs;</para><para>(3) Options counseling;</para><para>(4) A convenient point of entry to the range of publicly supported long-term care programs for an eligible individual;</para><para>(5) A process for identifying unmet service needs in communities and developing recommendations to respond to those unmet needs;</para><para>(6) Facilitation of person-centered transition support to assure that an eligible individual is able to find the services and support that are most appropriate to his or her need;</para><para>(7) Mobility management to promote the appropriate use of public transportation services by a person who does not own or is unable to operate an automobile; and</para><para>(8) A home care provider registry that will provide a person who needs home care with the names of home care providers and information about his or her rights and responsibilities as a home care consumer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB320, &#167; 6. </para><operativedate>August 30, 2015</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>