<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-1117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>68-1117</statuteno><catchline>Area agency on aging or partnering organization; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) An area agency on aging or partnering organization receiving funding pursuant to section 68-1115, may work in partnership with one or more partnering organizations that specialize in serving persons with congenital and acquired disabilities to provide services as described in subsection (2) of section 68-1116, including, but not limited to, centers for independent living and the University Center for Excellence in Developmental Disability Education, Research and Service, for the purpose of developing an aging and disability resource center plan. After consultation with a collaboration of organizations providing advocacy, protection, and safety for aging persons and persons with congenital and acquired disabilities, the partnership may submit to the department an aging and disability resource center plan. The plan shall specify how organizations currently serving eligible individuals will be engaged in the process of delivery of services through the aging and disability resource center. The plan shall indicate how resources will be utilized by the collaborating organizations to fulfill the responsibilities of an aging and disability resource center.</para><para>(2) Two or more area agencies on aging or partnering organizations may develop a joint aging and disability resource center plan to serve all or a portion of their planning-and-service areas. A joint plan shall provide information on how the services described in section 68-1116 will be provided in the counties to be served by the aging and disability resource center.</para><para>(3) A partnering organization may: (a) Contract with an area agency on aging for the purpose of providing services pursuant to this section; or (b) contract with the department for the purpose of providing services pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB320, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB793, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB856, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>