<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id305"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Assistance" statutenumber="68-2103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>68-2103</statuteno><catchline>Hospital inpatient and outpatient services; assessments and directed-payment programs; establish; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall amend the medicaid state plan or file other federal authorizing documents to establish assessments and directed-payment programs for hospital inpatient and outpatient services.</para><para>(2) Upon approval by the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services of a hospital assessment and a directed-payment program, the department shall impose an assessment on hospitals to assure quality and access in the medical assistance program.</para><para>(3) The department may establish different assessment rates based on categories of hospital or hospital services as allowed by federal law.</para><para>(4) The department shall consult with a statewide association representing a majority of hospitals and health systems in Nebraska regarding the development, implementation, and annual renewal of the assessments and the directed-payment programs.</para><para>(5) The department shall partner with a statewide association representing a majority of hospitals and health systems in Nebraska to:</para><para>(a) Aggregate inpatient, outpatient, and clinic claims data in order to establish quality improvement metrics and track progress on identified metrics; and</para><para>(b) Design and implement quality initiatives to improve children's mental health, adult mental health, maternity care, and senior care.</para><para>(6) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that are necessary to implement the Hospital Quality Assurance and Access Assessment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1087, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>March 28, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>