<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Warehouses" statutenumber="88-530"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>88-530</statuteno><catchline>Financial requirements; security; requirements; liability of surety.</catchline><para>Each applicant shall show sufficient net worth or stockholders' equity to conform with the financial requirements which the commission shall establish by the adoption and promulgation of rules and regulations. Applicants shall file with the commission security in the form of a bond, a certificate of deposit, an irrevocable letter of credit, United States bonds or treasury notes, or other public debt obligations of the United States which are unconditionally guaranteed as to both principal and interest by the United States in such sum as the commission may require and in the form and of the kind prescribed by the commission. The security shall be in an amount set by the commission pursuant to rules and regulations, but shall not be less than twenty-five thousand dollars. The security shall run to the State of Nebraska for the benefit of each person who stores grain in such warehouse and of each person who holds a check for purchase of grain stored in such warehouse which was issued by the warehouse licensee not more than five business days prior to the cutoff date of operation of the warehouse, which shall be the date the commission officially closes the warehouse. The security shall be conditioned upon (1) the warehouse licensee carrying combustion, fire, lightning, and tornado insurance sufficient to cover loss upon all stored grain in such warehouse, (2) the delivery of the grain upon surrender of the warehouse receipt, and (3) the faithful performance by the warehouse licensee of all provisions of law relating to the storage of grain by such warehouse licensee and rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission. The commission may require increases in the amount of the security from time to time as it may deem necessary for the protection of the storers. For an applicant who has filed a reviewed fiscal year-end financial statement pursuant to section 88-528, the commission shall require additional security in an amount set by the commission pursuant to rules and regulations, which shall not be less than twenty-five thousand dollars and not more than five hundred thousand dollars. The surety on a bond shall be a surety company licensed by the Department of Insurance. An irrevocable letter of credit or certificate of deposit shall be issued by a federally insured depository institution.</para><para>The security shall particularly describe the warehouse intended to be covered by the security. The liability of the surety on a bond shall not accumulate for each successive license period which the bond covers. The liability of the surety shall be limited to the amount stated on the bond or on an appropriate rider or endorsement to the bond.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 164, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 78, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 735, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>