<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id587"><amendatorysection chaptername="Notaries Public" statutenumber="64-415"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>64-415</statuteno><catchline>Electronic certificate of authority; form; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Electronic evidence of the authenticity of the electronic signature and online notary seal of an online notary public of this state, if required, shall be attached to, or logically associated with, a document with an online notary public's electronic signature transmitted to another state or nation and shall be in the form of an electronic certificate of authority signed by the Secretary of State in conformance with any current and pertinent international treaties, agreements, and conventions subscribed to by the United States Government.</para><para>(2) An electronic certificate of authority evidencing the authenticity of the electronic signature and online notary seal of an online notary public of this state shall contain substantially the following words:</para><para>Certificate of Authority for an Online Notarial Act</para><para>I ................... (name, title, jurisdiction of commissioning official) certify that .................... (name of online notary public), the person named as an online notary public in the attached or associated document, was indeed registered as an online notary public for the State of Nebraska and authorized to act as such at the time of the document's electronic notarization. To verify this Certificate of Authority for an Online Notarial Act, I have included herewith my electronic signature this .................... day of ...................., 20.....................</para><para>(Electronic signature (and seal) of commissioning official)</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State may charge a fee of twenty dollars for issuing an electronic certificate of authority. The Secretary of State shall remit the fees to the State Treasurer for credit to the Administration Cash Fund for use in administering the Online Notary Public Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB186, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>