
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Notaries Public" id="id12" statutenumber="64-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>64-101</statuteno><catchline id="id15">Appointment; qualifications;
term.</catchline><para>(1) The Secretary of State may appoint and
commission such number of persons to the office of notary public as he or
she deems necessary.</para>
<para>(2) There shall be one class of such appointments which shall
be valid in the entire state and referred to as general notaries public.</para>
<para>(3) The term effective date, as used with reference to a commission
of a notary public, shall mean the date of the commission unless the commission
states when it goes into effect, in which event that date shall be the effective
date.</para>
<para>(4) A general commission may refer to the office as notary
public and shall contain a provision showing that the person therein named
is authorized to act as a notary public anywhere within the State of Nebraska
or, in lieu thereof, may contain the word general or refer to the office as
general notary public.</para>
<para>(5) No person shall be appointed a notary public unless he
or she has taken and passed a written examination on the duties and obligations
of a notary public as provided in section 64-101.01.</para>
<para>(6) No appointment shall be made if such applicant has been
convicted of (a) a
felony or (b) a crime involving fraud
or dishonesty within the previous
five years.</para>
<para>(7) No appointment shall be made until such applicant has
attained the age of nineteen years nor unless such applicant certifies to
the Secretary of State under oath that he or she has carefully read and understands
the laws relating to the duties of notaries public and will, if commissioned,
faithfully discharge the duties pertaining to the office and keep records
according to law.</para>
<para>(8) No person shall be
appointed a notary public unless he or she resides in the State of Nebraska,
except that the Secretary of State may appoint and commission a person as
a notary public who resides in a state that borders the State of Nebraska
if such person is employed in or has a regular place of work or business in
this state and the Secretary of State has obtained evidence of an address
of the physical location of such employment or place of work or business prior
to such appointment and commission.</para><para>(9) Each person appointed a notary public shall
hold office for a term of four years from the effective date of his or her
commission unless sooner removed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 1, p. 20; </para><para>G.S.1873, p. 493; </para><para>Laws 1883, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 248; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5517; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 293; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 99, &#167; 2, p. 365; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4813; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 64-101; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 136, &#167; 1, p. 467; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 64-101; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 145, &#167; 1, p. 487; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 205, &#167; 1, p. 763; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 396, &#167; 2, p. 1241; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 88, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 622, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 315, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB398, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The Governor is authorized to appoint such number of persons to the office of notary public as he shall deem necessary. Cohn v. Butterfield, 89 Neb. 849, 132 N.W. 400 (1911).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>