<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Notaries Public" statutenumber="64-113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>64-113</statuteno><catchline>Removal; grounds; procedure; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever charges of malfeasance in office are preferred to the Secretary of State against any notary public in this state, or whenever the Secretary of State has reasonable cause to believe any notary public in this state is guilty of acts of malfeasance in office, the Secretary of State may appoint any disinterested person, not related by consanguinity to either the notary public or person preferring the charges, and authorized by law to take testimony of witnesses by deposition, to notify such notary public to appear before him or her on a day and at an hour certain, after at least ten days from the day of service of such notice. At such appearance, the notary public may show cause as to why his or her commission should not be canceled or temporarily revoked. The appointee may issue subpoenas to require the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of any pertinent records, papers, or documents, may administer oaths, and may accept any evidence he or she deems pertinent to a proper determination of the charge. The notary public may appear, at such time and place, and cross-examine witnesses and produce witnesses in his or her behalf. Upon the receipt of such examination, duly certified in the manner prescribed for taking depositions to be used in suits in the district courts of this state, the Secretary of State shall examine the same, and if therefrom he or she finds that the notary public is guilty of acts of malfeasance in office, he or she may remove the person charged from the office of notary public or temporarily revoke such person's commission. Within fifteen days after such removal or revocation and notice thereof, such notary public shall deposit, with the Secretary of State, the commission as notary public and notarial seal. The commission shall be canceled or temporarily revoked by the Secretary of State. A person so removed from office shall be forever disqualified from holding the office of notary public. A person whose commission is temporarily revoked shall be returned his or her commission and seal upon completion of the revocation period and passing the examination described in section 64-101.01. The fees for taking such testimony shall be paid by the state at the same rate as fees for taking depositions by notaries public. The failure of the notary public to deposit his or her commission and seal with the Secretary of State as required by this section shall subject him or her to a penalty of one thousand dollars, to be recovered in the name of the state.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, malfeasance in office means, while serving as a notary public, (a) failure to follow the requirements and procedures for notarial acts provided for in Chapter 64, (b) violating the confidentiality provisions of section 71-6911, or (c) being convicted of a felony or other crime involving fraud or dishonesty.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 14, p. 25; </para><para>G.S.1873, p. 497; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5529; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4825; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 64-113; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 64-113; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 145, &#167; 10, p. 493; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 396, &#167; 8, p. 1244; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 315, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB690, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB398, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB186, &#167; 21. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former law where charges of malfeasance in office were brought to the Governor against a notary public, Governor was required to hold hearing, and if satisfied that charges were proven, remove the notary from office. Cohn v. Butterfield, 89 Neb. 849, 132 N.W. 400 (1911).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>