<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Notaries Public" statutenumber="64-102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>64-102</statuteno><catchline>Commission; how obtained; bond.</catchline><para>Any person may apply for a commission authorizing the applicant to act as a notary public anywhere in the State of Nebraska, and thereupon the Secretary of State may, at his or her discretion, issue a commission authorizing such notary public to act as such anywhere in the State of Nebraska. A general commission shall not authorize the holder thereof to act as a notary public anywhere in the State of Nebraska until a bond in the sum of fifteen thousand dollars, with an incorporated surety company as surety, has been executed and approved by and filed in the office of the Secretary of State. Upon the filing of such bond with the Secretary of State and the issuance of such commission, such notary public shall be authorized and empowered to perform any and all the duties of a notary public in any and all the counties in the State of Nebraska. Such bond shall be conditioned for the faithful performance of the duties of such office. Such person so appointed to the office of notary public shall make oath or affirmation, to be endorsed on such bond, and subscribed by him or her before some officer authorized by law to administer oaths, and by him or her certified thereon, that he or she will support the Constitution of the United States and the Constitution of Nebraska and will faithfully and impartially discharge and perform the duties of the office of notary public.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 293; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 99, &#167; 2, p. 365; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4813; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 64-101; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 136, &#167; 1, p. 468; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 64-102; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 145, &#167; 2, p. 489; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 396, &#167; 3, p. 1242; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1030, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 315, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>