<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Notaries Public" statutenumber="64-105.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>64-105.03</statuteno><catchline>Notary public; unauthorized practice of law; prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) A notary public who is not an attorney shall not engage in the unauthorized practice of law as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) If notarial certificate wording is not provided or indicated for a document, a notary public who is not an attorney shall not determine the type of notarial act or certificate to be used.</para><para>(3) A notary public who is not an attorney shall not assist another person in drafting, completing, selecting, or understanding a document or transaction requiring a notarial act.</para><para>(4) A notary public who is not an attorney shall not claim to have powers, qualifications, rights, or privileges that the office of notary public does not provide, including the power to counsel on immigration matters.</para><para>(5) A notary public who is not an attorney and who advertises notarial services in a language other than English shall include in any advertisement, notice, letterhead, or sign a statement prominently displayed in the same language as follows: "I am not an attorney and have no authority to give advice on immigration or other legal matters".</para><para>(6) A notary public who is not an attorney may not use the term notario publico or any equivalent non-English term in any business card, advertisement, notice, or sign.</para><para>(7) This section does not preclude a notary public who is duly qualified, trained, or experienced in a particular industry or professional field from selecting, drafting, completing, or advising on a document or certificate related to a matter within that industry or field.</para><para>(8) A violation of any of the provisions of this section shall be considered the unauthorized practice of law and subject to the penalties provided in section 7-101.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 315, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc>