<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Notaries Public" statutenumber="64-205" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>64-205</statuteno><catchline>Acknowledgment, defined.</catchline><para>(1) The words acknowledged before me means:</para><para>(a) That the person acknowledging appeared before the person taking the acknowledgment;</para><para>(b) That he or she acknowledged he or she executed the instrument;</para><para>(c) That, in the case of:</para><para>(i) A natural person, he or she executed the instrument for the purposes therein stated;</para><para>(ii) A corporation, the officer or agent acknowledged he or she held the position or title set forth in the instrument and certificate, he or she signed the instrument on behalf of the corporation by proper authority and the instrument was the act of the corporation for the purpose therein stated;</para><para>(iii) A partnership, the partner or agent acknowledged he or she signed the instrument on behalf of the partnership by proper authority and he or she executed the instrument as the act of the partnership for the purposes therein stated;</para><para>(iv) A limited liability company, the member or agent acknowledged he or she signed the instrument on behalf of the limited liability company by proper authority and he or she executed the instrument as the act of the limited liability company for the purposes therein stated;</para><para>(v) A person acknowledging as principal by an attorney in fact, he or she executed the instrument by proper authority as the act of the principal for the purposes therein stated; or</para><para>(vi) A person acknowledging as a public officer, trustee, administrator, guardian, or other representative, he or she signed the instrument by proper authority and he or she executed the instrument in the capacity and for the purposes therein stated; and</para><para>(d) That the person taking the acknowledgment either knew or had satisfactory evidence that the person acknowledging was the person named in the instrument or certificate.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, appearance before the person taking an acknowledgment includes an appearance outside the presence of a notary public if such acknowledgment was completed in accordance with the Online Notary Public Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 523, &#167; 5, p. 2141; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 393; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB186, &#167; 23. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Online Notary Public Act,</emphasis> see section 64-401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>