<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-209"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-209</statuteno><catchline>Registration by paying agent; when; content; interest requirement; procedure; order of payment.</catchline><para>Except as otherwise expressly specified by statute or the ordinance, resolution, or instrument authorizing the issuance of any bond or interest coupon mentioned in this section, whenever a bond or an interest coupon appertaining thereto issued by a county, city, village, school district, irrigation district, or other municipal or public corporation or political subdivision of the State of Nebraska is presented for payment to the county treasurer, city treasurer, or other person or corporation designated as the paying agent and there is not sufficient money to pay the same in the fund out of which such bond or coupon is payable, the county treasurer, city treasurer, or other person or corporation designated by law as the paying agent shall register such bond or coupon in a book kept by him or her for that purpose. No such bond or coupon shall be presented or registered prior to its maturity date. Each such bond or coupon so registered shall be registered in order of its presentation for payment, and in the event that several of such bonds or coupons are presented for payment simultaneously, such bonds or coupons shall be registered in accordance with the numbers assigned to such bonds at the time of their issue or in accordance with the numbers assigned to the bonds to which such coupons appertain at the time of their issue. Thereafter money coming into such fund shall be applied to payment of such bonds or interest coupons, as the case may be, in the order of their registration. The county treasurer, city treasurer, or other person or corporation designated by law as the paying agent shall keep a record of such registrations showing the time, date, and serial number of each registration, the name of the county, city, village, irrigation district, or other municipal or public corporation or political subdivision of the state or the corporate name of the school district as described in section 79-405 issuing such bond or coupon, the date, kind, and serial number of such registered bond and of the bond to which each registered coupon appertains, the maturity date, the principal amount of the bond or coupon so registered, and the name and address of the person presenting such bond or coupon for payment. On the back of each of such bonds or coupons, the county treasurer, city treasurer, or other person or corporation designated by law as the paying agent shall enter the word Registered with the time, date, and serial number of such registration and return such bond or coupon to the person who has so presented the same for payment. All such bonds and coupons shall contain a provision fixing the rate of interest they shall bear after due if the paying agent does not have sufficient money to pay such bonds or coupons on the due date thereof, but if any such bonds or coupons shall not contain such provision, such bonds or coupons shall bear interest at the rate of nine percent per annum from due date until the paying agent has funds to pay such bonds or coupons and interest thereon.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 157, &#167; 1, p. 579; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 11-210; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 10-209; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 983, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1142, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1016.</para></source></law></legaldoc>