<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bonds" id="id6" statutenumber="10-703.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>10-703.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Issuance; election; notice; counting of ballots; canvass of vote.</catchline><para>In all special elections called for voting on the question of issuing bonds of the school district, the county clerk or election commissioner or, if the school district lies in more than one county, the county clerk or election commissioner in the county having the greatest number of electors entitled to vote on the question shall designate the polling places and appoint the election officials, who need not be the regular election officials, and otherwise conduct the election as provided under the Election Act except as otherwise specifically provided in this section. Any special election held under this section shall be subject to section 32-405. The school district shall designate the form of ballot and reimburse the county clerk or election official for the expenses of conducting the election as provided in sections 32-1201 to 32-1208 and at the minimum rate as described in subdivision (2)(d) of section 32-1203. The school district officers shall give notice of the election at least twenty days prior to the election and cause the sample ballot to be published in a newspaper of general circulation in the school district one time not more than ten days nor less than three days prior to the election, and no notice of the election shall be required to be given by the county clerk or election commissioner. The notice of election shall state where ballots for early voting may be obtained.</para><para>The ballots shall be counted by the county clerk or election commissioner conducting the election and two disinterested persons appointed by him or her. When the polls are closed, the receiving board shall deliver the ballots to the county clerk or election commissioner conducting the election who, with the two disinterested persons appointed by him or her, shall proceed to count the ballots.</para><para>Ballots for early voting shall be furnished to the county clerk or election commissioner and ready for distribution by the county clerk or election commissioner conducting the election not less than fifteen days prior to the election.</para><para>When a school district lies in more than one county, the county clerk or election commissioner in any other county containing part of such school district shall, upon request, certify its registration books for those precincts in which the school district is located to the county clerk or election commissioner conducting the election and shall immediately forward all requests for ballots for early voting to the county clerk or election commissioner charged with the issuing of such ballots. Not less than five days prior to the election, the school district officers shall certify to the county clerk or election commissioner conducting the election a list of all registered voters of the school district in any other county or counties qualified to vote on the bond issue.</para><para>All ballots cast at the election shall be counted by the same board. When all the ballots have been counted, the returns of such election shall be turned over to the school board or board of education of the district in which the election was held for the purpose of making a canvass thereof.</para><para>The two disinterested persons appointed on the counting board shall receive wages at no less than the minimum rate set in section 48-1203 for each hour of service rendered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 352, &#167; 1, p. 1198; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 175; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 661, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 550, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 421, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 920, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 424, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 466; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 764, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 935, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 521, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 98, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>In school district election, mail ballots are required to be endorsed by election official. Mommsen v. School Dist. No. 25, 181 Neb. 187, 147 N.W.2d 510 (1966).</para><para>This section is not unconstitutional because it delegates to school board the power to designate the polling places at which election is held. Peterson v. Cook, 175 Neb. 296, 121 N.W.2d 399 (1963).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>