<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-406</statuteno><catchline>Railroad aid bonds; precinct, township, city of the second class, or village; petition; election; issuance; conditions; limitations.</catchline><para>Any precinct, township, city of the second class, or village organized according to law is hereby authorized to issue bonds in aid of the construction of steam railroads, or railroads using electricity or gasoline as motive power, of standard gauge, to an extent not exceeding three and five-tenths percent of the taxable value of the taxable property at the last assessment within such precinct, township, city of the second class, or village, in the manner provided in this section:</para><para>(1) A petition for such purpose signed by not less than fifty freeholders or by not less than ten percent of all the freeholders, whichever number is the least, of the precinct, township, city of the second class, or village shall be presented to the county board, city council of cities of the second class, board of trustees of villages, or the board authorized by law to conduct the business of such precinct, township, city of the second class, or village. Such petition shall set forth the nature of the work contemplated, the amount of bonds sought to be voted, the rate of interest, and the length of time the bonds will run, which in no event shall be less than five years nor more than twenty years from the date thereof. The petitioners shall give bond, to be approved by the county board, city council of cities of the second class, or board of trustees of villages, for the payment of expenses of the election in the event that the proposition fails to receive a majority of the votes cast at such election;</para><para>(2) Upon receiving such petition, the county board, city council of cities of the second class, or board of trustees of villages shall give notice and call an election in the precinct, township, city of the second class, or village, as the case may be. The notice, call, and election shall be governed by the laws regulating the election for voting bonds for a county; and</para><para>(3) Upon a majority of the votes cast being in favor of the proposition submitted, the county board, city council of cities of the second class, or board of trustees of villages, as the case may be, shall issue the bonds in accordance with the petition and notice of election. Such bonds shall be signed by the chairperson of the county board and attested by the county clerk in the case of precinct or township bonds, by the mayor and city clerk in the case of city bonds, and by the chairperson of the board of trustees and village clerk in case of village bonds and shall be attested by their respective seals. Such bonds shall be a subsisting debt against such precinct, township, city of the second class, or village until they are paid and discharged.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 79, &#167; 1, p. 341; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 410; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 327; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 164, &#167; 1, p. 569; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 11-406; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 10-406; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 15, &#167; 5, p. 83; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 3, p. 274; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 534, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 17.</para></source></law></legaldoc>