<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-137"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-137</statuteno><catchline>Bond anticipation notes; issuance authorized; conditions.</catchline><para>Any issuer, except a sanitary and improvement district, which is authorized to issue warrants to pay costs of any water, sanitary, or storm sewer or other utility improvement or any street improvement, pending permanent financing by issuance of bonds, is hereby authorized to provide temporary financing for costs of such improvements by issuance of bond anticipation notes in lieu of issuing warrants. Such notes may be issued in the amount of the estimated cost of the improvements to be financed, including interest to accrue on such notes, as such estimated costs shall be determined by the governing body. Such notes shall be paid from the proceeds of bonds which the issuer is otherwise authorized to issue for such improvements and from any other funds available for the purpose. Bond anticipation notes may be issued on such terms and conditions and sold in such manner and at such prices as the governing body of the issuer shall determine. An issuer which has issued and has outstanding bond anticipation notes pursuant to this section may issue refunding notes with which to call and redeem all or any part of the outstanding notes at or before maturity or the redemption day of the notes. Such refunding notes may be issued in an amount sufficient to pay any redemption premium and interest to accrue and become payable on the notes being refunded to the date of payment of such notes. The refunding notes may be issued on such terms and conditions and sold in such manner and at such prices as the governing body of the issuer shall determine and shall be payable from the same sources as would have been available for payment of the notes being refunded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 421, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>