<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-409"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-409</statuteno><catchline>Precinct, township, city of the second class, or village bonds; petition; election; issuance; conditions; limitations; tax levy.</catchline><para>Any precinct, township, city of the second class, or village organized according to law is hereby authorized to issue bonds in aid of works of internal improvements, such as improving streets in cities of the second class and villages, highways, bridges, jails, city and town halls, high schools, county high schools, school dormitories, and the drainage of swamp and wet lands, within such municipal divisions, and for the construction or purchase of a telephone system for use of the inhabitants thereof, in an amount not exceeding seven-tenths of one percent of the taxable valuation of all the taxable property as shown by the last assessment within such precinct, township, city of the second class, or village, in the manner directed in this section:</para><para>(1) A petition signed by not less than fifty freeholders of the precinct, township, city of the second class, or village shall be presented to the county board, city council of cities of the second class, board of trustees of villages, or the board authorized by law to conduct the business of such precinct, township, city of the second class, or village. Such petition shall set forth the nature of the work contemplated, the amount of bonds sought to be voted, the rate of interest, and the length of time the bonds will run, which in no event shall be less than two years nor more than twenty years from the date thereof. The petitioners shall give bond, to be approved by the county board, city council of cities of the second class, or board of trustees of villages, for the payment of the expenses of the election in the event that the proposition fails to receive a majority of the votes cast at such election; and</para><para>(2) Upon the receipt of such petition, the county board, city council of cities of the second class, or board of trustees of villages shall give notice and call an election in the precinct, township, city of the second class, or village, as the case may be. Such notice, call, and election shall be governed by the laws regulating an election for voting bonds for a county. When a proposition is submitted for the issuance of bonds for the acquisition of a site or the construction of a single building to be used as a city hall, auditorium, fire station, or community house in cities of the second class, it shall be required, as a condition precedent to the issuance of such bonds, that a majority of the votes cast shall be in favor of such proposition. Bonds in such a city shall not be issued for such purpose in the aggregate to exceed one and four-tenths percent of the taxable valuation of all the taxable property in such city as shown by the last assessment within such city. The mayor and council in cities of the second class upon the issuance of bonds shall have the power to levy a tax each year not to exceed three and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such city for the purpose of maintaining the city hall constructed as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 268; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 49, &#167; 1, p. 261; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 76, &#167; 1, p. 286; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 413; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 241; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 330; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 11-409; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 23, &#167; 1, p. 96; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 5, &#167; 1, p. 64; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 11-409; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 10-409; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 15, &#167; 6, p. 84; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 287, &#167; 1, p. 926; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 45, &#167; 1, p. 160; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 153; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 5, p. 275; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 534, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 599, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 19.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Election proceeding</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Bonds authorized</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Election proceeding</emphasis></para><para>Precinct special election to issue bridge bonds held valid. Petition, notice, and official ballot considered and held sufficient. Lewis v. Eyerly, 120 Neb. 343, 232 N.W. 570 (1930).</para><para>Nonresident freeholders owning land in precinct may join in petition. Brooks v. MacLean, 95 Neb. 16, 144 N.W. 1067 (1914).</para><para>Terms of proposition set forth in notice of election define authority of county board in contracting with reference to work of internal improvement. Keith County v. Ogallala Power Irrigation Co., 64 Neb. 35, 89 N.W. 375 (1902).</para><para>Married woman who is freeholder is lawful petitioner. Cummings v. Hyatt, 54 Neb. 35, 74 N.W. 411 (1898).</para><para>To confer jurisdiction on county commissioners to order election to vote bonds by a township in aid of internal improvements, it is necessary that a petition be presented signed by not less than fifty freeholders of the township. Hoxie v. Scott, 45 Neb. 199, 63 N.W. 387 (1895).</para><para>Where signing of petition is induced by false representations, bond issue will be enjoined. Wullenwaber v. Dunigan, 30 Neb. 877, 47 N.W. 420 (1890).</para><para>President and board of trustees, before election of mayor and council, may call election. State ex rel. Fremont, E. &amp; M. V. R. R. Co. v. Babcock, 25 Neb. 709, 41 N.W. 654 (1889).</para><para>In absence of petition signed by fifty freeholders setting forth the nature of the work contemplated, the amount of bonds to be voted, the rate of interest, and date when principal and interest become due, proceedings are invalid. Adoption of amount of tax to be levied is mandatory. State ex rel. Omaha &amp; R. V. R. R. Co. v. Babcock, 21 Neb. 187, 31 N.W. 682 (1887).</para><para><emphasis>2. Bonds authorized</emphasis></para><para>Authority is provided for issuance of bonds for minor political subdivisions. Lang v. Sanitary District, 160 Neb. 754, 71 N.W.2d 608 (1955).</para><para>Bonds for normal school are not authorized, as it is not one of the objects enumerated in qualifying clause for which bonds may be issued. State ex rel. Ainsworth Precinct v. Weston, 69 Neb. 695, 96 N.W. 668 (1903).</para><para>Bonds for irrigation purposes are authorized. Cummings v. Hyatt, 54 Neb. 35, 74 N.W. 411 (1898); Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R.R. Co. v. Dundy County, 3 Neb. Unof. 391, 91 N.W. 554 (1902).</para><para>Bonds issued under this section to aid in construction of courthouse are valid in hands of bona fide purchaser, even though petition asking for calling of election was signed by less than fifty freeholders. Chilton v. Town of Gratton, 82 F. 873 (Cir. Ct., D. Neb. 1897).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>County is liable for expense of publishing notice of township election. Kearney County v. Stein, 26 Neb. 132, 41 N.W. 1071 (1889).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>