<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-711"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-711</statuteno><catchline>Tax levy; sinking fund; exception; funds; distribution.</catchline><para>It shall be the duty of the county board in each county to levy annually upon all the taxable property in each school district in such county a tax sufficient to pay the interest accruing upon any bonds issued by such school district and to provide a sinking fund for the final redemption of the same. Such levy shall be made with the annual levy of the county and the taxes collected with other taxes and when collected shall be paid over to the county treasurer of the county in which the administrative office of such school district is located and shall remain in the hands of such county treasurer as a specific fund for the payment of the interest upon such bonds and for the final payment of the same at maturity. At the request of the school board of any district, the county board shall omit making a levy to pay the principal of the bonds when no bonds will be due within fifteen years thereafter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 13, p. 173; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 458; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 375; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 11-911; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 22, &#167; 2, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 11-911; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 10-711; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 269; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 924, &#167; 6.</para></source><annotation><para>In absence of an order by the school board to county treasurer to pay school bonds out of sinking fund, county is not liable for interest accruing on such bonds even though bonds were payable and sinking fund sufficient to discharge them. School District No. 22, of Harlan County v. Harlan County, 127 Neb. 4, 254 N.W. 701 (1934).</para><para>Levy of tax for bonds is subject to tax limitation for all school purposes. School Dist. of Central City v. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co., 60 Neb. 454, 83 N.W. 667 (1900).</para><para>District liable to holder of bond where county treasurer deposited fund in insolvent bank. Jacobson v. Cary, 51 Neb. 762, 71 N.W. 723 (1897).</para><para>Where levy of taxes in one year to pay bonds issued by a school district would be a burden on taxpayers, court on mandamus may apportion the levy over a number of years. State ex rel. Gregory v. School Dist. No. 7, of Sherman County, 22 Neb. 700, 36 N.W. 278 (1888).</para><para>Transfer from sinking fund to general fund enjoined. Levy beyond limit is not authorized. Union P. Ry. Co. v. Dawson County, 12 Neb. 254, 11 N.W. 307 (1882).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>