<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-606</statuteno><catchline>City of the second class and village; issuance; limitations; election; notice.</catchline><para>Any city of the second class and any village in the State of Nebraska may issue bonds for the purpose of funding any and all indebtedness now existing or hereafter created, now due or to become due; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> said bonds shall be payable in not less than two years and not more than twenty years from date of their issue, and that said bonds shall bear interest at a rate set by the governing body, with interest coupons attached, payable annually or semiannually; and may levy a tax on all the taxable property in the city or village in addition to other taxes for the payment of said coupons as they respectively become due, and the taxes levied to pay the same shall be payable only in cash or coupons; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> the city council of said cities or said board of trustees of said villages shall further authorize the issuing of said bonds by ordinance when so instructed by a majority of all of the votes cast at an election held in such city or village for that purpose; notice of said election shall be published in four issues of some legal newspaper, published in the city or village seeking to issue bonds, or if there be no newspaper published in said city or village then by posting said notices in five conspicuous places in said city or village for at least four weeks prior to the date of said election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 19, &#167; 1, p. 161; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 142; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 429; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 346; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 42, &#167; 1, p. 162; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 11-605; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 10-606; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 10, p. 279.</para></source><annotation><para>A claim sounding in contract, which may be enforced in the courts, is an indebtedness for the payment of which funding bonds may be issued. State ex rel. City of Tekamah v. Marsh, 108 Neb. 835, 189 N.W. 381 (1922).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>