<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-142"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-142</statuteno><catchline>Refunding bonds; issuance; conditions; application of proceeds.</catchline><para>Any county, city, village, municipal county, school district, drainage district, irrigation district, metropolitan utilities district, rural water district, airport authority, or hospital authority, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, the governing board of any community college, or any other municipal or public corporation, governmental subdivision, or body politic or corporate created under Nebraska law exercising essential public functions of the state which has issued or shall issue bonds for any purpose, and such bonds or any part of such bonds remain unpaid and are a legal liability against such issuer and are bearing interest, is hereby authorized to issue refunding bonds with which to call and redeem all or any part of such outstanding bonds at or before the maturity or the redemption date of such bonds. Such issuer may include various series and issues of the outstanding bonds in a single issue of refunding bonds and issue refunding bonds to pay any redemption premium and interest to accrue and become payable on the outstanding bonds being refunded. The refunding bonds may be issued and delivered at any time prior to the date of maturity or the redemption date of the bonds to be refunded that the governing body of such issuer determines to be in its best interests. The proceeds derived from the sale of the refunding bonds issued pursuant to this section may be invested in obligations of or guaranteed by the United States Government pending the time the proceeds are required for the purposes for which such refunding bonds were issued. To further secure the refunding bonds, any such issuer may enter into a contract with any bank or trust company within or without the state with respect to the safekeeping and application of the proceeds of the refunding bonds and the safekeeping and application of the earnings on the investment. All bonds issued under the provisions of this section shall be redeemable at such times and under such conditions as the governing body of the issuer shall determine at the time of issuance.</para><para>Any outstanding bonds or other evidences of indebtedness issued by any such issuer for which sufficient funds or obligations of or guaranteed by the United States Government have been pledged and set aside in safekeeping to be applied for the complete payment of such bonds or other evidence of indebtedness at maturity or upon redemption prior to maturity, interest thereon, and redemption premium, if any, shall not be considered as outstanding and unpaid.</para><para>Each new refunding bond so issued shall state on the bond (1) the object of its issue, (2) this section or sections of the law under which such issue was made, including a statement that the issue is made in pursuance of such section or sections, and (3) the date and principal amount of the bond or bonds for which the refunding bonds are being issued.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 421, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 692, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 24.</para></source></law></legaldoc>