<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-127</statuteno><catchline>Replacement bond; issuance authorized; when.</catchline><para>The State Highway Commission, any county, city, village, municipal county, school district, drainage district, irrigation district, public power district, public power and irrigation district, metropolitan utilities district, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, community colleges, sanitary and improvement districts, rural water districts, airport authorities, hospital authorities, or any other municipal corporation or governmental subdivision of the state which has the power to issue bonds or other evidences of indebtedness may issue bonds or other evidences of indebtedness of like date, tenor, amount, and maturity to replace mutilated, destroyed, stolen, or lost bonds or other evidences of indebtedness previously issued and having attached thereto the same corresponding unmatured coupons, if any, as were attached to the mutilated, destroyed, stolen, or lost bonds or other evidences of indebtedness. Issuance of replacement bonds or other evidences of indebtedness of like date, tenor, amount, and maturity may be made (1) in exchange and in substitution for such mutilated bond or other evidence of indebtedness and attached unmatured coupons, if any, upon surrender of such mutilated bond or other evidence of indebtedness and attached unmatured coupons, if any, or (2) in lieu of and in substitution for the destroyed, stolen, or lost bond or other evidence of indebtedness and attached unmatured coupons. In the event such bond or other evidence of indebtedness and attached unmatured coupons, if any, have been destroyed, stolen, or lost, the holder thereof shall first file with the issuer evidence satisfactory to it that such bond or other evidence of indebtedness and attached unmatured coupons have been destroyed, stolen, or lost and of such holder's ownership thereof and shall in any event furnish the issuer with indemnity satisfactory to it and shall comply with any statutory requirements and with such other requirements as the issuer may require. A charge, not exceeding the actual cost thereof, shall be imposed upon such owner to reimburse the issuer for the expenses for issuing each such new bond or evidence of indebtedness, which cost shall be paid before the delivery of the new bond or evidence of indebtedness. Instead of issuing a substituted bond or evidence of indebtedness or instead of delivery of any coupon for a bond or evidence of indebtedness, as the case may be, which has matured or which is about to mature and instead of issuing a substituted bond or other evidence of indebtedness for a bond or other evidence of indebtedness which has been called for redemption, the issuer, upon receiving evidence and being indemnified as provided in this section, at its option may pay the bond or other evidence of indebtedness or such coupon from any source lawfully available therefor without the surrender thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 873, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 802, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1135, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 21.</para></source></law></legaldoc>