<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds" statutenumber="10-1106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>10-1106</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement; determination of default.</catchline><para>The terms of any applicable authorizing statute shall govern the enforcement of any security interest to the extent that the authorizing statute contains express provisions relating to enforcement or authorizes a governmental unit to contract with respect to enforcement. In the absence of any such express provisions in an authorizing statute, the following provisions apply:</para><para>(1) Any measure may include provisions determining what events constitute events of default. In the absence of any express provision relating to default in any measure, the governmental unit is in default so long as any default in payment with respect to principal, interest, or premium on a bond has occurred and remains uncured;</para><para>(2) Any trustee designated in or under the terms of a measure shall have the right, if a default has occurred, to have a receiver appointed for the collection of any revenue or property in which a security interest is granted, and if the revenue is from any revenue-producing undertaking, any such receiver may also be appointed to operate and manage such revenue-producing undertaking for the benefit of the owners of the bonds in accordance with the terms of the measure or measures authorizing their issuance;</para><para>(3) If there is no trustee designated in or under the terms of a measure, any owner of a bond shall have the right, if a default has occurred, to have a receiver appointed for the collection of any revenue or property in which a security interest is granted and, if the revenue is from any revenue-producing undertaking, any such receiver may also be appointed to operate and manage such revenue-producing undertaking for the benefit of the owners of the bonds in accordance with the terms of the measure or measures authorizing their issuance;</para><para>(4) Any trustee designated in or under the terms of any measure or any owner of a bond, if there is no trustee designated, shall have the right to bring proceedings against the governing body of the governmental unit to order the imposing of rates or charges with respect to any revenue-producing undertaking sufficient to provide for payment of principal, interest, and premium on a bond or bonds as the same fall due; and</para><para>(5) Any trustee designated in or under the terms of any measure or any owner of a bond shall have the right to exercise any other remedy provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 929, &#167; 22.</para></source></law></legaldoc>