<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-202"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>52-202</statuteno><catchline>Lien; perfection; financing statement; filing.</catchline><para>Any person who makes, alters, repairs, or in any way enhances the value of any vehicle, automobile, machinery, or farm implement or tool or shoes any horse or mule, at the request of or with the consent of the owner or owners thereof, has a lien upon such property, in cases when he or she has parted with the possession of such property, for his or her reasonable or agreed charges for the work performed or material furnished. A lien created under this section shall be perfected as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code. Any financing statement filed to perfect such lien shall be filed within sixty days after performing such work or furnishing such material and shall contain or have attached thereto (1) the name and address and the social security number or federal tax identification number of the person claiming the lien, (2) the name and address and the social security number or federal tax identification number, if known, of the person for whom the work was performed or material furnished, (3) a description of the work performed or material furnished, (4) a description of the property upon which such work was performed or material furnished, and (5) the amount due for such work performed or material furnished. The failure to include the social security number or federal tax identification number shall not render any filing unperfected. At the time the lien is filed, the lienholder shall send a copy to the person for whom the work was performed or material furnished.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 123, &#167; 2, p. 310; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3842; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3226; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 52-202; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 52-202; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 943, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 54, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Under this section, an artisan's lien attaches if the necessary documents are filed within 60 days of the furnishing of an item of labor or material which is part of a simple contract or undertaking. Cool v. Sahling Trucks, Inc., 237 Neb. 541, 466 N.W.2d 796 (1991).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 