<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-701"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>52-701</statuteno><catchline>Lien; perfection; financing statement;
filing; enforcement; fee.</catchline><para>Whenever any person procures, contracts
with, or hires any person licensed to practice veterinary medicine and surgery
to treat, relieve, or in any way take care of any kind of livestock, such
veterinarian shall have a first, paramount, and prior lien upon such livestock
so treated for the contract price agreed upon or, in case no price has been
agreed upon, for the reasonable value of the services and any medicines or
biologics furnished. A lien created under this section shall be treated in
all respects as an agricultural lien as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial
Code, and may be enforced in the manner and form provided for the enforcement
of secured transactions as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code.
A lien created under this section shall be perfected as provided in article
9, Uniform Commercial Code. Any financing statement filed to perfect such
lien shall be filed within ninety days after the furnishing of the services
and any medicines or biologics and shall contain or have attached thereto
(1) the name and address and the social security number or federal tax identification
number of the veterinarian claiming the lien, (2) the name and address and
the social security number or federal tax identification number, if known,
of the person to whom the services and medicines or biologics were furnished,
(3) a correct description of the livestock to be charged with the lien, and
(4) the amount of the services and any medicines or biologics furnished. The
failure to include the social security number or federal tax identification
number shall not render any filing unperfected. At the time the lien is filed,
the lienholder shall send a copy to the person to whom the services and medicines
or biologics were furnished. The fee for filing, amending, or releasing such
lien shall be the same as set forth in section 9-525, Uniform Commercial Code. Effective January 1, 2015, this section
applies to a lien created under this section regardless of when the lien was
created.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 117, &#167; 1, p. 432; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 52-701; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 52-701; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 436, &#167; 4, p. 1465; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 808, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 943, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 54, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB750, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>