<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-903"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>52-903</statuteno><catchline>Lien; effect of filing; sale of crop,
effect; enforcement.</catchline><para>From and after the date of the filing
of the lien as provided in section 52-902, the person claiming the lien shall
have a lien upon the crops produced and owned by the person to whom the fuel
or lubricant was furnished to the amount of the purchase price of such fuel
or lubricant so furnished to such person. In the event the person to whom
such fuel or lubricant was furnished desires to sell or deliver any portion
of the crops so produced, such person shall notify the purchaser or consignee
that such fuel or lubricant bill has not been paid. Such lien shall shift
to the purchase price thereof in the hands of such purchaser or consignee.
In the event any portion of such crops is sold or consigned with the consent
or knowledge of the person entitled to a lien thereon within six months after
the date such fuel or lubricant was furnished, such lien shall not attach
to any portion of such crops or to the purchase price thereof unless the person
entitled to such lien notifies the purchaser in writing thereof. A lien created
under section 52-901 shall be treated in all respects as an agricultural lien
as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code, and may be enforced in
the manner and form provided for the enforcement of secured transactions as
provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code, except that such enforcement
proceedings shall be instituted within ninety days after the filing of the
lien. Effective January 1,
2015, this section applies to a lien created under section 52-901 regardless
of when the lien was created.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 226, &#167; 3, p. 776; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 436, &#167; 5, p. 1465; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 314, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 54, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB750, &#167; 8.</para></source><annotation><para>Purchase price, under this section, means more than money and may include credits applied to a debt. Galyen Petroleum Co. v. Svoboda, 222 Neb. 268, 383 N.W.2d 49 (1986).</para><para>Under former law, this section required that proceedings to foreclose a petroleum products lien be instituted within thirty days after the filing of the lien. Circle 76 Fertilizer v. Nelsen, 219 Neb. 661, 365 N.W.2d 460 (1985).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>