<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-1801"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1801</statuteno><catchline>Mobile home security interest; perfection; mobile home certificate of title; notation of lien; laws applicable.</catchline><para>(1) Any security interest in a mobile home perfected on or after July 15, 1992, and prior to April 8, 1993, shall continue to be perfected:</para><para>(a) Until the financing statement perfecting such security interest is terminated or would have lapsed in the absence of the filing of a continuation statement pursuant to article 9, Uniform Commercial Code; or</para><para>(b) Until a lien is noted on the face of the certificate of title for the mobile home pursuant to section 60-164.</para><para>(2) Any lien noted on the face of a mobile home certificate of title on or after April 8, 1993, pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of this section on behalf of the holder of a security interest in the mobile home which was perfected on or after July 15, 1992, and prior to April 8, 1993, shall have priority as of the date such security interest was originally perfected.</para><para>(3) The holder of a mobile home certificate of title shall, upon request, surrender the mobile home certificate of title to a holder of a security interest in the mobile home which was perfected on or after July 15, 1992, and prior to April 8, 1993, to permit notation of a lien on the mobile home certificate of title and shall do such other acts as may be required to permit such notation.</para><para>(4) If the owner of a mobile home subject to a security interest perfected on or after July 15, 1992, and prior to April 8, 1993, fails or refuses to obtain a certificate of title after April 8, 1993, the security interest holder may obtain a certificate of title in the name of the owner of the mobile home following the procedures of subsection (2) of section 60-147 and may have a lien noted on the certificate of title pursuant to section 60-164.</para><para>(5) The assignment, release, or satisfaction of a security interest in a mobile home shall be governed under the laws under which it was perfected.</para><para>(6) This section shall not affect the validity or priority of a lien established against a mobile home by the notation of such lien on the mobile home certificate of title prior to July 15, 1992.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 340, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 101. </para></source></law></legaldoc>