<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-1602"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1602</statuteno><catchline>Master lien list; distribution; registration to receive list; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The master lien list prescribed in section 52-1601 shall be distributed by the Secretary of State on a quarterly basis corresponding to the date on which the lists provided pursuant to sections 52-1301 to 52-1322 are distributed. Such master lien list may be mailed with the list provided pursuant to sections 52-1301 to 52-1322. If mailed separately, the master lien list shall be mailed by either certified or registered mail, return receipt requested.</para><para>(2) Any person may register with the Secretary of State to receive the master lien list prescribed in section 52-1601. Such registration shall be on an annual basis. The Secretary of State shall provide the form for registration. A registration shall not be completed until the form provided is properly completed and received by the Secretary of State accompanied by the proper registration fee. The fee for annual registration shall be thirty dollars, except that a registrant under sections 52-1301 to 52-1322 shall not be required to pay the registration fee provided by this section in addition to the registration fee paid pursuant to sections 52-1301 to 52-1322 for the same annual registration period. Beginning for calendar year 1989, a registrant under sections 52-1601 to 52-1605 shall pay an additional annual fee to receive quarterly master lien lists prescribed in section 52-1601. For each master lien list provided on microfiche, the annual fee shall be twenty-five dollars. For each master lien list provided on paper, the annual fee shall be two hundred dollars. The Secretary of State may provide for the distribution of master lien lists on any other medium and may establish reasonable charges therefor.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State, by rule and regulation, shall establish the dates after which a filing of liens will not be reflected on the next quarterly distribution of the master lien list and the date by which a registrant shall complete a registration in order to receive the next quarterly master lien list.</para><para>(4) The Secretary of State shall deposit any funds received pursuant to subsection (2) of this section in the Uniform Commercial Code Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 987, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 4, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 69.</para></source></law></legaldoc>