<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-1602"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1602</statuteno><catchline>Master lien list; distribution or publication; registration to receive or obtain list; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The master lien list prescribed in section 52-1601 shall be distributed or published by the Secretary of State not more often than once every month and not less often than once every three months on the date corresponding to the date on which the lists provided pursuant to sections 52-1301 to 52-1322 are distributed or published.</para><para>(2) Any person may register with the Secretary of State to receive or obtain the master lien list prescribed in section 52-1601. Such registration shall be on an annual basis. The Secretary of State shall provide the form for registration. A registration shall not be completed until the form provided is properly completed and received by the Secretary of State accompanied by the proper registration fee. The fee for annual registration shall be thirty dollars, except that a registrant under sections 52-1301 to 52-1322 shall not be required to pay the registration fee provided by this section in addition to the registration fee paid pursuant to sections 52-1301 to 52-1322 for the same annual registration period. A registrant under sections 52-1601 to 52-1605 shall pay an additional annual fee to receive or obtain the master lien lists prescribed in section 52-1601. For each master lien list, the fee shall be an amount determined by the Secretary of State not to exceed two hundred dollars per year. The Secretary of State may provide for the distribution or publication of master lien lists on any medium and may establish reasonable charges for such lists, not to exceed the charges provided for in this subsection.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State, by rule and regulation, shall establish the dates after which a filing of liens will not be reflected on the next distribution or publication of the master lien list and the date by which a registrant shall complete a registration in order to receive or obtain the next master lien list.</para><para>(4) The Secretary of State shall deposit any funds received pursuant to subsection (2) of this section in the Uniform Commercial Code Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 987, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 4, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB124, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1035, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>