<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-1202" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1202</statuteno><catchline>Lien; perfection; financing statement; filing; fee.</catchline><para>(1) A lien created under section 52-1201 shall be perfected as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code. Such lien shall be perfected within one hundred twenty days after the last date on which (a) the seed was furnished or (b) the meter was read with respect to the electrical power or energy furnished.</para><para>(2) Any financing statement filed to perfect a lien created under section 52-1201 shall contain or have attached thereto (a) the name and address and the social security number or federal tax identification number of the person claiming the lien, (b) the name and address and the social security number or federal tax identification number, if known, of the person to whom the seed or electrical power or energy was furnished, (c) the contract price or reasonable value of the seed or electrical power or energy, and (d)(i) the type and amount of the seed and the date of delivery of the seed or (ii) the type and amount of the electrical power or energy and the period during which such power or energy was furnished. The failure to include the social security number or federal tax identification number shall not render any filing unperfected. At the time the lien is filed, the lienholder shall send a copy to the person to whom the seed or electrical power or energy was furnished. The fee for filing, amending, or releasing the lien shall be as provided in section 9-525, Uniform Commercial Code.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 503, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 943, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 54, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB177, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>