<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" id="id00" statutenumber="52-1603"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1603</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Buyer of farm products; purchase subject to lien; when; waiver or release of lien.</catchline><para>(1) A buyer of farm products who is registered to receive or obtain the master lien list as provided in section 52-1602 and who, in the ordinary course of business, buys farm products from a seller engaged in farming operations shall take free of any lien created under the provisions of Chapter 52, article 2, 5, 9, 11, 12, or 14, if such lien is not on the most recent master lien list received or obtained by the buyer pursuant to sections 52-1601 to 52-1605, except that such buyer shall take subject to any such lien if the lien was filed after the last date for inclusion in the most recent distribution or publication of the master lien list and if the buyer has received from the lienholder or seller written notice of the lien. For purposes of this subsection, the form of such written notice of the lien may be a copy of the lien filing. For purposes of this subsection, received or obtained by the buyer means the first date upon which delivery of the master lien list, in whatever form, is attempted by a carrier or, in the case of electronic publication, the first date upon which the Secretary of State made the most current master lien list available electronically, and in all cases in which delivery of the master lien list is involved, a buyer shall be presumed to have received the master lien list ten days after it was mailed by the Secretary of State.</para><para>(2) If a buyer buying property subject to a lien created under the provisions of Chapter 52, article 2, 5, 9, 11, 12, or 14, tenders to the seller the total purchase price by means of a check or other instrument payable to such seller and the lienholder of any such lien for such property and if such lienholder authorizes the negotiation of such check or other instrument, such authorization or endorsement and payment thereof shall constitute a waiver or release of the lien specified to the extent of the amount of the check or instrument. Such waiver or release of the lien shall not serve to establish or alter in any way security interest or lien priorities under Nebraska law.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in the provisions of subsections (1) and (2) of this section, sections 52-1601 to 52-1605 shall not be interpreted or construed to alter liability of buyers of property subject to liens created under the provisions of Chapter 52, article 2, 5, 9, 11, 12, or 14.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 987, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 70, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1035, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB142, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>May 11, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>