<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id34">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" id="id36" statutenumber="52-1004"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1004</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Notice; filing;
fees; billing.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This subdivision applies until January 1, 2018. The uniform
fee, payable to the Secretary of State, for presenting for filing and indexing
and for filing and indexing each notice of lien or certificate or notice affecting
the lien pursuant to the Uniform Federal Lien Registration Act shall be two times the fee required for recording instruments with
the register of deeds as provided in section 33-109. There shall
be no fee for the filing of a termination statement. The uniform fee for each
county more than one designated pursuant to subsection (1) of section 52-1001
shall be the fee required for recording instruments
with the register of deeds as provided in section 33-109. The
Secretary of State shall deposit each fee received pursuant to this subdivision in the Uniform Commercial Code Cash
Fund. Of the fees received and deposited pursuant to this subdivision, the
Secretary of State shall remit the fee
required for recording instruments with the register of deeds as provided
in section 33-109 to the register of deeds of a county for each
designation of such county in a filing pursuant to subsection (1) of section
52-1001.</para>
<para>(b) This subdivision
applies on and after January 1, 2018. The uniform fee, payable to the Secretary
of State, for presenting for filing and indexing and for filing and indexing
each notice of lien or certificate or notice affecting the lien pursuant to
the Uniform Federal Lien Registration Act shall be six dollars. There shall
be no fee for the filing of a termination statement. The uniform fee for each
county more than one designated pursuant to subsection (1) of section 52-1001
shall be three dollars. The Secretary of State shall deposit each fee received
pursuant to this subdivision in the Uniform Commercial Code Cash Fund. Of
the fees received and deposited pursuant to this subdivision, the Secretary
of State shall remit three dollars to the register of deeds of a county for
each designation of such county in a filing pursuant to subsection (1) of
section 52-1001.</para><para>(2) The Secretary of State
shall bill the district directors of internal revenue or other appropriate
federal officials on a monthly basis for fees for documents presented or filed
by them.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 433, &#167; 4, p. 1458; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 808, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 933, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB14, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>