<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Liens" statutenumber="52-1407"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>52-1407</statuteno><catchline>Lien; perfection; financing statement;
filing; priority; enforcement; fee.</catchline><para>(1) An agricultural production
input lien shall be perfected as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial
Code. Any financing statement filed to perfect such lien shall contain or
have attached thereto the information required in subsection (2) of section
52-1402 and shall be filed within three months after the last date that the
agricultural production input was furnished. The failure to include the social
security number or federal tax identification number shall not render any
filing unperfected. Perfection occurs as of the date such financing statement
is filed.</para>
<para>(2) An agricultural production input lien that is not perfected has
the priority of an unperfected security interest under section 9-322, Uniform
Commercial Code.</para>
<para>(3) An agricultural production input lien shall be treated in all respects
as an agricultural lien as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code,
and may be enforced in the manner and form provided for the enforcement of
secured transactions as provided in article 9, Uniform Commercial Code. For
purposes of enforcement of the lien, the lienholder is the secured party and
the person to whom the agricultural production input was furnished is the
debtor, and each has the respective rights and duties of a secured party and
a debtor under article 9, Uniform Commercial Code.</para>
<para>(4) The fee for filing, amending, or releasing such lien shall be the
same as set forth in section 9-525, Uniform Commercial Code.</para>
<para>(5) Effective January
1, 2015, this section applies to a lien created under this section regardless
of when the lien was created.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 101, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 943, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 54, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB750, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>