<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Liens" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="52-2001"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>52-2001</statuteno><catchline>Lien; foreclosure; notice; priority;
costs and attorney's fees; homeowners' association; furnish statement.</catchline><para>(1) A homeowners' association
has a lien on a member's real estate for any assessment levied against real
estate or fines imposed against its owner from the time the assessment or
fine becomes due and a notice containing the dollar amount of such lien is
recorded in the office where mortgages or deeds of trust are recorded. The
homeowners' association's lien may be foreclosed in like manner as a mortgage
on real estate but the homeowners' association shall give reasonable notice
of its action to all lienholders of real estate whose interest would be affected.
Unless the homeowners' association declaration or agreement otherwise provides,
fees, charges, late charges, fines, and interest charged are enforceable as
assessments under this section. If an assessment is payable in installments,
the full amount of the assessment may be a lien from the time the first installment
thereof becomes due.</para>
<para>(2) A lien under this
section is prior to all other liens and encumbrances on real estate except
(a) liens and encumbrances recorded before the recordation of the declaration
or agreement, (b) a first mortgage or deed of trust on real estate recorded
before the date on which the assessment sought to be enforced became delinquent,
and (c) liens for real estate taxes and other governmental assessments or
charges against real estate. The lien under this section is not subject to
the homestead exemption pursuant to section 40-101.</para><para>(3) Unless the declaration or agreement
otherwise provides, if two or more homeowners' associations have liens for
assessments created at any time on the same real estate, those liens have
equal priority.</para><para>(4)
A lien for unpaid assessments is extinguished unless proceedings to enforce
the lien are instituted within three years after the full amount of the assessments
becomes due.</para><para>(5)
This section does not prohibit actions to recover sums for which subsection
(1) of this section creates a lien or prohibit a homeowners' association from
taking a deed in lieu of foreclosure.</para><para>(6) A judgment or decree in any action brought under
this section must include costs and reasonable attorney's fees for the prevailing
party.</para><para>(7)
The homeowners' association, upon written request, shall furnish to a homeowners'
association member a recordable statement setting forth the amount of unpaid
assessments against his or her real estate. The statement must be furnished
within ten business days after receipt of the request and is binding on the
homeowners' association, the governing board, and every homeowners' association
member.</para><para>(8)
For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Declaration means any instruments, however denominated,
that create the homeowners' association and any amendments to those instruments;</para>
<para>(b)(i) Homeowners' association
means an association whose members consist of a private group of fee simple
owners of residential real estate formed for the purpose of imposing and receiving
payments, fees, or other charges for:</para><para>(A) The use, rental, operation, or maintenance of
common elements available to all members and services provided to the member
for the benefit of the member or his or her real estate;</para>
<para>(B) Late payments of
assessments and, after notice and opportunity to be heard, the levying of
fines for violations of homeowners' association declarations, agreements,
bylaws, or rules and regulations; or</para><para>(C) The preparation and recordation of amendments
to declarations, agreements, resale statements, or statements for unpaid assessments;
and</para><para>(ii)
Homeowners' association does not include a unit owners association organized
under the Nebraska Condominium Act; and</para><para>(c) Real estate means the real estate of a homeowners'
association member as such real estate is specifically described in the member's
homeowners' association declaration or agreement.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB736, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Condominium Property Act,</emphasis> see section 76-801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Condominium Act,</emphasis> see section 76-825.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>