<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-391" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-391</statuteno><catchline>Motor carrier transportation contracts; exculpatory provisions prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) A provision, a clause, a covenant, or an agreement contained in, collateral to, or affecting a motor carrier transportation contract that purports to indemnify, defend, or hold harmless or has the effect of indemnifying, defending, or holding harmless the motor carrier transportation contract's promisee from or against any liability for loss or damage resulting from the negligence or intentional acts or omissions of the motor carrier transportation contract's promisee or any agents, employees, servants, or independent contractors who are directly responsible to the motor carrier transportation contract's promisee, is against the public policy of this state and is unenforceable.</para><para>(2) Nothing contained in this section affects a provision, a clause, a covenant, or an agreement in which a motor carrier indemnifies or holds harmless a motor carrier transportation contract's promisee against liability for damages to the extent that the damages were caused by and resulting from the negligence of the motor carrier or its agents, employees, servants, or independent contractors who are directly responsible to the motor carrier.</para><para>(3) As used in this section:</para><para>(a) Motor carrier means any person who or which owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes to be operated any motor vehicle used to transport goods over any public highway in this state, whether in intrastate or interstate commerce;</para><para>(b) Motor carrier transportation contract means a contract, agreement, or understanding covering:</para><para>(i) The transportation of property for compensation or hire by a motor carrier;</para><para>(ii) The entrance on property by a motor carrier for the purpose of loading, unloading, or transporting property for compensation or for hire; or</para><para>(iii) A service incidental to activity described in subdivision (i) or (ii) of this subdivision, including, but not limited to, storage of property.</para><para>A motor carrier transportation contract does not include provisions of the Uniform Intermodal Interchange and Facilities Access Agreement administered by the Intermodal Association of North America or any other provision, clause, covenant, or agreement providing for the interchange, use, or possession of intermodal chassis, containers, or other intermodal equipment; and</para><para>(c) Promisee means the party to a motor carrier transportation contract who or which is not a motor carrier or, if the promisee is a motor carrier, is not the motor carrier actually doing the transporting.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 21.</para></source></law></legaldoc>