<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-720"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-720</statuteno><catchline>Proposed construction; electrical lines; application, notice, or hearing; unnecessary; when.</catchline><para>Provisions of law requiring filing of applications with the commission and other procedures for proposed construction of any electrical line pursuant to section 75-711 need not be complied with when the electric transmission carrier has given written notice by certified mail, with a copy to the commission by certified mail, of such proposed construction providing full information, including location drawing, electrical characteristics, physical configuration, and length of parallel of and proposed separation from other electrical, communication, or railroad signal lines, to any person who owns or operates electrical, communication, or railroad signal lines within the respective distances described in section 75-710, and such person has failed to file with such electric transmission carrier, within sixty days of receipt of the notice, a written protest, together with the reasons for objecting to the proposed construction. The sixty-day notice period for protest may be waived by signed agreement between such person and the electric transmission carrier. Receipt of a waiver shall be evidence that the sixty-day notice period is also waived. When the electric transmission carrier proposing the construction is required by section 75-713 to file an application with the commission or wants to receive a commission ruling, it shall file with its application copies of the notices sent by certified mail or signed copies of agreements with any person who owns or operates electrical, communication, or railroad signal lines within the respective distances described in section 75-710 and a signed copy of the agreement of the Director of Aeronautics if required by law, indicating their concurrence in the proposed construction. Upon receipt of such filing, the commission may approve the application to construct and may grant a permit without notice or a public hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. VII, &#167; 20, p. 1428; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 611, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 485, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 130. </para></source></law></legaldoc>