<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-303.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-303.03</statuteno><catchline>Reimbursement for transportation costs; conditions; exemption from commission regulation or commission rate regulation.</catchline><para>(1) The commission, in consultation with the Department of Health and Human Services, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing minimum liability insurance requirements, equipment standards, driver qualification requirements, and the issuance and filing of notice for any contractor utilized by the department or any agency organized under the Nebraska Community Aging Services Act pursuant to section 75-303.02.</para><para>(2) The Department of Health and Human Services or any agency organized under the Nebraska Community Aging Services Act shall reimburse common and contract carriers for transportation of passengers at a rate not to exceed the rate of reimbursement pursuant to section 81-1176 multiplied by three. The maximum reimbursement rate provided for in this subsection shall not apply when the carrier (a) transports such person wholly within the corporate limits of the city or village where the transportation of the person originated, (b) transports a disabled person as defined by the federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 in a vehicle that is compliant with the regulations providing for the transportation of such disabled person, or (c) provides nonemergency medical transportation of medicaid clients pursuant to subsection (3) of section 75-311.</para><para>(3) Rates for nonemergency medical transportation service providers with a designation of authority issued pursuant to subsection (3) of section 75-311 are not subject to commission regulation, and regulated motor carriers with such a designation reimbursed under this section are not subject to commission rate regulation for such reimbursement rates.</para><para>(4)(a) The Department of Health and Human Services may reimburse an individual for the costs incurred by such individual in the transportation of a person eligible to receive transportation services through the department if:</para><para>(i) The individual is under contract with the department and provides transportation to the eligible person; and</para><para>(ii) The eligible person has chosen the individual to provide the transportation.</para><para>(b) The department shall reimburse for the costs incurred in the transportation at a rate no greater than that provided for reimbursement of state employees pursuant to section 81-1176.</para><para>(c) Transportation provided to an eligible person by an individual pursuant to this section does not constitute transportation for hire.</para><para>(d) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to implement this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1069, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 699; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 84. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Community Aging Services Act,</emphasis> see section 81-2201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>