<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id403">
<sectno id="id404" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 36.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id405" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-159"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>75-159</statuteno><catchline>Public Service Commission Housing
and Recreational Vehicle Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1)
The Public Service Commission Housing and Recreational Vehicle Cash Fund is
created. The fund shall consist of fees collected under the Nebraska Uniform
Standards for Modular Housing Units Act and fees collected pursuant to the
Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles.</para>
<para>(2)
Money credited to the fund shall be used by the Public Service Commission
for the purposes of administering the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular
Housing Units Act and the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and
Recreational Vehicles.</para><para>(3) Transfers from the fund to the General
Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Public
Service Commission Housing and Recreational Vehicle Cash Fund available for
investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the
Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(4)
On July 1, 2010, the State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the Modular
Housing Units Cash Fund and any money in the Manufactured Homes and Recreational
Vehicles Cash Fund to the Public Service Commission Housing and Recreational
Vehicle Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 36.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1555.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles,</emphasis> see section 71-4601.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>