
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id570"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="75-328"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-328</statuteno><catchline>Use of personal vehicle; requirements; initial safety inspection; annual inspection; reports available.</catchline><para>(1) In order to be used under sections 75-323 to 75-343, a personal vehicle shall be in compliance with the Motor Vehicle Registration Act as required for a passenger car as defined in section 60-345.</para><para>(2) A transportation network company or a certified mechanic shall perform an initial safety inspection on each personal vehicle prior to approving it for use as a personal vehicle. The inspection shall include inspection of at least the following components and such components shall be in good working order:</para><para>(a) Foot brakes;</para><para>(b) Parking or emergency brakes;</para><para>(c) Steering mechanism;</para><para>(d) Windshield;</para><para>(e) Rear window and other glass;</para><para>(f) Windshield wipers;</para><para>(g) Headlights;</para><para>(h) Tail lights;</para><para>(i) Turn indicator lights;</para><para>(j) Stop lights;</para><para>(k) Front seat adjustment mechanism;</para><para>(l) The opening, closing, and locking capability of doors;</para><para>(m) Horn;</para><para>(n) Speedometer;</para><para>(o) Bumpers;</para><para>(p) Muffler and exhaust system;</para><para>(q) Tire conditions, including tread depth;</para><para>(r) Interior and exterior rear-view mirrors; and</para><para>(s) Safety belts for driver and passengers.</para><para>(3) Annually thereafter, a driver shall obtain such an inspection and approval of the driver's personal vehicle in order to continue its use as a personal vehicle. A driver shall maintain proof of the current inspection.</para><para>(4) A transportation network company shall make the initial and annual inspection reports available to the commission upon request.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB629, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>