<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id159" statutenumber="75-128"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>75-128</statuteno><catchline id="id162">Hearings; when held; filing fee.</catchline><para>(1) It is hereby declared to be the policy of the Legislature that all matters presented to the commission be heard and determined without delay. All matters requiring a hearing shall be set for hearing at the earliest practicable date and in no event, except for good cause shown, which showing shall be recited in the order, shall the time fixed for hearing be more than six months after the date of filing of the application, complaint, or petition on which such hearing is to be had. Except in case of an emergency and upon a motion to proceed with less than a quorum made by all parties and supported by a showing of clear and convincing evidence of such emergency and benefit to all parties, a quorum of the commission shall hear all matters set for hearing. Except as otherwise provided in the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act or section 75-121 and except for good cause shown, a decision of the commission shall be made and filed within thirty days after completion of the hearing or after submission of affidavits in nonhearing proceedings.</para><para>(2) In the case of any proceeding upon which a hearing is held, the transcript of testimony shall be prepared and submitted to the commission prior to entry of an order, except that it shall not be necessary to have prepared prior to a commission decision the transcripts of testimony on hearings involving noncontested proceedings and hearings involving emergency rate applications under section 75-121.</para><para>(3) For each application, complaint, or petition filed with the commission, except those filed under sections 75-303.01 to 75-303.03, the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act, or the State Natural Gas Regulation Act, the commission shall charge a filing fee to be determined by the commission, but in an amount not to exceed the sum of five hundred dollars, payable at the time of such filing. The commission shall also charge to persons regulated by the commission, except persons regulated under the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act or the State Natural Gas Regulation Act, a hearing fee to be determined by the commission, but in an amount not to exceed the sum of two hundred fifty dollars, for each half day of hearings if the person regulated by the commission files an application, complaint, or petition which necessitates a hearing.</para><para>(4) For each new tariff filed with the commission, except those filed under sections 75-301 to 75-322, the commission shall charge a fee not to exceed fifty dollars. This subsection does not apply to amendments to existing tariffs.</para><para>(5) The commission shall remit the fees received to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. I, &#167; 28, p. 1365; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 479, &#167; 8, p. 1479; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 604, &#167; 1, p. 2464; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 24, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 839, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1068, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 633, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 384, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 78, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 412, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 872, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 424, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 487; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB1, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 81. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act,</emphasis> see section 57-1401.</para><para><emphasis>State Natural Gas Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>On any matter heard by an examiner, a decision should be filed within thirty days after oral argument before the commission. Ready Mix, Inc. v. Nebraska Railroads, 181 Neb. 697, 150 N.W.2d 275 (1967).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>