  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-369.07"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-369.07</statuteno><catchline>Summary order; hearing; procedure; final order; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) If no hearing is requested and none is ordered by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety, the summary order shall automatically become a final order after fifteen business days after receipt of the order pursuant to section 75-369.05.</para><para>(2) If a hearing is requested or ordered, the superintendent shall appoint as hearing officer an attorney licensed to practice law in Nebraska. Every hearing pursuant to sections 75-369.01 to 75-369.07 shall be conducted in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(3) Every hearing in an administrative proceeding under this section shall be public unless the hearing officer grants a request joined in by all the respondents that the hearing be conducted privately.</para><para>(4) Upon agreement by all the parties any time before or during the hearing under this section, the hearing officer may compromise, mitigate, or aggravate any civil penalty. In determining the amount of the civil penalty, the hearing officer shall consider the appropriateness of the civil penalty in light of the gravity of the violation and the good faith of such violator in attempting to achieve compliance after notification of the violation.</para><para>(5) The hearing officer, within ten days after the conclusion of the hearing, shall make written findings of fact and conclusions of law to the superintendent. Such findings of fact and conclusions of law shall not be binding upon the superintendent.</para><para>(6) If a hearing is requested or ordered, the superintendent, after notice of and opportunity for hearing to all interested persons, may modify or vacate the order or extend it until final determination.</para><para>(7) No final order or order after hearing may be returned by the superintendent without (a) appropriate notice to all interested persons, (b) opportunity for hearing to all interested persons, and (c) entry of written findings of fact and conclusions of law. Any order or decision of the superintendent may be appealed. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 358, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 