<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-362"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>75-362</statuteno><catchline>Federal regulations; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 75-362 to 75-369.07, unless the context otherwise
requires:</para>
<para>(1) Accident means:</para>
<para>(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subdivision, an occurrence
involving a commercial motor vehicle operating on a highway in interstate
or intrastate commerce which results in:</para>
<para>(i) A fatality;</para>
<para>(ii) Bodily injury to a person who, as a result of the injury, immediately
receives medical treatment away from the scene of the accident; or</para>
<para>(iii) One or more motor vehicles incurring disabling damage as a result
of the accident, requiring the motor vehicles to be transported away from
the scene by a tow truck or other motor vehicle.</para>
<para>(b) The term accident does not include:</para>
<para>(i) An occurrence involving only boarding and alighting from a stationary
motor vehicle; or</para>
<para>(ii) An occurrence involving only the loading or unloading of cargo;</para>
<para>(2) Bulk packaging means a packaging, other than a vessel or a barge,
including a transport vehicle or freight container, in which hazardous materials
are loaded with no intermediate form of containment and which has:</para>
<para>(a) A maximum capacity greater than one hundred nineteen gallons as
a receptacle for a liquid;</para>
<para>(b) A maximum net mass greater than eight hundred eighty-two pounds
and a maximum capacity greater than one hundred nineteen gallons as a receptacle
for a solid; or</para>
<para>(c) A water capacity greater than one thousand pounds as a receptacle
for a gas as defined in 49 C.F.R. 173.115;</para>
<para>(3) Cargo tank means a bulk packaging that:</para>
<para>(a) Is a tank intended primarily for the carriage of liquids or gases
and includes appurtenances, reinforcements, fittings, and closures;</para>
<para>(b) Is permanently attached to or forms a part of a motor vehicle or
is not permanently attached to a motor vehicle but which, by reason of its
size, construction, or attachment to a motor vehicle, is loaded or unloaded
without being removed from the motor vehicle; and</para>
<para>(c) Is not fabricated under a specification for cylinders, intermediate
bulk containers, multi-unit tank-car tanks, portable tanks, or tank cars;</para>
<para>(4) Cargo tank motor vehicle means a motor vehicle with one or more
cargo tanks permanently attached to or forming an integral part of the motor
vehicle;</para>
<para>(5) Commercial enterprise means any business activity relating to or
based upon the production, distribution, or consumption of goods or services;</para>
<para>(6) Commercial motor vehicle means any self-propelled or towed motor
vehicle used on a highway in interstate commerce or intrastate commerce to
transport passengers or property when the vehicle:</para>
<para>(a) Has a gross vehicle weight rating or gross combination weight rating
or gross vehicle weight or gross combination weight of ten thousand one pounds
or more, whichever is greater;</para>
<para>(b) Is designed or used to transport more than eight passengers, including
the driver, for compensation;</para>
<para>(c) Is designed or used to transport more than fifteen passengers, including
the driver, and is not used to transport passengers for compensation; or</para>
<para>(d) Is used in transporting material found to be hazardous and such
material is transported in a quantity requiring placarding pursuant to section
75-364;</para>
<para>(7) Compliance review means an onsite examination of motor carrier operations,
such as drivers' hours of service, maintenance and inspection, driver qualification,
commercial driver's license requirements, financial responsibility, accidents,
hazardous materials, and other safety and transportation records to determine
whether a motor carrier meets the safety fitness standard. A compliance review
may be conducted in response to a request to change a safety rating, to investigate
potential violations of safety regulations by motor carriers, or to investigate
complaints or other evidence of safety violations. The compliance review may
result in the initiation of an enforcement action with penalties;</para>
<para>(8) Disabling damage means damage which precludes departure of a motor
vehicle from the scene of the accident in its usual manner in daylight after
simple repairs.</para>
<para>(a) Inclusions: Damage to motor vehicles that could have been driven
but would have been further damaged if so driven.</para>
<para>(b) Exclusions:</para>
<para>(i) Damage which can be remedied temporarily at the scene of the accident
without special tools or parts;</para>
<para>(ii) Tire disablement without other damage even if no spare tire is
available;</para>
<para>(iii) Headlight or taillight damage; and</para>
<para>(iv) Damage to turnsignals, horn, or windshield wipers which makes them
inoperative;</para>
<para>(9) Driver means any person who operates any commercial motor vehicle;</para>
<para>(10) Elevated temperature material means a material which, when offered
for transportation or transported in a bulk packaging:</para>
<para>(a) Is in a liquid phase and at a temperature at or above two hundred
twelve degrees Fahrenheit;</para>
<para>(b) Is in a liquid phase with a flash point at or above one hundred
degrees Fahrenheit that is intentionally heated and offered for transportation
or transported at or above its flash point; or</para>
<para>(c) Is in a solid phase and at a temperature at or above four hundred
sixty-four degrees Fahrenheit;</para>
<para>(11) Employee means any individual, other than an employer, who is employed
by an employer and who in the course of his or her employment directly affects
commercial motor vehicle safety. Such term includes a driver of a commercial
motor vehicle, including an independent contractor while in the course of
operating a commercial motor vehicle, a mechanic, and a freight handler. Such
term does not include an employee of the United States, any state, any political
subdivision of a state, or any agency established under a compact between
states and approved by the Congress of the United States who is acting within
the course of such employment;</para>
<para>(12) Employer means any person engaged in a business affecting commerce
who owns or leases a commercial motor vehicle in connection with that business
or assigns employees to operate it. Such term does not include the United
States, any state, any political subdivision of a state, or an agency established
under a compact between states approved by the Congress of the United States;</para>
<para>(13) Exempt motor carrier means a person engaged in transportation exempt
from economic regulation under 49 U.S.C. 13506. An exempt motor carrier is
subject to the safety regulations adopted in sections 75-362 to 75-369.07;</para>
<para>(14) Farm vehicle driver means a person who drives only a commercial
motor vehicle that is controlled and operated by a farmer as a private motor
carrier of property;</para>
<para>(15) Farmer means any person who operates a farm or is directly involved
in the cultivation of land, crops, or livestock which:</para>
<para>(a) Are owned by that person; or</para>
<para>(b) Are under the direct control of that person;</para>
<para>(16) Fatality means any injury which results in the death of a person
at the time of the motor vehicle accident or within thirty days after the
accident;</para>
<para>(17) Fertilizer and agricultural
chemical application and distribution equipment means:</para>
<para>(a) Self-propelled or
towed equipment, designed and used exclusively to apply commercial fertilizer,
as that term is defined in section 81-2,162.02, chemicals, or related products
to agricultural soil and crops; or</para><para>(b) Towed equipment designed and used exclusively
to carry commercial fertilizer, as that term is defined in section 81-2,162.02,
chemicals, or related products for use on agricultural soil and crops, which
are equipped with implement or floatation tires;</para><para>(18) For-hire motor carrier means a person engaged
in the transportation of goods or passengers for compensation;</para>
<para>(19) Gross combination weight
means the sum of the empty weight of a motor vehicle plus the total weight
of any load carried thereon and the empty weight of the towed unit or units
plus the total weight of any load carried on such towed unit or units;</para>
<para>(20) Gross combination weight
rating means the value specified by the manufacturer as the loaded weight
of a combination (articulated) motor vehicle. In the absence of a value specified
by the manufacturer, gross combination weight rating will be determined by
adding either the gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight of the
motor vehicle plus the gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight
of the towed unit or units;</para>
<para>(21) Gross vehicle weight
means the sum of the empty weight of a motor vehicle plus the total weight
of any load carried thereon;</para>
<para>(22) Gross vehicle weight
rating means the value specified by the manufacturer as the loaded weight
of a single motor vehicle. In the absence of such value specified by the manufacturer
or the absence of any marking of such value on the vehicle, the gross vehicle
weight rating shall be determined from the sum of the axle weight ratings
of the vehicle or the sum of the tire weight ratings as marked on the sidewall
of the tires, whichever is greater. In the absence of any tire sidewall marking,
the tire weight ratings shall be determined for the specified tires from any
of the publications of any of the organizations listed in 49 C.F.R. 571.119;</para>
<para>(23) Hazardous material means
a substance or material that the Secretary of the United States Department
of Transportation has determined is capable of posing an unreasonable risk
to health, safety, and property when transported in commerce and has designated
as hazardous under 49 U.S.C. 5103. The term includes hazardous substances,
hazardous wastes, marine pollutants, elevated temperature materials, materials
designated as hazardous in the Hazardous Materials Table, 49 C.F.R. 172.101,
and materials that meet the defining criteria for hazard classes and divisions
in 49 C.F.R. part 173;</para>
<para>(24) Hazardous substance means
a material, including its mixtures and solutions, that is listed in 49 C.F.R.
172.101, Appendix A, List Of Hazardous Substances and Reportable Quantities,
and is in a quantity, in one package, which equals or exceeds the reportable
quantity listed in 49 C.F.R. 172.101, Appendix A. This definition does not
apply to petroleum products that are lubricants or fuels or to mixtures or
solutions of hazardous substances if in a concentration less than that shown
in the table in 49 C.F.R. 171.8 under the definition of hazardous substance
based on the reportable quantity specified for the materials listed in 49
C.F.R. 172.101, Appendix A;</para>
<para>(25) Hazardous waste means
any material that is subject to the hazardous waste manifest requirements
of the United States Environmental Protection Agency specified in 40 C.F.R.
262;</para>
<para>(26) Highway means the entire
width between the boundary limits of any street, road, avenue, boulevard,
or way which is publicly maintained when any part thereof is open to the use
of the public for purposes of vehicular travel;</para>
<para>(27) Interstate commerce means
trade, traffic, or transportation provided in the furtherance of a commercial
enterprise in the United States:</para>
<para>(a) Between a place in a state and a place outside of such state, including
a place outside of the United States;</para>
<para>(b) Between two places in a state through another state or a place outside
of the United States; or</para>
<para>(c) Between two places in a state as part of trade, traffic, or transportation
originating or terminating outside the state or the United States;</para>
<para>(28) Intrastate commerce means
any trade, traffic, or transportation provided in the furtherance of a commercial
enterprise between any place in the State of Nebraska and any other place
in Nebraska and not through any other state;</para>
<para>(29) Marine pollutant means
a material which is listed in the Hazardous Materials Table, 49 C.F.R. 172.101,
Appendix B, as a marine pollutant (see 49 C.F.R. 171.4 for applicability to
marine pollutants) and, when in a solution or mixture of one or more marine
pollutants, is packaged in a concentration which equals or exceeds:</para>
<para>(a) Ten percent by weight of the solution or mixture for materials listed
in 49 C.F.R. 172.101, Appendix B; or</para>
<para>(b) One percent by weight of the solution or mixture for materials that
are identified as severe marine pollutants in the Hazardous Materials Table,
49 C.F.R. 172.101, Appendix B;</para>
<para>(30) Motor carrier means a
for-hire motor carrier or a private motor carrier. The term includes a motor
carrier's agents, officers, and representatives as well as employees responsible
for hiring, supervising, training, assigning, or dispatching of drivers and
employees concerned with the installation, inspection, and maintenance of
motor vehicle equipment or accessories. This definition includes the terms
employer and exempt motor carrier;</para>
<para>(31) Motor vehicle means any
vehicle, truck, truck-tractor, trailer, or semitrailer propelled or drawn
by mechanical power except (a) farm tractors, (b) vehicles which run only
on rails or tracks, and (c) road and general-purpose construction and maintenance
machinery which by design and function is obviously not intended for use on
a public highway, including, but not limited to, motor scrapers, earthmoving
equipment, backhoes, trenchers, motor graders, compactors, tractors, bulldozers,
bucket loaders, ditchdigging apparatus, asphalt spreaders, leveling graders,
power shovels, and crawler tractors;</para>
<para>(32) Nonbulk packaging means
a packaging which has:</para>
<para>(a) A maximum capacity of one hundred nineteen gallons or less as a
receptacle for a liquid;</para>
<para>(b) A maximum net mass of eight hundred eighty-two pounds or less and
a maximum capacity of one hundred nineteen gallons or less as a receptacle
for a solid; or</para>
<para>(c) A water capacity of one thousand pounds or less as a receptacle
for a gas as defined in 49 C.F.R. 173.115;</para>
<para>(33) Out-of-service order
means a declaration by an authorized enforcement officer of a federal, state,
Canadian, Mexican, or local jurisdiction that a driver, a commercial motor
vehicle, or a motor carrier operation is out of service pursuant to 49 C.F.R.
386.72, 392.5, 392.9a, 395.13,
or 396.9, or compatible laws or the North American Uniform Out-of-Service
Criteria;</para>
<para>(34) Packaging means a receptacle
and any other components or materials necessary for the receptacle to perform
its containment function in conformance with the minimum packing requirements
of Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations. For radioactive materials
packaging, see 49 C.F.R. 173.403;</para>
<para>(35) Person means any individual,
partnership, association, corporation, business trust, or any other organized
group of individuals;</para>
<para>(36) Principal place of business
means the single location designated by the motor carrier, normally its headquarters,
for purposes of identification. The motor carrier must make records required
by the regulations referred to in sections 75-363 to 75-369.07 and this section
available for inspection at this location within forty-eight hours, Saturdays,
Sundays, and state or federal holidays excluded, after a request has been
made by an officer of the Nebraska State Patrol;</para>
<para>(37) Private motor carrier
means a person who provides transportation of property or passengers by commercial
motor vehicle and is not a for-hire motor carrier;</para>
<para>(38) Safety audit means an
examination of a motor carrier's operations to provide educational and technical
assistance on drivers' hours of service, maintenance and inspection, driver
qualification, commercial driver's license requirements, financial responsibility,
accidents, hazardous materials, and other safety and transportation records
to determine whether a motor carrier meets the safety fitness standard. The
purpose of a safety audit is to gather critical safety data needed to make
an assessment of the carrier's safety performance and basic safety management
controls. Safety audits do not result in safety ratings; and</para>
<para>(39) Tank means a container,
consisting of a shell and heads, that forms a pressure-tight vessel having
openings designed to accept pressure-tight fittings or closures, but excludes
any appurtenances, reinforcements, fittings, or closures.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB725, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>