<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id63"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="75-333"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>75-333</statuteno><catchline>Transportation network company insurance; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning on September 1, 2015, a transportation network company and a participating driver shall maintain transportation network company insurance as provided in this section. Unless otherwise specified, the following requirements shall apply to transportation network company insurance during the engaged stage and during the passengers on board stage:</para><para>(a) Primary liability coverage in the amount of at least one million dollars for death, personal injury, and property damage; and</para><para>(b) Uninsured and underinsured motorist coverage for both the driver and passengers in the amounts required by the Uninsured and Underinsured Motorist Insurance Coverage Act.</para><para>(2) The requirements for the coverage required by this section may be satisfied by any of the following:</para><para>(a) Transportation network company insurance maintained by a participating driver;</para><para>(b) Transportation network company insurance maintained by a transportation network company; or</para><para>(c) Any combination of subdivisions (2)(a) and (b) of this section.</para><para>(3) The insurer providing transportation network company insurance under this section shall have the duty to defend and indemnify the insured.</para><para>(4) An insurance policy required under sections 75-332 to 75-341 shall be placed with an authorized Nebraska insurer or with a surplus-lines insurer pursuant to Chapter 44.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB629, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uninsured and Underinsured Motorist Insurance Coverage Act,</emphasis> see section 44-6401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>