<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-104"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>75-104</statuteno><catchline>Commissioners; salary; commissioners and employees; expenses; when allowed.</catchline><para>(1) Until January 4, 2007, the annual salary of each commissioner shall be fifty thousand dollars. Commencing January 4, 2007, the annual salary of each commissioner shall be seventy-five thousand dollars.</para><para>(2) Each commissioner shall be entitled to receive from the state his or her mileage expenses incurred while traveling in the line of duty to and from his or her residence to the office of the Public Service Commission in Lincoln pursuant to the following conditions:</para><para>(a) The Public Service Commission has adopted and promulgated rules and regulations establishing guidelines for allowable reimbursement of such mileage expenses, except that such mileage rate shall not exceed the mileage rate established by the Department of Administrative Services pursuant to section 81-1176;</para><para>(b) The request for such reimbursement falls within such guidelines; and</para><para>(c) The total amounts authorized for such reimbursement of mileage expenses in any fiscal year does not cause the total expenses to exceed the total funds appropriated to the program established for commissioners' expenses. In addition thereto, the commissioners, executive director, clerks, and other employees of the commission shall be reimbursed for expenses, including the cost of transportation while traveling on the business of the commission, to be paid in the same manner as other requests for payment or reimbursement from the state. In computing the cost of transportation for the commissioners, executive director, clerks, and other employees, no mileage or other traveling expense shall be requested or allowed unless sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 are strictly complied with.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. I, &#167; 4, p. 1355; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 477, &#167; 1, p. 1473; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 603, &#167; 1, p. 2464; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1389, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 311, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 872, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 826, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 43, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 503, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 872, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 16, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 956, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 817, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 82. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>