<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id237" statutenumber="75-366"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>75-366</statuteno><catchline id="id240">Enforcement powers.</catchline><para>For the purpose of enforcing Chapter 75, article 3, any officer of the Nebraska State Patrol may, upon demand, inspect the accounts, records, and equipment of any motor carrier or shipper. Any officer of the Nebraska State Patrol shall have the authority to enforce the federal motor carrier safety regulations, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2021, and federal hazardous materials regulations, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2021, and is authorized to enter upon, inspect, and examine any and all lands, buildings, and equipment of any motor carrier, any shipper, and any other person subject to the federal Interstate Commerce Act, the federal Department of Transportation Act, and other related federal laws and to inspect and copy any and all accounts, books, records, memoranda, correspondence, and other documents of a motor carrier, a shipper, and any other person subject to Chapter 75, article 3, for the purposes of enforcing Chapter 75, article 3. To promote uniformity of enforcement, the carrier enforcement division of the Nebraska State Patrol shall cooperate and consult with the Public Service Commission and the Division of Motor Carrier Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 301, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 538, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 424, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 93, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 480, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB35, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB313, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB929, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB79, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB149, &#167; 23. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>