<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id145">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id147" statutenumber="75-118"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>75-118</statuteno><catchline id="id150">Commission;
duties.</catchline><para>The commission shall:</para>
<para>(1) Fix all necessary rates, charges, and regulations governing
and regulating the transportation, storage, or handling of household goods
and passengers by any common carrier in Nebraska intrastate commerce;</para>
<para>(2) Make all necessary classifications of household goods
that may be transported, stored, or handled by any common carrier in Nebraska
intrastate commerce, such classifications applying to and being the same for
all common carriers;</para>
<para>(3) Prevent and correct the unjust discriminations set forth
in section 75-126;</para>
<para>(4) Enforce all statutes and commission regulations pertaining
to rates and, if necessary, institute actions in the appropriate court of
any county in which the common carrier involved operates except actions instituted
pursuant to sections 75-140 and 75-156 to 75-158. All suits shall be brought
and penalties recovered in the name of the state by or under the direction
of the Attorney General; and</para>
<para>(5) Enforce the
Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act and the State Natural Gas Regulation
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. I, &#167; 18, p. 1360; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 78, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 424, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB1, &#167; 17.</para><effectivedate>November 23, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Natural Gas Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Evidence of the existing rates for services as established by the Interstate Commerce Commission constitutes prima facie evidence of the reasonableness of the rates for the same services when performed in intrastate commerce in this state. Nebraska Railroads of Omaha v. Nebco, Inc., 194 Neb. 322, 231 N.W.2d 505 (1975).</para><para>The Nebraska Public Service Commission is without jurisdiction or authority to fix rates and charges for motor vehicle carriers transporting livestock in intrastate commerce. Livestock Carriers Div. of M. C. Assn. v. Midwest Packers Traf. Assn., 191 Neb. 1, 213 N.W.2d 443 (1973).</para><para>This section referred to in decision to the effect that the State Railway Commission is empowered to fix joint line rates. Howard McLean Co. v. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R.R. Co., 187 Neb. 30, 187 N.W.2d 300 (1971).</para><para>Railway Commission has a duty to prescribe necessary rates and classification of freight. Ready Mix, Inc. v. Nebraska Railroads, 181 Neb. 697, 150 N.W.2d 275 (1967).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>