<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id128" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-364">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id130">75-364</statuteno><catchline id="id131">Additional federal
motor carrier regulations; provisions adopted; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1)
The parts, subparts, and sections of Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations
listed below, or any other parts, subparts, and sections referred to by such
parts, subparts, and sections, in existence and effective as of January 1, 2010, are adopted as part of Nebraska law and,
except as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, shall be applicable
to all motor carriers whether engaged in interstate or intrastate commerce,
drivers of such motor carriers, and vehicles of such motor carriers:</para>
<para>(a) Part 107 - Hazardous Materials Program Procedures, subpart F-Registration
Of Cargo Tank And Cargo Tank Motor Vehicle Manufacturers, Assemblers, Repairers,
Inspectors, Testers, and Design Certifying Engineers;</para>
<para>(b) Part 107 - Hazardous Materials Program Procedures, subpart G-Registration
Of Persons Who Offer Or Transport Hazardous Materials; </para>
<para>(c) Part 171 - General Information, Regulations, And Definitions;</para>
<para>(d) Part 172 - Hazardous Materials Table, Special Provisions, Hazardous
Materials Communications, Emergency Response Information, and Training Requirements;</para>
<para>(e) Part 173 - Shippers - General Requirements For Shipments And Packagings;</para>
<para>(f) Part 177 - Carriage By Public Highway;</para>
<para>(g) Part 178 - Specifications For Packagings; and</para>
<para>(h) Part 180 - Continuing Qualification And Maintenance Of Packagings.</para>
<para>(2) Agricultural operations exceptions:</para>
<para>(a) The transportation of an agricultural product other than a Class
2 material (Compressed Gases) as defined in 49 C.F.R. 171.8, over roads, other
than the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways, between fields
of the same farm, is excepted from subsection (1) of this section when:</para>
<para>(i) The agricultural product is transported by a farmer who is an intrastate
private motor carrier; and</para>
<para>(ii) The movement of the agricultural product conforms to all other
laws in effect on or before July 1, 1998, and 49 C.F.R. 173.24, 173.24a, and
173.24b;</para>
<para>(b) The transportation of an agricultural product to or from a farm,
within one hundred fifty miles of the farm, is excepted from the requirements
in 49 C.F.R. part 172, subparts G (emergency response information) and H (training),
and from the specific packaging requirements of subsection (1) of this section
when:</para>
<para>(i) The agricultural product is transported by a farmer who is an intrastate
private motor carrier;</para>
<para>(ii) The total amount of agricultural product being transported on a
single vehicle does not exceed:</para>
<para>(A) Sixteen thousand ninety-four pounds of ammonium nitrate fertilizer
properly classed as Division 5.1, PGIII, in a bulk packaging; or</para>
<para>(B) Five hundred two gallons for liquids or gases, or five thousand
seventy pounds for solids, of any other agricultural product;</para>
<para>(iii) The packaging conforms to the requirements of state law and is
specifically authorized for transportation of the agricultural product by
state law and such state law has been in effect on or before July 1, 1998;
and</para>
<para>(iv) Each person having any responsibility for transporting the agricultural
product or preparing the agricultural product for shipment has been instructed
in the applicable requirements of the parts, subparts, and sections of Title
49 of the Code of Federal Regulations adopted in this section; and</para>
<para>(c) Formulated liquid agricultural products in specification packagings
of fifty-eight-gallon capacity or less, with closures manifolded to a closed
mixing system and equipped with positive dry disconnect devices, may be transported
by a private motor carrier between a final distribution point and an ultimate
point of application or for loading aboard an airplane for aerial application.</para>
<para>(3) Exceptions for nonspecification packagings used in intrastate transportation:</para>
<para>(a) Nonspecification cargo tanks for petroleum products: Notwithstanding
requirements for specification packagings in 49 C.F.R. part 173, subpart F,
and 49 C.F.R. parts 178 and 180, a nonspecification metal tank permanently
secured to a transport vehicle and protected against leakage or damage in
the event of a turnover, having a capacity of less than three thousand five
hundred gallons, may be used by an intrastate motor carrier for transportation
of a flammable liquid petroleum product in accordance with subdivision (c)
of this subsection;</para>
<para>(b) Permanently secured nonbulk tanks for petroleum products: Notwithstanding
requirements for specification packagings in 49 C.F.R. part 173, subpart F,
and 49 C.F.R. parts 178 and 180, a nonspecification metal tank permanently
secured to a transport vehicle and protected against leakage or damage in
the event of a turnover, having a capacity of less than one hundred nineteen
gallons, may be used by an intrastate motor carrier for transportation of
a flammable liquid petroleum product in accordance with subdivision (c) of
this subsection; and</para>
<para>(c) Additional requirements: A packaging used pursuant to subdivision
(a) or (b) of this subsection must:</para>
<para>(i) Be operated by an intrastate motor carrier and in use as a packaging
for hazardous material before July 1, 1998;</para>
<para>(ii) Be operated in conformance with the requirements of the State of
Nebraska;</para>
<para>(iii) Be specifically authorized by state law in effect before July
1, 1998, for use as a packaging for the hazardous material being transported
and by 49 C.F.R. 173.24, 173.24a, and 173.24b;</para>
<para>(iv) Be offered for transportation and transported in conformance with
all other applicable requirements of the hazardous material regulations;</para>
<para>(v) Not be used to transport a flammable cryogenic liquid, hazardous
substance, hazardous waste, or marine pollutant as defined in 49 C.F.R. 171.8;
and</para>
<para>(vi) On and after July 1, 2000, for a tank authorized under subdivision
(a) or (b) of this subsection, conform to all requirements in 49 C.F.R. part
180, except for 49 C.F.R. 180.405(g), in the same manner as required for a
United States Department of Transportation specification MC306 cargo tank
motor vehicle.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Agricultural product means a hazardous material, other than a hazardous
waste, whose end use directly supports the production of an agricultural commodity,
including, but not limited to, a fertilizer, pesticide, soil amendment, or
fuel. An agricultural product is limited to a material in Class 3 (Flammable
Liquids), Class 8 (Corrosives), or Class 9 (Miscellaneous), Division 2.1 (Flammable
Gas), Division 2.2 (Nonflammable Gas), Division 5.1 (Oxidizers), or Division
6.1 (Poisons), or an ORM-D material (Consumer Commodity), as defined in 49
C.F.R. 171.8;</para>
<para>(b) Bulk package means a packaging, including a transport vehicle or
freight container, in which hazardous materials are loaded with no other intermediate
form of containment and which has:</para>
<para>(i) A maximum capacity greater than one hundred nineteen gallons as
a receptacle for a liquid;</para>
<para>(ii) A maximum net mass greater than eight hundred eighty-two pounds
and a maximum capacity greater than one hundred nineteen gallons as a receptacle
for a solid; or</para>
<para>(iii) A water capacity greater than one thousand pounds as a receptacle
for a gas, pursuant to standards set forth in 49 C.F.R. 173.115;</para>
<para>(c) Farmer means a person engaged in the production or raising of crops,
poultry, or livestock; and</para>
<para>(d) Private motor carrier means a person or persons engaged in the transportation
of persons or product while in commerce, but not for hire.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 301, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 538, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 884, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 854, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 410, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1061, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 461, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 938, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 722, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1056, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 161, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 375, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 499, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 480, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 878, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 83, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB239, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB48, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB331, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>