<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-302"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>75-302</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of sections 75-301 to 75-322 and in all rules
and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission pursuant to such
sections, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Attended services
means an attendant or caregiver accompanying a minor or persons who are physically,
mentally, or developmentally disabled and unable to travel or wait without
assistance or supervision;</para><para>(2) Carrier
enforcement division means the carrier enforcement division of the Nebraska
State Patrol or the Nebraska State Patrol;</para>
<para>(3) Certificate means a certificate
of public convenience and necessity issued under Chapter 75, article 3, to
common carriers by motor vehicle;</para>
<para>(4) Civil penalty means any
monetary penalty assessed by the commission or carrier enforcement division
due to a violation of Chapter 75, article 3, or section 75-126 as such section
applies to any person or carrier specified in Chapter 75, article 3; any term,
condition, or limitation of any certificate or permit issued pursuant to Chapter
75, article 3; or any rule, regulation, or order of the commission, the Division
of Motor Carrier Services, or the carrier enforcement division issued pursuant
to Chapter 75, article 3;</para>
<para>(5) Commission means the Public
Service Commission;</para>
<para>(6) Common carrier means any
person who or which undertakes to transport passengers or household goods
for the general public in intrastate commerce by motor vehicle for hire, whether
over regular or irregular routes, upon the highways of this state;</para>
<para>(7) Contract carrier means
any motor carrier which transports passengers or household goods for hire
other than as a common carrier designed to meet the distinct needs of each
individual customer or a specifically designated class of customers without
any limitation as to the number of customers it can serve within the class;</para>
<para>(8) Division of Motor Carrier
Services means the Division of Motor Carrier Services of the Department of
Motor Vehicles;</para>
<para>(9) Highway means
the roads, highways, streets, and ways in this state;</para>
<para>(10) Household goods means personal effects and property used
or to be used in a dwelling, when a part of the equipment or supply of such
dwelling, and similar property as the commission may provide by regulation
if the transportation of such effects or property, is:</para>
<para>(a) Arranged and paid for by the householder, including transportation
of property from a factory or store when the property is purchased by the
householder with the intent to use in his or her dwelling; or</para>
<para>(b) Arranged and paid for by another party;</para>
<para>(11) Intrastate commerce means commerce between any place
in this state and any other place in this state and not in part through any
other state;</para>
<para>(12) Licensed care transportation
services means transportation provided by an entity licensed by the Department
of Health and Human Services as a child-caring agency as defined in section
71-1902 or child-placing agency as defined in such section or a child care
facility licensed under the Child Care Licensing Act to a client of the entity
or facility when the person providing transportation services also assists
and supervises the passenger or, if the client is a minor, to a family member
of a minor when it is necessary for agency or facility staff to accompany
or facilitate the transportation in order to provide necessary services and
support to the minor. Licensed care transportation services must be incidental
to and in furtherance of the social services provided by the entity or facility
to the transported client;</para><para>(13) Motor
carrier means any person other than a regulated motor carrier who or which
owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes to be operated any motor vehicle
used to transport passengers or property over any public highway in this state;</para>
<para>(14) Motor vehicle means any
vehicle, machine, tractor, trailer, or semitrailer propelled or drawn by mechanical
power and used upon the highways in the transportation of passengers or property
but does not include any vehicle, locomotive, or car operated exclusively
on a rail or rails;</para>
<para>(15) Permit means a permit
issued under Chapter 75, article 3, to contract carriers by motor vehicle;</para>
<para>(16) Person means any individual,
firm, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, company, association,
or joint-stock association and includes any trustee, receiver, assignee, or
personal representative thereof;</para>
<para>(17) Private carrier means
any motor carrier which owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes to be
operated a motor vehicle to transport passengers or property to or from its
facility, plant, or place of business or to deliver to purchasers its products,
supplies, or raw materials (a) when such transportation is within the scope
of and furthers a primary business of the carrier other than transportation
and (b) when not for hire. Nothing in sections 75-301 to 75-322 shall apply
to private carriers;</para>
<para>(18) Regulated motor carrier
means any person who or which owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes
to be operated any motor vehicle used to transport passengers, other than
those excepted under section 75-303, or household goods over any public highway
in this state;</para>
<para>(19) Residential care
means care for a minor or a person who is physically, mentally, or developmentally
disabled who resides in a residential home or facility regulated by the Department
of Health and Human Services, including, but not limited to, a foster home,
treatment facility, group home, or shelter;</para><para>(20) Residential care transportation services means
transportation services to persons in residential care when such residential
care transportation services and residential care are provided as part of
a services contract with the Department of Health and Human Services or pursuant
to a subcontract entered into incident to a services contract with the department;
and</para><para>(21) Supported transportation services means transportation services
to a minor or for a person who is physically, mentally, or developmentally
disabled when the person providing transportation services also assists and
supervises the passenger or transportation services to a family member of
a minor when it is necessary for provider staff to accompany or facilitate
the transportation in order to provide necessary services and support to the
minor. Supported transportation services must be provided as part of a services
contract with the Department of Health and Human Services or pursuant to a
subcontract entered into incident to a services contract with the department,
and the driver must meet department requirements for (a) training or experience
working with minors or persons who are physically, mentally, or developmentally
disabled, (b) training with regard to the specific needs of the client served,
(c) reporting to the department, and (d) age. Assisting and supervising the
passenger shall not necessarily require the person providing transportation
services to stay with the passenger after the transportation services have
been provided.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. III, &#167; 2, p. 1375; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 606, &#167; 1, p. 2467; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1370, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 78, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 464; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 412, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 424, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1069, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB358, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB112, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>April 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child Care Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1908.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The Nebraska Public Service Commission is without jurisdiction or authority to fix rates and charges for motor vehicle carriers transporting livestock in intrastate commerce. Livestock Carriers Div. of M. C. Assn. v. Midwest Packers Traf. Assn., 191 Neb. 1, 213 N.W.2d 443 (1973).</para><para>In considering an application for a permit as a contract carrier, the Nebraska State Railway Commission is required to weigh the special needs of shippers desiring contract service against the adequacy of existing common carrier service. Wells Fargo Armored Service Corp. v. Bankers Dispatch Corp., 188 Neb. 584, 198 N.W.2d 195 (1972).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>