<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-132.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-132.01</statuteno><catchline>Exclusive original jurisdiction; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding the provisions of section 75-131, the commission shall have exclusive original jurisdiction over any action concerning a violation of any provision of (a) the Automatic Dialing-Announcing Devices Act, the Emergency Telephone Communications Systems Act, the Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act, the Intrastate Pay-Per-Call Regulation Act, the Nebraska Telecommunications Regulation Act, the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act, the Telecommunications Relay System Act, or the Telephone Consumer Slamming Prevention Act by any person providing telecommunications service for a fee in Nebraska intrastate commerce pursuant to such acts or (b) sections 86-574 to 86-578 by an agency or political subdivision of the state.</para><para>(2) If the commission enters an order declining jurisdiction under subsection (1) of this section, any interested person may petition the district court of the county in which such alleged violation has occurred. If it appears to the court, after a hearing, that a provision of such acts or sections has been violated, the court may issue an injunction or other proper process to restrain the telecommunications company and its directors, officers, employees, or agents or the agency or political subdivision of the state from continuing such violation and may order additional relief. Any party to the case shall have the right to appeal the decision of the district court to the Court of Appeals under the rules provided by law for appeals in civil cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1285, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 827, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 488; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Automatic Dialing-Announcing Devices Act,</emphasis> see section 86-236.</para><para><emphasis>Emergency Telephone Communications Systems Act,</emphasis> see section 86-420.</para><para><emphasis>Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act,</emphasis> see section 86-442.</para><para><emphasis>Intrastate Pay-Per-Call Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 86-258.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Telecommunications Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 86-101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act,</emphasis> see section 86-316.</para><para><emphasis>Telecommunications Relay System Act,</emphasis> see section 86-301.</para><para><emphasis>Telephone Consumer Slamming Prevention Act,</emphasis> see section 86-201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>