<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id65" statutenumber="75-156"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>75-156</statuteno><catchline id="id68">Civil penalty; procedure; order; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to other penalties and relief provided by law, the Public Service Commission may, upon a finding that the violation is proven by clear and convincing evidence, assess a civil penalty of up to ten thousand dollars per day against any person, motor carrier, regulated motor carrier, common carrier, contract carrier, licensee, grain dealer, or grain warehouseman for each violation of (a) any provision of the laws of this state within the jurisdiction of the commission as enumerated in section 75-109.01, (b) any term, condition, or limitation of any certificate, permit, license, or authority issued by the commission pursuant to the laws of this state within the jurisdiction of the commission as enumerated in section 75-109.01, or (c) any rule, regulation, or order of the commission issued under authority delegated to the commission pursuant to the laws of this state within the jurisdiction of the commission as enumerated in section 75-109.01.</para><para>(2) In addition to other penalties and relief provided by law, the Public Service Commission may, upon a finding that the violation is proven by clear and convincing evidence, assess a civil penalty not less than one hundred dollars and not more than one thousand dollars against any jurisdictional utility for each violation of (a) any provision of the State Natural Gas Regulation Act, (b) any rule, regulation, order, or lawful requirement issued by the commission pursuant to the act, (c) any final judgment or decree made by any court upon appeal from any order of the commission, or (d) any term, condition, or limitation of any certificate issued by the commission issued under authority delegated to the commission pursuant to the act. The amount of the civil penalty assessed in each case shall be based on the severity of the violation charged. The commission may compromise or mitigate any penalty prior to hearing if all parties agree. In determining the amount of the penalty, the commission shall consider the appropriateness of the penalty in light of the gravity of the violation and the good faith of the violator in attempting to achieve compliance after notification of the violation is given.</para><para>(3) In addition to other penalties and relief provided by law, the Public Service Commission may, upon a finding that the violation is proven by clear and convincing evidence, assess a civil penalty of up to ten thousand dollars per day against any wireless carrier for each violation of the Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act or any rule, regulation, or order of the commission issued under authority delegated to the commission pursuant to the act.</para><para>(4) In addition to other penalties and relief provided by law, the Public Service Commission may, upon a finding that the violation is proven by clear and convincing evidence, assess a civil penalty of up to one thousand dollars against any person for each violation of the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act or the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles or any rule, regulation, or order of the commission issued under the authority delegated to the commission pursuant to either act. Each such violation shall constitute a separate violation with respect to each modular housing unit, manufactured home, or recreational vehicle, except that the maximum penalty shall not exceed one million dollars for any related series of violations occurring within one year from the date of the first violation.</para><para>(5) The civil penalty assessed under this section shall not exceed two million dollars per year for each violation except as provided in subsection (4) of this section. The amount of the civil penalty assessed in each case shall be based on the severity of the violation charged. The commission may compromise or mitigate any penalty prior to hearing if all parties agree. In determining the amount of the penalty, the commission shall consider the appropriateness of the penalty in light of the gravity of the violation and the good faith of the violator in attempting to achieve compliance after notification of the violation is given.</para><para>(6) Upon notice and hearing in accordance with this section and section 75-157, the commission may enter an order assessing a civil penalty of up to one hundred dollars against any person, firm, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, cooperative, or association for failure to file an annual report or pay the fee as required by section 75-116 and as prescribed by commission rules and regulations or for failure to register as required by section 86-125 and as prescribed by commission rules and regulations. Each day during which the violation continues after the commission has issued an order finding that a violation has occurred constitutes a separate offense. Any party aggrieved by an order of the commission under this section may appeal. The appeal shall be in accordance with section 75-136.</para><para>(7) When any person or party is accused of any violation listed in this section, the commission shall notify such person or party in writing (a) setting forth the date, facts, and nature of each act or omission upon which each charge of a violation is based, (b) specifically identifying the particular statute, certificate, permit, rule, regulation, or order purportedly violated, (c) that a hearing will be held and the time, date, and place of the hearing, (d) that in addition to the civil penalty, the commission may enforce additional penalties and relief as provided by law, and (e) that upon failure to pay any civil penalty determined by the commission, the penalty may be collected by civil action in the district court of Lancaster County.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 424, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1285, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 493; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1211, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 735, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 319, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB755, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB545, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB461, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act,</emphasis> see section 86-442.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1555.</para><para><emphasis>State Natural Gas Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1801.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles,</emphasis> see section 71-4601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>