<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-428"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-428</statuteno><catchline>Intersections; transfer facilities; duty to provide; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>Each owner of a railroad may cross, intersect, join, and unite its railroad with any other railroad at any point on its route and upon the grounds of the owner of such other railroad with the necessary turnouts, sidings, and switches and other conveniences in furtherance of the objects of its connection. Each owner of a railroad which is intersected by any new railroad shall unite with the owners of such new railroad to form such intersections and connections and grant the facilities specified in this section. If the two owners cannot agree upon the amount of compensation to be made therefor or the points and manner of such crossings and connections, they shall be ascertained and determined by the commission.</para><para>All owners of railroads in this state, at all points of connection, intersection, or crossing at grade of different railroads, where it is practicable, shall provide reasonable, ample, and equal facilities by track connection, passenger platforms, and otherwise, for transferring cars, passengers, and property between their respective roads without unreasonable delay. At any place where the tracks of the two owners are within five hundred feet apart, whether on the same grade or not, when it is practicable and deemed reasonably necessary, the commission, upon application of any interested person, may require such track connection. No owner shall discriminate in its rates or charges between such connecting lines or on freight coming over them, but no such owner shall be required to furnish to another owner its tracks, equipment, or terminal facilities without reasonable compensation. Each of the connecting lines shall pay its proportionate share for the building and maintenance of such track and switches as may be necessary to furnish the transfer facilities required by this section. In case they cannot agree on the amount which each line shall pay, the amount shall, upon application by either party, be determined and adjusted by the commission. When the commission has refused to require track connection as requested by the applicant, if the applicant agrees in writing to pay the cost of making and maintaining the track connection and offers adequate security, the commission shall order such track connection to be made by such owners whether the commission deems the track connection practicable or reasonably necessary or not. The railroad tracks, at the point where the connection is to be made, shall run within one mile of the corporate limits of any city or village.</para><para>Any owner of a railroad who fails or neglects to comply with the order within the time fixed shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. IV, &#167; 28, p. 1408; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 202; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 94. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 