<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-302"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-302</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 75-301 to 75-322 and in all rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission pursuant to such sections, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Carrier enforcement division means the carrier enforcement division of the Nebraska State Patrol or the Nebraska State Patrol;</para><para>(2) Certificate means a certificate of public convenience and necessity issued under Chapter 75, article 3, to common carriers by motor vehicle;</para><para>(3) Civil penalty means any monetary penalty assessed by the commission or carrier enforcement division due to a violation of Chapter 75, article 3, or section 75-126 as such section applies to any person or carrier specified in Chapter 75, article 3; any term, condition, or limitation of any certificate or permit issued pursuant to Chapter 75, article 3; or any rule, regulation, or order of the commission, the Division of Motor Carrier Services, or the carrier enforcement division issued pursuant to Chapter 75, article 3;</para><para>(4) Commission means the Public Service Commission;</para><para>(5) Common carrier means any person who or which undertakes to transport passengers or household goods for the general public in intrastate commerce by motor vehicle for hire, whether over regular or irregular routes, upon the highways of this state;</para><para>(6) Contract carrier means any motor carrier which transports passengers or household goods for hire other than as a common carrier designed to meet the distinct needs of each individual customer or a specifically designated class of customers without any limitation as to the number of customers it can serve within the class;</para><para>(7) Division of Motor Carrier Services means the Division of Motor Carrier Services of the Department of Motor Vehicles;</para><para>(8) Escort services means an attendant or caregiver accompanying a minor or persons who are physically, mentally, or developmentally disabled and unable to travel or wait without assistance or supervision;</para><para>(9) Highway means the roads, highways, streets, and ways in this state;</para><para>(10) Household goods means personal effects and property used or to be used in a dwelling, when a part of the equipment or supply of such dwelling, and similar property as the commission may provide by regulation if the transportation of such effects or property, is:</para><para>(a) Arranged and paid for by the householder, including transportation of property from a factory or store when the property is purchased by the householder with the intent to use in his or her dwelling; or</para><para>(b) Arranged and paid for by another party;</para><para>(11) Intrastate commerce means commerce between any place in this state and any other place in this state and not in part through any other state;</para><para>(12) Motor carrier means any person other than a regulated motor carrier who or which owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes to be operated any motor vehicle used to transport passengers or property over any public highway in this state;</para><para>(13) Motor vehicle means any vehicle, machine, tractor, trailer, or semitrailer propelled or drawn by mechanical power and used upon the highways in the transportation of passengers or property but does not include any vehicle, locomotive, or car operated exclusively on a rail or rails;</para><para>(14) Permit means a permit issued under Chapter 75, article 3, to contract carriers by motor vehicle;</para><para>(15) Person means any individual, firm, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, company, association, or joint-stock association and includes any trustee, receiver, assignee, or personal representative thereof;</para><para>(16) Private carrier means any motor carrier which owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes to be operated a motor vehicle to transport passengers or property to or from its facility, plant, or place of business or to deliver to purchasers its products, supplies, or raw materials (a) when such transportation is within the scope of and furthers a primary business of the carrier other than transportation and (b) when not for hire. Nothing in sections 75-301 to 75-322 shall apply to private carriers; and </para><para>(17) Regulated motor carrier means any person who or which owns, controls, manages, operates, or causes to be operated any motor vehicle used to transport passengers, other than those excepted under section 75-303, or household goods over any public highway in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. III, &#167; 2, p. 1375; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 606, &#167; 1, p. 2467; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1370, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 78, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 464; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 412, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 424, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1069, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB358, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>The Nebraska Public Service Commission is without jurisdiction or authority to fix rates and charges for motor vehicle carriers transporting livestock in intrastate commerce. Livestock Carriers Div. of M. C. Assn. v. Midwest Packers Traf. Assn., 191 Neb. 1, 213 N.W.2d 443 (1973).</para><para>In considering an application for a permit as a contract carrier, the Nebraska State Railway Commission is required to weigh the special needs of shippers desiring contract service against the adequacy of existing common carrier service. Wells Fargo Armored Service Corp. v. Bankers Dispatch Corp., 188 Neb. 584, 198 N.W.2d 195 (1972).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>