<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Service Commission" id="id170" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="75-363"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>75-363</statuteno><catchline id="id173">Federal motor carrier safety regulations; provisions adopted; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) The parts, subparts, and sections of Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations listed below, as modified in this section, or any other parts, subparts, and sections referred to by such parts, subparts, and sections, in existence and effective as of January 1, 2016, are adopted as Nebraska law.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this section, the regulations shall be applicable to:</para><para>(a) All motor carriers, drivers, and vehicles to which the federal regulations apply; and</para><para>(b) All motor carriers transporting persons or property in intrastate commerce to include:</para><para>(i) All vehicles of such motor carriers with a gross vehicle weight rating, gross combination weight rating, gross vehicle weight, or gross combination weight over ten thousand pounds;</para><para>(ii) All vehicles of such motor carriers designed or used to transport more than eight passengers, including the driver, for compensation, or designed or used to transport more than fifteen passengers, including the driver, and not used to transport passengers for compensation;</para><para>(iii) All vehicles of such motor carriers transporting hazardous materials required to be placarded pursuant to section 75-364; and</para><para>(iv) All drivers of such motor carriers if the drivers are operating a commercial motor vehicle as defined in section 60-465 which requires a commercial driver's license.</para><para>(3) The Legislature hereby adopts, as modified in this section, the following parts of Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations:</para><para>(a) Part 382 - CONTROLLED SUBSTANCES AND ALCOHOL USE AND TESTING;</para><para>(b) Part 385 - SAFETY FITNESS PROCEDURES;</para><para>(c) Part 386 - RULES OF PRACTICE FOR MOTOR CARRIER, INTERMODAL EQUIPMENT PROVIDER, BROKER, FREIGHT FORWARDER, AND HAZARDOUS MATERIALS PROCEEDINGS;</para><para>(d) Part 387 - MINIMUM LEVELS OF FINANCIAL RESPONSIBILITY FOR MOTOR CARRIERS;</para><para>(e) Part 390 - FEDERAL MOTOR CARRIER SAFETY REGULATIONS; GENERAL;</para><para>(f) Part 391 - QUALIFICATIONS OF DRIVERS AND LONGER COMBINATION VEHICLE (LCV) DRIVER INSTRUCTORS;</para><para>(g) Part 392 - DRIVING OF COMMERCIAL MOTOR VEHICLES;</para><para>(h) Part 393 - PARTS AND ACCESSORIES NECESSARY FOR SAFE OPERATION;</para><para>(i) Part 395 - HOURS OF SERVICE OF DRIVERS;</para><para>(j) Part 396 - INSPECTION, REPAIR, AND MAINTENANCE;</para><para>(k) Part 397 - TRANSPORTATION OF HAZARDOUS MATERIALS; DRIVING AND PARKING RULES; and</para><para>(l) Part 398 - TRANSPORTATION OF MIGRANT WORKERS.</para><para>(4) The provisions of subpart E - Physical Qualifications And Examinations of 49 C.F.R. part 391 - QUALIFICATIONS OF DRIVERS AND LONGER COMBINATION VEHICLE (LCV) DRIVER INSTRUCTORS shall not apply to any driver subject to this section who: (a) Operates a commercial motor vehicle exclusively in intrastate commerce; and (b) holds, or has held, a commercial driver's license issued by this state prior to July 30, 1996.</para><para>(5) The regulations adopted in subsection (3) of this section shall not apply to farm trucks registered pursuant to section 60-3,146 with a gross weight of sixteen tons or less. The following parts and sections of 49 C.F.R. chapter III shall not apply to drivers of farm trucks registered pursuant to section 60-3,146 and operated solely in intrastate commerce:</para><para>(a) All of part 391;</para><para>(b) Section 395.8 of part 395; and</para><para>(c) Section 396.11 of part 396.</para><para>(6) The following parts and subparts of 49 C.F.R. chapter III shall not apply to the operation of covered farm vehicles:</para><para>(a) Part 382 - CONTROLLED SUBSTANCES AND ALCOHOL USE AND TESTING;</para><para>(b) Part 391, subpart E - Physical Qualifications and Examinations;</para><para>(c) Part 395 - HOURS OF SERVICE OF DRIVERS; and</para><para>(d) Part 396 - INSPECTION, REPAIR, AND MAINTENANCE.</para><para>(7) Part 393 - PARTS AND ACCESSORIES NECESSARY FOR SAFE OPERATION and Part 396 - INSPECTION, REPAIR, AND MAINTENANCE shall not apply to fertilizer and agricultural chemical application and distribution equipment transported in units with a capacity of three thousand five hundred gallons or less.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section, intrastate motor carriers shall not include any motor carrier or driver excepted from 49 C.F.R. chapter III by section 390.3(f) of part 390.</para><para>(9)(a) Part 395 - HOURS OF SERVICE OF DRIVERS shall apply to motor carriers and drivers who engage in intrastate commerce as defined in section 75-362, except that no motor carrier who engages in intrastate commerce shall permit or require any driver used by it to drive nor shall any driver drive:</para><para>(i) More than twelve hours following eight consecutive hours off duty; or</para><para>(ii) For any period after having been on duty sixteen hours following eight consecutive hours off duty.</para><para>(b) No motor carrier who engages in intrastate commerce shall permit or require a driver of a commercial motor vehicle, regardless of the number of motor carriers using the driver's services, to drive, nor shall any driver of a commercial motor vehicle drive, for any period after:</para><para>(i) Having been on duty seventy hours in any seven consecutive days if the employing motor carrier does not operate every day of the week; or</para><para>(ii) Having been on duty eighty hours in any period of eight consecutive days if the employing motor carrier operates motor vehicles every day of the week.</para><para>(10) Part 395 - HOURS OF SERVICE OF DRIVERS, as adopted in subsections (3) and (9) of this section, shall not apply to drivers transporting agricultural commodities or farm supplies for agricultural purposes during planting and harvesting season when:</para><para>(a) The transportation of such agricultural commodities is from the source of the commodities to a location within a one-hundred-fifty-air-mile radius of the source of the commodities;</para><para>(b) The transportation of such farm supplies is from a wholesale or retail distribution point of the farm supplies to a farm or other location where the farm supplies are intended to be used which is within a one-hundred-fifty-air-mile radius of the wholesale or retail distribution point; or</para><para>(c) The transportation of such farm supplies is from a wholesale distribution point of the farm supplies to a retail distribution point of the farm supplies which is within a one-hundred-fifty-air-mile radius of the wholesale distribution point.</para><para>(11) 49 C.F.R. 390.21 - Marking of self-propelled CMVs and intermodal equipment shall not apply to farm trucks and farm truck-tractors registered pursuant to section 60-3,146 and operated solely in intrastate commerce.</para><para>(12) 49 C.F.R. 392.9a - Operating authority shall not apply to Nebraska motor carriers operating commercial motor vehicles solely in intrastate commerce.</para><para>(13) No motor carrier shall permit or require a driver of a commercial motor vehicle to violate, and no driver of a commercial motor vehicle shall violate, any out-of-service order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 301, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 224, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 884, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 140; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 854, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 410, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1061, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 461, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 938, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 722, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1056, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 161, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 375, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 499, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 480, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 878, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 83, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 271; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB239, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB845, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB48, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB331, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB725, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB212, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB35, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB313, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB929, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Violation of section,</emphasis> penalty, see section 75-367.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>