<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" statutenumber="75-903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-903</statuteno><catchline>Grain dealer; licensure; requirements; fee.</catchline><para>All grain dealers doing business in this state shall be licensed by the commission. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. To procure and maintain a license, each grain dealer shall:</para><para>(1) Pay an annual fee of sixty dollars which shall be due on or before the date established by the commission for each license and a registration fee not to exceed forty dollars per year for each vehicle used by such licensee to transport grain. Such fees shall be paid to the State Treasurer and credited to the General Fund;</para><para>(2) Equip each vehicle used by the licensee for grain transportation with a commercial license plate registered with the Department of Motor Vehicles, except that a licensee who resides in another state shall license such vehicles according to the laws of his or her state of residence;</para><para>(3) Affix a grain dealer plate issued by the commission to each vehicle used by the licensee;</para><para>(4) File security which may be a bond issued by a corporate surety company and payable to the commission, an irrevocable letter of credit, or a certificate of deposit, subject to the approval of the commission, for the benefit of any producer or owner within this state who files a valid claim arising from a sale to or purchase from a grain dealer. The security shall be in the amount of thirty-five thousand dollars or seven percent of grain purchases or exchanges by the grain dealer in the grain dealer's preceding fiscal year, whichever is greater, not to exceed three hundred thousand dollars. Amounts used in the calculation of the security shall include all direct delivery grain purchases and exchanges valued on the date delivery is made. Amounts used in the calculation of the security shall not include any transactions in which direct delivery grain is exchanged for a post-direct delivery storage position and the post-direct delivery storage position is created by an in-store transfer on the same date as the delivery of the direct delivery grain. Such security shall be furnished on the condition that the licensee will pay for any grain purchased upon demand, not later than thirty days after the date of the last shipment of any contract. The liability of the surety shall cover purchases and sales made or arranged by the grain dealer during the time the bond is in force. A grain dealer's bond filed with the commission shall be in continuous force and effect until canceled by the surety. The liability of the surety on any bond required by this section shall not accumulate for each successive license period during which the bond is in force; and</para><para>(5) File a reviewed or audited fiscal year-end financial statement prepared either by an independent certified public accountant or by an independent public accountant who holds a permit granted by the Nebraska State Board of Public Accountancy. If licensing as an individual, the financial statement shall be prepared in accordance with Other Comprehensive Basis of Accountancy, as filed with the board, for a personal financial statement, using historical cost and accrual basis of accounting. If licensing as a partnership, corporation, or limited liability company, the financial statement shall be prepared in accordance with accounting principles generally accepted. The financial statement shall include: (a) A statement of income showing profit or loss; (b) a balance sheet; (c) a statement of cash flow; (d) a statement of proprietor's capital or retained earnings; (e) the volume and dollar value of the grain purchases the licensee made in Nebraska during the fiscal year; (f) the volume and dollar value of transactions in which direct delivery grain is exchanged for a post-direct delivery storage position and the post-direct delivery storage position is not created by an in-store transfer on the same date as the delivery of the direct delivery grain; and (g) the accountant's certification, assurances, opinions, and comments and the notes with respect to the financial statement. If the volume and dollar value of the grain purchases is not reported, the grain dealer shall file the maximum grain dealer security as required by the Grain Dealer Act.</para><para>If an applicant for a grain dealer license is a wholly owned subsidiary of a parent company and such a financial statement is not prepared for the subsidiary, the parent company shall submit its reviewed or audited fiscal year-end financial statement and shall execute an unconditional guarantee agreement as prescribed by the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 389, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 507, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1123, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 201; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 735, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 52, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 439, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>