<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id100"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="75-332"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>75-332</statuteno><catchline>Driver; disclosure by transportation network company; contents; acknowledgment; notice to lienholder; record.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to permitting a person to act as a driver, a transportation network company shall disclose in writing to each participating driver:</para><para>(a) The insurance coverage, the limits of liability, and any deductible amounts that the transportation network company maintains while the driver uses a personal vehicle in connection with a transportation network company's online-enabled application or platform;</para><para>(b) That in many personal automobile insurance policies, the driver's policy does not provide coverage for damage to the vehicle used by the driver, uninsured and underinsured motorist coverage, and other first-party claims from the moment the driver logs on to the transportation network company's online-enabled application or platform to the moment the driver logs off the transportation network company's online-enabled application or platform. The driver should contact his or her insurer to determine coverage;</para><para>(c) That if the driver is planning to use a vehicle that has a lien against it to provide service in connection with a transportation network company, the driver of the vehicle must notify the lienholder at least seven days prior to using the vehicle to provide such service that the driver intends to use the vehicle to provide service in connection with a transportation network company by complying with subsection (3) of this section; and</para><para>(d) That the driver is responsible to know the laws, rules, and regulations that govern the service he or she provides in connection with a transportation network company.</para><para>(2) The transportation network company shall make the disclosure required by subdivision (1)(c) of this section a distinctive part of the driver's terms of service and shall require a separate acknowledgment of this disclosure by each driver by electronic or handwritten signature.</para><para>(3) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish a procedure to confirm that drivers have notified lienholders as required by subdivision (1)(c) of this section. The commission shall keep a record of such confirmation for at least five years and shall make such record available to lienholders.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB629, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>