
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id324"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Service Commission" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="75-324"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>75-324</statuteno><catchline>Operation of transportation network company; permit required; application; contents; commission; duties.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall operate a transportation network company in Nebraska without first obtaining a permit from the commission. The application for a permit shall be in writing, under oath, submitted to the commission, and accompanied by the fee required under section 75-305. A duly authorized official of the applicant who possesses the full power and authority to make binding representations on the applicant's behalf shall subscribe to the oath on the application. The application shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) The legal name of the applicant;</para><para>(b) Any name under which the applicant will or does conduct business in Nebraska;</para><para>(c) The applicant's primary business address and telephone number;</para><para>(d) A copy of the articles of organization or certificate to transact business in Nebraska;</para><para>(e) The name, address, and telephone number of the applicant's registered agent in Nebraska; and</para><para>(f) A statement that the applicant agrees to adhere to the statutes of Nebraska and to the rules and regulations of the commission regulating transportation network companies.</para><para>(2)(a) The commission shall review the application for completeness and verify the information submitted. If the commission finds any information incomplete or inaccurate, the commission shall notify the applicant and give the applicant the opportunity to complete the application.</para><para>(b) If an applicant is duly certified or permitted to operate a transportation network company in at least one other state, the commission shall, within sixty days after receiving a complete application, issue a permit to the applicant if the applicant meets the requirements of sections 75-323 to 75-343.</para><para>(c) If an applicant is not duly certified or permitted to operate a transportation network company in at least one other state, the applicant shall bear the burden of demonstrating that (i) the applicant has sufficient financial resources to provide transportation network company services in the proposed service territory, (ii) the applicant has sufficient technical competency to provide transportation network company services in the proposed service territory, and (iii) the applicant has sufficient managerial resources to provide transportation network company services in the proposed service territory. If the requirements of subdivisions (i) through (iii) of this subdivision are met and the applicant has satisfactorily provided all of the information in the application required under this section, the commission shall, within ninety days after receiving a complete application, issue a permit to the applicant if the applicant meets the requirements of sections 75-323 to 75-343.</para><para>(3) A participating driver contracting with a transportation network company holding a valid permit from the commission shall not be required to obtain a permit or certificate from the commission when driving pursuant to the terms of the contract with the transportation network company.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB629, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>