<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id6" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="37-915"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>37-915</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Youth Conservation Program;
legislative findings and intent.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para>
<para>(a) Every Nebraska
youth should be encouraged to reach his or her full potential, but that many
youth require guidance and support to reach their goals and make positive
changes in their lives;</para><para>(b) Conserving and developing natural resources and enhancing and
maintaining environmentally important land and water through the employment
of Nebraska's at-risk youth is beneficial not only to the youth by providing
them with education and employment opportunities but also to the state's economy
and environment; and</para><para>(c) The Nebraska Youth Conservation Program will offer Nebraska
a unique opportunity to meet the goals of increasing understanding and appreciation
of the environment and helping at-risk youth become productive adults.</para>
<para>(2) It is the
intent of the Legislature:</para><para>(a) That Nebraska Youth Conservation Program
participants complete their participation in the program having learned good
work habits, positive attitudes, and broadened professional horizons;</para>
<para>(b) That the
program combine academic, environmental, and job skills training with personal
growth opportunities in order to develop productive youth who can make substantial
contributions as Nebraska workers and citizens; and</para><para>(c) To ensure that the
Game and Parks Commission coordinate and collaborate with partners from other
state and federal government agencies, political subdivisions, postsecondary
educational institutions, and community organizations and enter into agreements
with such partners for the benefit of the program, as appropriate.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB549, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>