<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id139" statutenumber="37-440"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-440</statuteno><catchline id="id142">Display and
issuance of permits; where procured; clerical fee.</catchline><para>(1) The
commission shall prescribe the type and design of permits and the method for displaying permits on the driver's
side of the windshield of motor vehicles. The commission may provide
for the electronic issuance of permits and may enter into contracts to procure
necessary services and supplies for the electronic issuance of permits.</para>
<para>(2) The permits may be procured from the central and district offices
of the commission, at areas of the Nebraska state park system where commission
offices are maintained, from self-service vending stations at designated park
areas, from designated commission employees, through Internet sales from the
commission's web site, from appropriate offices of county government, and
from various private persons, firms, or corporations designated by the commission
as permit agents. The commission and county offices or private persons, firms,
or corporations designated by the commission as permit agents shall be entitled
to collect and retain a fee of not more than one dollar, as established by the commission
pursuant to section 37-327, for each permit as reimbursement for the clerical
work of issuing the permits and remitting therefor. The commission shall be
entitled to collect and retain a fee of one dollar for each permit sold through
its web site as reimbursement for the clerical work and postage associated
with issuing the permit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 81, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 723, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 34; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-1108; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 150; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB421, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>