<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id44">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id46" statutenumber="37-411"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>37-411</statuteno><catchline id="id49">Hunting, fishing,
or fur harvesting without permit; unlawful; exceptions; violations; penalties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Unless issued a permit as required in the Game Law, it
shall be unlawful:</para>
<para>(a) For any resident of Nebraska who is sixteen years of age
or older or any nonresident of Nebraska to engage in fur harvesting or possess
any fur-bearing animal or raw fur. Nonresident
fur-harvesting permits may be issued only to residents of states which issue
similar permits to residents of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(b) For any resident of Nebraska who is sixteen years of age
or older or any nonresident of Nebraska to hunt or possess any kind of game
birds, game animals, or crows;</para>
<para>(c) For any person who is sixteen years of age or older to
hunt or possess any migratory waterfowl without a federal migratory bird hunting
stamp and a Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp as required under the Game
Law and rules and regulations of the commission; or</para>
<para>(d) For any person who is sixteen years of age or older to
take any kind of fish, bullfrog, snapping turtle, tiger salamander, or mussel
from the waters of this state or possess the same except as provided in section
37-402. All nonresident anglers under sixteen years of age shall be accompanied
by a person who has a valid fishing permit.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be unlawful for a nonresident to hunt or possess
any kind of game birds or game animals, to take any kind of fish, mussel,
turtle, or amphibian, or to harvest fur with a resident permit illegally obtained.</para>
<para>(3) It shall be unlawful for anyone to do or attempt to do
any other thing for which a permit is required by the Game Law without first
obtaining such permit and paying the fee required.</para>
<para>(4) Any nonresident who hunts or has in his or her possession
any wild mammal or wild bird shall first have a nonresident hunting permit
as required under the Game Law and rules and regulations of the commission.</para>
<para>(5) Any nonresident who takes or has in his or her possession
any wild turtle, mussel, or amphibian shall first have a nonresident fishing
permit as required under the Game Law and rules and regulations of the commission.</para>
<para>(6) Except as provided in this section and sections 37-407
and 37-418, it shall be unlawful for any nonresident to trap or attempt to
trap or to harvest fur or attempt to harvest fur from any wild mammal.</para>
<para>(7)(a) Any person violating this section shall be guilty of
a Class II misdemeanor and, upon conviction, shall be fined at least fifty
dollars for failure to hold the appropriate stamp under subdivision (1)(c)
of this section, at least one hundred dollars for failure to hold a fishing
permit, at least one hundred fifty dollars for failure to hold a small game,
fur-harvesting, paddlefish, or deer permit, at least two hundred fifty dollars
for failure to hold an antelope permit, at least five hundred dollars for
failure to hold an elk permit, and at least one thousand dollars for failure
to hold a mountain sheep permit.</para>
<para>(b) If the offense is failure to hold a hunting, fishing,
fur-harvesting, deer, turkey, or antelope permit as required, unless issuance
of the required permit is restricted so that permits are not available, the
court shall require the offender to purchase the required permit and exhibit
proof of such purchase to the court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 112, II, &#167; 13, p. 412; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 37-213; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 89, &#167; 4, p. 292; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 72, &#167; 3, p. 301; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 37-213; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 37-213; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 102, &#167; 2, p. 280; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 139, &#167; 5, p. 466; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 149, &#167; 2, p. 565; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 150, &#167; 4, p. 571; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 154, &#167; 1, p. 580; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 169, &#167; 2, p. 502; </para>
<para>Laws 1961, c. 171, &#167; 1, p. 511; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 194, &#167; 2, p. 592; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 197, &#167; 1, p. 598; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 216, &#167; 5, p. 581; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 777, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 331, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 176; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 435, &#167; 1; </para>
<para>Laws 1979, LB 553, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 72, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 105, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 171, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 34, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 127, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 37-213; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 121; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 404, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB41, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Predatory animals,</emphasis> subject to destruction, see sections 23-358 and 81-2,236.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Legislature was constitutionally free to determine by what authority licenses should be imposed upon those desiring to hunt and fish. State ex rel. Stevens v. Nickerson, 97 Neb. 837, 151 N.W. 981 (1915).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>