<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<sectno id="id12">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id13" statutenumber="37-559"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id15">37-559</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Destruction of
predators; permit required; when;
mountain lion; actions authorized.</catchline><para>(1)
Any farmer or rancher owning or operating a farm or ranch may destroy or have
destroyed any predator preying on livestock or poultry or causing other agricultural
depredation on land owned or controlled by him or her without a permit issued
by the commission. For purposes
of this subsection, predator means a badger, bobcat, coyote, gray fox, long-tailed
weasel, mink, opossum, raccoon, red fox, or skunk.</para>
<para>(2) Any farmer
or rancher owning or operating a farm or ranch, or his or her agent, may kill
a mountain lion immediately without prior notice to or permission from the
commission if he or she encounters a mountain lion and the mountain lion is
in the process of stalking, killing, or consuming livestock on the farmer's
or rancher's property. The farmer or rancher or his or her agent shall be
responsible for immediately notifying the commission and arranging with the
commission to transfer the mountain lion to the commission.</para>
<para>(3) Any person
shall be entitled to defend himself or herself or another person without penalty
if, in the presence of such person, a mountain lion stalks, attacks, or shows
unprovoked aggression toward such person or another person.</para>
<para>(4) This section shall not
be construed to allow a farmer or rancher or his or her agent to destroy
or have destroyed species which are protected by the
Nongame and Endangered Species Conservation Act or rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under
the act, the federal Endangered Species Act of 1973, as amended, 16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.,
the federal Fish and Wildlife Coordination Act, as amended, 16 U.S.C. 661
et seq., the federal Bald and Golden Eagle Protection Act, as amended, 16
U.S.C. 668 et seq., the federal Migratory Bird Treaty Act, as amended, 16
U.S.C. 703 et seq., or federal regulations under such federal
acts.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 279; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB836, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nongame and Endangered Species Conservation Act,</emphasis> see section 37-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>