<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id102" statutenumber="37-426"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-426</statuteno><catchline id="id105">Taking birds, animals, and aquatic organisms; stamps; when required; exhibit on request; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section:</para><para>(a) No resident of Nebraska sixteen years of age or older and no nonresident of Nebraska regardless of age shall hunt, harvest, or possess any game bird, upland game bird, game animal, or fur-bearing animal unless, at the time of such hunting, harvesting, or possessing, such person has an unexpired habitat stamp as prescribed by the rules and regulations of the commission prior to the time of hunting, harvesting, or possessing such bird or animal;</para><para>(b) No resident or nonresident of Nebraska shall take or possess any aquatic organism requiring a Nebraska fishing permit, including any fish, bullfrog, snapping turtle, tiger salamander, or mussel, unless, at the time of such taking or possessing, such person has an unexpired aquatic habitat stamp as prescribed by the rules and regulations of the commission prior to the time of taking or possessing a fish, bullfrog, snapping turtle, tiger salamander, or mussel; and</para><para>(c) No resident of Nebraska sixteen years of age or older and no nonresident of Nebraska regardless of age shall hunt, harvest, or possess any migratory waterfowl unless, at the time of such hunting, harvesting, or possessing, such person has an unexpired Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp as prescribed by the rules and regulations of the commission prior to the time of hunting, harvesting, or possessing such migratory waterfowl.</para><para>(2)(a) The commission may issue a lifetime habitat stamp upon application and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a lifetime habitat stamp shall be twenty times the fee required in subsection (5) of this section for an annual habitat stamp. Payment of such fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application. A replacement lifetime habitat stamp may be issued if the original is lost or destroyed. The fee for a replacement shall be not more than five dollars, as established by the commission.</para><para>(b) The commission may issue a lifetime Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp upon application and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a lifetime Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp shall be twenty times the fee required in subsection (5) of this section for an annual Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp. Payment of such fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application. A replacement Nebraska lifetime migratory waterfowl stamp may be issued if the original is lost or destroyed. The fee for a replacement shall be not more than five dollars, as established by the commission.</para><para>(c) The commission may issue a lifetime aquatic habitat stamp upon application and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a lifetime aquatic habitat stamp shall be twenty times the fee required in subdivision (5)(c) of this section for an annual aquatic habitat stamp. Payment of such fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application. A replacement lifetime aquatic habitat stamp may be issued if the original is lost or destroyed. The fee for a replacement shall be not more than five dollars, as established by the commission.</para><para>(3)(a) The commission may issue a multiple-year habitat stamp upon application and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a multiple-year habitat stamp shall be established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327 and shall not be more than the number of years the stamp is valid times the fee required in subsection (5) of this section for an annual habitat stamp. Payment of such fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application. A replacement multiple-year habitat stamp may be issued if the original is lost or destroyed.</para><para>(b) The commission may issue a multiple-year Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp upon application and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a multiple-year Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp shall be established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327 and shall not be more than the number of years the stamp is valid times the fee required in subsection (5) of this section for an annual Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp. Payment of such fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application. A replacement Nebraska multiple-year migratory waterfowl stamp may be issued if the original is lost or destroyed.</para><para>(c) The commission may issue a multiple-year aquatic habitat stamp upon application and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a multiple-year aquatic habitat stamp shall be established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327 and shall not be more than the number of years the stamp is valid times the fee required in subsection (5) of this section for an annual aquatic habitat stamp. Payment of such fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application. A replacement multiple-year aquatic habitat stamp may be issued if the original is lost or destroyed.</para><para>(4) Habitat stamps are not required for holders of limited permits issued under section 37-455. Aquatic habitat stamps are not required (a) when a fishing permit is not required, (b) for holders of permits pursuant to section 37-424, or (c) for holders of lifetime fishing permits or lifetime combination hunting and fishing permits purchased prior to January 1, 2006. Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamps are not required for hunting, harvesting, or possessing any species other than ducks, geese, or brant. For purposes of this section, a showing of proof of the electronic issuance of a stamp by the commission shall fulfill the requirements of this section.</para><para>(5)(a) Any person to whom a stamp has been issued shall, immediately upon request, exhibit evidence of issuance of the stamp to any officer. Any person hunting, fishing, harvesting, or possessing any game bird, upland game bird, game animal, or fur-bearing animal or any aquatic organism requiring a fishing permit in this state without evidence of issuance of the appropriate stamp shall be deemed to be without such stamp.</para><para>(b) An annual habitat stamp shall be issued upon the payment of a fee of twenty-five dollars per stamp. A multiple-year habitat stamp shall be issued in conjunction with a multiple-year hunting permit or a multiple-year combination hunting and fishing permit at a fee of not more than twenty-five dollars times the number of years the multiple-year permit is valid.</para><para>(c) An aquatic habitat stamp shall be issued in conjunction with each fishing permit for a fee of fifteen dollars per stamp for annual fishing permits, three-day fishing permits, or combination hunting and fishing permits, a fee of not more than fifteen dollars times the number of years the multiple-year fishing permit or a multiple-year combination hunting and fishing permit is valid, and a fee of not more than twenty times the fee required for an annual aquatic habitat stamp for lifetime fishing or combination hunting and fishing permits. The fee established under section 37-407 for a one-day fishing permit shall include an aquatic habitat stamp. One dollar from the sale of each one-day fishing permit shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Aquatic Habitat Fund.</para><para>(d) An annual Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp shall be issued upon the payment of a fee of not less than ten dollars and not more than sixteen dollars per stamp. A multiple-year Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp may only be issued in conjunction with a multiple-year hunting permit or a multiple-year combination hunting and fishing permit at a fee of not more than the annual fee times the number of years the multiple-year permit is valid.</para><para>(e) The commission shall establish the fees pursuant to section 37-327.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 861, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 72, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 170, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 340, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 19, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-216.01; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB41, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB745, &#167; 9. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>