<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-488"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-488</statuteno><catchline>Privileges conferred by license; game birds, requirements; marking; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The licensee of any licensed game breeding and controlled shooting area may take or authorize to be taken, within the season fixed and designated and in such numbers as provided in sections 37-484 to 37-496, game birds as specified in rules and regulations of the commission and released on licensed areas during the shooting season as provided in such sections.</para><para>(2) All game birds that are released for shooting purposes shall be at least twelve weeks of age before liberation date.</para><para>(3) All game birds released for hunting on a controlled shooting area shall be marked by banding, toe clipping, or some other method approved by the commission prior to release. Any game bird killed by a hunter on a controlled shooting area which does not have a band shall be banded prior to being transported from such area. The licensee shall pay to the commission the sum of not less than ten cents and not more than fifteen cents, as established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327, for each band used to mark game birds.</para><para>(4) The licensee shall furnish a receipt to each hunter taking game birds on the controlled shooting area which shall indicate the name of the hunter, the date of the taking, the sex and species of the game birds taken, and the name of the controlled shooting area.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 152, &#167; 5, p. 493; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 766, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 446, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-905; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 198. </para></source></law></legaldoc>