<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id15" statutenumber="37-614"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>37-614</statuteno><catchline id="id18">Revocation and
suspension of permits; grounds.</catchline><para>(1) When a person pleads
guilty to or is convicted of any violation listed in this subsection, the
court shall, in addition to any other penalty, revoke and require the immediate
surrender of all permits to hunt, fish, and harvest fur held by such person
and suspend the privilege of such person to hunt, fish, and harvest fur and
to purchase such permits for a period of not less than one nor more than three
years. The court shall consider the number and severity of the violations
of the Game Law in determining the length of the revocation and suspension.
The violations shall be:</para>
<para>(a) Carelessly or purposely killing or causing injury to livestock with
a firearm or bow and arrow;</para>
<para>(b) Purposely taking or having in his or her possession a number of
game animals, game fish, game birds, or fur-bearing animals exceeding twice
the limit established pursuant to section 37-314;</para>
<para>(c) Taking any species of wildlife protected by the Game Law during
a closed season in violation of section 37-502;</para>
<para>(d) Resisting or obstructing any officer or any employee of the commission
in the discharge of his or her lawful duties in violation of section 37-609;
and</para>
<para>(e) Being a habitual offender of the Game Law.</para>
<para>(2) When a person pleads guilty to or is convicted of any violation
listed in this subsection, the court may, in addition to any other penalty,
revoke and require the immediate surrender of all permits to hunt, fish, and
harvest fur held by such person and suspend the privilege of such person to
hunt, fish, and harvest fur and to purchase such permits for a period of not
less than one nor more than three years. The court shall consider the number
and severity of the violations of the Game Law in determining the length of
the revocation and suspension. The violations shall be:</para>
<para>(a) Hunting, fishing, or fur harvesting without a permit in violation
of section 37-411;</para>
<para>(b) Hunting from a vehicle, aircraft, or boat in violation of section
37-513, 37-514, 37-515, 37-535, or 37-538; and</para>
<para>(c) Knowingly taking any wildlife on private land without permission
in violation of section 37-722.</para>
<para>(3) When a person pleads guilty to or is convicted of any violation
of the Game Law, the rules and regulations
of the commission, or commission
orders not listed in subsection (1) or (2) of this section, the
court may, in addition to any other penalty, revoke and require the immediate
surrender of all permits to hunt, fish, and harvest fur held by such person
and suspend the privilege of such person to hunt, fish, and harvest fur and
to purchase such permits for a period of one year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 304; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB5, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB499, &#167; 16.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>