<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id76">
<sectno id="id77">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id78" statutenumber="37-415"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id80">37-415</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Lifetime fur-harvesting, fishing, hunting,
or combination permit; fees; replacement; rules and regulations.</catchline>
<para>(1) The commission may issue to any Nebraska resident a lifetime fur-harvesting, fishing, hunting,
or combination hunting and fishing permit upon application and payment of
the appropriate fee. The fee
for a resident lifetime fur-harvesting permit shall be not more than two hundred
ninety-nine dollars, the fee for a resident lifetime hunting permit
shall be not more than two hundred ninety-nine dollars, the fee for a resident
lifetime fishing permit shall be not more than three hundred forty-five dollars
plus the cost of a lifetime aquatic habitat stamp, and the fee for a resident
lifetime combination hunting and fishing permit shall be not more than five
hundred ninety-eight dollars plus the cost of a lifetime aquatic habitat stamp,
as such fees are established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327.
Payment of the fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application.</para>
<para>(2) A resident lifetime permit shall not be made invalid by
reason of the holder subsequently residing outside the state.</para>
<para>(3) The commission may issue to any nonresident a lifetime
fishing, hunting, or combination hunting and fishing permit upon application
and payment of the appropriate fee. The fee for a nonresident lifetime hunting
permit shall be not more than twelve hundred fifty dollars, the fee for a
nonresident lifetime fishing permit shall be not more than eight hundred fifty
dollars plus the cost of a lifetime aquatic habitat stamp, and the fee for
a nonresident lifetime combination hunting and fishing permit shall be not
more than two thousand dollars plus the cost of a lifetime aquatic habitat
stamp, as such fees are established by the commission pursuant to section
37-327. Payment of the fee shall be made in a lump sum at the time of application.</para>
<para>(4) A replacement resident or nonresident lifetime permit
may be issued if the original has been lost or destroyed. The fee for a replacement
shall be not less than one dollar and fifty cents and not more than five dollars,
as established by the commission.</para>
<para>(5) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to carry out this section and sections 37-416 and 37-417. Such rules and regulations
may include, but need not be limited to, establishing fees which vary based
on the age of the applicant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 173, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-202.01; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>