<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-724"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-724</statuteno><catchline>Hunting; privately owned land; posting; where placed.</catchline><para>The landowner or tenant who is the principal operator of a farm or ranch may post such property to allow for hunting, by written permission only, in the following ways:</para><para>(1) With signs reading Hunting By Written Permission Only. The signs shall be at least eleven by fourteen inches with letters at least one and one-half inches high and shall be placed at each field entrance and at intervals of not more than four hundred forty yards and at all property corners. The name and address of the owner or tenant shall be on each sign; or</para><para>(2) By placing identifying red paint marks on trees or posts in the following manner:</para><para>(a) The identifying red paint marks shall be vertical lines of at least eight inches in length and three inches in width on trees or on any post which is not metal, or if metal posts are used, the identifying red paint marks shall completely surround the post and extend down at least eight inches from the top of the metal post. The bottom edge of the identifying red paint marks shall be not less than three feet and not more than five feet off the ground;</para><para>(b) The identifying red paint marks shall be readily visible to any person approaching the property; and</para><para>(c) The identifying red paint marks shall be placed at each field entrance and shall not be more than one hundred yards apart.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 199, &#167; 2, p. 646; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 284, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-213.03; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 338; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 32. </para></source></law></legaldoc>