<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id62"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id64" statutenumber="37-462"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id66">37-462</statuteno><catchline id="id67">Taxidermists; permit; fees; renewal; authorizations; records; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to perform taxidermy services on any game for any person other than himself or herself without first obtaining a taxidermist permit from the commission. The permit shall be conspicuously posted at the location where taxidermy services are performed. The application for the permit shall include the applicant's social security number. The annual fee for such permit shall be not more than eight dollars and fifty cents, as established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327. Such permit shall expire on December 31 of the year for which issued.</para><para>(2) Original application for a taxidermist permit shall be made to the commission upon such form and containing such information as may be prescribed by the commission. The application shall include the address of the premises where taxidermist services will be provided and a statement of the applicant's qualifications and experience as a taxidermist. Requests for renewals of existing permits shall be made by letter to the commission not later than thirty days preceding the expiration date of the permit.</para><para>(3) A permit shall authorize a taxidermist to (a) receive, transport, hold in custody or possession, mount, or otherwise prepare game and return such game to the legal owner or his or her agent from whom received and (b) sell game which he or she has lawfully acquired and mounted. Such mounted specimens may be placed on consignment by the taxidermist for sale and may be held by such consignee for the purpose of sale.</para><para>(4) Permitholders shall keep accurate records of operations, on a calendar-year basis, showing the names and addresses of persons from and to whom specimens of game or the nests or eggs of such game were received or delivered, the number and species, and the dates of receipt and delivery. In addition to other records required by this subsection, the permitholder shall maintain proper invoices or other documents confirming his or her lawful acquisition of game being held by him or her, including game which is on consignment for sale. Permitholders shall retain such records not less than one year following the end of the calendar year covered by the records. Such records shall be available for inspection by duly authorized employees or agents of the commission during normal business hours.</para><para>(5) Any violation of this section shall constitute a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 356, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 175; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 88; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-211.01; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 172; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>