<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-729"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-729</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 37-729 to 37-736:</para><para>(1) Land includes roads, water, watercourses, private ways, and buildings, structures, and machinery or equipment thereon when attached to the realty;</para><para>(2) Owner includes tenant, lessee, occupant, or person in control of the premises;</para><para>(3) Recreational purposes includes, but is not limited to, any one or any combination of the following: Hunting, fishing, swimming, boating, camping, picnicking, hiking, pleasure driving, nature study, waterskiing, winter sports, and visiting, viewing, or enjoying historical, archaeological, scenic, or scientific sites, or otherwise using land for purposes of the user; and</para><para>(4) Charge means the amount of money asked in return for an invitation to enter or go upon the land.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 193, &#167; 8, p. 590; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-1008; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 343.</para></source><annotation><para>Spectating at a youth football game is not a recreational purpose under this section. Iodence v. City of Alliance, 270 Neb. 59, 700 N.W.2d 562 (2005).</para><para>Subsection (3) of this section is not unconstitutionally vague. Dykes v. Scotts Bluff Cty. Ag. Socy., Inc., 260 Neb. 375, 617 N.W.2d 817 (2000).</para><para>The viewing of livestock exhibits at a county fair is not a recreational purpose under subsection (3) of this section. Dykes v. Scotts Bluff Cty. Ag. Socy., Inc., 260 Neb. 375, 617 N.W.2d 817 (2000).</para><para>Recreation Liability Act does not apply to independent indoor recreational facilities, including indoor swimming pools. Cassio v. Creighton University, 233 Neb. 160, 446 N.W.2d 704 (1989).</para><para>Recreation Liability Act, the provisions of which apply to urban as well as rural areas, is not limited to private persons; governmental subdivisions are "owners" within meaning of section 37-1003. Gallagher v. Omaha Public Power Dist., 225 Neb. 354, 405 N.W.2d 571 (1987).</para><para>A city park which provides camping, picnic, and sports facilities is a recreational facility within the meaning of the act. Garreans v. City of Omaha, 216 Neb. 487, 345 N.W.2d 309 (1984).</para><para>In order to constitute a charge within the meaning of the act, money must be paid for the right to enter the facility. Garreans v. City of Omaha, 216 Neb. 487, 345 N.W.2d 309 (1984).</para><para>The term "owner", as used in the Recreation Liability Act, sections 37-1001 et seq., includes a political subdivision as well as a private person. The term "recreational purposes", as used in the Recreation Liability Act, sections 37-1001 et seq., is broad enough to include the normal activities afforded by public parks. Watson v. City of Omaha, 209 Neb. 835, 312 N.W.2d 256 (1981).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>