<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id129"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id131" statutenumber="37-4,104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id133">37-4,104</statuteno><catchline id="id134">Commercial fishing permit; issuance; fees; expiration; tag requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Individuals shall apply to the commission on forms prescribed by the commission for an annual commercial fishing permit and shall not take or sell fish as prescribed in this section and section 37-543 before receiving such permit.</para><para>(2) The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and collect fees from residents and nonresidents for all commercial fishing permits as follows:</para><para>(a) Not more than ninety-eight dollars for residents and not more than one hundred ninety-five dollars and fifty cents for nonresidents for each commercial fishing permit permitting the legal use of five hundred lineal feet of seine or fraction thereof, and five hundred lineal feet of trammel net or fraction thereof, and ten hoop nets without wings, and permitting the use of one helper if the helper is in the same boat as the person holding the permit;</para><para>(b) Not more than twenty-nine dollars for residents and not more than sixty dollars for nonresidents for each additional five hundred lineal feet of seine or trammel net or fraction thereof; and</para><para>(c) Not more than three dollars and fifty cents for residents and not more than seven dollars for nonresidents for each additional hoop net, wing net, or fish trap or other device, permitted by the commission and used under the commercial fishing permit.</para><para>(3) All commercial fishing permits shall expire at midnight on December 31 following their issuance. All money received by the commission shall be deposited as provided in section 37-323. The commission shall furnish to any permitholder without cost a tag numbered and stamped so as to show the year of issuance and for what issued for each net, seine, or device, and it shall be unlawful to use such net, seine, or device without first having procured such tag and fastened it to such net, seine, or device.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 214; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167;  15.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
