<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-414"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-414</statuteno><catchline>Bow hunter education program; certificate; issuance; required; when.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall establish and administer a bow hunter education program consisting of a minimum of (a) ten hours of classroom instruction or (b) independent study on the part of the student sufficient to pass an examination given by the commission followed by such student's participation in a minimum of four hours of practical instruction. The program shall provide instruction in the safe use of bow hunting equipment, the fundamentals of bow hunting, shooting and hunting techniques, game identification, conservation management, and hunter ethics. When establishing such a program, the commission shall locate and train volunteers as bow hunter education instructors. The commission shall issue a certificate of successful completion to any person who satisfactorily completes a bow hunter education program established by the commission and shall print, purchase, or otherwise acquire materials necessary for effective program operation. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for carrying out and administering such program.</para><para>(2) A person twelve through twenty-nine years of age who is hunting antelope, deer, elk, or mountain sheep with a bow and arrow pursuant to any provision of sections 37-447 to 37-453 shall have on his or her person (a) proof of successful completion of a bow hunter education course issued by his or her state or province of residence or by an accredited program recognized by the commission or (b) the appropriate hunting permit and an apprentice hunter education exemption certificate issued and enforced by the commission pursuant to section 37-413.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 403, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 107, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-105; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB690, &#167;  2.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
