<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id31" statutenumber="37-438"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>37-438</statuteno><catchline id="id34">Annual, temporary, and disabled veteran permits; fees.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall devise annual, temporary, and disabled veteran permits.</para><para>(2) The annual permit may be purchased by any person and shall be valid through December 31 in the year for which the permit is issued. The fee for the annual permit for a resident motor vehicle shall be not more than thirty-five dollars per permit. The fee for the annual permit for a nonresident motor vehicle shall not be less than the fee for a resident motor vehicle and not more than sixty-five dollars. The commission shall establish such fees by the adoption and promulgation of rules and regulations.</para><para>(3) A temporary permit may be purchased by any person and shall be valid until noon of the day following the date of issue. The fee for the temporary permit for a resident motor vehicle shall be not more than seven dollars. The fee for the temporary permit for a nonresident motor vehicle shall be not more than twelve dollars. The commission shall establish such fees by the adoption and promulgation of rules and regulations. The commission may issue temporary permits which are either valid for any area or valid for a single area.</para><para>(4)(a) A veteran who is a resident of Nebraska shall, upon application and without payment of any fee, be issued one disabled veteran permit for a resident motor vehicle if the veteran:</para><para>(i) Was discharged or separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions); and</para><para>(ii)(A) Is rated by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs as fifty percent or more disabled as a result of service in the armed forces of the United States; or</para><para>(B) Is receiving a pension from the United States Department of Veterans Affairs as a result of total and permanent disability, which disability was not incurred in the line of duty in the military service.</para><para>(b) All disabled veteran permits issued pursuant to this subsection shall be perpetual and shall become void only upon termination of eligibility as provided in this subsection.</para><para>(c) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out this subsection.</para><para>(5) The commission may offer permits or combinations of permits at temporarily reduced rates for specific events or during specified timeframes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 81, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 742, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 723, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 74, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 199, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 32; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-1105; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 148; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 122, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB421, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB745, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB287, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB770, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>November 14, 2020</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>