<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id29">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id31" statutenumber="37-455"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-455</statuteno><catchline id="id34">Limited deer,
antelope, wild turkey, or elk permit; conditions; fee.</catchline><para>(1)
The commission may issue a limited permit for deer, antelope, wild turkey,
or elk to a person who is a qualifying landowner or leaseholder and his or
her immediate family as described in this section. The commission may issue
nonresident landowner limited permits after preference has been given for
the issuance of resident permits as provided in rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated by the commission. A permit shall be valid during the predetermined
period established by the commission pursuant to sections 37-447 to 37-450,
37-452, 37-456, or 37-457. Upon receipt of an application in proper form as
prescribed by the rules and regulations of the commission, the commission
may issue (a) a limited deer, antelope, or wild turkey permit valid for hunting
on all of the land which is owned or leased by the qualifying landowner or
leaseholder if such lands are identified in the application or (b) a limited
elk permit valid for hunting on the entire elk management unit of which the
land of the qualifying landowner or leaseholder included in the application
is a part.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and
regulations prescribing procedures and forms and create requirements for documentation
by an applicant or permittee to determine whether the applica<?Pub Caret?>nt
or permittee is a Nebraska resident and is a qualifying landowner or leaseholder
of the described property or is a member of the immediate family of such qualifying
landowner or leaseholder. The
commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that create requirements
for documentation to designate one qualifying landowner among partners of
a partnership or officers or shareholders of a corporation that owns or leases
eighty acres or more of farm or ranch land for agricultural purposes and among
beneficiaries of a trust that owns or leases eighty acres or more of farm
or ranch land for agricultural purposes. Only a person who is
a qualifying landowner or leaseholder and such person's immediate family may
apply for a limited permit. An applicant may apply for no more than one permit
per species per year except as otherwise provided in the rules and regulations
of the commission. For purposes of this section, immediate family means and
is limited to a husband and wife and their children or siblings sharing ownership
in the property.</para>
<para>(b) The conditions applicable to permits issued pursuant to
sections 37-447 to 37-450, 37-452, 37-456, or 37-457, whichever is appropriate,
shall apply to limited permits issued pursuant to this section, except that
the commission may pass commission orders for species harvest allocation
pertaining to the sex and age of the species harvested which are different
for a limited permit than for other hunting permits. For purposes of this
section, white-tailed deer and mule deer shall be treated as one species.</para>
<para>(3)(a) To qualify for a limited permit to hunt deer or antelope,
the applicant shall be a Nebraska resident who (i) owns or leases eighty acres or more of farm
or ranch land for agricultural purposes or a member of such person's immediate
family or (ii) is the partner,
officer, shareholder, or beneficiary designated as the qualifying landowner
by a partnership, corporation, or trust as provided in the rules and regulations
under subdivision (2)(a) of this section or a member of the immediate family
of the partner, officer, shareholder, or beneficiary. The number
of limited permits issued annually per species for each farm or ranch shall
not exceed the total acreage of the farm or ranch divided by eighty. The fee
for a limited permit to hunt deer or antelope shall be one-half the fee for
the regular permit for such species.</para>
<para>(b) A nonresident of Nebraska who owns three hundred twenty
acres or more of farm or ranch land in the State of Nebraska for agricultural
purposes or a member of such person's immediate family may apply for a limited
deer or antelope permit. The number of limited permits issued annually per
species for each farm or ranch shall not exceed the total acreage of the farm
or ranch divided by three hundred twenty. The fee for such a permit to hunt
deer or antelope shall be one-half the fee for a nonresident permit to hunt
such species.</para>
<para>(c) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
providing for the issuance of an additional limited deer permit to a qualified
individual for the taking of a deer without antlers at a fee equal to or less
than the fee for the original limited permit.</para>
<para>(4)(a) To qualify for a limited permit to hunt wild turkey,
the applicant shall be a Nebraska resident who (i) owns or leases eighty acres or more of farm
or ranch land for agricultural purposes or a member of such person's immediate
family or (ii) is the partner,
officer, shareholder, or beneficiary designated as the qualifying landowner
by a partnership, corporation, or trust as provided in the rules and regulations
under subdivision (2)(a) of this section or a member of the immediate family
of the partner, officer, shareholder, or beneficiary. The number
of limited permits issued annually per season for each farm or ranch shall
not exceed the total acreage of the farm or ranch divided by eighty. An applicant
may apply for no more than one limited permit per season. The fee for a limited
permit to hunt wild turkey shall be one-half the fee for the regular permit
to hunt wild turkey.</para>
<para>(b) A nonresident of Nebraska who owns three hundred twenty
acres or more of farm or ranch land in the State of Nebraska for agricultural
purposes or a member of such person's immediate family may apply for a limited
permit to hunt wild turkey. Only one limited wild turkey permit per three
hundred twenty acres may be issued annually for each wild turkey season under
this subdivision. The fee for such a permit to hunt shall be one-half the
fee for a nonresident permit to hunt wild turkey.</para>
<para>(5) To qualify for a limited permit to hunt elk, (a) the applicant
shall be (i) a Nebraska resident who owns three hundred twenty acres or more
of farm or ranch land for agricultural purposes, (ii) a Nebraska resident
who leases six hundred forty acres or more of farm or ranch land for agricultural
purposes or has a leasehold interest and an ownership interest in farm or
ranch land used for agricultural purposes which when added together totals
at least six hundred forty acres, (iii) a nonresident of Nebraska who owns
at least one thousand two hundred eighty acres of farm or ranch land for agricultural
purposes, or (iv) a member of such owner's or lessee's immediate family and
(b) the qualifying farm or ranch land of the applicant shall be within an
area designated as an elk management zone by the commission in its rules and
regulations. An applicant shall not be issued a limited bull elk permit more
than once every three years, and the commission may give preference to a person
who did not receive a limited elk permit or a specified type of limited elk
permit during the previous years. The fee for a resident landowner limited
permit to hunt elk shall not exceed one-half the fee for the regular permit
to hunt elk. The fee for a nonresident landowner limited permit to hunt elk
shall not exceed three times the cost of a resident elk permit. The number
of applications allowed for limited elk permits for each farm or ranch shall
not exceed the total acreage of the farm or ranch divided by the minimum acreage
requirements established for the property. No more than one person may qualify
for the same described property.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 761, &#167; 1, p. 2878; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 767, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 270, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 170, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 557, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 107, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 173, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-215.03; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 165; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1149, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB94, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB499, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>