<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id13" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="37-327.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>37-327.02</statuteno><catchline>Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund is created. The fund shall consist of money credited to the fund pursuant to section 77-27,132, transfers authorized by the Legislature, and any gifts, grants, bequests, or donations to the fund. The fund shall be administered by the commission and shall be used to build, repair, renovate, rehabilitate, restore, modify, or improve any infrastructure within the statutory authority and administration of the commission. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>Transfers may be made from the Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature through June 30, 2019. The State Treasurer shall transfer four million five hundred thousand dollars from the Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund to the General Fund between June 1, 2018, and June 30, 2018, on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services. The State Treasurer shall transfer four million five hundred thousand dollars from the Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund to the General Fund between June 1, 2019, and June 30, 2019, on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB814, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>May 16, 2017</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>