<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-102</statuteno><catchline>Game and Parks Commission; districts.</catchline><para>For purposes of section 37-101, the state is hereby divided into eight districts. The limits and designations of the eight districts shall be as follows:</para><para>(1) District No. 1. The counties of Richardson, Pawnee, Nemaha, Johnson, Otoe, Cass, Sarpy, Saunders, Butler, Gage, Seward, Saline, and Jefferson;</para><para>(2) District No. 2. Douglas County;</para><para>(3) District No. 3. The counties of Washington, Dodge, Colfax, Platte, Merrick, Nance, Boone, Madison, Stanton, Cuming, Burt, Thurston, Wayne, Pierce, Antelope, Knox, Cedar, Dixon, and Dakota;</para><para>(4) District No. 4. The counties of Thayer, Nuckolls, Webster, Adams, Clay, Fillmore, York, Polk, Hamilton, Hall, Buffalo, Kearney, and Franklin;</para><para>(5) District No. 5. The counties of Harlan, Furnas, Red Willow, Hitchcock, Dundy, Chase, Hayes, Frontier, Gosper, Phelps, Dawson, Lincoln, and Perkins;</para><para>(6) District No. 6. The counties of Howard, Greeley, Wheeler, Sherman, Valley, Garfield, Holt, Boyd, Keya Paha, Rock, Brown, Loup, Blaine, Custer, Logan, McPherson, Arthur, Grant, Hooker, Thomas, and Cherry;</para><para>(7) District No. 7. The counties of Deuel, Garden, Keith, Sheridan, Cheyenne, Morrill, Box Butte, Dawes, Sioux, Scotts Bluff, Banner, and Kimball; and</para><para>(8) District No. 8. Lancaster County.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 315, &#167; 2, p. 954; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 513, &#167; 1, p. 1628; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 81-801.01; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc>