<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id184" statutenumber="37-451"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-451</statuteno><catchline id="id187">Permit to hunt mountain sheep; regulation and limitation by commission; issuance; fee; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue permits for hunting mountain sheep and may adopt and promulgate separate and, when necessary, different rules and regulations therefor within the limitations prescribed in subsection (1) of section 37-447 and section 37-452 for hunting deer. Such rules and regulations shall include provisions allowing persons who find dead mountain sheep, or any part of a mountain sheep, to turn over to the commission such mountain sheep or part of a mountain sheep. The commission may dispose of such mountain sheep or part of a mountain sheep as it deems reasonable and prudent. Except as otherwise provided in this section, the permits shall be issued to residents of Nebraska.</para><para>(2) The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a nonrefundable application fee of not more than thirty-four dollars for permits issued only to residents. Any number of resident-only permits, as authorized by the commission, shall be awarded by random drawing to eligible applicants. No permit fee shall be charged in addition to the nonrefundable application fee.</para><para>(3) No more than one additional permit may be authorized and issued pursuant to an auction open to residents and nonresidents. The auction shall be conducted according to rules and regulations prescribed by the commission. Any money derived from the sale of permits by auction shall be used only for perpetuation and management of mountain sheep, elk, and deer.</para><para>(4) If the commission determines to limit the number of permits issued for any or all management units, the commission shall by rule and regulation determine eligibility requirements for the permits.</para><para>(5) A person may obtain only one mountain sheep permit in his or her lifetime.</para><para>(6) Any person violating the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor and shall be fined at least five hundred dollars upon conviction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 161; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB745, &#167; 14. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>