<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-811"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>37-811</statuteno><catchline>Wildlife Conservation Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>There is hereby created the Wildlife Conservation Fund. The fund shall be used to assist in carrying out the Nongame and Endangered Species Conservation Act, to pay for research into and management of the ecological effects of the release, importation, commercial exploitation, and exportation of wildlife species pursuant to section 37-548, and to pay any expenses incurred by the Department of Revenue or any other agency in the administration of the income tax designation program required by section 77-27,119.01. The fund shall consist of money credited pursuant to section 60-3,238 and any other money as determined by the Legislature. The fund shall also consist of money transferred from the General Fund by the State Treasurer in an amount to be determined by the Tax Commissioner which shall be equal to the total amount of contributions designated pursuant to section 77-27,119.01. Any money in the Wildlife Conservation Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 466, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 258, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 23; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 37-439; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 361; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB356, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>