<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id24">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id26" statutenumber="37-413"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>37-413</statuteno><catchline id="id29">Firearm hunter
education program; commission issue certificate; hunting, lawful when; apprentice
hunter education exemption certificate; fee.</catchline><para>(1)
For the purpose of establishing and administering a mandatory firearm hunter
education program for persons twelve through twenty-nine years of age who
hunt with a firearm or air gun any species of game,
game birds, or game animals, the commission shall provide a program of firearm
hunter education training leading to obtaining a certificate of successful
completion in the safe handling of firearms and shall locate and train volunteer
firearm hunter education instructors. The
program shall provide instruction in the areas of safe firearms use, shooting
and sighting techniques, hunter ethics, game identification, and conservation
management. The commission shall issue a firearm hunter education certificate
of successful completion to persons having satisfactorily completed a firearm
hunter education course accredited by the commission and shall print, purchase,
or otherwise acquire materials as necessary for effective program operation.
The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for carrying
out and administering such programs.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person twenty-nine years
of age or younger to hunt with a firearm or air gun any species of game,
game birds, or game animals except:</para>
<para>(a) A person under the age of twelve years who is accompanied as described in subsection (4) of this section;</para>
<para>(b) A person twelve through twenty-nine years of age who has
on his or her person proof of successful completion of a hunter education
course as described in subsection
(1) of this section or a hunter
education course issued by the person's state or province of residence or
by an accredited program recognized by the commission;</para>
<para>(c) A person twelve through twenty-nine years of age who has
on his or her person the appropriate hunting permit and an apprentice hunter
education exemption certificate issued by the commission pursuant to subsection
(3) of this section and who is accompanied as described in subsection (4)
of this section; or</para>
<para>(d) A person
who has a developmental disability, who holds the appropriate hunting permit
and a license-purchase exemption certificate issued pursuant to section 37-404.01,
and who is accompanied as described in subsection (4) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) An apprentice hunter education exemption certificate may
be issued to a person twelve through twenty-nine years of age, once during
such person's lifetime with one renewal, upon payment of a fee of five dollars
and shall expire at midnight on December 31 of the year for which the apprentice
hunter education exemption certificate is issued. The commission may adopt
and promulgate rules and regulations allowing for the issuance of apprentice
hunter education exemption certificates. All fees collected under this subsection
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Game Fund.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section, accompanied means under
the direct supervision of a person who is: (a) Nineteen years of age or older
having a valid hunting permit. If such person is nineteen years of age or
older but not older than twenty-nine years of age, he or she shall have also
completed the required course of instruction to receive a certificate of completion
for hunter
education; and
(b) at all times in unaided visual and verbal communication of persons who have a developmental disability
and who are authorized under section 37-404.01 or no more than
two persons having an apprentice hunter education exemption certificate. This
subsection does not prohibit the use by such person nineteen years of age
or older of ordinary prescription eyeglasses or contact lenses or ordinary
hearing instruments.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 766, &#167; 1, p. 2903; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 865, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 37-104; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB690, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB871, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB699, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>April 3, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>