<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>37-604</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement of Game Law; duties; fees
and mileage.</catchline><para>It shall be the duty of all conservation officers,
sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, and other peace officers to make prompt investigation
of and arrests for any violations of the Game Law observed or reported by
any person and to cause a complaint to be filed before a court having jurisdiction
thereof in case there seems just ground for such complaint and evidence procurable
to support the same. Upon the filing of such a complaint, it shall be the duty of such officer to render
assistance in the prosecution of the party complained against. Sheriffs, deputy
sheriffs, and other peace officers making arrests and serving warrants under
this section shall receive fees and mileage under the provisions of the statutes
of the state with mileage to be computed at the rate provided for county sheriffs
in section 33-117. Conservation officers shall serve writs and processes,
civil and criminal, when such writs and processes pertain to enforcement of
duties imposed by law on the commission. Any officer or person purporting
to enforce the laws of this state or rules and regulations adopted and promulgated or commission orders passed pursuant
thereto shall on the demand of any person apprehended by him or her exhibit
to such person his or her written commission of authority as such enforcement
officer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 294; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB499, &#167; 15.</para></source><annotation><para>A search warrant would obviously not be required to authorize service on plaintiff's lake property of writs and process. Kuester v. State, 191 Neb. 680, 217 N.W.2d 180 (1974).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>