<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id86">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id88" statutenumber="37-421.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>37-421.01</statuteno><catchline id="id91">Military deployment; permits; stamps; conditions; fee.</catchline><para>(1)
Notwithstanding any provision of section 37-407 to the contrary, a Nebraska
resident who is deployed out of state with
a branch of the United States military or
has been so deployed within the last twelve months at the time of application shall
be entitled to receive an annual
combination fishing and hunting permit, habitat stamp, aquatic habitat stamp,
and Nebraska migratory waterfowl stamp on a one-time basis upon
returning to the state if the resident:</para>
<para>(a) Submits
an application to the commission with a fee of five dollars; and</para>
<para>(b) Provides to the commission evidence of the resident's deployment out
of state.</para>

<para>(2)(a) Notwithstanding any provision of section 37-447, 37-449,
37-450, 37-451, or 37-457 to the contrary, a Nebraska resident who purchased
a big game permit and who was deployed out of state with a branch of the United
States military for the entire season of the hunt and who was unable to use
the permit shall be entitled to receive a discounted permit on a one-time
basis upon returning to the state if the resident provides to the commission evidence of deployment. Alternatively, the member of the military
may request a refund of the amount paid for a big game permit and the commission
shall pay such amount.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of this subsection, big game means antelope,
deer, elk, mountain sheep, and wild turkeys.</para>
<para>(c) The commission shall establish
a fee of five dollars for the discounted permits authorized in this subsection.</para>
<para>(3) The commission may authorize
electronic issuance of the discounted permits authorized under this section.</para>
<para>(4) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
that set forth the procedures for applying for, and the issuance of, the discounted
permits authorized in this section,
including what constitutes evidence of deployment to qualify for the permits.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 121, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB41, &#167; 8.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
