<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id162" statutenumber="37-449"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>37-449</statuteno><catchline id="id165">Permit to hunt antelope; regulation and limitation by commission; issuance; fees; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue permits for hunting antelope and may adopt and promulgate separate and, when necessary, different rules and regulations therefor within the limitations prescribed in sections 37-447 and 37-452 for hunting deer. The commission may offer permits or combinations of permits at reduced rates for specific events or during specified timeframes.</para><para>(2) The commission may, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a nonrefundable application fee of not more than seven dollars for antelope permits in those management units awarded on the basis of a random drawing. The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than thirty-nine dollars for residents and not more than two hundred fifty-seven dollars for nonresidents for each permit issued under this section except as provided in subsection (4) of this section. The commission may, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than twenty-four dollars for residents and not more than seventy-two dollars for nonresidents for the issuance of a preference point, in addition to any application fee, in lieu of entering the draw for an antelope permit during the application period for the random drawing.</para><para>(3) The provisions for the distribution of deer permits and the authority of the commission to determine eligibility of applicants for permits as described in sections 37-447 and 37-452 shall also apply to the distribution of antelope permits.</para><para>(4) The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than twenty-five dollars for residents and not more than forty-five dollars for nonresidents for a youth antelope permit.</para><para>(5) Any person violating the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor and shall be fined at least one hundred dollars upon conviction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 159; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB745, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB287, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB565, &#167; 26. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>