<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id145">
<sectno id="id146">Sec. 15.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id147" statutenumber="37-447"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id149">37-447</statuteno><catchline id="id150">Permit to hunt
deer; regulation and limitation by commission; issuance; fee; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)
The commission may issue permits for the hunting of deer and prescribe and adopt and promulgate rules and regulations and
limitations for the hunting, transportation, and possession of deer. The commission
may offer multiple-year permits or combinations of permits at reduced rates.
The commission may specify by regulation the information to be required on
applications for such permits. Regulations and limitations for the hunting,
transportation, and possession of deer may include, but not be limited to,
regulations and limitations as to the type, caliber, and other specifications
of firearms and ammunition used and specifications for bows and arrows used.
Such regulations and limitations may further specify and limit the method
of hunting deer and may provide for dividing the state into management units
or areas, and the commission may enact different deer hunting regulations
for the different management units pertaining to sex, species, and age of
the deer hunted.</para>
<para>(2) The number of such permits may be limited as provided
by the rules and regulations of the commission, and except as provided in
section 37-454, the permits shall be disposed of in an impartial manner. Whenever
the commission deems it advisable to limit the number of permits issued for
any or all management units, the commission shall, by rules and regulations,
determine who shall be eligible to obtain such permits. In establishing eligibility,
the commission may give preference to persons who did not receive a permit or a specified type of permit during
the previous year or years.</para>
<para>(3) Such permits may be issued to allow deer hunting in the
Nebraska National Forest and other game reserves and such other areas as the
commission may designate whenever the commission deems that permitting such
hunting will not be detrimental to the proper preservation of wildlife in
Nebraska in such forest, reserves, or areas.</para>
<para>(4)(a) The commission shall,
pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than twenty-nine
dollars for residents and not more than two hundred fourteen dollars for nonresidents
for each permit issued under this section except as otherwise provided in subdivision (b) of this
subsection and subsection (6) of this section.</para>
<para>(b) The fee
for a statewide buck-only permit shall be no more than two and one-half times
the amount of a regular deer permit. The commission may provide different
fees for different species.</para><para>(5) The commission
may issue nonresident permits after preference has been given for the issuance
of resident permits as provided in rules and regulations adopted and promulgated
by the commission. The commission may require a predetermined application
period for permit applications in specified management units. Such permits
shall be issued after a reasonable period for making application, as established
by the commission, has expired. When more valid applications are received
for a designated management unit than there are permits available, such permits
shall be allocated on the basis of a random drawing. All valid applications
received during the predetermined application period shall be considered equally
in any such random drawing without regard to time of receipt of such applications
by the commission.</para>
<para>(6) The commission
shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more
than twenty-five dollars for residents and not more than forty-five dollars
for nonresidents for a youth deer permit.</para><para>(7) Any person violating the rules and
regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section shall be guilty
of a Class II misdemeanor and shall be fined at least one hundred dollars
upon conviction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 85, &#167; 1, p. 305; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 133, &#167; 1, p. 376; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 103, &#167; 1(1), p. 282; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 109, &#167; 1, p. 517; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 124, &#167; 1, p. 389; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 141, &#167; 1, p. 477; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 156, &#167; 1, p. 584; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 292, &#167; 1, p. 1063; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 777, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 767, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 861, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 437, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 72, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1001, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 557, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1088, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 583, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 862, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 107, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-215; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 157; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 15.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>