<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id38">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id40" statutenumber="37-414"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-414</statuteno><catchline id="id43">Bow hunter education
program; certificate; issuance; hunting, lawful; when.</catchline>
<para>(1) The commission shall establish and administer a bow hunter
education program providing instruction in the
safe use of bow hunting equipment, the fundamentals of bow hunting, shooting
and hunting techniques, game identification, conservation management, and
hunter ethics. When establishing such a program, the commission shall locate
and train volunteers as bow hunter education instructors. The commission shall
issue a certificate of successful completion to any person who satisfactorily
completes a bow hunter education program accredited by the commission
and shall print, purchase, or otherwise acquire materials necessary for effective
program operation. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
for carrying out and administering such program.</para>
<para>(2) A person twelve through twenty-nine years of age who is
hunting antelope, deer, elk, or mountain sheep with a bow and arrow or crossbow pursuant to any
provision of sections 37-447 to 37-453 shall (a) have on his or her person proof of successful
completion of a bow hunter education course issued by his or her state or
province of residence or by an accredited program recognized by the commission, (b) have
on his or her person the appropriate hunting permit and an apprentice hunter education exemption
certificate issued by the commission pursuant to subsection (3) of section
37-413 and be accompanied as described in subsection (4) of section 37-413,
or (c) hold the appropriate hunting permit and a license-purchase exemption
certificate issued pursuant to section 37-404.01 if required pursuant to such
section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 403, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 107, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-105; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB690, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB699, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>