<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id21">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id23" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="37-917"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>37-917</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Youth Conservation Program;
created; purpose; participants; qualification; payment; status; coordination
with federal, state, and local programs.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Youth Conservation Program
is created. The purpose of the program is to employ Nebraska's at-risk youth
on projects which contribute to conserving or developing natural resources
and enhancing and maintaining environmentally important land and water under
the jurisdiction of the commission. The program shall combine academic, environmental,
and job skills training with personal growth opportunities for the participants.
The commission may administer and maintain the program, directly or by means
of contractual arrangement with an experienced service provider or the Department
of Labor.</para>
<para>(2) Participants
shall be at-risk youth who are at least sixteen years of age and not older
than twenty-one years of age, unemployed, and residents of Nebraska. Special
effort shall be made to select applicants residing in rural and urban high-poverty
areas, as determined by the most recent federal census data.</para>
<para>(3) Participants
shall be paid not less than the minimum wage described in section 48-1203.
Participation in the program shall be for a period of six weeks for each participant.
Participants and program supervisory personnel may be provided meals during
the six-week work period. Protective clothing items shall be provided to participants
and supervisory personnel as work conditions warrant.</para><para>(4) Participants in the
Nebraska Youth Conservation Program may be considered temporary employees.
This subsection does not apply to crew chiefs and other administrative and
supervisory personnel of the program, all of whom may be employees of the
commission or employees of an entity hired by or under contract with the commission
or the Department of Labor to administer the program. The program shall not
result in displacement of current employees or cause a reduction in current
employees' hours or wages and shall be in compliance with applicable federal
and state labor and education laws.</para><para>(5)  The commission may coordinate with
federal, state, and local programs that provide job training and placement
services and education opportunities for participants after completing the
program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB549, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>