<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id12" statutenumber="37-327"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-327</statuteno><catchline id="id15">Commission; fees; duty to establish; limit on increase.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall establish fees for licenses, permits, stamps, bands, registrations, and certificates issued under the Game Law and the State Boat Act as provided in the Game Law and State Boat Act. The commission shall not increase any fee more than six percent per year, except that if a fee has not been increased by such percentage in the immediately preceding two years, the difference between a six percent increase and the actual percentage increase in such preceding two years may be added to the percentage increase in the following year. Such fees shall be collected and disposed of as provided in the Game Law and State Boat Act. The commission shall, as provided in the Game Law and State Boat Act, establish issuance fees to be retained by authorized agents issuing such licenses, permits, stamps, bands, registrations, and certificates. The commission shall establish such fees by the adoption and promulgation of rules and regulations.</para><para>(2) Prior to establishing any fee, the commission shall, at least thirty days prior to the hearing required in section 84-907, make the following information available for public review:</para><para>(a) The commission's policy on the minimum cash balance to be maintained in the fund in which the revenue from the fee being established is deposited and the justification in support of such policy;</para><para>(b) Monthly estimates of cash fund revenue, expenditures, and ending balances for the current fiscal year and the following two fiscal years for the fund in which the revenue from the fee being established is deposited. Estimates shall be prepared for both the current fee schedule and the proposed fee schedule; and</para><para>(c) A statement of the reasons for establishing the fee at the proposed level.</para><para>(3) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish fees for expired licenses, permits, stamps, bands, registrations, and certificates issued under the Game Law and the State Boat Act. The commission shall collect the fees and remit them to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Game Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 81-814.02; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB41, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB745, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Boat Act,</emphasis> see section 37-1201.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>