<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-327.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-327.01</statuteno><catchline>Game Law Investigation Cash Fund; created; use; investment; record-keeping duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Game Law Investigation Cash Fund is created. The commission shall use the fund for the purpose of obtaining evidence for enforcement of the Game Law. The fund shall be funded through revenue collected under the Game Law and budgeted or allocated to the fund by the commission, and through donations from persons, wildlife groups, and other charitable sources. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) For the purpose of establishing and maintaining legislative oversight and accountability, the commission shall formulate record-keeping procedures for all expenditures, disbursements, and transfers of cash from the Game Law Investigation Cash Fund. Based on these record-keeping procedures, the commission shall prepare and deliver to the Clerk of the Legislature by September 15 of each year a detailed report of the previous fiscal year which includes, but is not limited to: (a) The June 30 balance in the Game Law Investigation Cash Fund and the amounts delivered to the commission for distribution to agents and informants; (b) the total amount of expenditures; (c) the purpose of the expenditures including: (i) Salaries and any expenses of all agents and informants; (ii) front money for wildlife purchases; (iii) type of wildlife and amount purchased; and (iv) amount of front money recovered; (d) the total number of informants on payroll; and (e) the results procured through such transactions. Each member of the Legislature shall receive a copy of such report by making a request for it to the secretary of the commission.</para><para>(3) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 788, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>