<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-464"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-464</statuteno><catchline>Holding fur after close of season; permit required; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>Except as otherwise provided in the Game Law, it shall be unlawful for any person, other than a person holding a captive wildlife permit, a fur buyer's permit, or a permit issued pursuant to section 37-460, with regard to pelts of beaver taken pursuant to such permits, and officers and employees of the commission, to possess the raw fur or pelt of any fur-bearing animal protected by the Game Law at any time other than during the open season for such fur-bearing animal and ten days immediately thereafter. Any person who by trapping or other lawful means has become the owner of the raw furs or pelts of such fur-bearing animals during the open season thereon and who during the ten days immediately after the close of such open season has been unable to obtain a satisfactory price for such furs or otherwise has been prevented from lawfully disposing of the same may, during such ten-day period, obtain from the commission a permit to retain possession of such furs for such further period of time as the commission may by rule and regulation designate. All applications for such permits shall be verified under oath, state the number and kind of untanned pelts on hand which it is desired to carry over, be filed with the commission before the expiration of such ten-day period, and be accompanied by the certificate of an employee of the commission or the county sheriff that the applicant, to the personal knowledge of such employee or sheriff, then has on hand the number and kinds of furs for which the permit is applied for. Any person knowingly making or assisting in making a false certificate in connection with such an application shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 112, III, &#167; 7, p. 418; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 37-307; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 37-306; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 227; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 181; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 34, &#167; 16; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-306; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 48. </para></source></law></legaldoc>