<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id13" statutenumber="37-327.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>37-327.02</statuteno><catchline>Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund; created; use; investment; projects; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund is created. The fund shall consist of money credited to the fund pursuant to section 77-27,132, transfers authorized by the Legislature, and any gifts, grants, bequests, or donations to the fund. The fund shall be administered by the commission and shall be used to build, repair, renovate, rehabilitate, restore, modify, or improve any infrastructure within the statutory authority and administration of the commission. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para><para>(2) On or before December 1, 2021, and on or before December 1 of each year thereafter through 2027, the commission shall electronically submit a report to the Clerk of the Legislature and the Revenue Committee of the Legislature. The report shall include (a) a list of each project that received funding from the Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund under subsection (1) of this section during the most recently completed fiscal year and (b) a list of projects that will receive such funding during the current fiscal year.</para><para>(3) Transfers may be made from the Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund to the Nebraska Emergency Medical System Operations Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer one million two hundred seventy thousand dollars from the Game and Parks Commission Capital Maintenance Fund to the Nebraska Emergency Medical System Operations Fund in June of each fiscal year beginning in June 2025, from the proceeds of the sales and use taxes imposed pursuant to section 77-2703 on the sale or lease of all-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles as provided in section 77-27,132, on such date as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB814, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB945, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB595, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1108, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 6. </para><note>Changes made by Laws 2024, LB1108, became effective April 16, 2024.</note><note>Changes made by Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, became effective August 21, 2024.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>