<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id73"><sectno id="id74">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id75" statutenumber="37-463"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id77">37-463</statuteno><catchline id="id78">Dealing in raw furs; fur buyer's permit required; annual fee; record; unlawful acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person, firm, or corporation dealing in raw furs to conduct such business without first obtaining from the commission a fur buyer's permit. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. The annual fee for this permit shall be not more than one hundred thirty-eight dollars for residents, as established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327. Any resident who has resided in this state continuously for a period of six months before making an application for a permit under this section shall be deemed to be a resident and may be issued a resident permit under this section. The fees for nonresidents of this state shall be equal to the fees charged for similar permits by the states of their respective residences but not less than five hundred dollars per annum for such nonresidents. Before a fur buyer's permit is issued to a nonresident of this state, the applicant shall execute and deliver to the secretary of the commission a corporate surety bond, running to the State of Nebraska, in the penal sum of one thousand dollars to be approved by the commission, conditioned that the permitholder shall faithfully comply with all the laws of this state. Dealers sending buyers into the field away from their place of business shall provide each such buyer with a separate fur buyer's permit. Every nonresident buyer entering the state or who has buyers in this state shall carry a nonresident fur buyer's permit.</para><para>(2) Every resident and nonresident fur buyer shall keep a complete record of all furs bought or sold in a record book to be provided by the commission or any other form of record keeping approved by the commission. Such record shall include, but not be limited to, the number and kind of furs bought or sold, the name and address of the seller or buyer, the date and place of purchase or sale, and the permit number of the seller or fur buyer.</para><para>(3) It shall be unlawful for any fur buyer to have raw furs in his, her, or its possession unless the record gives positive evidence of the origin of such furs and unless such record balances at all times. Such record shall be open to inspection by conservation officers at any and all times and shall be made available to such officers upon demand.</para><para>(4) Any violation of any of the provisions of this section shall constitute a Class IV misdemeanor, and as a part of the penalty the court shall require the offender to purchase the required permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 112, II, &#167; 11, p. 412; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 37-211; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 89, &#167; 3, p. 291; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 72, &#167; 2, p. 301; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 37-211; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 37-211; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 78, &#167; 3, p. 289; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 131, &#167; 1, p. 378; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 150, &#167; 3, p. 570; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 216, &#167; 4, p. 580; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 811, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 861, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 72, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 56, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 87; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1997, &#167; 37-211; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 173; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
