<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id120">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id122" statutenumber="37-432"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id124">37-432</statuteno><catchline id="id125">Stamps; money
received from fees; administered by commission; purposes.</catchline><para>(1) All money received from the sale of habitat stamps, as provided
by sections 37-426 to 37-433, shall be administered by the commission for
the acquisition of, on
a willing-seller willing-buyer basis only, leasing of, development of, management of, enhancement
of, access to, and
taking of easements on wildlife lands and habitat areas. Such funds may be
used in whole or in part for the matching of federal funds. Up to twenty-five percent of the money received from the
sale of habitat stamps may be used to provide access to private wildlife lands
and habitat areas.</para>
<para>(2) All money received from the sale of aquatic habitat stamps,
as provided by sections 37-426 to 37-433, shall be administered by the commission
and shall be used for
the maintenance and restoration of existing aquatic habitat if maintenance and restoration is practicable, for the enhancement
of existing aquatic habitat,
for public waters angler access enhancements, and for administration of programs
related to aquatic habitat and public waters angler access enhancements.
Such funds may be used in whole or in part for the matching of federal funds. Up to thirty percent of the money received
from the sale of aquatic habitat stamps may be used to provide public waters
angler access enhancements and to provide funding for administration of programs
related to aquatic habitat and public waters angler access enhancements.</para>
<para>(3) All money received from the sale of Nebraska migratory
waterfowl stamps, as provided by sections 37-426 to 37-433, shall be administered
by the commission for the acquisition on a willing-seller willing-buyer basis
only, leasing, development, management, and enhancement of and taking of easements
on migratory waterfowl habitat. Such funds may be used in whole or in part
for the matching of federal funds.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 861, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 174, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 16; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 37-216.08; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 142; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>