<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id43">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id45" statutenumber="37-524"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>37-524</statuteno><catchline id="id48">Aquatic
invasive species; wild or nonnative animals; importation, possession,
or release; prohibition; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)
It shall be unlawful for any person, partnership, limited liability company,
association, or corporation to import into the state or possess aquatic invasive species, the
animal known as the San Juan rabbit, or
any other species of wild vertebrate animal, including domesticated cervine
animals as defined in section 54-701.03, declared by the commission following
public hearing and consultation with the Department of Agriculture to constitute
a serious threat to economic or ecologic conditions, except that the commission
may authorize by specific written permit the acquisition and possession of
such species for educational or scientific purposes. It shall also be unlawful
to release to the wild any nonnative bird or nonnative mammal without written
authorization from the commission. Any person, partnership, limited liability
company, association, or corporation violating the provisions of this subsection
shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(2) Following public hearing and consultation with the Department
of Agriculture, the commission may, by rule and regulation, regulate or limit
the importation and possession of any aquatic
invasive species or wild vertebrate animal, including a domesticated
cervine animal as defined in section 54-701.03, which is found to constitute
a serious threat to economic or ecologic conditions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 139, &#167; 20, p. 474; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 222, &#167; 1, p. 597; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 331, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 205; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 203; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 830, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 718, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 37-719; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 244; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB391, &#167; 8.</para><effectivedate>April 6, 2012</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Domesticated Cervine Animal Act,</emphasis> possession of certain animals prohibited, see section 54-2324.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>