<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id6" statutenumber="37-448"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>37-448</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Special deer, antelope, and elk depredation season; extension of existing hunting season; permit; issuance; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the commission, the secretary of the commission may designate, by order, special deer, antelope, and elk depredation seasons or extensions of existing hunting seasons. The secretary may designate a depredation season or an extension of an existing hunting season whenever he or she determines that deer, antelope, or elk are causing excessive property damage. The secretary shall specify the number of permits to be issued, the species, sex, and number or quota of animals allowed to be taken, the bag limit for such species, the beginning and ending dates for the depredation season or hunting season extension, any limitations on nonresident permits, shooting hours, the length of the depredation season or hunting season extension, and the geographic area in which hunting will be permitted. The rules and regulations shall allow use of any weapon permissible for use during the regular deer, antelope, or elk season.</para><para>(2) The depredation season may commence not less than five days after the first public announcement that the depredation season has been established. Permits shall be issued in an impartial manner at a location determined by the secretary. The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than twenty-five dollars for a resident special depredation season permit and a fee of not more than seventy-five dollars for a nonresident special depredation season permit. The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than ten dollars for a landowner special depredation season permit for the taking of deer and antelope for any person owning or operating at least twenty acres of farm or ranch land within the geographic area in which hunting will be permitted and to any member of the immediate family of any such person as defined in subdivision (2)(a) of section 37-455, and for the taking of elk for any person owning or operating at least eighty acres of farm or ranch land within the geographic area in which hunting will be permitted and to any member of the immediate family of such person as defined in subdivision (2)(a) of section 37-455. A special depredation season permit shall be valid only within such area and only during the designated depredation season. The commission shall use the income from the sale of special depredation season permits for abatement of damage caused by deer, antelope, and elk. Receipt of a depredation season permit shall not in any way affect a person's eligibility for a permit issued under section 37-447, 37-449, 37-450, or 37-455.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 158; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB836, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB928, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB499, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB507, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB565, &#167; 25. </para><operativedate>September 2, 2023</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>