<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-562"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-562</statuteno><catchline>Beaver or muskrat; destruction authorized, when; reports; fees.</catchline><para>It shall be lawful for any officer or employee of any public power, irrigation, or drainage district organized under the laws of this state to kill or destroy or to have trapped any beaver or muskrat which may be found to be destroying or damaging any dams, ditches, or other works needed and useful in the operation of such district. Such district may cause such trapping to occur if, within thirty days after notice in writing is given to the secretary of the commission of such destruction or damage and the location thereof, the commission fails, neglects, or refuses to cause the beaver or muskrat doing such destruction or damage to be removed from the place where such destruction or damage is occurring or to take such other steps as may be effective to prevent further damage to the works of such district. Before any such district has such beaver or muskrat trapped, it shall submit to the secretary of the commission the names and addresses of the trappers to do the trapping. If no written objection is received, stating the reasons for such objection, from the secretary within five days after the receipt of the names, they shall be deemed to be approved. No trapper who has been objected to in writing by the commission shall trap under this section. The district shall report to the commission every thirty days the number of beaver or muskrat killed or destroyed and shall forward with such report a fee of up to three dollars, as established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327, for each beaver so killed or destroyed. Under such circumstances, no permit shall be required to so kill or destroy such beaver or muskrat, but fees shall be paid for beaver killed as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 79, &#167; 1(3), (4), (5), p. 295; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 173, &#167; 1, p. 514; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 72, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 19; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-304.02; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 282; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc>