<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-809"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-809</statuteno><catchline>Violations; penalties; conservation or peace officer; powers and duties; regulations.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who violates the provisions of subsection (3) of section 37-805 or any regulations issued in implementation thereof or whoever fails to procure or violates the terms of any permit issued pursuant to section 37-805 shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) Any person who violates the provisions of subsection (8) of section 37-806 or any regulations issued pursuant to subsection (7) of section 37-806 or whoever fails to procure any permit required by subsection (11) of section 37-806 or violates the terms of any such permit shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Any conservation officer or any peace officer of this state or any municipality or county within this state shall have authority to conduct searches as provided by law, and to execute a warrant to search for and seize any equipment other than equipment owned or operated by any common or contract motor carrier under the jurisdiction of the Public Service Commission or the Interstate Commerce Commission, business records, wildlife, wild plants, or other contraband taken, used, or possessed in connection with any violation of the Nongame and Endangered Species Conservation Act. Any such officer or agent may, without a warrant, arrest any person whom he or she has probable cause to believe is violating, in his or her presence or view, the act or any regulation or permit provided for in the act. Any officer or agent who has made an arrest of a person in connection with any such violation may search such person or business records at the time of arrest and may seize any wildlife, wild plants, records, or property taken or used in connection with any such violation.</para><para>(4) Equipment other than equipment owned or operated by any common or contract motor carrier under the jurisdiction of the Public Service Commission or the Interstate Commerce Commission, wildlife, wild plants, records, or other contraband seized under the provisions of subsection (3) of this section shall be held by an officer or agent of the commission pending disposition of court proceedings, and thereafter be forfeited to this state for destruction or disposition as the commission may deem appropriate. Prior to forfeiture, the commission may direct the transfer of wildlife or wild plants so seized to a qualified zoological, botanical, educational, or scientific institution for safekeeping, with the costs thereof to be assessable to the defendant. The commission shall issue regulations to implement this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 145, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 188; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-437; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 359. </para></source></law></legaldoc>