<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id101" statutenumber="37-413"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id103">37-413</statuteno><catchline id="id104">Firearm hunter
education program; commission issue certificate; hunting, lawful when; apprentice
hunter education exemption certificate; fee.</catchline><para>(1) For the
purpose of establishing and administering a mandatory firearm hunter education
program for persons twelve through twenty-nine years of age who hunt with
a firearm or crossbow any species of game, game birds, or game animals, the
commission shall provide a program of firearm hunter education training leading
to obtaining a certificate of successful completion in the safe handling of
firearms and shall locate and train volunteer firearm hunter education instructors.
The program shall provide a training course having a minimum of (a) ten hours
of classroom instruction or (b) independent study on the part of the student
sufficient to pass an examination given by the commission followed by such
student's participation in a minimum of four hours of practical instruction.
The program shall provide instruction in the areas of safe firearms use, shooting
and sighting techniques, hunter ethics, game identification, and conservation
management. The commission shall issue a firearm hunter education certificate
of successful completion to persons having satisfactorily completed a firearm
hunter education course accredited by the commission and shall print, purchase,
or otherwise acquire materials as necessary for effective program operation.
The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for carrying
out and administering such programs.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person twenty-nine years of age or
younger to hunt with a firearm or crossbow any species of game, game birds,
or game animals except:</para>
<para>(a) A person under the age of twelve years who is accompanied by a person
nineteen years of age or older having a valid hunting permit;</para>
<para>(b) A person twelve through twenty-nine years of age who has on his
or her person proof of successful completion of a hunter education course
or a firearm hunter education course issued by the person's state or province
of residence or by an accredited program recognized by the commission; or</para>
<para>(c) A person twelve through twenty-nine years of age who has on his
or her person the appropriate hunting permit and an apprentice hunter education
exemption certificate issued by the commission pursuant to subsection (3)
of this section and who is accompanied as described in subsection (4) of this
section.</para>
<para>(3) An apprentice hunter education exemption certificate may be issued
to a person twelve through twenty-nine years of age, once during such person's
lifetime with one renewal, upon payment of a fee of five dollars and shall
expire at midnight on December 31 of the year for which the apprentice hunter
education exemption certificate is issued. The commission may adopt and promulgate
rules and regulations allowing for the issuance of apprentice hunter education
exemption certificates. All fees collected under this subsection shall be
remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the State Game Fund.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section, accompanied means under the direct
supervision of a person who is: (a) Nineteen years
of age or older having a valid hunting permit. If such person is nineteen years of age or older but not
older than twenty-nine years of age, he or she shall have also completed the
required course of instruction to receive a certificate of completion for
firearm hunter education if hunting with a firearm or crossbow as described
in subdivision (2)(b) of this section or for bow hunter education if hunting
with a bow and arrow as described in section 37-414; and (b) at all times in unaided
visual and verbal communication of no more than two persons having an apprentice
hunter education exemption certificate. This subsection does not prohibit
the use by such person nineteen years of age or older of ordinary prescription
eyeglasses or contact lenses or ordinary hearing instruments.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 766, &#167; 1, p. 2903; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 865, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 584, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1996, &#167; 37-104; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 123; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 111, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 305, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB690, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB195, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB871, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>