<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-421"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-421</statuteno><catchline>Combination hunting and fishing permits; persons eligible; exempt from payment of fees, when; special permits, limitation.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue an annual combination fishing and hunting permit upon application and payment of a fee of five dollars to (a) any Nebraska resident who is a veteran, who is sixty-four years of age or older, and who was discharged or separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions) or (b) any Nebraska resident who is sixty-nine years of age or older. A person who is issued a permit under this section shall be exempt from the payment of any additional fees provided by the laws of the State of Nebraska and established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327 for the privilege of fishing or hunting in Nebraska, except that such exemption shall not extend to the privilege of commercial fishing, trapping of fur-bearing animals, or hunting for deer, antelope, wild turkey, or any other species of fish and game on which the open season is limited to a restricted number of permits or to special permits for a restricted area or game management unit.</para><para>(2) A permit issued as provided in this section shall expire as provided in section 37-405. Permits issued under this section as it existed before January 1, 2006, shall not expire as provided in section 37-405.</para><para>(3) If disabled persons are unable by reason of physical infirmities to hunt and fish in the normal manner, the commission may issue special permits without cost to those persons to hunt and fish from a vehicle, but such permits shall not authorize any person to shoot from any public highway.</para><para>(4) The commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1204, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 138, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 79, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 434, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-214.04; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 227, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>