<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-623"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-623</statuteno><catchline>Illegally used nets, traps, ferrets, and devices; seizure and confiscation; destruction; return of guns, legal fish nets, or other hunting and fishing equipment; when made.</catchline><para>Every device, net, and trap and every ferret possessed, used, or attempted to be used by any person in taking any game contrary to the Game Law is hereby declared to be a public nuisance and subject to seizure and confiscation by any conservation officer or other person charged with the enforcement of the Game Law. Ferrets and every device, net, and trap, the use of which is wholly prohibited, shall be destroyed upon seizure. All guns and nets while being used illegally shall be seized upon the arrest of the person so using them, but all guns, legal fish nets, or other hunting or fishing equipment, used illegally which are seized for evidence upon arrest, shall be returned by the court to the person from whom such guns, legal fish nets, or other hunting or fishing equipment was seized following disposition of the case.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 112, VI, &#167; 10, p. 435; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 37-610; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 72, &#167; 3, p. 194; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 89, &#167; 17, p. 299; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 37-610; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 37-610; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 78, &#167; 8, p. 293; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 150, &#167; 1, p. 488; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 150, &#167; 9, p. 574; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 175, &#167; 5, p. 524; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 177, &#167; 1, p. 527; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 204, &#167; 2, p. 657; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 201; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 629, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 34, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-610; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 313; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 93. </para></source></law></legaldoc>