<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id120"><sectno id="id121">Sec. 14.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id122" statutenumber="37-497"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id124">37-497</statuteno><catchline id="id125">Raptors; protection; management; falconry license; captive propagation license; fees.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may take such steps as it deems necessary to provide for the protection and management of raptors.</para><para>(2) The commission may issue falconry licenses to permit the taking and possession of raptors for the purpose of practicing falconry. No such license may be issued to an applicant unless he or she is a resident of the state, has paid the fees required in this subsection, and has passed a written and oral examination concerning raptors given by the commission or an authorized representative of the commission. The commission shall charge a fee for each license of not more than seventeen dollars for persons fourteen to seventeen years of age and not more than forty-six dollars for persons eighteen years of age and older, as established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327. If the applicant fails to pass either examination or both of them, he or she shall not be entitled to reapply for a falconry license for a period of six months after the date of the examination. A person less than fourteen years of age shall not be issued a falconry license, and a person from fourteen to seventeen years of age may be issued such a license only if he or she is sponsored by an adult person who has a valid falconry license. All falconry licenses shall be nontransferable and shall expire three years after the date of issuance. If the commission is satisfied as to the competency and fitness of an applicant whose license has expired, a license may be renewed without requiring further examination under such terms and conditions as are established by the commission. Species of raptors which may be taken, captured, or held in possession shall include only those species authorized by the commission. The number of each species of raptors which may be taken, captured, or held in possession shall be subject to regulation by the commission.</para><para>(3) The commission may issue captive propagation licenses to permit the captive propagation of raptors. No such license may be issued to an applicant unless he or she is a resident of the state and has paid the fee required in this subsection. The fee for each license shall be not more than two hundred thirty dollars, as established by the commission pursuant to section 37-327. All such licenses shall be nontransferable, shall expire three years after the date of issuance, and may be renewed under terms and conditions established by the commission. The commission shall authorize the species and the number of each such species which may be taken, captured, acquired, or held in possession. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the issuance and conditions of captive propagation licenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 733, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 154, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 940, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 28; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-720; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 207; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
