<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-422"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-422</statuteno><catchline>Special daily fishing permits; fee;
form; requirements; commission; establish; educational fishing project permits.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may require special daily fishing permits on areas
designated by it and subject to intensive fishery management. Such permits
may be vended by mechanical or electronic methods. The commission may establish
the fee, form, and requirements of such special daily fishing permit, and
establish rules and regulations and
commission orders pursuant to section 37-314 governing seasons,
limits, methods of taking, open or closed waters, and such other regulations and commission orders as it
deems necessary on such designated areas. Such special daily fishing permit
shall be required of any and all persons fishing on the designated area and
shall be the only fishing permit required thereon. The commission may only
issue the permits authorized by this section on staffed areas or on portions
of staffed areas under its ownership or control which are intensively managed
or stocked for a high level of fish production.</para>
<para>(2) An educational fishing project permit may be issued to any instructor
of a university, college, or high school and his or her students participating
in an educational fishing project. Such persons shall be exempt from the payment
of any fees provided by the Game Law for the privilege of fishing in Nebraska
while participating in the project. Such exemption shall not extend to the
privilege of commercial fishing or to the privilege of fishing for any species
of fish on which an open season is limited to a restricted number of permits
or to special permits for a restricted area. The commission shall adopt and
promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out this subsection.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 212, &#167; 1, p. 573; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-204.02; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 132; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB499, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>