<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id20" statutenumber="37-450"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>37-450</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Permit to hunt elk; regulation and limitation by commission; issuance; fee; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The commission may issue permits for hunting elk and may adopt and promulgate separate and, when necessary, different rules and regulations therefor within the limitations prescribed in sections 37-447 and 37-452 for hunting deer.</para><para>(2) The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge (a) a nonrefundable application fee of not more than twelve dollars for a resident elk permit and not to exceed three times such amount for a nonresident elk permit and (b) a fee of not more than one hundred ninety-eight dollars for each resident elk permit issued and three times such amount for each nonresident elk permit issued. The commission may, pursuant to section 37-327, establish and charge a fee of not more than twenty-four dollars for residents and not more than seventy-two dollars for nonresidents for the issuance of a preference point or a bonus point, in addition to any application fee, in lieu of entering the draw for an elk permit during the application period for the random drawing.</para><para>(3) An applicant shall not be issued a resident elk permit that allows the harvest of an antlered elk more than once every five years. A person may only harvest one antlered elk in his or her lifetime except when harvesting an antlered elk with a limited permit to hunt elk pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of section 37-455 or an auction or lottery permit pursuant to section 37-455.01.</para><para>(4) The provisions for the distribution of deer permits and the authority of the commission to determine eligibility of applicants for permits as described in sections 37-447 and 37-452 shall also apply to the distribution of elk permits.</para><para>(5) Any person violating the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor and shall be fined at least two hundred dollars upon conviction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 160; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 306, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 162, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB299, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB105, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB41, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB94, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB745, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB287, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>