<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id6" statutenumber="37-448"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>37-448</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Special deer depredation
season; extension of existing deer hunting season; permit; issuance; fee;
free permits; when issued.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to rules and regulations
adopted and promulgated by the commission, the secretary of the commission
may designate, by order, special
deer depredation seasons or extensions of existing deer hunting seasons. The secretary may designate
a depredation season or an extension of an existing deer hunting season whenever
he or she determines that deer are causing excessive property damage. The
secretary shall specify the number of permits to be issued, the species of
deer allowed to be taken, the bag limit for such species including deer for
donation in accordance with the deer donation program established pursuant
to sections 37-1501 to 37-1510, the beginning and ending dates for the depredation
season or hunting season extension, shooting hours, the length of the depredation
season or hunting season extension, and the geographic area in which hunting
will be permitted. Hunting during a special depredation season or hunting
season extension shall be limited to residents, and the rules and regulations
shall allow use of any weapon permissible for use during the regular deer
season.</para>
<para>(2) The depredation season may commence not less than five days after
the first public announcement that the depredation season has been established.
Permits shall be issued in an impartial manner at a location determined by
the secretary. The commission shall, pursuant to section 37-327, establish
and charge a fee of not more than twenty-five dollars for a special depredation
season permit. The commission shall use the income from the sale of special
depredation season permits for abatement of damage caused by deer. The commission
shall also provide for an unlimited number of free permits for the taking
of antlerless deer upon request to any person owning or operating at least
twenty acres of farm or ranch land within the geographic area in which hunting
will be permitted and to any member of the immediate family of any such person
as defined in subdivision (2)(a) of section 37-455. A free permit shall be
valid only within such area and only during the designated deer depredation
season. Receipt of a depredation season permit shall not in any way affect
a person's eligibility for a regular season permit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 158; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1162, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB836, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB928, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB499, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>