<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id10">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id12" statutenumber="37-618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-618</statuteno><catchline id="id15">Suspension or
revocation in other jurisdiction; effect; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as otherwise provided in subsection
(3) of this section, any person whose privilege or permit to hunt, fish, or harvest fur has
been suspended or revoked in any jurisdiction within the United States or
Canada shall be prohibited from obtaining a permit for such activity in this
state during the period of suspension or revocation in the prosecuting jurisdiction
if the offense for which the privilege or
permit is suspended or revoked is an offense under the Game Law or would constitute grounds for suspension
or revocation under sections 37-614 to 37-617.</para>
<para>(2) If such person has previously
obtained a permit under the
Game Law for such activity, the permit shall become invalid and
shall be suspended for the same period as determined in the prosecuting jurisdiction.
The person shall immediately return the permit to the commission. No person
shall possess a permit which has been suspended or revoked under this section except as otherwise provided in subsection
(3) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) The commission
may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to create a process to (a)
review the suspension or revocation of a privilege or permit to hunt, fish,
or harvest fur imposed by any jurisdiction other than Nebraska to determine
if the offense for which the privilege or permit is suspended or revoked is
an offense under the Game Law or would constitute grounds for suspension or
revocation under sections 37-614 to 37-617 and (b) provide for a hearing,
if necessary, to confirm the suspension or revocation in Nebraska or reinstate
the privilege or affirm the eligibility of the person to purchase a permit
in Nebraska. The process may include an application for the review and a procedure
for screening applications to determine if the hearing before the commission
is necessary or appropriate.</para><para>(4) Any person who violates the provisions of
this section shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 308; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB41, &#167; 29.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>