<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-512"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-512</statuteno><catchline>Transfer of raw fur by carriers; tagging required; penalty.</catchline><para>Every express company and common carrier, their officers, agents, and servants, and every other person who (1) transfers or carries from one point to another within the state, (2) takes out of the state, or (3) receives, for the purpose of transferring from this state, any raw furs protected by the Game Law, except as permitted in this section, shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor. It shall be lawful for any express company, railroad, common carrier, or postmaster to receive raw furs protected by the Game Law for transportation from one point to another by express, baggage, or mail during the open season and ten days thereafter, or such further period as may be specifically granted a shipper by the commission, when such raw fur is accompanied by a tag furnished by the commission and placed upon the package giving the name of the consignee, the number of his or her fur-harvesting permit, and a description of the kind and number of each kind of raw fur in the shipment. A duplicate portion of such tag shall be filled out and sent to the secretary of the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 112, V, &#167; 8, p. 428; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 37-508; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 67, &#167; 2, p. 306; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 37-508; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 37-508; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 78, &#167; 6, p. 291; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 72, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 34, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 37-508; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 232. </para></source></law></legaldoc>