<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-108</statuteno><catchline>Game and Parks Commission; employees; appointment; compensation; interference with an election; prohibited.</catchline><para>The secretary, under the direction of the Game and Parks Commission acting in official session, is authorized to appoint such conservation officers, agents, office employees, and such other employees as may be required efficiently to enforce the laws for the protection of wildlife and for the administration of hatcheries, game preserves, recreational areas, and parks. In addition to the necessary conservation officers, the commission shall specify and require the appointment of such other agents and employees as may be required to execute its plans and projects and to administer its affairs, and the commission shall prescribe their duties. The commission shall fix the compensation of conservation officers and other agents and employees. Conservation officers and other agents and employees may be removed by the commission but only after a hearing. While retaining the right to vote as he or she may please and to express privately his or her opinion on all political subjects, no employee or officer of the commission shall use his or her official authority or influence for the purpose of interfering with an election or affecting the results thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 113, &#167; 11, p. 446; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-6511; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 174, &#167; 8, p. 643; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 81-6511; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-809; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 585, &#167; 11, p. 1980; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 398, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 81-809; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>