<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1254.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1254.06</statuteno><catchline>Boating under influence of alcoholic liquor or drug; blood test; withdrawing requirements; damages; liability.</catchline><para>(1) Any physician, registered nurse, other trained person employed by a licensed health care facility or health care service defined in the Health Care Facility Licensure Act, a clinical laboratory certified pursuant to the federal Clinical Laboratories Improvement Act of 1967, as amended, or Title XVIII or XIX of the federal Social Security Act, as amended, to withdraw human blood for scientific or medical purposes, or a hospital shall be an agent of the State of Nebraska when performing the act of withdrawing blood at the request of a peace officer pursuant to section 37-1254.02. The state shall be liable in damages for any illegal or negligent acts or omissions of such agents in performing the act of withdrawing blood. The agent shall not be individually liable in damages or otherwise for any act done or omitted in performing the act of withdrawing blood at the request of a peace officer pursuant to such section except for acts of willful, wanton, or gross negligence of the agent or of persons employed by such agent.</para><para>(2) Any person listed in subsection (1) of this section withdrawing a blood specimen for purposes of section 37-1254.02 shall, upon request, furnish to any law enforcement agency or the person being tested a certificate stating that such specimen was taken in a medically acceptable manner. The certificate shall be signed under oath before a notary public and shall be admissible in any proceeding as evidence of the statements contained in the certificate. The form of the certificate shall be prescribed by the Department of Health and Human Services and such forms shall be made available to the persons listed in subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 195, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 210, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1115, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 54.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>