<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-1284"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1284</statuteno><catchline>Certificate; loss or destruction;
replacement; subsequent purchaser, rights; recovery of original; duty of owner.</catchline><para>In the event of a lost or destroyed certificate of title, the owner
of the motorboat or the holder of a lien on the motorboat shall apply, upon
a form prescribed by the Department of Motor Vehicles, to any county treasurer or to
the department for
a certified copy of the certificate of title and shall pay the fee prescribed
by section 37-1287. The application shall be signed and sworn to by the person
making the application. The county treasurer, with
the approval of the department, or the department shall issue a certified
copy of the certificate of title to the person entitled to receive the certificate
of title. If the county treasurer's records
of the title have been destroyed pursuant to section 37-1279, the county treasurer shall issue a duplicate
certificate of title to the person entitled to receive the certificate upon
such showing as the county treasurer deems
sufficient. If the applicant cannot produce such proof of ownership, he or
she may apply directly to the department and submit such evidence as he or
she may have, and the department may, if it finds the evidence sufficient,
authorize the county treasurer to
issue a duplicate certificate of title. The new purchaser shall be entitled
to receive an original title upon presentation of the assigned duplicate copy
of the certificate of title, properly assigned to the new purchaser, to the
county treasurer as
prescribed in section 37-1278. Any purchaser of the motorboat may at the time
of purchase require the seller of the motorboat to indemnify him or her and
all subsequent purchasers of the motorboat against any loss which he, she,
or they may suffer by reason of any claim presented upon the original certificate.
In the event of the recovery of the original certificate of title by the owner,
he or she shall immediately surrender the certificate to the county treasurer or the department
for cancellation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 123, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 464, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 20.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>