<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1254.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1254.02</statuteno><catchline>Boating under influence of alcohol or controlled substance; implied consent to submit to chemical test; preliminary test; refusal; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who has in his or her actual physical control a motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state shall be deemed to have given his or her consent to submit to a chemical test of his or her blood or breath for the purpose of determining the amount of alcohol content in such blood or breath.</para><para>(2) Any law enforcement officer who has been duly authorized to make arrests for violations of laws of this state or ordinances of any city or village may require any person arrested for any offense arising out of acts alleged to have been committed while the person was in the actual physical control of a motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state under the influence of alcohol to submit to a chemical test of his or her blood or breath for the purpose of determining the alcohol content of such blood or breath when the officer has reasonable grounds to believe that the person was in the actual physical control of a motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state while under the influence of alcohol.</para><para>(3) Any law enforcement officer who has been duly authorized to make arrests for violations of laws of this state or ordinances of any city or village may require any person who has in his or her actual physical control a motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state to submit to a preliminary test of his or her breath for alcohol content if the officer has reasonable grounds to believe that such person has alcohol in his or her body or has committed any violation of this section and section 37-1254.01. Any person who refuses to submit to such preliminary breath test or whose preliminary breath test results indicate an alcohol content of eight-hundredths of one gram or more by weight of alcohol per two hundred ten liters of his or her breath shall be placed under arrest. Any person who refuses to submit to such preliminary breath test shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para><para>(4) Any person arrested pursuant to this section may, upon the direction of a law enforcement officer, be required to submit to a chemical test of his or her blood or breath for a determination of the alcohol content. Any person who refuses to submit to a chemical blood or breath test required pursuant to this section shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as part of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to be in the actual physical control of any motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state for any purpose for a period of six months from the date of such conviction. If the court places such person on probation or suspends the sentence for any reason, the court shall, as one of the conditions of probation or sentence suspension, order such person not to be in the actual physical control of any motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state for any purpose for a period of sixty days from the date of the order.</para><para>(5) Any person who is required to submit to a preliminary breath test or to a chemical blood or breath test pursuant to this section shall be advised of the consequences of refusing to submit to such test.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 195, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 176, &#167; 121; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 166, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 773, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>