<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1279"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1279</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of title; issuance; form;
county treasurer; duties;
filing.</catchline><para>(1) The county treasurer shall
issue the certificate of title. The county treasurer shall
sign and affix his or her seal to the original certificate of title and deliver
the certificate to the applicant if there are no liens on the motorboat. If
there are one or more liens on the motorboat, the certificate of title shall
be handled as provided in section 37-1282.  The county treasurer shall keep on hand
a sufficient supply of blank forms which shall be furnished and distributed
without charge to manufacturers, dealers, or other persons residing within
the county, except that certificates of title shall only be issued by the
county treasurer or
the Department of Motor Vehicles. Each county shall issue and file certificates
of title using the vehicle titling and registration computer system.</para>
<para>(2) Each county treasurer of
the various counties shall provide his or her seal without charge to the applicant
on any certificate of title, application for certificate of title, duplicate
copy, assignment or reassignment, power of attorney, statement, or affidavit
pertaining to the issuance of a certificate of title. The department shall
prescribe a uniform method of numbering certificates of title.</para>
<para>(3) The county treasurer shall
(a) file all certificates of title according to rules and regulations of the
department, (b) maintain in the office indices for such certificates of title,
(c) be authorized to destroy all previous records five years after a subsequent
transfer has been made on a motorboat, and (d) be authorized to destroy all
certificates of title and all supporting records and documents which have
been on file for a period of five years or more from the date of filing the
certificate or a notation of lien, whichever occurs later.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 123, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 464, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 16.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Certificate of title,</emphasis> negligent execution by government employee, see sections 13-910 and 81-8,219.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>