<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-1280"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1280</statuteno><catchline>Department of Motor Vehicles; powers
and duties; rules and regulations; cancellation of certificate of title.</catchline>
<para>The Department of Motor Vehicles shall adopt and promulgate rules and
regulations necessary to carry out sections 37-1275 to 37-1290, and the county treasurers shall conform to
the rules and regulations and act at the direction of the department. The
department shall also provide the county treasurers with
the necessary training for the proper administration of such sections. The
department shall receive and file in its office all instruments forwarded
to it by the county treasurers under
such sections and shall maintain indices covering the entire state for the
instruments so filed. These indices shall be by hull identification number
and alphabetically by the owner's name and shall be for the entire state and
not for individual counties. The department shall provide and furnish the
forms required by section 37-1286 to the county treasurers except manufacturers'
or importers' certificates. The department shall check with its records all
duplicate certificates of title received from the county treasurers. If it appears
that a certificate of title has been improperly issued, the department shall
cancel the certificate of title. Upon cancellation of any certificate of title,
the department shall notify the county treasurer who
issued the certificate, and the county treasurer shall
enter the cancellation upon his or her records. The department shall also
notify the person to whom such certificate of title was issued and any lienholders
appearing on the certificate of the cancellation and shall demand the surrender
of the certificate of title, but the cancellation shall not affect the validity
of any lien noted on the certificate. The holder of the certificate of title
shall return the certificate to the department immediately. If a certificate
of number has been issued pursuant to section 37-1216 to the holder of a certificate
of title so canceled, the department shall notify the commission. Upon receiving
the notice, the commission shall immediately cancel the certificate of number
and demand the return of the certificate of number and the holder of the certificate
of number shall return the certificate to the commission immediately.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 123, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 464, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>