<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1254.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1254.01</statuteno><catchline>Boating under influence of alcohol or controlled substance; penalty; probation; prohibit operation; city or village ordinances; alcoholism treatment program.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall be in the actual physical control of any motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state:</para><para>(a) While under the influence of alcohol or of any controlled substance as defined in section 28-401;</para><para>(b) When such person has a concentration of eight-hundredths of one gram or more by weight of alcohol per one hundred milliliters of his or her blood; or</para><para>(c) When such person has a concentration of eight-hundredths of one gram or more by weight of alcohol per two hundred ten liters of his or her breath.</para><para>(2) Any person who is in the actual physical control of any motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state while in a condition described in subsection (1) of this section shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor. Upon conviction the court shall, as part of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to be in the physical control of a motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state for any purpose for a period of six months from the date of such conviction, except that if the court places such person on probation or suspends the sentence for any reason, the court shall, as one of the conditions of probation or sentence suspension, order such person not to be in the physical control of any motorboat under propulsion upon the waters of this state for any purpose for a period of sixty days from the date of the order.</para><para>(3) Any city or village may enact ordinances in conformance with this section and section 37-1254.02.</para><para>(4) At the discretion of the court, any person convicted of violating this section or violating any city or village ordinance adopted in conformance with this section may be required to attend, at the convicted person's expense, an alcoholism treatment program as a term of probation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 195, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 166, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 773, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>