<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id165">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Game And Parks" id="id167" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="37-1254.11"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1254.11</statuteno><catchline>Boating under influence of alcoholic
liquor or drug; violation; sentencing; terms, defined; prior convictions;
use; prosecutor; present evidence; convicted person; rights.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes
of sentencing under section 37-1254.12:</para>
<para>(a) Prior
conviction means a conviction for which a final judgment has been entered
prior to the offense for which the sentence is being imposed as follows:</para>
<para>(i) For a
violation of section 37-1254.01:</para><para>(A) Any conviction for a violation of section
37-1254.01;</para><para>(B) Any conviction for a violation of a city or village ordinance
enacted in conformance with section 37-1254.01; or</para><para>(C) Any conviction under
a law of another state if, at the time of the conviction under the law of
such other state, the offense for which the person was convicted would have
been a violation of section 37-1254.01; or</para><para>(ii) For a violation of section 37-1254.02:</para>
<para>(A) Any conviction
for a violation of section 37-1254.02;</para><para>(B) Any conviction for a violation of a
city or village ordinance enacted in conformance with section 37-1254.02;
or</para><para>(C) Any conviction under a law of another state if, at the time
of the conviction under the law of such other state, the offense for which
the person was convicted would have been a violation of section 37-1254.02;
and</para><para>(b) Prior conviction includes any conviction under section 37-1254.01
or 37-1254.02, or any city or village ordinance enacted in conformance with
either of such sections, as such sections or city or village ordinances existed
at the time of such conviction regardless of subsequent amendments to any
of such sections or city or village ordinances.</para><para>(2) The prosecutor shall
present as evidence for purposes of sentence enhancement a court-certified
copy or an authenticated copy of a prior conviction in another state. The
court-certified or authenticated copy shall be prima facie evidence of such
prior conviction.</para><para>(3) For each conviction for a violation of section 37-1254.01 or
37-1254.02, the court shall, as part of the judgment of conviction, make a
finding on the record whether the convicted person has a usable prior conviction.
The convicted person shall be given the opportunity to review the record of
his or her prior convictions, bring mitigating facts to the attention of the
court prior to sentencing, and make objections on the record regarding the
validity of such prior convictions.</para><para>(4) A person arrested for a violation of
section 37-1254.01 or 37-1254.02 before January 1, 2012, but sentenced for
such violation on or after January 1, 2012, shall be sentenced according to
the provisions of section 37-1254.01 or 37-1254.02 in effect on the date of
arrest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 18.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>