<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-12,101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-12,101</statuteno><catchline>Local authority or state agency; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except for motorboats covered by section 37-12,100, the local authority or state agency having custody of an abandoned motorboat shall make an inquiry concerning the last-registered owner of such motorboat to the Department of Motor Vehicles.</para><para>(2) The local authority or state agency shall notify the last-registered owner, if any, that the motorboat in question has been determined to be abandoned and that, if unclaimed, either (a) it will be sold or will be offered at public auction after five days from the date such notice was mailed or (b) title will vest in the local authority or state agency thirty days after the date such notice was mailed. If the Department of Motor Vehicles also notifies the local authority or state agency that a lien or mortgage exists, such notice shall also be sent to the lienholder or mortgagee. Any person claiming such motorboat shall be required to pay the cost of removal and storage of such motorboat.</para><para>(3) Title to an abandoned motorboat, if unclaimed, shall vest in the local authority or state agency (a) five days after the date the notice is mailed if the motorboat will be sold or offered at public auction under subdivision (2)(a) of this section, (b) thirty days after the date the notice is mailed if the local authority or state agency will retain the motorboat, or (c) if the last-registered owner cannot be ascertained, when notice of such fact is received.</para><para>(4) After title to the abandoned motorboat vests pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, the local authority or state agency may retain for use, sell, or auction the abandoned motorboat. If the local authority or state agency has determined that the motorboat should be retained for use, the local authority or state agency shall, at the same time that the notice, if any, is mailed, publish in a newspaper of general circulation in the jurisdiction an announcement that the local authority or state agency intends to retain the abandoned vehicle for its use and that title will vest in the local authority or state agency thirty days after the publication.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 560, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc>