<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1211</statuteno><catchline>Motorboat; numbering required; operation
of unnumbered motorboat prohibited; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except
as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section and sections 37-1249
and 37-1250, every motorboat on the waters of this state shall be numbered
and no person shall operate or give permission for the operation of any vessel
on such waters unless the vessel is numbered in accordance with the State
Boat Act or in accordance with the laws of another state if the commission
has by regulation approved the numbering system of such state and unless the
certificate of number awarded to such vessel is in full force and effect and
the identifying number set forth in the certificate of number is displayed
and legible on each side of the forward half of the vessel.</para>
<para>(2) The owner of each motorboat may operate or give permission for the
operation of such vessel for thirty days from the date the vessel was acquired
in anticipation of the vessel being numbered. A duly executed bill of sale,
certificate of title, or other satisfactory evidence of the right of possession
of the vessel as prescribed
by the Department of Motor Vehicles must be available for inspection
at all times from the operator of the vessel.</para>
<para>(3) The owner or his or her invitee who operates a personal watercraft
on any body of water (a) which is entirely upon privately owned land owned
by only one person or one family and, if leased, leased by only one person
or one family, (b) which does not connect by any permanent or intermittent
inflow or outflow with other water outside such land, and (c) which is not
operated on a commercial basis for profit may operate any personal watercraft
on such body of water without complying with subsection (1) of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 21, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 376, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 394; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>