<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id16">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" id="id18" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="37-1403"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1403</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Invasive Species Council;
created; members; expenses; Game and Parks Commission; rules and regulations;
meetings.</catchline><para>(1)
The Nebraska Invasive Species Council is created. Members of the council shall
serve without compensation and shall not be reimbursed for expenses associated
with their service on the council. The Game and Parks Commission shall provide
administrative support to the council to carry out the council's duties, and
the commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out
sections 37-1401 to 37-1406. </para>
<para>(2) Voting
members of the council shall be appointed by the Governor and shall include
a representative of:</para><para>(a) An electric generating utility;</para><para>(b) The Department of
Agriculture;</para><para>(c) The Game and Parks Commission;</para><para>(d) The Nebraska Forest
Service of the University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture and Natural
Resources;</para><para>(e) The University of Nebraska-Lincoln;</para><para>(f) The Nebraska Cooperative
Fish and Wildlife Research Unit of the University of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(g) The Nebraska Weed Control
Association; and</para><para>(h)
The Nebraska Association of Resources Districts.</para><para>(3) Voting members of the council shall
also include up to five members at large appointed by the Governor who shall
represent public interests, at least three of which shall represent agricultural
land owner interests.</para><para>(4)
Nonvoting, ex officio members of the council shall include a representative
of:</para><para>(a)
The Midwest Region of the National Park Service of the United States Department
of the Interior;</para><para>(b)
The Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of the United States Department
of Agriculture;</para><para>(c)
The Natural Resources Conservation Service of the United States Department
of Agriculture;</para><para>(d)
The United States Geological Survey; and</para><para>(e) The Nature Conservancy, Nebraska Field Office.</para>
<para>(5) The council
may seek additional advisory support from representatives of relevant federal,
state, or local agencies as it deems necessary to accomplish its duties.</para>
<para>(6) The council shall
select a chairperson from among its members. The council shall meet at the
call of the chairperson or upon the request of a majority of the members.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB391, &#167; 13.</para><effectivedate>April 6, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>