<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-1286"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1286</statuteno><catchline>Forms; contents; assignment of hull
identification number; fee.</catchline><para>A certificate of title shall
be printed upon safety security paper to be selected by the Department of
Motor Vehicles. The certificate of title, manufacturer's statement of origin,
and assignment of manufacturer's certificate shall be upon forms prescribed
by the department and may include county of issuance, date of issuance, certificate
of title number, previous certificate of title number, name and address of
the owner, acquisition date, manufacturer's name, model year, hull identification
number, hull material, propulsion, hull length, issuing county treasurer's signature and
official seal, and sufficient space for the notation and release of liens,
mortgages, or encumbrances, if any. If a motorboat does not have a hull identification
number, the state shall assign a hull identification number.</para>
<para>An assignment of certificate of title shall appear on each certificate
of title and shall include a statement that the owner of the motorboat assigns
all his or her right, title, and interest in the motorboat, the name and address
of the assignee, the name and address of the lienholder or secured party,
if any, and the signature of the owner.</para>
<para>A reassignment by a dealer shall appear on each certificate of title
and shall include a statement that the dealer assigns all his or her right,
title, and interest in the motorboat, the name and address of the assignee,
the name and address of the lienholder or secured party, if any, and the signature
of the dealer or designated representative. Reassignments shall be printed
on the reverse side of each certificate of title as many times as convenient.
The department may, with the approval of the Attorney General, require additional
information on such forms.</para>
<para>The county treasurer, subject
to the approval of the department, shall assign a distinguishing hull identification
number to any homebuilt motorboat or any motorboat manufactured prior to November
1, 1972. Hull identification numbers shall be assigned and affixed in conformity
with the Federal Boat Safety Act of 1971. The county treasurer shall charge a nonrefundable
fee of twenty dollars for each hull identification number and shall remit
the fee to the department. The department shall remit the fees to the State
Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 123, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 464, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 720, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 22.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>