<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1804"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1804</statuteno><catchline>Water Recreation Enhancement Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Water Recreation Enhancement Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Game and Parks Commission. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund any money transferred to the fund by the Legislature and such donations, gifts, bequests, or other money received from any federal or state agency or public or private source. Except as otherwise provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, the fund shall be used for water and recreational projects pursuant to the Water Recreation Enhancement Act. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the fund.</para><para>(2) For any amount credited to the fund from a source other than a transfer authorized by the Legislature, the State Treasurer shall transfer an equal amount from the Water Recreation Enhancement Fund to the Jobs and Economic Development Initiative Fund at the end of the fiscal year in which such funds were credited, on such dates as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services to be used pursuant to section 61-405.</para><para>(3) Transfers may be made from the investment earnings in the Water Recreation Enhancement Fund to the Panhandle Improvement Project Cash Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer one million dollars on July 1, 2023, or as soon thereafter as administratively possible, from the Water Recreation Enhancement Fund to the Panhandle Improvement Project Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Panhandle Improvement Project Cash Fund,</emphasis> see section 81-1213.03.</para><para><emphasis>Water Recreation Enhancement Act,</emphasis> see section 37-1801.</para>></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>