<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game And Parks" statutenumber="37-1012"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1012</statuteno><catchline>Responsibility for fences.</catchline><para>(1) The Game and Parks Commission shall have the same responsibility with regard to division fences as a private landowner as provided in sections 34-102 to 34-117, except that in those areas where a state recreational trail is developed, the commission shall have the same responsibility as a railroad as provided in sections 74-601 to 74-604, but the type of fence required under section 74-601 shall not be required for those areas where a state recreational trail is developed. All fences shall be constructed and maintained as required under this subsection unless such construction and maintenance is waived in writing by affected adjoining landowners. The commission shall be responsible for the construction and replacement cost of any fence agreed to by the commission and adjoining landowner. The commission shall also be responsible for providing supplies for the maintenance of any fence along a state recreational trail or for the reimbursement to the adjoining landowner for the cost of supplies for the maintenance of any fence along a state recreational trail. The adjoining landowner shall be responsible for the maintenance of the fence. In such areas the type of fence may be (a) wire fence of at least four barbed wires, of a size not less than twelve and one-half gauge fencing wire, to be secured to posts, the posts to be at no greater distance than one rod from each other, or (b) a fence of any type that is agreed to by the commission and adjoining landowners. All fences constructed under either subdivision (a) or (b) of this subsection shall be deemed to be manifestly designed to exclude intruders for the purposes of subdivision (1)(c) of section 28-521.</para><para>(2) The responsibility of the commission for fences along a state recreational trail shall not exceed the amount appropriated to the commission by the Legislature for such purpose during any biennium, except that the commission may use any funds specifically gifted or obtained by grant application to the commission the sole purpose of which is to provide fencing for a state recreational trail.</para><para>(3) The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 739, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 81-815.61; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 387; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 701, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB108, &#167; 8.</para></source></law></legaldoc>