<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1278"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1278</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of title; application;
issuance; transfer of motorboat.</catchline><para>(1) Application for a certificate
of title shall be presented to the county treasurer, shall
be made upon a form prescribed by the Department of Motor Vehicles, and shall
be accompanied by the fee prescribed in section 37-1287. The owner of a motorboat
for which a certificate of title is required shall obtain a certificate of
title prior to registration required under section 37-1214.</para>
<para>(2) If a certificate of title has previously been issued for the motorboat
in this state, the application for a new certificate of title shall be accompanied
by the certificate of title duly assigned. If a certificate of title has not
previously been issued for the motorboat in this state, the application shall
be accompanied by a certificate of number from this state, a manufacturer's
or importer's certificate, a duly certified copy thereof, proof of purchase
from a governmental agency or political subdivision, a certificate of title
from another state, or a court order issued by a court of record, a manufacturer's
certificate of origin, or an assigned registration certificate, if the motorboat
was brought into this state from a state which does not have a certificate
of title law. The county treasurer shall
retain the evidence of title presented by the applicant on which the certificate
of title is issued. When the evidence of title presented by the applicant
is a certificate of title or an assigned registration certificate issued by
another state, the department shall notify the state of prior issuance that
the certificate has been surrendered. If a certificate of title has not previously
been issued for the motorboat in this state and the applicant is unable to
provide such documentation, the applicant may apply for a bonded certificate
of title as prescribed in section 37-1278.01.</para>
<para>(3) The county treasurer shall
use reasonable diligence in ascertaining whether or not the statements in
the application for a certificate of title are true by checking the application
and documents accompanying the same with the records of motorboats in his
or her office. If he or she is satisfied that the applicant is the owner of
the motorboat and that the application is in the proper form, the county treasurer shall issue a certificate
of title over his or her signature and sealed with his or her seal.</para>
<para>(4) In the case of the sale of a motorboat, the certificate of title
shall be obtained in the name of the purchaser upon application signed by
the purchaser, except that for titles to be held by husband and wife, applications
may be accepted by the county treasurer upon
the signature of either spouse as a signature for himself or herself and as
an agent for his or her spouse.</para>
<para>(5) In all cases of transfers of motorboats, the application for a certificate
of title shall be filed within thirty days after the delivery of the motorboat.
A dealer need not apply for a certificate of title for a motorboat in stock
or acquired for stock purposes, but upon transfer of a motorboat in stock
or acquired for stock purposes, the dealer shall give the transferee a reassignment
of the certificate of title on the motorboat or an assignment of a manufacturer's
or importer's certificate. If all reassignments printed on the certificate
of title have been used, the dealer shall obtain title in his or her name
prior to any subsequent transfer.</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 123, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 464, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 635, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 720, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1317, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 15.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Certificate of title,</emphasis> negligent execution by government employee, see sections 13-910 and 81-8,219.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>