<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id790"><amendatorysection chaptername="Game and Parks" statutenumber="37-1726"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>37-1726</statuteno><catchline>Process for selection of construction manager and entering into construction manager-general contractor contract.</catchline><para>(1) The process for selecting a construction manager and entering into a construction manager-general contractor contract shall be in accordance with this section and sections 37-1727 to 37-1729.</para><para>(2) The commission shall prepare a request for qualifications for construction manager-general contractor contract proposals and shall prequalify construction managers. The request for qualifications shall describe the project in sufficient detail to permit a construction manager to respond. The request for qualifications shall identify the maximum number of eligible construction managers the commission will place on a short list as qualified and eligible to receive a request for proposals.</para><para>(3) The request for qualifications shall be (a) published in a newspaper of statewide circulation at least thirty days prior to the deadline for receiving the request for qualifications and (b) sent by first-class mail to any construction manager upon request.</para><para>(4) The commission shall create a short list of qualified and eligible construction managers in accordance with the guidelines adopted pursuant to section 37-1720. The commission shall select at least two construction managers, except that if only one construction manager has responded to the request for qualifications, the commission may, in its discretion, proceed or cancel the procurement. The request for proposals shall be sent only to the construction managers placed on the short list.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB775, &#167; 27. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>