<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Newspapers And Periodicals" statutenumber="63-105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>63-105</statuteno><catchline>Digital voice newspaper delivery system; legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(a) Newspapers are a significant and important source of daily information;</para><para>(b) As a written form of media, newspapers are able to provide indepth coverage of issues as well as coverage of a breadth of issues which may be absent in other electronic or broadcast media;</para><para>(c) While a newspaper's written format has advantages, such written format severely limits the ability of blind and other print-reading-impaired persons to obtain information from newspapers;</para><para>(d) This information deficit contributes to an unemployment rate estimated at seventy-five percent among working-age blind persons to whom the availability of such detailed news coverage would vastly improve opportunities for meaningful employment;</para><para>(e) There are a significant number of blind and other print-reading-impaired persons in Nebraska who would benefit from having timely and complete access to local and national newspapers;</para><para>(f) Due to technological advances, newspapers can be efficiently and effectively distributed by voice to enable access by blind and other print-reading-impaired persons; and</para><para>(g) The state should maintain a system by which blind and other print-reading-impaired persons can access the information newspapers provide.</para><para>(2) The purpose of this section and section 63-106 is to provide a digital voice newspaper delivery system to enable blind and other print-reading-impaired persons to access newspapers in a timely and comprehensive manner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 352, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 