<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Primary Class" statutenumber="15-725"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-725</statuteno><catchline>Public improvements; special tax assessments.</catchline><para>Special tax assessments to pay cost of local improvements, except special assessments for sidewalk purposes or as herein otherwise provided, shall be made in the manner following: (1) Assessment shall be made on the district by resolution of the council at any meeting, stating cost of the improvement and benefit accruing to the property in the district to be taxed, which, with the vote by yeas and nays, shall be recorded in the minutes. Therewith shall be submitted a proposed distribution of the tax on each separate property to be taxed subject to action of the board of equalization as prescribed therein; and (2) notice of time of assessment shall be published in some newspaper published and of general circulation in the city ten days before the assessment, and that the council will sit as a board of equalization to distribute the tax at a time in such notice fixed, not less than five days after such assessment, and the proper distribution of such special tax shall be open to examination of all persons interested. Property shall not be specially taxed for more than the total cost of the improvement nor more than the special benefit accruing thereto by the improvement. If the aggregate tax be less than the cost of improvement the excess shall be paid from the general fund. Special taxes may be assessed as the improvement progresses and as soon as completed in front of or along property taxed, or when the whole is complete, as the council shall determine. Special assessments for local benefits shall be a lien on all property so specially benefited superior and prior to all other liens save general taxes or other special assessments and equal therewith. If any special assessment be declared void, or doubt of its validity exist, the mayor and council, to pay the cost of improvement, may make a reassessment thereof on the original estate within the district, and any sums paid on the original assessment shall be credited to the property on which it was paid and any excess refunded to the owner paying it, with lawful interest. Taxes reassessed and not paid shall be enforced and collected as other special taxes. No special tax or assessment which the mayor and council acquire jurisdiction to make shall be void for any irregularity, defect, error or informality in procedure, in levy or equalization thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 102, p. 109; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4535; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3921; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-714; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-725.</para></source><annotation><para>Reassessment of benefits is provided for when original assessment is invalid. Shanahan v. Johnson, 170 Neb. 399, 102 N.W.2d 858 (1960).</para><para>Blanket notice of sitting of council as board of equalization is sufficient. Price v. City of Lincoln, 103 Neb. 366, 171 N.W. 921 (1919).</para><para>When lots are subdivided, assessment for paving is made on equitable basis. Lansing v. City of Lincoln, 32 Neb. 457, 49 N.W. 650 (1891).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>