
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-208"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-208</statuteno><catchline>Signs and obstructions on streets and public property; traffic and safety regulations; powers.</catchline><para>A city of the primary class shall have the power to (1) prevent and remove all encroachments on streets, avenues, alleys, and other city property, (2) prevent and punish horseracing, fast driving or riding in the streets, highways, alleys, bridges, or other places in the city, (3) regulate all games, practices, or amusements within the city likely to result in damage to any person or property, (4) regulate the riding, driving, or passing along any street of the city, (5) regulate and prevent the use of streets, sidewalks, and public grounds for signs, signposts, awnings, telephone or other poles, racks, bulletin boards, and the posting of handbills and advertisements, (6) regulate traffic and sales upon the streets, (7) prohibit and punish cruelty to animals, and (8) regulate and prevent the moving of buildings through or upon the streets.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 129, IX, p. 129; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4421; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3805; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-208; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-208; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 27. </para></source><annotation><para>The fact that the Legislature enacts a law making driving a motor vehicle while intoxicated a crime, does not abrogate city ordinance defining and prescribing a penalty for same offense, or deprive municipality of power to legislate on same subject in future. State v. Hauser, 137 Neb. 138, 288 N.W. 518 (1939).</para><para>City of Lincoln does not have power under home rule charter to require by ordinance a sign painter to pay ten dollars annual license fee in addition to inspectors' regulatory permit and fee of one dollar for each sign. State v. Wiggenjost, 130 Neb. 450, 265 N.W. 422 (1936).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>