<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-316"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>15-316</statuteno><catchline>City clerk; duties; deputy.</catchline><para>The city clerk of a city of the primary class shall have the custody of all laws and ordinances and shall keep a correct journal of the proceedings of the city council. After<emphasis type="italic" /> the period of time specified by the State Records Administrator pursuant to the Records Management Act, the city clerk may transfer such journal of the proceedings of the city council to the State Archives of the Nebraska State Historical Society, for permanent preservation. The city clerk shall keep a correct record of all outstanding bonds against the city showing the number and amount of each, for what and to whom issued, and when purchased, paid, or canceled, and shall make an annual report showing particularly the bonds issued and sold during the year, and the terms of sale, with each item of expense thereof. The city clerk shall perform such other or further duties as may be required of him or her by ordinances of the city. The city clerk shall also make a monthly report to the city council showing the amount appropriated to each fund, and the whole amount of funds drawn thereon, which report shall be recorded in the minutes. The city clerk may, if the city council deem assistance necessary, appoint a deputy who shall give a bond in favor of the city the same as is required of the city clerk.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 30, p. 79; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4493; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3879; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-316; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-316; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 224, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 93. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Joint control of funds by principal and surety on bond,</emphasis> see section 11-130.</para><para><emphasis>Records Management Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1220.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>