<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Primary Class" statutenumber="15-702.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-702.01</statuteno><catchline>Controlled-access facilities; designation.</catchline><para>A city of the primary class shall have the power to designate and establish controlled-access facilities, and may design, construct, maintain, improve, alter, and vacate such facilities, and may regulate, restrict, or prohibit access to such facilities so as best to serve the traffic for which such facilities are intended. Such a city may provide for the elimination of intersections at grade with existing roads, streets, highways or alleys, if the public interest shall be served thereby. An existing road, street, alley or other traffic facility may be included within such facilities or such facilities may include new or additional roads, streets, highways, or the like. In order to carry out the purposes of this section, the city, in addition to any other powers it may have, may acquire, in private or public property, such rights of access as are deemed necessary, including but not necessarily limited to air, light, view, egress, and ingress. Such acquisitions may be by gift, devise, purchase, agreement, adverse possession, prescription, condemnation, or otherwise as provided by law and may be in fee simple absolute or in any lesser estate or interest. The city may make provision to mitigate damages caused by such acquisitions, terms, and conditions regarding the abandonment or reverter of such acquisitions, and any other provisions or conditions that are desirable for the needs of the city and the general welfare of the public.</para><para>No automotive service stations or other commercial establishments for serving motor vehicle users shall be constructed or located on the publicly owned right-of-way of, or on any publicly owned or publicly leased land used for, or in connection with, a controlled-access facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 45, &#167; 1, p. 226.</para></source></law></legaldoc>