<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Primary Class" statutenumber="15-905"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-905</statuteno><catchline>Building regulations; zoning; distance from city authorized; powers granted.</catchline><para>Every city of the primary class shall have power to regulate in the area which is within the city or within three miles of the corporate limits of the city and outside of any organized city or village, and except as to construction on farmsteads outside of the corporate limits (1) the minimum standards of construction of buildings, dwellings and other structures, in order to provide safe and sound condition thereof for the preservation of health, safety, security and general welfare, which standards may include regulations as to electric wiring, heating, plumbing, pipefitting, sewer connections, ventilation, size of habitable rooms, and the method of constructing buildings, dwellings and other structures, and to provide for inspection thereof, and building permits and fees therefor, (2) the removal and tearing down of buildings, dwellings, and other structures in such areas which constitute nuisances because of the dilapidated, unsafe, or rundown condition or conditions, and (3) except as to the United States of America, the State of Nebraska, a county or village, in the area outside of the corporate limits of the city of the primary class, the nature, kind, and manner of constructing streets, alleys, sidewalks, curbing or abridging curbs, driveway approaches constructed on or to public right-of-way, and sewage disposal facilities. A farmstead is defined as property of twenty acres or more which produces one thousand dollars or more of farm products each year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 57, &#167; 3, p. 240; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 40, &#167; 2, p. 233.</para></source></law></legaldoc>