<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-848"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-848</statuteno><catchline>Deposit of city funds; limitations; city treasurer liability.</catchline><para>The city treasurer shall not have on deposit in any bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution at any time more than the maximum amount of the bond given by such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution if the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution gives a surety bond, nor in any bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution giving a personal bond, more than one-half of the amount of the bond of such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution. The amount on deposit plus accretions at any time with any such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution shall not in either case exceed the paid-up capital stock and surplus of such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution. The city treasurer shall not be liable for any loss sustained by reason of the failure of any such bonded depository whose bond shall have been duly approved by the city attorney as provided by section 15-846 or which has, in lieu of a surety bond, given security as provided by section 15-847. Section 77-2366 shall apply to deposits in capital stock financial institutions. Section 77-2365.01 shall apply to deposits in qualifying mutual financial institutions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 54, &#167; 4, p. 234; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 440, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 33, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 384, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1274, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 17.</para></source></law></legaldoc>