
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" id="id00" statutenumber="15-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-101</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Cities of the primary class, defined; population required.</catchline><para id="id00">All cities having more than one hundred thousand and less than four hundred thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census shall be known as cities of the primary class. The population of a city of the primary class shall consist of the people residing within the territorial boundaries of such city and the residents of any territory duly and properly annexed to such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4404; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3780; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-101; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 50, &#167; 2, p. 171; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 58, &#167; 2, p. 216; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 85, &#167; 2, p. 328; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 726, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB820, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>A city may put into its home rule charter any provisions that it deems proper so long as they do not run contrary to the Constitution or to any general statute. Eppley Hotels Co. v. City of Lincoln, 133 Neb. 550, 276 N.W. 196 (1937).</para><para>In matters relating exclusively to local and municipal affairs, home rule charter prevails over conflicting provisions in statute. Pester v. City of Lincoln, 127 Neb. 440, 255 N.W. 923 (1934).</para><para>Home rule charter may not contravene Constitution or general statutes. Schroeder v. Zehrung, 108 Neb. 573, 188 N.W. 237 (1922).</para><para>Classification is not special legislation although only one city in state falls within class. State ex rel. Pentzer v. Malone, 74 Neb. 645, 105 N.W. 893 (1905).</para><para>Act was not void as to tax commissioners, nor was it amendatory of state revenue law. State ex rel. Prout v. Aitken, 62 Neb. 428, 87 N.W. 153 (1901).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>