<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-808"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-808</statuteno><catchline>Board of equalization; hearings; duties.</catchline><para>The city council sitting as a board of equalization shall hold a session of not less than three or more than thirty days annually commencing on the first Tuesday after the third Monday in June and shall have power:</para><para>(1) To assess any taxable property, real and personal, not assessed;</para><para>(2) To review assessments made and correct the same as appears to be just. The board shall not increase the assessment of any person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation until such person, partnership, limited liability company, or corporation has been notified by the board to appear and show cause, if any, why the assessment should not be increased. If personal service of such notice cannot be made in the city, notice may be given by publication and it shall be sufficient if such notice is published in one issue of a daily paper of general circulation within the city; and</para><para>(3) To equalize the assessments of all taxable property in the city and to correct any errors in the listing or value thereof. The city council sitting as a board of equalization shall be authorized and empowered to meet at any time for the purpose of equalizing assessment of any omitted or undervalued property and to add to the assessment rolls any taxable property not included.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 78, p. 99; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 9, &#167; 7, p. 79; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4548; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3935; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-806; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-808; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 39, &#167; 1, p. 167; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 132.</para></source><annotation><para>Owner of tax exempt real estate is entitled to enjoin collection of taxes thereon even though statute provides a remedy, inasmuch as tax is absolutely void. East Lincoln Lodge No. 210, A.F. &amp; A.M. v. City of Lincoln, 131 Neb. 379, 268 N.W. 91 (1936).</para><para>Upon notice, board may assess property omitted from list. White v. City of Lincoln, 79 Neb. 153, 112 N.W. 369 (1907).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>