<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-841"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>15-841</statuteno><catchline>Claims; allowance; disallowance; appeal.</catchline><para>Any taxpayer of a city of the primary class, after the allowance in whole or in part of any liquidated or unliquidated claim, or the claimant, after the disallowance in whole or in part of any such claim, may appeal therefrom to the district court of the county in which the city is situated in accordance with the procedures set forth in sections 15-1201 to 15-1205. In an appeal by a taxpayer in case the claimant finally recovers judgment for as great a sum exclusive of interest as was allowed by the city council, such appellant shall pay all costs of such appeal. In an appeal by a claimant in case claimant fails to recover as great a sum exclusive of interest as was allowed by the city council, such claimant shall pay all costs. No warrant shall issue for the payment of any such claim until the appeal is finally determined. No appeal bond shall be required of the city by any court in case of appeal by the city, and judgment shall be stayed pending such appeal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 126, p. 124; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4581; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3968; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-840; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-841; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 59, &#167; 2, p. 196; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 52, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 149. </para></source><annotation><para>In a wage claim brought under this section against a city of the primary class, there is nothing in the plain language of section 48-1231 that requires an employee to plead a specific cause of action for attorney fees or to file a separate proceeding for attorney fees in order to receive an award of attorney fees under the Nebraska Wage Payment and Collection Act. Rauscher v. City of Lincoln, 269 Neb. 267, 691 N.W.2d 844 (2005).</para><para>Concerning a contract claim against a city of the primary class, section 15-840 requires that such claim be filed with the city clerk and disallowed before a claimant, pursuant to this section, may timely appeal from the city's disallowance and thereby become entitled to invoke a district court's power to adjudicate the merit of the disallowed claim. Andrews v. City of Lincoln, 224 Neb. 748, 401 N.W.2d 467 (1987).</para><para>An appeal from the disallowance of a claim against a city of the primary class is perfected by filing a notice of appeal and bond. The filing of a transcript is not a jurisdictional requirement. Cole Investment Co. v. City of Lincoln, 213 Neb. 422, 329 N.W.2d 356 (1983).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>