<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id140">
<sectno id="id141">Sec. 12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities of the Primary Class" id="id142" statutenumber="15-258"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id144">15-258</statuteno><catchline id="id145">Billiard halls;
disorderly houses; desecration of Sabbath.</catchline><para>A city
of the primary class may restrain, prohibit, and suppress unlicensed tippling
shops, billiard tables, bowling alleys, houses of prostitution, opium joints,
dens, and other disorderly houses and practices, games, gambling houses, desecration
of the Sabbath day, commonly called Sunday, and may prohibit all public amusements,
shows, exhibitions, or ordinary business pursuits upon such day, all lotteries,
all fraudulent devices and practices for the purposes of obtaining money or
property, all shooting galleries except
as provided in the Nebraska Shooting Range Protection Act, and
all kinds of public indecencies, except that nothing in this section shall
be construed to apply to bingo, lotteries, lotteries by the sale of pickle
cards, or raffles conducted in accordance with the Nebraska Bingo Act, the
Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act, the Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act, the
Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act, or the State Lottery Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 129, LVIII, p. 142; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4468; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3853; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-256; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-258; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 187; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 849, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 138, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB503, &#167; 12.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Bingo Act,</emphasis> see section 9-201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Pickle Card Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Shooting Range Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 37-1301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Small Lottery and Raffle Act,</emphasis> see section 9-501.</para><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Ordinance prohibiting all business except of necessity on Sunday is not void as discriminatory. Liberman v. State, 26 Neb. 464, 42 N.W. 419 (1889).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>