<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-735"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>15-735</statuteno><catchline>Special sidewalk assessments; collection.</catchline><para>Special sidewalk assessments assessed as provided in section 15-734 may be collected:</para><para>(1) In the manner usual for the collection or foreclosure of county taxes against real estate;</para><para>(2) By foreclosure as in case of county taxes against real estate. In<emphasis type="italic" /> the foreclosure of such special sidewalk assessments, any number of parties, owners of abutting property against which property a special sidewalk assessment has been made, may be made parties defendant, and any number of special sidewalk assessments may be foreclosed in one action, the decree, however, to be separate as to each particular piece of abutting property against which such special sidewalk assessments have been levied. A<emphasis type="italic" /> certified copy by the city clerk of the action of the city council in making such special sidewalk assessments shall be received in evidence as prima facie evidence of the regularity of all proceedings in the matter of making and levying such special sidewalk assessments, and such special sidewalk assessments shall constitute a lien prior and superior to all other liens except liens for taxes or other special assessments upon such abutting property. In<emphasis type="italic" /> the foreclosure of such special assessments, the action may be brought in the name of the city against any and all parties subject to the payment of such special sidewalk assessments in one or more actions, and the city may become a purchaser thereof for an amount not exceeding the amount of the special sidewalk assessment and interest and penalties thereon; or</para><para>(3) The city clerk, upon the request of the city council, shall, under seal of the city, make out a statement containing a description of the property against which special sidewalk assessments are delinquent, the amount of such special sidewalk assessments together with interest and penalties thereon, the name of the owner of such abutting property at the time of the levy, and the date of the levy, and shall transmit the same to the clerk of the district court. Upon request of the city the clerk of the district court shall issue an order of sale of such abutting property and deliver the same to the county sheriff, who shall thereupon cause such property to be advertised and sold as in case of sale of real estate under judgment and execution, except that it shall not be necessary for the county sheriff to cause such property to be appraised. Upon sale the county sheriff shall report the sale thereof to the district court for confirmation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 16, &#167; 109, p. 116; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 4542; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3928; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 15-721; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 15-735; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 125. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>