<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-271"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>15-271</statuteno><catchline>Offstreet parking; revenue bonds; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) In order to pay the cost required by any purchase, construction, lease, or condemnation of property and equipping of offstreet motor vehicle parking facilities, or the enlargement of presently owned offstreet motor vehicle parking facilities, a city of the primary class may issue revenue bonds to provide the funds for such improvements, except<emphasis type="italic" /> that any such city may not issue revenue bonds under sections 15-269 to 15-276 to acquire any privately owned parking garage or privately owned commercial parking lot having space for the parking of two hundred or more motor vehicles.</para><para>(2) Any ordinance authorizing such revenue bonds may contain such covenants and provisions to protect and safeguard the security of the holders of such bonds as shall be deemed necessary to assure the prompt payment of the principal thereof and the interest thereon.</para><para>(3) Such revenue bonds shall not be sold at discounts exceeding five percent, and such bonds shall not bear interest in excess of the rate of interest specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature. Such bonds shall be issued for such terms as the ordinance authorizing them shall prescribe but shall not mature later than fifty years after the date of issuance thereof.</para><para>(4) Any such revenue bonds which may be issued shall not be included in computing the maximum amount of bonds which the issuing city of the primary class may be authorized to issue under its charter or any statute of this state. If any city has installed or installs onstreet parking meters, it may pledge all or any part of the revenue of such parking meters, not previously pledged, as security for the bonds authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 51, &#167; 3, p. 186; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 933, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 81. </para><operativedate>November 14, 2020</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>