<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-1105"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>15-1105</statuteno><catchline>Planning director; duties; commission; hearings.</catchline><para>The planning director of a city of the primary class shall be responsible for preparing any proposed zoning ordinance and for submitting such ordinance to the city planning commission for its consideration and action. The planning commission shall review the proposed zoning ordinance and, after holding at least one public hearing on each proposed action, shall approve or reject it in whole or in part and with or without modifications. When approved by the planning commission, the proposed zoning ordinance shall be submitted to the city council for its consideration, and such zoning ordinance shall become effective when adopted by the city council. The city council may amend, supplement, or otherwise modify the zoning ordinance. Any such proposed amendment, supplement, or modification shall first be submitted to the planning commission for its recommendations and report. The planning commission shall hold at least one public hearing on such proposed amendment, supplement, or modification, before submitting its recommendations and report. After the recommendations and report of the planning commission have been filed, the city council shall, before enacting any proposed amendment, supplement, or modification, hold a public hearing on such proposed amendment, supplement, or modification. Notice of the time and place of such hearings shall be given by publication thereof in a legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city at least one time at least five days before the date of hearing. Notice with reference to proposed amendments, supplements, or modifications of the zoning ordinance shall also be posted in a conspicuous place on or near the property upon which the action is pending. Such notice shall be easily visible from the street and shall be posted at least five days before the hearing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 46, &#167; 5, p. 231; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 161. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>