<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-1202"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-1202</statuteno><catchline>Appeal; procedure; fees; bond; indigent appellant.</catchline>
<para>(1) The party
appealing shall within thirty days after the date of the order
or decision complained of (a) file a notice of appeal with the city clerk
specifying the parties taking the appeal and the order or decision appealed
from and serve
a copy of the notice upon the city attorney and
(b) deposit the fees and bond or undertaking required pursuant to subsection
(2) of this section or file an affidavit pursuant to subsection (3) of this
section. The notice of appeal shall serve as a praecipe for a
transcript.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided
in subsection (3) of this section, the appellant shall:</para>
<para>(a) Deposit with the city
clerk a docket fee in the amount of the filing fee in district court for cases
originally commenced in district court;</para>
<para>(b) Deposit with the city
clerk a cash bond or undertaking with at least one good and sufficient surety
approved by the city clerk, in the amount of two hundred dollars, on condition
that the appellant will satisfy any judgment and costs that may be adjudged
against him or her; and</para>
<para>(c) Deposit with the city
clerk the fees for the preparation of a certified and complete transcript
of the proceedings of the city relating to the order or decision appealed.</para>
<para>(3)(a) An appellant may
file with the city clerk an affidavit alleging that the appellant is indigent.
The filing of such an affidavit shall relieve the appellant of the duty to
deposit any fee, bond, or undertaking required by subsection (2) of this section
as a condition for the preparation of the transcript or the perfecting of
the appeal by the appellant subject to the determination of the court as provided
in section 15-1204. In conjunction with the filing of the petition for appeal
as provided for in section 15-1204, the appellant shall file a copy of the
affidavit alleging his or her indigency and the district court shall rule
upon the issue of indigency prior to the consideration of any other matter
relating to the appeal as provided in section 15-1204.</para>
<para>(b) An appellant determined
to be indigent under this subsection shall not be required to deposit any
fee, bond, or undertaking required by subsection (2) of this section. For
purposes of this section, indigent means the inability to financially pursue
the appeal without prejudicing the appellant's ability to provide economic
necessities for the appellant or the appellant's family.</para>
<para>(c) An appellant determined
not to be indigent shall, within thirty days after the determination, deposit
with the city clerk the fees and bond or undertaking required by subsection
(2) of this section. The appeal shall not proceed further until the city clerk
notifies the court that the appropriate deposit has been made.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 65, &#167; 2, p. 377; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 52, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB441, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The time for appeal under this section begins to run as of the date the administrative body votes on the action to be taken, rather than the date on which the body finalizes its order. McCorison v. City of Lincoln, 218 Neb. 827, 359 N.W.2d 775 (1984).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>