<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-1102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>15-1102</statuteno><catchline>Comprehensive plan; requirements; contents.</catchline><para>(1) The general plan for the improvement and development of a city of the primary class shall be known as the comprehensive plan. This plan for governmental policies and action shall include the pattern and intensity of land use, the provision of public facilities including transportation and other governmental services, the effective development and utilization of human and natural resources, the identification and evaluation of area needs including housing, employment, education, and health and the formulation of programs to meet such needs, surveys of structures and sites determined to be of historic, cultural, archaeological, or architectural significance or value, long-range physical and fiscal plans for governmental policies and action, and coordination of all related plans and activities of the state and local governments and agencies concerned. The comprehensive plan, with the accompanying maps, plats, charts, and descriptive and explanatory materials, shall show the recommendations concerning the physical development pattern of such city and of any land outside its boundaries related thereto, taking into account the availability of and need for conserving land and other irreplaceable natural resources, the preservation of sites of historic, cultural, archaeological, and architectural significance or value, the projected changes in size, movement, and composition of population, the necessity for expanding housing and employment opportunities, and the need for methods of achieving modernization, simplification, and improvements in governmental structures, systems, and procedures related to growth objectives. The comprehensive plan shall, among other things, show:</para><para>(a) The general location, character, and extent of existing and proposed streets and highways and railroad, air, and other transportation routes and terminals;</para><para>(b) Existing and proposed public ways, parks, grounds, and open spaces;</para><para>(c) The general location, character, and extent of schools, school grounds, and other educational facilities and properties;</para><para>(d) The general location and extent of existing and proposed public utility installations;</para><para>(e) The general location and extent of community development and housing activities;</para><para>(f) The general location of existing and proposed public buildings, structures, and facilities; and</para><para>(g) An energy element which: Assesses energy infrastructure and energy use by sector, including residential, commercial, and industrial sectors; evaluates utilization of renewable energy sources; and promotes energy conservation measures that benefit the community.</para><para>(2) The comprehensive plan shall include a land-use plan showing the proposed general distribution and general location of business and industry, residential areas, utilities, and recreational, educational, and other categories of public and private land uses. The land-use plan shall also show the recommended standards of population density based upon population estimates and providing for activities for which space should be supplied within the area covered by the plan. The comprehensive plan shall include and show proposals for acquisition, extension, widening, narrowing, removal, vacation, abandonment, sale, and other actions affecting public improvements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 46, &#167; 2, p. 229; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB997, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB731, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 158. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB731, section 2, with LB1003, section 158, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB731 became effective November 14, 2020. Changes made by LB1003 became operative November 14, 2020.</note></source><annotation><para>A comprehensive plan is a general guide to community development. Holmgren v. City of Lincoln, 199 Neb. 178, 256 N.W.2d 686 (1977).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>