<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" statutenumber="15-1201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-1201</statuteno><catchline>Appeals; exception.</catchline><para>Any person or persons, jointly or severally aggrieved by any final administrative or judicial order or decision of the board of zoning appeals, the board of equalization, the city council, or any officer, department, or board of a city of the primary class, shall, except as provided for claims in sections 15-840 to 15-842.01, appeal from such order or decision to the district court in the manner provided in sections 15-1201 to 15-1205.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 65, &#167; 1, p. 377; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1003, &#167; 163. </para></source><annotation><para>This section applies only where the various bodies controlled thereby act judicially or quasi-judicially. Quasi-judicial decisions by various organs of a city are reviewable in both the trial and appellate courts. Whitehead Oil Co. v. City of Lincoln, 245 Neb. 660, 515 N.W.2d 390 (1994).</para><para>That municipal code decision shall be final and binding upon appointing authority in collective-bargaining agreement means definitive act of official or agency is binding until and unless set aside by judicial review. City of Lincoln v. Soukup, 215 Neb. 732, 340 N.W.2d 420 (1983).</para><para>The enactment of a zoning ordinance by a municipal governing body is an exercise of legislative authority from which no direct appeal lies. This statute applies only where the bodies mentioned therein act judicially or quasi-judicially. An increase in business competition is not sufficient to confer standing to challenge a change of zone. Copple v. City of Lincoln, 210 Neb. 504, 315 N.W.2d 628 (1982).</para><para>On appeal of a final decision of a city council, only the subject matter in question may be appealed, not collateral issues beyond the scope of the particular decision. Cather &amp; Sons Constr., Inc. v. City of Lincoln, 200 Neb. 510, 264 N.W.2d 413 (1978).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>