<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Primary Class" id="id116" statutenumber="15-1017"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>15-1017</statuteno><catchline id="id119">Pension funds; investment; reports.</catchline><para>(1) A city of the primary class which has a city pension and retirement plan or fund, or a city fire and police pension plan or fund, or both, may provide by ordinance as authorized by its home rule charter, and not prohibited by the Constitution of Nebraska, for the investment of any plan or fund, and it may provide that (a) such a city shall place in trust any part of such plan or fund, (b) it shall place in trust any part of any such plan or fund with a corporate trustee in Nebraska, or (c) it shall purchase any part of any such plan from a life insurance company licensed to do business in the State of Nebraska. The powers conferred by this section shall be independent of and in addition and supplemental to any other provisions of the laws of the State of Nebraska with reference to the matters covered hereby and this section shall be considered as a complete and independent act and not as amendatory of or limited by any other provision of the laws of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(2) Beginning December 31, 1998, through December 31, 2017:</para><para>(a) The clerk of a city of the primary class shall file with the Public Employees Retirement Board an annual report on each retirement plan established pursuant to this section, section 15-1026, and section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code and shall submit copies of such report to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The annual report shall be in a form prescribed by the Public Employees Retirement Board and shall contain the following information for each such retirement plan:</para><para>(i) The number of persons participating in the retirement plan;</para><para>(ii) The contribution rates of participants in the plan;</para><para>(iii) Plan assets and liabilities;</para><para>(iv) The names and positions of persons administering the plan;</para><para>(v) The names and positions of persons investing plan assets;</para><para>(vi) The form and nature of investments;</para><para>(vii) For each defined contribution plan, a full description of investment policies and options available to plan participants; and</para><para>(viii) For each defined benefit plan, the levels of benefits of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a benefit, and the total present value of such members' benefits, as well as the funding sources which will pay for such benefits.</para><para>If a plan contains no current active participants, the city clerk may file in place of such report a statement with the Public Employees Retirement Board indicating the number of retirees still drawing benefits, and the sources and amount of funding for such benefits; and</para><para>(b) If such retirement plan is a defined benefit plan which was open to new members on January 1, 2004, in addition to the reports required by section 13-2402, the city council of a city of the primary class shall cause to be prepared an annual report and shall file the same with the Public Employees Retirement Board and the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and submit to the Auditor of Public Accounts a copy of such report. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If the city council does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor of Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the city. All costs of the audit shall be paid by the city. The report shall consist of a full actuarial analysis of each such retirement plan established pursuant to this section and section 15-1026. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization offering investment advice or which provides investment management services to the retirement plan. The report to the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(3)(a) Beginning December 31, 2018, and each December 31 thereafter, for a defined benefit plan, the clerk of a city of the primary class or his or her designee shall prepare and electronically file an annual report with the Auditor of Public Accounts and the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature. If such retirement plan is a defined benefit plan which was open to new members on January 1, 2004, the report shall be in addition to the reports required by section 13-2402. The report shall be on a form prescribed by the Auditor of Public Accounts and shall include, but not be limited to, the following information:</para><para>(i) The levels of benefits of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a benefit, the total present value of such members' benefits, and the funding sources which will pay for such benefits; and</para><para>(ii) A copy of a full actuarial analysis of each such defined benefit plan. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization which offers investment advice or provides investment management services to the retirement plan.</para><para>(b) The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If the city council does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor of Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the city. All costs of the audit shall be paid by the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 52, &#167; 1, p. 188; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB759, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 6. </para><effectivedate>May 24, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>