<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities of the Primary Class" statutenumber="15-1102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>15-1102</statuteno><catchline>Comprehensive plan; requirements;
contents.</catchline><para>The general plan for the improvement and development
of the city of the primary class shall be known as the comprehensive plan.
This plan for governmental policies and action shall include the pattern and
intensity of land use, the provision of public facilities including transportation
and other governmental services, the effective development and utilization
of human and natural resources, the identification and evaluation of area
needs including housing, employment, education, and health and the formulation
of programs to meet such needs, surveys of structures and sites determined
to be of historic, cultural, archaeological, or architectural significance
or value, long-range physical and fiscal plans for governmental policies and
action, and coordination of all related plans and activities of the state
and local governments and agencies concerned. The comprehensive plan, with
the accompanying maps, plats, charts and descriptive and explanatory materials,
shall show the recommendations concerning the physical development pattern
of such city and of any land outside its boundaries related thereto, taking
into account the availability of and need for conserving land and other irreplaceable
natural resources, the preservation of sites of historic, cultural, archaeological,
and architectural significance or value, the projected changes in size, movement,
and composition of population, the necessity for expanding housing and employment
opportunities, and the need for methods of achieving modernization, simplification,
and improvements in governmental structures, systems, and procedures related
to growth objectives. The comprehensive plan shall, among other things, show:</para>
<para>(1) The general location, character, and extent of existing and proposed
streets and highways and railroad, air, and other transportation routes and
terminals;</para>
<para>(2) Existing and proposed public ways, parks, grounds, and open spaces;</para>
<para>(3) The general location, character, and extent of schools, school grounds,
and other educational facilities and properties;</para>
<para>(4) The general location and extent of existing and proposed public
utility installations;</para>
<para>(5) The general location and extent of community development and housing
activities;</para>
<para>(6) The general location of existing and proposed public buildings,
structures, and facilities;
and</para>
<para>(7) When a new comprehensive
plan or a full update to an existing comprehensive plan is developed on or
after July 15, 2010, but not later than January 1, 2015, an energy element
which: Assesses energy infrastructure and energy use by sector, including
residential, commercial, and industrial sectors; evaluates utilization of
renewable energy sources; and promotes energy conservation measures that benefit
the community.</para><para>The comprehensive plan shall include
a land-use plan showing the proposed general distribution and general location
of business and industry, residential areas, utilities, and recreational,
educational, and other categories of public and private land uses. The land-use
plan shall also show the recommended standards of population density based
upon population estimates and providing for activities for which space should
be supplied within the area covered by the plan. The comprehensive plan shall
include and show proposals for acquisition, extension, widening, narrowing,
removal, vacation, abandonment, sale, and other actions affecting public improvements.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 46, &#167; 2, p. 229; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB997, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>A comprehensive plan is a general guide to community development. Holmgren v. City of Lincoln, 199 Neb. 178, 256 N.W.2d 686 (1977).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>