<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Railroads" statutenumber="74-1419.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>74-1419.02</statuteno><catchline>Division; duties; Department of Roads; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The division shall conduct research on basic railroad problems, plan and assist in the development of rail transportation, develop and maintain a federal-state relationship with regard to programs relating to railroads, assist any public or private agency or corporation in coordinating railroad services with those of other transportation modes, and recommend, prepare, and review plans and specifications for any project to be proposed to the council.</para><para>(2) The division shall:</para><para>(a) Conduct studies and investigations and act in an advisory capacity to the council in the establishment of broad policies for carrying out the Light-Density Rail Line Assistance Act;</para><para>(b) Advise the public regarding the policies, conditions, and activities of the division;</para><para>(c) Hold hearings, make investigations, studies, and inspections, and do all other things necessary to carry out the duties imposed upon it by law;</para><para>(d) Advance information and advice conducive to providing adequate and safe railroads in the state;</para><para>(e) Submit to the council its written advice regarding the feasibility of the acquisition, rehabilitation or improvement, or operation of a fragment or section of light-density rail line or of an entire light-density rail line or a rail line facility construction project when proposed by the division;</para><para>(f) Furnish necessary assistance to the council in making its inspection and study of any proposed project;</para><para>(g) Perform all planning functions required for participation in the federal act; and</para><para>(h) Make data and information of the division available to the council.</para><para>(3) The Department of Roads shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary for the division to carry out its duties under the Light-Density Rail Line Assistance Act and to participate in the federal act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 783, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 463, &#167; 25. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 