<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Railroads" statutenumber="74-1317"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>74-1317</statuteno><catchline>Grade Crossing Protection Fund; created; purpose; investment.</catchline><para>In order to promote public safety at the intersection of railroad lines and all classes of highways, there is hereby created a special fund known as the Grade Crossing Protection Fund which shall be established in the state treasury to be used in furnishing financial assistance in the improvement of the safety of railroad grade crossings in this state, including the elimination of such crossings, the construction, substantial modification, or improvement of and the maintenance of automatic crossing protection at such grade crossings, and the construction and maintenance of overpasses and underpasses at railroad crossings. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 359, &#167; 1, p. 1126; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1961, &#167; 75-219.01; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 241, &#167; 1, p. 732; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 40, p. 2368; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 144, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 39-7,136; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 249, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1979, &#167; 39-6,194; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 42, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 27. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>