<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Railroads" statutenumber="74-1335" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>74-1335</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Crossings; private; railroad; duties.</catchline><para id="id00">Whenever any person owns land on both sides of the right-of-way of any railroad, such railroad shall provide and keep in repair at least one adequate means for such landowner to cross the right-of-way. Any interested landowner with land on both sides of the right-of-way of any railroad may file written complaint with the Department of Transportation against any such railroad that the crossing is not adequate or is unsafe and dangerous to the life and property of those who use it, and the department thereupon shall make such investigation, hold such hearing, and issue such orders as it deems necessary, proper, and adequate. If circumstances warrant, the department may require overhead, underground, or grade crossings and wing fences at underground crossings or may require existing crossings to be relocated so as to be safe to those who use them, but when a special crossing involves an expenditure of more than one thousand five hundred dollars, the landowner shall bear one-half the expenses in excess of one thousand five hundred dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 425, art. IV, &#167; 13, p. 1402; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 88; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 75-413; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 255, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 259. </para></source><annotation><para>Railroad was under duty to deceased truck driver, a member of crew repairing gas pipelines on farm property, to exercise reasonable care at private farm road crossing being used by decedent with permission of landowner. Kloewer v. Burlington Northern, Inc., 512 F.2d 300 (8th Cir. 1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>