<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Railroads" statutenumber="74-1342" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>74-1342</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Comprehensive public safety program; department; duties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The Department of Transportation shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing a comprehensive public safety program to deal with problems associated with public and private highway-rail grade crossings. In designing such a program, the department shall establish a process for assessing the risk to the public from particular grade crossings and for reducing or eliminating such risk in a cost-effective and timely manner. The department shall actively solicit input from the public and from representatives of county and municipal governments, the Federal Highway Administration, the Federal Railroad Administration, and any other individuals or entities with an interest in grade crossing safety.</para><para id="id00">(2) The grade crossing safety assessment process may include the following factors:</para><para id="id00">(a) Volume of trains;</para><para id="id00">(b) Volume of motor vehicles, including character, function, and type of vehicular traffic through the crossing;</para><para id="id00">(c) Number of tracks at the crossing;</para><para id="id00">(d) Geometry of the crossing, including acute angles;</para><para id="id00">(e) Sight-distance restrictions, if any;</para><para id="id00">(f) Train and motor vehicle speed;</para><para id="id00">(g) Accident history;</para><para id="id00">(h) Character of proximate road network, including distance and travel time to adjacent crossings;</para><para id="id00">(i) Frequency and duration of roadway blockage by trains, including citation history;</para><para id="id00">(j) Emergency response routes, including alternatives;</para><para id="id00">(k) Economic impact of crossing;</para><para id="id00">(l) Current and foreseeable development in the vicinity of the crossing; and</para><para id="id00">(m) Location of schools and hospitals.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 255, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 264. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>