<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id272">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Special Acts" id="id274"  statutenumber="90-517"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-517</statuteno><catchline id="id277">State aid for
community college areas.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, state aid for each community
college area for fiscal year 2010-11 shall equal:</para>
<para>(a) For the Central Community College Area, $8,289,499;</para>
<para>(b) For the Metropolitan Community College Area, $18,389,499;</para>
<para>(c) For the Mid-Plains Community College Area, $8,251,373;</para>
<para>(d) For the Northeast Community College Area, $12,784,454,
including $38,815 for Nebraska Indian Community College and $13,120 for Little
Priest Tribal College;</para>
<para>(e) For the Southeast Community College Area, $27,133,220;
and</para>
<para>(f) For the Western Community College Area, $11,909,980.</para>
<para>(2) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, state aid
for each community college area for fiscal years 2011-12 and 2012-13 shall
equal the amount of state aid appropriated by the Legislature for the respective
fiscal year multiplied by the following percentage for each community college
area:</para>
<para>(a) For the Central Community College Area, eight and eighty-six
hundredths percent;</para>
<para>(b) For the Metropolitan Community College Area, twenty-six
and fifty-one hundredths percent;</para>
<para>(c) For the Mid-Plains Community College Area, nine and five-hundredths
percent;</para>
<para>(d) For the Northeast Community College Area, fourteen and
four-hundredths percent. Of such amount provided for the Northeast Community
College Area, one-tenth of one percent shall be provided for Nebraska Indian
Community College and two-tenths of one percent for Little Priest Tribal College;</para>
<para>(e) For the Southeast Community College Area, twenty-eight
and twenty-seven hundredths percent; and</para>
<para>(f) For the Western Community College Area, thirteen and
twenty-seven hundredths percent.</para>
<para>(3) The Department of Administrative Services shall distribute
the amounts provided in subsection (1) or (2) of this section for the respective
fiscal year to each community college area in ten as nearly as possible equal
monthly payments between the fifth and the twentieth day of each month beginning
in September of each year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB59, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 24.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>