<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts" statutenumber="90-270" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-270</statuteno><catchline>Joint Operations Center Capital Construction Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Joint Operations Center Capital Construction Fund is created. The fund shall consist of revenue administratively transferred from the Vacant Building and Excess Land Cash Fund pursuant to section 90-269 and may also include administrative interfund transfers from the Governor's Emergency Cash Fund and the Military Department Cash Fund, which are hereby authorized, except that any administrative interfund transfers made pursuant to this section from the Governor's Emergency Cash Fund and the Military Department Cash Fund shall be reversed on or before June 30, 2015. The Joint Operations Center Capital Construction Fund shall be used to construct and furnish combined office space for the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency and the Nebraska State Patrol Communications Operations Center, including any necessary relocation expenses of the offices and the Nebraska State Patrol communications switcher. The fund shall be administered by the State Administrator of the Nebraska Emergency Management Agency. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The fund balance in the Joint Operations Center Capital Construction Fund existing as of June 30, 2015, plus any investment income credited to the fund after June 30, 2015, shall be transferred to the General Fund.</para><para>This section terminates on July 1, 2015.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 403, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 21.</para><terminationdate>July 1, 2015</terminationdate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>