
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts"  statutenumber="90-276"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-276</statuteno><catchline>Game and Parks Commission; convey
property to village of Brownville.</catchline><para>The Game and Parks Commission is authorized to convey to
the village of Brownville, Nebraska, for public park purposes the following
described real estate now known as Brownville State Recreation Area, situated
in the county of Nemaha, in the State of Nebraska, to wit:</para>
<para>(1) From the southeast
corner of Block 1 in the Original Town of Brownville, Nebraska, running east
parallel to the center line of Main Street a distance of 237.1 feet to the
place of beginning, said place of beginning being 90 feet east of the center
line of the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track; thence south 6 degrees, 26 minutes east,
parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point;
thence south 7 degrees, 11 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R.
track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 7 degrees, 24 minutes
east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to
a point; thence south 7 degrees, 16 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp;
Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 7 degrees,
12 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100
feet to a point; thence south 6 degrees, 35 minutes east, parallel to the
C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south
5 degrees, 00 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance
of 100 feet to a point; thence south 3 degrees, 58 minutes east, parallel
to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence
south 2 degrees, 26 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track,
a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 1 degree, 11 minutes east,
parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point;
thence south 0 degrees, 03 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R.
track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 0 degrees, 42 minutes
west, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 60.3 feet to
a point, said point being 90 feet east of the center line of the C.B. &amp;
Q. R.R. track; thence east 860.4 feet to a point on the right high mark of
the Missouri River; thence north 27 degrees, 14 minutes west along the said
high bank of the Missouri River, a distance of 199.9 feet to a point; thence
north 21 degrees, 39 minutes west along the said high bank of the Missouri
River a distance of 635.51 feet to a point; thence north 18 degrees, 50 minutes
west along said high bank of the Missouri River a distance of 408.21 feet
to a point; thence west 497.90 feet to the place of beginning, all in Nemaha
County, Nebraska, containing 17.20 acres, more or less, plus all accretions
thereto; and</para><para>(2)
Commencing at the southeast corner of Block 1 in the Original Town of Brownville,
Nebraska, running east parallel to the center line of Main Street a distance
of 237.1 feet to a point, said point being 90 feet east of the center line
of the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track; thence south 6 degrees, 26 minutes east,
parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point;
thence south 7 degrees, 11 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R.
track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 7 degrees, 24 minutes
east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to
a point; thence south 7 degrees, 16 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp;
Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 7 degrees,
12 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100
feet to a point; thence south 6 degrees, 35 minutes east, parallel to the
C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south
5 degrees, 00 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance
of 100 feet to a point; thence south 3 degrees, 58 minutes east, parallel
to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence
south 2 degrees, 26 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track,
a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 1 degree, 11 minutes east,
parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point;
thence south 0 degrees, 03 minutes east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R.
track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 0 degrees, 42 minutes
west, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 60.3 feet to
a point, said point being 90 feet east of the center line of the C.B. &amp;
Q. R.R. track, being the place of beginning; thence south 2 degrees, 04 minutes
east, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 52.5 feet to
a point; thence south 4 degrees, 46 minutes west, parallel to the C.B. &amp;
Q. R.R. track, a distance of 100 feet to a point; thence south 9 degrees,
48 minutes west, parallel to the C.B. &amp; Q. R.R. track, a distance of 46.4
feet to a point; said point being 90 feet east of the center line of the C.B.
&amp; Q. R.R. track and on the section line between sections 18 and 19, township
5 north, range 16 east of the 6th principal meridian; thence north 88 degrees,
42 minutes east along the section line between sections 18 and 19, township
5 north, range 16 east, a distance of 906.9 feet to the corners of sections
17, 18, 19, and 20, township 5 north, range 16 east; thence continuing north
88 degrees, 42 minutes east along the section line between sections 17 and
20, township 5 north, range 16 east, a distance of 449.4 feet to a point on
the right high bank of the Missouri River; thence north 34 degrees, 17 minutes
west along said right high bank of the said Missouri River, a distance of
202.41 feet to a point; thence west a distance of 1,224.44 feet to the place
of beginning, containing 5.41 acres, more or less, all in Nemaha County, Nebraska,
plus all accretions thereto.</para><para>The above described tract being immediately south
of the tract described and recorded in Book number 79, page 398 of the Deed
records of Nemaha County, Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB621, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>