<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts" statutenumber="90-251"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-251</statuteno><catchline>State Department of Education; sell described property; proceeds.</catchline><para>(1) The State Department of Education may sell and convey by quitclaim deed two parcels of land generally described as follows:</para><para>(a) A parcel of land in the northwest quarter of section 31, township 9, range 14, in Otoe County, Nebraska, designated as tract number 4, consisting of eleven and nine-tenths acres, more or less, as shown by the plat of Lester Ehlers, engineer and surveyor, sworn to November 22, 1950, filed December 4, 1950, in Deeds Book 97, page 298, in the Office of the Register of Deeds of Otoe County, Nebraska, subject to and less public road and Missouri Pacific Railroad right-of-way; and</para><para>(b) A triangular tract of land starting at the northeast corner of the southeast quarter of the northeast quarter of section 36, township 9, range 13, thence south on the section line three hundred fifty feet, thence in a northwesterly direction four hundred four feet along the center line of the Missouri Pacific Railroad right-of-way to the north line of the southeast quarter of the northeast quarter, thence east on such line to the point of beginning, containing one and six-tenths acres, more or less, all of the above-described land being subject to the Missouri Pacific Railroad right-of-way and the public road and all of such land being in Otoe County, Nebraska.</para><para>(2) The income from the sale of all or any portion of the land described in subsection (1) of this section shall be deposited in the State Department of Education Trust Fund. The department may use the income from the sale of the land to pay any selling expenses associated with the sale.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 526, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>