<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts" statutenumber="90-404" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-404</statuteno><catchline>Game and Parks Commission; additions to Arbor Lodge State Historical Park; purchase of property in the city of Bassett.</catchline><para>(1) The Game and Parks Commission may enter into an agreement to accept as a gift from the Nebraska Game and Parks Foundation all of the real estate described as Lot 1 in the northwest quarter of the northwest quarter of section 8, township 8 north, range 14 east, Otoe County, Nebraska, except that part of Lot 1, commencing at the northwest corner of Lot 1, thence east 265 feet, thence south 462 feet, thence west 265 feet to a point on the west line of Lot 1, thence north 462 feet to the place of beginning, also described as the east 678.14 feet of Lot 1, all located in Otoe County, Nebraska, containing 7.1 acres more or less and including all gas, oil, and mineral rights.</para><para>(2) The Game and Parks Commission may enter into an agreement to accept as a gift from the United States Government all of the real estate described as a tract of land situated in the southwest quarter of section 8, township 8 north, range 14 east of the 6th principal meridian, Otoe County, Nebraska, more particularly described as follows: Commencing at the northeast corner of said southwest quarter of section 8; thence west 990.00 feet; thence south to a point that intersects the north right-of-way line of State Highway No. 2, said intersection being the point of beginning; thence easterly along said north right-of-way line of State Highway No. 2, for a distance of 200 feet; thence north 400 feet; thence west 200 feet; thence south to the point of beginning, all located in Otoe County, Nebraska, containing 1.84 acres, more or less, or 80,000 square feet.</para><para>(3) In consideration of such conveyances, the commission agrees that the land shall be designated and utilized as additions to Arbor Lodge State Historical Park.</para><para>(4) The Game and Parks Commission may purchase from a willing seller, when funds on hand are sufficient, or acquire by gift, devise, or otherwise title in the name of the State of Nebraska to property within Block 27, Pierce's Addition, and adjacent previous railroad right-of-way, all located within the city of Bassett, Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 235, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1410, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 792, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>