<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts" statutenumber="90-201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-201</statuteno><catchline>Department of Health and Human Services; convey property to University of Nebraska at Kearney; revenue; restriction.</catchline><para>The Department of Health and Human Services is authorized and directed to convey to the University of Nebraska at Kearney for academic and developmental purposes at the termination of the current lease of the real estate on February 28, 2006, the following described real estate located in Buffalo County, Nebraska:</para><para>A tract of land being part of Government Lot 1, part of Government Lot 2, part of Government Lot 3, part of Government Lot 4, part of the South half of the Northwest Quarter, part of the Northwest Quarter of the Southwest Quarter, part of the South half of the Northeast Quarter and part of the North half of the Southeast Quarter of Section 4, Township 8 North, Range 16 West of the 6th P.M., Buffalo County, Nebraska, all more particularly described as follows: Referring to the Southeast Corner of the Northeast Quarter of said Section 4 and assuming the South line of said Northeast Quarter as bearing N 89&#176; 59&#8242; 10&#8243; W and all bearings contained herein are relative thereto; thence N 89&#176; 59&#8242; 10&#8243; W and on the South line of the Northeast Quarter of said section a distance of 660.0 feet to the ACTUAL PLACE OF BEGINNING; thence S 01&#176; 37&#8242; 34&#8243; W a distance of 18.65 feet to a point on the North property line of an existing road; thence N 89&#176; 29&#8242; 57&#8243; W and on the aforesaid North property line a distance of 3372.3 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 1332.72 foot radius curve to the left forming a central angle of 13&#176; 10&#8242; a distance of 306.26 feet to the point of tangency; thence tangent S 77&#176; 20&#8242; 03&#8243; W a distance of 224.85 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 687.31 foot radius curve to the right forming a central angle of 07&#176; 31&#8242; 16&#8243; a distance of 90.32 feet; thence leaving said curve N 01&#176; 39&#8242; E a distance of 85.39 feet to a point on the South line of the Northwest Quarter of said Section 4; thence N 01&#176; 31&#8242; 22&#8243; E a distance of 310.2 feet to the Northeast corner of a tract of land known as Reservation No. 2 as located in State Application Resurvey No. 154 and filed in the Buffalo County Surveyors Office; thence N 89&#176; 57&#8242; 11&#8243; W and on the North line of said Reservation No. 2 tract a distance of 243.86 feet; thence N 01&#176; 43&#8242; 30&#8243; W a distance of 1501.2 feet; thence S 85&#176; 38&#8242; E a distance of 681.66 feet to the Southeast corner of a tract of land known as Reservation No. 1, thence N 21&#176; 02&#8242; W and on the easterly line of said Reservation No. 1 a distance of 535.07 feet; thence S 80&#176; 22&#8242; 31&#8243; E a distance of 365.02 feet; thence S 86&#176; 03&#8242; 12&#8243; E a distance of 351.11 feet; thence N 86&#176; 44&#8242; 38&#8243; E a distance of 359.33 feet; thence N 79&#176; 19&#8242; 21&#8243; E a distance of 443.41 feet; thence N 77&#176; 14&#8242; 05&#8243; E a distance of 660.05 feet; thence N 83&#176; 05&#8242; E a distance of 195.54 feet; thence N 89&#176; 51&#8242; 32&#8243; E a distance of 1503.54 feet to a point, said point being 660.0 feet West of the East line of said Section 4; thence S 01&#176; 37&#8242; 34&#8243; W a distance of 2450.53 feet to the place of beginning. Containing 221.3 acres, more or less.</para><para>A tract of land being part of the North half of the South half of Section 4, Township 8 North, Range 16 West of the 6th P.M., Buffalo County, Nebraska, more particularly described as follows: Referring to the Northeast corner of the Southeast Quarter of Section 4 and assuming the North line of said Southeast Quarter as bearing N 89&#176; 59&#8242; 10&#8243; W and all bearings contained herein are relative thereto; thence N 89&#176; 59&#8242; 10&#8243; W and on the North line of said Southeast Quarter a distance of 660.0 feet; thence S 01&#176; 37&#8242; 34&#8243; W a distance of 84.67 feet to the ACTUAL PLACE OF BEGINNING, said place of beginning being on the South property line of an existing road; thence N 89&#176; 29&#8242; 57&#8243; W and on the aforesaid South property line a distance of 3369.9 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 1266.72 foot radius curve to the left forming a central angle of 13&#176; 10&#8242; a distance of 291.1 feet to the point of tangency; thence tangent S 77&#176; 20&#8242; 03&#8243; W a distance of 224.85 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 753.31 foot radius curve to the right forming a central angle of 12&#176; 40&#8242; 30&#8243; a distance of 166.65 feet to the point of tangency; thence tangent N 89&#176; 59&#8242; 27&#8243; W a distance of 126.4 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 1673.61 foot radius curve to the right forming a central angle of 05&#176; 35&#8242; a distance of 163.09 feet to the point of tangency; thence tangent N 84&#176; 24&#8242; 27&#8243; W a distance of 158.4 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 1232.18 foot radius curve to the right forming a central angle of 06&#176; 21&#8242; 40&#8243; a distance of 136.8 feet to the point of intersection of the West line of the Southwest Quarter of said Section 4; thence leaving said curve S 01&#176; 41&#8242; W and on the West line of said Southwest Quarter a distance of 501.45 feet to a point on the North property line of the Union Pacific Railroad; thence N 85&#176; 39&#8242; 06&#8243; E and on the aforesaid North property line a distance of 188.78 feet to the point of curvature; thence on a 11017.1 foot radius curve to the left forming a central angle of 01&#176; 29&#8242; a distance of 285.22 feet to the point of tangency; thence tangent N 84&#176; 10&#8242; 06&#8243; E a distance of 4185.03 feet to a point, said point being 660.0 feet West of the East line of said Section 4; thence N 01&#176; 37&#8242; 34&#8243; E a distance of 61.84 feet to the place of beginning. Containing 31.8 acres, more or less, of which 0.4 acres, more or less, are presently being used for road purposes on the West side.</para><para>If the University of Nebraska at Kearney sells any part of the real estate before development of the real estate, the funds received shall be remitted to the Department of Health and Human Services. Any continuing agriculture-related net revenue from the real estate conveyed to the University of Nebraska at Kearney under this section shall be remitted to the Department of Health and Human Services for a period of ten years after conveyance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 668, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 