<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts" statutenumber="90-253"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-253</statuteno><catchline>Department of Economic Development; convey described property; proceeds.</catchline><para>The Department of Economic Development is authorized, upon written approval of the Governor, to sell, lease, or otherwise convey the following described real estate: All of lots 4 thru 15, block 6, Murray's Addition to Oklahoma, an addition to the city of Omaha, in section 34, township 15 north, range 13 east of the 6th P.M.; Douglas County, Nebraska, together with the easterly part of lots 16 and 17 more particularly described as follows: Beginning at the southeast corner of lot 16 thence one hundred thirty-four feet to the northeast corner of lot 17; thence east sixty-two and eight-tenths feet; thence southwesterly to a point thirty-eight and nine-tenths feet east of the southwest corner of lot 17; thence southwesterly to a point eight and six-tenths feet east of the southwest corner of lot 16; thence east to the point of beginning; together with the easterly part of lot 19 more particularly described as follows: Beginning at the southeast corner of said lot 19; thence north fifty and eight-tenths feet; thence southwesterly sixty and three-tenths feet to a point thirty-two and one-half feet west of the said southeast corner; thence east thirty-two and one-half feet to the point of beginning. Together with the following described parts of lots 9 thru 16, block 5, said Murray's Addition: Beginning at the southwest corner of lot 9; said block 5; thence north seventy-five feet; thence southeasterly to a point on the east line of said lot 9, fifty-five feet north of the southeast corner of said lot 9 then southeasterly to a point on the east line of lot 11; said block 5 said point being twenty-seven feet north of the southeast corner of said lot 11, thence east to a point on the east line of lot 12; said block 5, said point being twenty-seven feet north of the southeast corner of said lot 12; thence northeasterly to a point on the east line of lot 13; said block 5; said point being forty feet north of the southeast corner of said lot 13; thence northeasterly to a point on the east line of lot 14; said block 5; said point being sixty feet north of the southeast corner of said lot 14; thence northeasterly to a point on the east line of lot 16; said block 5, said point being one hundred twenty-nine feet north of the southeast corner of said lot 16; thence south to the southeast corner of said lot 16; thence west to the southwest corner of said lot 9. Together with the streets and alleys lying between the above described lots; commonly referred to as the Nebraska Omaha Travel Information Center. If the real estate is leased, such lease may contain an option to purchase the property at a value in the best interests of the state to be determined by the department. Proceeds of the sale or lease shall be deposited in the appropriate fund in the same manner as proceeds are deposited in section 81-161.04 and used for the purposes set forth for the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 1143, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>