<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Special Acts" statutenumber="90-223"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>90-223</statuteno><catchline>Governor; convey easement and property to city of Lincoln.</catchline><para>(1) The Governor is authorized by the Legislature to convey to the city of Lincoln, Nebraska, a permanent easement for the construction, reconstruction, inspection, maintenance, operation, and replacement of a water main over and through certain real property, situated in the city of Lincoln, Lancaster County, Nebraska, described as follows:</para><para>(a) The south fifteen feet of Lot 7, Block 15, Riverside Addition;</para><para>(b) The south fifteen feet of the north-south alley vacated by Ordinance Number 7620 of the city of Lincoln abutting Lots 6 and 7, Block 15, Riverside Addition;</para><para>(c) The south fifteen feet of that portion of Lot C, Riverside Addition, lying north of the north line of Military Road;</para><para>(d) The north fifteen feet of the west fifteen feet of that portion of Lot C, Riverside Addition, lying south of the south line of Military Road;</para><para>(e) The north fifteen feet of that portion of 12th Street vacated by Ordinance Number 1886 of the city of Lincoln lying south of the south line of Military Road; and</para><para>(f) The north fifteen feet of the east four hundred fifty-two feet of that portion of Lot E, Riverside Addition, lying south of the south line of Military Road.</para><para>(2) The Governor is authorized by the Legislature to convey to the city of Lincoln, Nebraska, ownership of the water main and appurtenances thereto owned by the State of Nebraska located beneath such property and also located in public right-of-way known as Military Road and 14th Street within the city of Lincoln, Lancaster County, Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 602, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>