<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id13"><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id15"  statutenumber="69-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-402</statuteno><catchline>Secondary metals recycler; purchase of regulated metals property; information required; duration; receipt.</catchline><para>(1) A secondary metals recycler shall maintain a record, either as a hard copy or electronically, of all purchase transactions in which the secondary metals recycler purchases regulated metals property.</para><para>(2) The following information shall be maintained for transactions in which a secondary metals recycler purchases regulated metals property:</para><para>(a) The name and address of the secondary metals recycler;</para><para>(b) The name and signature of the individual entering the information;</para><para>(c) The date and time of the transaction;</para><para>(d) The weight and grade of the regulated metals property purchased;</para><para>(e) The description made in accordance with the custom of the trade of the type of regulated metals property purchased;</para><para>(f) The amount of consideration given for the regulated metals property, if any;</para><para>(g) The name, signature, and address of the vendor of the regulated metals property;</para><para>(h) The motor vehicle operator's license number, state identification card number, or federal government-issued identification card number of the person delivering the regulated metals property to the secondary metals recycler;</para><para>(i) A photocopy of the current motor vehicle operator's license, state-issued identification card, or federal government-issued identification card of the person delivering the regulated metals property to the secondary metals recycler;</para><para>(j) A fingerprint from the person, but only if the person is delivering copper or catalytic converters. The fingerprint shall be taken from the right index finger, but if the right index finger is missing, the fingerprint shall be taken from the left index finger; and</para><para>(k) A date-and-time-stamped photograph or a date-and-time-stamped video recording of the regulated metals property.</para><para>(3) The vendor of the regulated metals property shall receive at no charge a plain written or printed receipt of the recorded transaction containing a copy of the entries required by this section.</para><para>(4) A secondary metals recycler shall keep and maintain the information required under this section for not less than one year after the date of the purchase of the regulated metals property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB766, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>