<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-206</statuteno><catchline>Pawned or secondhand goods; restrictions on disposition; jewelry defined.</catchline><para>No personal property received or purchased by any pawnbroker, dealer in secondhand goods, or junk dealer, shall be sold or permitted to be taken from the place of business of such person for fourteen days or, in the case of secondhand jewelry, for five days, after the copy of the card or ledger entry required to be delivered to the police department or sheriff's office shall have been delivered as required by section 69-205. Secondhand jewelry shall not be destroyed, damaged, or in any manner defaced for a period of seventy-two hours after the time of its purchase or receipt. For purposes of this section, jewelry shall mean any ornament which is intended to be worn on or about the body and which is made in whole or in part of any precious metal, including gold, silver, platinum, copper, brass, or pewter.</para><para>All property accepted as collateral security or purchased by a pawnbroker shall be kept segregated from all other property in a separate area for a period of forty-eight hours after its receipt or purchase, except that valuable articles may be kept in a safe with other property if grouped according to the day of purchase or receipt. Notwithstanding the provisions of this section, a pawnbroker may return any property to the person pawning the same after the expiration of such forty-eight-hour period or when permitted by the chief of police, sheriff, or other authorized law enforcement officer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 10, &#167; 6, p. 66; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 541; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 433; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 69-206; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 69-206; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 44, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 