<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-1701" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-1701</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Outdoor advertising sign; removal by public body; compensation; how determined; exception.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Before an outdoor advertising sign, display, or device is removed, taken, or appropriated through the use of zoning or any other power or authority possessed by the state, a state agency, or a political subdivision of the state:</para><para id="id00">(a) The value of the sign, display, or device shall be determined by the taking entity without the use of any amortization schedule; and</para><para id="id00">(b) The owners of the sign, display, or device shall be paid the fair and reasonable market value for such removal, taking, or appropriation, which fair and reasonable market value shall be based upon the depreciated reproduction cost of such sign, display, or device using as a guideline the Nebraska Sign Schedule developed and used by the Department of Transportation, except that, when feasible, the taking entity may elect to relocate such sign, display, or device, in which event the owners of the sign, display, or device shall be paid the actual and necessary relocation cost therefor.</para><para id="id00">(2) Subsection (1) of this section shall not apply to:</para><para id="id00">(a) Actions taken by the Department of Transportation pursuant to sections 39-212 to 39-226 and 39-1320; and</para><para id="id00">(b) The removal, taking, or appropriation of a sign, display, or device which (i) is insecurely fixed or inadequately maintained such that the sign, display, or device constitutes a danger to the public health or safety, or (ii) has been abandoned or no longer used by the owners for at least six months.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 241, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 264, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 244. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>