<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id3"> <sectno id="id4">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id5" statutenumber="69-1317"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">69-1317</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Abandoned property; trust funds; record; professional finder's fee; information withheld; when; proceeds of sale; transfers; Unclaimed Property Cash Fund; created; investment.</catchline> <para>(a)(1) Except as otherwise provided in this subdivision, all funds received under the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act, including the proceeds from the sale of abandoned property under section 69-1316, shall be deposited by the State Treasurer in a separate trust fund from which he or she shall make prompt payment of claims allowed pursuant to the act and payment of any auditing expenses associated with the receipt of abandoned property. All funds received under section 69-1307.05 shall be deposited by the State Treasurer in a separate life insurance corporation demutualization trust fund, which is hereby created, from which he or she shall make prompt payment of claims regarding such funds allowed pursuant to the act. Transfers from the separate life insurance corporation demutualization trust fund to the General Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Before making the deposit he or she shall record the name and last-known address of each person appearing from the holders' reports to be entitled to the abandoned property, the name and last-known address of each insured person or annuitant, and with respect to each policy or contract listed in the report of a life insurance corporation, its number, the name of the corporation, and the amount due. The record shall be available for public inspection during business hours.</para> <para>The record shall not be subject to public inspection or available for copying, reproduction, or scrutiny by commercial or professional locators of property presumed abandoned who charge any service or finders' fee until twenty-four months after the names from the holders' reports have been published or officially disclosed. Records concerning the social security number, date of birth, amount due, and last-known address of an owner shall be treated as confidential and subject to the same confidentiality as tax return information held by the Department of Revenue, except that the Auditor of Public Accounts shall have unrestricted access to such records.</para>  <para>A professional finders' fee shall be limited to ten percent of the total dollar amount of the property presumed abandoned. To claim any such fee, the finder shall disclose to the owner the nature, location, and value of the property, provide notice of when such property was reported to the State Treasurer, and provide notice that the property may be claimed by the owner from the State Treasurer free of charge. To claim any such fee if the property has not yet been abandoned, the finder shall disclose to the owner the nature, location, and value of the property, provide notice of when such property will be reported to the State Treasurer, if known, and provide notice that, upon receipt of the property by the State Treasurer, such property may be claimed by the owner from the State Treasurer free of charge.</para><para>(2) The unclaimed property records of the State Treasurer, the unclaimed property reports of holders, and the information derived by an unclaimed property examination or audit of the records of a person or otherwise obtained by or communicated to the State Treasurer may be withheld from the public. Any record or information that may be withheld under the laws of this state or of the United States when in the possession of such a person may be withheld when revealed or delivered to the State Treasurer. Any record or information that is withheld under any law of another state when in the possession of that other state may be withheld when revealed or delivered by the other state to the State Treasurer.</para> <para>Information withheld from the general public concerning any aspect of unclaimed property shall only be disclosed to an apparent owner of the property or to the escheat, unclaimed, or abandoned property administrators or officials of another state if that other state accords substantially reciprocal privileges to the State Treasurer.</para> <para>(b)(1) On or after October 6, 1992, the State Treasurer shall periodically transfer any balance in excess of an amount not to exceed five hundred thousand dollars from the separate trust fund to the General Fund no less frequently than on or before November 1 and May 1 of each year, except that the total amount of all such transfers shall not exceed five million dollars.</para> <para>(2)(i) On the next succeeding November 1 after five million dollars has been transferred to the General Fund in the manner described in subdivision (b)(1) of this section or (ii) on November 1, 1996, whichever occurs first, and on or before November 1 of each year thereafter, the State Treasurer shall transfer any balance in excess of an amount not to exceed five hundred thousand dollars from the separate trust fund to the permanent school fund.</para> <para>(3) On July 15, 2003, the State Treasurer shall transfer two hundred thousand dollars from the separate trust fund to the General Fund and one hundred thousand dollars from the separate trust fund to the Treasury Management Cash Fund. On September 15, 2004, the State Treasurer shall transfer five hundred thousand dollars from the separate trust fund to the General Fund.</para> <para>(c) Before making any deposit to the credit of the permanent school fund or the General Fund, the State Treasurer may deduct (1) any costs in connection with sale of abandoned property, (2) any costs of mailing and publication in connection with any abandoned property, and (3) reasonable service charges and place such funds in the Unclaimed Property Cash Fund which is hereby created. Transfers from the fund to the General Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Unclaimed Property Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 611, &#167; 17, p. 2488; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 648, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 305, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 754, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 212, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 26, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1048, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1049, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 57, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 424, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB432, &#167;  1.</para><effectivedate>August 30, 2009</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>