<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-1305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-1305</statuteno><catchline>Stock, shareholding, or other intangible ownership interest; presumed abandoned; when.</catchline><para>(a) Any stock, shareholding, or other intangible ownership interest in a business association, the existence of which is evidenced by records available to the association, is presumed abandoned and, with respect to the interest, the association is the holder, if:</para><para>(1) The interest in the association is owned by a person who for more than five years has not claimed a dividend, distribution, or other sum payable as a result of the interest or has not communicated with the association regarding the interest or a dividend, distribution, or other sum payable as a result of the interest, as evidenced by a memorandum or other record on file with the association prepared by an employee of the association; and</para><para>(2) The association does not know the location of the owner at the end of the five-year period.</para><para>(b) The return of official shareholder notifications or communications by the postal service as undeliverable shall be evidence that the association does not know the location of the owner.</para><para>(c) The Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act shall be applicable to both the underlying stock, shareholdings, or other intangible ownership interests of an owner, and any stock, shareholdings, or other intangible ownership interest of which the business association is in possession of the certificate or other evidence or indicia of ownership, and to the stock, shareholdings, or other intangible ownership interests of dividend- and non-dividend-paying business associations whether or not the interest is represented by a certificate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 611, &#167; 5, p. 2482; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 212, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 26, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1048, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 