<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="69-1301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-1301</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>As used in the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act
unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(a) Banking organization means any bank, trust company, savings
bank, industrial bank, land bank, or safe deposit company.</para>
<para>(b) Business association means any corporation, joint-stock
company, business trust, partnership, limited liability company, or association
for business purposes of two or more individuals, but does not include a public
corporation.</para>
<para>(c) Financial organization means any savings and loan association,
building and loan association, credit union, cooperative bank, or investment
company, doing business in this state.</para>
<para>(d) General-use prepaid card means a plastic card or other
electronic payment device usable with multiple, unaffiliated sellers of goods
or services.</para>
<para>(e) Holder means any person in possession of property subject
to the act belonging to another, or who is trustee in case of a trust, or
is indebted to another on an obligation subject to the act.</para>
<para>(f) Life insurance corporation means any association or corporation
transacting within this state the business of insurance on the lives of persons
or insurance appertaining thereto, including, but not limited to, endowments
and annuities.</para>
<para>(g) Military
medal means any decoration or award that may be presented or awarded to a
member of a unit of the United States Armed Forces or National Guard.</para>
<para>(h) Owner means a depositor
in case of a deposit, a beneficiary in case of a trust, a creditor, claimant,
or payee in case of other choses in action, or any person having a legal or
equitable interest in property subject to the act, or his or her legal representative.</para>
<para>(i) Person means any individual,
business association, governmental or political subdivision, public corporation,
public authority, estate, trust, two or more persons having a joint or common
interest, or any other legal or commercial entity.</para>
<para>(j) Utility means any person
who owns or operates within this state, for public use, any plant, equipment,
property, franchise, or license for the transmission of communications or
the production, storage, transmission, sale, delivery, or furnishing of electricity,
water, steam, or gas.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 611, &#167; 1, p. 2478; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 26, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 414; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 173, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB819, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>The State Board of Agriculture while operating parimutuel betting is a business association, as contemplated by the Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act. State ex rel. Marsh v. Nebraska St. Bd. of Agr., 217 Neb. 622, 350 N.W.2d 535 (1984).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>