<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2116</statuteno><catchline>Director of Banking and Finance; investigations; other proceedings; powers.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Director of Banking and Finance in his or her discretion may make such investigations within or without this state as he or she deems necessary to determine whether any person has violated or is about to violate the Consumer Rental Purchase Agreement Act or to aid in the enforcement of the act or in the adopting and promulgating of rules, regulations, and forms under the act. In the discretion of the director, the actual expense of any such investigation may be charged to the person who is the subject of the investigation.</para><para>(b) The director may publish information concerning any violation of the act or any rule, regulation, or order of the director.</para><para>(c) For the purpose of any investigation or proceeding under the act, the director or any officer designated by him or her may administer oaths and affirmations, subpoena witnesses, compel their attendance, take evidence, and require the production of any books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, agreements, or other documents or records which the director deems relevant or material to the inquiry.</para><para>(2) In case of contumacy by or refusal to obey a subpoena issued to any person, any court of competent jurisdiction, upon application by the director, may issue to that person an order requiring him or her to appear before the director or the officer designated by the director to produce documentary evidence if so ordered or to give evidence touching on the matter under investigation or in question. Any failure to obey the order of the court may be punished by the court as a contempt of court. The request for an order of compliance may be addressed to either (a) the district court of Lancaster County or the district court in the county where service may be obtained on the person refusing to testify or produce, if the person is within this state, or (b) the appropriate district court of the state having jurisdiction over the person refusing to testify or produce, if the person is outside this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 111, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 