<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id57">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id59" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="69-2439">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2439</statuteno><catchline id="id62">Permit; application
for revocation; prosecution; fine; costs.</catchline><para>(1) Any
peace officer having probable cause to believe that a permitholder is no longer
in compliance with one or more requirements of section 69-2433, except as provided in subsection (4) of section 69-2443, shall
bring an application for revocation of the permit to be prosecuted as provided
in subsection (2) of this section.</para>
<para>(2) It is the duty of the county attorney or his or her deputy
of the county in which such permitholder resides to prosecute a case for the
revocation of a permit to carry a concealed handgun brought pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section. In case the county attorney refuses or is unable to prosecute
the case, the duty to prosecute shall be upon the Attorney General or his
or her assistant.</para>
<para>(3) The case shall be prosecuted as a civil case, and the
permit shall be revoked upon a showing by a preponderance of the evidence
that the permitholder does not meet one or more of the requirements of section
69-2433, except as provided
in subsection (4) of section 69-2443.</para>
<para>(4) A person who has his or her permit revoked under this
section may be fined up to one thousand dollars and shall be charged with
the costs of the prosecution. The money collected under this subsection as
an administrative fine shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution
in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 454, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB807, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>April 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>