  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2108</statuteno><catchline>Agreement; contents.</catchline><para>Each consumer rental purchase agreement shall:</para><para>(1) Provide that the consumer may terminate the agreement without penalty by voluntarily surrendering or returning the property upon expiration of any lease term; and</para><para>(2) Contain a provision for reinstatement which shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) Permitting a consumer who fails to make a timely lease payment to reinstate the agreement without losing any rights or options which exist under the agreement by the payment of all past-due lease charges, the reasonable costs of pickup, redelivery, and any refurbishing, and any applicable late fee within five business days of the renewal date of the agreement if the consumer pays monthly or within three business days of the renewal date of the agreement if the consumer pays more frequently than monthly; and</para><para>(b) Permitting the consumer to reinstate the agreement during a period of not less than thirty days after the date of the return of the property if the consumer promptly returns or voluntarily surrenders the property upon request by the lessor or its agent. In the event the consumer has paid not less than sixty percent and not more than eighty percent of the total of payments to acquire ownership, the reinstatement period shall be extended to a total of ninety days after the date of the return of the property. In the event the consumer has paid eighty percent or more of the total of payments to acquire ownership, the reinstatement period shall be extended to a total of one hundred eighty days after the date of the return of the property.</para><para>Nothing in this section shall prevent a lessor from attempting to repossess property during the reinstatement period, but such repossession shall not affect the consumer's right to reinstate. Upon reinstatement, the lessor shall provide the consumer with the same property or substitute property of comparable quality and condition.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 681, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 641, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 