<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <source><para>Laws 1991, LB 355, <section id="id329"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id331" statutenumber="69-2404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id333">69-2404</statuteno><catchline id="id334">Certificate; application; fee.</catchline><para>Any person desiring to purchase, lease, rent, or receive transfer of a handgun shall apply with the chief of police or sheriff of the applicant's place of residence for a certificate. The application may be made in person or by mail. The application form and certificate shall be made on forms approved by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety. The application shall include the applicant's full name, address, date of birth, and country of citizenship. If the applicant is not a United States citizen, the application shall include the applicant's place of birth and his or her alien or admission number. If the application is made in person, the applicant shall also present a current Nebraska motor vehicle operator's license, state identification card, or military identification card, or if the application is made by mail, the application form shall describe the license or card used for identification and be notarized by a notary public who has verified the identification of the applicant through such a license or card. An applicant shall receive a certificate if he or she is twenty-one years of age or older and is not prohibited from purchasing or possessing a handgun by 18 U.S.C. 922. A fee of five dollars shall be charged for each application for a certificate to cover the cost of a criminal history record check.</para> </amendatorysection></section>&#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1227, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 33.</para></source> <annotation><para>The applicant was prohibited from purchasing or possessing a handgun where his conviction for third degree assault met the criteria for domestic violence under federal law due to the circumstances of the offense. Scalise v. Davis, 312 Neb. 518, 980 N.W.2d 27 (2022).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>