<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2409.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2409.01</statuteno><catchline>Mental health treatment data base; created; disclosure; limitation; liability; prohibited act; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of sections 69-2401 to 69-2425, the Nebraska State Patrol shall be furnished upon the patrol's request with only such information as may be necessary for the sole purpose of determining whether an individual is disqualified from purchasing or possessing a handgun pursuant to state or federal law. Such information shall be furnished by the Department of Health and Human Services. The clerks of the various courts shall furnish to the Department of Health and Human Services, within thirty days after the order of commitment or finding and the discharge, all information necessary to set up and maintain the data base required by this section. This information shall include (a) information regarding those persons who are currently receiving mental health treatment pursuant to a commitment order of a mental health board or who have been discharged and (b) information regarding those persons who have been committed to treatment pursuant to section 29-3702. The Department of Health and Human Services shall also maintain in the data base a listing of persons committed to treatment pursuant to section 29-3702. Information regarding mental health board commitments and commitments pursuant to section 29-3702 shall not be retained in the data base maintained by the department on persons who have been discharged from those commitments more than five years previously. Any such information maintained or disclosed under this subsection shall remain privileged and confidential and shall not be redisclosed or utilized for any other purpose. The procedures for furnishing such information shall guarantee that no information is released beyond what is necessary for purposes of this section.</para><para>(2) In order to comply with sections 69-2401 and 69-2403 to 69-2408 and this section, the Nebraska State Patrol shall provide to the chief of police or sheriff of an applicant's place of residence or a licensee in the process of a criminal history record check pursuant to section 69-2411 only the information regarding whether or not the applicant is disqualified from purchasing or possessing a handgun.</para><para>(3) Any person, agency, or mental health board participating in good faith in the reporting or disclosure of records and communications under this section is immune from any liability, civil, criminal, or otherwise, that might result by reason of the action.</para><para>(4) Any person who intentionally causes the Nebraska State Patrol to request information pursuant to this section without reasonable belief that the named individual has submitted a written application under section 69-2404 or has completed a consent form under section 69-2410 shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor in addition to other civil or criminal liability under state or federal law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1055, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 112. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 