<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2432" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2432</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska State Patrol; handgun training and safety courses and instructors; duties; certificate of completion of course; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska State Patrol shall prepare and publish minimum training and safety requirements for and adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing handgun training and safety courses and handgun training and safety course instructors. Minimum safety and training requirements for a handgun training and safety course shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) Knowledge and safe handling of a handgun;</para><para>(b) Knowledge and safe handling of handgun ammunition;</para><para>(c) Safe handgun shooting fundamentals;</para><para>(d) A demonstration of competency with a handgun with respect to the minimum safety and training requirements;</para><para>(e) Knowledge of federal, state, and local laws pertaining to the purchase, ownership, transportation, and possession of handguns;</para><para>(f) Knowledge of federal, state, and local laws pertaining to the use of a handgun, including, but not limited to, use of a handgun for self-defense and laws relating to justifiable homicide and the various degrees of assault;</para><para>(g) Knowledge of ways to avoid a criminal attack and to defuse or control a violent confrontation; and</para><para>(h) Knowledge of proper storage practices for handguns and ammunition, including storage practices which would reduce the possibility of accidental injury to a child.</para><para>(2) A person or entity conducting a handgun training and safety course and the course instructors shall be approved by the patrol before operation. The patrol shall issue a certificate evidencing its approval.</para><para>(3) A certificate of completion of a handgun training and safety course shall be issued by the person or entity conducting a handgun training and safety course to persons successfully completing the course. The certificate of completion shall also include certification from the instructor that the person completing the course does not suffer from a readily discernible physical infirmity that prevents the person from safely handling a handgun.</para><para>(4) Any fee for participation in a handgun training and safety course is the responsibility of the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 454, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>