<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id172">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id174" statutenumber="69-2708"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2708</statuteno><catchline id="id177">Stamping agent;
duties; Tax Commissioner; Attorney General; powers.</catchline><para>(1)
Not later than fifteen
days following the end of each month, each stamping agent shall
submit, in the manner directed
by the Tax Commissioner, such information as the Tax Commissioner
requires to facilitate compliance with sections 69-2704 to 69-2711, including,
but not limited to (a) a list by brand family
of the total number of cigarettes or, in the case of roll-your-own, the equivalent
stick count for which the stamping agent affixed stamps during the previous month or otherwise paid the total due for such cigarettes, the total number of cigarettes contained in the packages
to which it affixed each respective type of stamp, and by name and number
of cigarettes, the tobacco product manufacturers and brand families of the
packages to which it affixed each respective type of stamp or similar information
for roll-your-own on which tax was paid and (b) the total number of cigarettes
acquired by the stamping agent during that month for sale in or into the state
or for sale from this state into another state, sold in or into the state
by the stamping agent during that month and held in inventory in the state
or for sale into the state by the stamping agent as of the last business day
of that month, in each case identifying by name and number of cigarettes,
(i) the manufacturers of those cigarettes and (ii) the brand families of those
cigarettes. In the case of a stamping agent that is a retailer, reports under
subdivision (1)(a) of this section do not have to include cigarettes contained
in packages that bore a stamp required under section 77-2603 or 77-2603.01
at the time the stamping agent received them and that the stamping agent then
sold at retail. The stamping agent shall also submit a certification stating
that the information provided to the Tax Commissioner is complete and accurate.
The stamping agent shall maintain, and make available to the Tax Commissioner,
all invoices and documentation of sales of all nonparticipating manufacturer
cigarettes and any other information relied upon in reporting to the Tax Commissioner
for a period of five years. The
Tax Commissioner may share the information reported under this section with
the taxing or law enforcement authorities of this state or other states. The
Tax Commissioner may also share with a nonparticipating manufacturer information
reported under this section pertaining to such nonparticipating manufacturer's
cigarettes.</para>
<para>(2) The Attorney General may require at any time from the
nonparticipating manufacturer proof, from the financial institution in which
such manufacturer has established a qualified escrow fund for the purpose
of compliance with section 69-2703, of the amount of money in such fund, exclusive
of interest, the amounts and dates of each deposit to such fund, and the amounts
and dates of each withdrawal from such fund.</para>
<para>(3) In addition to the information required to be submitted
pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the Tax Commissioner or Attorney
General may require a stamping agent, distributor, or tobacco product manufacturer
to submit any additional information, including, but not limited to, samples
of the packaging or labeling of each brand family, as is necessary to enable
the Tax Commissioner or Attorney General to determine whether a tobacco product
manufacturer is in compliance with sections 69-2704 to 69-2711.</para>
<para>(4) The
Tax Commissioner or the Attorney
General may require production of information sufficient to enable
the Tax Commissioner or Attorney
General to determine the adequacy of the amount of a
quarterly escrow deposit under subdivision (2) of section 69-2703. The Tax
Commissioner may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations implementing how
tobacco product manufacturers subject to subdivision (2) of section 69-2703
make quarterly payments.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 572, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB580, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
