<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="69-2402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2402</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of sections 69-2401 to 69-2425:</para>
<para>(1) Antique handgun or pistol means any
handgun or pistol, including those with a matchlock, flintlock, percussion
cap, or similar type of ignition system, manufactured in or before 1898 and
any replica of such a handgun or pistol if such replica (a) is not designed
or redesigned for using rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition
or (b) uses rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition which is no
longer manufactured in the United States and which is not readily available
in the ordinary channels of commercial trade;</para>
<para>(2) Criminal history record check includes a
check of the criminal history records of the Nebraska State Patrol and a check
of the Federal Bureau of Investigation's National Instant Criminal Background
Check System;</para>
<para>(3) Firearm-related
disability means a person is not permitted to (a) purchase, possess, ship,
transport, or receive a firearm under either state or federal law, (b) obtain
a certificate to purchase, lease, rent, or receive transfer of a handgun under
section 69-2404, or (c) obtain a permit to carry a concealed handgun under
the Concealed Handgun Permit Act; and</para><para>(4) Handgun means any
firearm with a barrel less than sixteen inches in length or any firearm designed
to be held and fired by the use of a single hand.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 355, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1055, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1227, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB512, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Concealed Handgun Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 69-2427.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
