<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id166">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" id="id168" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="69-2707.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2707.01</statuteno><catchline>Nonparticipating manufacturers;
bond; amount; failure to make escrow deposits; execution upon bond.</catchline>
<para>(1) All nonparticipating
manufacturers shall post a bond or its cash equivalent for the benefit of
the state which is subject to execution under subsection (3) of this section.
The bond shall be posted by corporate surety located within the United States,
or the cash equivalent of the bond shall be posted by the nonparticipating
manufacturer in an account approved by the state. The bond or its cash equivalent
shall be posted and evidence of such posting shall be provided to the Tax
Commissioner at least ten days in advance of each calendar quarter as a condition
to the nonparticipating manufacturer and its brand families being included
in the directory for that quarter.</para>
<para>(2) The amount
of the bond shall be determined as follows:</para><para>(a) Unless subdivision (c) of this subsection is applicable,
for a nonparticipating manufacturer or its affiliates which have been listed
on any state's directory for at least three years or for any nonparticipating
manufacturer whose sales are authorized pursuant to an agreement under section
77-2602.06, the amount of the bond required shall be twenty-five thousand
dollars;</para><para>(b)
Unless subdivision (c) of this subsection is applicable, for a nonparticipating
manufacturer or its affiliates which have not been listed on any state's directory
for at least three years, the amount of the bond required shall be fifty thousand
dollars; and</para><para>(c)
For a nonparticipating manufacturer or its affiliates which have failed, in
the past three years, to make a full and timely escrow deposit due under section
69-2703, unless the failure was not knowing or intentional and was promptly
cured upon notice, or for any nonparticipating manufacturer or its affiliates
which were involuntarily removed from any state's directory, unless the removal
was determined to have been erroneous or illegal, the amount of the bond required
shall be the greater of (i) fifty thousand dollars or (ii) the greatest amount
of escrow owed by the nonparticipating manufacturer or its predecessor in
any calendar year in Nebraska within the preceding five calendar years.</para>
<para>(3) If a nonparticipating
manufacturer that posted a bond has failed to make, or have made on its behalf
by an entity with joint and several liability, escrow deposits equal to the
full amount owed for a quarter within fifteen days following the due date
for the quarter under section 69-2703, the state may execute upon the bond,
first to recover delinquent escrow, which amount shall be deposited into a
qualified escrow account under section 69-2703, and then to recover civil
penalties and costs authorized under such section. Escrow obligations above
the amount collected on the bond remain due from that nonparticipating manufacturer
and, as provided in subdivision (2)(d) of section 69-2703 and section 69-2708.01,
from the importers and stamping agents that sold its cigarettes during that
calendar quarter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>