<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id838"><amendatorysection statutenumber="69-2703.02" chaptername="Personal Property"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2703.02</statuteno><catchline>Tobacco product manufacturer; qualified escrow fund; irrevocable assignment; form; amounts withdrawn; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding subdivision (2)(b) of section 69-2703, a tobacco product manufacturer that elects to place funds into a qualified escrow fund pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of section 69-2703 may make an irrevocable assignment of its interest in the fund to the benefit of the State of Nebraska. Such assignment shall be permanent and apply to all monetary amounts in the subject qualified escrow fund or that may subsequently come into the fund, including those deposited into the qualified escrow fund prior to the assignment being executed, those deposited into the qualified escrow fund after the assignment is executed, and interest or other appreciation on the amounts. The tobacco product manufacturer, the Attorney General, and the financial institution where the qualified escrow fund is maintained may make such amendments to the qualified escrow fund agreement, the title to the account, and the account itself as may be necessary to effectuate an assignment of rights executed pursuant to this subsection (1) or a withdrawal of amounts from the qualified escrow fund pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. An assignment of rights executed pursuant to this section shall be in writing, shall have received prior approval issued in writing by the Attorney General, shall be signed by the tobacco product manufacturer or a duly authorized representative of the tobacco product manufacturer making the assignment, and shall become effective upon delivery of the assignment to the Attorney General and the financial institution where the qualified escrow fund is maintained.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding subdivision (2)(b) of section 69-2703, any escrow amounts assigned to the State of Nebraska pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall be withdrawn by the state upon request by the State Treasurer and approval by the Attorney General. Any amounts withdrawn pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska, and shall be calculated on a dollar-for-dollar basis as a credit against any judgment or settlement described in subdivision (2)(b) of section 69-2703 which may be obtained against the tobacco product manufacturer who has assigned the amounts in the subject qualified escrow fund. Nothing in this section shall be construed to relieve a tobacco product manufacturer from any past, current, or future obligations the manufacturer may have pursuant to sections 69-2701 to 69-2711.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB397, &#167; 12. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>