<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2411" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2411</statuteno><catchline>Request for criminal history record check; Nebraska State Patrol; duties; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receipt of a request for a criminal history record check, the Nebraska State Patrol shall as soon as possible during the licensee's telephone call or by return telephone call:</para><para>(a) Check its criminal history records and check the Federal Bureau of Investigation's National Instant Criminal Background Check System to determine if the potential buyer or transferee is prohibited from receipt or possession of a handgun pursuant to state or federal law; and</para><para>(b) Either (i) inform the licensee that its records demonstrate that the potential buyer or transferee is prohibited from receipt or possession of a handgun or (ii) provide the licensee with a unique approval number.</para><para>(2) In the event of electronic failure or similar emergency beyond the control of the Nebraska State Patrol, the patrol shall immediately notify a requesting licensee of the reason for and estimated length of such delay. In any event, no later than the end of the next business day the Nebraska State Patrol shall either (a) inform the licensee that its records demonstrate that the potential buyer or transferee is prohibited from receipt or possession of a handgun or (b) provide the licensee with a unique approval number. If the licensee is not informed by the end of the next business day that the potential buyer is prohibited from receipt or possession of a handgun, and regardless of whether the unique approval number has been received, the licensee may complete the sale or delivery and shall not be deemed to be in violation of sections 69-2410 to 69-2423 with respect to such sale or delivery.</para><para>(3) A fee of three dollars shall be charged for each request of a criminal history record check required pursuant to section 69-2410, which amount shall be transmitted monthly to the Nebraska State Patrol. Such amount shall be for the purpose of covering the costs of the criminal history record check.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 355, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1227, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>