<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id75">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id77" statutenumber="69-2703">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2703</statuteno><catchline id="id80">Tobacco product
manufacturer; requirements to sell within the state.</catchline><para>Any
tobacco product manufacturer selling cigarettes to consumers within the state,
whether directly or through a distributor, retailer, or similar intermediary
or intermediaries, after April 29, 1999, shall do one of the following:</para>
<para>(1) Become a participating manufacturer, as that term is defined
in section II(jj) of the Master Settlement Agreement, and generally perform
its financial obligations under the Master Settlement Agreement; or</para>
<para>(2)(a) Place into a qualified escrow fund on a quarterly basis, no later than thirty
days after the end of each calendar quarter in which sales are made, the
following amounts, as such amounts are adjusted for inflation:</para>
<para>(i) 1999: $.0094241 per unit sold after April 29, 1999;</para>
<para>(ii) 2000: $.0104712 per unit sold;</para>
<para>(iii) For each of the years 2001 and 2002: $.0136125 per unit
sold;</para>
<para>(iv) For each of the years 2003, 2004, 2005, and 2006: $.0167539
per unit sold; and</para>
<para>(v) For the year 2007 and each year thereafter: $.0188482
per unit sold.</para>
<para>(b) A tobacco product manufacturer that places funds into
escrow pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section shall receive the interest
or other appreciation on such funds as earned. Such funds shall be released
from escrow only under the following circumstances:</para>
<para>(i) To pay a judgment or settlement on any released claim
brought against such tobacco product manufacturer by the state or any releasing
party located or residing in the state. Funds shall be released from escrow
under this subdivision (2)(b)(i) in the order in which they were placed into
escrow and only to the extent and at the time necessary to make payments required
under such judgment or settlement;</para>
<para>(ii) To the extent that a tobacco product manufacturer establishes
that the amount it was required to place into escrow on account of units sold
in the state in a particular year was greater than the Master Settlement Agreement
payments, as determined pursuant to section IX(i) of that Agreement including
after final determination of all adjustments, that such manufacturer would
have been required to make on account of such units sold had it been a participating
manufacturer, the excess shall be released from escrow and revert back to
such tobacco product manufacturer;</para>
<para>(iii) To the extent not released from escrow under subdivision
(2)(b)(i) or (2)(b)(ii) of this section, funds shall be released from escrow
and revert back to such tobacco product manufacturer twenty-five years after
the date on which they were placed into escrow; or</para>
<para>(iv) An Indian
tribe may seek release of escrow deposited pursuant to this section on cigarettes
sold on an Indian tribe's Indian country to its tribal members pursuant to
an agreement entered into between the state and the Indian tribe pursuant
to section 77-2602.06. Amounts the state collects on a bond under section
69-2707.01 shall not be subject to release under this section.</para>
<para>(c) Each tobacco product manufacturer that elects to place
funds into escrow pursuant to subdivision (2) of this section shall annually
certify to the Attorney General that it is in compliance with subdivision
(2) of this section. The Attorney General may bring a civil action on behalf
of the state against any tobacco product manufacturer that fails to place
into escrow the funds required under this section. Any tobacco product manufacturer
that fails in any calendar quarter to place
into escrow the funds required under this section shall:</para>
<para>(i) Be required within fifteen days to place such funds into
escrow as shall bring the manufacturer into compliance with this section.
The court, upon a finding of a violation of subdivision (2) of this section,
may impose a civil penalty in an amount not to exceed five percent of the
amount improperly withheld from escrow per day of the violation and in a total
amount not to exceed one hundred percent of the original amount improperly
withheld from escrow;</para>
<para>(ii) In the case of a knowing violation, be required within
fifteen days to place such funds into escrow as shall bring the manufacturer
into compliance with this section. The court, upon a finding of a knowing
violation of subdivision (2) of this section, may impose a civil penalty in
an amount not to exceed fifteen percent of the amount improperly withheld
from escrow per day of the violation and in a total amount not to exceed three
hundred percent of the original amount improperly withheld from escrow. Such
civil penalty shall be remitted to
the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article
VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska; and</para>
<para>(iii) In the case of a second knowing violation, be prohibited
from selling cigarettes to consumers within the state, whether directly or
through a distributor, retailer, or similar intermediary, for a period not
to exceed two years.</para>
<para>(d) An importer
shall be jointly and severally liable for escrow deposits due from a nonparticipating
manufacturer with respect to nonparticipating manufacturer cigarettes that
it imported and which were then sold in this state, except as provided for
by an agreement entered into pursuant to section 77-2602.06.</para>
<para>(e) Each
failure to make a quarterly deposit required
under this section constitutes a separate violation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 574, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 944, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 5.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
