<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2409"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2409</statuteno><catchline>Automated criminal history files;
legislative intent; system implementation; Nebraska State Patrol; superintendent;
duties; purchase, lease, rental, or transfer; election.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the
Legislature that the Nebraska State Patrol implement an expedited program
of upgrading Nebraska's automated criminal history files to be utilized for,
among other law enforcement purposes, an instant criminal history record check
on handgun purchasers when buying a handgun from a licensed importer, manufacturer,
or dealer so that such instant criminal history record check may be implemented
as soon as possible on or after January 1, 1995.</para>
<para>(2) The patrol's
automated arrest and conviction records shall be reviewed annually by the
Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety who shall report the status
of such records within thirty days of such review to the Governor and the
Clerk of the Legislature. The
report submitted to the Clerk of the Legislature shall be submitted electronically. The
instant criminal history record check system shall be implemented by the patrol
on or after January 1, 1995, when, as determined by the Superintendent of
Law Enforcement and Public Safety, eighty-five percent of the Nebraska arrest
and conviction records since January 1, 1965, available to the patrol are
included in the patrol's automated system. Not less than thirty days prior
to implementation and enforcement of the instant check system, the patrol
shall send written notice to all licensed importers, manufacturers, and dealers
outlining the procedures and toll-free number described in sections 69-2410
to 69-2423.</para>
<para>(3) Upon
implementation of the instant criminal history record check system, a person
who desires to purchase, lease, rent, or receive transfer of a handgun from
a licensed importer, manufacturer, or dealer may elect to obtain such handgun
either under sections 69-2401, 69-2403 to 69-2408, and 69-2409.01 or under
sections 69-2409.01 and 69-2410 to 69-2423.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 355, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1055, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 99.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>