<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<sectno id="id4">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="69-2433"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">69-2433</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Applicant; requirements.</catchline><para>An applicant shall:</para>
<para>(1) Be at least twenty-one years of age;</para>
<para>(2) Not be prohibited from purchasing or possessing a handgun
by 18 U.S.C. 922, as such section existed on January 1, 2005;</para>
<para>(3) Possess the same powers of eyesight as required under
section 60-4,118 for a Class O operator's license. If an applicant does not
possess a current Nebraska motor vehicle operator's license, the applicant
may present a current optometrist's or ophthalmologist's statement certifying
the vision reading obtained when testing the applicant. If such certified
vision reading meets the vision requirements prescribed by section 60-4,118
for a Class O operator's license, the vision requirements of this subdivision
shall have been met;</para>
<para>(4) Not have pled guilty to, not have pled nolo contendere
to, or not have been convicted of a felony under the laws of this state or under the
laws of any other jurisdiction;</para>
<para>(5) Not have
pled guilty to, not have pled nolo contendere to, or not have been convicted
of a misdemeanor crime of violence under the laws of this state or under the
laws of any other jurisdiction within the ten years immediately preceding
the date of application;</para><para>(6) Not
have been found in the previous ten years to be a mentally ill and dangerous
person under the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act or a similar law of
another jurisdiction or not be currently adjudged mentally incompetent;</para>
<para>(7)(a) Have been a resident
of this state for at least one hundred eighty days. For purposes of this section,
resident does not include an applicant who maintains a residence in another
state and claims that residence for voting or tax purposes except as provided
in subdivision (b) of this subdivision; or</para>
<para>(b) If an applicant is a member of the United States Armed
Forces, such applicant shall be considered a resident of this state for purposes
of this section after he or she has been stationed at a military installation
in this state pursuant to permanent duty station orders even though he or
she maintains a residence in another state and claims that residence for voting
or tax purposes;</para>
<para>(8) Have had no violations
of any law of this state relating to firearms, unlawful use of a weapon, or
controlled substances or of any similar laws of another jurisdiction in the
ten years preceding the date of application;</para>
<para>(9) Not be on parole, probation,
house arrest, or work release;</para>
<para>(10) Be a citizen of the United
States; and</para>
<para>(11) Provide proof of training.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 454, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB430, &#167;  11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB817, &#167;  8.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>