
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id157">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id159" statutenumber="69-2707"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2707</statuteno><catchline id="id162">Nonresident
or foreign nonparticipating manufacturer; agent for service of process.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any nonresident or foreign nonparticipating manufacturer
that has not registered to do business in the state as a foreign corporation
or business entity shall, as a condition precedent to having its brand families
included or retained in the directory created in subsection (2) of section
69-2706, appoint and continually engage without interruption the services
of an agent in Nebraska to act as agent for
the service of process on whom all process, and any action or proceeding against
it concerning or arising out of the enforcement of sections 69-2703 to 69-2711, may be served in any manner authorized
by law. Such service shall constitute legal and valid service of process on
the nonparticipating manufacturer. The nonparticipating manufacturer shall
provide the name, address, telephone number, and proof of the appointment
and availability of such agent to the Tax Commissioner and Attorney General.</para>
<para>(2) The nonparticipating manufacturer shall provide notice
to the Tax Commissioner and Attorney General thirty calendar days prior to
termination of the authority of an agent and shall further provide proof to
the satisfaction of the Attorney General of the appointment of a new agent
no less than five calendar days prior to the termination of an existing agent
appointment. In the event an agent terminates an agency appointment, the nonparticipating
manufacturer shall notify the Tax Commissioner and Attorney General of the
termination within five calendar days and shall include proof to the satisfaction
of the Attorney General of the appointment of a new agent.</para>
<para>(3) Any nonparticipating manufacturer whose products are
sold in this state who has not appointed and engaged the services of an agent
as required by this section shall be deemed to have appointed the Secretary
of State as its agent for service of process. The appointment of the Secretary
of State as agent shall not satisfy the condition precedent required in subsection
(1) of this section to have the nonparticipating manufacturer's brand families
included or retained in the directory.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 572, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB580, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
