<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id15">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id17" statutenumber="69-2409.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2409.01</statuteno><catchline id="id20">Data base; created; disclosure;
limitation; liability; prohibited act; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of sections 69-2401 to 69-2425, the Nebraska State
Patrol shall be furnished with only such information as may be necessary
for the sole purpose of determining whether an individual is disqualified
from purchasing or possessing a handgun pursuant to state law or
is subject to the disability provisions of 18 U.S.C. 922(d)(4) and (g)(4).
Such information shall be furnished by the Department of Health and Human
Services. The clerks of the various courts shall furnish to the Department
of Health and Human Services and Nebraska State Patrol, as soon as
practicable but within thirty days after an order
of commitment or discharge is
issued or after removal of firearm-related disabilities pursuant to section
71-963, all information necessary to set up and maintain the data
base required by this section. This information shall include (a) information
regarding those persons who are currently receiving mental health treatment
pursuant to a commitment order of a mental health board or who have been discharged, (b) information regarding those persons
who have been committed to treatment pursuant to section 29-3702, and (c) information regarding those
persons who have had firearm-related disabilities removed pursuant to section
71-963. The mental health board shall notify the Department of Health and
Human Services and the Nebraska State Patrol when such disabilities have been
removed. The Department of Health and Human Services shall also
maintain in the data base a listing of persons committed to treatment pursuant
to section 29-3702. To
ensure the accuracy of the data base, any information maintained
or disclosed under this subsection shall be
updated, corrected, modified, or removed, as appropriate, and as soon as practicable,
from any data base that the state or federal government maintains and makes
available to the National Instant Criminal Background Check System. The
procedures for furnishing the information shall guarantee
that no information is released beyond what is necessary for purposes of this
section.</para>
<para>(2) In order to comply with sections 69-2401 and 69-2403 to
69-2408 and this section, the Nebraska State Patrol shall provide to the chief
of police or sheriff of an applicant's place of residence or a licensee in
the process of a criminal history record check pursuant to section 69-2411
only the information regarding whether or not the applicant is disqualified
from purchasing or possessing a handgun.</para>
<para>(3) Any person, agency, or mental health board participating
in good faith in the reporting or disclosure of records and communications
under this section is immune from any liability, civil, criminal, or otherwise,
that might result by reason of the action.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who intentionally causes the Nebraska State
Patrol to request information pursuant to this section without reasonable
belief that the named individual has submitted a written application under
section 69-2404 or has completed a consent form under section 69-2410 shall
be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor in addition to other civil or criminal
liability under state or federal law.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1055, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 307, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB512, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
