 <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id343"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id345" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="69-2410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id347">69-2410</statuteno><catchline id="id348">Importer, manufacturer, or dealer; sale or delivery; duties.</catchline><para>No importer, manufacturer, or dealer licensed pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 923 shall sell or deliver any handgun to another person other than a licensed importer, manufacturer, dealer, or collector until he or she has:</para> <para>(1)(a) Inspected a valid certificate issued to such person pursuant to sections 69-2401, 69-2403 to 69-2408, and 69-2409.01; and</para> <para>(b) Inspected a valid identification containing a photograph of such person which appropriately and completely identifies such person; or</para> <para>(2)(a) Obtained a completed consent form from the potential buyer or transferee, which form shall be established by the Nebraska State Patrol and provided by the licensed importer, manufacturer, or dealer. The form shall include the name, address, date of birth, gender, race, and country of citizenship of such potential buyer or transferee. If the potential buyer or transferee is not a United States citizen, the completed consent form shall contain the potential buyer's or transferee's place of birth and his or her alien or admission number;</para> <para>(b) Inspected a valid identification containing a photograph of the potential buyer or transferee which appropriately and completely identifies such person;</para> <para>(c) Requested by toll-free telephone call or other electromagnetic communication that the Nebraska State Patrol conduct a criminal history record check; and</para> <para>(d) Received a unique approval number for such inquiry from the Nebraska State Patrol indicating the date and number on the consent form.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 355, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1055, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1227, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 35.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>