<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" statutenumber="69-2103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2103</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For
purposes of the Consumer Rental Purchase Agreement Act:</para>
<para>(1) Advertisement means a commercial message in any medium that aids,
promotes, or assists directly or indirectly a consumer rental purchase agreement
but does not include in-store merchandising aids such as window signs and
ceiling banners;</para>
<para>(2) Cash price means the price at which the lessor would have sold the
property to the consumer for cash on the date of the consumer rental purchase
agreement for the property;</para>
<para>(3) Consumer means a natural person who rents property under a consumer
rental purchase agreement;</para>
<para>(4) Consumer rental purchase agreement means an agreement which is for
the use of property by a consumer primarily for personal, family, or household
purposes, which is for an initial period of four months or less, whether or
not there is any obligation beyond the initial period, which is automatically
renewable with each payment, and which permits the consumer to become the
owner of the property. A consumer rental purchase agreement in compliance
with the act shall not be construed to be a lease or agreement which constitutes
a credit sale as defined in 12 C.F.R. 226.2(a)(16), as such regulation existed
on January 1, 2011, and 15 U.S.C.
1602(g), as such section existed on January
1, 2011, or a lease which constitutes a consumer lease as defined
in 12 C.F.R. 213.2(e), as such regulation existed on January 1, 2011. Consumer rental purchase agreement
does not include:</para>
<para>(a) Any lease for agricultural, business, or commercial purposes;</para>
<para>(b) Any lease made to an organization;</para>
<para>(c) A lease or agreement which constitutes an installment sale or installment
contract as defined in section 45-335;</para>
<para>(d) A security interest as defined in subdivision (35) of section 1-201,
Uniform Commercial Code; and</para>
<para>(e) A home solicitation sale as defined in section 69-1601;</para>
<para>(5) Consummation means the occurrence of an event which causes a consumer
to become contractually obligated on a consumer rental purchase agreement;</para>
<para>(6) Department means the Department of Banking and Finance;</para>
<para>(7) Lease payment means a payment to be made by the consumer for the
right of possession and use of the property for a specific lease period but
does not include taxes imposed on such payment;</para>
<para>(8) Lease period means a week, month, or other specific period of time,
during which the consumer has the right to possess and use the property after
paying the lease payment and applicable taxes for such period;</para>
<para>(9) Lessor means a person who in the ordinary course of business operates
a commercial outlet which regularly leases, offers to lease, or arranges for
the leasing of property under a consumer rental purchase agreement;</para>
<para>(10) Property means any property that is not real property under the
laws of this state when made available for a consumer rental purchase agreement;
and</para>
<para>(11) Total of payments to acquire ownership means the total of all charges
imposed by the lessor and payable by the consumer as a condition of acquiring
ownership of the property. Total of payments to acquire ownership includes
lease payments and any initial nonrefundable administrative fee or required
delivery charge but does not include taxes, late charges, reinstatement fees,
or charges for optional products or services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 681, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 111, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 641, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 570, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB76, &#167; 6.</para><effectivedate>February 23, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
