<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id239">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Personal Property" id="id241" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="69-2710.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>69-2710.02</statuteno><catchline>License of stamping agent; termination;
grounds; cure; notice; reinstatement; removal from directory; grounds; cure;
notice; procedure.</catchline><para>(1)
The license of a stamping agent may be subject to termination if its similar
license is terminated in any other state based on acts or omissions that would
be grounds for license termination under subsection (2) of section 69-2709,
unless the stamping agent demonstrates that its termination in the other state
was effected without due process. If a stamping agent's license is terminated
in another state for a violation similar to a violation listed in subdivision
(2)(a), (b), (c), or (d) of section 69-2709 that was not knowing or intentional,
the stamping agent shall not be subject to license termination if the stamping
agent fully cures such violation and provides notice of such cure to the Department
of Revenue within ten days after receipt of notice of such violation. A stamping
agent whose license is terminated under this subsection shall be eligible
for reinstatement upon the earlier of the date specified by subsection (7)
of section 69-2709 for the act or omission in question or reinstatement of
its license by the other state.</para>
<para>(2) A tobacco
product manufacturer and its brand families may be removed from the directory
if it is removed from the directory of another state based on acts or omissions
that would, if done in this state, be grounds for removal from the directory
under section 69-2706, 69-2707, 69-2707.01, or 69-2710 or subsection (6) of
section 69-2709, unless the tobacco product manufacturer demonstrates that
its removal from the other state's directory was effected without due process,
that it fully cured such violation and provided notice of such cure to the
Department of Revenue within thirty days after receipt of notice of the violation,
or that it secured a temporary injunction against removal from the directory
in the district court of Lancaster County. For purposes of a temporary injunction
sought pursuant to this subsection, loss of the ability to sell tobacco products
as a result of removal from the directory shall constitute irreparable harm.
If, after thirty days, the tobacco product manufacturer remains in noncompliance
and has not obtained a temporary injunction pursuant to this subsection, the
tobacco product manufacturer shall be removed from the directory. A manufacturer
that is removed from the directory under this subsection shall be eligible
for reinstatement upon the earlier of the date on which it cures the violation
or is reinstated to the directory in the other state.</para><para>(3) The applicable procedures
under section 77-2615.01 shall apply to terminations and removals under this
section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 15.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>