<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id121"> <sectno id="id122">Sec. 10.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Personal Property" id="id123" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="69-2430"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id125">69-2430</statuteno><catchline id="id126">Application; form; contents; prohibited acts; penalty; permit issuance; denial; appeal.</catchline> <para>(1) Application for a permit to carry a concealed handgun shall be made in person at any Nebraska State Patrol Troop Headquarters or office provided by the patrol for purposes of accepting such an application. The applicant shall present a current Nebraska motor vehicle operator's license, Nebraska-issued state identification card, or military identification card and shall submit two legible sets of fingerprints for a criminal history record information check pursuant to section 69-2431. The application shall be made on a form prescribed by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety. The application shall state the applicant's full name, motor vehicle operator's license number or state identification card number, address, and date of birth and contain the applicant's signature and shall include space for the applicant to affirm that he or she meets each and every one of the requirements set forth in section 69-2433. The applicant shall attach to the application proof of training and proof of vision as required in subdivision (3) of section 69-2433.</para> <para>(2) A person applying for a permit to carry a concealed handgun who gives false information or offers false evidence of his or her identity is guilty of a Class IV felony.</para> <para>(3)(a) Until January 1, 2010, the permit to carry a concealed handgun shall be issued by the Nebraska State Patrol within five business days after completion of the applicant's criminal history record information check, if the applicant has complied with this section and has met all the requirements of section 69-2433.</para> <para>(b) Beginning January 1, 2010, the permit to carry a concealed handgun shall be issued by the Nebraska State Patrol within forty-five days after the date an application for the permit has been made by the applicant if the applicant has complied with this section and has met all the requirements of section 69-2433.</para> <para>(4) An applicant denied a permit to carry a concealed handgun may appeal to the district court of the judicial district of the county in which he or she resides or the county in which he or she applied for the permit pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 454, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB63, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB430, &#167; 10.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>