
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id383"><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Protection Orders" statutenumber="26-102" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>26-102</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Protection Orders Act:</para><para>(1) Abuse has the same meaning as in section 42-903;</para><para>(2) Family or household members has the same meaning as in section 42-903;</para><para>(3) Harass has the same meaning as in section 28-311.02;</para><para>(4) Household pet means any animal maintained for companionship or pleasure but does not include any animal kept primarily for commercial purposes or for consumption or any livestock animal as defined in section 54-902;</para><para>(5) Law enforcement agency means the police department or town marshal in incorporated municipalities, the office of the sheriff in unincorporated areas, and the Nebraska State Patrol;</para><para>(6) Military protective order has the same meaning as in 32 C.F.R. 635.19, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2026; and</para><para>(7) Sexual assault offense means:</para><para>(a) Conduct amounting to sexual assault under section 28-319 or 28-320, sexual abuse by a school worker under section 28-316.01, sexual assault of a child under section 28-319.01 or 28-320.01, a violation of section 28-311.08, or an attempt to commit any of such offenses; or</para><para>(b) Subjecting or attempting to subject another person to sexual contact or sexual penetration without such person's consent, as such terms are defined in section 28-318.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB80, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB753, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB935, &#167; 9.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB753, section 2, with LB935, section 9, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB753 became effective July 18, 2026. Changes made by LB935 became operative July 18, 2026.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>