<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-915" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>57-915</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who violates any provision of sections 57-901 to 57-921, or any rule, regulation or order of the commission shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor. Each day that such violation continues shall constitute a separate offense.</para><para>(2) If any person, for the purpose of evading the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921, or any rule, regulation or order of the commission, shall make or cause to be made any false entry or statement in a report required by the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921, or by any such rule, regulation or order, or shall make or cause to be made any false entry in any record, account or memorandum required by the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921, or by any such rule, regulation or order, or shall remove from this state or destroy, mutilate, alter or falsify any such record, account or memorandum, such person shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para><para>(3) Any person knowingly aiding or abetting any other person in the violation of any provision of sections 57-901 to 57-921, or any rule, regulation or order of the commission shall be subject to the same penalty as that prescribed by the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921 for the violation by such other person.</para><para>(4) The penalties provided in this section shall be recoverable by suit filed by the Attorney General in the name and on behalf of the commission, in the district court of the county in which the defendant resides, or in which any defendant resides, if there be more than one defendant, or in the district court of any county in which the violation occurred. The payment of any such penalty shall not operate to relieve a person on whom the penalty is imposed from liability to any other person for damages arising out of such violation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 262, &#167; 15, p. 913; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1082, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>