<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" statutenumber="57-501" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-501</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in sections 57-501 to 57-507, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Person means and includes any person, firm, or corporation;</para><para>(2) Owner means and includes (a) any person who holds a written bill of sale or other instrument under which title to the container was transferred to such person, (b) any person who holds a paid or receipted invoice showing purchase and payment of such container, (c) any person whose name, initials, mark, or other identifying device has been plainly and legibly stamped or otherwise shown upon the surface of such container for a period of not less than one year prior to the final enactment and approval of sections 57-501 to 57-507, or (d) any manufacturer of a container who has not sold or transferred ownership thereof by written bill of sale or otherwise;</para><para>(3) Liquefied petroleum gas means and includes any material which is composed predominantly of hydrocarbons or mixtures of the same, such as propane, propylene, butanes (normal butane and isobutane), and butylenes;</para><para>(4) Container means any vessel, including a cylinder or tank, used for storing of liquefied petroleum gas; and</para><para>(5) Cylinder means a container constructed in accordance with the United States Department of Transportation specifications in Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations as they existed on March 7, 2006.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 188, &#167; 1, p. 695; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 137, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>