<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-601</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in sections 57-601 to 57-607, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Eminent domain statutes shall mean sections 76-701 to 76-724;</para><para>(2) Underground reservoir shall mean any subsurface sand, stratum, or formation suitable for the injection and storage of natural gas or liquefied petroleum gas or both therein or which is capable of being made suitable for the storage of natural gas or liquefied petroleum gas, or both, by the construction of underground caverns by means of mining operations and the withdrawal of natural gas or liquefied gas therefrom;</para><para>(3) Underground storage shall mean the right to inject and store natural gas or liquefied petroleum gas or both within and to withdraw natural gas or liquefied petroleum gas from an underground reservoir;</para><para>(4) Natural gas shall mean gas which has been produced from the earth in its original state or such gas after the same has been processed or treated;</para><para>(5) Native gas shall mean gas which has not been previously withdrawn from the earth;</para><para>(6) Liquefied petroleum gas shall mean hydrocarbons or mixtures thereof which have been extracted from natural gas or crude oil and which consist primarily of propane or butane or mixtures thereof;</para><para>(7) Condemner shall mean any person, partnership, limited liability company, corporation, association, or municipal corporation authorized to transport or distribute natural gas as a public utility within this state for ultimate public use or consumption;</para><para>(8) Condemnee, property, and county judge shall have the same meaning as in the eminent domain statutes;</para><para>(9) Public owner shall mean (a) the state, (b) any agency or political subdivision thereof, (c) any municipal corporation, (d) any quasi-municipal corporation, or (e) any public authority which has an interest in any of the lands in and under which a condemner requires the right to underground storage;</para><para>(10) Commercially recoverable native gas shall mean that native gas which would provide revenue in excess of direct operating expenses if produced;</para><para>(11) Reasonable notice shall mean notice served in the same manner as is provided in the code of civil procedure for the service of process in civil actions in the district courts of this state; and</para><para>(12) Interested parties shall mean the owners of any oil or gas leasehold, mineral, or royalty interest in the underground stratum or formation sought to be acquired and the owners of the surface rights to the underground stratum or formation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 191, &#167; 1, p. 613; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 325, &#167; 1, p. 983; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 350. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 