<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-717"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-717</statuteno><catchline>Severance tax collection; Tax Commissioner; powers and duties; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall establish procedures to insure that all severance taxes which are due are paid in full and in a timely manner and shall undertake to insure that all oil and natural gas producing property classifications are current and correct.</para><para>(2) If the Tax Commissioner is not satisfied with the return or returns of the tax or the amount of tax required to be paid to the state by any person, he or she may compute and determine the amount required to be paid upon the basis of the facts contained in the return or returns or upon the basis of any information within his or her possession or which may come into his or her possession. One or more deficiency determinations of the amount due for one or more than one period may be made. To the amount of the deficiency determination for each period shall be added a penalty equal to ten percent thereof. In making a determination, the Tax Commissioner may offset overpayments for any period, together with interest on the overpayments, against underpayments for any period, against penalties, and against interest on the underpayments. The interest on underpayments and overpayments shall be computed in the manner set forth in this section.</para><para>(3) If any person fails to make a return the Tax Commissioner shall make an estimate of the amount of severance tax due. The estimate shall be made for the period or periods in respect to which the person failed to make a return and shall be based upon any information which is in the Tax Commissioner's possession or may come into his or her possession. Upon the basis of this estimate, the Tax Commissioner shall compute and determine the amount required to be paid to the state, adding to the sum thus arrived at a penalty equal to ten percent thereof. One or more determinations may be made for one or more than one period.</para><para>(4) The amount of the determination of any deficiency, exclusive of penalties, shall bear interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted, from the last day of the month following the period for which the amount should have been returned until the date of payment.</para><para>(5) If any part of a deficiency for which a deficiency determination is made is the result of fraud or an intent to evade Chapter 57, article 7, or authorized rules and regulations, a penalty of twenty-five percent of the amount of the determination shall be added thereto.</para><para>(6) Promptly after making his or her determination, the Tax Commissioner shall give to the person written notice of his or her determination.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 228, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1992, Fourth Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>