<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-903</statuteno><catchline>Oil and gas; terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in sections 57-901 to 57-921, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1)(a) Waste, as applied to oil, shall include underground waste, inefficient, excessive, or improper use, or dissipation of reservoir energy, including gas energy and water drive, surface waste, open pit storage, and waste incident to the production of oil in excess of the producer's aboveground storage facilities and lease and contractual requirements, but excluding storage, other than open pit storage, reasonably necessary for building up or maintaining crude stocks and products thereof for consumption, use, and sale; (b) waste, as applied to gas shall include (i) the escape, blowing, or releasing, directly or indirectly, into the open air of gas from wells productive of gas only, or gas from wells producing oil or both oil and gas and (ii) the production of gas in quantities or in such manner as will unreasonably reduce reservoir pressure or unreasonably diminish the quantity of oil or gas that might ultimately be produced, but excluding gas that is reasonably necessary in the drilling, completing, testing, and producing of wells and gas unavoidably produced with oil if it is not economically feasible for the producer to save or use such gas; and (c) waste shall also mean the abuse of the correlative rights of any owner in a pool due to nonuniform, disproportionate, unratable, or excessive withdrawals of oil or gas therefrom causing reasonably avoidable drainage between tracts of land or resulting in one or more owners in such pool producing more than his or her just and equitable share of the oil or gas from such pool;</para><para>(2) Commission shall mean the Nebraska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission;</para><para>(3) Person shall mean any natural person, corporation, association, partnership, limited liability company, receiver, trustee, executor, administrator, guardian, fiduciary, or other representative of any kind and any department, agency, or instrumentality of the state or of any governmental subdivision thereof;</para><para>(4) Oil shall mean crude petroleum oil and other hydrocarbons regardless of gravity which are produced at the wellhead in liquid form and the liquid hydrocarbons known as distillate or condensate recovered or extracted from gas other than gas produced in association with oil and commonly known as casing-head gas;</para><para>(5) Gas shall mean all natural gas and all other fluid hydrocarbons not defined as oil;</para><para>(6) Pool shall mean an underground reservoir containing a common accumulation of oil or gas or both, each zone of the structure which is completely separated from any other zone in the same structure is a pool as that term is used in sections 57-901 to 57-921;</para><para>(7) Field shall mean the general area underlaid by one or more pools;</para><para>(8) Owner shall mean the person who has the right to drill into and produce from a pool and to appropriate the oil or gas he or she produces therefrom either for himself or herself or for himself or herself and others;</para><para>(9) Producer shall mean the owner of a well or wells capable of producing oil or gas or both or any person who owns and operates a lease, or a unit of producing leases in which other persons own interests, with respect to such well or wells;</para><para>(10) Correlative rights shall mean the opportunity afforded to the owner of each property in a pool to produce, so far as it is reasonably practicable to do so without waste, his or her just and equitable share of the oil or gas, or both, in the pool; and</para><para>(11) The word and shall include the word or, and the word or shall include the word and.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 262, &#167; 3, p. 901; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 228, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 224, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 353. </para></source><annotation><para>The definition of waste embraces abuse of a correlative right resulting in an owner in the pool producing more than his just and equitable share of the oil therefrom. Ohmart v. Dennis, 188 Neb. 260, 196 N.W.2d 181 (1972).</para><para>One form of waste is abuse of correlative rights of any owner in a pool of oil or gas whereby another owner avoidably drains more than a just and equitable share from the pool. Farmers Irr. Dist. v. Schumacher, 187 Neb. 825, 194 N.W.2d 788 (1972).</para><para>Cited in discussion in recovery allowed lessee who refused to participate in a precompulsory unitization agreement. Baumgartner v. Gulf Oil Co., 184 Neb. 384, 168 N.W.2d 510 (1969).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 