<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-917" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>57-917</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Commission; director; appointment; compensation; bond or insurance.</catchline><para>To enable the commission to carry out its duties and powers under the laws of this state with respect to conservation of oil and gas and to enforce sections 57-901 to 57-921 and the rules and regulations so prescribed, the commission shall employ one chief administrator who shall not be a member of the commission and who shall be known as the Director of the Nebraska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission, and as such he or she shall be charged with the duty of administering and enforcing the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921 and all rules, regulations, and orders promulgated by the commission, subject to the direction of the commission. The director shall be a qualified petroleum engineer with not less than three years' actual field experience in the drilling and operation of oil and gas wells. Such director shall hold office at the pleasure of the commission and receive a salary to be fixed by the commission. The director, with the concurrence of the commission, shall have the authority, and it shall be his or her duty, to employ assistants and other employees necessary to carry out the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921. The director shall be ex officio secretary of the Nebraska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission and shall keep all minutes and records of the commission. The director shall, as secretary, be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201. The premium shall be paid by the State of Nebraska. The director and other employees of the commission performing duties authorized by sections 57-901 to 57-921 shall be paid their necessary traveling and living expenses when traveling on official business at such rates and within such limits as may be fixed by the commission, subject to existing laws.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 262, &#167; 17, p. 914; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1082, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>