<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" statutenumber="57-517"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-517</statuteno><catchline>Liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system; container warning label; affixed by provider; limitation on liability.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds it is necessary that a leak check be performed following an interruption of service of a liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system to ensure safe and proper operation. Further, the Legislature finds that a leak check must be performed by a qualified service technician.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature to create a mechanism that will educate users of liquefied petroleum gas of the requirements for a leak check when an interruption of service occurs. </para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Interruption of service means the gas supply to a liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system is turned off;</para><para>(b) Leak check means an operation performed on a complete liquefied petroleum gas piping system and the connection equipment to verify that the liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system does not leak;</para><para>(c) Liquefied petroleum gas provider means any person or entity engaged in the business of supplying, handling, transporting, or selling at retail liquefied petroleum gas in this state; and</para><para>(d) Liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system means an installation with a maximum operating pressure of one hundred twenty-five pounds per square inch or less and includes, but is not limited to, the container assembly, pressure regulator or regulators, piping system, gas utilization equipment and components thereof, and venting system in residential, commercial, or institutional installations. Liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system does not include:</para><para>(i) Portable liquefied petroleum gas appliances and equipment of all types that are not connected to a fixed-fuel piping system;</para><para>(ii) Farm appliances and equipment in liquid service, including, but not limited to, brooders, dehydrators, dryers, and irrigation equipment;</para><para>(iii) Liquefied petroleum gas equipment for vaporization, gas mixing, and gas manufacturing;</para><para>(iv) Liquefied petroleum gas piping for buildings under construction or renovations that is not to become part of the permanent building piping system, such as temporary fixed piping for building heat; or</para><para>(v) Fuel gas system engines, including, but not limited to, tractors, mowers, trucks, and recreational vehicles.</para><para>(4) The liquefied petroleum gas provider shall affix a container warning label on each tank supplying liquefied petroleum gas to a liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system. The container warning label shall be affixed near the tank shutoff. </para><para>(5) The container warning label required by subsection (4) of this section shall include this warning:</para><para>WARNING: Do Not Open Container Shutoff Valve! If this valve is turned off for any reason, the National Fuel Gas Code (NFPA 54) requires a leak check of the system serviced by the container at the time the valve is turned back on. The leak check must be conducted by a qualified service technician. Do Not Attempt To Open The Valve Yourself! Failure to follow this warning may result in the ignition of leaking gas, causing serious and potentially fatal injury, fire, or explosion.</para><para>The container warning label shall include the statutory reference to this section.</para><para>(6) If the container warning label is affixed near the tank shutoff as required by subsection (4) of this section and the liquefied petroleum gas vapor service system is turned on prior to a leak check by a qualified service technician approved by the liquefied petroleum gas provider, the liquefied petroleum gas provider shall not be liable for any damage, injury, or death if the proximate cause of the damage, injury, or death was the negligence of a person or persons other than the liquefied petroleum gas provider.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB274, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>