<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-813"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-813</statuteno><catchline>Filing of bond; procedure; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any lien or liens shall be fixed or attempted to be fixed under the provisions of sections 57-801 to 57-820 then the owner or owners of the property on which the lien or liens are claimed or the contractor or subcontractor through whom such lien or liens are claimed, or either of them, may file a bond with the county clerk of the county in which the property is located. Such bond shall describe the property on which the lien or liens are claimed, shall refer to the lien or liens claimed in manner sufficient to identify them and shall be in double the amount of the claimed lien or liens referred to and shall be payable to the party or parties claiming same. Such bond shall be executed by the party filing the same as principal and by a corporate surety authorized to execute such bonds as surety in the State of Nebraska. It shall be conditioned substantially that the principal and surety will pay to the obligees named or their assigns the amounts of the liens so claimed by them with all costs in the event same shall be proven to be liens on such property.</para><para>(2) Upon the filing of such bond, the county clerk shall send a notice thereof, to all obligees named therein, by registered or certified mail addressed to such obligees at the address set forth in their respective claims for lien.</para><para>(3) Such bond, when filed, and such notice, when mailed, shall be recorded by the county clerk in the Oil and Gas Lien Record, and any purchaser or lender may rely upon the record of such bond and notice in acquiring any interest in said property and shall be protected absolutely thereby.</para><para>(4) Such bond, when filed, shall take the place of the property against which any claim for lien referred to in such bond is asserted. At any time within the period of time provided in section 57-814, any person claiming such lien may sue upon such bond but no action shall be brought upon such bond after the expiration of such period. One action upon the bond shall not exhaust the remedies thereon but each obligee or assignee of an obligee named therein may maintain a separate suit thereon in any court having jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 241, &#167; 13, p. 813. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 