<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-801"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-801</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in sections 57-801 to 57-820, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Person shall mean an individual, corporation, firm, partnership, limited liability company, or association;</para><para>(2) Owner shall mean a person or persons holding any interest, legal or equitable, in a leasehold interest held for oil or gas purposes or any pipeline, or his or her agent, and shall include purchasers under executory contract, receivers, trustees, guardians, executors, and administrators;</para><para>(3) Contract shall mean a contract, written or oral, express or implied, or partly express and partly implied, or executory or executed, or partly executory and partly executed;</para><para>(4) Material shall mean material, water, machinery, equipment, appliances, buildings, structures, tools, bits, or supplies but does not include rigs or hoists or their integral component parts except wire lines;</para><para>(5) Labor shall mean work performed in return for wages;</para><para>(6) Services shall mean work performed exclusive of labor, including the hauling of material, whether or not involving the furnishing of materials;</para><para>(7) Furnish shall mean sell or rent;</para><para>(8) Drilling shall mean drilling, digging, torpedoing, acidizing, cementing, completing, or repairing;</para><para>(9) Operating shall mean all operations in connection with or necessary to the production of oil or gas;</para><para>(10) Construction or constructing shall mean construction, maintenance, fabrication, or repair;</para><para>(11) Pipeline shall mean any pipeline laid and designed as a means of transporting natural gas, oil, or gasoline, or their components or derivatives, and the right-of-way therefor; and</para><para>(12) Original contractor shall mean any person for whose benefit a lien is prescribed by section 57-802.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 241, &#167; 1, p. 807; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 352. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 