<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" statutenumber="57-904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-904</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission; members; qualifications; appointment; term; quorum; vacancy; compensation.</catchline><para>There is hereby established the Nebraska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission. The commission shall consist of three members to be appointed by the Governor. The director of the state geological survey shall serve the commission in the capacity as its technical advisor, but with no power to vote. Any two commissioners shall constitute a quorum for all purposes. At least one member of the commission shall have had experience in the production of oil or gas and shall have resided in the State of Nebraska for at least one year. Each of the other members of the commission shall have resided in the State of Nebraska for at least three years. Initially, two of said members shall be appointed for a term of two years each; and one shall be appointed for a term of four years. At the expiration of the initial terms all members thereafter appointed shall serve for a term of four years. The Governor may at any time remove any appointed member of the commission for cause, and by appointment, with the approval of the Legislature, shall fill any vacancy on the commission. The members of the commission shall receive as compensation for their services the sum of fifty dollars per day for each day actually devoted to the business of the commission; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that they shall not receive a sum in any one year in excess of two thousand dollars each. In addition, each member of the commission shall be reimbursed for his or her actual and necessary traveling and other expenses incurred in connection with the carrying out of his or her duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 for state employees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 262, &#167; 4, p. 902; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 90, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 99. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 