<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-916.01" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>57-916.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Violations; civil penalty; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to the penalties prescribed in section 57-915, any person who violates any provision of sections 57-901 to 57-921, any rule, regulation, or order of the commission, or any term, condition, or limitation of any permit issued pursuant to such sections, rule, regulation, or order may be subject to a civil penalty imposed by the commission of not to exceed one thousand dollars. No civil penalty shall be imposed until written notice is sent pursuant to subsection (2) of this section and a period of ten days has elapsed in which the person may come into compliance if possible. If any violation is a continuing one, each day a violation continues after such ten-day period shall constitute a separate violation for the purpose of computing the applicable civil penalty. The commission may compromise, mitigate, or remit such penalties.</para><para>(2) Whenever the commission intends to impose a civil penalty under this section, the commission shall notify the person in writing (a) setting forth the date, facts, and nature of each violation with which the person is charged, (b) specifically identifying the particular provision or provisions of the section, rule, regulation, order, or permit involved in the violation, and (c) specifying the amount of each penalty which the commission intends to impose. Such written notice shall be sent by registered or certified mail to the last-known address of such person. The notice shall also advise such person of his or her right to a hearing and that failure to pay any civil penalty subsequently imposed by the commission will result in a civil action by the commission to collect such penalty. The person so notified may, within thirty days of receipt of such notice, submit a written request for a hearing to review any penalty to be imposed by the commission. A hearing shall be held in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act, and any person upon whom a civil penalty is subsequently imposed may appeal such penalty pursuant to such act. On the request of the commission, the Attorney General or county attorney may institute a civil action to collect a penalty imposed pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 922, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1082, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>