<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" statutenumber="57-920" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-920</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Sections; jurisdiction.</catchline><para>The State of Nebraska being a sovereign state and not disposed to jeopardize or surrender any of its sovereign rights, sections 57-901 to 57-921 shall apply to all lands in the State of Nebraska lawfully subject to its police powers, except it shall apply to lands of the United States or to lands subject to the jurisdiction of the United States only to the extent that control and supervision of conservation of oil and gas by the United States on its lands shall fail to effect the intent and purposes of sections 57-901 to 57-921 and otherwise shall apply to such lands to such extent as an officer of the United States having jurisdiction, or his or her duly authorized representative, shall approve any of the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921 or the order or orders of the commission which affects such lands, and the same shall apply to any lands committed to a unit agreement approved by the Secretary of the Interior of the United States, or his or her duly authorized representative, except that the commission may, under such unit agreements, suspend the application of the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921 or any part of sections 57-901 to 57-921 so long as the conservation of oil and gas and the prevention of waste, as provided in sections 57-901 to 57-921, is accomplished thereby but such suspension shall not relieve any operator from making such reports as are necessary or advised to be fully informed as to operations under such agreement and as the commission may require under the provisions of sections 57-901 to 57-921.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 262, &#167; 20, p. 917; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1082, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>The commission is authorized to suspend the operation of the conservation act in certain situations subject to the requirement that conservation and prevention of waste be accomplished. Ohmart v. Dennis, 188 Neb. 260, 196 N.W.2d 181 (1972).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>