<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id336">
<sectno id="id337">Sec. 33.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" id="id338" statutenumber="57-919"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id340">57-919</statuteno><catchline id="id341">Oil and Gas
Conservation Fund; investment; charges; exemptions; payment; report of producer;
filing; interest; lien; penalties.</catchline><para>(1) All money
collected by the Tax Commissioner or the commission or as civil penalties
under sections 57-901 to 57-921 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for
credit to a special fund to be known as the Oil and Gas Conservation Fund.
Expenses incident to the administration of such sections shall be paid out
of the fund. Transfers may
be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any
money in the Oil and Gas Conservation Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
<para>(2) There is hereby levied and assessed on the value at the
well of all oil and gas produced, saved, and sold or transported from the
premises in Nebraska where produced a charge not to exceed fifteen mills on
the dollar. The commission shall by order fix the amount of such charge in
the first instance and may, from time to time, reduce or increase the amount
thereof as in its judgment the expenses chargeable against the Oil and Gas
Conservation Fund may require, except that the amounts fixed by the commission
shall not exceed the limit prescribed in this section. It shall be the duty
of the Tax Commissioner to make collection of such assessments. The persons
owning an interest, a working interest, a royalty interest, payments out of
production, or any other interest in the oil and gas, or in the proceeds thereof,
subject to the charge provided for in this section shall be liable to the
producer for such charge in proportion to their ownership at the time of production.
The producer shall, on or before the last day of the month next succeeding
the month in which the charge was assessed, file a report or return in such
form as prescribed by the commission and Tax Commissioner together with all
charges due. In the event of a sale of oil or gas within this state, the first
purchaser shall file this report or return together with any charges then
due. If the final filing date falls on a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday,
the next secular or business day shall be the final filing date. Such reports
or returns shall be considered filed on time if postmarked before midnight
of the final filing date. Any such charge not paid within the time herein
specified shall bear interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.02,
as such rate may from time to time be adjusted, from the date of delinquency
until paid, and such charge together with the interest shall be a lien as
provided in section 57-702. The Tax Commissioner shall charge and collect
a penalty for the delinquency in the amount of one percent of the charge for
each month or part of the month that the charge has remained delinquent, but
in no event shall the penalty be more than twenty-five percent of the charge.
The Tax Commissioner may waive all or part of the penalty provided in this
section but shall not waive the interest. The person remitting the charge
as provided in this section is hereby authorized, empowered, and required
to deduct from any amounts due the persons owning an interest in the oil and
gas or in the proceeds thereof at the time of production the proportionate
amount of such charge before making payment to such persons. This subsection
shall apply to all lands in the State of Nebraska, anything in section 57-920
to the contrary notwithstanding, except that there shall be exempted from
the charge levied and assessed in this section the following: (a) The interest
of the United States of America and the interest of the State of Nebraska
and the political subdivisions thereof in any oil or gas or in the proceeds
thereof; (b) the interest of any Indian or Indian tribe in any oil or gas
or in the proceeds thereof produced from land subject to the supervision of
the United States; and (c) oil and gas used in producing operations or for
repressuring or recycling purposes. All money so collected shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Oil and Gas Conservation Fund and
shall be used exclusively to pay the costs and expenses incurred in connection
with the administration and enforcement of sections 57-901 to 57-921.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 262, &#167; 19, p. 915; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 56, p. 2380; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 527, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 804, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 709, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 224, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 198; </para><para>Laws 1992, Fourth Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 407, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 97, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 33.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>