<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" id="id24" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="57-1402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>57-1402 </statuteno><catchline>Purposes of act.</catchline>
<para>(1) The purposes of the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act are
to:</para>
<para>(a) Ensure the welfare of Nebraskans, including protection
of property rights, aesthetic values, and economic interests;</para>
<para>(b) Consider the lawful protection of Nebraska's natural resources
in determining the location of routes of major oil pipelines within Nebraska;</para>
<para>(c) Ensure that a major oil pipeline is not constructed within
Nebraska without receiving the approval of the commission under section 57-1408;</para>
<para>(d) Ensure that the location of routes for major oil pipelines
is in compliance with Nebraska law; and</para>
<para>(e) Ensure that a coordinated and efficient method for the
authorization of such construction is provided.</para>
<para>(2) Nothing in the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act shall be
construed to regulate any safety issue with respect to any aspect of any interstate
oil pipeline. The Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act is intended to deal solely
with the issue of siting or choosing the location of the route aside and apart
from safety considerations. The Legislature acknowledges and respects the
exclusive federal authority over safety issues established by the federal
law, the Pipeline Safety Act of 1994, 49 U.S.C. 60101 et seq., and the express
preemption provision stated in that act. The Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act
is intended to exercise only the remaining sovereign powers and purposes of
Nebraska which are not included in the category of safety regulation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB1, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1161, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>