<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" id="id6" statutenumber="57-1101"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>57-1101</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Acquisition of
property by eminent domain; authorized; procedure.</catchline><para>Any
person engaged in, and any company, corporation, or association formed or
created for the purpose of, transporting or conveying crude oil, petroleum,
gases, or other products thereof in interstate commerce through or across
the State of Nebraska or intrastate within the State of Nebraska, and desiring
or requiring a right-of-way or other interest in real estate and being unable
to agree with the owner or lessee of any land, lot, right-of-way, or other
property for the amount of compensation for the use and occupancy of so much
of any lot, land, real estate, right-of-way, or other property as may be reasonably
necessary for the laying, relaying, operation, and maintenance of any such
pipeline or the location of any plant or equipment necessary to operate such
pipeline, shall have the right to acquire the same for such purpose through
the exercise of the power of eminent domain, except that for any major oil
pipeline as defined in section 57-1404 to
be placed in operation in the State of Nebraska after November 23, 2011, any such person, company,
corporation, or association shall comply
with section 57-1503 and receive the approval of the Governor for the route
of the pipeline under such section or shall apply for and receive
an order approving the application under the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act, prior to having the rights
provided under this section. If
condemnation procedures have not been commenced within two years after the
date the Governor's approval is granted or after the date of receipt of an
order approving an application under the Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act, the
right under this section expires. The procedure to condemn property
shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 323, &#167; 1, p. 979; </para><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB1, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1161, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act,</emphasis> see section 57-1401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>