<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id56">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, And Gas" id="id58"  statutenumber="57-1406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>57-1406</statuteno><catchline>Commission; assess expenses; payment;
neglect or refusal to pay; failure to file objection; notice of delinquency;
collection.</catchline><para>(1)
The commission shall assess the expenses reasonably attributable to investigation
and hearing regarding an application filed under section 57-1405, including
expenses billed by agencies filing reports as required in subsection (3) of
section 57-1407 and both direct and indirect expenses incurred by the commission
or its staff or consultants, to the applicant as agreed under section 57-1405.</para>
<para>(2) The commission
shall ascertain the expenses of any such investigation and hearing and by
order assess such expenses against the applicant and shall render a bill therefor,
by United States mail, to the applicant, either at the time the order under
section 57-1408 is issued or from time to time during such application process.
Such bill shall constitute notice of such assessment and demand of payment
thereof. Upon a bill rendered to such applicant, within fifteen days after
the mailing thereof, such applicant shall pay to the commission the amount
of the assessment for which it is billed. The commission shall remit the payment
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Public Service Commission Pipeline
Regulation Fund. The commission may render bills in one fiscal year for costs
incurred within a previous fiscal year. The commission shall direct the State
Treasurer to credit any reimbursement of expenses billed by agencies pursuant
to subsection (3) of section 57-1407 to the appropriate fund of the appropriate
agency.</para><para>(3) If any applicant against which an assessment has been made pursuant
to this section, within fifteen days after the notice of such assessment,
(a) neglects or refuses to pay the same or (b) fails to file objections to
the assessment with the commission as provided in subsection (4) of this section,
the commission shall transmit to the State Treasurer a certified copy of the
notice of assessment, together with notice of neglect or refusal to pay the
assessment, and on the same day the commission shall mail by registered mail
to the applicant against which the assessment has been made a copy of the
notice which it has transmitted to the State Treasurer. If any such applicant
fails to pay such assessment to the State Treasurer within ten days after
receipt of such notice and certified copy of such assessment, the assessment
shall bear interest at the rate of fifteen percent per annum from and after
the date on which the copy of the notice was mailed by registered mail to
such applicant.</para><para>(4) Within fifteen days after the date of the mailing of any notice
of assessment under subsection (2) of this section, the applicant against
which such assessment has been made may file with the commission objections
setting out in detail the ground upon which the applicant regards such assessment
to be excessive, erroneous, unlawful, or invalid. The commission shall determine
if the assessment or any part of the assessment is excessive, erroneous, unlawful,
or invalid and shall render an order upholding, invalidating, or amending
the assessment. An amended assessment shall have in all respects the same
force and effect as though it were an original assessment.</para>
<para>(5) If any
assessment against which objections have been filed is not paid within ten
days after service of an order finding that such objections have been overruled
and disallowed by the commission, the commission shall give notice of such
delinquency to the State Treasurer and to the applicant in the manner provided
for in subsection (3) of this section. The State Treasurer shall then collect
the amount of such assessment. If an amended assessment is not paid within
ten days after service of the order of the commission, the commission shall
notify the State Treasurer and the applicant as in the case of delinquency
in the payment of an original assessment. The State Treasurer shall then collect
the amount of such assessment as provided in the case of an original assessment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB1, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>