<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" id="id21" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="57-1503"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo>
<statuteno>57-1503</statuteno><catchline>Supplemental environmental impact
statement; department; powers and duties; funding; submit to Governor; duty.</catchline>
<para>(1) The department
may collaborate with a federal agency or agencies in a review under the National
Environmental Policy Act involving a supplemental environmental impact statement
for oil pipeline projects within, through, or across the state. Prior to entering
into such shared jurisdiction and authority with a federal agency or agencies,
the department shall enter into a memorandum of understanding with such federal
agency or agencies that sets forth the responsibilities and schedules that
will lead to an effective and timely review under the National Environmental
Policy Act involving a supplemental environmental impact statement.</para>
<para>(2) Since the
objectives of the process are to ensure adequate information gathering, full
and careful agency and public review, objective preparation of a supplemental
environmental impact statement, adherence to a defined schedule, and an appropriate
role for a pipeline carrier which avoids the appearance of conflicts of interest,
it is the intent of the Legislature that the state fully fund the process
of preparation of a supplemental environmental impact statement and that no
fees will be required of an applicant. The department may contract with outside
vendors in the process of preparation of a supplemental environmental impact
statement. The department shall make every reasonable effort to ensure that
each vendor has no conflict of interest or relationship to any pipeline carrier
that applies for an oil pipeline permit.</para><para>(3) In order for the process to be efficient
and expeditious, the department's contracts with vendors pursuant to this
section for a supplemental environmental impact statement shall not be subject
to the Nebraska Consultants' Competitive Negotiation Act or sections 73-301
to 73-306 or 73-501 to 73-509.</para><para>(4) After the supplemental environmental
impact statement is prepared, the department shall submit it to the Governor.
Within thirty days after receipt of the supplemental environmental impact
statement from the department, the Governor shall indicate, in writing, to
the federal agency or agencies involved in the review as to whether he or
she approves any of the routes reviewed in the supplemental environmental
impact statement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB4, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>November 23, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Major Oil Pipeline Siting Act,</emphasis> see section 57-1401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Consultants' Competitive Negotiation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1702.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>