<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" statutenumber="57-1619"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>57-1619</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of project completion; notice; hearing; consultation; issuance; conditions; effect.</catchline><para>(1) After carbon dioxide injections into a reservoir end and upon application by the storage operator, the commission shall consider issuing a certificate of project completion.</para><para>(2) The certificate may only be issued after public notice and hearing. The commission shall establish notice requirements for such hearing.</para><para>(3) The certificate may only be issued after the commission has consulted with the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment and the Underground Injection Control program permitting authority.</para><para>(4) The certificate may only be issued if the storage operator:</para><para>(a) Is in full compliance with all laws governing the storage facility;</para><para>(b) Shows that it has addressed all pending claims regarding the storage facility's operation;</para><para>(c) Shows that it has received an authorization of site closure from the applicable underground injection control program permitting authority for each storage facility injection well; and</para><para>(d) Shows that any wells, equipment, and facilities to be used in the post-closure period are in good condition and retain mechanical integrity.</para><para>(5) Once a certificate is issued:</para><para>(a) Title to the storage facility and to the stored carbon dioxide transfers, without payment of any compensation, to the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(b) Title acquired by the state includes all rights and interests in, and all responsibilities associated with, the stored carbon dioxide;</para><para>(c) The storage operator and all persons who generated any injected carbon dioxide streams are released from all regulatory requirements associated with the storage facility;</para><para>(d) Any financial assurance provided by the storage operator shall be released; and</para><para>(e) Monitoring and managing the storage facility is the state's responsibility to be overseen by the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB650, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 320. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>