<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id83">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Minerals, Oil, and Gas" id="id85" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="57-1408"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>57-1408</statuteno><catchline>Commission order; findings; extension
of time; status reports; notice of completion; denial of application; amended
application; commission; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Within seven months after the receipt of the application
under section 57-1405, the commission shall enter an order approving the application
or denying the application. The commission shall include in the order the
findings of the commission regarding the application and the reasons for approving
or denying the application. The order approving the application shall state
that the application is in the public interest and shall authorize the pipeline
carrier to act under section 57-1101.</para>
<para>(2) The commission
may, for just cause, extend the time for the entry of an order under subsection
(1) of this section. The extension shall not exceed twelve months after the
receipt of the application under section 57-1405 unless all parties agree
to a longer extension, except that no extension shall extend more than eight
months after the issuance of a presidential permit authorizing the construction
of the major oil pipeline.</para><para>(3) If the commission approves the application,
the pipeline carrier shall file a status report with the commission regarding
the construction of the major oil pipeline every six months until the completion
of the major oil pipeline within Nebraska. The pipeline carrier shall notify
the commission of the completion of the major oil pipeline within Nebraska
within thirty days after such completion.</para><para>(4) If the commission denies the application,
the pipeline carrier may amend the denied application in accordance with the
findings of the commission and submit the amended application within sixty
days after the issuance of the order denying the application. Within sixty
days after the receipt of the amended application, the commission shall enter
an order approving or denying the amended application after making new findings
under subsection (4) of section 57-1407.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB1, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>