<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id41"><amendatorysection
amended="yes" chaptername="Libraries And Museums" id="id43" statutenumber="51-201.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id45">51-201.03</statuteno><catchline
id="id46">County library; petition to establish; procedure; election.</catchline><para>(1)
The registered voters of the incorporated and unincorporated areas of a county
which do not have a public library may file an initiative petition with the
county board requesting the establishment of a county library. The petition
shall be filed by July 31 prior to a statewide general election. Signatures
gathered before the last statewide general election shall not be counted.
An initiative petition shall conform to the requirements of section 32-628.
Petition signers and petition circulators shall conform to the requirements
of sections 32-629 and 32-630. The county board shall submit the petitions
to the election commissioner or county clerk for signature verification pursuant
to section 32-631. The required number of signatures shall be five percent
of the voters registered at the last statewide general election in the incorporated
and unincorporated areas of the county which do not have a public library.
The election commissioner or county clerk shall notify the county board within
thirty days after receiving the petitions from the county board whether the
required number of signatures has been gathered.</para><para>(2) If the county
board determines that the petitions are in proper form and signed by the necessary
number of registered voters, the county board shall notify the governing body
and library board of each incorporated area within the county within ten days
after such determination and shall publish in a newspaper of general circulation
in the county that the registered voters of the unincorporated area of the
county and of the incorporated areas which do not have a public library will
be asked to vote on the issue at the next statewide general election and shall
submit the question of whether to establish a county library to the voters
as required in section 51-201.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1997, LB 250, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB269, &#167; 12.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
