<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Libraries And Museums" statutenumber="51-403"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>51-403</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Library Commission; powers and duties; director; appointment; salary.</catchline><para>The powers and duties of the Nebraska Library Commission shall be (1) to make rules and regulations not inconsistent with law for its government and operations, (2) to appoint a director, at a salary to be fixed by the commission, who shall be a technically trained, qualified, and experienced librarian, a graduate of an American Library Association accredited library school, to administer the work of the commission as hereinafter specified, (3) to authorize the director to employ such assistance as may be necessary to properly carry out the requirements of sections 51-401 to 51-410, (4) to be responsible for the statewide promotion, development, and coordination of library programs and services in accordance with nationally acceptable library standards, (5) to receive, as the legally designated state governmental agency, federal library funds which by federal law are to be dispersed within the state by a prescribed formula, (6) to accept and administer any gifts, bequests, and legacies which, in the opinion of the director and the commission, may be of value to it, and (7) to make a biennial report for the past two fiscal years to the Governor of its activities and the progress of its work on or before December 15 in each even-numbered year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 115, &#167; 3, p. 370; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 124, &#167; 1, p. 435; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 51-503; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 51-403; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 238, &#167; 21, p. 713; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 311, &#167; 3, p. 1066; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 171, &#167; 1, p. 659; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 178, &#167; 1, p. 562; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 231, &#167; 10, p. 721; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 256, &#167; 1, p. 750; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 315, &#167; 1, p. 878; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1033, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 369, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 