<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Libraries And Museums" statutenumber="51-805"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>51-805</statuteno><catchline>Public library federation board; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The public library federation board shall be responsible for the general governance of the public library federation, but affiliated libraries shall retain governance of all aspects of local library operations. The board shall make and adopt bylaws, rules, and regulations for the board's guidance and for the governance of the federation. The board shall develop a long-range public library service plan for the provision of public library service to the area included in the federation.</para><para>(2) The board may designate and determine the compensation of a library federation director. The director shall be responsible to the board only in relationship to federation operations.</para><para>(3) The board shall develop and present an annual budget in support of the annual public library plan to each participating county board. The public library federation board shall administer and authorize the expenditure of all money received from taxes and other sources in support of federation public library service.</para><para>(4) The board may contract with other public entities for services.</para><para>(5) The method of federating libraries provided in sections 51-801 to 51-811 shall not be the exclusive way to provide joint or cooperative library services. Nothing in sections 51-801 to 51-811 shall prohibit a county, city, village, or township from entering into an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act concerning library services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 362, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 