<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Libraries and Museums" statutenumber="51-211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>51-211</statuteno><catchline>Library board; general powers and duties; discrimination prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) The library board shall have the power to erect, lease, or occupy an appropriate building for the use of such library and to appoint a suitable librarian and assistants, to fix their compensation, and to remove such appointees at pleasure. It shall have the power to establish rules and regulations for the government of such library as may be deemed necessary for its preservation and to maintain its usefulness and efficiency. It shall have the power to fix and impose, by general rules, penalties and forfeitures for trespasses upon or injury to the library grounds, rooms, books, or other property, for failure to return any book, or for violation of any bylaw, rule, or regulation and to fix and impose reasonable fees, not to exceed the library's actual cost, for nonbasic services. The board shall have and exercise such power as may be necessary to carry out the spirit and intent of sections 51-201 to 51-219 in establishing and maintaining a public library and reading room.</para><para>(2) The public library shall make its basic services available without charge to all residents of the political subdivision which supplies its tax support.</para><para>(3) No service shall be denied to any person because of race, sex, religion, age, color, national origin, ancestry, physical handicap, or marital status.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 73, &#167; 6, p. 316; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3797; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 86, &#167; 1, p. 223; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3190; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 51-206; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 51-211; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1236, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 250, &#167; 22. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 