<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Libraries and Museums" statutenumber="51-211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>51-211</statuteno><catchline>Library board; general powers and
duties; governing body; duty; discrimination
prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) The library board may erect, lease, or occupy an appropriate building
for the use of a library, appoint a suitable librarian and assistants, fix the compensation of such appointees, and remove such appointees
at the pleasure of the board. The governing body of the county, city,
or village in which the library is located shall approve any personnel administrative
or compensation policy or procedure before implementation of such policy or
procedure by the library board.</para>
<para>(2) The library board may establish
rules and regulations for the government of such library as may be deemed
necessary for its preservation and to maintain its usefulness and efficiency. The library board may fix
and impose, by general rules, penalties and forfeitures for trespasses upon
or injury to the library grounds, rooms, books, or other property, for failure
to return any book, or for violation of any bylaw, rule, or regulation and fix and impose reasonable
fees, not to exceed the library's actual cost, for nonbasic services. The
board shall have and exercise such power as may be necessary to carry out
the spirit and intent of sections 51-201 to 51-219 in establishing and maintaining
a public library and reading room.</para>
<para>(3) The public library shall
make its basic services available without charge to all residents of the political
subdivision which supplies its tax support.</para>
<para>(4) No service shall be denied
to any person because of race, sex, religion, age, color, national origin,
ancestry, physical handicap, or marital status.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 73, &#167; 6, p. 316; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3797; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 86, &#167; 1, p. 223; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3190; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 51-206; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 51-211; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1236, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 250, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB470, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>