  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Libraries And Museums" statutenumber="51-216"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>51-216</statuteno><catchline>Real estate; sale and conveyance; conditions; remonstrance; procedure.</catchline><para>The library board may, by resolution, direct the sale and conveyance of any real estate owned by the library board or by the public library, which is not used for library purposes, or of any real estate so donated or devised to the library board or to the public library upon such terms as the library board may deem best. Before any such sale is made the library board shall advertise such sale once each week for three consecutive weeks in a legal newspaper published or, if none is published, of general circulation in the city, village, township, or county in which the public library is situated, and such notice shall set out the time, place, terms, manner of sale, legal description of such real estate, and the right to reject any and all bids. If such bid or bids have not been rejected, then the real estate shall be sold to the highest bidder for cash, and the chairperson of the library board, upon resolution of the library board directing him or her so to do, shall convey such real estate to the purchaser of such real estate upon his or her payment of his or her bid. If within thirty days after the third publication of such notice a remonstrance against such sale is signed by thirty percent of the registered voters of such city, village, township, or county voting at the last regular city, village, or county election and is filed with the governing body of such city, village, township, or county, such property shall not then, nor within one year thereafter, be sold. If the date for filing the remonstrance falls upon a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday, the signatures shall be collected within the thirty-day period, but the filing shall be considered timely if filed or postmarked on or before the next business day.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 434; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 103, &#167; 2, p. 422; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 51-210; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 51-216; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 59, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 