<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Libraries And Museums" statutenumber="51-703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>51-703</statuteno><catchline>Notice; contents.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to any other information prescribed for a particular notice, each notice given to the lender or claimant pursuant to the Museum Property Act shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) The lender's or claimant's name as appropriate;</para><para>(b) The lender's last-known address or the claimant's last-known address as appropriate;</para><para>(c) A brief description of the property on loan;</para><para>(d) The date of the loan, if known;</para><para>(e) The name of the museum; and</para><para>(f) The name, address, and telephone number of the appropriate person or office to be contacted regarding the property.</para><para>(2) Each notice given by a museum pursuant to the act shall be mailed to the lender's and any claimant's last-known address by restricted certified mail. Notice is deemed given if the museum receives proof of receipt within thirty days after mailing the notice.</para><para>(3) Notice may be given by publication if the museum does not:</para><para>(a) Know the identity of the lender;</para><para>(b) Have the address or telephone number for the lender or the address or telephone number for the claimant; or</para><para>(c) Receive proof of receipt of the notice by the person to whom the notice was sent within thirty days after the notice was mailed.</para><para>(4) Notice by publication must be given by posting online on the museum's website for a minimum of three consecutive weeks and by publication of a statement for one week in a newspaper of general circulation in both the county where the museum is located and the county of the lender's or claimant's address, if any. The statement published in the newspaper must contain (a) the museum's name and contact information, (b) notification that the museum is acting to assert title, and (c) notification that interested parties should contact the museum for a complete listing of property to which the museum is asserting title.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1276, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB926, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>