<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id57">
<sectno id="id58" opdate="January 1, 2010">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Rules of Evidence" id="id59" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="27-415"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>27-415</statuteno><catchline>Civil case; evidence of crimes in
sexual assault cases.</catchline><para>(1) In a civil case in which a claim for damages or other
relief is predicated on a party's alleged commission of conduct constituting
an offense of sexual assault, evidence of that party's commission of another
offense or offenses of sexual assault is admissible if there is clear and
convincing evidence otherwise admissible under the Nebraska Evidence Rules
that the party committed the other offense or offenses. If admissible, such
evidence may be considered for its bearing on any matter to which it is relevant.</para>
<para>(2) A party
who intends to offer evidence under this section shall disclose the evidence
to the party against whom it will be offered, including statements of witnesses
or a summary of the substance of any testimony that is expected to be offered,
at least fifteen days before the scheduled date of trial or at such later
time as the court may allow for good cause.</para><para>(3) Before admitting evidence of a party's
commission of another offense or offenses of sexual assault under this section,
the court shall conduct a hearing outside the presence of any jury. At the
hearing, the rules of evidence shall apply and the court shall apply a section
27-403 balancing and admit the evidence unless the risk of prejudice substantially
outweighs the probative value of the evidence. In assessing the balancing,
the court may consider any relevant factor such as (a) the probability that
the other offense occurred, (b) the proximity in time and intervening circumstances
of the other offenses, and (c) the similarity of the other acts to the crime
charged.</para>
<para>(4) This
section shall not be construed to limit the admission or consideration of
evidence under any other section of the Nebraska Evidence Rules.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>