<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id50">
<sectno id="id51" opdate="January 1, 2010">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Rules Of Evidence" id="id52" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="27-414"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>27-414</statuteno><catchline>Criminal use; evidence of similar
crimes in sexual assault cases.</catchline><para>(1) In a criminal case in which the accused is accused of
an offense of sexual assault, evidence of the accused's commission of another
offense or offenses of sexual assault is admissible if there is clear and
convincing evidence otherwise admissible under the Nebraska Evidence Rules
that the accused committed the other offense or offenses. If admissible, such
evidence may be considered for its bearing on any matter to which it is relevant.</para>
<para>(2) In a
case in which the prosecution intends to offer evidence under this section,
the prosecuting attorney shall disclose the evidence to the accused, including
statements of witnesses or a summary of the substance of any testimony that
is expected to be offered, at least fifteen days before the scheduled date
of trial or at such later time as the court may allow for good cause.</para>
<para>(3) Before admitting
evidence of the accused's commission of another offense or offenses of sexual
assault under this section, the court shall conduct a hearing outside the
presence of any jury. At the hearing, the rules of evidence shall apply and
the court shall apply a section 27-403 balancing and admit the evidence unless
the risk of prejudice substantially outweighs the probative value of the evidence.
In assessing the balancing, the court may consider any relevant factor such
as (a) the probability that the other offense occurred, (b) the proximity
in time and intervening circumstances of the other offenses, and (c) the similarity
of the other acts to the crime charged.</para>
<para>(4) This
section shall not be construed to limit the admission or consideration of
evidence under any other section of the Nebraska Evidence Rules.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>