<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Rules of Evidence" statutenumber="27-802"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>27-802</statuteno><catchline>Rule 802. Hearsay rule.</catchline><para>Hearsay is not admissible except as provided by these rules, by other rules adopted by the statutes of the State of Nebraska, or by the discovery rules of the Supreme Court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 279, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 921, &#167; 29.</para></source><annotation><para>The language of section 25-1273.01, in combination with this section, indicates a clear intention by the Legislature to create an independent avenue to admit deposition testimony. Walton v. Patil, 279 Neb. 974, 783 N.W.2d 438 (2010).</para><para>A trial judge does not have discretion to admit inadmissible hearsay statements. State v. Draganescu, 276 Neb. 448, 755 N.W.2d 57 (2008).</para><para>Apart from rulings under the residual hearsay exception, an appellate court reviews for clear error the factual findings underpinning a trial court's hearsay ruling and reviews de novo the court's ultimate determination to admit evidence over a hearsay objection. State v. Draganescu, 276 Neb. 448, 755 N.W.2d 57 (2008).</para><para>With certain exceptions, hearsay evidence is not admissible. In re Interest of Constance G., 254 Neb. 96, 575 N.W.2d 133 (1998).</para><para>Medical reports produced out of court are hearsay. Vacanti v. Master Electronics Corp., 245 Neb. 586, 514 N.W.2d 319 (1994).</para><para>An insurer's estimate of the cost of repairing damage to a vehicle, without further testimony by the insurer or the repair person, is inadmissible hearsay testimony. State v. Larkin, 222 Neb. 398, 383 N.W.2d 804 (1986).</para><para>Facts of the case held to be sufficient to place young child's statement as within the hearsay exceptions. State v. Roy, 214 Neb. 204, 333 N.W.2d 398 (1983).</para><para>Hearsay evidence is not admissible except as otherwise provided by the statutes of the state. State v. Williams, 203 Neb. 649, 279 N.W.2d 847 (1979).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>