<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Rules Of Evidence" statutenumber="27-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>27-402</statuteno><catchline>Rule 402. Relevant evidence admissible; exceptions; irrelevant evidence inadmissible.</catchline><para>All relevant evidence is admissible except as otherwise provided by the Constitution of the United States or the State of Nebraska, by Act of Congress or of the Legislature of the State of Nebraska, by these rules, or by other rules adopted by the Supreme Court of Nebraska which are not in conflict with laws governing such matters. Evidence which is not relevant is not admissible.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 279, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>Evidence of a prior accident was not admissible when the plaintiff failed to show how the prior accident was substantially similar to the accident at issue. Holden v. Wal-Mart Stores, Inc., 259 Neb. 78, 608 N.W.2d 187 (2000).</para><para>The injection of evidence into a trial that one party's losses may be covered by insurance may substantially outweigh any probative value of such evidence when the injection occurs merely to indicate the employment of a witness and when the injection of insurance could have been prevented by merely substituting for the injection of insurance a stipulation that the witness is an agent of the insured. Stumpf ex rel. Selzer Nintendo of America, Inc., 257 Neb. 920, 601 N.W.2d 735 (1999).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, evidence of other bad acts which is relevant for any purpose other than to show the actor's propensity to commit the act is admissible under subsection (2) of section 27-404. Subsection (2) of section 27-404 divides evidence of other bad acts into two categories according to the basis of relevance of the acts: (1) Relevant only to show propensity, which is not admissible, and (2) otherwise relevant (nonpropensity), which is admissible. If evidence of other bad acts is admitted into evidence, the court, if requested, must give a limiting instruction. On appeal, an analysis of subsection (2) of section 27-404 considers whether the (1) evidence was relevant for some purpose other than to prove the character of a person to show that he or she acted in conformity therewith, (2) probative value of the evidence is substantially outweighed by its potential for unfair prejudice, and (3) trial court, if requested, instructed the jury to consider the evidence only for the limited purpose for which it was admitted. State v. McManus, 257 Neb. 1, 594 N.W.2d 623 (1999).</para><para>Judicial discretion is a factor involved in admissibility of evidence under this section and section 27-403. State v. Jacob, 253 Neb. 950, 574 N.W.2d 117 (1998).</para><para>In an eminent domain action, an expert's use of the wrong measure of damages in formulating just compensation would not assist the jury either in understanding the evidence or in determining a fact in issue and, therefore, is not relevant. Lantis v. City of Omaha, 237 Neb. 670, 467 N.W.2d 649 (1991).</para><para>Rule 402 of the Nebraska Evidence Rules permits the admission of relevant evidence only. State v. Robertson, 219 Neb. 782, 366 N.W.2d 429 (1985).</para><para>Where a defendant has detailed a plan or scheme to commit a crime and ultimately carries out that plan or scheme, evidence concerning the same is admissible to show the defendant's plan and intent to commit the alleged crime. State v. Plymate, 216 Neb. 722, 345 N.W.2d 327 (1984).</para><para>An expert witness retained by one party may be compelled or will be allowed to testify to a matter of opinion upon request of the opposing party. IAFF Local 831 v. City of No. Platte, 215 Neb. 89, 337 N.W.2d 716 (1983).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>