<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Rules Of Evidence" id="id00" statutenumber="27-1101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>27-1101</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Rule 1101. Applicability of rules; courts; proceedings generally; rules inapplicable; grand jury, miscellaneous proceedings; rules applicable in part.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Evidence Rules apply to the following courts in the State of Nebraska: Supreme Court, Court of Appeals, district courts, county courts, and juvenile courts. The word judge when used in the rules shall mean any judge of any court to which the rules apply or other officer who is authorized by statute to hold any hearing to which the rules apply.</para><para>(2) The rules apply generally to all civil and criminal proceedings, including contempt proceedings except those in which the judge may act summarily.</para><para>(3) The rules with respect to privileges apply at all stages of all actions, cases, and proceedings.</para><para>(4) The rules, other than those with respect to privileges, do not apply in the following situations:</para><para>(a) Proceedings before grand juries;</para><para>(b) Proceedings for extradition or rendition; preliminary examinations or hearings in criminal cases; sentencing, granting or revoking probation, or imposing custodial sanctions; issuance of warrants for arrest, criminal summonses, and search warrants; and proceedings with respect to release on bail or otherwise;</para><para>(c) Contested cases before an administrative agency under the Administrative Procedure Act unless a party to the case requests that the agency be bound by the rules of evidence applicable in the district court; or</para><para>(d) Proceedings before the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court or the Small Claims Court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 279, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 13, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>April 20, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Proceedings exempt from rules</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Proceedings exempt from rules</emphasis></para><para>In a criminal case, the Nebraska rules of evidence do not apply to suppression hearings. State v. Piper, 289 Neb. 364, 855 N.W.2d 1 (2014).</para><para>Preliminary examinations or hearings in criminal cases are exempt from application of the evidence rules under subsection (4)(b) of this section. State v. Peterson, 280 Neb. 641, 788 N.W.2d 560 (2010).</para><para>The Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court is not bound by the usual common-law or statutory rules of evidence. Sheridan v. Catering Mgmt., Inc., 252 Neb. 825, 566 N.W.2d 110 (1997).</para><para>Nebraska Evidence Rules do not apply in juvenile court dispositional hearings such as one to terminate parental rights. The requirements of due process control a proceeding to terminate parental rights and the type of evidence which may be used by the State in an attempt to prove that parental rights should be terminated. In re Interest of P.D., 231 Neb. 608, 437 N.W.2d 156 (1989).</para><para>The Nebraska Evidence Rules do not apply at a sentencing hearing. An affidavit may be used for purposes of sentencing if it is relevant to the sentence to be imposed. State v. Dillon, 222 Neb. 131, 382 N.W.2d 353 (1986).</para><para>Nebraska Evidence Rules do not apply to proceedings for the granting or revoking of probation. State v. Ozmun, 221 Neb. 481, 378 N.W.2d 170 (1985).</para><para>Statutory rules of evidence do not apply to, among other things, proceedings for extradition. In re Application of Mahan for Writ of Habeas Corpus, 211 Neb. 671, 319 N.W.2d 760 (1982).</para><para>The statutory rules of evidence, except those governing privilege, do not apply to proceedings for extradition. Dovel v. Adams, 207 Neb. 766, 301 N.W.2d 102 (1981).</para><para>The Board of Nursing is not bound by the law of evidence unless a party so requests. Scott v. State ex rel. Board of Nursing, 196 Neb. 681, 244 N.W.2d 683 (1976).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>A suppression hearing is a preliminary hearing within the meaning of subdivision (4)(b) of this section. State v. Piper, 289 Neb. 364, 855 N.W.2d 1 (2014).</para><para>The Nebraska Evidence Rules, sections 27-101 to 27-1103, do not apply in juvenile court dispositional hearings, such as one to terminate parental rights; however, they do provide guidance in determining the type of evidence which meets due process requirements. In re Interest of D.L.S., 230 Neb. 435, 432 N.W.2d 31 (1988).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>