<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Rules Of Evidence" statutenumber="27-1002"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>27-1002</statuteno><catchline>Rule 1002. Requirement of original; exception.</catchline><para>To prove the content of a writing, recording, or photograph, the original writing, recording, or photograph is required, except as otherwise provided in these rules or by Act of Congress or of the Legislature of the State of Nebraska or by other rules adopted by the Supreme Court of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 279, &#167; 65.</para></source><annotation><para>This section is a rule of preference for the production of the original of a writing, recording, or photograph when the contents of the item are sought to be proved. Richter v. City of Omaha, 273 Neb. 281, 729 N.W.2d 67 (2007).</para><para>This "original writings" rule, which is sometimes inaccurately referred to as the "best evidence" rule, applies only if the party offering the evidence is seeking to prove the contents of a writing, recording, or photograph. State v. Decker, 261 Neb. 382, 622 N.W.2d 903 (2001).</para><para>The best evidence rule, which might more properly be called the "original writing" rule or, more correctly, the rule for "production of an original writing or document", is in reality a rule of preference for the production of the original of a writing, recording, or photograph when the contents of the item are sought to be proved. The original writing or "original document" rule does not set up a hierarchy for admissibility of evidence, but applies when a party seeks to prove material contents of a writing, recording, or photograph. The purpose of this section is the prevention of fraud, inaccuracy, mistake, or mistransmission of critical facts contained in a writing, recording, or photograph when its contents are an issue in a proceeding. By its terms, this section applies to proof of the contents of a recording. State v. Kula, 260 Neb. 183, 616 N.W.2d 313 (2000).</para><para>The original document rule does not set up a hierarchy for admissibility of evidence, but applies when a party seeks to prove material contents of a writing, recording, or photograph. The purpose of this section is the prevention of fraud, inaccuracy, mistake, or mistransmission of critical facts contained in a writing, recording, or photograph when its contents are at issue in a proceeding. Equitable Life v. Starr, 241 Neb. 609, 489 N.W.2d 857 (1992).</para><para>Not error to admit in evidence a transcription of a tape recording which was itself in evidence. State v. Martin, 198 Neb. 811, 255 N.W.2d 844 (1977).</para><para>The best evidence rule, also known as the original document rule, states that the original writing, recording, or photograph is required to prove the content of that writing, recording, or photograph. Flodman v. Robinson, 22 Neb. App. 943, 864 N.W.2d 716 (2015).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>