<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-495"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-495</statuteno><catchline>Purchase of undyed diesel fuel; exemption certificate; requirements; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) A purchaser of undyed diesel fuel may present an exemption certificate to the seller when not more than fifty gallons of such fuel is placed directly into the supply tank of a temperature control unit or power take-off unit. To qualify for this exemption, the supply tank of the temperature control unit or power take-off unit cannot be connected to the engine which provides motive power to a motor vehicle or connected to any fuel supply tank connected to the engine of a motor vehicle.</para><para>(2) The seller of undyed diesel fuel may in good faith accept the exemption certificate and sell undyed diesel fuel without collecting the tax. The seller may accept an exemption certificate for multiple purchases. Such a certificate shall be renewed annually. If the seller is a producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer, the seller may deduct the number of gallons sold without the tax from the return for the period during which the fuel was sold or for a subsequent period. If the seller is not a producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer, the seller may provide a monthly exemption certificate to the producer, distributor, wholesaler, or importer or other supplier of the taxed diesel fuel for the total number of gallons of undyed diesel fuel sold without tax during the prior month.</para><para>(3) Receipt of an exemption certificate taken in good faith shall be conclusive proof for the seller that the sale was exempt.</para><para>(4) Any person who wrongfully claims an exemption and presents an exemption certificate shall be liable for the tax on the diesel fuel. The department shall, on the basis of information available, determine the tax that would have been due on such transaction and assess the tax against such person.</para><para>(5) Any person who unlawfully issues an exemption certificate shall be subject to an administrative penalty of one thousand dollars for each violation to be assessed and collected by the department. All such penalties collected shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Highway Trust Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc>