<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-727"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-727</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited acts; criminal penalties.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to:</para><para>(a) Knowingly import, distribute, sell, produce, refine, compound, blend, or use any motor vehicle fuel, diesel fuel, or compressed fuel in the State of Nebraska without remitting the full amount of tax imposed by the provisions of the motor fuel laws;</para><para>(b) Refuse or knowingly and intentionally fail to make and file any return, report, or statement required by the motor fuel laws in the manner or within the time required;</para><para>(c) Knowingly and with intent to evade or to aid or abet any other person in the evasion of the tax imposed by the motor fuel laws (i) make any false or incomplete report, return, or statement, (ii) conceal any material fact in any record, report, return, or affidavit provided for in the motor fuel laws, (iii) improperly claim any exemption from tax imposed by the motor fuel laws, or (iv) create or submit any false documentation purporting to show that tax-free fuel has been purchased or sold tax paid or that tax-paid fuel has been used for a tax-exempt purpose;</para><para>(d) Knowingly conduct any activities requiring a license under the provisions of the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act, the Compressed Fuel Tax Act, and Chapter 66, articles 4, 5, and 7, without a license or after a license has been surrendered, suspended, or canceled;</para><para>(e) Knowingly conduct any activities requiring a permit under the provisions of the motor fuel laws without such permit or after such permit has been surrendered, suspended, or canceled;</para><para>(f) Knowingly assign or attempt to assign a license or permit;</para><para>(g) Knowingly fail to keep and maintain books and records required by the motor fuel laws;</para><para>(h) Knowingly fail or refuse to pay a fuel tax when due;</para><para>(i) Knowingly make any false statement in connection with an application for the refund of any money or tax;</para><para>(j) Fail or refuse to produce for inspection any license or permit issued under the motor fuel laws; or</para><para>(k) Knowingly violate any of the motor fuel laws or any rule or regulation under the motor fuel laws.</para><para>(2) Any person who violates subdivision (1)(b), (f), (h), or (k) of this section shall be guilty of a Class IV felony. Failing to report or pay taxes due shall constitute a separate offense for each reporting period.</para><para>(3) Any person who violates subdivision (1)(a), (c), (d), (g), or (i) of this section shall be guilty of a Class IV felony if the amount of tax involved is less than five thousand dollars and a Class III felony if the amount of tax is five thousand dollars or more. Failing to report or pay taxes due shall constitute a separate offense for each reporting period.</para><para>(4) Any person who violates subdivision (1)(e) or (j) of this section shall be guilty of a separate Class IV misdemeanor for each day of operation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 440, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 182, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1121, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1067, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 52. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Compressed Fuel Tax Act,</emphasis> see section 66-697.</para><para><emphasis>Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1501.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>