<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-4,140"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-4,140</statuteno><catchline>Motor fuels; excise tax; disposition; payment.</catchline><para>(1) Each producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer required by section 66-489 to pay motor fuels taxes shall, in addition to all other taxes provided by law, pay an excise tax at a rate set pursuant to section 66-4,144 for motor fuels received, imported, produced, refined, manufactured, blended, or compounded by such producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer within the State of Nebraska as motor fuels suitable for retail sale. All sums of money received under this section shall be credited to the Highway Trust Fund. Credits and refunds of such tax allowed to producers, suppliers, distributors, wholesalers, or importers shall be paid from the Highway Trust Fund. The balance of the amount credited, after credits and refunds, shall be allocated to the Highway Restoration and Improvement Bond Fund if bonds are issued pursuant to subsection (2) of section 39-2223 and to the Highway Cash Fund if no bonds are issued pursuant to such subsection.</para><para>(2) Producers, suppliers, distributors, wholesalers, and importers of motor fuels subject to taxation under subsection (1) of this section shall pay such excise tax and shall make a report concerning the tax in like manner, form, and time and be allowed the same exemptions, deductions, and rights of reimbursement as are authorized producers, suppliers, distributors, wholesalers, or importers for taxes paid pursuant to Chapter 66, article 4.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 722, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 599, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 632, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1039, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 258, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 602, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-473; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc>