<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id69">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" id="id71" statutenumber="66-719"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id73">66-719</statuteno><catchline id="id74">Prohibited acts;
financial penalties; department; powers; waiver of interest.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who neglects or refuses to file the report or return
due for any period or to pay the tax due for any period within the time prescribed
for the filing of such report or return or for the payment of such tax under
the motor fuel laws shall automatically accrue a penalty of fifty dollars.</para>
<para>(2) Any person who neglects or refuses to file the report
or return due for any period or to pay the tax due for any period within ten
days after the time prescribed for the filing of such report or return or
the payment of such tax under the motor fuel laws shall, in addition to the
penalty in subsection (1) of this section, be subject to the larger of:</para>
<para>(a) A penalty of one hundred dollars; or</para>
<para>(b) A penalty of ten percent of the tax not paid.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Notwithstanding anything in subsection (1) or (2) of
this section to the contrary, no penalty shall be imposed upon any person
who voluntarily reports an underpayment of tax by filing an amended return
and paying such tax if such amended return is filed and payment is made within
thirty days after the date such tax was due.</para>
<para>(b) Except as provided in subsection (8) of this section,
interest shall not be waived on any additional tax due as reported on any
amended return, and such interest shall be computed from the date such tax
was due.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who neglects or refuses to report and pay motor
fuel tax on methanol, naphtha, benzine, benzol, kerosene, or any other volatile,
flammable, or combustible liquid that is blended with motor vehicle fuel or
undyed diesel fuel shall be subject to a penalty equal to one hundred percent
of the tax not paid or one thousand dollars, whichever is larger. Such penalty
shall be in addition to the motor fuel tax due and all other penalties provided
by law.</para>
<para>(5) If any person knowingly files a false report or return,
the penalty shall be equal to one hundred percent of the tax not paid or one
thousand dollars, whichever is larger, which penalty shall be in addition
to all other penalties provided by law.</para>
<para>(6) Any person who knowingly conducts any activities requiring
a license or permit under the motor fuel laws without a license or permit
or after a license or permit has been surrendered, suspended, or canceled
shall automatically accrue a penalty of one hundred dollars per day for each
day such violation continues.</para>
<para>(7) The department may in its discretion waive all or any
portion of the penalties incurred upon sufficient showing by the taxpayer
that the failure to file or pay is not due to negligence, intentional disregard
of the law, rules, or regulations, intentional evasion of the tax, or fraud
committed with intent to evade the tax or that such penalties should otherwise
be waived.</para>
<para>(8) The department may in
its discretion waive any and all interest incurred upon sufficient showing
by the taxpayer that such interest should be waived.</para>
<para>(9)
All penalties collected by the department under this section shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Highway Trust Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 440, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1121, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1067, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB879, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>