<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id55"><sectno id="id56" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy " id="id57" statutenumber="66-488"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id59">66-488</statuteno><catchline id="id60">Producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, importer, and exporter; return; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Every producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, importer, and exporter who engages in the sale, distribution, delivery, and use of motor fuels shall render and have on file with the department a return reporting the number of gallons of motor fuels, based on gross gallons, received, imported, or exported and unloaded and emptied or caused to be received, imported, or exported and unloaded and emptied by such producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer in the State of Nebraska and the number of gallons of motor fuels produced, refined, manufactured, blended, or compounded by such producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer within the State of Nebraska, during the preceding reporting period, and defining the nature of such motor fuels. The return shall also show such information as the department reasonably requires for the proper administration and enforcement of sections 66-482 to 66-4,149. The return shall contain a declaration, by the person making the same, to the effect that the statements contained therein are true and are made under penalties of perjury, which declaration shall have the same force and effect as a verification of the return and shall be in lieu of such verification. The return shall be signed by the producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, importer, or exporter or a principal officer, general agent, managing agent, attorney in fact, chief accountant, or other responsible representative of the producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, importer, or exporter, and such return shall be entitled to be received in evidence in all courts of this state and shall be prima facie evidence of the facts therein stated. The producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, importer, or exporter shall file the return in such format as prescribed by the department on or before the twenty-fifth day of the next succeeding calendar month following the reporting period to which it relates. If the final filing date for such return falls on a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday, the next secular or business day shall be the final filing date. The return shall be considered filed on time if transmitted or postmarked before midnight of the final filing date.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, reporting period means calendar month unless otherwise provided by rules and regulations of the department, but under no circumstance shall such reporting period extend beyond an annual basis.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 172, &#167; 5, p. 450; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 151, &#167; 2, p. 406; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 149, &#167; 4, p. 522; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 166, &#167; 1, p. 572; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 66-405; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 113, &#167; 1, p. 331; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 106, &#167; 4, p. 436; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 110, &#167; 3, p. 448; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 161, &#167; 1, p. 586; </para><para>Laws 1935, Spec. Sess., c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 127; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 148, &#167; 1, p. 566; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 86, &#167; 2, p. 367; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 133, &#167; 1, p. 522; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 66-405; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 138, &#167; 2(1), p. 473; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 141, &#167; 1(1), p. 482; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 66-409; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 376, &#167; 2, p. 1210; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-409; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1067, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 168, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB846, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 