
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id310">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" id="id312" statutenumber="66-525"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-525</statuteno><catchline id="id315">Carriers; transportation
companies; shipments of motor fuel or diesel fuel into or out of state; reports;
contents.</catchline><para>The department may require every railroad
or railroad company, motor truck or motor truck transportation company, water
transportation company, pipeline company, and other person transporting or
bringing into the State of Nebraska or transporting from a refinery, ethanol
or biodiesel facility, pipeline, pipeline terminal, or barge terminal within
the State of Nebraska for the purpose of delivery within or export from this
state any motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel which is or may be produced and
compounded for the purpose of operating or propelling any motor vehicle, to
furnish a return on forms prescribed by the department to be delivered and
on file in the office of the department by the twentieth day
of each calendar month, showing all quantities of such motor vehicle fuel
or diesel fuel transported during the preceding calendar month for which the
report is made, giving the name of the consignee, the point at which delivery
was made, the date of delivery, the method of delivery, the quantity of each
such shipment, and such other information as the department requires.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 284, &#167; 1, p. 1032; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 376, &#167; 5, p. 1211; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 397, &#167; 9, p. 1251; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-426.01; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 26; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 66-4,104; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1067, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>