<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id276"><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="66-202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>66-202</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Clean-burning Motor Fuel Development Act:</para><para>(1) Flex-fuel dispenser means a fuel dispenser that is certified by the manufacturer for use with ethanol blended fuels containing at least fifteen percent by volume ethanol;</para><para>(2) Motor vehicle means a motor vehicle originally designed by the manufacturer to operate lawfully and principally on highways, roads, and streets;</para><para>(3) Qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel means a hydrogen fuel cell, compressed natural gas, liquefied natural gas, liquefied petroleum gas, or gasoline containing at least fifteen percent by volume ethanol; and</para><para>(4) Qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel property means:</para><para>(a) New equipment that:</para><para>(i) Is installed:</para><para>(A) By a certified installer;</para><para>(B) On a motor vehicle registered pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Registration Act; and</para><para>(C) To convert a motor vehicle propelled by gasoline or diesel fuel to be propelled by a qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel;</para><para>(ii) Is approved by the United States Environmental Protection Agency under 40 C.F.R. part 85, subpart F, and 40 C.F.R. part 86, subpart S, as such subparts existed on January 1, 2015; and</para><para>(iii) Has not been used to modify or retrofit any other motor vehicle propelled by gasoline or diesel fuel;</para><para>(b) The portion of the basis of a motor vehicle that was originally equipped to be propelled by a qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel that is attributable to the:</para><para>(i) Storage of the qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel;</para><para>(ii) Delivery of the qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel to the motor vehicle's engine; and</para><para>(iii) Exhaust of gases from the combustion of the qualified clean-burning motor vehicle fuel; or</para><para>(c) New property that:</para><para>(i) Is directly related to the dispensing of ethanol-blended fuels containing at least fifteen percent by volume ethanol or the compression and delivery of natural gas from a private home or residence for noncommercial purposes into the fuel tank of a motor vehicle propelled by compressed natural gas; and</para><para>(ii) Has not been previously installed or used at another location to refuel motor vehicles powered by natural gas.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB581, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>