<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-503</statuteno><catchline>License; other documents; possession required; motor fuel delivery permit number required; when; inspections; enforcement.</catchline><para>(1) Every person in charge of any vehicle in which motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel is carried into, within, or out of the State of Nebraska shall have and keep a copy of the liquid fuel carriers license with him or her during the entire transportation and also a copy of the bill of sale, bill of lading, manifest, purchase order, sales invoice or delivery ticket, or similar documentation covering all such motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel which is individually numbered and dated and shows the kind and amount of the motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel, where obtained and of whom, the destination state or delivery location, and the name and address of the owner and of the consignee or purchaser, if applicable. Such person shall exhibit every such paper or document, immediately upon demand, to the department, any employee thereof, or any peace officer of this state.</para><para>(2)(a) Any person importing motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel into the State of Nebraska for the purpose of delivery in this state who does not have in his or her possession an original unaltered bill of sale, bill of lading, or manifest identifying Nebraska as the destination state shall obtain a motor fuel delivery permit number prior to delivering such fuel. A separate motor fuel delivery permit number shall be required each time such person enters Nebraska for the purpose of delivering motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel in Nebraska. Prior to issuance of a motor fuel delivery permit number, the person shall provide his or her Nebraska liquid fuel carriers license number, the type and amount of fuel being imported, where obtained, the destination, the original bill of sale, bill of lading, or manifest number, if applicable, and such other information as the Department of Revenue deems necessary.</para><para>(b) Any person obtaining motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel from a bulk fuel storage facility located in this state, other than a pipeline terminal, barge line terminal, or refinery, who exits this state and returns with all or any portion of such fuel remaining shall not be deemed to be importing such remaining fuel and shall not be required to obtain a motor fuel delivery permit number if such person maintains the documents and papers required by subsection (1) of this section establishing that such remaining fuel was obtained from a bulk fuel storage facility located in this state.</para><para>(3) Any person transporting motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel shall be deemed to have given his or her consent to submit to an inspection of licenses and permits required for the transportation of fuel and the documents and papers required by this section for the purpose of determining compliance with the motor fuel laws. The issuance of a motor fuel delivery permit number under this section shall be deemed to be the issuance of a permit for purposes of enforcing the motor fuel laws.</para><para>(4) Any law enforcement officer who has been duly authorized to make arrests for violations of traffic laws of this state or ordinances of any city or village or any carrier enforcement officer who has reasonable grounds to believe that a vehicle is transporting motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel may require the operator of such vehicle to display any or all licenses and permits required for the transportation of fuel and the documents and papers required by this section. Such law enforcement officer or carrier enforcement officer may make a record of any of the information contained on the licenses or permits or any of the information from the bill of sale, bill of lading, manifest, or other documents and papers required by sections 66-501 to 66-512 and 66-525 to 66-531.</para><para>(5) The Legislature declares that it does not intend to place any burden upon the transportation of motor vehicle fuel or diesel fuel in interstate commerce under such circumstances as federal law and the Constitution of the United States preclude.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 130, &#167; 3, p. 463; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 66-803; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 66-503; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 255, &#167; 1, p. 797; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 526, &#167; 2, p. 2148; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 11, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 440, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 143, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 