<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-737"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-737</statuteno><catchline>Committee to oversee trust fund; members; terms; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall appoint a committee to oversee the operation of the trust fund created in section 66-733. The committee shall consist of seven members. Two members shall be diesel fuel producers, suppliers, distributors, wholesalers, or importers, two members shall be motor vehicle fuel producers, suppliers, distributors, wholesalers, or importers, two members shall be compressed fuel retailers, and one member shall be selected at large. Members shall be appointed for terms of four years.</para><para>(2) The committee shall have access to information concerning any transfers occurring from the trust fund, the collection efforts of the department to collect from the person owing the tax, and the management of the trust fund.</para><para>(3) Members of the committee shall be considered employees of the department solely for the purpose of the disclosure of confidential information and the imposition of penalties for the unauthorized disclosure of such information.</para><para>(4) The committee may receive confidential information only for the purpose of determining the effectiveness of the department in collecting the amounts transferred from the cash bond collected pursuant to section 66-734.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-610.06; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 132; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 182, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 57. </para></source></law></legaldoc>