<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id365">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" id="id367" statutenumber="66-738"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>66-738</statuteno><catchline id="id370">Motor Fuel Tax
Enforcement and Collection Division; created within Department of Revenue;
powers and duties; funding; contracts authorized.</catchline><para>The
Motor Fuel Tax Enforcement and Collection Division is hereby created within
the Department of Revenue. The division shall be funded by a separate appropriation
program within the department. All provisions of the Compressed Fuel Tax Act,
the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act, the State Aeronautics Department
Act, and sections 66-482 to 66-4,149, 66-501 to 66-531, and 66-712 to 66-736, pertaining to the Department of Revenue,
the Tax Commissioner, or the division, shall be entirely and separately undertaken
and enforced by the division, except that the division may utilize services
provided by other programs of the Department of Revenue in functional areas
known on July 1, 1991, as the budget subprograms designated revenue operations
and administration. Appropriations for the division that are used to fund
costs allocated for such functional operations shall be expended by the division
in an appropriate pro rata share and shall be subject to audit by the Auditor
of Public Accounts, at such time as he or she determines necessary, which
audit shall be provided to the budget division of the Department of Administrative
Services and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst by October 1 of the year under
audit. Audit information useful to other divisions of the Department of Revenue
may be shared by the Motor Fuel Tax Enforcement and Collection Division with
the other divisions of the department and the Division of Motor Carrier Services
of the Department of Motor Vehicles, but audits shall not be considered as
a functional operation for purposes of this section. Except for staff performing
in functional areas, staff funded from the separate appropriation program
shall only be utilized to carry out the provisions of such acts and sections.
The auditors and field investigators in the Motor Fuel Tax Enforcement and
Collection Division shall be adequately trained for the purposes of motor
fuel tax enforcement and collection. The Tax Commissioner shall hire for or
assign to the division sufficient staff to carry out the responsibility of
the division for the enforcement of the motor fuel laws.</para>
<para>Funds appropriated to the division may also be used to contract
with other public agencies or private entities to aid in the issuance of motor
fuel delivery permit numbers as provided in subsection (2) of section 66-503,
and such contracted funds shall only be used for such purpose. The amount
of any contracts entered into pursuant to this section shall be appropriated
and accounted for in a separate budget subprogram of the division.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 141; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1121, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 143, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB289, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB337, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 25.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Compressed Fuel Tax Act,</emphasis> see section 66-697.</para><para><emphasis>Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1501.</para><para><emphasis>State Aeronautics Department Act,</emphasis> see section 3-154.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>