<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-4,100"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>66-4,100</statuteno><catchline>Highway Cash Fund; Roads Operations
Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Highway Cash Fund
and the Roads Operations Cash Fund are hereby created. If bonds are issued
pursuant to subsection (2) of section 39-2223, the balance of the share of
the Highway Trust Fund allocated to the Department of Roads and deposited
into the Highway Restoration and Improvement Bond Fund as provided in subsection
(6) of section 39-2215 and the balance of the money deposited in the Highway
Restoration and Improvement Bond Fund as provided in section 39-2215.01 shall
be transferred by the State Treasurer, on or before the last day of each month,
to the Highway Cash Fund. If no bonds are issued pursuant to subsection (2)
of section 39-2223, the share of the Highway Trust Fund allocated to the Department
of Roads shall be transferred by the State Treasurer on or before the last
day of each month to the Highway Cash Fund.</para>
<para>The Legislature may direct the State Treasurer to transfer funds from
the Highway Cash Fund to the Roads Operations Cash Fund. Both funds shall
be expended by the department (1) for acquiring real estate, road materials,
equipment, and supplies to be used in the construction, reconstruction, improvement,
and maintenance of state highways, (2) for the construction, reconstruction,
improvement, and maintenance of state highways, including grading, drainage,
structures, surfacing, roadside development, landscaping, and other incidentals
necessary for proper completion and protection of state highways as the department
shall, after investigation, find and determine shall be for the best interests
of the highway system of the state, either independent of or in conjunction
with federal-aid money for highway purposes, (3) for the share of the department
of the cost of maintenance of state aid bridges, (4) for planning studies
in conjunction with federal highway funds for the purpose of analyzing traffic
problems and financial conditions and problems relating to state, county,
township, municipal, federal, and all other roads in the state and for incidental
costs in connection with the federal-aid grade crossing program for roads
not on state highways, (5) for tests and research by the department or proportionate
costs of membership, tests, and research of highway organizations when participated
in by the highway departments of other states, (6) for the payment of expenses
and costs of the Board of Examiners for County Highway and City Street Superintendents
as set forth in section 39-2310, (7)
for support of the public transportation assistance program established under
section 13-1209 and the intercity bus system assistance program established
under section 13-1213, and
(8) for purchasing from political or governmental subdivisions or public corporations,
pursuant to section 39-1307, any federal-aid transportation funds available
to such entities.</para>
<para>Any money in the Highway Cash Fund and the Roads Operations Cash Fund
not needed for current operations of the department shall, as directed by
the Director-State Engineer to the State Treasurer, be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, subject to approval by the board of each
investment. All income received as a result of such investment shall be placed
in the Highway Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 148, &#167; 4, p. 570; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 84, &#167; 2, p. 363; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 133, &#167; 2, p. 525; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 134, &#167; 10, p. 536; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 66-411; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 138, &#167; 1(4), p. 472; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 139, &#167; 1(4), p. 479; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 66-424; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 214, &#167; 4, p. 698; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 131, &#167; 15, p. 410; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 393, &#167; 1, p. 1257; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 530, &#167; 3, p. 2171; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 21, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1496, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 599, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 632, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 602, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-424; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1194, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1144, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB98, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
