<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id18"><sectno id="id19" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" id="id20" statutenumber="66-482"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id22">66-482</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 66-482 to 66-4,149:</para><para>(1) Motor vehicle shall have the same definition as in section 60-339;</para><para>(2) Motor vehicle fuel shall include all products and fuel commonly or commercially known as gasoline, including casing head or natural gasoline, and shall include any other liquid and such other volatile and inflammable liquids as may be produced, compounded, or used for the purpose of operating or propelling motor vehicles, motorboats, or aircraft or as an ingredient in the manufacture of such fuel. Agricultural ethyl alcohol produced for use as a motor vehicle fuel shall be considered a motor vehicle fuel. Motor vehicle fuel shall not include the products commonly known as methanol, kerosene oil, kerosene distillate, crude petroleum, naphtha, and benzine with a boiling point over two hundred degrees Fahrenheit, residuum gas oil, smudge oil, leaded automotive racing fuel with an American Society of Testing Materials research method octane number in excess of one hundred five, and any petroleum product with an initial boiling point under two hundred degrees Fahrenheit, a ninety-five percent distillation (recovery) temperature in excess of four hundred sixty-four degrees Fahrenheit, an American Society of Testing Materials research method octane number less than seventy, and an end or dry point of distillation of five hundred seventy degrees Fahrenheit maximum;</para><para>(3) Agricultural ethyl alcohol shall mean ethyl alcohol produced from cereal grains or agricultural commodities grown within the continental United States and which is a finished product that is a nominally anhydrous ethyl alcohol meeting American Society for Testing and Materials D4806 standards. For the purpose of sections 66-482 to 66-4,149, the purity of the ethyl alcohol shall be determined excluding denaturant and the volume of alcohol blended with gasoline for motor vehicle fuel shall include the volume of any denaturant required pursuant to law;</para><para>(4) Alcohol blend shall mean a blend of agricultural ethyl alcohol in gasoline or other motor vehicle fuel, such blend to contain not less than five percent by volume of alcohol;</para><para>(5) Supplier shall mean any person who owns motor fuels imported by barge, barge line, or pipeline and stored at a barge, barge line, or pipeline terminal in this state;</para><para>(6) Distributor shall mean any person who acquires ownership of motor fuels directly from a producer or supplier at or from a barge, barge line, pipeline terminal, or ethanol or biodiesel facility in this state;</para><para>(7) Wholesaler shall mean any person, other than a producer, supplier, distributor, or importer, who acquires motor fuels for resale;</para><para>(8) Retailer shall mean any person who acquires motor fuels from a producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer for resale to consumers of such fuel;</para><para>(9) Importer shall mean any person who owns motor fuels at the time such fuels enter the State of Nebraska by any means other than barge, barge line, or pipeline. Importer shall not include a person who imports motor fuels in a tank directly connected to the engine of a motor vehicle, train, watercraft, or airplane for purposes of providing fuel to the engine to which the tank is connected;</para><para>(10) Exporter shall mean any person who acquires ownership of motor fuels from any licensed producer, supplier, distributor, wholesaler, or importer exclusively for use or resale in another state;</para><para>(11) Gross gallons shall mean measured gallons without adjustment or correction for temperature or barometric pressure;</para><para>(12) Diesel fuel shall mean all combustible liquids and biodiesel which are suitable for the generation of power for diesel-powered vehicles, except that diesel fuel shall not include kerosene;</para><para>(13) Compressed fuel shall mean any fuel defined as compressed fuel in section 66-6,100;</para><para>(14) Person shall mean any individual, firm, partnership, limited liability company, company, agency, association, corporation, state, county, municipality, or other political subdivision. Whenever a fine or imprisonment is prescribed or imposed in sections 66-482 to 66-4,149, the word person as applied to a partnership, a limited liability company, or an association shall mean the partners or members thereof;</para><para>(15) Department shall mean the Motor Fuel Tax Enforcement and Collection Division of the Department of Revenue;</para><para>(16) Semiannual period shall mean either the period which begins on January 1 and ends on June 30 of each year or the period which begins on July 1 and ends on December 31 of each year;</para><para>(17) Producer shall mean any person who manufactures agricultural ethyl alcohol or biodiesel at an ethanol or biodiesel facility in this state;</para><para>(18) Highway shall mean every way or place generally open to the use of the public for the purpose of vehicular travel, even though such way or place may be temporarily closed or travel thereon restricted for the purpose of construction, maintenance, repair, or reconstruction;</para><para>(19) Kerosene shall mean kerosene meeting the specifications as found in the American Society for Testing and Materials publication D3699 entitled Standard Specifications for Kerosene;</para><para>(20) Biodiesel shall mean mono-alkyl esters of long chain fatty acids derived from vegetable oils or animal fats which conform to American Society for Testing and Materials D6751 specifications for use in diesel engines. Biodiesel refers to the pure fuel before blending with diesel fuel;</para><para>(21) Motor fuels shall mean motor vehicle fuel, diesel fuel, aircraft fuel, or compressed fuel;</para><para>(22) Ethanol facility shall mean a plant which produces agricultural ethyl alcohol under the provisions described in section 66-1344; and</para><para>(23) Biodiesel facility shall mean a plant which produces biodiesel.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 172, &#167; 1, p. 448; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 150, &#167; 1, p. 525; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 66-401; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 3, &#167; 15, p. 63; </para><para>Laws 1935, Spec. Sess., c. 13, &#167; 1, p. 86; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 86, &#167; 1, p. 366; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 66-401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 66-401; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 246, &#167; 1, p. 777; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 377, &#167; 1, p. 1214; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 375, &#167; 2, p. 1206; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 360, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1039, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-401; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 395; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 182, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1121, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 479, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 267; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB846, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For additional definitions,</emphasis> see section 66-712.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Motor fuels tax law is constitutional. State v. Cheyenne County, 127 Neb. 619, 256 N.W. 67 (1934).</para><para>Dry cleaner's solvents capable of use for operating motor vehicles are subject to tax. Pantorium v. McLaughlin, 116 Neb. 61, 215 N.W. 798 (1927).</para><para>The Nebraska gasoline tax is an excise tax upon use of gasoline, and is collected for convenience from the dealer. Standard Oil Co. v. Kurtz, 330 F.2d 178 (8th Cir. 1964).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc> 