<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-4,144"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>66-4,144</statuteno><catchline>Highway Restoration and Improvement Bond Fund; Highway Cash Fund; maintain adequate balance; setting of excise tax rates; procedure; Department of Transportation; provide information.</catchline><para>(1) In order to insure that an adequate balance in the Highway Restoration and Improvement Bond Fund is maintained to meet the debt service requirements of bonds to be issued by the commission under subsection (2) of section 39-2223, the Director-State Engineer shall certify to the department the excise tax rate to be imposed by sections 66-4,140 and 66-6,108 for each year during which such bonds are outstanding necessary to provide in each such year money equal in amount to not less than one hundred twenty-five percent of such year's bond principal and interest payment requirements. The department shall adjust the rate as certified by the Director-State Engineer. Such rate shall be in addition to the rate of excise tax set pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. Each such rate shall be effective from July 1 of a stated year through June 30 of the succeeding year or during such other period not longer than one year as the Director-State Engineer certifies to be consistent with the principal and interest requirements of such bonds. Such excise tax rates set pursuant to this subsection may be increased, but such excise tax rates shall not be subject to reduction or elimination unless the Director-State Engineer has received from the State Highway Commission notice of reduced principal and interest requirements for such bonds, in which event the Director-State Engineer shall certify the new rate or rates to the department. The new rate or rates, if any, shall become effective on the first day of the following semiannual period.</para><para>(2) In order to insure that there is maintained an adequate Highway Cash Fund balance to meet expenditures from such fund as appropriated by the Legislature, by June 15 or five days after the adjournment of the regular legislative session each year, whichever is later, the Director-State Engineer shall certify to the department the excise tax rate to be imposed by sections 66-4,140 and 66-6,108. The department shall adjust the rate as certified by the Director-State Engineer to be effective from July 1 through June 30 of the succeeding year. The rate of excise tax for a given July 1 through June 30 period set pursuant to this subsection shall be in addition to and independent of the rate or rates of excise tax set pursuant to subsection (1) of this section for such period. The Director-State Engineer shall determine the cash and investment balances of the Highway Cash Fund at the beginning of each fiscal year under consideration and the estimated receipts to the Highway Cash Fund from each source which provides at least one million dollars annually to such fund. The rate of excise tax shall be an amount sufficient to meet the appropriations made from the Highway Cash Fund by the Legislature. Such rate shall be set in increments of one-tenth of one percent.</para><para>(3) The Department of Transportation shall provide to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst an electronic copy of the information that is submitted to the Department of Revenue and used to set or adjust the excise tax rate.</para><para>(4) If the actual receipts received to date added to any projections or modified projections of deposits to the Highway Cash Fund for the current fiscal year are less than ninety-nine percent or greater than one hundred two percent of the appropriation for the current fiscal year, the Director-State Engineer shall certify to the department the adjustment in rate necessary to meet the appropriations made from the Highway Cash Fund by the Legislature. The department shall adjust the rate as certified by the Director-State Engineer to be effective on the first day of the following semiannual period.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to abrogate the duties of the Department of Transportation or attempt to change any highway improvement program schedule.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 722, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 172, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 632, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-476; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 255, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 182, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1067, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1135, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 239. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2017</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>