<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id409"><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-915"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>66-915</statuteno><catchline>Wind energy conversion system; light-mitigating technology system; required, when.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) FAA approval means approval by the Federal Aviation Administration that meets the requirements set forth in Chapter 10 of the Federal Aviation Administration's 2020 Advisory Circular AC 70/7460-1M, Obstruction Marking and Lighting;</para><para>(b) Light-mitigating technology system means aircraft detection lighting or any other comparable system capable of reducing the impact of facility obstruction lighting while maintaining conspicuity sufficient to assist aircraft in identifying and avoiding collision with a wind energy conversion system;</para><para>(c) Repower means a substantial physical modification of at least seventy-five percent of the wind turbines in a wind energy conversion system that results in an increase of ten percent or more in nameplate capacity; and</para><para>(d) Wind energy conversion system means an electric generation facility consisting of ten or more wind turbines that are two hundred fifty feet or more in height and any accessory or appurtenant structures and buildings including substations, meteorological towers, electrical infrastructure, and transmission lines.</para><para>(2) Beginning July 1, 2025:</para><para>(a)(i) A developer, owner, or operator of a wind energy conversion system shall make application to the Federal Aviation Administration for FAA approval to install and operate a light-mitigating technology system on such wind energy conversion system as follows:</para><para>(A) Before a wind energy conversion system commences commercial operation in this state, if such system did not exist prior to July 1, 2025;</para><para>(B) Within thirty days after a wind energy conversion system existing prior to July 1, 2025, commences a repower; or</para><para>(C) If on July 1, 2025, such developer, owner, or operator has five years or less remaining on a power purchase agreement with an electric supplier for a wind energy conversion system, within thirty days after the existing power purchase agreement is extended or renewed or a new power purchase agreement is executed; and</para><para>(ii) Within twenty-four months after receiving FAA approval, the developer, owner, or operator of the wind energy conversion system shall install a light-mitigating technology system on wind turbines covered under such FAA approval; and</para><para>(b) Any developer, owner, or operator of a wind energy conversion system existing prior to July 1, 2025, that does not commence a repower shall on or before July 1, 2035, install a light-mitigating technology system on the wind turbines in such wind energy conversion system that meets Federal Aviation Administration requirements.</para><para>(3) Any application made pursuant to subsection (2) of this section shall be submitted in good faith and reasonably intended to obtain FAA approval. If FAA approval is not granted after application is made pursuant to such subsection, the wind energy conversion system may commence or continue, as applicable, commercial operation without a light-mitigating technology system.</para><para>(4) Any costs associated with the installation, implementation, operation, and maintenance of a light-mitigating technology system shall be the responsibility of the developer, owner, or operator of the wind energy conversion system.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to require mitigation of light pollution to be carried out in a manner that conflicts with federal law or requirements, including requirements of the Federal Aviation Administration or the United States Department of Defense.</para><para>(6) Nothing in this section shall be construed to require any new or separate approval from any state or local governmental agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1370, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>