  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-4,101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-4,101</statuteno><catchline>Highway Allocation Fund; share of counties and municipalities; how used.</catchline><para>Any county may by resolution of the county board, any city may by ordinance of the mayor and city council, and any village may by ordinance of the chairperson and board of trustees issue bonds for the construction of roads of the county and street and state highway or federal-aid routes of cities and villages and to pay the interest on and to retire any such bonds by pledging funds received from the Highway Allocation Fund. Any city of the primary class may by ordinance of the mayor and city council issue bonds for the construction of offstreet parking facilities of such city and to pay the interest on and to retire any such bonds by pledging funds received from the Highway Allocation Fund.</para><para>The issuance of bonds by any county, city, or village under the authority of this section shall not be subject to any charter or statutory limitations of indebtedness or be subject to any restrictions imposed upon or conditions precedent to the exercise of the powers of counties, cities, and villages to issue bonds or evidences of indebtedness which may be contained in such charters or other statutes. Any county, city, or village which has heretofore or may hereafter issue bonds under the authority of this section shall levy property taxes upon all the taxable property in such county, city, or village issuing such bonds at such rate or rates within any applicable charter, statutory, or constitutional limitations as will provide funds which, together with receipts from the Highway Allocation Fund pledged to the payment of such bonds and any other money made available and used for that purpose, will be sufficient to pay the principal of and interest on such bonds as they severally mature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 392, &#167; 2, p. 1254; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 401, &#167; 2, p. 1259; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 530, &#167; 2, p. 2170; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 866, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 66-423.01; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 157. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 