<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id28">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" id="id30" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="66-1016"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1016</statuteno><catchline id="id33">Program of eligible
energy conservation grants; establishment and administration; certification
of improvement; cost share.</catchline><para>(1) An eligible entity
that has remitted funds
to the department as provided in section 66-1015 may establish and administer
a program of eligible energy conservation grants.</para>
<para>(2) The program shall provide for an eligible energy conservation
grant from the Energy Conservation Improvement Fund to an eligible person
for installing an eligible energy conservation improvement upon certification
by the eligible entity that it has approved an eligible energy conservation
improvement for the residence of the eligible person. The eligible entity
shall verify the purchase and installation of the eligible energy conservation
improvement at the eligible person's residence.</para>
<para>(3) The eligible entity may require the eligible person to
pay for a share of the cost of the eligible energy conservation improvement,
not to exceed twenty percent of the total cost. The share of the cost to be
paid by the eligible person may be recovered by the eligible entity in monthly
installments after completion of the eligible energy conservation improvement
by adding an amount to the eligible person's electrical bill.</para>
<para>(4) The eligible entity shall certify to the department the
amount of money to be distributed from the applicable subaccount of the Energy
Conservation Improvement Fund for payments of the energy conservation grants
approved in subsection (2) of this section. Requests for distribution may
be filed no more frequently than monthly. The department shall distribute
money only to the eligible entity.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1001, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB385, &#167; 4.</para><terminationdate>July 1, 2019</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
