<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-1345.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1345.01</statuteno><catchline>Corn and grain sorghum; excise
tax; procedure.</catchline><para>An excise tax is levied upon all corn and
grain sorghum sold through commercial channels in Nebraska or delivered in
Nebraska. For any sale or delivery of corn or grain sorghum occurring on or
after July 1, 1995, and before January 1, 2000, the tax is three-fourths cent
per bushel for corn and three-fourths cent per hundredweight for grain sorghum.
For any sale or delivery of corn or grain sorghum occurring on or after January
1, 2000, and before January 1, 2001, the tax is one-half cent per bushel for
corn and one-half cent per hundredweight for grain sorghum. For any sale or
delivery of corn or grain sorghum occurring on or after October 1, 2001, and
before October 1, 2004, the tax is one-half cent per bushel for corn and one-half
cent per hundredweight for grain sorghum. For any sale or delivery of corn
or grain sorghum occurring on or after October 1, 2004, and before October
1, 2005, the tax is three-fourths cent per bushel for corn and three-fourths
cent per hundredweight for grain sorghum. For any sale or delivery of corn
or grain sorghum occurring on or after October 1, 2005, and before October
1, 2012, the tax is seven-eighths cent per bushel for corn and seven-eighths
cent per hundredweight for grain sorghum. The
tax shall be in addition to any fee imposed pursuant to sections 2-3623 and
2-4012.</para>
<para>The excise tax shall be imposed at the time of sale or delivery and
shall be collected by the first purchaser. The tax shall be collected, administered,
and enforced in conjunction with the fees imposed pursuant to sections 2-3623
and 2-4012. The tax shall be collected, administered, and enforced by the
Department of Agriculture. No corn or grain sorghum shall be subject to the
tax imposed by this section more than once.</para>
<para>In the case of a pledge or mortgage of corn or grain sorghum as security
for a loan under the federal price support program, the excise tax shall be
deducted from the proceeds of such loan at the time the loan is made. If,
within the life of the loan plus thirty days after the collection of the excise
tax for corn or grain sorghum that is mortgaged as security for a loan under
the federal price support program, the grower of the corn or grain sorghum
so mortgaged decides to purchase the corn or grain sorghum and use it as feed,
the grower shall be entitled to a refund of the excise tax previously paid.
The refund shall be payable by the department upon the grower's written application
for a refund. The application shall have attached proof of the tax deducted.</para>
<para>The excise tax shall be deducted whether the corn or grain sorghum is
stored in this or any other state. The excise tax shall not apply to the sale
of corn or grain sorghum to the federal government for ultimate use or consumption
by the people of the United States when the State of Nebraska is prohibited
from imposing such tax by the Constitution of the United States and laws enacted
pursuant thereto.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 377, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1336, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 605, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 536, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 479, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1065, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 90, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB689, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>