<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id506">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" id="id508" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="66-1406.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1406.02</statuteno><catchline id="id511">License;
director; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The director may suspend,
revoke, cancel, or refuse to issue or renew a license under the International
Fuel Tax Agreement Act:</para>
<para>(a) If the applicant's or licensee's registration certificate
issued pursuant to the International Registration Plan Act has been suspended,
revoked, or canceled or the director refused to issue or renew such certificate;</para>
<para>(b) If the applicant or licensee is in violation of sections
75-392 to 75-399;</para>
<para>(c) If the applicant's or licensee's security has been canceled;</para>
<para>(d) If the applicant or licensee failed to provide additional
security as required;</para>
<para>(e) If the applicant or licensee failed to file any report
or return required by the motor fuel laws, filed an incomplete report or return
required by the motor fuel laws, did not file any report or return required
by the motor fuel laws electronically, or did not file a report or return
required by the motor fuel laws on time;</para>
<para>(f) If the applicant or licensee failed to pay taxes required
by the motor fuel laws due within the time provided;</para>
<para>(g) If the applicant or licensee filed any false report,
return, statement, or affidavit, required by the motor fuel laws, knowing
it to be false;</para>
<para>(h) If the applicant or licensee would no longer be eligible
to obtain a license; or</para>
<para>(i) If the applicant or licensee committed any other violation
of the International Fuel Tax Agreement Act or the rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated under the act.</para>
<para>(2) Prior to taking any action pursuant to subsection (1)
of this section, the director shall notify and advise the applicant or licensee
of the proposed action and the reasons for such action in writing, by regular United States mail,
to his or her last-known business address as shown on the application or license.
The notice shall also include an advisement of the procedures in subsection
(3) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) The applicant or licensee may, within thirty days after
the mailing of the notice, petition the director in writing for a hearing
to contest the proposed action. The hearing shall be commenced in accordance
with the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Department of
Motor Vehicles. If a petition is filed, the director shall, within twenty
days after receipt of the petition, set a hearing date at which the applicant
or licensee may show cause why the proposed action should not be taken. The
director shall give the applicant or licensee reasonable notice of the time
and place of the hearing. If the director's decision is adverse to the applicant
or licensee, the applicant or licensee may appeal the decision in accordance
with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
<para>(4) Except as provided in subsection (2) of section 60-3,205
and subsection (8) of this section, the filing of the petition shall stay
any action by the director until a hearing is held and a final decision and
order is issued.</para>
<para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (2) of section 60-3,205
and subsection (8) of this section, if no petition is filed at the expiration
of thirty days after the date on which the notification was mailed, the director
may take the proposed action described in the notice.</para>
<para>(6) Except as provided in subsection (2) of section 60-3,205
and subsection (8) of this section, if, in the judgment of the director, the
applicant or licensee has complied with or is no longer in violation of the
provisions for which the director took action under this section, the director
may reinstate the license without delay. An applicant for reinstatement, issuance,
or renewal of a license within three years after the date of suspension, revocation,
cancellation, or refusal to issue or renew shall submit a fee of one hundred
dollars to the director. The director shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer
for credit to the Highway Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(7) Suspension of, revocation of, cancellation of, or refusal
to issue or renew a license by the director shall not relieve any person from
making or filing the reports or returns required by the motor fuel laws in
the manner or within the time required.</para>
<para>(8) Any person who receives notice from the director of action
taken pursuant to subsection (1) of this section shall, within three business
days, return such registration certificate and license plates issued pursuant
to section 60-3,198 to the department. If any person fails to return the registration
certificate and license plates to the department, the department shall notify
the Nebraska State Patrol that any such person is in violation of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1056, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 563, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 853, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB358, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB331, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 47.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>International Registration Plan Act,</emphasis> see section 60-3,192.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>