<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" id="id19" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="66-1015"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1015</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Energy Conservation
Improvement Fund; created; investment; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Energy Conservation Improvement Fund is created. There shall
be a separate subaccount within the fund for each eligible entity remitting funds and administering
a program of eligible energy conservation improvements. The fund shall be
administered by the department. Funds shall be remitted by the department
to the State Treasurer for deposit in the proper subaccount of the fund from funds
remitted by the eligible entity and
state matching funds as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para>
<para>(2)(a) No later
than September 1, 2012, and no later than September 1 of each even-numbered
year thereafter, any eligible entity planning on administering a program of
eligible energy conservation improvements shall notify the department of the
amount the entity plans to remit pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section
for each of the next two fiscal years.</para>
<para>(b) Commencing July 1, 2014, any eligible entity may remit up to fifty thousand dollars per
fiscal year for deposit in the subaccount of the fund for that
eligible entity. The amount
deposited shall be matched from the amount transferred by the state to the
fund as provided in subsection (3) of this section and deposited in the subaccount
of the eligible entity. Amounts for deposit shall be accepted on a first-come,
first-served basis, and when a total of two hundred fifty thousand dollars
of deposits from eligible entities has been received in a fiscal year, no
further deposits shall be accepted. Any deposits received from eligible entities
after the dollar limit has been reached shall be returned to the eligible
entity. Any nonencumbered amount remaining in the fund at the end of the fiscal
year shall be transferred to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(3) Commencing July 1, 2014, and each fiscal year thereafter, it
is the intent of the Legislature to transfer two hundred fifty thousand dollars
from the General Fund to the Energy Conservation Improvement Fund for the
purposes of this section.</para><para>(4) Any money
in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment
officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State
Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1001, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB385, &#167; 3.</para><terminationdate>July 1, 2019</terminationdate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
