<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-1065"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1065</statuteno><catchline>Energy financing contract; contents; energy service company; bond requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Any energy financing contract entered into by a governmental unit shall:</para><para>(a) Detail the responsibilities of a Nebraska-licensed professional engineer in the design, installation, and commissioning of the energy conservation measures selected by the governmental unit. Any design shall conform to all statutes of the State of Nebraska pertaining to engineering design and public health, safety, and welfare;</para><para>(b) Set forth the calculated energy cost savings during the contract period attributable to the energy conservation measures to be installed by the energy service company. Operational savings may be included in the total savings amount, not guaranteed, but approved by the governmental unit;</para><para>(c) Estimate the useful life of each of the selected energy conservation measures;</para><para>(d) Provide that, except for obligations on termination of the contract prior to its expiration, payments on the contract are to be made over time, within a period not to exceed thirty years after the date of the installation of the energy conservation measures provided for under the contract;</para><para>(e) Provide that the calculated savings for each year of the contract period will meet or exceed all payments to be made during each year of the contract;</para><para>(f) Disclose the effective interest rate being charged by the energy service company; and</para><para>(g) In the case of a guaranteed savings contract, set forth the method by which savings will be calculated and a method of resolving any dispute in the amount of the savings. The energy service company shall have total responsibility for the savings guarantee for each guaranteed savings contract.</para><para>(2) An energy service company entering into an energy financing contract shall provide a performance bond to the governmental unit in an amount equal to one hundred percent of the total cost of the contract to assure the company's faithful performance. The energy service company shall also supply a guarantee bond equal to one hundred percent of the guaranteed energy savings for the entire term of the contract. For purposes of this section, total cost means all costs associated with the design, installation, modification, commissioning, maintenance, and financing of all energy conservation measures contemplated under the contract.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB747, &#167;  1.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2008</effectivedate></source>  </law></legaldoc> 