<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-1418"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1418</statuteno><catchline>Trip permits; issuance; fees.</catchline><para>(1) This subsection applies
until the implementation date designated by the director pursuant to subsection
(2) of this section. The department shall provide for a trip permit
to be issued. Such trip permits shall be issued for a fee of twenty dollars
and shall be valid for a period of seventy-two hours. The carrier enforcement
division designated under section 60-1303 shall act as an agent for the department
in collecting the fees prescribed in this section and shall remit all such
fees collected to the State Treasurer for credit to the Highway Cash Fund.
Such trip permits shall be available at weighing stations operated by the
carrier enforcement division and at various vendor stations as determined
appropriate by the carrier enforcement division. Trip permits shall be obtained
at the first available location, whether that is a weighing station or a vendor
station. The vendor stations shall be entitled to collect and retain an additional
fee of ten percent of the fee collected pursuant to this section as reimbursement
for the clerical work of issuing the permits.</para><?Pub Caret?>
<para>(2) This subsection applies
beginning on an implementation date designated by the director. The director
shall designate an implementation date which is on or before January 1, 2015.
A trip permit shall be issued before any person required to obtain a trip
permit enters this state. The trip permit shall be issued by the director
through Internet sales from the department's web site. The trip permit shall
be issued for a fee of twenty dollars and shall be valid for a period of seventy-two
hours. The fee collected by the director shall be remitted to the State Treasurer
for credit to the Highway Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB250, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>