<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-1844"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1844</statuteno><catchline>Jurisdictional utility; objections to assessment; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Within fifteen days after the date of the mailing of any notice of assessment under sections 66-1840 and 66-1841, the jurisdictional utility against which such assessment has been made may file with the commission objections setting out in detail the ground upon which such objector regards such assessment to be excessive, erroneous, unlawful, or invalid. The commission, after notice to the objector, shall hold a hearing in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 75-110. The commission shall determine if the assessment or any part of the assessment is excessive, erroneous, unlawful, or invalid and shall render an order upholding, invalidating, or amending the assessment. An amended assessment shall have in all respects the same force and effect as though it were an original assessment.</para><para>(2) If any assessment against which objections have been filed is not paid within ten days after service of an order finding that such objections have been overruled and disallowed by the commission, the commission shall give notice of such delinquency to the State Treasurer and to the objector in the manner provided for in the State Natural Gas Regulation Act. The State Treasurer shall then collect the amount of such assessment. If an amended assessment is not paid within ten days after service of the order of the commission, the commission shall notify the State Treasurer and the objector as in the case of delinquency in the payment of an original assessment. The State Treasurer shall then collect the amount of such assessment as provided in the case of an original assessment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 44. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 