<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1861" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1861</statuteno><catchline>Enlargement or extension of area; rebuttable presumptions.</catchline><para>In determining whether an enlargement or extension of a natural gas service area, natural gas mains, or natural gas services is in the public interest pursuant to section 66-1860, the following shall constitute rebuttable presumptions:</para><para>(1) Any enlargement or extension by a metropolitan utilities district within a city of the metropolitan class or its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction is in the public interest;</para><para>(2) Any enlargement or extension by a jurisdictional utility within a city other than a city of the metropolitan class in which it serves natural gas on a franchise basis or its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction is in the public interest; and</para><para>(3) Any enlargement or extension by a metropolitan utilities district within its statutory boundary or within a city other than a city of the metropolitan or primary class in which it serves natural gas on a franchise basis or its extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction is in the public interest.</para><para>Any enlargement or extension by a metropolitan utilities district within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan class involving the exercise of the power of eminent domain pursuant to subsection (2) of section 14-2116 shall, by reason of such exercise, be conclusively determined to be in the public interest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 78, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2004), &#167; 57-1304; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1249, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>