<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1064"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1064</statuteno><catchline>Governmental unit; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to entering into an energy financing contract, a governmental unit shall obtain a written opinion from a professional engineer licensed in the State of Nebraska whose interests are independent from the financial savings outcome of the contract. The opinion shall contain a review of recommendations proposed by an energy service company pertaining to energy conservation measures designed to reduce energy consumption to the governmental unit.</para><para>(2) At least fourteen days prior to entering into an energy financing contract, a governmental unit shall furnish public notice of its intention to enter into such contract, the general nature of the proposed work being considered under the contract, and the name and telephone number of a person to be contacted by any energy service company interested in submitting a proposal to contract for such work. The governmental unit shall also directly solicit requests for qualifications from at least three energy service companies relating to the proposed contract.</para><para>(3) Upon receiving responses to its request for qualifications pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the governmental unit may select the most qualified energy service company based on the company's experience, technical expertise, and financial arrangements, the overall benefits to the governmental unit, and other factors determined by the governmental unit to be relevant and appropriate. The governmental unit may thereafter negotiate and enter into an energy financing contract pursuant to section 66-1065 with the company selected based on the criteria established by the governmental unit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 