<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="66-1866"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1866</statuteno><catchline>Jurisdictional utility; prior filing not subject to negotiations; application for infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge; duties; public advocate; duties; commission; powers; change in rate schedules.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies to applications for an infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge by a jurisdictional utility whose last general rate filing was not the subject of negotiations with affected cities as provided for in section 66-1838.</para> <para>(2) When a jurisdictional utility governed by this section files an application with the commission seeking to establish or change any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules, it shall submit to the commission with the application proposed infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules and supporting documentation regarding the calculation of the proposed infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules, including (a) a list of eligible projects, (b) a description of the projects, (c) the location of the projects, (d) the purpose of the projects, (e) the dates construction began and ended, (f) the total expenses for each project at completion, and (g) the extent to which such expenses are eligible for inclusion in the calculation of the infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge.</para><para>(3)(a) When an application, along with any associated proposed rate schedules and documentation, is filed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the public advocate shall conduct an examination of the proposed infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules.</para><para>(b) The public advocate shall cause an examination to be made of information regarding the jurisdictional utility to confirm that the underlying costs are in accordance with the State Natural Gas Regulation Act and to confirm proper calculation of the proposed infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rates and rate schedules. The commission shall require a report regarding such examination to be prepared and filed with the commission not later than sixty days after the application is filed. No other revenue requirement or ratemaking issue shall be examined in consideration of the application or associated proposed rate schedules filed pursuant to the act unless the consideration of such affects the determination of the validity of the proposed infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules.</para><para>(c) The commission shall hold a hearing on the application and any associated rate schedules at which the public advocate shall present his or her report and shall act as trial staff before the commission. The commission shall issue an order to become effective not later than one hundred twenty days after the application is filed, except that the commission may, for good cause, extend such period for an additional thirty days.</para><para>(d) If the commission finds that an application complies with the requirements of the act, the commission shall enter an order authorizing the jurisdictional utility to impose an infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate that is sufficient to recover appropriate pretax revenue, as determined by the commission pursuant to the act.</para><para>(4) A jurisdictional utility may apply for a change in any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules approved pursuant to this section no more than once in any twelve-month period. Any such application for a change shall be pursued in the manner provided for in this section.</para> <para>(5) In determining the appropriate pretax revenue, the commission shall consider the following factors:</para> <para>(a) The net original cost of eligible infrastructure system replacements. For purposes of this section, the net original cost means the original cost of eligible infrastructure system replacements minus associated retirements of existing infrastructure;</para> <para>(b) The accumulated deferred income taxes associated with the eligible infrastructure system replacements;</para> <para>(c) The accumulated depreciation associated with the eligible infrastructure system replacements;</para> <para>(d) The state, federal, and local income tax or excise tax rates at the time of such determination;</para> <para>(e) The jurisdictional utility's actual regulatory capital structure as determined during the most recent general rate proceeding of the jurisdictional utility;</para> <para>(f) The actual cost rates for the jurisdictional utility's debt and preferred stock as determined during the most recent general rate proceeding of the jurisdictional utility;</para> <para>(g) The jurisdictional utility's cost of common equity as determined during the most recent general rate proceeding of the jurisdictional utility; and</para><para>(h) The depreciation rates applicable to the eligible infrastructure system replacements at the time of the most recent general rate proceeding of the jurisdictional utility.</para> <para>(6)(a) The monthly infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate shall be allocated among the jurisdictional utility's classes of customers in the same manner as costs for the same type of facilities were allocated among classes of customers in the jurisdictional utility's most recent general rate proceeding. An infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate shall be assessed to customers as a monthly fixed charge and not based on volumetric consumption. Such monthly charge shall not increase more than fifty cents per residential customer over the base rates in effect at the time of the initial filing for any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules. Thereafter, each subsequent filing shall not increase the monthly charge by more than fifty cents per residential customer over that charge in existence at the time of the most recent application for any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules.</para><para>(b) At the end of each twelve-month period during which the infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules are in effect, the jurisdictional utility shall reconcile the differences between the revenue resulting from the infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge and the appropriate pretax revenue as found by the commission for that period and shall submit the reconciliation and any proposed infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules adjustment to the commission for approval to recover or refund the difference, as appropriate, through adjustments of the infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate.</para> <para>(7)(a) A jurisdictional utility that has implemented any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules pursuant to the act shall cease to collect such charges when new base rates and charges become effective for the jurisdictional utility following a commission order establishing customer rates in a general rate proceeding.</para><para>(b) In any subsequent general rate proceeding involving a jurisdictional utility which is collecting charges pursuant to any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules, the commission shall reconcile any previously unreconciled infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge revenue as necessary to ensure that the revenue matches as closely as possible to the appropriate pretax revenue as found by the commission for that period.</para> <para>(8) In the event the commission disallows, during a subsequent general rate proceeding, recovery of costs associated with eligible infrastructure system replacements previously included in any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules, the commission shall order the jurisdictional utility to make such rate adjustments as necessary to recognize and account for any such overcollections.</para> <para>(9) Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the authority of the commission to review and consider infrastructure system replacement costs along with other costs during any general rate proceeding of any jurisdictional utility.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB658, &#167;  5.</para><effectivedate>August 30, 2009</effectivedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>