<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1062" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1062</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 66-1062 to 66-1066:</para><para>(1) Energy conservation measure means a training, service, or operations program, facility alteration, or capital equipment acquisition designed to reduce wastewater or energy, utility, or water consumption, enhance revenue, or reduce operating or capital costs. Energy conservation measure includes:</para><para>(a) Repair or renovation of heating, ventilation, and air conditioning systems;</para><para>(b) Installation or repair of automated or computerized energy control systems;</para><para>(c) Replacement or modification of lighting fixtures;</para><para>(d) Insulation of a building structure or systems within that structure;</para><para>(e) Installation of energy recovery systems;</para><para>(f) Installation of cogeneration systems that produce steam or forms of energy such as heat, as well as electricity, for use primarily within a building or complex of buildings;</para><para>(g) Replacement, weatherstripping, caulking, or other insulation of windows or doors;</para><para>(h) Meter replacement, installation, or modification or installation of automated meter reading systems;</para><para>(i) Replacement or installation of energy or water conservation equipment or improvements thereto, or the substitution of non-water-using fixtures, appliances, or equipment; or</para><para>(j) Any other measure designed to reduce wastewater or energy, utility, or water consumption, enhance revenue, or reduce operating or capital costs;</para><para>(2) Energy financing contract means an agreement between an energy service company and a governmental unit for the implementation of one or more energy conservation measures in an existing facility in order to reduce wastewater or energy, utility, or water consumption, enhance revenue, or reduce operating or capital costs. Energy financing contract includes, but is not limited to, a performance contract, shared-savings contract, guaranteed contract, and lease-purchase contract;</para><para>(3) Energy service company means a person or business experienced in the implementation and installation of energy conservation measures; and</para><para>(4) Governmental unit means a school district, community college area, village, city, county, or department or agency of the State of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 236, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB881, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>