<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1335"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1335</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Ethanol Board; established; terms; vacancy; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Ethanol Board is hereby established. The board shall consist of seven members to be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature. The Governor shall make the initial appointments within thirty days after September 1, 1993. Four members shall be actually engaged in farming in this state, one in general farming and one each in the production of corn, wheat, and sorghum. One member shall be actively engaged in business in this state. One member shall represent labor interests in this state. One member shall represent Nebraska petroleum marketers in this state.</para><para>(2) Members shall be appointed for terms of four years, except that of the initial appointees the terms of the member representing labor interests and the member engaged in general farming shall expire on August 31, 1994, the terms of the member engaged in sorghum production and the member engaged in wheat production shall expire on August 31, 1995, the term of the member representing petroleum marketers shall expire on August 31, 1996, and the terms of the member engaged in business and the member engaged in corn production shall expire on August 31, 1997. A member shall serve until a successor is appointed and qualified. Not more than four members shall be members of the same political party.</para><para>(3) A vacancy on the board shall exist in the event of death, disability, resignation, or removal for cause of a member. Any vacancy on the board arising other than from the expiration of a term shall be filled by appointment for the unexpired portion of the term. An appointment to fill a vacancy shall be made by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature, and any person so appointed shall have the same qualifications as the person whom he or she succeeds.</para><para>(4) The board shall meet at least once annually.</para><para>(5) The members shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The members shall receive twenty-five dollars for each day while engaged in the performance of board duties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 364, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 53. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>