<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-1811"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1811</statuteno><catchline>Complaint; investigation; hearing; where held; commission; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Upon a complaint in writing made against any jurisdictional utility (a) that any rates or terms and conditions of service of such utility are in any respect unreasonable, unjust, unjustly discriminatory, or unduly preferential, (b) that any terms and conditions of service or act whatsoever affecting or relating to any service performed or to be performed by such utility for the public, is in any respect unreasonable, unjust, unjustly discriminatory, or unduly preferential, or (c) that any service performed or to be performed by such utility for the public is inadequate, insufficient, or cannot be obtained, the commission may proceed, with or without notice, to make such investigation as it deems necessary.</para><para>(2) No order changing such rates, terms and conditions, or acts complained of shall be made or entered by the commission without a formal public hearing in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 75-110, of which due notice shall be given by the commission to such utility or to such complainant or complainants, if any.</para><para>(3) The commission shall have power to require jurisdictional utilities to make such improvements and do such acts as are or may be required by law to be done by any such utility, including refunds as authorized by law.</para><para>(4) The commission may hold public hearings in the area being impacted by any rate investigation or rate increase being considered by the commission to hear public comments.</para><para>(5) If after investigation and hearing the rates or terms and conditions of service of any jurisdictional utility are found unjust, unreasonable, unjustly discriminatory, or unduly preferential, or in any way in violation of the provisions of the State Natural Gas Regulation Act or of any of the laws of the State of Nebraska, the commission shall have the power to establish, and to order substituted therefor, to be effective as of the date of the order, such rates or terms and conditions of service as the commission determines to be just, reasonable, and necessary. If it is found that any term or condition of service, practice, or act relating to any service performed or to be performed by such utility is in any respect unreasonable, unjust, insufficient, unjustly discriminatory, or unduly preferential, or otherwise in violation of any of the provisions of the act or of any of the laws of the State of Nebraska, the commission may substitute therefor by order such other terms and conditions of service, practice, service, or act as it determines to be just, reasonable, and necessary, to be effective as of the date of the order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 