<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-1345"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1345</statuteno><catchline>Ethanol Production Incentive Cash
Fund; created; use; investment; transfers; duties.</catchline><para>(1) There
is hereby created the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund which shall be
used by the board to pay the credits created in section 66-1344 to the extent
provided in this section. Any money in the fund available for investment shall
be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The State Treasurer
shall transfer to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund such money as
shall be (a) appropriated to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund by
the Legislature, (b) given as gifts, bequests, grants, or other contributions
to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund from public or private sources,
(c) made available due to failure to fulfill conditional requirements pursuant
to investment agreements entered into prior to April 30, 1992, (d) received
as return on investment of the Ethanol Authority and Development Cash Fund,
(e) credited to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund from the excise
taxes imposed by section 66-1345.01 through December 31, 2012, and (f) credited
to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund pursuant to sections 66-489,
66-726, 66-1345.04, and 66-1519.</para>
<para>(2) The Department of Revenue shall, at the end of each calendar month,
notify the State Treasurer of the amount of motor fuel tax that was not collected
in the preceding calendar month due to the credits provided in section 66-1344.
The State Treasurer shall transfer from the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash
Fund to the Highway Trust Fund an amount equal to such credits less the following
amounts:</para>
<para>(a) For 1993, 1994, and 1995, the amount generated during the calendar
quarter by a one-cent tax on motor fuel pursuant to sections 66-489 and 66-6,107;</para>
<para>(b) For 1996, the amount generated during the calendar quarter by a
three-quarters-cent tax on motor fuel pursuant to such sections;</para>
<para>(c) For 1997, the amount generated during the calendar quarter by a
one-half-cent tax on motor fuel pursuant to such sections; and</para>
<para>(d) For 1998 and each year thereafter, no reduction.</para>
<para>For 1993 through 1997, if the amount generated pursuant to subdivisions
(a), (b), and (c) of this subsection and the amount transferred pursuant to
subsection (1) of this section are not sufficient to fund the credits provided
in section 66-1344, then the credits shall be funded through the Ethanol Production
Incentive Cash Fund but shall not be funded through either the Highway Cash
Fund or the Highway Trust Fund. For 1998 and each year thereafter, the credits
provided in such section shall be funded through the Ethanol Production Incentive
Cash Fund but shall not be funded through either the Highway Cash Fund or
the Highway Trust Fund.</para>
<para>If, during any month, the amount of money in the Ethanol Production
Incentive Cash Fund is not sufficient to reimburse the Highway Trust Fund
for credits earned pursuant to section 66-1344, the Department of Revenue
shall suspend the transfer of credits by ethanol producers until such time
as additional funds are available in the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash
Fund for transfer to the Highway Trust Fund. Thereafter, the Department of
Revenue shall, at the end of each month, allow transfer of accumulated credits
earned by each ethanol producer on a prorated basis derived by dividing the
amount in the fund by the aggregate amount of accumulated credits earned by
all ethanol producers.</para>
<para>(3) The State Treasurer shall transfer from the Ethanol Production Incentive
Cash Fund to the Management Services Expense Revolving Fund the amount reported
under subsection (4) of section 66-1345.02 for each calendar month of the
fiscal year as provided in such subsection.</para>
<para>(4) On December 31, 2012, the State Treasurer shall transfer one-half of the unexpended
and unobligated funds, including all subsequent investment interest, from
the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund to the Nebraska Corn Development, Utilization, and Marketing Fund
and the Grain Sorghum Development, Utilization, and Marketing Fund in the
same proportion as funds were collected pursuant to section 66-1345.01 from
corn and grain sorghum. The Department of Agriculture shall assist the State
Treasurer in determining the amounts to be transferred to the funds. The State
Treasurer shall transfer the remaining one-half of the unexpended and unobligated
funds to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(5) Whenever the unobligated balance in the Ethanol Production Incentive
Cash Fund exceeds twenty million dollars, the Department of Revenue shall
notify the Department of Agriculture at which time the Department of Agriculture
shall suspend collection of the excise tax levied pursuant to section 66-1345.01.
If, after suspension of the collection of such excise tax, the balance of
the fund falls below ten million dollars, the Department of Revenue shall
notify the Department of Agriculture which shall resume collection of the
excise tax.</para>
<para>(6) On or before December 1, 2003, and each December 1 thereafter, the
Department of Revenue and the Nebraska Ethanol Board shall jointly submit
a report to the Legislature which shall project the anticipated revenue and
expenditures from the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund through the termination
of the ethanol production incentive programs pursuant to section 66-1344.
The initial report shall include a projection of the amount of ethanol production
for which the Department of Revenue has entered agreements to provide ethanol
production credits pursuant to section 66-1344.01 and any additional ethanol
production which the Department of Revenue and the Nebraska Ethanol Board
reasonably anticipate may qualify for credits pursuant to section 66-1344.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 754, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 66-1327; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 364, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 961, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 182, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 377, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 605, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 329, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 536, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 479, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1065, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB689, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>