  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1809"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1809</statuteno><catchline>Commission; investigations authorized; hearing; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The commission, upon its own initiative, may investigate all schedules of rates, contracts, and terms and conditions of service of jurisdictional utilities. If after notice, investigation, and hearing the commission finds that such rates or terms and conditions of service are unjust, unreasonable, unjustly discriminatory, or unduly preferential, the commission shall have the power to establish and order substituted therefor such rates and such terms and conditions of service as are just and reasonable, effective as of the date of the order.</para><para>(2) If after investigation and hearing it is found that any term or condition of service, measurement, practice, act, or service complained of is unjust, unreasonable, unduly preferential, unjustly discriminatory, or otherwise in violation of the State Natural Gas Regulation Act or of the orders of the commission or if it is found that any service is inadequate or that any reasonable service cannot be obtained, the commission may substitute therefor, effective as of the date of the order, such other terms or conditions of service, measurements, practices, acts, or service and make such order respecting any such changes in such terms and conditions of service, measurements, practices, acts, or service as are just and reasonable. When, in the judgment of the commission, public necessity and convenience require, the commission may establish just and reasonable rates, charges, or privileges, but all such rates, charges, and privileges shall be open to all users of a like kind of service under similar circumstances and conditions. Hearings shall be conducted in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to section 75-110.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 