<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1519"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1519</statuteno><catchline>Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund to be administered by the department. Revenue from the following sources shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund:</para><para>(a) The fees imposed by sections 66-1520 and 66-1521;</para><para>(b) Money paid under an agreement, stipulation, cost-recovery award under section 66-1529.02, or settlement; and</para><para>(c) Money received by the department in the form of gifts, grants, reimbursements, property liquidations, or appropriations from any source intended to be used for the purposes of the fund.</para><para>(2) Money in the fund may be spent for: (a) Reimbursement for the costs of remedial action by a responsible person or his or her designated representative and costs of remedial action undertaken by the department in response to a release first reported after July 17, 1983, and on or before June 30, 2020, including reimbursement for damages caused by the department or a person acting at the department's direction while investigating or inspecting or during remedial action on property other than property on which a release or suspected release has occurred; (b) payment of any amount due from a third-party claim; (c) fee collection expenses incurred by the State Fire Marshal; (d) direct expenses incurred by the department in carrying out the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act; (e) other costs related to fixtures and tangible personal property as provided in section 66-1529.01; (f) interest payments as allowed by section 66-1524; (g) claims approved by the State Claims Board authorized under section 66-1531; and (h) the direct and indirect costs incurred by the department in responding to spills and other environmental emergencies related to petroleum or petroleum products.</para><para>(3) Transfers may be made from the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The State Treasurer shall transfer one million five hundred thousand dollars from the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund on July 1 of each of the following years: 2004 through 2011.</para><para>(4) Any money in the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 289, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 409, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 237, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 270, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 461, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 367, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 105; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1065, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 40, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1145, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB154, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB2, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB29, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB873, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB887, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>April 8, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>