<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1335"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1335</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Ethanol Board; established; terms; vacancy; meetings; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Ethanol Board is hereby established. The board shall consist of nine members to be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature.</para><para>(2)(a) Four members shall be actually engaged in farming in this state, one in general farming and one each in the production of corn, wheat, and sorghum.</para><para>(b)(i) Until August 31, 2026, one member shall be actively engaged in business in this state.</para><para>(ii) Beginning September 1, 2026, the member under this subdivision (2)(b) shall be an ethanol producer in this state. If the member under this subdivision (2)(b) is an ethanol producer on August 31, 2026, then such member may serve as the member under this subdivision (2)(b) for the remainder of the term without reappointment by the Governor. If the member under this subdivision (2)(b) is not an ethanol producer on August 31, 2026, the Governor shall appoint a new member that is an ethanol producer to serve as the member under this subdivision (2)(b) for the remainder of the term within thirty days after September 1, 2026.</para><para>(c) One member shall represent labor interests in this state.</para><para>(d) One member shall represent Nebraska petroleum marketers in this state.</para><para>(e) Two members shall be ethanol producers in this state, and such members shall be in addition to the member that is an ethanol producer under subdivision (2)(b) of this section. The Governor shall make the initial appointments of such members within thirty days after September 1, 2026.</para><para>(3) Members shall be appointed for terms of four years, except that the initial terms of the two initial appointees under subdivision (2)(e) of this section shall expire on August 31, 2028, for one of such members and on August 31, 2029, for the other of such members. A member shall serve until a successor is appointed and qualified. Not more than five members shall be members of the same political party.</para><para>(4) A vacancy on the board shall exist in the event of death, disability, resignation, or removal for cause of a member. Any vacancy on the board arising other than from the expiration of a term shall be filled by appointment for the unexpired portion of the term. An appointment to fill a vacancy shall be made by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature, and any person so appointed shall have the same qualifications as the person whom he or she succeeds.</para><para>(5) The board shall meet at least once annually.</para><para>(6) The members shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177. The members shall receive twenty-five dollars for each day while engaged in the performance of board duties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 364, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB815, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>