<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id95">
<sectno id="id96">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" id="id97" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="66-1901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1901</statuteno><catchline>Wind measurement equipment; registration
with Department of Aeronautics; data available to public; removal of equipment;
report required.</catchline><para>(1)
All wind measurement equipment associated with the development or study of
wind-powered electric generation, whether owned or leased, shall be registered
with the Department of Aeronautics if the equipment is at least fifty feet
in height above the ground and is located outside the boundaries of any incorporated
city or village.</para>
<para>(2)(a) On or
before January 1, 2013, all such equipment installed prior to July 15, 2010,
shall be either lighted, marked with balls at least twenty-one inches in diameter,
painted, or modified in some other manner so it is recognizable in clear air
during daylight hours from a distance of not less than two thousand feet.</para>
<para>(b) All such
equipment installed on or after July 15, 2010, shall be either lighted or
painted.</para><para>(3) The person or firm that owns or leases equipment described
in subsection (1) of this section shall register it within fifteen days after
July 15, 2010, in the case of equipment installed before such date or within
thirty days after installation in the case of equipment installed on or after
such date. Such registration shall include the equipment's exact location
and height above the ground, the name of the person or firm registering the
equipment, the method used to make the equipment recognizable as provided
in subsection (2) of this section, and the name and telephone number of a
contact person for any issues related to such equipment. Within five days
after receiving such registration, the department shall make all data included
in the registration available to the public.</para><para>(4) Any person or firm
that removes equipment subject to the registration requirements of this section
shall report the removal to the department within thirty days after such removal.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>