<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id14"><sectno id="id15" opdate="January 1, 2009">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" id="id16" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="66-1014"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1014</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Low-Income Home Energy Conservation Act:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Revenue;</para><para>(2) Eligible energy conservation grant means a grant paid to an eligible person for an eligible energy conservation improvement;</para><para>(3) Eligible energy conservation improvement means a device, a method, equipment, or material that reduces consumption of or increases efficiency in the use of electricity or natural gas for a residence owned by an eligible person, including, but not limited to, insulation and ventilation, storm or thermal doors or windows, awnings, caulking and weatherstripping, furnace efficiency modifications, thermostat or lighting controls, replacement or modification of lighting fixtures or bulbs to increase the energy efficiency of the home's lighting system, and systems to turn off or vary the delivery of energy;</para><para>(4) Eligible entity means an entity providing matching funds pursuant to section 66-1015 and which is a public power district organized under Chapter 70, article 6, a rural public power district organized under Chapter 70, article 8, an electric cooperative corporation organized under the Electric Cooperative Corporation Act, a nonprofit corporation organized for the purpose of furnishing electric service, a joint entity organized under the Interlocal Cooperation Act, or a municipality; and</para><para>(5) Eligible person means any resident of Nebraska who owns his or her residence and whose household income is at or below one hundred fifty percent of the federal poverty level, as determined in accordance with the Low-Income Home Energy Conservation Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1001, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Electric Cooperative Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 70-701.</para><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 