<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1529.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1529.01</statuteno><catchline>Remedial action; fixtures and tangible personal property; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall reimburse the responsible person from the fund for damages to fixtures and costs of tangible personal property related to the remedial action as set forth in subsections (2) and (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) The responsible person shall be reimbursed from the fund for reasonable repair or replacement costs approved in a remedial action plan for fixtures which are damaged by the remedial action, except in the case of intentional acts or gross negligence by the responsible person or his or her agents. Costs for removal of fixtures are eligible for reimbursement at the time of site closure if such fixtures were a part of the approved remedial action. All fixtures reimbursed by the fund which are attached to real property are owned by the responsible person or the property owner, if different from the responsible person.</para><para>(3) The responsible person shall be reimbursed from the fund for the value of tangible personal property purchased by the responsible person and used in the remedial action. Reimbursement shall be according to the current schedule of reasonable rates made available by the department pursuant to section 66-1518. All tangible personal property reimbursed by the fund is owned by the state. The department may use tangible personal property reimbursed by the fund in other remedial actions, store such property until needed, maintain the property, or sell or dispose of such property in a manner beneficial to the fund. Any proceeds from the sale or disposal of such property shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 409, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 34. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 