<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1345.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1345.02</statuteno><catchline>Excise tax; records required;
remittance of tax; duties; calculations required by Department of Agriculture;
report.</catchline><para>(1) The first purchaser, at the time of sale or delivery,
shall retain the excise tax as provided in section 66-1345.01 and shall maintain
the necessary records of the excise tax for each sale or delivery of corn
or grain sorghum. Records maintained by the first purchaser shall provide
(a) the name and address of the seller or deliverer, (b) the date of the sale
or delivery, (c) the number of bushels of corn or hundredweight of grain sorghum
sold or delivered, and (d) the amount of excise tax retained on each sale
or delivery. The records shall be open for inspection and audit by authorized
representatives of the Department of Agriculture during normal business hours
observed by the first purchaser.</para>
<para>(2) The first purchaser shall render and have on file with the department
by the last day of each January, April, July, and October on forms prescribed
by the department a statement of the number of bushels of corn and hundredweight
of grain sorghum sold or delivered in Nebraska. At the time the statement
is filed, the first purchaser shall pay and remit to the department the excise
tax.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall remit the excise tax collected to the State
Treasurer for credit to the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund within
thirty days after the end of each quarter.</para>
<para>(4) The department shall calculate its costs in collecting and enforcing
the excise tax imposed by section 66-1345.01 and shall report such costs to
the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services within thirty
days after the end of the fiscal year. Sufficient funds to cover such costs
shall be transferred from the Ethanol Production Incentive Cash Fund to the
Management Services Expense Revolving Fund at the end of each calendar month.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 377, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 605, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 536, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB689, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>