<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1519.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1519.01</statuteno><catchline>Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund; transfer to Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund; authorized; repayment; contracts authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to December 31, 1996, the department may authorize the State Treasurer to transfer funds from the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund to the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund in such amount as determined by the department to be necessary to satisfy the state match requirement necessary to obtain federal capitalization grants under the federal Clean Water Act, as defined in section 81-15,149. The department may enter into contracts for repayment of such amounts, plus any additional amounts, including interest, determined by the department to be reasonable and necessary with respect to such transfers. Such contracts may allow repayments to be completed on or after December 31, 1996.</para><para>(2) Prior to December 31, 1996, the department may authorize the State Treasurer to deposit amounts received from the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund, including amounts due from federal capitalization grants for the benefit of the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund, in the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund. The department may authorize the State Treasurer to repay such amounts, plus any additional amounts, including interest, determined by the department to be reasonable and necessary with respect to such deposits, and the department may enter into contracts with respect thereto for the benefit of the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund. The terms of any such contracts or authorizations may end on or after December 31, 1996.</para><para>(3) The department may agree, in the contracts authorized under subsection (2) of this section, that specific amounts or sources of money in the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Cash Fund shall be obligated or pledged to the repayment of deposits from the Wastewater Treatment Facilities Construction Loan Fund, and that some or all of such specified amounts shall not be available to provide reimbursement pursuant to section 66-1523 or payments pursuant to section 66-1529.01 or 66-1529.02. Such specified amounts shall not exceed the amounts the department deems reasonably necessary to provide adequate security for the repayment of deposits. Any such pledge shall be valid and binding from the time the pledge is made, the amounts or sources of money so pledged shall immediately be subject to the lien of such pledge without any physical delivery thereof or further act, the lien shall be valid and binding as against all parties having claims of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise, regardless of whether the parties have notice thereof, and no such pledge agreement need be recorded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 29. </para></source></law></legaldoc>