<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id61"> <sectno id="id62">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" id="id63" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="66-1865"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1865</statuteno><catchline>Jurisdictional utility; application and proposed rate schedules; filing; commission; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning January 1, 2010, a jurisdictional utility may file an application and proposed rate schedules with the commission to establish or change infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules that will allow for the adjustment of the jurisdictional utility's rates and charges to provide for the recovery of costs for eligible infrastructure system replacements. The commission shall not approve any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules if such schedules would produce total annualized infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge revenue below the lesser of one million dollars or one-half percent of the jurisdictional utility's base revenue level approved by the commission in the jurisdictional utility's most recent general rate proceeding. The commission shall not approve any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules if such schedules would produce total annualized infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge revenue exceeding ten percent of the jurisdictional utility's base revenue level approved by the commission in the jurisdictional utility's most recent general rate proceeding. Any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules and any future changes thereto shall be calculated and implemented in accordance with the State Natural Gas Regulation Act. Infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge revenue shall be subject to a refund based upon a finding and order of the commission to the extent provided in subsections (6) and (8) of section 66-1866 or as approved by the affected cities to the extent provided in subsection (6) and subdivision (7)(c) of section 66-1867.</para> <para>(2) The commission shall not approve any infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate schedules for any jurisdictional utility that has not had a general rate proceeding decided or dismissed by issuance of a commission order within the sixty months immediately preceding the application by the jurisdictional utility for an infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge.</para> <para>(3) A jurisdictional utility shall not collect an infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate for a period exceeding sixty months after its initial approval unless within such sixty-month period the jurisdictional utility has filed for or is the subject of a new general rate proceeding, except that the infrastructure system replacement cost recovery charge rate may be collected until the effective date of new rate schedules established as a result of the new general rate proceeding or until the general rate proceeding is otherwise decided or dismissed by issuance of a commission order without new rates being established.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB658, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>