<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1509</statuteno><catchline>Owner, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Owner shall mean:</para><para>(a) In the case of a tank in use on or after November 8, 1984, or brought into use after such date, any person who owns a tank used for the storage, use, or dispensing of petroleum; and</para><para>(b) In the case of a tank in use before November 8, 1984, but no longer in use on such date, any person who owned such tank immediately before the discontinuation of its use.</para><para>(2) Owner shall not include a person who, without participating in the management of a tank and otherwise not engaged in petroleum production, refining, and marketing:</para><para>(a) Holds indicia of ownership primarily to protect his or her security interest in a tank or a lienhold interest in the property on or within which a tank is or was located; or</para><para>(b) Acquires ownership of a tank or the property on or within which a tank is or was located:</para><para>(i) Pursuant to a foreclosure of a security interest in the tank or of a lienhold interest in the property; or</para><para>(ii) If the tank or the property was security for an extension of credit previously contracted, pursuant to a sale under judgment or decree, pursuant to a conveyance under a power of sale contained within a trust deed or from a trustee, or pursuant to an assignment or deed in lieu of foreclosure.</para><para>(3) Ownership of a tank or the property on or within which a tank is or was located shall not be acquired by a voidable transfer, as provided in the Uniform Voidable Transactions Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 289, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 409, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1226, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB70, &#167; 16. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Voidable Transactions Act,</emphasis> see section 36-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>