<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1849"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1849</statuteno><catchline>Competitive natural gas providers and aggregators; certification by commission; costs and expenses; allocation.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall certify all competitive natural gas providers and aggregators providing natural gas services. In an application for certification, a competitive natural gas provider or aggregator shall reasonably demonstrate managerial, technical, and financial capability sufficient to obtain and deliver the services such provider or aggregator proposes to offer. The commission may establish reasonable conditions or restrictions on the certificate at the time of issuance. The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish specific criteria for certification. The commission shall make a determination on an application for certification within ninety days after its submission unless the commission determines that additional time is necessary to consider the application. If the commission determines that additional time is necessary to consider the application, the commission may extend the time for making a determination for an additional sixty days.</para><para>(2) The commission may resolve disputes involving the provision of natural gas services by a competitive natural gas provider or aggregator.</para><para>(3) The commission shall allocate the costs and expenses reasonably attributable to certification and dispute resolution as authorized in this section to persons identified as parties to such proceeding who are engaged in or who seek to engage in providing natural gas services or other persons identified as participants in such proceeding. The funds received for the costs and expenses of certification and dispute resolution shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Public Service Commission Regulation Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 49. </para></source></law></legaldoc>