<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" statutenumber="66-1618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1618</statuteno><catchline>Council; members; appointment; terms.</catchline><para>(1) The council shall be appointed by the Governor within sixty days after the date the vote is certified to the Governor pursuant to section 66-1617. The council shall consist of nine members, including four members representing retail marketers, one member representing wholesalers, suppliers, and importers, one member representing manufacturers and distributors of liquefied petroleum gas equipment, one member representing the academic or propane research community, one propane user or consumer, and the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee. Other than the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee and the representatives of the research community and consumers, members shall be full-time employees or owners of businesses in the industry or representatives of agriculture cooperatives. Only one person from any company or an affiliated company may serve on the council at a time. All members shall be Nebraska residents, except that the members representing wholesalers, suppliers, and importers and manufacturers and distributors of liquefied petroleum gas equipment may be residents of other states.</para><para>(2) Members of the council shall serve terms of three years, except that, of the initial members, three shall be appointed for terms of one year and three shall be appointed for terms of two years. Members filling unexpired terms shall be appointed in a manner consistent with this section. Members may serve a maximum of two consecutive full terms, except that members filling unexpired terms may serve a maximum of seven consecutive years. Members filling unexpired terms shall be appointed in a manner consistent with this section. Former members may be reappointed if they have not been members for a period of two years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 699, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB805, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 