<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id113">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" id="id115" statutenumber="66-1831"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1831</statuteno><catchline id="id118">Public advocate;
powers.</catchline><para>(1) The public advocate shall have the
power to:</para>
<para>(a) Investigate the legality and reasonableness of rates,
charges, and practices of jurisdictional utilities except for tariffs subject to section 66-1868;</para>
<para>(b) Petition for relief, request, initiate, and intervene
in any proceeding before the commission concerning such utilities except for tariffs subject to section
66-1868;</para>
<para>(c) Represent and appear for ratepayers and the public in
proceedings before the commission and in any negotiations or other measures
to resolve disputes that give rise to such proceedings except for tariffs subject to section 66-1868;</para>
<para>(d) Represent and appear for ratepayers and the public in
any negotiations or other measures to resolve disputes that give rise to proceedings
before the commission and make and seek approval of agreements to settle such
disputes except for tariffs
subject to section 66-1868; and</para>
<para>(e) Make motions for rehearing or reconsideration, appeal,
or seek judicial review of any order or decision of the commission regarding
jurisdictional utilities except
for tariffs subject to section 66-1868.</para>
<para>(2) The public advocate shall not advocate for or on behalf
of any single individual, organization, or entity.</para>
<para>(3) The public advocate may enter into stipulations with
other parties in any proceeding to balance the interests of those it represents
with the interests of the jurisdictional utilities as a means of improving
the quality of resulting decisions in a highly technical environment and minimizing
the cost of regulation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 790, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1115, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>