<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Oils, Fuels, And Energy" id="id375" statutenumber="66-1521"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>66-1521</statuteno><catchline id="id378">Petroleum release remedial action fee; amount; license required; filing; violation; penalty; Department of Revenue; powers and duties; Petroleum Release Remedial Action Collection Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) A petroleum release remedial action fee is hereby imposed upon the producer, refiner, importer, distributor, wholesaler, or supplier who engages in the sale, distribution, delivery, and use of petroleum within this state, except that the fee shall not be imposed on petroleum that is exported. The fee shall also be imposed on diesel fuel which is indelibly dyed. The amount of the fee shall be nine-tenths of one cent per gallon on motor vehicle fuel as defined in section 66-482 and three-tenths of one cent per gallon on diesel fuel as defined in section 66-482. The amount of the fee shall be used first for payment of claims approved by the State Claims Board pursuant to section 66-1531; second, up to three million dollars of the fee per year shall be used for reimbursement of owners and operators under the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Act for investigations of releases ordered pursuant to section 81-15,124; and third, the remainder of the fee shall be used for any other purpose authorized by section 66-1519. The fee shall be paid by all producers, refiners, importers, distributors, wholesalers, and suppliers subject to the fee by filing a monthly return on or before the twentieth day of the calendar month following the monthly period to which it relates. The pertinent provisions, specifically including penalty provisions, of the motor fuel laws as defined in section 66-712 shall apply to the administration and collection of the fee except for the treatment given refunds. There shall be a refund allowed on any fee paid on petroleum which was taxed and then exported, destroyed, or purchased for use by the United States Government or its agencies. The department may also adjust for all errors in the payment of the fee. In each calendar year, no claim for refund related to the fee can be for an amount less than ten dollars.</para><para>(2) No producer, refiner, importer, distributor, wholesaler, or supplier shall engage in the sale, distribution, delivery, or use of petroleum in this state without having first obtained a petroleum release remedial action license. Application for a license shall be made to the Department of Revenue upon a form prepared and furnished by the Department of Revenue. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. Failure to obtain a license prior to engaging in the sale, distribution, delivery, or use of petroleum shall be a Class IV misdemeanor. The Department of Revenue may suspend or cancel the license of any producer, refiner, importer, distributor, wholesaler, or supplier who fails to pay the fee imposed by subsection (1) of this section in the same manner as licenses are suspended or canceled pursuant to section 66-720.</para><para>(3) The Department of Revenue may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out this section.</para><para>(4) The Department of Revenue shall deduct and withhold from the petroleum release remedial action fee collected pursuant to this section an amount sufficient to reimburse the direct costs of collecting and administering the petroleum release remedial action fee. Such costs shall not exceed one hundred fifty thousand dollars for each fiscal year. The one hundred fifty thousand dollars shall be prorated, based on the number of months the fee is collected, whenever the fee is collected for only a portion of a year. The amount deducted and withheld for costs shall be deposited in the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Collection Fund which is hereby created. The Petroleum Release Remedial Action Collection Fund shall be appropriated to the Department of Revenue, except that transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Petroleum Release Remedial Action Collection Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(5) The Department of Revenue shall collect the fee imposed by subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 289, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 409, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 139; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1160, &#167; 120; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 153; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1067, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB165, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>