<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id515"><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-2305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>66-2305</statuteno><catchline>Nuclear and Hydrogen Industry Work Group; created; members; per diems; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall create the Nuclear and Hydrogen Industry Work Group.</para><para>(2) The work group shall consist of the following twelve members:</para><para>(a) One representative of the Nebraska community college system;</para><para>(b) One representative of the Nebraska state college system;</para><para>(c) Two representatives of the nuclear industry;</para><para>(d) Two representatives of the hydrogen industry;</para><para>(e) One representative of a public power district;</para><para>(f) Two at-large members;</para><para>(g) The Director of Economic Development or a designee of the director;</para><para>(h) The chairperson of the Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature or a designee of the chairperson; and</para><para>(i) The chairperson of the Government, Military and Veterans Affairs Committee of the Legislature or a designee of the chairperson. </para><para>(3) The work group members described in subdivisions (2)(a) through (f) of this section shall be appointed by the Governor. The work group members described in subdivisions (2)(h) and (i) of this section shall serve as ex officio, nonvoting members.</para><para>(4)(a) Each work group member described in subdivisions (2)(a) through (f) of this section may receive a per diem of sixty dollars for each day such member attends a meeting of the work group or is engaged in matters concerning the work group, except that no work group member shall receive more than one thousand dollars in per diems per year under this subdivision.</para><para>(b) Each such work group member shall be reimbursed for travel and lodging expenses for the performance of such member's duties while carrying out the Nuclear and Hydrogen Development Act as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 to be paid out of the Nuclear and Hydrogen Development Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB565, &#167; 38. </para><operativedate>May 27, 2023</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>