<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Oils, Fuels, and Energy" statutenumber="66-2210" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>66-2210</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the E-15 Access Standard Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Agriculture;</para><para>(2) Director means the Director of Agriculture;</para><para>(3) E-15 access standard means the requirements described in subsections (1) and (2) of section 66-2211;</para><para>(4) E-15 gasoline means a classification of ethanol blended gasoline formulated with a percentage of more than ten percent but no more than fifteen percent by volume of ethanol;</para><para>(5) Ethanol has the same meaning as agricultural ethyl alcohol as defined in section 66-482;</para><para>(6) Motor fuel means all products and fuel commonly or commercially known as gasoline, including ethanol and the various ethanol and gasoline blends;</para><para>(7) Motor fuel dispenser means equipment that is the part of motor fuel storage and dispensing infrastructure that includes mechanical or electrical systems that operate a motor fuel pump dispensing motor fuel from a motor fuel storage tank to the end point of the equipment's nozzle;</para><para>(8) Motor fuel pump means the part of motor fuel storage and dispensing infrastructure that is a meter or similar commercial weighing and measuring device used to measure and dispense motor fuel originating from a motor fuel storage tank, on a retail basis;</para><para>(9)(a) Motor fuel storage and dispensing infrastructure means equipment used to:</para><para>(i) Store and dispense motor fuel; or</para><para>(ii) Store, blend, and dispense motor fuel.</para><para>(b) Motor fuel storage and dispensing infrastructure includes, but is not limited to, motor fuel storage tanks, motor fuel pumps, and motor fuel dispensers. Motor fuel storage and dispensing infrastructure does not include signage not located on the motor fuel dispenser or motor fuel pump;</para><para>(10) Motor fuel storage tank means the part of motor fuel storage and dispensing infrastructure that includes an aboveground or belowground container constituting a fixture used to store an accumulation of motor fuel;</para><para>(11) Nonqualifying motor fuel dispenser means:</para><para>(a) A dispenser that exclusively dispenses any of the following:</para><para>(i) Aviation fuel;</para><para>(ii) Diesel fuel;</para><para>(iii) Kerosene; or</para><para>(iv) Diesel exhaust fluid;</para><para>(b) A dispenser that is part of a tank vehicle as defined in section 60-4,131 that is not used to dispense motor fuel on the premises of the retail motor fuel site; or</para><para>(c) A dispenser that is part of a commercial marina;</para><para>(12) Qualifying motor fuel dispenser means a motor fuel dispenser that is capable of dispensing motor fuel at all times that it is in operation. The term does not include nonqualifying motor fuel dispensers;</para><para>(13) Retail dealer means a person engaged in the business of storing and dispensing motor fuel from a motor fuel pump for sale on a retail basis; and</para><para>(14) Retail motor fuel site means a geographic location in this state where a retail dealer sells and dispenses motor fuel on a retail basis.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB562, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1095, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>