<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, and Funds" statutenumber="72-803"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-803</statuteno><catchline>Public buildings; construction; improvement and repair; contracts; bidding; procedure; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) The state and any department or agency thereof, subject to the powers of the state building division of the Department of Administrative Services, shall have general charge of the erection of new buildings which are being erected for such department or agency, the repair and improvement of buildings under the control of such department or agency, including fire escapes, and the improvement of grounds under the control of such department or agency.</para><para>(2) Buildings and other improvements costing more than fifty thousand dollars shall be (a) constructed under the general charge of the department or agency as provided in subsection (1) of this section and (b) let by contract to the lowest responsible bidder after proper advertisement as set forth in subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(3) The successful bidder at the letting shall enter into a contract with the department or agency, prepared as provided for by subsection (4) of this section, and shall furnish a bond for the faithful performance of his or her contract, except that a performance bond shall not be required for any project which has a total cost of one hundred thousand dollars or less unless the department or agency includes a bond requirement in the specifications for the project.</para><para>(4) When contracts are to be let by the department or agency as provided in subsection (2) of this section, advertisements shall be published in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the state building division stating that sealed proposals will be received by the department or agency at its office on the date therein stated for the furnishing of materials, the construction of buildings, or the making of repairs or improvements and that plans and specifications can be seen at the office of the department or agency. All bids or proposals shall be accompanied by a certified check or by a bid bond in a sum fixed by the department or agency and payable thereto. All such contracts shall be awarded to the lowest responsible bidder, but the right shall be reserved to reject any and all bids. Whenever any material described in any contract can be obtained from any state institution, the department or agency shall exclude it from such a contract.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 257, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1241, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 530, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB256, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>