<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id659"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-805"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>72-805</statuteno><catchline>Buildings constructed with state funds; code requirements; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, the 2018 International Energy Conservation Code, published by the International Code Council, applies to all new buildings constructed in whole or in part with state funds after July 1, 2020. The Department of Water, Energy, and Environment shall review building plans and specifications necessary to determine whether a building will meet the requirements of this subsection, except that the department shall not be required to review building plans and specifications upon evidence that the building plans and specifications have previously been reviewed by a county, city, or village enforcing a local building or construction code adopted pursuant to section 71-6406 if such local building or construction code includes the requirements of the 2018 International Energy Conservation Code. The department shall provide a copy of any review to the agency receiving funding. The agency receiving the funding shall verify that the building as constructed meets or exceeds the code. The verification shall be provided to the department.</para><para>(2) This section does not apply to any building that (a) is constructed or repaired using state funds received in the form of a grant or loan from the state and (b) will not be owned or managed by the state upon the completion of such construction or repair.</para><para>(3) The Director of Water, Energy, and Environment may, in consultation with the State Building Administrator of the Department of Administrative Services, adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 755, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 888, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB329, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB405, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB288, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 384; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB768, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>