<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-728"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-728</statuteno><catchline>Persons named to Nebraska Hall of Fame; limitations; Nebraskans awarded Medal of Honor; plaque.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, the Nebraska Hall of Fame Commission shall not name more than one person to the Nebraska Hall of Fame during each five-year period beginning on and after January 1, 2005. During the first two years of each five-year period, the commission shall receive nominations of candidates to be named to the Nebraska Hall of Fame. The commission shall review the nominations and may select the finalists for induction. During the subsequent two years of each five-year period, the commission shall review the finalists, if any, and shall hold public hearings regarding the finalists in each of the congressional districts. After the hearings, the commission may select one finalist for induction. If a finalist is selected for induction, the commission shall name him or her to the Nebraska Hall of Fame during the final year of each five-year period. No individual shall be named to the Nebraska Hall of Fame until at least thirty-five years after such person's demise.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding the limitations imposed by subsection (1) of this section, the commission shall procure an appropriate plaque upon which shall be placed the names of each Nebraskan awarded the Medal of Honor as a result of such person's services in the armed forces of the United States. Such plaque shall have sufficient space for listing the names of persons who shall be awarded the Medal of Honor in the future. The plaque shall have a suitable place in the State Capitol.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 355, &#167; 5, p. 1119; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 595, &#167; 1, p. 2448; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 670, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 37, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>