<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-410</statuteno><catchline>Board; office; records; organization; officers; meetings.</catchline><para>The board shall maintain its office or principal place of business in the office of the county clerk of the county where its treasurer has his or her office and shall hold its meetings, which shall be open to the public, in the district courtroom of such county. The minute book of the board and all other papers, records, or correspondence shall be kept on file and preserved by its secretary in the office of the county clerk. The first board shall organize within ten days after the date of its written notice of appointment by the Governor. The county treasurer shall, upon receipt of his or her copy of the letters of appointment from the Governor, issue a call for the initial meeting of the trustees for a day and hour certain, shall call the meeting to order, shall act as temporary chairperson, shall examine and verify the credentials of the Governor's appointees to the board with his or her copy thereof, and shall deliver all documents of credentials to the secretary of the board when he or she is later chosen. The appointees shall select from their own number a chairperson and a secretary, whose terms of office shall be for a period of one year. Each year thereafter the board shall hold its annual meeting and shall meet and organize for the ensuing year at the place designated in this section for holding its regular meetings on the day and hour prescribed by the bylaws. Notice of the time and place of holding the annual meeting of the board shall be given by the secretary by publication one time in a legal newspaper published in and of general circulation in the county or, if none is published in the county, in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the county not less than ten days before the day when the annual meeting is held. The chairperson and secretary shall hold office until their successors are selected and qualified.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 148, &#167; 2, p. 584; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 72-412; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 72-410; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 38. </para></source></law></legaldoc>