<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-201.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-201.01</statuteno><catchline>Plan for sale of educational lands; plan for investment of funds; state investment officer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Board of Educational Lands and Funds shall prepare a plan for the sale of educational lands over which the board has general management and control on July 19, 1996. The plan shall be submitted to the Education Committee of the Legislature on or before December 1, 1996. The plan shall provide for the sale of enough of the total of the educational lands by January 1, 2008, to result in one-fourth of the value of the school trust permanent portfolio being invested by the board in real property located within the State of Nebraska and the remaining three-fourths of the value of the school trust permanent portfolio being invested by the state investment officer. The plan shall be implemented beginning on July 1, 1997. In no case shall the plan or any part of it be executed if such execution violates the fiduciary duties of the board.</para><para>(2) Any sale under this section shall not include mineral rights.</para><para>(3) The state investment officer shall prepare a plan for investment of the funds derived from the sale of educational lands under the board's plan developed under this section. The state investment officer's plan shall be submitted to the Education Committee of the Legislature on or before December 1, 1996. The plan shall include estimated rates of return for the invested funds.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, value of the school trust permanent portfolio means the total fair market value of the educational lands and of all stocks, bonds, and other assets comprising the permanent school fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1205, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>