<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-701.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-701.05</statuteno><catchline>Emergency seat of state government; designation, when; plans and preparations; Governor; adopt; purchase of real estate prohibited; exception.</catchline><para>(1) The official designation of the location or locations of the emergency seat of state government, and the removal thereto of the government of the state, shall in no event precede: (a) The inception of an attack; or (b) the inception of a strategic or tactical warning period duly proclaimed by the President of the United States, the Governor of Nebraska, or by both such officials, and based on the imminence of an attack.</para><para>(2) Prior to any such attack or warning period, however, and subject to such rules and regulations as the Governor may promulgate, such preliminary plans and preparations may be made as shall be deemed necessary and advisable to facilitate the subsequent accomplishment, during such emergency, of the actions provided in sections 72-701.01 to 72-701.06. Such planning and preparations may include any or all of the following steps, but shall not necessarily be limited thereto: (a) Selection of a tentative location or locations for the emergency seat of state government in the event that, as provided in subsection (1) of this section, it subsequently becomes necessary and advisable to designate such tentative location or locations as the official location or locations of the emergency seat of state government; (b) negotiation with local authorities, property owners, and other proper persons, for the possible use and occupancy of specific buildings or areas or buildings and areas, at or near such tentative location or locations, for the purposes mentioned in sections 72-701.01 to 72-701.06 during a subsequent emergency; and (c) storing and stockpiling, at or near the tentative location or locations, of essential supplies and equipment, and vital records or duplicates thereof which would be necessary to permit the continuity of the governmental operations of the state in an emergency.</para><para>(3) Prior to an attack or warning period, as set out in subsection (1) of this section, neither the state, nor any official or agency thereof, shall, except only for the storage and safeguarding of vital records and duplicates thereof, purchase, contract for the purchase of, or obligate funds of the state for the purchase of any real estate or appurtenance thereto, for subsequent use as an emergency seat of state government.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 332, &#167; 5, p. 1208. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 