<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, and Funds" statutenumber="72-819"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>72-819</statuteno><catchline>Museum and visitor center honoring Chief Standing Bear; grants; Fort Robinson State Park; museum; Game and Parks Commission; powers and duties; appropriations; legislative intent; Nebraska State Historical Society; memorandum of understanding or contract, authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The Game and Parks Commission shall award grants to a federally recognized Indian tribe to construct, develop, and manage a museum and visitor center honoring Chief Standing Bear.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate to the Game and Parks Commission for the Chief Standing Bear Museum and visitor center:</para><para>(a) Not more than fifteen million dollars for fiscal year 2025-26 from the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund for construction of the museum and visitor center; and</para><para>(b) Seven hundred fifty thousand dollars for fiscal year 2024-25 from the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund for exhibit fabrication and historical interpretation.</para><para>(3)(a) The Game and Parks Commission shall construct, develop, and manage a museum at Fort Robinson State Park.</para><para>(b) It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate to the Game and Parks Commission for the museum at Fort Robinson State Park not more than seven million dollars for fiscal year 2025-26 from the Museum Construction and Maintenance Fund.</para><para>(c) The Game and Parks Commission may execute a memorandum of understanding or contract with the Nebraska State Historical Society for purposes of museum development, exhibit fabrication, and historical interpretation at Fort Robinson State Park.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB531, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB164, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1413, &#167; 47. </para></source></law></legaldoc>