<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-230"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-230</statuteno><catchline>School and saline lands; sale; when subject to taxation.</catchline><para>Educational or saline lands sold under the provisions of any law of this state, or such as have been sold, shall not be taxable until the right to a deed shall have become absolute, but the value of the interest of such purchaser shall be taxable, which interest shall be determined by the value of the land and improvements, less the amount due the state; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> when such land shall be situated within the limits of any city or village and shall have been subdivided into lots, then it shall be subject to all special assessments for sidewalk, grading, paving, guttering, curbing, sewerage, and all other municipal improvements, in the same manner as other lots and lands in such city or village, except that a sale of such school lots to collect such assessment or assessments shall only pass the interest or title of the purchaser from the state, his heirs or assigns, and his or their right to a conveyance of the same, upon the payment of any residue of the purchase price or interest.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1899, c. 69, &#167; 13, p. 305; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 135, &#167; 1, p. 441; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5859; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5195; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 72-215; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 72-230.</para></source><annotation><para>School lands that have been sold by the state under contract are properly included in a drainage district, and are assessable for benefits derived therein. Morehouse v. Elkhorn River Drainage District, 90 Neb. 406, 133 N.W. 446 (1911).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 