<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-1704"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1704</statuteno><catchline>Community board; appointment; members; meetings; public records; certain disclosures prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) A political subdivision, educational institution, or other organization that desires to have a vacant or partially vacant public building designated, in whole or in part, as a business incubation center shall appoint, in conjunction with political subdivisions or private organizations that agree to contribute monetarily or in kind to the center, a community board to perform the duties required by the Nebraska Small Business Incubator Act. The appointing body may designate an existing board of an economic development entity, upon consent of that entity, as the community board.</para><para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, the community board shall consist of not more than fifteen persons. The members of the community board shall consist of representatives from key segments of the community, including, but not limited to, political, financial, business, labor, and educational representatives. The community board shall elect from its members a chairperson.</para><para>(3) An existing board of an economic development entity designated as a community board pursuant to subsection (1) of this section need not meet the number requirements of subsection (2) of this section but shall meet the composition requirements of subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) Community board members shall serve at the pleasure of the appointing bodies or until the community board is dissolved by the appointing body. Dissolution shall not occur before the expiration of any lease agreement between the community board and a public agency.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (7) of this section, the business which the community board may perform shall be conducted at a public meeting held in compliance with the Open Meetings Act.</para><para>(6) Except as provided in subsection (7) of this section, a community board shall be subject to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09.</para><para>(7) The community board shall not disclose, orally or in writing, matters of a proprietary nature as described in subsection (7) of section 72-1708 without the consent of the applicant or tenant submitting the information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 409, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 21. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>