<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" id="id00" statutenumber="72-1239.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1239.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Council; duties and responsibilities.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The appointed members of the council shall have the responsibility for the investment management of the assets of the retirement systems administered by the Public Employees Retirement Board as provided in section 84-1503, the assets of the Nebraska educational savings plan trust created pursuant to sections 85-1801 to 85-1817, the assets of the achieving a better life experience program pursuant to sections 77-1401 to 77-1409, and beginning January 1, 2017, the assets of each retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act. Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section, the appointed members shall be deemed fiduciaries with respect to the investment of the assets of the retirement systems, of the Nebraska educational savings plan trust, and of the achieving a better life experience program and shall be held to the standard of conduct of a fiduciary specified in subsection (3) of this section. The nonvoting, ex officio members of the council shall not be deemed fiduciaries.</para><para>(b) As fiduciaries, the appointed members of the council and the state investment officer shall discharge their duties with respect to the assets of the retirement systems, of the Nebraska educational savings plan trust, and of the achieving a better life experience program solely in the interests of the members and beneficiaries of the retirement systems or the interests of the participants and beneficiaries of the Nebraska educational savings plan trust and the achieving a better life experience program, as the case may be, for the exclusive purposes of providing benefits to members, members' beneficiaries, participants, and participants' beneficiaries and defraying reasonable expenses incurred within the limitations and according to the powers, duties, and purposes prescribed by law.</para><para>(2)(a) The appointed members of the council shall have the responsibility for the investment management of the assets of state funds. The appointed members shall be deemed fiduciaries with respect to the investment of the assets of state funds and shall be held to the standard of conduct of a fiduciary specified in subsection (3) of this section. The nonvoting, ex officio members of the council shall not be deemed fiduciaries.</para><para>(b) As fiduciaries, the appointed members of the council and the state investment officer shall discharge their duties with respect to the assets of state funds solely in the interests of the citizens of the state within the limitations and according to the powers, duties, and purposes prescribed by law.</para><para>(3) The appointed members of the council shall act with the care, skill, prudence, and diligence under the circumstances then prevailing that a prudent person acting in like capacity and familiar with such matters would use in the conduct of an enterprise of a like character and with like aims by diversifying the investments of the assets of the retirement systems, the Nebraska educational savings plan trust, the achieving a better life experience program, and state funds so as to minimize risk of large losses, unless in light of such circumstances it is clearly prudent not to do so. No assets of the retirement systems, the Nebraska educational savings plan trust, or the achieving a better life experience program shall be invested or reinvested if the sole or primary investment objective is for economic development or social purposes or objectives.</para><para>(4) Neither the appointed members of the council nor the state investment officer shall be deemed fiduciaries with respect to investments of the assets of a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act made by or on behalf of the board of education as defined in section 79-978 or the board of trustees provided for in section 79-980. Neither the council nor any member thereof nor the state investment officer shall be liable for the action or inaction of the board of education or the board of trustees with respect to the investment of the assets of a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act, the consequences of any such action or inaction of the board of education or the board of trustees, and any claims, suits, losses, damages, fees, and costs related to such action or inaction or consequences thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB591, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB610, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Class V School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-978.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>