<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, and Funds" statutenumber="72-1237" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1237</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Investment Council; created; members; appointment; term; vacancy; immunity.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Investment Council is created. For purposes of the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, council means the Nebraska Investment Council. The council shall consist of five members, appointed by the Governor with the approval of the Legislature, and the State Treasurer and the director of the Nebraska Public Employees Retirement Systems as nonvoting, ex officio members. One of the appointed members shall be designated chairperson by the Governor.</para><para>Prior to September 1, 2006, each of the appointed members of the council shall serve for a term of five years and may be removed by the Governor for cause after notice and an opportunity to be heard. The term of any appointed member shall be extended until the date on which his or her successor's appointment is effective. Beginning September 1, 2006, each of the appointed members of the council shall serve for a term of five years that begins on January 1 and may be removed by the Governor for cause after notice and an opportunity to be heard. Such term shall be extended until the date on which his or her successor's appointment is effective. For members serving on September 1, 2006, and whose terms would otherwise end on September 18, such terms shall be extended until the following December 31, or until the date on which his or her successor's appointment is effective. A member may be reappointed. A successor shall be appointed in the same manner as provided for the members first appointed, and in case of a vacancy caused by death, resignation, or otherwise, the Governor shall appoint a qualified person to fill the vacancy for the unexpired term.</para><para>No member of the council shall be personally liable, except in cases of willful dishonesty, gross negligence, or intentional violation of law, for actions relating to his or her duties as a member of the council.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 1, p. 2350; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 368, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>