<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" id="id39" statutenumber="72-1001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1001</statuteno><catchline id="id42">Nebraska Capital Construction Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Capital Construction Fund is created. The fund shall consist of revenue and transfers credited to the fund as authorized by law. Money shall be appropriated from the fund to state agencies for making payments on projects as determined by the Legislature, including, but not limited to, purchases of land, structural improvements to land, acquisition of buildings, construction of buildings, including architectural and engineering costs, replacement of or major repairs to structural improvements to land or buildings, additions to existing structures, remodeling of buildings, and acquisition of equipment and furnishings of new or remodeled buildings. The fund shall be administered by the State Treasurer as a multiple-agency-use fund and appropriated to state agencies as determined by the Legislature. Transfers may be made from the fund to the Capitol Restoration Cash Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Any investment earnings from investment of money in the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund shall be credited to such fund, except that for fiscal years 2023-24, 2024-25, and 2025-26, any investment earnings from investment of money in the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund from transfers credited to such fund that are designated for the construction of a new state prison shall be credited to the Economic Recovery Contingency Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB2, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB531, &#167; 28. </para><operativedate>June 7, 2023</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>