<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" id="id00" statutenumber="72-1249"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1249</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Expenses; costs; how paid.</catchline><para>(1) Any expenses with respect to the purchase, sale, or exchange of any security shall be charged to the fund or funds on behalf of which such purchase, sale, or exchange was made. All other expenses of the state investment officer shall be paid out of appropriations for the office of the state investment officer.</para><para>(2) Beginning on March 31, 2016, any expenses with respect to the transfer to and assumption by the council and the state investment officer of the duty and authority to invest the assets of a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act shall be charged to the Class V School Employees Retirement Fund established in section 79-9,115. Such expenses shall be paid without the approval of the board of education as defined in section 79-978 or the board of trustees provided for in section 79-980.</para><para>(3) Management, custodial, and service costs which are a direct expense of investing the assets of a retirement system provided for under the Class V School Employees Retirement Act may be paid from the income of such assets when it is not prohibited by statute or the Constitution of Nebraska. For purposes of this section, management, custodial, and service costs include investment counsel fees for managing assets, real estate mortgage loan service fees, real estate management fees, and custody fees for fund securities. All such fees shall be approved by the council and the state investment officer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 13, p. 2354; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1279, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 364, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB447, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB29, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Class V School Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 79-978.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>