<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, and Funds" statutenumber="72-1246.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1246.06</statuteno><catchline>Northern Ireland investments; state investment officer; duties; MacBride principles; report.</catchline><para>(1) By January 1 of each year, the state investment officer shall (a) compile a list of corporations that directly or through a subsidiary do business in Northern Ireland and in whose stocks or obligations the state investment officer has invested state funds and (b) determine whether each corporation on the list has during the preceding year taken affirmative action to eliminate religious or ethnic discrimination in Northern Ireland.</para><para>(2) In making the determination required by this section, the state investment officer shall consider whether a corporation has during the preceding year taken substantial action designed to lead toward the achievement of the following goals, known internationally as the MacBride principles:</para><para>(a) Increasing representation of persons from underrepresented religious groups at all levels on its work force;</para><para>(b) Providing adequate security for employees who are members of minority religious groups, both at the workplace and while traveling to and from work;</para><para>(c) Banning provocative religious or political emblems from the workplace;</para><para>(d) Publicly advertising all job openings and making special recruiting efforts to attract applicants from underrepresented religious groups;</para><para>(e) Providing that layoff, recall, and termination procedures do not in practice favor or discriminate against workers who are members of particular religious groups;</para><para>(f) Abolishing job reservations, apprenticeship restrictions, and differential employment criteria that discriminate on the basis of religious or ethnic origin;</para><para>(g) Developing new programs and expanding existing programs to prepare current employees who are members of minority religious groups for skilled jobs;</para><para>(h) Establishing procedures to assess, identify, and recruit employees who are members of minority religious groups and who have potential for advancement; and</para><para>(i) Appointing senior management employees to oversee affirmative action efforts and the setting of timetables for carrying out this section.</para><para>(3) The state investment officer shall provide to the Legislature a copy of his or her report and findings on the first day of each regular session of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 144. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 