<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-1005"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-1005</statuteno><catchline>State Building Fund; created; use; transfer of funds.</catchline><para>The State Building Fund is created. The fund shall consist of administrative General Fund transfers credited to the State Building Fund as authorized by law. Money shall be appropriated from the fund to state agencies for making payments on projects as determined by the Legislature, including, but not limited to, purchases of land, structural improvements to land, acquisition of buildings, construction of buildings, including architectural and engineering costs, replacement of or major repairs to structural improvements to land or buildings, additions to existing structures, remodeling of buildings, and acquisition of equipment and furnishings of new or remodeled buildings. The fund shall be administered by the State Treasurer as a multiple-agency-use fund and appropriated to state agencies as determined by the Legislature.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall administratively transfer from the General Fund to the State Building Fund such amounts as required to make expenditures, except that the fund balance in the State Building Fund plus any administrative fund transfers made shall not exceed the total state unexpended appropriations balances from the State Building Fund, as authorized by law. Such administrative transfers shall be made periodically as required to make expenditures from the State Building Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 236, &#167; 1, p. 751; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 287, &#167; 71, p. 971; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 279, &#167; 2, p. 883; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 307, &#167; 1, p. 1113; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 413, &#167; 1, p. 1379; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 331, &#167; 3, p. 1206; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 334, &#167; 1, p. 1212; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 335, &#167; 1, p. 1214; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 418, &#167; 4, p. 1344; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 422, &#167; 1, p. 1348; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 441, &#167; 1, p. 1398; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 478, &#167; 3, p. 1540; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 594, &#167; 2, p. 2447; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 78, p. 2392; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 260; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 14. </para></source><annotation><para>Under former law, the State Institutional and Military Department Fund was made up of other funds, namely, (1) the proceeds derived from a special tax, and (2) a part of the state's share of the intangible tax. Board of Regents v. Gillette, 149 Neb. 56, 30 N.W.2d 296 (1947).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>