<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" id="id496" statutenumber="72-2211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>72-2211</statuteno><catchline id="id499">Capitol Restoration Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Capitol Restoration Cash Fund is created. The administrator shall administer the fund, which shall consist of money received from the sale of material, rental revenue, private donations, public donations, transfers from the Capitol Preservation, Restoration, and Enhancement Endowment Fund, and transfers from the Nebraska Capital Construction Fund as directed by the Legislature. </para><para>(2)(a) The Capitol Restoration Cash Fund shall be used to finance projects for the restoration, preservation, and enhancement of the State Capitol and its courtyards and grounds, to purchase and conserve items to be added to the Nebraska Capitol Collections housed in the State Capitol, to produce promotional material concerning the State Capitol, its grounds, and the Nebraska State Capitol Environs District, and to pay the expenditures for a project manager for the Capitol Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning Systems Replacement Project until such time as the project is completed, except that transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Such expenditures shall be prescribed by the administrator and approved by the commission. </para><para>(b) Money transferred to the fund from the Capitol Preservation, Restoration, and Enhancement Endowment Fund shall only be used for the restoration, preservation, and enhancement of the courtyards located at the State Capitol.</para><para>(3) Any money in the Capitol Restoration Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>