<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" statutenumber="72-2205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-2205</statuteno><catchline>Administrator; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The administrator shall have the authority to develop, produce, and distribute books, brochures, pictures, slides, postcards, and other informational or promotional material concerning the State Capitol. The administrator shall have control over money received from the distribution of such material and from private or public donations. Such proceeds and donations shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Capitol Restoration Cash Fund.</para><para>(2) The administrator, after receiving advice from the commission, is authorized to provide facilities for restaurants, cafeterias, or other services and newsstands for convenience of state officers and employees in the State Capitol when such space is not needed for public use. Proceeds from the operations and rental of such facilities shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Capitol Restoration Cash Fund.</para><para>(3) The administrator, after receiving advice from the commission, is authorized to lease, rent, or permit for use as apartments, dwellings, or offices any or all of the property acquired for future building needs for the State Capitol and capitol grounds, except that all leases shall contain the provision that upon notice that such property is needed for public use, the use or occupancy thereof shall cease. All money received as rent from such property shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Capitol Restoration Cash Fund and, with interest accrued, be designated as prescribed in section 72-2211.</para><para>(4) The administrator shall see that all parts and apartments of the State Capitol and capitol grounds are properly ventilated and kept clean and orderly.</para><para>(5) The administrator shall acquire a flag of the United States of America of suitable and convenient size. The colors of the flag shall be fast colors, and the cloth shall be of substantial material. The administrator shall display this flag and the Nebraska State Flag of similar specifications prominently on State Capitol grounds.</para><para>(6) The administrator shall ensure that, at proper hours, all visitors are properly escorted through the State Capitol and over the capitol grounds, free of expense.</para><para>(7) The administrator shall at all times have charge of and supervision over janitors and other employees in and about the State Capitol and capitol grounds.</para><para>(8) The administrator shall institute, in the name of the state and with the advice of the Attorney General, civil and criminal proceedings against any person for injury or threatened injury to any public property in the State Capitol or on the capitol grounds or for committing or threatening to commit a nuisance therein or thereon.</para><para>(9) The administrator shall keep in his or her office a complete record containing plans, specifications, and surveys of the State Capitol and capitol grounds and of underground construction thereto.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>