<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, and Funds" statutenumber="72-2213"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-2213</statuteno><catchline>Office space; determination of use; maintenance of building.</catchline><para>(1) The office space in the State Capitol or any other state office building occupied by the Governor, Lieutenant Governor, Secretary of State, State Treasurer, Attorney General, Auditor of Public Accounts, or Chief Justice and judges of the Supreme Court and Court of Appeals, including the office of the Clerk of the Supreme Court and courtrooms, shall remain under the control of such constitutional officer or Chief Justice. The Executive Board of the Legislative Council shall determine its office space requirements in the State Capitol and may occupy such office space as it requires except as provided in this subsection.</para><para>(2) After the determination by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the administrator, with the advice of the commission, shall determine the space needs of all other departments and agencies of the state located in the State Capitol and assign the remaining office space. The determination of such needs shall be based on the following considerations: (a) The availability of space within the State Capitol as provided in this section; (b) the desirability of locating all divisions and other organizational subunits of each department and agency of the state in physical proximity to the office of its head; (c) the degree to which the convenience of the public may be served by assignment of various areas within the State Capitol; (d) the interdependence of functions and operating procedures of the various agencies; (e) applicable standards governing office requirements; and (f) the availability of appropriations with which to finance renovations, remodeling, and movement of equipment necessary to accommodate any proposed assignment or reassignment of area.</para><para>(3) The office shall have responsibility for provision and replacement of lighting, lighting fixtures, heating, cooling and ventilation, and janitorial, custodial, and all other building services, including care and custody of the State Capitol and capitol grounds, as may now be provided by law.</para><para>(4) Responsibility for employment and supervision of custodial workers for areas of the State Capitol occupied by the Legislature, the courts, and executive departments and agencies shall be in accordance with such agreements as may be defined by authorized representatives of the three branches. All funds for improvements, remodeling, renovation, partitioning, or replacement of major fixtures, including carpeting, flooring, provision of drapes, lighting fixtures, and lamps, within any area of the State Capitol shall be at the disposal of the administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 439, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc>