<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id66"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, and Funds" statutenumber="72-2215"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>72-2215</statuteno><catchline>Flags of Indian tribes; display in State Capitol; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Clerk of the Legislature shall cause to be displayed within the Warner Legislative Chamber flags representing the four federally recognized tribes with headquarters in Nebraska: the Omaha Tribe of Nebraska, the Ponca Tribe of Nebraska, the Santee Sioux Nation, and the Winnebago Tribe of Nebraska.</para><para>(b) The Commission on Indian Affairs shall obtain such flags, as well as poles and bases, through donations from the tribes. The Commission on Indian Affairs shall be responsible for replacing such flags, poles, and bases.</para><para>(c) The Clerk of the Legislature shall approve placement locations within the Warner Legislative Chamber. The size, proportion, and placement of such flags shall be similar to that of the flag of the United States and the flag of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(2)(a) The State Capitol Administrator shall cause to be displayed in the Memorial Chamber on the fourteenth floor of the State Capitol the flags of any Indian tribes with historic and regional connections to Nebraska.</para><para>(b) The Commission on Indian Affairs shall designate the tribes with historic and regional connections to Nebraska and the flags to be displayed under subdivision (2)(a) of this section. The Commission on Indian Affairs shall obtain such flags, as well as poles and bases, through donations from the tribes. The Commission on Indian Affairs shall be responsible for replacing such flags, poles, and bases.</para><para>(c) The Nebraska Capitol Commission shall approve placement locations in the Memorial Chamber.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB848, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>