<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lands, Buildings, And Funds" id="id00" statutenumber="72-2304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>72-2304</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Bonds authorized; public hearing; notice; election, when required; remonstrance petition.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This section applies to bonds issued prior to April 18, 2018.</para><para id="id00">(b) In addition to any other borrowing powers provided for by law, a qualified public agency shall have the power to issue its negotiable bonds to any joint entity as defined in section 13-803 or to any joint public agency as defined in section 13-2503 in connection with any joint project which is to be owned, operated, or financed by the joint entity or joint public agency for the benefit of the qualified public agency. The bonds may be issued only if the second-largest participant in the joint project has a financial contribution in the joint project of at least twenty-five percent of the debt service. Such bonds may be issued after the qualified public agency has conducted a public hearing on the issuance of bonds. Notice of such public hearing shall be given by publication in a newspaper of general circulation within the territory of the qualified public agency by at least one publication occurring not less than ten days prior to the time of hearing. After the public hearing, the governing body of the qualified public agency may proceed to adopt a bond measure authorizing bonds.</para><para id="id00">(2) Notice of any such bond measure shall be given by publication of notice of intention to issue bonds in a newspaper of general circulation within the territory of the qualified public agency at least twice after the adoption of the bond measure. Such publications shall be at least three weeks apart. The notice shall state:</para><para id="id00">(a) The name of the qualified public agency;</para><para id="id00">(b) The purpose of the issue;</para><para id="id00">(c) The principal amount of the issue;</para><para id="id00">(d) The amount of annual debt service payment anticipated for the bonds, which may be stated as an approximation or estimate, and the anticipated duration for such debt service payments; and</para><para id="id00">(e) The time and place where a copy of the form of the bond measure may be examined for a period of at least thirty days.</para><para id="id00">(3) For bonds issued prior to April 18, 2018, no election shall be required prior to the issuance of bonds under the Public Facilities Construction and Finance Act unless, within sixty days after the first publication of the notice of intention to issue bonds, a remonstrance petition against the issuance of bonds is filed with the clerk or secretary of the qualified public agency. Such remonstrance petition shall be signed by registered voters of the qualified public agency equal in number to at least five percent of the number of registered voters of the qualified public agency at the time the remonstrance petition is filed or at least the number of signatures listed in subsection (5) of this section for the applicable qualified public agency, whichever is less. If a remonstrance petition with the necessary number of qualified signatures is timely filed, the question shall be submitted to the voters of the qualified public agency at a general election or a special election called for the purpose of approving the bonds proposed to be issued. Any joint project for which bonds are issued in accordance with the procedures of the act shall not require any other approval or proceeding by the governing body or the voters of the qualified public agency.</para><para id="id00">(4) For bonds issued prior to April 18, 2018, no election shall be required for any qualified public agency not issuing bonds to participate in such joint project unless, within sixty days after the governing body of the qualified public agency adopts the measure approving the interlocal or cooperative agreement related to the joint project, a remonstrance petition is filed with the clerk or secretary of the qualified public agency. Such remonstrance petition shall be signed by registered voters of the qualified public agency equal in number to at least five percent of the number of registered voters of the qualified public agency at the time the remonstrance petition is filed or at least the number of signatures listed in subsection (5) of this section for the applicable qualified public agency, whichever is less. If a remonstrance petition with the necessary number of qualified signatures is timely filed, the question shall be submitted to the voters of the qualified public agency at a general election or a special election called for the purpose of approving the interlocal or cooperative agreement related to the joint project.</para><para id="id00">(5) The chart in this subsection provides the alternative number of signatures of registered voters of a qualified public agency which may be used to submit a remonstrance petition under subsection (3) or (4) of this section. The classification of counties in section 23-1114.01 applies for purposes of this section.</para><para id="id00"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1.44*" /><colspec align="right" colname="col2" colwidth="1.00*" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Qualified Public Agency</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Number of Signatures</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">of Registered Voters</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para><para id="id00"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="2.42*" /><colspec align="right" colname="col2" colwidth="0.63*" /><tbody><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">City of the Metropolitan Class</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">City of the Primary Class</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1000</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">City of the First Class</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">750</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">City of the Second Class</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">250</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Villages</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">50</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Municipal County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 7 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 6 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1000</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 5 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">750</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 4 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 3 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">250</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 2 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">100</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class 1 County</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">50</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class V School District</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class IV School District</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1000</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Class III School District</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Educational Service Unit</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">250</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Community College Area</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Fire Protection District</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Hospital District</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">500</entry></row><row valign="middle"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Sanitary and Improvement District</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">500</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 217, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1000, &#167; 4. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB377, section 7, with LB1000, section 4, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB1000 became effective April 18, 2018. Changes made by LB377 became operative January 1, 2019.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>