<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-404</statuteno><catchline>Declaration relating to use of life-sustaining treatment.</catchline><para>(1) An adult of sound mind may execute at any time a declaration governing the withholding or withdrawal of life-sustaining treatment. The declaration must be signed by the declarant or another person at the declarant's direction and witnessed by two adults or a notary public. No more than one witness to a declaration shall be an administrator or employee of a health care provider who is caring for or treating the declarant, and no witness shall be an employee of a life or health insurance provider for the declarant. The restrictions upon who may witness the signing shall not apply to a notary public.</para><para>(2) A declaration directing a physician to withhold or withdraw life-sustaining treatment may, but need not, be in the form provided in this subsection.</para><para>DECLARATION</para><para>If I should lapse into a persistent vegetative state or have an incurable and irreversible condition that, without the administration of life-sustaining treatment, will, in the opinion of my attending physician, cause my death within a relatively short time and I am no longer able to make decisions regarding my medical treatment, I direct my attending physician, pursuant to the Rights of the Terminally Ill Act, to withhold or withdraw life sustaining treatment that is not necessary for my comfort or to alleviate pain.</para><para>Signed this .... day of .............. .</para><para>Signature ..........................</para><para>Address ............................</para><para>The declarant voluntarily signed this writing in my presence.</para><para>Witness ............................</para><para>Address ............................</para><para>Witness ............................</para><para>Address ............................</para><para>Or</para><para>The declarant voluntarily signed this writing in my presence.</para><para>.................. Notary Public</para><para>(3) A physician or other health care provider who is furnished a copy of the declaration shall make it a part of the declarant's medical record and, if unwilling to comply with the declaration, shall promptly so advise the declarant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 671, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>