<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id49">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Civil Rights" id="id51" statutenumber="20-506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>20-506</statuteno><catchline id="id54">Racial Profiling
Advisory Committee; created; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1)
The Racial Profiling Advisory Committee is created.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The committee shall consist of:</para>
<para>(i) The executive director of the Nebraska Commission on Law
Enforcement and Criminal Justice, who also shall be the chairperson of the
committee;</para>
<para>(ii) The Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety
or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(iii) The director of the Commission on Latino-Americans or
his or her designee; and</para>
<para>(iv) The executive director of the Commission on Indian Affairs
or his or her designee.</para>
<para>(b) The committee shall also consist of the following persons,
each appointed by the Governor from a list of five names
submitted to the Governor for each position:</para>
<para>(i) A representative of the Fraternal Order of Police;</para>
<para>(ii) A representative of the Nebraska County Sheriffs Association;</para>
<para>(iii) A representative of the Police Officers Association
of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(iv) A representative of the American Civil Liberties Union
of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(v) A representative of the AFL-CIO;</para>
<para>(vi) A representative of the Police Chiefs Association of
Nebraska;</para>
<para>(vii) A representative of the Nebraska branches of the National
Association for the Advancement of Colored People; and</para>
<para>(viii) A representative of the Nebraska State Bar Association
appointed by the Governor from a list of attorneys submitted by the executive
council of the Nebraska State Bar Association.</para>
<para>(3) The committee shall meet and organize within thirty days
after the appointment of the members. The committee shall meet semiannually
at a time and place to be fixed by the committee. Special meetings may be
called by the chairperson or at the request of two or more members of the
committee.</para>
<para>(4) The committee shall advise the commission and its executive director in the conduct
of their duties regarding (a) the completeness and acceptability
of written racial profiling prevention policies submitted by individual law
enforcement agencies as required by subsection (1) of section 20-504, (b)
the collection of data by law enforcement agencies, any needed additional
data, and any needed additional analysis, investigation, or inquiry as to
the data provided pursuant to subsection (3) of section 20-504, (c) the
review, analysis, inquiry,
study, and recommendations required pursuant to subsection (7) of section 20-504, including an
analysis of the review, analysis,
inquiry, study, and recommendations, and (d) policy recommendations with respect
to the prevention of racial
profiling and the need, if
any, for enforcement by the Department of Justice of the prohibitions found
in section 20-502.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1162, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB746, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB99, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>