 <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-162" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-162</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 20-161 to 20-166, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Complaint shall mean any oral or written allegation by a person with a developmental disability or a mentally ill individual, the parent or guardian of such persons, a state agency, or any other responsible named individual or entity to the effect that the person with developmental disabilities or the mentally ill individual is being subjected to injury or deprivation with regard to his or her health, safety, welfare, rights, or level of care;</para><para>(2) Developmental disability shall mean a severe chronic mental or physical disability as defined in the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act, 42 U.S.C. 6000 et seq., as amended;</para><para>(3) Facility for mentally ill individuals shall mean any place within Nebraska where a mentally ill individual is an inpatient or a resident and that is organized to provide treatment, shelter, food, care, or supervision including, but not limited to, those facilities described in the Health Care Facility Licensure Act and sections 71-1901 to 71-1916, 83-107.01, and 83-108;</para><para>(4) Facility for persons with developmental disabilities shall mean a facility or a specified portion of a facility designed primarily for the delivery of one or more services to persons with one or more developmental disabilities including, but not limited to, those facilities described in the Health Care Facility Licensure Act and sections 71-1901 to 71-1916, 83-107.01, and 83-108 whenever a person with a developmental disability is residing in such facility;</para><para>(5) Mentally ill individual shall mean an individual who has a significant mental illness or emotional impairment as determined by a mental health professional qualified under the laws, rules, and regulations of this state and who is an inpatient or resident in a facility for mentally ill individuals;</para><para>(6) Protection and advocacy system shall mean the entity designated pursuant to the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act, 42 U.S.C. 6000 et seq., as amended;</para><para>(7) Records shall mean all information and data obtained, collected, or maintained by a facility for persons with developmental disabilities or a facility for mentally ill individuals in the course of providing services to such persons which are reasonably related to the complaint to be investigated; and</para><para>(8) Services for persons with developmental disabilities shall mean services as defined in the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act, 42 U.S.C. 6000 et seq., as amended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 697, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 994, &#167; 50. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>