<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Civil Rights" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="20-504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-504</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Written policy;
records maintained; immunity.</catchline><para>(1) On or before January 1,
2002, the Nebraska State Patrol, the county sheriffs, all city and village
police departments, and any other law enforcement agency in this state shall
adopt a written policy that prohibits the detention of any person or a motor
vehicle stop when such action is motivated by racial profiling and the action
would constitute a violation of the civil rights of the person.</para>
<para>(2) With respect to a motor vehicle stop, on and after January 1, 2002,
and until January 1, 2014, the Nebraska State Patrol, the county sheriffs,
all city and village police departments, and any other law enforcement agency
in this state shall record and retain the following information using the
form developed and promulgated pursuant to section 20-505:</para>
<para>(a) The number of motor vehicle stops;</para>
<para>(b) The characteristics of race or ethnicity of the person stopped.
The identification of such characteristics shall be based on the observation
and perception of the law enforcement officer responsible for reporting the
motor vehicle stop and the information shall not be required to be provided
by the person stopped;</para>
<para>(c) If the stop is for a law violation, the nature of the alleged law
violation that resulted in the motor vehicle stop;</para>
<para>(d) Whether a warning or citation was issued, an arrest made, or a search
conducted as a result of the motor vehicle stop. Search does not include a
search incident to arrest or an inventory search; and</para>
<para>(e) Any additional information that the Nebraska State Patrol, the county
sheriffs, all city and village police departments, or any other law enforcement
agency in this state, as the case may be, deems appropriate.</para>
<para>(3) The Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice
may develop a uniform system for receiving allegations of racial profiling.
The Nebraska State Patrol, the county sheriffs, all city and village police
departments, and any other law enforcement agency in this state shall provide
to the commission (a) a copy of each allegation of racial profiling received
and (b) written notification of the review and disposition of such allegation.
No information revealing the identity of the law enforcement officer involved
in the stop shall be used, transmitted, or disclosed in violation of any collective-bargaining
agreement provision or personnel rule under which such law enforcement officer
is employed. No information revealing the identity of the complainant shall
be used, transmitted, or disclosed in the form alleging racial profiling.</para>
<para>(4) Any law enforcement officer who in good faith records information
on a motor vehicle stop pursuant to this section shall not be held civilly
liable for the act of recording such information unless the law enforcement
officer's conduct was unreasonable or reckless or in some way contrary to
law.</para>
<para>(5) On or before October 1, 2002, and annually thereafter until January
1, 2014, the Nebraska State Patrol, the county sheriffs, all city and village
police departments, and all other law enforcement agencies in this state shall
provide to the commission, in such form as the commission prescribes, a summary
report of the information recorded pursuant to subsection (2) of this section.</para>
<para>(6) On and after January 1, 2002, and until April 1, 2014, the commission
may, within the limits of its existing appropriations, provide for a review
of the prevalence and disposition of motor vehicle stops based on racial profiling
and allegations reported pursuant to this section. The results of such review
shall be reported annually to the Governor and the Legislature beginning on
or before April 1, 2004, until April 1, 2014. The report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted
electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 593, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1162, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB746, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 21.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>