<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-412"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-412</statuteno><catchline>Miscellaneous provisions.</catchline><para>(1) Death resulting from the withholding or withdrawal of life-sustaining treatment in accordance with the Rights of the Terminally Ill Act shall not constitute, for any purpose, a suicide or homicide.</para><para>(2) The making of a declaration pursuant to section 20-404 shall not affect the sale, procurement, or issuance of a policy of life insurance or annuity or affect, impair, or modify the terms of an existing policy of life insurance or annuity. A policy of life insurance or annuity shall not be legally impaired or invalidated by the withholding or withdrawal of life-sustaining treatment from an insured, notwithstanding any term to the contrary.</para><para>(3) No person shall prohibit or require the execution of a declaration as a condition to being insured for or receiving health care services. No insurance company or health care provider shall charge a higher or lower rate for signers of declarations under the act as opposed to nonsigners.</para><para>(4) The act shall create no presumption concerning the intention of an individual who has revoked or has not executed a declaration with respect to the use, withholding, or withdrawal of life-sustaining treatment in the event of a terminal condition.</para><para>(5) The act shall not affect the right of a patient to make decisions regarding use of life-sustaining treatment so long as the patient is able to do so or impair or supersede a right or responsibility that a person has to effect the withholding or withdrawal of medical care.</para><para>(6) The act shall not require a physician or other health care provider to take action contrary to reasonable medical standards.</para><para>(7) The act shall not confer any new rights regarding the provision or rejection of any specific medical treatment and shall not alter any existing laws concerning homicide, suicide, or assisted suicide. Nothing in the act shall be construed to condone, authorize, or approve homicide, suicide, or assisted suicide.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 671, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>